<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pleasant conference upon the Observator and Heraclitus together with a brief relation of the present posture of the French affairs.</title>
            <author>Phillips, John, 1631-1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-03">2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2540</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4454</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13197954</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13197954</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98431</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A55123)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98431)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 434:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pleasant conference upon the Observator and Heraclitus together with a brief relation of the present posture of the French affairs.</title>
                  <author>Phillips, John, 1631-1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Jones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A satire on the Tories and their periodicals.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Phillips. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tories, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-07</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98431:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98431:1"/>
            <p>A
PLEASANT CONFERENCE
UPON THE
OBSERVATOR,
AND
Heraclitus: TOGETHER
With a brief RELATION
OF THE
PRESENT POSTURE
OF THE
French Affairs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
Printed for <hi>H. Iones.</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98431:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98431:2"/>
            <head>A Pleasant Conference
UPON THE
OBSERVATOR and HERACLITVS.</head>
            <p>ABout the time that the third Head of <hi>Cerberus</hi>
had set the Watch for the other two that were
fallen asleep, in came a Spirit Booted and
Spur'd, and commanded the Gates of the Infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
Palace to be opened: which was immediately done,
without a word of Pray Sir remember the Porter.</p>
            <p>Who should this be, but one of <hi>Lucifers</hi> Emissaries,
that he had sent into this world to Eves-drop for Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,
to keep Company, to counterfeit sometimes <hi>Tory,</hi>
and sometimes <hi>Whigg,</hi> and make what Discoveries he
could.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucifer</hi> had been Gaming most part of the night, and
was very drowsie, when they brought him word that
such a one was attending below: but understanding his
business, he ordered him present admittance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it please your most Illustrious Highness,</hi> said <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fagor,</hi>
for that was the Name of the <hi>Plutonian</hi> Emissary,
You sent me into the other world to make Discoveries;
and it was upon this ground, for that you believed your
two Brorhers, <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Neptune,</hi> had been injurious to
you, in giving you the worst share of the <hi>Vniverse,</hi>
and therefore you were resolved upon new pretensions,
to make an Exchange or an Invasion, and not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined
any longer to Shades or Tenebrosity. And to this
purpose you sent me to discover the Genius of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98431:3"/>
Subjects. Sir, take my advice, and stay where
you are. For as for your Brother <hi>Iupiter,</hi> I have made
some inquiry after him, but find him to be althogether
worn out of date; so far from being Adored and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped,
that you shall hardly hear him nam'd, unless it
be now and then in a Thunder-thumping Tragedy. And
for your Brother <hi>Neptune,</hi> 'tis said that the French King
has bought him out of all his Dominions, and intends to
be Lord of the whole Ocean that flows between both the
Poles himself. And for the Earth, I mean that part of
the <hi>Vniverse</hi> where those Creatures call'd Mortals live,
the fore-mentioned French King, no more dreaming of
Mortality, than you of dying, is resolved to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
the Universal Monarch of it. To which purpose,
he daily goes on, vexing, tormenting, and incroaching
upon his Neighbours, that no body can live in quiet for
him. No Leagues will hold him, no Faith will bind him
up; so that altough your most <hi>Serene Sootiness</hi> wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
know how much you are bound up, if you only Swear
by <hi>Styx,</hi> yet is he so regardless of those things, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
you mind him of his Treatie-Attestations, he presently
shrugs up his shoulders and laughs at ye,—as much as to
say,—he knows better things.—He buyes Towns by
whole-sale, and I wish you yourself may be safe from his
Treasure.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Let him be never so rich, and never so great a
Ruffler, I think I am able to match him both in number
and wealth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>I grant it, Sir, you excel him in number, but
then, alas, Sir, what signifie your Millions of Skeletons,
shadows only of Men, that live merely upon the Air, to
encounter with so many thousands of well-disciplined
<hi>Sa, Sa's,</hi> whose bones are covered with hard flesh, and
outwardly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ortified with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loaths and Armour, within
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98431:3"/>
with Beef, Pudding, Strong-beer, and Canary, which
they will have if it be upon earth.—Then for your
wealth, Sir,—'Tis true, you may make these Mortals,
especially the most active, they'l do e'en what you please
for your Money; but then again, they are so Quarrel-some,
so Mutinous, so Seditious, so Turbulent, so restless,
that you who have raigned always in peace, and in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
Unity with your own Natural Subjects, and with
so much aw and Arbitrary Dominion over Forreigners,
will never endure to be pestred, harrased, worryed, ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered,
and perplexed, by these humane Terrestrials, as
you must expect to be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>But how if I can get in by Conquest?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Ah, Sir, I would not have you attempt it,
for they'l be too hard for you in two things; the one side
will out-pray ye, and the other will out-swear ye; and
then pray tell me, what will become of all your Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?
all the vast Army, and all the numerous Captains
that <hi>Miltons Paradise lost</hi> musters up for ye, they'l all
do you not a pins worth of good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>This seems somewhat strange, I thought I could
have dealt well enough with Mankind; I am sure I find
the proude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of 'em all tame enough here.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>That's nothing, Sir, when they are incarnate
they are quite another thing; and therefore if your
Sootiness will not believe me, you had best go <hi>incognito,</hi>
and try your self. Nay, Sir, to tell you more, there is
in one little spot of the Terrestrial Globe, a place called
<hi>Plotter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Island,</hi> which you may easily cover with one of
your Princely Black Thumbs, where they are in the
strangest confusion imaginable; and all about a business
that I am sure you would never trouble your head with;
much less would endure to have your rest disturbed,
your repose disordered, and your pleasures interrupted
for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98431:4"/>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Prithee what's that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Religion, Sir, or, at least, that's the grand
pretence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>I believe that which you call <hi>Plotters Island,</hi> is
<hi>Sicilie;</hi> for that Island is monstrous hot, as they say, as
having a continual burning Mountain in it, fancied to be
the vent of my Kitchin Chimney, and therefore it may
be rationally thought to have some more than ordinary
influence upon the heads of the people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>No, no, Sir, 'tis called <hi>Plotters Island,</hi> where
all the Inhabitants are under Disguises, Jealousies, Fears,
and Misconstructions; one man calls his Neighbour
<hi>Whigg,</hi> and his Neighbour calls him <hi>Tory;</hi> another
man calls his Neighbour <hi>Fanatick,</hi> and his Neighbour
calls him <hi>Tantivie-man.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>By the Mass, I never heard of such feat Names
be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>No, Sir, I believe you did not; but 'tis come
to that pass now, that all the Goosequillers are got into
the field, skirmishing continually, without any thoughts
of Winter-quarters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>The Goosequillers, prithee what are those?
who commands them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Why, may it please your most <hi>Serene Sooti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi>
they are for the most conversed with in the shapes
of Men, but I rather look on them with a <hi>partie per
pale</hi> prospect, half <hi>Devil,</hi> half <hi>Man.</hi> The great Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals
of the Parties are, General <hi>Observator,</hi> General
<hi>Heraclitus,</hi> General <hi>Advice from Rome,</hi> with several
Brigadeers of lesser fame, as <hi>Col. Fetterlanio,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>What sort of Weapons do they use?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Pamphlets<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sir: You may go into a Coffee-house,
and see a Table of an Acre long covered with
nothing but Tobacco-pipes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Pamphlets, and all the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98431:4"/>
se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts full of Mort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> leaning upon their Elbowes, licking
in Tobacco, Lyes, and Lac'd Coffee, and studying for
Arguments to revile one another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>How comes all this to pass?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>By vertue of a certain Devilish Engine, Sir,
of your own inventing, called a Printing-press.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Ay, but all this while these are only Tools;
who are the Artists that manage and handle these Tools?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, the Inhabitants of the Island told me,
those Artists were great friends of yours; that is to say,
the <hi>Pope,</hi> and certain Viperous Animals of his fostering,
called Priests and Jesuits.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>O hang 'em, they'd embroyl my Kingdoms too,
if they could; but thou knowest what massie Bolts and
Locks I have been forced to keep 'em under, ever since
I smelt 'em out, and what extraordinary corrections I
give to keep them low and quiet. Well, but what
pranks had these fellows been playing in <hi>Plotters Island?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Why, Sir, they have been playing the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
with two sticks. They had set up a most cruel and
dangerous Plot to destroy the Prince of the <hi>Island,</hi> and
the greatest part of his <hi>best Subjects,</hi> which they call
Hereticks; but it being in time discovered, the design
seemed so execrable, so detestable, so abominable, so
pernitious and destructive to the very Being and Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare
of Mankind, that the Pope, his Priests and Jesuits,
have been labouring all the ways imaginable to throw
off the shame and ignominie of the thing from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
and fix it upon the Hereticks. To this purpose
they laid down this for a Maxim, That if the Prince of
the <hi>Island</hi> were once set against that part of his Subjects
which they most dreaded, and by them lately called
<hi>Whiggs,</hi> and they provoked against the Government, he
would not only be alienated from them, but be in a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98431:5"/>
manner compelled, for his own security, to joyn with
them against his new displayed Enemies. The design being
thus laid, to imbitter the Prince against the Subject, &amp; the
Subject against the Prince, the Pope and the Jesuits em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodyed
themselves with the <hi>Tories,</hi> among whom credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
and heat of the brains raign very powerfully, and
made them believe strange stories and Romances of the
<hi>Whiggs,</hi> as if they were Machinating against Regal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
setting up Republicks, building Castles in
the Air for Garrisons, and lastly, that they intended to
have seized upon the Person of the King; Tales all as
false as improbable, and such as have ridiculously, it
seems, suffered since by the unsuccessful choice of the
Witnesses and Proofs. Then the <hi>Observator</hi> and <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clitus</hi>
were left loose to bawl out <hi>Forty One, Forty One,
Oh, Forty One,</hi> have a care of <hi>Forty One,</hi> beware of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
One,</hi> Bow, wow, wow, wow, <hi>Forty One.</hi> Don't you
remember, Sir, what a dreadful noise our <hi>Dog Cerberus</hi>
made one night, when <hi>Theseus</hi> came Hectoring down hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and broke your Highnesses Palace-Windows?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Very well, for which <hi>Theseus</hi> gave the Cur
such a confounded palt, after his manner, that his Tripple
pate was forced to be noynted with butter and beer for
six Months after.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Well, Sir, even such a wicked noise do these
two wide-mouth'd <hi>Melampus</hi>'s make. And all this
while the <hi>Tantivie-men</hi> spit i' their Mouths, collect silver
sops for 'em among the rest of the Tribe; and when they
have reduced them into <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> present it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or
their farther incouragement.</p>
               <p>Having by these ways endeavoured to render the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
suspected to the Prince, their next game was to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the Prince odious to the Subject, by advising him
to recal his gracious Dispensation of severe Laws, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98431:5"/>
to cause penalties to be put in execution for the enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of their Conscience, of which the <hi>Whiggs</hi> are said
to be extreamly nice and tender. A thing which the
<hi>Whiggs</hi> lament very much, as knowing how little they
vary in points of Controversie from the <hi>Tories.</hi> And
the better to colour this design, they seized and imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
several of the <hi>Whiggs,</hi> and were so fortunate to hang
a poor intruder; by which means they thought to have
struck at the whole Party; but the ruine being circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scrib'd
to his only Microcosme, the Intreague was buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with his Quarters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>So, then you say the Jesuits are they, that set
the <hi>Tories</hi> and <hi>Whiggs</hi> together by the ears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>You have it right, Sir, and they still conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
the fewd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>All this while, good <hi>Belfagor</hi> what is a <hi>Tory?</hi>
what is a <hi>Whigg?</hi> what are these <hi>Tantivie-men,</hi> these
<hi>Observators,</hi> and these <hi>Heraclitus?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>May it please your most Serene <hi>Tenebrositie,</hi>
When I first came to hear of these uncooth Names, I was
as much a gast as your Highness seems now to be; I
nere was so fraid i'my life, but that they had been some
new inventions of the men of Schemes, to send us trot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
about the world upon their Fools Errands; but
long it was not ere they began to make Characters one
of another, or some body for them; and that puts us
out of those fears, all which I presently bought up, as
well to inform my own ignorance, as your Highnesses
curiosity. The first I met with was that of a <hi>Tory.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>And where is it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis here in my paw, I intend if your <hi>Soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiness</hi>
will give me leave, to read it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Do so.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>A <hi>Tory</hi> is a Monster with an <hi>English Face,</hi> a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98431:6"/>
                  <hi>French Heart,</hi> and an <hi>Irish Conscience.</hi> A Creature of
a large <hi>Forehead,</hi> prodigious <hi>Mouth,</hi> supple <hi>Hams,</hi> and
no <hi>Brains<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> The Country-mans Description of him, was
both Rhyme and Reason<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Roary, Whorey, Sworey, Scorey,</hi>
That's a <hi>Tory;</hi> for <hi>Noise</hi> and <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>chery, Oaths</hi> and <hi>Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery,</hi>
are the Four <hi>Elements</hi> that compose him: His <hi>Arms</hi>
are those of <hi>Istacher,</hi> an <hi>Ass Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hant;</hi> and his Mark is a
<hi>Red Ribbon</hi> in his Cap, to shew, That he belongs to the
<hi>Scarlet Whore,</hi> by her Bloody Lvery; or else, you may
take it for a <hi>Wedding Favour,</hi> That whenever <hi>Popery</hi>
and <hi>Tyranny</hi> shall make a <hi>Match,</hi> he would fain be a
<hi>Bride man.</hi> He seems descended from <hi>Esau,</hi> since he is
so ready to Truck away an Invalluable <hi>Birthright</hi> for a
<hi>French Kick shaw,</hi> and a Naus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous Mess of <hi>Italian Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</hi>
Or if you will run his Pedigree higher, you may
call him a <hi>Noddite,</hi> one of the Race of <hi>Cain</hi> the <hi>Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi>
that would fain be Persecuting his Brother, meerly
because he is more Righteous than himself.</p>
               <p>Take our <hi>Tories</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> and they are Caterpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
that Devour every green thing in a flourishing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
and would Stab Liberty and Property to the Heart,
that they themselves like <hi>Beasts of Prey,</hi> might live
wholly upon <hi>Sport and Rapine,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it only to be Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
to <hi>Neb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chadnezzar,</hi> when bereav'd of Humane
sence, he hearded with the <hi>Wild Asses</hi> of the <hi>Desert.</hi>
Though they boast themselves <hi>Englishmen,</hi> yet they act
in all things as <hi>Antipodes</hi> to their Native Countrey, and
seem rather <hi>Bogg-trotters</hi> Transplanted, the Spawn of
some <hi>Redshanks,</hi> or the By-blows of the old lazy <hi>Lord-Danes,</hi>
that once Domineer'd over our Ancestors. They
are a sort of <hi>Wild Boars,</hi> that would root out the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution,
and break the Ballance of our happy Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
and render that <hi>Despotick,</hi> which hitherto has
been both Established and bounded by Law. <hi>Fauxes</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98431:6"/>
in Masquerade, that with <hi>Dark-lanthorn</hi> Policies, would
at once blow up the two Bulwarks of our Freedom, <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments</hi>
and <hi>Iuries;</hi> making the first only a Parliament
of <hi>Paris:</hi> and the latter, but meer Tools, to Eccho back
the pleasure of a Judge. They are so certain, that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy
is <hi>Iure Divino,</hi> that they look upon all people
living under Aristocracies, or Democracies, to be in a
state of <hi>Damnation;</hi> and fancie, That the <hi>Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior,</hi>
the <hi>Czar</hi> of <hi>Moscovy,</hi> and the <hi>French King,</hi> dropt
down from <hi>Heaven</hi> with <hi>Crowns</hi> on their Heads, and
that all their Subjects were born with <hi>Saddles</hi> on their
backs. Your true <hi>Tory</hi> is as fond of <hi>Slavery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> as others are
of <hi>Liberty,</hi> and will be at as much pains and charge to
obtain it; for he envies the happiness of <hi>Canvas Bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi>
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>Wooden Shooes;</hi> and extreamly admires the
Mercy of the Inquisition. He rails at <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> as
the Seed-plot of <hi>Sedition;</hi> swears, that it was first obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d
by <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and that all our Fore-fathers were <hi>Rogues
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd Fools,</hi> and did not understand <hi>Prerogative.</hi> He
wonders why people should squander away their time at
the <hi>Inns of Court,</hi> or what need there is either of the
<hi>Common-Law</hi> or the <hi>Statute-book,</hi> since the King might
at any time, with quicker dispatch declare his pleasure
in any Point or Controversie, and each Loyal Subject
were bound to acquiesce, on pain of Damnation. Yet
after all, his boasted <hi>Loyalty</hi> extends no further than a
Drunken Health; he <hi>Roars</hi> and <hi>Swaggers,</hi> but does not
<hi>Serve</hi> the King; he promises Mountains, and by Lies and
Misrepresentations, gives false Measures, but performs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;
nor is it the Cause, but the Crust that he Barks
for.</p>
               <p>Then in relation to the Church; <hi>Tory</hi> is either a <hi>Crab-Protestant,</hi>
that <hi>crawls backwards</hi> as fast as he can to
<hi>Rome;</hi> or at best, but the <hi>Cats foot</hi> wherewith the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98431:7"/>
                  <hi>Monkeys</hi> Claw the Protestant Religion till the
Blood comes; one that does their Drudgery, though
he has not always the Wit to see it, and all the Wages he
must expect, is <hi>Polyphemus</hi>'s C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtesie, to be Devoured
<hi>last.</hi> He is a <hi>Flambeau</hi> kindled by the Jesuits, and flung
in to make a Combustion amongst us. Whilst we
were Hunting down their Plot with a full Cry, they
slipt in their Deep mouth'd-Hound, who spending on
a false <hi>Seent,</hi> diverted the Chase, and so the Popish Puss
squats safe in her Form; and now quitting the pursuit
of the <hi>Foxes,</hi> he begins to worry the <hi>Sheep.</hi> He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
high for the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but as he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstands
not her Doctrine, so he dishonours her by
his lewd Conversation. What a pretty pious Confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of Faith is it, to hear a <hi>Bully</hi> Cry, <hi>God-Dam-Mee, I am
of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and all the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>are
Sons of Whores.</hi>) Indeed, the only proof both of his
Religion and Courage, is, that he swears most frequently
by that <hi>Tremendous</hi> Name, at which, lesser Devils Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
and his Christianity consists in <hi>Cursing</hi> all those
that he is pleased to call <hi>Phanaticks;</hi> and <hi>Phanaticks</hi> he
calls all those, that are not content to be either Papists
or Atheists. His Tongue is always tipt with <hi>Dam-mee,</hi>
and <hi>Forty One;</hi> and so hot, (being set on Fire of <hi>Hell</hi>)
that he is fain to drink Healths, (sometimes to the Pope,
and sometimes to the Devil,) Sixty times an hour to
quench it; and then belches out <hi>Huzza</hi>'s as fast, as Mount
<hi>Strombulo</hi> does Fire and Brimstone.</p>
               <p>Whilst he clamours at Dissenters for not coming to
Church, he thinks 'tis Canonical enough to sleep over
the <hi>Lords-day,</hi> to digest the Fumes of Saturdays De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch,
or take a walk in <hi>Guild-hall-yard,</hi> peep in at
the Preacher, and presently retire to the Tavern for a
whet to Dinner, or else to meet the Club of <hi>Witty good-mockers</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98431:7"/>
by <hi>Fleet-ditch</hi> side, and Droll away the day in
Blasphemy, Ridiculing Religious Duties, or inventing
<hi>Iack pudding Lies</hi> of some pretended <hi>Nonconformists</hi>
Preaching. If he be somewhat of a more serious Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
he is as very a superstitious <hi>Bigot,</hi> as any in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy,
he would rather have no Preaching, than that the
Surplice should be left off, and thinks his Child not
Christned, fit be not done with the sign of the <hi>Cross;</hi>
he counts <hi>Opus operatum</hi> sufficient, and if he have but
been at <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> and made his <hi>Responses</hi> loud e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to drown the Clark, and had the Parsons Blessing,
his Task is done and all is safe. Flesh on a Friday is more
abomination to him, than his Neighbours Bed, aud he
abhors more not to bow at the Syllables of the word <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi>
than to swear by the Name of God.</p>
               <p>He has got a <hi>New English Dictionary,</hi> framed by the
Indefatigable skill of <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> and the <hi>Observator,</hi>
whereby the Traversties the most Loyal honest sense into
<hi>Blasphemy</hi> and <hi>Treason.</hi> Talk soberly of <hi>Religion,</hi> and
he flaps you over the face with Heresie, Schism, Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticism,
and Faction, or roundly calls you confounded
Whigg, and so you are confuted. Urge never so mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destly,
<hi>Legal Fundamental Rights,</hi> and mention Irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities,
though in a place appointed to remedy them, he
cryes out <hi>Rebellion! Treason!</hi> you <hi>Depose the King!</hi>
you <hi>Arraign the Government,</hi> &amp;c. Mention the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi>
of <hi>England,</hi> and the general sense of the Nation,
and he exclaims, Dam the <hi>Mobile</hi> and your <hi>Appeals</hi> to
the <hi>Rabble;</hi> and yet at the same time Courts and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauds
Tag-Rag and Long-tail, the <hi>Cooks and Chandlers
of New-Sarum,</hi> and such other Worshipful Patriots, for
declaring their three half-penny Judgments of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
Affairs of State, in their <hi>Addresses.</hi> And as for the
two last Parliaments, every petty <hi>Chap-man</hi> or <hi>Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice-boy,</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98431:8"/>
takes upon him to Censure the grave Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
of those <hi>Venerable Senates,</hi> as malepartly as if they
had been but a Company of Fidlers.</p>
               <p>Yet still he fears not <hi>God</hi> so much as a <hi>Parliament,</hi> but
the reason why he Blasphemes the <hi>one,</hi> and Rails at the
<hi>other,</hi> is, because as he really believes not a Future Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
in the other world, so he puts <hi>far off</hi> the other (to
him) evil day in <hi>this,</hi> and hopes to escape the Justice of
both by the Mediation of Saint <hi>Noli prosequi.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Well, what's the next? for I like this so well,
I must hear all the rest.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Why, Sir, the next is the Character of a
<hi>Whigg,</hi> but a thing so scurralously and weakly penn'd,
that it cannot afford your Highness matter enough for
one smile; and therefore if you please, we'll hang that
by on the Jesuits file.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Do so, but what's the next?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Why the Character of a <hi>Tantivie-man.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Come read that then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>He is a jolly brisk young huff in Crape, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteeing,
Rayling, Diolling, and Drinking; his Library
besides Comedies and Novels, are <hi>Grotius</hi> on the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles,</hi>
his <hi>Votum propapacia, Ovid de acte a Mandi,
Cassander, Pece Maimbourg, Sham History of Lutherism,</hi>
and <hi>Bennets Spinoza,</hi> which you must know he reads for
Confutation and direction only. As for his Religion, it
is an Aristocracie, he can burlesque our little Discenting
slaves at whom, while like a true Spiritual <hi>Venetian,</hi> he
opposes the Priviledges of his Enthusiastick Parliament,
to the Royalties of Holy Daddy; and this under the
specious pretence of their Liberties and Immunities, of
the <hi>Gallicane</hi> and other <hi>Iure Divino</hi> Grandees, though
he cannot for all that easily brook the Infallible Cheat;
yet should at this time of day go by the <hi>Elsabeth</hi> name of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98431:8"/>
Anti-Christ. He is a Man-Midwife, and hath been for
some years an Apprentice to Mother <hi>Celliers,</hi> yet affects
a singularity in the Mysterie; he would deliver the
Monster with the heels foremost, all Systems in Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie
he dislikes, as savouring of <hi>Wittemberg</hi> and the Lake
<hi>Lemaune,</hi> excepting this one concise and pithy one of
his own compiling, which as being a lover of the art
of climbing, he hath made in a Climax or Ladder, fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
thus; <hi>No Christnings, no Salvation, no Salvation, no
Grace, no Grace, no Bishops, no Bishop, no Salvation;</hi>
whence as clear as day light, Damnation to all <hi>Geneva</hi>
men. His Church is much to large for a British-head; for
of late it reaches from the Isles of <hi>Orcades,</hi> to the Grand
Seigniors <hi>Seraglio,</hi> and better fits the tearm of Fifth
Monarchy Monsieur, then of a Protestant English Prince.
He hath taken an Oath that his most Sacred Majesty,
(whom God for ever preserve from him and all false
Traitors) <hi>is in all causes and over all persons, in these
his Dominions, supream Head and Governour;</hi> and yet
would perfidiously advance into his place, a Juncto of
Forreign Mitre-men, wherein the very Pope if he'll but
for once disclaim Arbitrary power, and give his word to
be Civil, may preside in <hi>pontificalibus.</hi> In a word, he
is a servile Parasite, a proud Hector, the Cats foot to the
Jesuit, an underminer of Civil power, a Monopolizer of
base Spirits, a Disbeliever of Popish Plots, turns Faith
into Pollicie, Religion into Intreague, and Devotion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
Hypocrasie, Banters Heaven, abuses the World, and
betrays his Country.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Belfagor,</hi> thou art a Rogue, I never laughed so
heartily before; specious pretences, and Bantring of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
with a Rope to 'em. Well, the next.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Why, Sir, the next, for the sake of dearly
beloved Brotherhood, have so wrapt themselves up in one
another, that I cannot read them distinctly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:98431:9"/>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Why then let's have them as they are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>The Character of the <hi>Observator</hi> and <hi>Herae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clitus
Ridens.</hi> The one is a meer <hi>Fidler</hi> in Dialogues,
the other plays the <hi>Treble</hi> to his <hi>Base.</hi> They skin and
skarifie the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Oblivion,</hi> and teize about <hi>Forty One,</hi>
till they loose it, to get Twenty shillings a week. <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
all their deep Contemplations, and delving in the
Rubbish of the late times, the <hi>Observator</hi> keeps a great
bustle in the world, to prove there is as much pleasure
in borrowing discourse, as in stealing the affections of a
young Lady against the consent of her Parents. He is
one that tugs at the Labour Oare of Mischief, to turn
the head of Conscience with his Tide. He and <hi>Heracli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>
are the men, for whose sake <hi>Colledge</hi> may be in some
measure pittied, for lying under the lash and sweet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge
of their Nonsensical and inhumane Triumphs.
The <hi>Observator</hi> is one that <hi>Strange le</hi> thirsts and panteth
after <hi>Adoration</hi> in Coffee-houses, and is the very <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi>
of <hi>Sam</hi>'s in <hi>Ludgate-street;</hi> where because he takes
no Tobacco, he talks nothing but smoak. He and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclitus</hi>
have reason to shake hands, in regard their Tails
are so close tyed together, like <hi>Samsons Foxes,</hi> to fire the
Nation. Neither Truth, Honesty, Reason, nor right
Maxim of State do they consider, nor how to temper the
various mixtures in the variety of Opinions; suffering
themselves to be carried away with the stream of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
Transactions, and forgetting the rules of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession,
to which they both aspire, that there is <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi>
in <hi>Discord;</hi> which since it cannot be avoided, is
to be well and artificially bound and sweetned, not exas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated.
It may be questioned whether the <hi>Observator</hi>
and <hi>Heraclitus</hi> may not more truly be said to be the
<hi>Iack-puddings</hi> of the Nation, that play the Fool du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
the Fair-time, for the private advantage of them
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98431:9"/>
that set 'em at work; or the <hi>Ignes Fatui,</hi> that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
to lead the people astray with their false lights,
appearances of Reason only, and the evening-flashes
and dazlings of unpondred truth. They are the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Receptacles of <hi>Contribution Drollery.</hi> Were eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
Mans Name to his Conceit, their Pamphlets would
look like the Roll of Benefactors in <hi>Pauls,</hi> the true
experiment of the Proverb, <hi>Tot homines, quot sententiae.</hi>
It may be thought, that like <hi>Castor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> they
were hatch'd out of a <hi>Leda's Egg,</hi> while they make
such havock of Goosequils, and act the parts of offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<hi>Ganders</hi> over the rest of the vulgar flock: though
it is not to be imagined, that the <hi>Capitol</hi> of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale</hi>
should ever be saved by their clamorous imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nences,
yet they may be said to be like <hi>Mongrels,</hi> that
bark at <hi>Sowgelders.</hi> They are afraid of something by a
sympathetick Compunction, yet know not what to call
it. <hi>Tory</hi> and <hi>Whigg</hi> are the ground-work upon which
they lay the <hi>Purle</hi> and <hi>Embroidery</hi> of their fictitious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances.
With these implements, and other sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks
of distinction, they endeavour to raise a Civil
War in every private Familie, to break and dissolve
the harmless bonds of honest Society and Conversation,
and <hi>Guelph</hi> and <hi>Ghibelline</hi> the Nation into confusion.
Sometimes they are so confident as to name particular
persons, and barbarously let loose the detested custom
of the <hi>Vetus Comoedia,</hi> so long ago exploded by the
Civil <hi>Greeks,</hi> to worry the Reputation of those that
will not feed their humours. The Jesuit is now got a
t'other side, and frisks it in his wanton conceits, like a
fat Heifer in a rich pasture; and chuckles again to see
those that confounded his <hi>Real presence,</hi> and other shams
of his prophane Idolatrie, now reviling and tongue-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuting
those that hope for the joys of Eternity by a
better <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98431:10"/>'Tis true, they are very merrie, but still they play like
Melancholly Gamesters, the right hand against the left;
so that 'tis no wonder they should win all they throw at.
Only sometimes they get a Rub from <hi>Ludgate-hill,</hi> and
then they crie, Hoop, here's work for another week.
But as one passionate word in scoulding draws on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and the feud will never abate, while the heat and
Fury of the animosities is continued; therefore it were
to be wished, that care might be taken for the suppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of all those <hi>Goosequil Pickerers.</hi> They are base and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerate,
more swayed by <hi>Pence, G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inies,</hi> and <hi>Irish
Consciences,</hi> than by true Loyaltie or Reason. They
make no distinction between <hi>Dissenters</hi> out of <hi>Faction,</hi>
and <hi>Dissenters</hi> out of pure and Immaculate Consciences;
but run tempestuously upon a most undoubted Body of
the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> without exception. Masquera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
Champions, and it seems well paid for their <hi>Tilting.</hi>
They consider not, that though Reflexions upon Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
Princes are abominable, yet the sober and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
discourse of Libertie was always allowed.</p>
               <p>Besides, they can never be said to write well, who
are not able to justifie themselves to all the Inquisitions
of the Government wherein they live; therefore neither
the <hi>Observator</hi> nor <hi>Hera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>litus</hi> can be said to write well,
because the very noise of a Parliament terrifies them,
more than the ratling of Thunder did <hi>Caligula;</hi> it drives
the one again to his <hi>Batavian</hi> Sanctuary, and without
blast founders the <hi>Sayling Vessel</hi> with all its Cargo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Why these are fine fellows indeed! Well, but
how <hi>Belfagor</hi> did you find these Characters to agree with
the persons?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>All the observation I could make was this,
that they agreed well enough with some, but very ill
with others. They hit the humours of the vain and looser
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98431:10"/>
sort of the one, and the more designing and turbulent
of the other party, but never touched the rest, who are
of all the far greater number. So that all this paper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scuffling
seemed to me, to be only to amuse the Vulgar
and the Ignorant, and to raise a general combustion in
the Nation, to the end the State-Salamanders might se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
themselves in the flames. And for the Scriblers
themselves, those great Generals of so many Battalions of
Wast-paper, I leave to your Highnesses judgment, for
I am sure it will one day come to that, whether or no
they would not write for your Sootiness upon occasion,
being such as only for the present farm out their extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant
fancies, and lowly surrender themselves to be the
Tools of Mischief and Disorder for a little immediate
gain; wherein they are yet so unsuccessful, as not to gain
the least conquest upon men of Reason or Discretion.
Sir, did you ever hear of <hi>Forty One?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and was my self a great actor too at that
time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>And what does your Highness think of an
old, cunning, weather-beaten States-man, that should
go about to recover an Intreague in which he had once
lost himself, by the same measures, by the same beaten
road, and by the same trite and common artifices, still so
fresh in memory, that every ordinary Politician in power
would easily know how to obviate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>I should think him a fool, a meer fisher for Frogs,
that thinks to catch the Multitude again with a bait,
which they had swallowed already, so much to their
prejudice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Wherefore then so much noise with <hi>Forty
One?</hi> the stale, over-worn, thread-bare pretences of
which, are now known to every Apprentice; which
makes me think, that the <hi>Whiggs,</hi> men of deep profound
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98431:11"/>
consideration, and that have much to loose upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
must have newe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> studyed and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esined intreagues,
if any at all, than those of <hi>Forty One,</hi> or else it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible
that they should be guilty of those practices
which are laid to their charge; from whence it is as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible
they should ever dream for the least success,
while there is but two penny-worth of vigilancy over
'em.</p>
               <p>Besides, Sir, one thing more I observed in my Travels,
that before the <hi>Grand Plot,</hi> the <hi>Whiggs</hi> were accounted
good Subjects, had all the Gratious Complyance, Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
hearts, and open Purses, that could be wished for; so<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
that all things past seemed to be buryed in the grave of
oblivion. But no sooner was the <hi>Grand Plot</hi> of your
<hi>Hignesses Nephew the Pope</hi> discovered, but up starts <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
One</hi> in a Winding-sheet, and made such a noise i'the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>treets, that nothing could stand in competition with
it. Then it was that the Popish-landers, countenanced
by some of the greatest personages in <hi>Plotters-Island,</hi>
like the Hare, that never makes more doublings and
turnings, than when she hears the full cry of fields ring
the peal of Death in her ears, finding the <hi>Whiggs</hi> in
chase of their <hi>Plot,</hi> and still tracing it upon the hot scent
of fresh discovery, were resolved, if they could, to spoil
their noses, by strewing good store of pepper all along up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the trail. To this purpose they set up one of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
to thwart the first Discoverer, to contradict him,
teaze him, vex him, discountenance, discourage and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
him fallacious, an Impostor, and consequently ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous
to the people. Nay, he was so venturous, though
he durst not absolutely deny the <hi>Plot,</hi> in the Infancie of
its Discovery, as to fix it so for a time by his Libelling
Charms, that it seemed to hang in an airy doubt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
Truth and Untruth; like your Highnesses Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98431:11"/>
                  <hi>Mahomets</hi> Tomb between Heaven and Earth. But
his Magick spells being broken by the <hi>Grand Senate</hi> of
<hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lotters Island,</hi> it rested again upon the <hi>Terra firma</hi> of
the so much upbraided discovery, and then the <hi>Maggot</hi>
was forced to creep into a <hi>Holland-Cheese,</hi> for fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
brought to condign punishment. For the <hi>Grand Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi>
of the <hi>Island,</hi> notwithstanding all his little potions
of Intoxication, found, and adjudged it to be a <hi>Plot,</hi>
caressed the Discoverers, and prosecuted the Criminals
with that Noble Zeal, that your Highness well knows
the Harvest you have reaped thereby.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Ah <hi>Belfagor, Belfagor,</hi> a poor Wheatsheaf to
what I should have had, could the design have been
complicated, and I have had but my due!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>I confess it, most Fuscous <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ifer;</hi> I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
had that experience of your Justice, that you love
not to be named with the Innocent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot say so <hi>Belfagor,</hi> for the Nocent and
Innocent are all one to me. But I must needs say, when
the Innocent come in shoals, I have a far worse opinion
of them that send, than of those that are sent, as veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
believing there must be most devillish foul play i'the
case.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Thus far, Sir, as I have hinted before, all
the Treason, all the Ignominie, all the Shame, all the
Villany of the design, all the blame that your Highness
could have had, had you been guilty of it your self, lay
upon the necks and shoulders of the Popish-landers. All
which rendred them so abnoxious all over the world,
and made the burthen so heavie, which otherwise they
would have made no more of, than of a Larks feather, that
they resolved to rid themselves of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if it were possible
to be done by the art of Jesuits; and I was informed,
that they had sent a most splendid Embassie of Thirty,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98431:12"/>
thousand Masses and <hi>Ora pro Nobis's,</hi> and that your
Nephew the <hi>Pope</hi> had offered you the Restitution of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie,
to give your assistance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis very true, <hi>Belfagor,</hi> what you say, and
thereupon we advised with our <hi>Chief Iustice Rhadaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus</hi>
about it, who told us, they were a company of Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains
and Poltrons, and had so much craft and cunning
already, that if we lent them any more, we might
chance to rue the fatal effects of our kindness; and desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
us to beware the sad example of our Father <hi>Saturn.</hi>
Thereupon we excused our selves, by telling 'em, that
neither we nor our Royal Consort had ever been bred
to Church-Musick, and therefore had no kindness for it;
and that for their Exorcisms, we had now learnt more
wit than to fear 'em.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Then I believe that it was upon the return
of their Embassie, that they set up to work for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,
for presently they raised a hugeous high Mountain
which they called <hi>Forty One,</hi> out of the Mines of an old
Garrison long ago dismantled; from the top of which
they daily discharged whole Volleys of Invectives, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels,
Tales, Stories, Shams, Surmises, Calumnies, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
other such kind of paper-Squibs against the <hi>Whiggs,</hi>
to make a breach in the Reputation of the whole Party.
This was diligenrly carryed on by their two principal
Generals of the Artillery, <hi>Don Observatore,</hi> and <hi>Don He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclitus,</hi>
who have laboured at the Battery day and
night for some time. Truly, Sir, it behoov'd the Papists
so to do, for their necessities pressed hard upon 'em at
first, for the principal Provinces of <hi>Plotters Island,</hi> that
is to say, <hi>Tory-land, Whigg-land,</hi> and <hi>Tantivie-shire,</hi> were
against 'em, and the chief Governour of <hi>Iusticia</hi> was a
<hi>Whigg-lander,</hi> by whose admirable Courage and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct
the Plotters were every where overthrown, defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98431:12"/>
and cut off; which the <hi>Popish-landers</hi> seeing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved,
if possible, to gain him to their side; and at
length so far prevailed, that for a good round sum
he being very poor and in debt, surrendred up the
Garrison of <hi>Iusticia,</hi> into the hands of the <hi>Popish-landers,</hi>
by which means the Seer <hi>W.</hi> the Princess of
<hi>Mealtubia,</hi> and several other most Notorious Plotters
made their escapes, to the incredible joy and advantage
of the whole party; who animated with this success,
with a very numerous army of specious pretences, large
promises, slie insinuations, cunning perswasions, false
Oaths, crafty protestations, and Masqueraded counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits,
soon reduc'd a great part of <hi>Tory-land</hi> under their
subjection, and are now endeavouring the utter ruine
and devastation of <hi>Whigg-land,</hi> not doubting but to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine
the whole Plot, and so blow it upon <hi>Whigg-land;</hi>
to which purpose these <hi>Tory-land</hi> Pamphleteers,
like Moles, lie delving and digging unwarily in the
dark and obscure Mines of Jesuitism, little dreaming
that the Mines will at length fall upon 'emselves; nor
considering that whatever Interests or Prerogatives of
Princes the Popish-landers may pretend, <hi>Perae il mondo,
e ruina il cielo,</hi> is their Motto; they care not though
all the Interests and Prerogatives of all the Princes in the
world were utterly ranverst, so they may uphold their
own. And all this proceeds from the enormous pride
of the Clergy, who not enduring any Equals, much
less Superiours, would have all the world under their
girdles. And thus having given your most <hi>Illustrious
Sootiness</hi> the best account I can, of the hazards and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances
you will meet with in attempting upon the
Globe of the Earth, I again advise you to keep your
old station, where you live at ease, with full Command
and Dominion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98431:13"/>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Well, but is there no appearance of Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Truly, Sir, by what I observe, my opinion
is, there's little probability for't, so long as these Swarms
of Pamphleteers are suffered. For though Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
and Accusations upon just ground are always to
be allowed of, yet Calumnies are never to be endured
among a Free people; they only irritate, never chastize,
but are often made use of to justifie the effects of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Well then, if it be so, I'le keep where I am.
But are they all so sullen and morose? is there no mirth
among 'em?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Why, truly Sir, I'le tell ye, not long since,
I met with two merry Relations, the one among the
<hi>Tory-landers,</hi> the other among the <hi>Whigg-landers;</hi> the
first concerned a <hi>Whigg-lander,</hi> who had been poysoned
with the blast of an <hi>Irish</hi> Conscience, flown from the
breath of a randan <hi>Tantivie-man;</hi> that among the <hi>Whigg-landers</hi>
concerned a certain stripling in the Law, son, as
they said, to the late Governour of the Fortress of <hi>Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
who so publickly was degraded for his Misdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
and commonly called the <hi>Catholick Lawyer;</hi> I
was shewed him once in the street in a Coach, hung a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
with loose ratling Irons, which made a noise like
little Bells, which made me look to see what Coaches
followed him; because I had observ'd, that the foremost
of your Carriers Horses always travail with a Coller of
Bells about their necks; whether it were his pride or his
ambition, I can't tell; however, he got a name by it,
and is like to keep it, for they call him <hi>Gingling Will;</hi>
he pretends, they say, to be a second <hi>Mercurie</hi> for swift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
of heels, and swears he would have undertaken to
have kept pace with the Eagle that carryed <hi>Ganymed</hi> to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98431:13"/>
your Brother <hi>Iupiter.</hi> Insomuch, that he had like to have got on
of the best places in the Penny-post-Office, had he not spoiled his
preferment by the loss of a Match which he made to run with a
Tinker, both naked, for Three Guineys, all the length of the <hi>Pall
Mall</hi> in St. <hi>Iames</hi>'s Park.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>And you say <hi>Gingling Will,</hi> as you call him, did run this
Match.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, a'nt like your Highness, and the Tinker won it too
for the Tinker put the sham upon him, by disguising another more
nimble of foot to run it for him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>By <hi>Styx,</hi> when he comes into my clutches, I'le make him
run't over again, rather than I'le have a Catholick Councellor so
baffled by a Tinker.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>The same Relation informed me likewise, that as he was a
great Racer himself, so he thought it also convenient to keep a run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<hi>Nag.</hi> To which purpose when the Carter brought the Money
to pay his Father for the surrender of the Garrison of <hi>Iusticia,</hi>
the young Squire knocks off the hoops of one of the Firkins, cram'd
his pockets, and presently tript it away to the chief City of <hi>Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>land;</hi> thither being come, his Money burning in his breeches,
he repaired for a Cooler to a Reverend old Matron, whom your
Highness well knows, as having been long famous for sin and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
called <hi>Betty Buly.</hi> Oh, Sir, I cannot pass her by without an
<hi>Encomium;</hi> she has sent many a restless piece of young <hi>Kid,</hi> and
<hi>Barren Doe</hi> to your Royal Consorts Table; and for Sauce, many a
small Barrel of Gentlemens Pallats, and Tips of Noses, instead of
champignions, pickl'd in Decoctions of <hi>Guiacum</hi> and <hi>Sarsaperi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a.</hi>
To this good Lady the vertuous Squire, full of his Fathers tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
Gold, goes and proffers her five Guinies to procure him a
<hi>Virgin Intact.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Five Guineys, <hi>Belfagor?</hi> why, are Maidenheads so flush
i'that place, that the price is fallen so low? I ha' known the time
when a Mortal could hardly get one for love or money.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, Sir, the case is altered now, for old Mother <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi>
Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sie has almost <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rought it self about, with five or six Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
to one man. But she presently took the measure of his nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
Soul, and fitted him accordingly; for instead of a Virgin, she
brought him an old, cunnings, Gilting Whore, that infused such a
Pabylonish Contagion into him, that what between the Tinker and
the Harlot, he is unrecovered to this day, and finds enough to do
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98431:14"/>
to keep himself upon his l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gs. And which was worse, the story<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
breaking forth with the Dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>per, it was carried to his Clyents the
Imprisoned Lords, in the chief Castle upon <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tters Island,</hi> which
gave occasion to the Ladies in company, not only to laugh heartily,
but also to make Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lections upon his dole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul condition. While
one of them could not refrain from discovering the intended grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
of the whole part to the fools that serve them, saving, <hi>Though</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
So that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is much to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Highness will loose your old
acquaintance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; it being the vogue of all <hi>Plotters Island,</hi>
that she des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a Canoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing thus instrumental in
the Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tion of this little <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>I should have disown'd the old <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de</hi> for my Scholar, as
thou well knowst she was, had she done otherwise. Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s five pound
and a Crown!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>After this, Sir, and the swallowing of many a bitter
Potion, and many a long Quick-silver spit, the young Squire being a
little recruited, would needs go a swan-hopping after a young G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman
in the Country, whom under the pretence of Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
he had formerly made love to, and obtained her promise. But
that not being his design, he inveigled her up to the Chief City of
the Island, where at a penurious Treat, he took occasion to drench
her with such an Opiate Dose, that the young Damsel fell into a
sound sleep, in which condition she was put to bed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</speaker>
               <p>By <hi>Styx;</hi> a most <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xcellent way to take a Maid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nhead nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.
But now I think on't, my Cousin <hi>Hecate</hi> plaid her beloved
<hi>Endymion</hi> just such another trick, and enjoyed him in a dream. But
I'le tell thee <hi>Belfagor,</hi> there must be great care taken of this <hi>Spark</hi>
when he comes here; for he that will lye with a Maid in a dead
sleep, will not spare to lye with the dead themselves. And if my
Subjects should once get the trick on't, what a new generation of
Devils should we have? I tell thee the cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quences of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se things
are evil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Now, Sir, when the vertue of the Potion was spent, the
unvirgined Gentlewoman awak'd; but when she <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound how the
<hi>Gingling Squire</hi> had used her, grief and Despair threw her into those
desperate fits, that brought a most violent Feaver upon her; and
such a dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raction seized her for the loss of her Honour, that she
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98431:14"/>
could scarcely recover her former temper in Nine Months; at the
end of which she made a worse Discoverry, and there was no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing
the business, for she was with Child. And now your <hi>Sooti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi>
according to your wonted justice, expects to hear that <hi>Ging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
Will</hi> should have made her amends by Marrying her. But he
took the more gentle and modish way; he only kept her for a year
or two; then that she might partake with him as well in his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity,
as prosperity, for he gave her a bountiful proportion of
those marks of affection which he had received at <hi>Betty Buly</hi>'s, and
so dismissed her. And these, Sir, are your <hi>Tory</hi> ways of courting
and consummating their Amours. Then, Sir, for their valour, they
are very quarrelsome, especially upon the refusal of a Health.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Oh <hi>Belfagor,</hi> I have always observed, that Love and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
go together.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>No, not too much of Honour neither, for, may it please
<hi>your Highness,</hi> there are various tempers of men. Some valiant
men cannot endure to see a Cat; others will never stand ye with a
Custard at the Swords point. And thus it fares with our man o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
Honour; for he cannot endure an Oaken plant in a Countrymans
hand, called <hi>Dorathey,</hi> but if he sees it, sneaks into an Alley, and if
pursued, surrenders up his silver-hilted Sword to be pawn'd at dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion,
and redeem it if he think it worth his labour. But up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the refusal of a Health he takes another course; for then he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds
gradually, first he star<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ye i'the face, and cries Zounds, what
not drink the D's Health? then he throws a glass of Wine i'you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
face; and if this be not taken well, he takes up a glass Bottle, beats
a point of War upon your face, and presently breaks out two or
three of your Teeth. And, Sir, let me tell you, there is nothing so
frequent as these squabbles in <hi>Plotters Island;</hi> but they are very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous
to your Highnesses Quarter-ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er-generals my L. <hi>Sata<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
and my L. <hi>Belzebub.</hi> As for example, if any person denies to drink the
D. <hi>de P.</hi> Health, presently another cries <hi>Damme, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at not drink the
health? Damme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he shall drink it.</hi> So by the refusal of one Health<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
ten or twenty swinging assurances of Body and Soul to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll up the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
Chinks of <hi>Hell.</hi> And all this proceeds from the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ties which
are daily blown up and cherished by the Pamphlet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, those Tools
of the <hi>Iesuits,</hi> the <hi>Observator</hi> and <hi>Heraclitus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Well, here's enough concerning the Son; but what's now
become of the Father?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98431:15"/>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Your Highness means the Governour of the fortress of
<hi>Iustice.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I do so.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Then I'm right: Why, Sir, no sooner had he surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd
up that Fortress, (which he did for such a sum of money as
would have tempted your Highness your self,) but he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entrusted
to look after the utter demolishing of that Fort; wherein
he shewed himself so active, as if he had had a Spleen against that
lovely Palace. Against the detectors of the Plot, no man more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious
and inveterate; nay, a person could not appear to give Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
against a <hi>Popish-la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>der,</hi> but 'twas presently, <hi>Whipstaff, Tip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aff,</hi>
take that Rog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and cast him into the Dung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on of <hi>Banco prisoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi>
which was no sooner said but done. But to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opish-landers,
no man more condescending, more soft, patient, and more indulgent:
to the Princes of <hi>Mealetubia,</hi> like <hi>Pyramus</hi> to <hi>Thisbe;</hi> to the Baron of
<hi>Astonaria,</hi> like <hi>Pylades</hi> to <hi>Orestes:</hi> And so a great part of the Walls
of the <hi>Fortress</hi> fell down: And doubtless it had been totally ruin'd,
had not the great Senate of <hi>Plotters Island</hi> opposed his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oceedings.
So that he was at length sent into the Countrey with a thing called
<hi>a Quietus e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t,</hi> to enjoy what he has so bas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly got, with the Curses of
the <hi>Islanders.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>I hope he does not now lye quiet, and study R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntance;
'sfoot he's a fat gobbet, I would not miss him for any thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and deserves to be severely handled for certain
Treasonable words, which I am informed he spoke against y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur
Highness, not long since.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>What words?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Why, Sir, he said, Dam me.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Well, what hurt in that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>None, Sir; but he said further, <hi>I demolished the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
Colemannia <hi>in spight of the Court; I delivered up the Fort of</hi> Wak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannia
<hi>in spight of the City, and I will be Governou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Fortr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Iusticia still, in spight of the Devil.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>Bid our Attorney-General take particular notice of this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>The sooner the better, Sir, for he begins to droop.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>How know you that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>By his own confession, Sir, for quoth he at the same time,
<hi>Though I am an Old fellow, and cannot drink, swear, fight and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re
so well as formerly I could, yet I have a Son that is</hi> Castor <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lux,
two in one skin,</hi> that can and shall do all together, to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rve the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98431:15"/>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>-landers.</hi> And then straining the point a little fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther, he th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s
proceeded: <hi>I have two Daughters also that shall perform their parts at
all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se accomplishments of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dish Galla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ry.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>A my word <hi>Belfagor,</hi> this Governour understands trap;
thou knowst 'tis our way to have our Temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ions ready for a brisk
opportunity. But if he don't being himself into play, both his Sons
and his Daughters too will be soon forgot. For the Sons of such
p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rsons, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou know, like the Sons of Parsons, seldome come to good,
and their Daughters are as little, regarded after their Fathers are laid
aside, and are consequently dead either in their authority, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ased
to us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, Sir, he has been endeavouring to glister in the
world again. And to that purpose, believing a <hi>Privy-Councellors</hi> place
might have been bought, offered some of his <hi>Popish-landers Gold</hi> for
the Imployment; but the impudent and impolitick offer rendred
him so despicable and unfit for so high a dignity among Mortals, that
they say <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he bit off both his Thumb-nails for madness that he had
committed such an Errour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <p>And well he might: he a Privy-Councellor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by <hi>Styx,</hi> that
Prince would be well served that makes use of him; he a Privy-Councellor!
he a Wine-Porter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belfagor.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, Sir, but this is not all; I was informed by my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Ramballat,</hi> who was either your Agent that conducted the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
that carried the Cordial Mass, or else Tempter-General to the
Governour in your behalf, who was present at a discourse that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
between a certain <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>sieur, Mons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ur Fran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is,</hi> who was Agent
in <hi>Plotters Island</hi> for the Soveraign of <hi>Francia,</hi> and the <hi>Popish-lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi>
It was in the Summer-time, when the decl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing Sun had
spread the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erth with the long shades of several tall Elms, that were
guarded from the brousing Cattle with s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndry sweet-smelling brakes.
Then I say it was, when Monsi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur <hi>Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is,</hi> and the Governour of
the Fortr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ss of <hi>Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ticia,</hi> wearied with Travail, or else to rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ate
their tired cogitations, had lain themselves down undiscovered from
each other; when on a suddain, Monsieur <hi>François</hi> disburth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning,
his mind to himself, uttered these words: <hi>By my Arbitrary power I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e
make him Absolute ere I return. Arbitrary? Absolute,</hi> quoth the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour,
why that's the thing I have been driving at; and present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
spying Monsieur <hi>Fran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is,</hi> made up to him, and with his broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brimm'd
Hat, and bended brows, accosted him. Who art thou,
quoth <hi>Monsieur Fran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ois?</hi> Why, I am that late famous Knight, the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98431:16"/>
Governour of the Fortress of <hi>Iusticia.</hi> To which Monsieur <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cois</hi>
replyed, O, ho, <hi>Bon jour, bon jour, Monsieur le Governur.</hi> Pray
speak English, Sir, quoth the Governour, for I have burnt my Tongue
already with learning to speak French. Thereupon my Brother
<hi>Ramballat</hi> was chosen to be Interpreter between them, so they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
and went on as follows.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur Francois.</speaker>
               <p>Why, man, what's the matter, are all things
turn'd topsie turvie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>So it seems, <hi>Monsieur:</hi> But did not you talk of <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,</hi>
and <hi>Absolute,</hi> just now?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Yes I did, and what then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Why because I was an Aslertor of the disquieted Title
to <hi>Plotters Island,</hi> which the <hi>Whigglanders</hi> call'd Crime, and an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring
to set up <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>Absolute</hi> Power.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>En bien, was that all your crime? that may be mine
too for ought I know; for such is my business, and I am not to stir,
until it be effectually done: But I have the Cash, the Cash, man, and
that alone will do the work at long run.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Cash, what Money?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Yes Money, the very Life and Nerves of Intrigue and
Design, the very weapon by which my Master hath made all those
great Conquests which he now enjoys; and by which, if he lives
but a few years longer, he'll subdue the whole World.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>How unhappy have I been, that could not be sooner
accquainted with you; perhaps I might have been serviceable, and
I'm sure his Coyn would have been acceptable enough to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>No matter, 'tis not too late yet; though you are out of
Power, yet your advice may be serviceable, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you'll come in for
your share at that, I'll take care to procure you a Pension.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Agreed, Monsieur <hi>Francois,</hi> with all my heart, and
bring my Son in too; for of Idleness comes nothing, 'tis the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
hand gets the pence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Your Son, I know him, he's a thick-s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul'd, hot-headed,
sottish Clown, that can do us little good, unless it be to go now
and then to Coffee-houses, and Huff, Swear, Ram and Dam against
the <hi>Whigglanders,</hi> and that will scarce do neither, for they are grave,
sober, serious, warie Sophisters, that must be handled gently, by
men of Parts, learned, affable, and obliging, not by the heats and
feuds of Ninnies and Fools.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:98431:16"/>
               <speaker>Governour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </speaker>
               <p>However, you see my good-will to your Cause. But
what sort of employment must mine be, and what my Pension?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Your employment must be at all, and your Pension
according as you deserve.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>By my troth this is very hard, though 'twas once in
my power to have made my own tearms, but now it seems I must,
be forc'd to come in upon yours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Ay, and a good shift too. But in short I'll tell you the
design, provided you will be sworn to secrecy, and then you will be
able to guess whether or no you can do us any service.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis agreed, I am sworn, now go on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Why, I suppose you have heard of my Masters preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
to the Dukedome of <hi>Burgundy, Luxemburg,</hi> &amp;c. All which is
as good as his own al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eady; you cannot but have heard likewise,
that he hath broke the <hi>Nimmeghen League</hi> by the taking of <hi>Stras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi>
why now he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esolves to fall upon <hi>Flanders,</hi> which he
hath reason to think himself pretty secure of: For though we have
been seemingly asleep, under a Notion of Peace, yet our powerful
Coyn hath been moving in all parts of the World, but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
in <hi>Flanders,</hi> where we have made so many of the <hi>Spanish</hi>
Officers our own, that whenever my Master pleases to draw his
Sword.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Draw his Sword, why must there be fighting again?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, a little for the colour of the thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Your Master is the devil of a man, he Conquers more
in the times of Peace, than all the European Princes besides can do,
by the greatest face of War they are able to make.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>And therefore he is so much the more to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>No, pardon me for that, Sir, pray where are the brave
and Heroe-like Feats of War? I find nothing but what's done by
<hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eachery,</hi> and Princes gul'd out of their Countries under the Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of Peace; which sort of Actions among Princes and Kings, are
of all others most base and mean.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>But if you prate at this rate, <hi>Monsieur</hi> le Governour,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are well, for I cannot endure.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, hold Sir, if you will not hear what I can say a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst,
as well as for, the Interest of your Master, how can you think
that I shall understand my business, or ever be able to serve him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>That's true.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:98431:17"/>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Then pray go on, but you must give me leave to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt
you sometimes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Why, when we are once in possession of <hi>Flanders,</hi> you
know what Inroads and other great advantages we have upon the
<hi>Vnited Provinces,</hi> so that they shall be constrained for their own safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
either to put themselves under my Masters protection, or else be
liable to have their whole Country Marched over when frozen, and
burnt, or set under water and ruined in a short time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>What then? what have I to do with all this? you know
that I am an old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ellow, and can't go abroad.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onsieur.</speaker>
               <p>I thought you a more judicious man, that's not required
of you, you must hear this and a great deal more, or else you'l never
understand any thing. This is the Scheme of my Masters Affairs
all over the world, and will you not hear it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, yes, pray go on, Sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Why, when we are secured from the danger of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
have taken in <hi>Savona, Geneva,</hi> and some other as considerable
Garrisons in those parts, which my Master hath now intitled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
to, by taking in <hi>Casal,</hi> when he hath procured his Son to be
Crowned King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> the thing he hath so long desir'd,
and either secur'd his Alliances with the <hi>Dane, Swede, Brandenburgh,</hi>
and some other of the <hi>Palatinate</hi> Princes, or put them into a state
of N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utrality: When he shall have brought the Malecontents of
<hi>Hungaria</hi> under the protection of the <hi>Turk,</hi> and secur'd him by an
Offensive and Defensive League, by that time my Master hopes his
Interest here may be so considerably increas'd, that it may be worth
while to bring a considerable Fleet of men of War into the narrow
Seas, to block up the Mouth of the River of <hi>Thames,</hi> and turn
the whole Trade into <hi>Holland,</hi> the East Country, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lsewhere, and
so having sufficiently weakned you, at once to pour into the bowels
of your Country an Army of Eighty or a hundred thousand men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>But if your Master do all this, what occasion is there
for such an interest to be made here, as you seem to desire?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, very material, for my Master never strikes till he be
secured every way, and therefore a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> well-insinuated interest here,
would be of great moment at such a juncto, when my Master should
Invade you; and in order thereunto, I am sent over to promote a
right understanding amongst all our Friends, and to see that such
as can be serviceable may have Pensions setled upon 'em. But as
for those that only pretend, and do us no service, as there are many
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98431:17"/>
such, they must e'en pack off; for my Master hath spent vast sums
of Money about this Affair already, and resolves to be bubbl'd out
of no more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Why now you're come to the point: But how are
those Pensions to be paid? have you a Fund here?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and have had one for several years past.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Well then, pray tell me wherein I can contribute to
the advancing your Masters Interest here, how the posture of your
Affairs stands, and who are your principal Friends. Unless I know
this, I can do you but little service. I finde you are no stranger to
my Affairs; and therefore you well knowing how much I have
been exposed already, I hope you will allow me instruments to work
at a distance with.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>We expect from you nothing so much as Advice in
points of Law, and in which we must be concern'd sometimes. As
for our Interest here, 'tis totally wrap'd up in the-so-much-disputed
Succession; and what that does, gives life and being to our designs.
The immediate posture of our Affairs, seems to be very secure, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
having more largely contributed thereto, than the late Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions
in <hi>Scotland;</hi> which to our best view hath brought all things
to a Crisis: so that all depends now upon a Senate here, that may
be as fit for our purpose as that in <hi>Scotland</hi> hath been.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>And how to procure that, is the great thing of all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>You're i'the right on't, <hi>Monsieur le Governour,</hi> and that
I believe will be your Task; which if you can but obtain, will not
onely give you the whip-hand of all your Whigland Antagonists, but
make your name great and famous to Posterity: for the time is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming,
according to the common Proverb in <hi>France, Vn Dieu, un Roy,
un Religion,</hi> over all the World; and if you can conttribue any
thing to this, happy will be the hour you were born in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>I'll do what I can. But I did desire to know your
Masters principal Friends that are concerned in this great Affair.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>All that will follow of course by and by.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Well then, what is it you would expect from a <hi>Senate</hi>
here, if it were possible to get one for your Masters purpose?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, I'll tell you. We should be modest enough: for
all our desire at present is, onely to procure a <hi>Bill</hi> for fixing the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession
on <hi>D. de P.</hi> another for <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> or Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
as some term it; a third, an Act of Oblivion or Indemnity; to
make room for which, we are endeavouring to render the <hi>Whig-landers</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:98431:18"/>
as criminal to the <hi>Senate,</hi> as the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> have been<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
and fourth, to prohibit all our Country-Commodities.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>As for the three first, I understand 'em well enough;
but what can you get by the last?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Why if a general Prohibition should pass upon all ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
Country-goods, and my Master have at the same time the command
of the Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, it would be an excellent colour to block up your River, as
I told you before, and turn your Trade another way; nay, it might
be a Shooi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g-horn to draw on a War between the two Crowns.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>But how do you think we shall be able to bring this
matter to pass, so as to have a <hi>Senate</hi> for our purpose?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, for that I'll tell you, <hi>Monsieur le Governour,</hi> you
have many Drinking Corporations; and some of 'em being well
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly'd with good Beef, Bag-pudding, Wine, Beer, Brandy, and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco,
cannot fail for some of our Friends, more especially if we
take but the least care to make the more mercenary part of 'em ours.
We are no niggards of our Money in those cases. This being done
according to our usual way of doing business, warily, will so en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hance
the Expences of the Competitors, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>Senate</hi> be called
but once in every year, according to our expectation, we shall so
win upon the Multitude by our Generosity, that it will be impossible
to fail of carrying all before us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>And then what fine sport will it be to find the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors
swindg'd off by Laws of their own making and consent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, that's not all; for we have this advantage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides;
There are many Gentlemen who serve for such Drinking
Corporations, whose Estates are not worth above five of six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> and out of that they have great Families
to maintain; so that the spending of a years Rent (as some of 'em
must do, if we take any care) once a year about their Elections,
for four or five years together, will so tire 'em, that they shall be
glad to lay down the Cudgels.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>In that, I believe you're right, Sir: but perhaps all of
'em may not quit the point so.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>No matter: As for those that will not, they must be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coasted
with great Offers and Advantages, and some considerable
Pensions for the time present; and these Offers with Necessities, are
great Temptations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>I know it full well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>And that person who has but five hundred pounds <hi>per
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98431:18"/>
Annum,</hi> and has been forc'd to spend it all about his Election, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
may be glad to snap at a Crust of 1000 l. <hi>per Annum,</hi> either to
decline the thing, or else to stand bound by promise to serve our
turn, and have all his Election-charges born besides.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Aye sure, a man would think so; but how long shall
such a Pension be made to continue payable?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Till the <hi>Senate</hi> have done our business.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>No longer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>No longer, no: Why do you think, <hi>Monsie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r le Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi>
that my Master intends to keep 'em in pay as long as they live?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and reason good too, I think, where a man must
hazard his <hi>All</hi> to serve him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Perhaps some few may be so paid, as your self, and, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
but my life for yours, my Master knows better, than to continue his
Bribes to all of 'em: He loves the Treason, but hates the Traytor
after he hath serv'd him; as his usage to the Governour of <hi>Messina</hi>
doth demonstrate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>What a fine condition had our last Pensionary-<hi>Senate</hi>
then been in, according to this account! But, Sir, do you think that
any Gentleman will be prevailed with to betray his King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
his Life and Fortune, his Religion, his Liberty and Property, for
a Song?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, believe it, yes: for you your self have made an
observation on the late Pensionary-<hi>Senate,</hi> and that's true enough:
for those Pensioners would have done all that, and a great deal more,
and yet they were very honest Gentlemen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Gentlemen, do you call 'em! what and so qualified!
Pray where's their Honour?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Pish; that you of all men living should ask such a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion!
Why Honour's laid aside then: for such a man must have no
Fortune, no Religion, no Honesty, no value for his own Life; and
such Qualifications as these, goes far in our business.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>You may expect from 'em long enough, I doubt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
you'll find your business done by such men in these parts: Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
more Northernly such a thing might take; but here—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Why now I find you are totally against me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>No, no, Sir; 'tis onely my unhappiness, that I cannot
be rightly, understood; I onely make Objections for my own satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction:
I am yours fast <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nough; but you must allow me to scruple
Niceties sometimes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98431:19"/>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Any reasonable thing, for your better information, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Why then suppose the Pretensions of your Maste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
(which you told me of just now) to <hi>Luxemburg, Burgundy</hi> &amp;c. should
prove a Fallacie, his interest in <hi>Flanders</hi> thrown out of doors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by
that means be put by those <hi>Inroads and great Advantages</hi> which he
expects to have into the <hi>Vnited, Provinces:</hi> Suppose they should
have no regard to, but rather slight his Protection: Suppose he
should, instead of taking in <hi>Savona, Genoa,</hi> and those other conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
places in them parts, which he now seems to have such a vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant
eye upon, and pretends such great right to, meet the <hi>Lati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
Princes</hi> united, and in a considerable posture of defence, ready to
oppose him: And suppose the <hi>Dane, Swede, Brandenburg,</hi> &amp;c. should
Ally with the <hi>Emperour,</hi> the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>States General,</hi> &amp;c.
And suppose you find the <hi>Malecontents</hi> of <hi>Hungaria</hi> reconciled to, and
under the protection of the <hi>Emperour.</hi> What would his invading of
<hi>England</hi> be worth then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>O fie, <hi>Monsieur le Governour,</hi> you talk at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> strange rate
now, and of such impossibilities,—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Why suppose the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> should send out a Fleet of
Men of War, some to examine your Masters power concerning the
Mountain which he is raising in the Sea before <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> others to
batter down the Castle wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch he is building in the Air at <hi>Marselles,</hi>
and to burn the Ships both there and at <hi>Tholose?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>These are more improbable, and but your own wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring
surmises, without the least ground. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut allowing all those
Alliances, and much more, yet if they have not <hi>England</hi> in with
'em, we remain still s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>How so?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>By our League; which I am of opinion they will not
adventure to break. Then as for the <hi>Emperour,</hi> though he should in
heat strike up an Agreement with the <hi>Malecontents,</hi> still we can call
the <hi>Turk</hi> into his Territories, as we use to do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Why, hath your Master such an interest in the <hi>Turk?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, yes, an entire League: Did you never hear of that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Surely the Devil is in him. Well, go on, pray, Sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Why the <hi>Turk</hi> will be able enough to divert the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,</hi>
having our Country to friend for all manner of Provisions
for War; and as for those his Allies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my Master will undertake him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.
As for the <hi>Latin Princes,</hi> have we not the Assistance of our
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98431:19"/>
Holy Father the <hi>Pope,</hi> when my Master pleases to require it? and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s
not <hi>Casal</hi> our own? and are not the <hi>Latins</hi> most grievously vexed
with the Plague? and is it not known to all the World, how vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
and different their interests are, like the Princes <hi>Palatine?</hi>
Therefore I say, all these things well considered, any reasonable Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lititian
would think that an Army of 20000 Horse and Foot that are
experienc'd, and well disciplin'd men, some for burning, others for
pillage and plundring, being in the very bowels of an Enemies Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
should in a short time make such havock, and bring such an awe
upon the spirits of the people, that they should be glad to take a
Protection, or a Peace upon any terms.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Why, but still there's the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniard,</hi> all the world knows his poverty, and
how unfit he is to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fend either by Sea or Land; and then his late
Match with <hi>Madam,</hi> and some other as prevailing Checks, which
his Necessities make him liable to, will divert him another way.
But notwithstanding all that, let him strike up his Alliance with the
<hi>Hollander, Dane, Swede,</hi> &amp;c. which before they can bring to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
my Master will have fetch'd in <hi>Flanders</hi> in spight of their teeth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Nevertheless, I doubt your Master has lick'd a Bur in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Throat of his Policks, by having to do with so much Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
at once, whose whole Countries are at stake. And again, have
they not at least two Millions of Friends (the <hi>Hugonots</hi>) in the
very heart of your Masters Country; besides vast stores of Men,
Money, Shipping, and all other Necessaries for War? Pray, Sir, do
you but state this to any reasonable Polititian, and I'll undertake he
shall tell you, Your Masters Affairs stand but in a bad posture; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
less than, his total Ruine can follow, if <hi>England</hi> be prevailed
with to ally.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Pish, why that can never be done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>No truely, I fear it very much: for I'm sure if they
do but consult Policy and their common Safe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, it must bring 'em
in, more especially at such a time as this is, when the greatness of
your Master threatens all the World with nothing but Vassalage and
Destruction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Policy! Why pray when do you find <hi>English-men</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulting
of Politicks, till it be upon the matter too late, or some great
trouble or misfortune threaten them? But besides, if they should en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
upon such Consults, perhaps it's now too late: for <hi>D. de P.</hi> hath so
much gain'd the ascenda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, that if he please, there's but few thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
can miss his party.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98431:20"/>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>That's in the North onely: but take my word for't,
the <hi>Whiglanders</hi> are too numerous and stubborn, to be swayed by his
interest, which runs so counter to their being.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>However, his interest in the North joyn'd to that which
is here, and the <hi>Irish</hi> joyn'd to both those, will do the Trick still, if
well manag'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Why I hope you don't intend all this during the Kings
Life?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Yes but I do though, if my Master should <hi>have occasion</hi>
to invade <hi>England,</hi> as he had to take in <hi>Strasburg:</hi> But if not, <hi>D.
de P.</hi> does the thing himself of course, if he survive. And as for
your Observation just now, that my Master hath two Millions of
<hi>Hugonots</hi> in the heart of his Country, I object against that as not
true: for above the half of'em are run away into other Countries
to shun the Persecution, as they term it. And as for those which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
behind, my Master is taking care they shall do him no hurt.
But when I have said all this, and much more, how do you know
but <hi>D. de P.</hi> has as great a number of <hi>Dark-lanthorn Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi>
here in the hearts of these Kingdoms?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Truly all I can say, if it be so, is bad enough; for
according to that account, whenever your Master pleases to invade
us, the <hi>Whiglanders,</hi> and <hi>Torylanders</hi> too, may have their Throats
very decently cut by their own Countrymen. But you were say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
more than half the <hi>Hugonots</hi> were ran away; and as for the
rest, your Master intends to take care they shall do him no hurt: pray
what does he intend to do with 'em?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Burn 'em, cut their Throats by way of Massacre, as they
call it; it's all for the good of the Catholick cause, man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, Sir, 'tis a bad cause which must be served by inu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations
of Blood; and your Master must be a Devil incarnate, that
can endure to wallow in the Blood of so many innocent Subjects.
For my part, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cannot understand any reasonable excuse that can be
made for him; or why so many hundred thousands of Souls should
be made a Sacrifice to his insatiate Tyranny.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>You'l never leave, <hi>Monsieur le Governour,</hi> till you spoil all;
you are very much mistaken: 'tis sore against the will and Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
of my Master, that such cruel Edicts should be publisht against
the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> but—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>How? sore against his Conscience? that's still worse,
why does he know it to be so, and yet persist? pray who p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts him
upon it then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:98431:20"/>
               <speaker>Mons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eur.</speaker>
               <p>Why the Jesuits, to be reveng'd for the persecution
which hath been here against the <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Say ye so? Blood! Revenge! by the Jesuits! and
does their Religion teach 'em that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Now you come with your Querks and Queries again;
why you know it does, as well as I do; and that the thing which
they call Religion, is a constitution Politick only of their own, which
desires and delights in having the ascendant over, and influencing
all the Kings and Princes in the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Why our <hi>Saviour Christ</hi> taught no such Doctrine, and
yet they pretend to be his Followers, and assume the Name of <hi>Iesus;</hi>
but do they influence your Master?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and he moves now, and hath done so ever since
the death of <hi>Mazarine,</hi> that is, only by the wheel of their Politicks.
They are, and have been a considerable time, perswading of my
Master to quarrel with the Pope.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>What will they get by that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Why they have had a great itching at the Chair<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ever<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <hi>Ignatius Loyola's</hi> time; and because they cannot come to it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly,
they hope to prevail with my Master to set up a <hi>Patriarc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate</hi>
in his own Countrey, and to choose the Patriarch out of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety;
but he sees into the bottom of this design, and will take bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
measures than to give them the upper hand of him, as they will
be sure to have, should he comply with 'em in that Affair.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>How? why is this the design? this clearly alters the
Popes Ecclesiastical Government, and sets up a new Model. These
mens Politicks will not only destroy both your Master and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,
but all that have to do with 'em. For according to their
Morals, no Prince in the world can ever be safe that corresponds
with 'em.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>No, no, now you're as much out again the tother ways<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
pray let us hold to our business.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Then pray satisfie me in this point; if <hi>England</hi> should
break the Leagne with your Master, and Ally with <hi>Holland, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>I'le tell ye, we have a reserve for that; for if we find
<hi>England</hi> that way inclin'd, we have those which will u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dertake up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
forfeiture of their Heads, to throw a bone between them, and
soon set them together by the ears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>How, what that way too? that would be fine work
indeed, and i'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Conscience feazable enough!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:98431:21"/>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis very certain, 'twill be done if we find our League
with <hi>England</hi> strain'd; and I'le ingage they shall be continued so
too, till my Masters work's done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>How, will you engage for the continuance of a War?
how can that be?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Why there's a certain <hi>Bannocklander,</hi> who is said to
have engag'd himself in the most sacred ties imaginable to serve my
Master; and we are well assured of his care about Officers, and
State-Ministers, so that in a short time,—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governor.</speaker>
               <p>In a short time, the <hi>Turk</hi> and your Master will subdue
the whole world, and divide it between 'emselves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>No, no, that's your mistake again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>How then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Why my Master will have all or none: for though he may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained
to use the Turk, yet you may be sure he'll give him <hi>Polyphemus</hi>'s Law,
devour him last, for he hates Compet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tors.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>But allowing a War between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d all your
Masters designs to take effect upon that, so as to give him the Conquest upon
both, pray what must <hi>D. de P.</hi> be?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>My Masters Vice-Roy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Where?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Here in these Kingdoms.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>And is that all he makes this bustle for? for my part I cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand
his politicks, for methinks it should be much better to be King,
though of a limited <hi>Monarchy,</hi> then to be <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> to a <hi>King Absolute &amp; Arbitrary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>That's true, but <hi>D. de P.</hi> has so over-acted his part, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
arrive at neither, without my Masters help.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>So that now it seems he must be contented with what your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster
will give him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Give him! no no, 'tis supposed to be his own choice, as having
declar'd, <hi>He would rather become a</hi> Vice-Roy <hi>to a Forreign power, though the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
Tyrant on Earth, than truckle to such who ought to be his Slaves and Vassals.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>My thinks, 'tis impossible he should speak such words.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis so reported, by those that pretend to know much.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Then I have been doing fine things indeed, who have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d as
for my own life to advance his Interest, which as you say, now proves to be
your Masters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Ay, but 'tis now too late to be sorry for that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Is it so? well then over boots over shooes; I'le rather choose
to die honourably, than live basely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>Why that's well resolved; 'tis Meritorious, and you dye in the
Service of the Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Governour.</speaker>
               <p>Then 'tis a bargain, but you told me I should have an account
of your Masters principal friend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Monsieur.</speaker>
               <p>You shall know those in due time; I have better considered of
that, and therefore desire to be excused till our next Meeting. <hi>Adieu Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur le Governour, Adieu.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98431:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
