<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A poem occasioned on the death of Mr. Henry Purcell, late musician in ordinary to His Majesty by a lover of music.</title>
            <author>Lover of music.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55240</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24058</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07944551</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07944551</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40629</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A55240)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40629)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1211:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A poem occasioned on the death of Mr. Henry Purcell, late musician in ordinary to His Majesty by a lover of music.</title>
                  <author>Lover of music.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Whitlock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Purcell, Henry, 1659-1695 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Elegiac poetry --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:40629:1"/>
A POEM Occaſioned on the Death of Mr. Henry Purcell, Late Muſician in Ordinary To His MAJESTY.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quocunque choros agitat mors Muſica dormit.</l>
               <bibl>Bat.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By a Lover of Muſick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Whitlock,</hi> near Stationers-Hall, MDCXCVI.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40629:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40629:2"/>
            <head>A POEM On the Death of Mr. <hi>Henry Purcell,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>YE Gentle Sphears</l>
               <l>Ceaſe now your wonted melody,</l>
               <l>Reſt and ever ſilent be—</l>
               <l>Nought now remains for Comfort or Relief,</l>
               <l>But a free vent to our juſt ſource of grief.</l>
               <l>An untaught Groan beſt language is,</l>
               <l>For ſuch a diſmal Scene as This.</l>
               <l>Yet like the dying Swans you firſt may tell,</l>
               <l>In ſofteſt Muſick to attending Ears,</l>
               <l>How the Lov'd <hi>Strephon</hi> liv'd, and how lamented fell:</l>
               <l>Tell then th' admiring World how often He,</l>
               <l>Has ev'n charm'd you to exſtaſie,</l>
               <l>How oft you've envy'd at the praiſe he won,</l>
               <l>Yet ſmil'd to ſee your ſelves out done.</l>
               <l>Tell this in diff'rent Notes, in ſuch as he,</l>
               <l>Was us'd to charm us hear below, that make one Harmony.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:40629:3"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>The little Birds throughout the Plains,</l>
               <l>Repeat their Notes in doleful Strain.</l>
               <l>In doleful ſtrains they all complain</l>
               <l>As if they never were to Sing again.</l>
               <l>Sad <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>omel</hi> amongſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he reſt</l>
               <l>As if ſome Story <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he relate,</l>
               <l>Not of her own, but of her Maſters cruel Fate,</l>
               <l>In mornful Notes her grief expreſt,</l>
               <l>In careleſs melancholy Lays</l>
               <l>She <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng his Praiſe.</l>
               <l>Now all her Art ſhe trys,</l>
               <l>Now all her Strength applys,</l>
               <l>To warble forth an Elegy</l>
               <l>Sacred to his Memory.</l>
               <l>She Sings, alas her Songs are all in vain,</l>
               <l>Nothing can alter Deſtiny,</l>
               <l>The Swain can ne're return to life again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>What do I hear, what diſmal Groans,</l>
               <l>What Sights, what Shreiks, what melancholy Moans,</l>
               <l>Now ſpread themſelves o're all the Penſive Plains,</l>
               <l>And tears the breaſts of all the tender Swains,</l>
               <l>'Tis for <hi>Strephon</hi> Dead and gone.</l>
               <l>Mourn all ye Shepherds, mourn with me your Maſters Fall,</l>
               <l>With me attend his Funeral,</l>
               <l>With me adorn his Herſe</l>
               <l>With never fadeing Garland, never dying Verſe.</l>
               <l>Alas! no Sounds will now prevail,</l>
               <l>To tell their melancholy Tale,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40629:3"/>
Since dead is He who made their Songs to live,</l>
               <l>He their dull numbers could inſpire,</l>
               <l>With charming Voice, and tuneful Lyre,</l>
               <l>He life to all, but to himſelf could give.</l>
               <l>No longer now the Swains unto each other play,</l>
               <l>Their Arms a croſs, their Heads hung down,</l>
               <l>Their Oaten Pipes, beſides them thrown,</l>
               <l>Their Flocks neglected ſtray,</l>
               <l>Ev'n <hi>Pan</hi> himſelf o'rewhelm'd with grief, has thrown his Pipe away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>See Love himſelf all bath'd in Tears,</l>
               <l>His Bow he brakes, away his Darts he flings,</l>
               <l>Then folds his Arms, and hangs his drooping Wings,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> her ſelf cloſe mourner here appears.</l>
               <l>No longer now ſhe thinks her ſelf ſecure,</l>
               <l>But ſighing from her Throne looks down,</l>
               <l>Her greatneſs cannot long endure</l>
               <l>Since it's ſupporter's dead and gone;</l>
               <l>Since that the tuneful <hi>Strephon</hi>'s Fall'n—</l>
               <l>Now ſilent lyes his Lyre,</l>
               <l>No longer warms our hearts into deſire,</l>
               <l>For dead is he who could our Paſſions move,</l>
               <l>Who beſt could gentle thoughts inſpire,</l>
               <l>Who beſt could fan the amorous fire,</l>
               <l>Make us at once ſubmit, and own the Pow'r of Love.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Gone is the glory of our Age,</l>
               <l>The Pride and Darling of the Stage.</l>
               <l>The Theatre his worth well knew,</l>
               <l>Saw how by him it's greatneſs grew.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:40629:4"/>
In him their honour Pride and Glory liv'd,</l>
               <l>Far as his Soul they now are fled,</l>
               <l>And ſcarce can ſooner be retriev'd,</l>
               <l>For all their hopes in him are dead.</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt he vouchſaf'd to ſtay below</l>
               <l>They were too bleſt long to continue ſo.</l>
               <l>But oh! no more the tuneful <hi>Strephon</hi>'s Songs they'l hear,</l>
               <l>No more his joyful Notes will glad the wondring Theatre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>Ye Sons of <hi>Phebus</hi> write his Elegy</l>
               <l>But let it be</l>
               <l>Great as the Subject, ſad as your Calamity,</l>
               <l>Let every Muſe his Praiſe aloud proclaim</l>
               <l>And to the diſtant Poles, let Echo ſpread his Fame.</l>
               <l>Write Epitaphs that ſo</l>
               <l>The world may know,</l>
               <l>How much to him ev'n Poetry did owe,</l>
               <l>For you but ſay, 'tis he that makes you ſing,</l>
               <l>His Art the Embrio words does to perfection bring.</l>
               <l>By us the Muſe at firſt conceives, 'tis true,</l>
               <l>He makes it fit to ſee the light, that gift to him we owe:</l>
               <l>Nake'd at firſt and rugged they appear,</l>
               <l>But when by him adorn'd they be,</l>
               <l>Aſſume a Pomp and Bravery,</l>
               <l>Nor need they longer bluſh to reach a Prnces Ear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40629:4"/>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>How rigid are the Laws of Fate,</l>
               <l>And how ſevere the black Decree,</l>
               <l>For nothing, nothing here is free,</l>
               <l>But all muſt enter th' Adamantine Gate.</l>
               <l>The Great, the Good, the Juſt, nay all, muſt come,</l>
               <l>To Natures dark retireing Room.</l>
               <l>He! he! alas is gone,</l>
               <l>Whoſe gentle Airs did make our Numbers live,</l>
               <l>Who Immortality could give,</l>
               <l>His Soul to't's firſt aboade away is flown,</l>
               <l>Blaſted are all our Glories now,</l>
               <l>Our Lawrels wither as they grow,</l>
               <l>The Muſe her ſelf forſakes us too.</l>
               <l>Come then, come quickly come,</l>
               <l>Let's pay our tears for off'rings at his Tomb.</l>
               <l>Let us not ſtrive, who beſt deſerves the Bays,</l>
               <l>He that grieves moſt, beſt claims the Higheſt Praiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>Ariſe ye bleſt Inhabitants above,</l>
               <l>From your immortal Seats ariſe,</l>
               <l>And on our Wonder, on our Love,</l>
               <l>Gaze with aſtoniſh'd eyes;</l>
               <l>Ariſe, Ariſe, make room,</l>
               <l>The wiſh'd for ſhade is come;</l>
               <l>Haſt and your ſelves prepare</l>
               <l>To me the joyful Choriſter,</l>
               <l>Meet him half way with Songs, ſuch as you ſing,</l>
               <l>Before the throne of the Eternal King,</l>
               <l>With welcomes let th' Aetherial Palace ring,</l>
               <l>Welcome the Gardian Angel ſays,</l>
               <l>Full of Songs, and full of Bays,</l>
               <l>Welcome thou art to me,</l>
               <l>And to theſe Regions of Serenity;</l>
               <l>Welcome the winged Choire reſounds,</l>
               <l>While with loud Euges all the ſacred place abounds.</l>
               <l>Low now above he chants Eternal Lays</l>
               <l>Above our wonder, and our Praiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
