<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Prince of Orange, his royall entertainment to the Qveen of England with the true description how the nobles inhabiting within the Hague, Rotterdam, Leyden, Amsterdam, Delph, Vtricke, Schedam and divers others congratulated Her Majesty into Holland : also the Prince of Orange his royall speech to Her Majesty at the Hague and her Majesties gracious answer unto the same : lastly the manner how Her Majesty with the Lady Elizabeth were feasted at the Princes palace at the Hague, Match [sic] 1, 1641.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8980</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12589764</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12589764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63860</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A55882)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63860)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 250:E138, no 17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Prince of Orange, his royall entertainment to the Qveen of England with the true description how the nobles inhabiting within the Hague, Rotterdam, Leyden, Amsterdam, Delph, Vtricke, Schedam and divers others congratulated Her Majesty into Holland : also the Prince of Orange his royall speech to Her Majesty at the Hague and her Majesties gracious answer unto the same : lastly the manner how Her Majesty with the Lady Elizabeth were feasted at the Princes palace at the Hague, Match [sic] 1, 1641.</title>
                  <author>Frederick Henry, Prince of Orange, 1584-1647.</author>
                  <author>Henrietta Maria, Queen, consort of Charles I, King of England, 1609-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for Henrie Barwicke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Original published : Holland : 1641?</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:63860:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Mercurij 29. Junij, 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is this day Ordered by the
Commons now aſſembled in
Parliament, That M. <hi>Aſh</hi> and M.
<hi>Hampden</hi> ſhall returne thankes to
M. <hi>Aſh</hi> for the good paines he took
in the Sermon he preach'd the laſt
Faſt day but two at the intreaty of
the ſaid Commons, and that he be
deſired to print his Sermon, And
that no man preſume to print it, but
ſuch as hee ſhall appoint, till the
Houſe ſhall take further Order.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>H.</hi> Elſyng<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I appoint <hi>Edward Brewſter</hi> and <hi>Iohn Burroughs</hi>
to print my Sermon.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Simeon Aſh.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63860:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
PRINCE
<hi>OF</hi>
ORANGE
HIS
ROYALL ENTERTAINMENT
TO THE QVEEN OF <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WITH,</hi>
The true Deſcription, how the Nobles inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
within the <hi>Hague, Rotterdam, Leyden, Amſterdam,
Delph, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricke, Schedam,</hi> and divers others congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
Her Majeſty into HOLLAND.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> His Royall Speech to
Her Majeſty at the Hague, and Her Majeſties graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Anſwer unto the ſame.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the manner how Her Majeſty with the
Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> were Feaſted at the Princes Palace
in the Hague, March. 1. 1641.</p>
            <p>Firſt imprinted at the Hague in Holland, and now Reprinted in
<hi>London</hi> for <hi>Henrie Barwicke.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="entertainment">
            <pb facs="tcp:63860:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63860:2"/>
            <head>THE
Prince of Oranges Royal Entertainment
to the Queen of ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>THe Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> having credible intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence
concerning the Queen of <hi>Englands</hi>
arriving at the <hi>Territories</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in expectation of her comming a long time.
But at length having information of her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
reſolution, and the Parliament of <hi>Englands</hi>
dubious ſuſpition, he began to be ambiguous till
afterwards being enformed by an Embaſſage
from her Majeſty, he began to be in preparation
of ſome Royal Entertainment, correſpondent, and
reſpectively congruent to the merits of ſo illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious
a Queen Firſt then with the concommi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
aſſociation of many Peers and Nobles atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
her comming <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Go<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, where ſhe landed,
and after ſome intercedent expreſſions of alacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
and tryumph on each ſide, he conſummated his
ſalutations in a brief and ſuccinct Speech, which
he alloquated her Majeſty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the ſubſtance of
theſe words following.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:63860:3"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="unk">
                  <body>
                     <div type="speech">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Illuſtrious Queen of England:</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>THe reſplondent irradiation of your inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable
vertue, and the obſequious adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
which I owe as tribute to your ſacred
Perſon, have by the delicious compulſion of
your attractive ſplendor reſpectively induced me
to preſent the engagement of my ſervice, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion
to your gracious Majeſty. For maturely
finding not only the liberal hand of Nature, boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
her Maſter-piece in each lineament of you,
(which is ſufficient to dazle the captive eye of
the amaz'd beholder in a repercuſive aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment)
but alſo the ſingular admiration of Art, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
her ſelf in the facetious eloquence of
thoſe Rhetoricall elocutions, which are included
in your faecundious brain (which tranſcends a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement
it ſelf) I conceive here from that either
my tongue is too barren of expreſſions to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe
the vertuous accent of your worth, or Our
Country too indigent to afford a correſpondent
entertainment for your Majeſty</p>
                        <p>Yet let the diſcreet reflection of your clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
be more propitious, and what in perfection
we are deficient, in the <hi>Embrio</hi> of Our deſired
exoptations ſhall be conſummated. For the obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quious
reſpects due unto your Leige, <hi>the Royall
Monarch of Britain,</hi> and the ſingular obligation
of my devotive affection to <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> our deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
Spouſe, had bin ſufficient Arguments of
inſtigation to have injoyned Vs to declare Our
affectionate humility of ardent devotion unto
<pb facs="tcp:63860:3"/>
you. But <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hen I perſpicuouſly behold both the
Majeſtick preſence of him, inhabited in the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
ſtructure of your Heroick countenance, and
the Reall <hi>Effigies</hi> of Her Angelicall Fabrick, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineated
in the perfect Symmetry of each arteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
dimenſion naturally in you, we are in a tripli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
of engagements induced coactively to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend
Our ſubmiſſive extent of gratitude un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
you.</p>
                        <p>For when wee apparently conſider the various
multiformity of vertues compendiouſly included
in the rich Storehouſe of your mature perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
we thence-from conclude, that you are the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted
Quinteſſence of artificiall Nature: your
glorious countenance is crowned with Majeſtie,
your brow interwoven with occaſionall Lenity,
and diſcreet auſterity, your eye (like mounted
<hi>Phebus</hi> in his meridian pride) ſhoots ſuch refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
beams of radiant brightneſſe, that it capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates
the dazled beholder: your Cupidinean
cheeks are cloathed with intermixed Lillies, and
Roſes: your purpureous lips (like a Nectarean
current) do redound with expreſſed Oratory:
your Mercurian tongue is guided with ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
Rhetorick, that the Muſes themſelves
ſeem to inhabit there, and make it their Helicon:
your Aromatick ſmelling-breath is ſo odorife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,
that it exceeds the Arabian Odours, and
ſeems rather celeſtial, then breathed from a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
creature, your melodious voice is ſo harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:63860:4"/>
that <hi>Apollo</hi> may now lay down his Harpe, and the
Sphears themſelves become aſtoniſhed.</p>
                        <p>Yea ſhould I dilate this continued expanſion
of your meritorious vertues, I might become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
for theſe particulars already declared, do
reſpectively reade captivity to my admiring
thoughts. This Country was lately deſolate of all
conſolation, but being now honoured with your
preſence, it ſeems a Paradice. But not to preſume
to far on your clement patience in a preliminary
or tedious diſcourſe; I will conſummate our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull
intentions, and gratefull devotion to your
M<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>jeſty, in a conciſe and concluſive period.</p>
                        <p>We are tranſported with joy having the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
of your enjoyed preſence; We do likewiſe
preſent our affectionate gratitude unto you, in
regard you would vouchſafe thus to honour us
with your illuſtrious perſon: and finally (in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation
of our humble duty) wee commend all
our Provinces to your Gracious acceptation,
which ſhall be at your command and pleaſure,
none interdicting you: yea we do lay Our Royal
Scepter at your feet, ſubmiſſively beſeeching you
to accept reſpectively, what Our Country doth
afford: while wee offer the Sacrifice of devotive
thankfulneſſe to your Deity.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:63860:4"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="unk">
                  <body>
                     <div type="speech">
                        <head>The Queen of Englands gracious Anſwer
to the Prince of Oranges Speech.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Thrice noble Prince,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>THe Heroick Dialect of your Rhetoricall
expreſſions have bin ſo incomparably inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious,
that you ſeem to me the God of eloquence.
For my part Our deſirous intent would regratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
you, but only we are barren of expreſſions, for
you have contracted the Monopoly of famous
elocutions to your ſelf, and ſome Language from
your facundious words. You have honour<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d us
too greatly, and more then either Nature or Art
have contributed to us in their various diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
have bin by you augmented. But as you
have honoured us in this place, ſo you have ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured
your ſelf more, and the place likewiſe is
honoured by your eloquence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And now give mee
leave to applaud your more meritorious worth:
you ſeem to me <hi>Cicero</hi> in your fluent words, <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gill</hi>
in your Seraphick Raptures, <hi>Cupid</hi> in your
face, <hi>Venus</hi> in your eye, <hi>Mercurie</hi> in your tongue,
<hi>Apollo</hi> in your voice, <hi>Diana</hi> in your chaſtity, <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi>
in your magnanimous mind, <hi>Paris</hi> in the
ſtatelineſſe of your body, and laſtly in your elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
a younger <hi>Iupiter,</hi> out of whoſe redundant
brain the <hi>Minerva</hi> of eloquence is extracted.
Your ſeverall parts are ſo admirable, that I went
Oratory to expreſſe them. But for your modeſty
in declaring the indigency of this Country, wee
find it otherwiſe; for rather then deficient (as you
<pb facs="tcp:63860:5"/>
confeſſed) it ſeemes ſuperfluous of all fertility.
And we do moſt reſpectively gratifie you, for
your ſedulous pains, and will to the largeſt extent
of our power endeavor to remunerate your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
courteſies.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe Speeches being ended, the Nobles <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting
within the <hi>Hague, Rotterdam, Leyden,
Amſterdam, Delph, Vtrick, Schedam,</hi> and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
congratulated her Majeſty with the Lady
<hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and were conducted to the Prince of
Oranges Palace at the Hague in a ſtately try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph,
every one welcomming her, and ſhewing
ſubmiſſive ſalutations to her Majeſty. She was
likewiſe Royally feaſted at the Princes Palace,
ſhewing her the greateſt honour and reſpects, that
can poſſibly be conceived. And ſhe likewiſe
gratefully thanked him, and the other Nobles aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociating
him for their liberall munificence. God
grant that ſhe may ſafely return to <hi>England</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
to the comfort of His Majeſty, and incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of the Kingdome.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:63860:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
