<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses</title>
            <author>Parker, Henry, 1604-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-10">2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56223</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21815</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12684134</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12684134</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A56223)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 252:E153, no 26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses</title>
                  <author>Parker, Henry, 1604-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Parker.  Cf. BLC.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Thomason Coll.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:65723:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65723:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>OBSERVATIONS
upon some of his Majesties late An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers
and Expresses.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this contestation betweene Regall and Paliamentary
power, for methods sake it is requisite to consider f<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>se of
Regall, then of Parliamentary Power, and in both to
consider the efficient, and finall causes, and the meanes
by which they are supported. <hi>The King attributeth the
originall of his royalty to God, and the Law, making no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the graunt, consent, or trust of man therein,</hi> but the truth is, God is
no more the author of Regall, then of Aristocraticall power, nor of
supreame, then of subordinate command; nay, that dominion which is
usurped, and not just, yet whilst it remaines dominion, and till it be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally
againe devested, referres to God, as to its Author and donor, as
much as that which is hereditary. <hi>And that Law which the King men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth,
is not to be understood to be any speciall ordinance sent from heaven
by the ministery of Angels or Prophets (as amongst the Jewes it some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
was)</hi> It can be nothing else amongst Christians but the Pactions
and agreements of such and such politique corporations. Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
is originally inherent in the people, and it is nothing else but that
might and vigour which such or such a societie of men containes in it
selfe, and when by such or such a Law of common consent and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
it is derived into such and such hands, God confirmes that Law:
and so man is the free and voluntary Author, the Law is the Instrument,
and God is the establisher of both. And we see, not that Prince which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65723:2"/>
is the most potent over his subjects, but that Prince which is most Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
in his subjects, is indeed most truely potent, for a King of one
small City, if he be intrusted with a large Prerogative, may bee sayd to
be more Potent over his subjects, then a King of many great Regions,
whose prerogative is more limited: and yet in true realitie of power,
that King is most great and glorious, which hath the most and strongest
subjects, and not he which tramples upon the most contemptible vas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sells.
This is therefore a great and fond errour in some Princes to
strive more to be great over their people, then in their people, and to
ecclipse themselves by impoverishing, rather then to magnifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
by infranchising their Subjects. This we see in France at this day,
for were the Peasants there more free, they would be more rich and
magnanimous, and were they so, their King were more puissant; but
now by affecting an adulterate power over his Subjects, the King
there looses a true power in his Subjects, imbracing a cloud instead of
<hi>Juno,</hi> but thus we see that power is but secondary and derivative in
Princes, the fountaine and efficient cause is the people, and from
hence the inference is just, the King, though he be <hi>singulis Major,</hi> yet he
is <hi>universis minor,</hi> for if the people be the true efficient cause of power,
it is a rule in nature <hi>quicquid efficit tale, est magis tale.</hi> And hence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares
that at the founding of authorities, when the consent of societies
convayes rule into such and such hands, it may ordaine what conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and prefix what bounds it pleases, and that no dissolution ought to
be thereof, but by the same power by which it had its constitution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As for the finall cause of Regall Authoritie, I doe not finde any
thing in the Kings papers denying, that the same people is the finall,
which is the efficient cause of it, and indeed it were strange if the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
in subjecting it selfe to command, should ayme at any thing but its
owne good in the first and last place. Tis true according to Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills
politicks,</hi> Princes ought to ayme at greatnes, not in, but over their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
and for the atchieving of the same, they ought to propose to themselves,
no greater good then the spoyling and breaking the spirits of their Subjects, nor
no greater mischiefe, then common freedome, neither ought they to promote
and cherish any servants but such as are most fit for rapine and oppression,
nor depresse and prosecute any as enemies, but such as are gracious with the
populacy for noble and gallant Acts.</p>
            <p>To be <hi>deliciae humani generis</hi> is growne fordid with Princes, to be
publike torments and carnificines, and to plot against those Subjects
whom by nature they ought to protect, is held <hi>Caesar</hi>-like, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
bloody <hi>Borgias</hi> by meere crueltie &amp; t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eachery hath gotten roome
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65723:2"/>
in the Calender of witty, and of spirited <hi>Heroes.</hi> And our English Court of
late yeares hath drunke too much of this State poyson, for eyther wee have
seene favorites raysed to poll the people, and razed againe to pacifie the
people; or else (which is worse for King and people too) we have seene
engines of mischiefe preserved against the people, and upheld against Law,
meerely that mischeefe might not want incouragement. <hi>But our King here,
doth acknowledge it the great businesse of his coronation oath to protect us:</hi> And
I hope under this word <hi>protect,</hi> he intends not onely to shield us from all
kind of evill, but to promote us also to all kind of Politicall happinesse
according to his utmost devoyre, and I hope hee holds himselfe bound
thereunto, not onely by his oath, but also by his very Office, and by the
end of his soveraigne dignitie. And though all single persons ought to
looke upon the late Bills passed by the King as matters of Grace with all
thankefulnesse and humility, yet the King himselfe looking upon the
whole State, ought to acknowledge that hee cannot merit of it, and that
whatsoever he hath granted, if it be for the prosperity of his people (but
much more for their ease) it hath proceeded but from his meere dutie. If
Ship money, if the Starre Chamber, if the High Commission, if the Votes
of Bishops and Popish Lords in the upper House, be inconsistent with the
welfare of the Kingdome, not onely honour but justice it selfe challenges
that they be abolisht; the King ought not to account that a profit or strength
to him, which is a losse and wasting to the people, nor ought he to thinke
that perisht to him which is gained to the people: The word grace sounds
better in the peoples mouthes then in his, his dignitie was erected to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
the Commonaltie, the Commonaltie was not created for his service:
and that which is the end is farre more honorable and valuable in nature
and policy, then that which is the meanes. This directs us then to the
transcendent <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of all Politiques, to the Paramount Law that shall give
Law to all humane Lawes whatsoever, and that is <hi>Salus Populi:</hi> The Law
of Prerogative it selfe, it is subservient to this Law, and were it not condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
thereunto, it were not necessary nor expedient. Neither can the right
of conquest be pleaded to acquit Princes of that which is due to the people
as the Authors, or ends of all power, for meere force cannot alter the course
of nature, or frustrate the tenour of Law, and if it could, there were more
reason, why the people might justifie force to regaine due libertie, then the
Prince might to subvert the same. And tis a shamefull stupidity in any man
to thinke that our Ancestors did not fight more nobly for their free cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes
and Lawes, of which the conqueror and his successors had in part
disinherited them by violence and perjury, then they which put them to
such conflicts, for it seemes unnatural to me that any nation should be bound
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65723:3"/>
to contribute its owne inherent puissance, meerely to abet Tiranny, and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
slavery: and to make that which is more excellent, a prey to that which
is of lesse worth. And questionlesse a native Prince, if meere Foree be right,
may disfranchise his Subjects as well as a stranger, if he can frame a suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
party, and yet we see this was the foolish sinne of <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
deserted and reiected out of an intollerable insolence, the strength of
ten tribes, ridiculously sought to reduce them againe with the strength of
two. I come now from the cause, which conveyes Royalty, and that for
which it is conveyed, to the nature of the conveyance. The word <hi>Trust</hi> is
frequent in the Kings Papers, and therefore I conceive the King does ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
that his interest in the Crowne is not absolute, or by a meere donation
of the people, but in part conditionate and fiduciary. And indeed all good
Princes without any expresse contract betwixt them and their Subjects,
have acknowledged that there did lie a great and high trust upon them; nay
Heathen Princes that have beene absolute, have acknowledged themselves
servants to the publike, and borne for that service, and professed that they
would manage the publike weale, as being well satisfied <hi>populi Rem esse, non
suam.</hi> And we cannot imagine in the fury of warre, (when lawes have the
least vigour) that any <hi>Generalissimo</hi> can be so uncircumscribed in power, but
that if he should turne his Canons upon his owne Souldiers, they vvere <hi>ipso
facto</hi> absolved of all obedience, and of all oathes and ties of allegiance
vvhatsoever for that time, and bound by higher dutie, to seeke their
owne preservation by resistance and defence: vvherefore if there bee such
tacite trusts and reservations in all publike commands, though of the most
absolute nature, that can be supposed, vve cannot but admit, that in all well
formed monarchies, vvhere kingly Prerogative has any limits set, this
must needs be one necessary condition, that the subject shall live both safe
and free. The Charter of nature intitles all Subjects of all Countries
vvhatsoever to safetie by its supreame Law. But freedome indeed has di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
degrees of latitude, and all Countries therein doe not participate alike,
but positive Lawes must every vvhere assigne those degrees.</p>
            <p>The great Charter of England is not strait in Priviledges to us, neither
is the Kings oath of small strength to that Charter, for that though it bee
more precise in the care of Canonicall Priviledges, and of Bishops and
Clergymen (as having beene penned by Popish Bishops) then of the
Commonalty, yet it confirmes all Lawes and rightfull customes, amongst
vvhich vve most highly esteeme Parliamentary Priviledges; and as for
the word <hi>Eligerit,</hi> whether it be future, or past, it skills not much; for if by
this oaths Law. Justice and descretion be executed amongst us in all judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
(as vvell in, as out of Parliament) and if peace and godly agreement
be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> amongst us all, and if the King defend and uphold all our
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65723:3"/>
lawes and customes, vve need not feare but the King is bound to consent to
new Lawes if they be necessary, as vvell as defend old: for both being of
the same necessity, the publique trust must needs equally extend to both;
and vve conceive it one Parliamentary right and custome, that nothing
necessary ought to be denyed. And the vvord <hi>Eligerit,</hi> if it be in the <hi>perfect
tense,</hi> yet shewes that the peoples election had beene the ground of anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
Lawes and customes, and vvhy the peoples election in Parliament
should not be now of as great moment as ever, I cannot discover.</p>
            <p>That vvhich results then from hence, is, if our Kings receive all royalty
from the people, and for the behoofe of the people, and that by a speciall
trust of safety and libertie expressely by the people limited, and by
their owne grants and oathes ratified, then our Kings cannot be sayd
to have so unconditionate and high a proprietie in all our lives, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
and possessions, or in any thing else to the Crowne appertayning, as
vve have in their dignity, or in our selves, and indeed if they had, they
vvere not borne for the people, but merely for themselves, neither were it
lawfull or naturall for them to expose their lives and fortunes for their
Country, as they have beene hitherto bound to doe, according to that of
our Saviour, <hi>Bonus Pastor ponit vitam pro ovibus.</hi> But now of Parliaments:
Parliaments have the same efficient cause as monarchies, if not higher,
for in the truth, the vvhole Kingdome is not so properly the Author as the
essence it selfe of Parliaments, and by the former rule tis <hi>magic tale,</hi> because
vve see <hi>ipsum quid quod efficit tale.</hi> And it is I thinke beyond all controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie,
that God and the Law operate as the same causes, both in Kings and
Parliaments, for God favours both, and the Law establishes both, and the
act of men still concurres in the sustentation of both. And not to stay lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
upon this, Parliaments have also the same finall cause as Monarchies, if
not greater, for indeed publike safety and liberty could not be so effectually
provided for by Monarchs till Parliaments were constituted, for the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying
of all defects in that Government.</p>
            <p>Two things especially are aymed at in Parliaments, not to be attayned to
by other meanes. First that the interest of the people might be satisfied; se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly
that Kings might be the better counsailed. In the summons of <hi>Edw.</hi>
the first <hi>(Claus. 7. 111. 3. Dors.)</hi> we see the first end of Parliaments expressed:
for he inserts in the writ that whatsoever affayre is of publike concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
ought to receive publike approbation, <hi>quod omnes tangit ab omnibus
approbari debet,</hi> or <hi>tructari.</hi> And in the same writ he saith, this is <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x ne tis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sima
&amp; provida circumspectione stabilita,</hi> there is not a word here, but it is
observeable, publique approbation, consent, or treatie is necessary in all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
expedients, and this is not a meere usage in England, but a Law, and
this Law is not subject to any doubt or dispute, there is nothing more
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65723:4"/>
knowne, neither is this knowne Law extorted from Kings, by the violence
and injustice of the people, it is duely and formally establisht, and that upon
a great deale of reason, not without the providence and circumspection of
all the states. Were there no further Antiquity, but the raigne of <hi>Edward</hi> the
first to recommend this to us, certainly so, there ought no reverence to be
withheld from it, for this Prince was wise, fortunate, just, and valiant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
all his Predecessors, if not successors also, and therefore it is the more
glory to our freedomes, that as weake and peevish Princes had most op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed
them, so that he first repaired the breaches which the conquest had
made upon them. And yet it is very probable that this Law was farre an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienter
then his raigne, and the words <hi>lex stabilita &amp; notissima</hi> seemes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate,
that the conquest it selfe, had never wholly buried this in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
ruine and confusion of the State. It should seeme at this time <hi>Llew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cllins</hi>
troubles in Wales were not quite suppressed, and the French King
was upon a designe to invade some peeces of ours in France, and therefore
he sends out this summons <hi>ad tractandum ordinandum, &amp; faciendum cum
Prelatis Proceris &amp; aliis incolis Regni,</hi> for the prevention of these dangers:
These words <hi>tractandum, ordinandum, faciendum,</hi> doe fully prove that the
people in those dayes were summoned <hi>ad consensum,</hi> as well as <hi>ad concilium,</hi>
and this Law, <hi>quod omnes tangit, &amp;c.</hi> shewes the reason and ground upon
which that consent and approbation is founded. It is true we finde in the
raigne of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, that the Commons did desire that they might
forbeare counselling in things <hi>de queux ils nount pas cognizance;</hi> the matters
in debate were concerning some intestine commotions, the guarding of the
Marches of Scotland and the Seas; and therein they renounce not their
right of consent, they onely excuse themselves in point of counsell, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
it rather to the King and his Counsell. How this shall derogate from
Parliaments either in point of consent or counsell I do not know, for at
last they did give both, and the King vvould not be satisfied vvithout them,
and the passage evinces no more but this, that that King was very wise and
Warlike, and had a very wise counsell of vvarre, so that in those paticulars
the Commons thought them most fit to be consulted, as perhaps the more
knowing men.</p>
            <p>Now upon a due comparing of these passages with some of the Kings
late Papers let the vvorld judge whether Parliaments have not beene of
late much lessened and injured. The King in one of his late Answers, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadges
that his Writs may teach the Lords and Commons the extent of their
Commission and trust, which is to be Counsellors, not commanders, and that
not in all things, but in quibusdam arduiis,</hi> and the case of <hi>Wentworth</hi> is cited,
who was by Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> committed (sitting the Parliament) for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65723:4"/>
proposing that they might advise the Queene in some things, which she
thought beyond their cognizance, although <hi>Wentworth</hi> was then of the
House of Commons.</p>
            <p>And in other places the <hi>King denies the assembly of the</hi> Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
when he withdrawes himselfe, to be rightly named a Parliament, or
to have any power of any Court, and consequently to be any thing, but
a meere convention of so many private men.</p>
            <p>Many things are here asserted utterly destructive to the honour, right, &amp;
being of Parliaments. For first, because the Law had trusted the King with
a Prerogative to discontinue Parliaments: therefore if he did discontinue
Parliaments to the danger or prejudice of the Kingdome, this was no
breach of that trust, because in formalitie of Law the people might not as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble
in Parliament but by the Kings writ, therefore in right and equity
they were concluded also, so that if the King would not graunt his Writ,
when it was expedient, he did not proove unfaithfull, or doe any wrong
to the people; for where no remedy is, there is no right. This doctrine
was mischievous to us when the King had a Prerogative to difuse Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and if it be not now exploded and protested against, may yet bee
mischievous in the future dissolution of Parliaments, for that power still
remaines in the Kings trust; and if to goe against the intent of trnst be no
wrong, because perhaps it is remedilesse, our Trienniall Parliaments may
prove but of little service to us; <hi>Secondly when Parliaments are assembled
they have no Commission to Counsell but in such points as the King pleases to
propose,</hi> if they make any <hi>transition in other matters, they are liable to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment
at the Kings pleasure, witnesse</hi> Wentworths <hi>Case.</hi> A meere exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
(though of Queene <hi>Elizabeth)</hi> is no Law, for some of her actions
were retracted, and yet without question Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> might do that
which a Prince lesse beloved could never have done: There is a way
by goodnesse and clemency for Princes to make themselves almost unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitable,
and this way Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> went, and without doubt had her
goodnesse and Grace beene fained, shee might have usurped an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troleable
arbitrary lawlesse Empire over us. The Sunne sooner makes
the travailour desert his Cloake, then the wind; And the gracious acts of
soft Princes (such as <hi>Tiberius</hi> did at first personate) if they be perfectly
dissembled may more easily invade the subiects liberty then the furious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
of such as <hi>Caligula</hi> was, but we must not be presidented in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
violations of Law by Queene <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> for as generall reverence
gave her power to doe more then ordinary, so her perfect undissembled
goodnesse, upon which her reverence was firmely planted, made the same
more then ordinary fact in her, lesse dangerous then it would have beene
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65723:5"/>
in another Prince. In this point then leaving the meere fact of
Queene <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> wee will retire backe to the ancient Law and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of <hi>Edward</hi> the first, and wee thereby shall maintaine that in all
cases wheresoever the generality is touched, the generality must bee
consulted.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if the Lords and Commons bee admitted to some Cognizance
of all things wherein they are concerned, yet they must meerely Counsell,
they must not command, and the King Reasons thus, that it is impossible
the same trust should bee irrevocably committed to Vs, and our Heires
for ever, and yet a power above that trust (for so the Parliament
pretends) bee committed to others, and the Parliament being a body
and dissolvable at pleasure, it is strange if they should bee guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
and controlers in the manage of that trust which is granted to
the King for ever. <hi>It is true, two supreames cannot bee in the same
sence and respect, but nothing is more knowne or assented to
then this, that the King is</hi> singulis major, <hi>and yet</hi> universis minor,
<hi>this wee see in all conditionall Princes, such as the Prince of</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>And though all Monarchies are not subject to the same condition,
yet there scarse is any Monarchy but is subiect to some conditions,
and I thinke to the most absolute Empire in the world this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
is most naturall and necessary, That the safetie of the people is
to bee valued above any right of his, as much as the end is to bee
preferred before the meanes; it is not just nor possible for any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
so to inslave it selfe, and to resigne its owne interest to the
will of one Lord, as that that Lord may destroy it without injury,
and yet to have no right to preserve it selfe: For since all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
power is in those which obay, they which contract to obay to
their owne ruine, or having so contracted, they which esteeme such
a contract before their owne preservation are felonious to themselves, and
rebellious to nature.</p>
            <p>The people then having intrusted their protection into the Kings
hands irrevocably, yet have not left that trust without all manner of
limits, some things they have reserved to themselves out of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and some thing in Parliament, and this reservation is not at
all inconsistent with the Princes trust, though hee desire to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
the same; but on the contrary, it is very ayding and strengthning
to that trust, so farre as the Prince seekes to performe it, for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
good; but it is objected, that a temporary power ought not to bee
greater then that which is lasting and unalterable, if this were so, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65723:5"/>
Romans had done unpolitikely, in creating Dictators, when any
great extremitie assailed them, and yet wee know it was verie
prosperous to them, sometimes to change the forme of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
neither alwayes living under circumscribed Consuls, nor
yet under uncircumscribed Dictators: but it in further objected,
that if wee allow the Lords and Commons <hi>to be more than Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors,
we make them Commanders and Controllers, and this is not
sutable to Royaltie.</hi> We say here, that to consent is more than to
counsell, and yet not alwayes so much as to command and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll;
for in inferiour Courts, the Judges are so Councellors for
the King, as that the King may not countermand their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and yet it were an harsh thing to say, that they are therfore
Guardians and Controllers of the King: and in Parliament,
where the Lords and Commons represent the whole Kingdome,
(to whom so great a Majestie is due) and sit in a far higher capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie
than inferiour Judges doe, being vested with a right both to
counsell and consent, the case is far stronger; and as wee ought
not to conceive, that they will either counsell or consent to any
thing, but what is publikely advantagious; so by such Councell
and consent, wee cannot imagine the King limited or lessened:
for if it was by so knowne a Law, and so wisely established in
<hi>Edward</hi> the firsts dayes, the right of the people, to be summoned
at <hi>tractandum, ordinandum, faciendum, approbandum,</hi> in all things
appertaining to the people, and this as then was not prejudiciall
to the King, why should the Kings Writ now abbreviate or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null
the same, if the King himselfe be disable for many high mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
till consent in Parliament adde vigour to him, it cannot
be supposed that hee comes thither meerly to heare Councell, or
that when he is more than councelled, that it is any derogation,
but rather a supply of vertue to him. A fourth thing alleaged to the
derogation of Parliaments is, <hi>That whatsoever the right of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
is to assemble or treat in all cases of a publique nature, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the Kings concurrence and consent, they are livelesse conventions
without all vertue and power, the verie name of Parliament is not due
to them.</hi> This allegation at one blow confounds all Parliaments,
and subjects us to as unbounded a regiment of the Kings meere
will, as any Nation under Heaven ever suffered under. For by the
same reason, that Parliaments are thus vertulesse and void Courts,
upon the Kings desertion of them, other Courts must needs be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65723:6"/>
the like, &amp; then what remains, but that all our lawes, rights, &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,
be either no where at all determinable, or else onely in
the Kings breast? We contend not meerly about the name Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
for the same thing was before that name, and therfore the
intent is, that the great Assembly of the Lords and Commons doe
not represent and appeare in the right of the whole Kingdome,
or else that there is no honour, nor power, nor judicature, resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
in that great and Majesticall Body, then which, scarce any
thing can be more unnaturall. But these divisions betweene the
King and Parliament, and betwixt the Parliament and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
seeming more uncouth, 'tis attempted to divide further
betweene part and part in Parliament, so making the major part
not fully concluding, and in the major part, between a facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
misleading, and a party mislead. Such excellent Masters of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision
has <hi>Machiavils</hi> rule <hi>(divide &amp; impera)</hi> made since the 3 of
<hi>November 1640.</hi> 'Tis a wonderfull thing, that the Kings Papers
being frayted scarce with any thing else but such doctrines of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision,
tending all to the subversion of our ancient fundamentall
constitutions which support all our ancient liberties, and to the
erection of arbitrary rule, should finde such applause in the world:
but we say further, that there is manifest difference between de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serting
and being deserted: if the wife leave her husbands bed,
and become an adulteresse, 'tis good reason that shee loose her
dowry, and the reputation of a wife, but if the husband will
causelesly reject her, 'tis great injustice that she should suffer any
detriment thereby, or be dismissed of any priviledge whatsoever.
So if the King have parted from His Parliament, meerely because
they sought His oppression, and he had no other meanes to
withstand their tyranny, let this proclaime them a voyd Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly:
but if ill Counsaile have withdrawne him, for this wicked
end meerely, that they might defeat this Parliament, and dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
from the fundamentall rights of all Parliaments (as His
Papers seeme to expresse) under colour of charging some few fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious
persons in this Parliament, (God forbid) that this should
disable them from saving themselves and the whole state, or
from seeking justice against their enemies. So much of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
right in Parliament.</p>
            <p>Now of that right which the Parliament may doe the King
by Councell, if the King could bee more wisely or faithfully
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65723:6"/>
advised by any other Court, or if His single judgement were to
to be preferred before all advise whatsoever, 'twere not onely
vaine, but extreamely inconvenient, that the whole Kingdome
should be troubled to make Elections, and that the parties ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
should attend the publique businesse; but little need to bee
said, I thinke every mans heart tels him, that in publique Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultations,
the many eyes of so many choyce Gentlemen out of
all parts, see more then fewer, and the great interest the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
has in common justice and tranquility, and the few private
ends they can have to deprave them, must needs render their
Counsell more faithfull, impartiall, and religious, then any other.
That dislike which the Court has ever conceived against Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
without all dispute is a most pregnant proofe of the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity,
and salubrity of that publique advise, and is no disparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
thereof; for we have ever found enmity and antipathy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
the Court and the countrey, but never any till now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
the Representatives, and the Body, of the Kingdome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented.
And were we not now, those dregges of humane
race upon whom the unhappy ends of the world are fallen, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny
and Envie herselfe would never have attempted, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude
upon us such impossible charges of Treason and Rebellion
against our most sacred Councell, from the mouthes of Popish,
Prelaticall, and Military Courtiers.</p>
            <p>The King sayes; <hi>'Tis imp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obable and impossible that His Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net
Counsellours, or his Bishops or seuldiers, who must have so great
a share in the misery, should take such paines in the procuring thereof,
and spend so much time, and run so many hazards to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
slaves, and to ruine the freedome of this Nation:</hi> how strange
is this? wee have had almost 40 yeeres experience, that the
Court way of preferment has beene by doing publicke ill Offices,
and we can nominate what Dukes, what Earles, what Lords,
what Knights, have been made great and rich by base disservices
to the State: and except Master <hi>Hollis</hi> his rich Widow, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
heard that promotion came to any man by serving in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
but I have heard of trouble and imprisonment, but now
see the traverse of fortune; The Court is now turned honest, my
Lord of <hi>Straffords</hi> death has wrought a sudden conversion
amongst them, and there is no other feare now, but that a few
Hypocrites in Parliament will beguile the major part there, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65723:7"/>
so usurpe over King, Kingdome, and Parliament for ever, sure
this is next to a prodigy, if it be not one: but let us consider the
Lords and Commons as meere Counsellors without any power
or right of Counselling or consenting, yet wee shall see if they
be not lesse knowing and faithfull than other men, they ought
not to be deserted, unlesse we will allow that the King may
cause whither he will admit of any counsell at all or no, in the
disposing of our lives, lands, and liberties. But the King sayes,
<hi>that he is not bound to renounce his owne understanding, or to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict
his owne conscience for any Counsellors sake whatsoever.</hi> 'Tis
granted in things visible and certaine, that judge which is a sole
judge and has competent power to see his owne judgement ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted,
ought not to determine against the light of nature, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
of fact.</p>
            <p>The sinne of <hi>Pilate</hi> was, that when he might have saved our
Saviour from an unjust death, yet upon accusations contradictory
in themselves, contrary to strange Revelations from Heaven, he
would suffer Innocence to fall, and passe sentence of death,
meerly to satisfie a bloud-thirsty multitude. But otherwise it
was in my Lord of <hi>Straffords</hi> case, for there the King was not
sole Judge, nay, he was uncapeable of sitting as judge at all, and
the delinquent was legally condemned, and such heynous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
had beene proved against him, that his greatest friends
were ashamed to justifie them, and all impartiall men of three
whole Kingdomes conceived them mortall; and therefore the
King might therin, with a clear conscience have signed a warrant
for his death, though he had dissented from the judgement. So
if one judge on the same bench, dissent from three, or one juror
at the barre from a eleven, they may submit to the major number,
though perhaps lesse skilfull then themselves without imputation
of guilt: and if it be thus in matters of Law, <hi>a fortiori,</hi> 'tis so in
matters of State, where the very satisfying of a multitude some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
in things not otherwise expedient, may proove not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
expedient, but necessary for the setling of peace, and ceasing
of strife. For example: It was the request of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
in the Parliament to the King, to intrust the <hi>Militiae,</hi> and
the Magazine of <hi>Hull, &amp;c.</hi> into such hands as were in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
good esteeme. Conscience and understanding could plead
nothing against this, and if it could have beene averred (as it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65723:7"/>
could not, for the contrary was true) that this would have bred
disturbance, and have beene the occasion of greater danger,
yet Where the people by publique authority will seeke any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience
to themselves, and the King is not so much intressed
in it as themselves, 'tis more inconvenience and injustice to deny
then grant it: what blame is it then in Princes when they will
pretend reluctance of conscience and reason in things behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
for the people? and will use their fiduciarie power in denying
just things, as if they might lawfully do whatsoever they have
power to do, when the contrary is the truth, and they have no
power to do but what is lawfull and fit to be done. So much for
the ends of Parliamentary power. I come now to the true na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of it, publike consent: we see consent as well as counsell is
requisite and due in Parliament and that being the proper foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
of all power (for <hi>omnis Potestas fundata est in voluntate)</hi> we
cannot imagine that publique consent should be any where more
vigorous or more orderly than it is in Parliament. Man being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved
by the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> grew so untame and uncivill a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
that the Law of God written in his brest was not suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
to restrayne him from mischiefe, or to make him sociable, and
therefore without some magistracy to provide new orders, and
to judge of old, and to execute according to justice, no society
could be upheld, without society men could not live, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
lawes men could not be sociable, and without authority
somewhere invested, to judge according to Law, and execute ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to judgement, Law was a vaine and void thing, it
was soon therefore provided that lawes agreeable to the dictates
of reason should be ratified by common consent, and that the
execution and interpretation of those Lawes should be intrusted
to some magistrate, for the preventing of common injuries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
Subject and Subject, but when it after appeared that man
was yet subject to unnaturall destruction, by the Tyranny of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted
magistrates, a mischiefe almost as fatall as to be without
all magistracie, how to provide a wholsome remedy therefore,
was not so easie to be prevented. 'Twas not difficult to invent
Lawes, for the limitting of supreme governors, but to invent
how those Lawes should be executed or by whom interpreted,
was almost impossible, <hi>nam quis custodiat ipsos custodes;</hi> To place a
superiour above a supreme, was held unnaturall, yet what a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65723:8"/>
livelesse fond thing would Law be, without any judge to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
it, or power to enforce it; and how could humaine conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation
be preserved, without some such Law? besides, if it be
agreed upon, that limits should be prefixed to Princes, and judges
appointed to decree according to those limits, yet an other great
inconvenience will presently affront us; for we cannot restraine
Princes too far, but we shall disable them from some good, as
well as inhibit them from some evill, and to be disabled from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
good in some things, may be as mischievous, as to be inabled
for all evils at meere discretion. Long it was ere the world could
extricate it selfe out of all these extremities, or finde out an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly
meanes whereby to avoid the danger of unbounded pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative
on this hand, and to excessive liberty on the other: and
scarce has long experience yet fully satisfied the mindes of all
men in it. In the infancy of the world, when man was not so ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall
and obdurate in cruelty and oppression as now, and when
policy was more rude, most Nations did chuse rather to submit
themselves to the meer discretion of their Lords, then to rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
any limits: and to be ruled by Arbitrary edicts, then written
Statutes. But since, Tyranny being growne more exquisite, and
policy more perfect, (especially in Countreys where Learning
and Religion flourish) few Nations will indure that thraldome
which uses to accompany unbounded &amp; unconditionate royalty,
yet long it was ere the bounds and conditions of supreme Lords
were so wisely determined or quietly conserved as now they are,
for at first when <hi>Ephori, Tribuni, Curatores &amp;c.</hi> were erected
to poyze against the scale of Soveraignty, much bloud was shed
about them, and, states were put into new broyles by them,
and in some places the remedy proved worse then the disease. In
all great distresses the body of the people was ever constrained
to rise, and by the force of a Major party to put an end to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testine
strifes, and make a redresse of all publique grievances, but
many times calamities grew to a strange height, before so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bersome
a body could be raised; and when it was raised, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
of it were so distracted and irregular, that after much spoile
and effution of bloud, sometimes onely one Tyranny was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed
for another: till some way was invented to regulate the
motions of the peoples moliminous body, I think arbitrary rule
was most safe for the world, but now since most Countries have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65723:8"/>
found out an Art and peaceable Order for Publique Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies,
whereby the people may assume its owne power to do it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
right without disturbance to it selfe, or injury to Princes, he
is very unjust that will oppose this Art and order. That Princes
may not be now beyond all limits and Lawes, nor yet left to be
tryed upon those limits and Lawes by any private parties, the
whole community in its underived Majesty shall convene to do
justice, and that this convention may not be without intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,
certaine-times and places and formes shall be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
for its regliment, and that the vastnesse of its owne bulke
may not breed confusion, by vertue of election and representati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
a few shall act for many, the wise shall consent for the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
the vertue of all shall redound to some, and the prudence of
some shall redound to all. And sure, as this admirably composed
Court which is now called a Parliament, is more regularly and
orderly formed, then when it was called the mickle Synod, or
Witenagenot, or when this reall body of the people did throng
together at it, so it is not yet perhaps without some defects,
which by art and policy might receive further amendment, some
divisions have beene sprung of late betweene both Houses,
and some betweene the King and both Houses, by reason of the
uncertainety of jurisdiction; and some Lawyers doubt how far
the Parliament is able to create new formes and presidents; and
has a jurisdiction over it selfe. All these doubts would be so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly
solved. But in the first place, the true Priviledges of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,
not onely belonging to the being and efficacy of it, but
to the honour also &amp; complement of it, would be clearly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:
for the very nameing of Priviledges of Parliament, as if they
were Chimera's to the ignoranter sort, &amp; utterly unknown to the
learned, hath beene entertained with scorne since the beginning
of this Parliament. The vertue of representation hath beene
denyed to the Commons, and a severance has beene made
betwixt the parties chosen and the parties choosing, and so
that great Priviledges of all Priviledges, that unmoveable Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis
of all honour and power, whereby the House of Commons
claimes the entire rite of all the Gentry and Commonalty of
<hi>England,</hi> has beene attempted to bee shaken and disturbed, most
of our late distempers and obstructions in Parliament have
proceeded from this: that the people upon causelesse defama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65723:9"/>
and unproved accusations have beene so prone to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw
themselves from their representations, and yet there can
be nothing under Heaven, next to renouncing God, which can
be more perfidious and more pernitious in the people than this.</p>
            <p>Having now premised these things, I come to the maine dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties
lying at this time in dispute before us, it is left unquestio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
that the legislative power of this Kingdome is partly in the
King, and partly in the Kingdome, and that in ordinary cases,
when it concernes not the saving of the people from some
great danger or inconvenience, neither the King can make a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
binding Law or Ordinance without the Parliament, or
the Parliament without the King, and this is by a knowne Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime,
<hi>Non recurrendum est ad extraordinaria &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ought to be also as unquestioned, that where this ordinary
course cannot be taken for the preventing of publike mischiefes,
any extraordinary course that is for that purpose the most effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
may justly be taken and executed by the most transcendent
over-ruling <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> of all humane Lawes, if the King
will not joyne with the people, the people may without disloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty
save themselves, and if the people should be so unnaturall
as to oppose their owne preservation, the King might use all
possible means for their safetie, yet this seemes to be denyed by
the King, <hi>for he sets forth Proclamations and cites Statutes in them
to prove, that the power of levying armes and forces is solely in
him,</hi> and he presses them indefinitely, not leaving to the Subject
any right at all of rising in armes, though for their owne necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
defence, except he joynes his consent and Authority: In the
same manner also, he so assumes to himselfe a share in the legisla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
power, as without his concurrence the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
have no right at all to make any temporary orders for put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
the Kingdome into a posture of defence, in what publique
distresse soever: And therefore in Sir <hi>Iohn Hothaems</hi> case, he
doth not onely charge him of Treason, for observing the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
instructions and Commissions in a pretended danger, but
he pronounceth the meere act Treason, let the circumstances be
what they will. Let the world judge whether this be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to the clearest beames of humaine reason, and the strongest
inclinations of nature, for every private man may defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
by force, if assaulted, though by the force of a Magistrate
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65723:9"/>
or his owne father, and though he be not without all
confidence by flight &amp;c. yet here whole nations being
exposed to enmity and hazard, being utterly uncapable
of flight, must yeeld their throats and submit to Assas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinates,
if their King will not allow, them defence.</p>
            <p>See if this be not contrary to the originall, end,
and trust of all power and Lawe, and whether it doe
not open a gap to as vast and arbitrary a prerogative
as the Grand Seignior has, and whither this be not the
maine ground of all those bitter invectives almost
which are iterated and inforced with so much eloquence
in all the Kings late papers. See if wee are not left
as a prety to the same bloudy hands as have done such
diabolicall exployts in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or to any others which
can perswade the King that the Parliament is not well
affected to him, if we may not take up armes for our
owne safety, or if it be possible for us to take up armes,
without some Votes or ordinances to regulate the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi>
or to make our defence manly, and not beastiall and
void of all Counsell, the name of a King is great I
confesse, and worthy of great honour, but is not the
name of people greater? let not meere tearms deceave
us, let us weigh names and things together, admit
that God sheds here some rayes of Majesty upon his
vicegerents on earth, yet except we thinke he doth
this out of particular love to Princes themselves, and
not to communties of men, wee must not hence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
the course of nature, and make nations subordinate
in end to Princes. My Lord of <hi>Strafford,</hi> sayes that the
Law of Prerogative is like that of the first table, but
the Law of Common safety and utility like that of the
second, and hence concludes, that precedence is to be
given to that which is more sacred, (that is) Regall
Prerogative. Upon this ground all Parasites build when
they seeke to hood-winke Princes for their owne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages,
and when they assay to draw that esteeme to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65723:10"/>
themselves, which they withdraw from the people: and
this doctrin is common, because 'tis so acceptable: for as
nothing is more pleasant to Princes then to be so deified,
so nothing is more gainefull to Courtiers then so to
please. But to look into termes a little more narrower,
and dispell umbrages; <hi>Princes are called Gods, Fathers,
Husbands, Lords, Heads, &amp;c. and this implyes them to be of
more worth and more unsubordinate in end, then their
Subjects are, who by the same relation must stand as Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
Children, Wives, Servants, Members, &amp;c.</hi> I
answer, these termes do illustrate some excellency in
Princes by way of similitude, but must not in all things
be applyed, and they are most truly applyed to Subjects,
taken <hi>divisim,</hi> but not <hi>conjunctim:</hi> Kings are Gods to
particular men, <hi>secundum quid,</hi> and are sanctified with
some of Gods royaltie; but it is not for themselves, it is
for an extrinsecall end, and that is the prosperitie of
Gods people, and that end is more sacred than the
meanes, as to themselves they are most unlike God; for
God cannot bee obliged by any thing extrinsecall, no
created thing whatsoever can be of sufficient value or
excellencie to impose any dutie or tye upon God, as Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
upon Princes: therefore granting Prerogative to
be but mediate, and the Weale Publike to be finall, wee
must rank the Lawes of libertie in the first Table, and
Prerogative in the second, as Nature doth require; and
not after a kind of blasphemy ascribe that unsubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to Princes, which is only due to God; so the King
is a Father to his People, taken singly, but not univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally;
for the father is more worthy than the son in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
and the son is wholly a debtor to the father, and can
by no merit transcend his dutie, nor chalenge any thing
as due from his father; for the father doth all his offices
meritoriously, freely, and unexactedly. Yet this holds
not in the relation betwixt King &amp; Subject, for its more
due in policie, and more strictly to be chalenged, that the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65723:10"/>
King should make happy the People, than the People
make glorious the King. This same reason is also in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
of Husband, Lord, &amp;c. for the wife is inferiour
in nature, and was created for the assistance of man, and
servants are hired for their Lords meere attendance;
but it is otherwise in the State betwixt man and man,
for that civill difference which is for civill ends, and those
ends are, that wrong and violence may be repressed by
one for the good of all not that servilitie and drudgerie
may be imposed upon all, for the pomp of one. So the
head naturally doth not more depend upon the body,
than that does upon the head, both head and members
must live and dye together; but it is otherwise with the
Head Politicall, for that receives more subsistence from
the body than it gives, and being subservient to that, it
has no being when that is dissolved, and that may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served
after its dissolution.</p>
            <p>And hence it appeares, that the verie order of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
binds them not to be insolent, but lowly; and not to
aime at their owne good but secondarily, contrarie to
the Florentines wretched Politiques. And it followes,
that such Princes, as contrarie to the end of government,
effect evill in stead of good, insulting in common servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,
rather than promoting common securitie, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
their chiefest pomp in the sufferance of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
commit such sins as God will never countenance;
nay, such as the unnaturall father, the tyrannous husband,
the mercilesse master is not capable of committing; nay,
we must conceive that Treason in Subjects against their
Prince, so far only as it concernes the Prince, is not so
horrid in nature, as oppression in the Prince exercised
violently upon Subjects. God commands Princes to
study his Law day and night, and not to amasse great
treasures, or to encrease their Cavaliers, or to lift up their
hearts above their brethren, nor to wast their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanes,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65723:11"/>
lest necessitie should tempt them to rapine. But
on the contrarie, <hi>Machiavels</hi> Instructions puffe up Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<hi>That they may treat Subjects not as brethren, but as
beasts, as the basest beasts of drudgerie, teaching them by
subtiltie, and by the strength of their</hi> Militia, <hi>to uphold their
owne will, and to make meere sponges of the publike coffers:</hi>
And sure if that cursed Heretike in policie could have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented
any thing more repugnant to Gods commands,
and Natures intention, he had been held a deeper States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
than hee is; but I conceive it is now sufficiently
cleared, that all rule is but fiduciarie, and that this and
that Prince is more or lesse absolute, as he is more or lesse
trusted, and that all trusts differ not in nature or intent,
but in degree only and extent: and therefore since it is
unnaturall for any Nation to give away its owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie
in it selfe absolutely, and to subject it selfe to a
condition of servilitie below men, because this is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie
to the supreme of all Lawes, wee must not think
that it can stand with the intent of any trust, that neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie
defence should be barred, and naturall preservation
denyed to any people; no man will deny, but that the
People may use meanes of defence, where Princes are
more conditionate, and have a soveraigntie more limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
and yet these being only lesse trusted than absolute
Monarchs, and no trust being without an intent of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation,
it is no more intended that the People shall be
remedilesly oppressed in a Monarchy, than in a Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.
But tracing this no further, I will now rest upon
this, that whatsoever the King has alleaged against rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
of Armes, and publishing of Orders indefinitely, is
of no force to make Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham,</hi> or those by whose
authoritie hee acted, Traytours, unlesse it fall out that
there was no ground nor necessitie of such defence. So
much of danger certaine.</p>
            <p>I will now suppose the danger of the Commonwealth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65723:11"/>
uncertaine, the King sayes; the Parliament denyes;
the King commands, the Parliament forbids: The
King sayes the Parliament is seduced by a traiterous fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;
the Parliament sayes the King is seduced by a
Malignant Party: the King sayes the Parliament tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
upon his Crowne; the Parliament sayes the King
intends Warre upon them: to whether now is the Subject
bound to adhere? I will not insist much upon gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
presumptions, though they are of moment in this
case: for without all question 'tis more likely, that
Princes may erre and have sinister ends, then such gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
conventions of the Nobility, Gentry, and Commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
so instituted, and regulated as ours are in England.
The King does highly admire <hi>the ancient, equall, happy,
well poyzed and never enough commended constitution of
this Government, which hath made this Kingdome, so
many years both famous and happy, to a great degree of envie,
and amongst the rest, our Courts of Parliament: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
more especially, that power which is legally placed in
both Houses, more than sufficient</hi> (as he sayes) <hi>to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
and restraine the power of Tyranny;</hi> But how can
this be? if the King may at His pleasure take away the
being of Parliament meerely by dissent, if they can doe
nothing but what pleases Him, or some Clandestine
Councellours, and if upon any attempt to doe any thing
else, they shall be called Traitors, and without further
arraignment, or legall proceeding, be deserted by the
Kingdome whose representations they are, what is
there remaining to Parliaments? are they not more ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile
then other inferiour Courts; nay, are they not in a
worse condition then the meanest Subject out of
Parliament? and how shall they restraine tyranny, when
they have no subsistance at all themselves; nay, nor no
benefit of Justice, but arbitrary. Surely if these princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
hold, they will be made the very Engines and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65723:12"/>
Scaffolds whereby to erect a government more tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall
then ever was knowne in any other Kingdome,
wee have long groaned for them, but we are likely now
to groane under them: but you will say, the King <hi>hath a
power of dissent, he may use it at his pleasure, if hee have
none, then he is a meere Cypher, and the Parliament may
tyrannize at pleasure: either the one or the other must bee
predominant, or else by a mutuall opposition all must perist;
and why not the King predominant rather then the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
We had a maxime, and it was grounded upon
Nature, and never till this Parliament withstood, that a
community can have no private ends to mislead it,
and make it injurious to it selfe, and no age will furnish
us with one story of any Parliament freely elected, and
held, that ever did injure a whole Kingdome, or exercise
any tyranny, nor is there any possibility how it should.
The King may safely leave his highest rights to Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
for none knowes better, or affects more the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of this so well-ballanced a Monarchy then they do,
and it hath been often in their power under great provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations
to load that rule with greater fetters &amp; clogs, but
they would not. Let us marke but the nature, the
right, the power, the wisedome, the justice, of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and we shall finde no cause to suspect them, of
such unmatchable treasons and conspiracies as are this
day, and never was before charged upon them; for
our Chronicles makes it apparent, that there is scarce
any other Nation wherein Monarchy has been more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused
by rash inconsiderate Princes, then in this, nor none
at all wherein it hath been more inviolably adored, and
loyally preserved from all diminution, I wish it were
not some incitement to those execrable Instruments,
which steale the Kings heart from us, that they thinke
the Religion of Protestants too tame, and the Nation
of the English too incensible of injuries; but I hope
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65723:12"/>
God will the more tenderly resent these things. The
composition of Parliaments, I say, takes away all jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies,
for it is so equally, and geometrically proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,
and all the States doe so orderly contribute their
due parts therein, that no one can be of any extreame
predominance, the multitude loves Monarchy better
then Aristocracy, and the Nobility and Gentry, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
it as much beyond Democracy, and we see the
multitude hath onely a representative influence, so that
they are not likely to sway, and yet some influence they
have, and that enough to preserve themselves from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
overswaid. We also in England have not a Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
and Gentry so independent and potent as in France,
Germany, Denmarke, &amp;c. Nor as they were here im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
after the Conquest, by reason of their great
Feoffes, whereby to give Lawes either to the Crowne,
or the people; but they stand at such faire and comely
distances between the King and people, and also be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
themselves, <hi>that they serve for an excellent Skreene
and banke</hi> (as the Kings words are) <hi>to assist both King and
people against the encroachments of each other.</hi> And as the
middle Region of the aire treats loving offices betwixt
heaven and earth, restraining the fumes and exhalations
of Sea and Land, that they ascend not too high, and at
the same instant, allaying that restlesse Planets scorching
flames, which else might prove insufferable to the lower
Elements: So doth both Houses of Parliament, as
peaceably and sweetly arbitrate betwixt the Prince and
his poorest Vassals, and declining. Tyranny on the one
side, and Ochlocracy on the other, preserving intire to
the King the honour of His Scopter, and to the people
the patrimony of freedome. Let us not then seeke to
corrupt this purity of composition, or conceive that both
Gentry; and Nobility can combine against the King,
when they have no power but derivative, the one more
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65723:13"/>
depending upon the King, and the other upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
but both most excellently to affect the good of the
whole, and to prevent the exorbitance of any one part.
Next, the right of all the Lords and Commons in this
State is so great, that no change of goverement can be
advantage to them in that temporary capacity, except
they could each one obtaine an hereditary Crowne,
which is a thing utterly impossible. Next, their power
is meerely derivative, so that except we will conceive
that both King and people will be consenting to the
usurpation, nothing can be done; and if wee conceive
that they may by fraud gaine their consent, nothing
can withstand them. Lastly, their wisedome hath beene
ever held unquestionable, and their justice inviolable,
no Prince that ever cast himselfe thereupon was defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
no Prince that ever declined the same, proved pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous.
In sum, Parliamentary government being used
as Physicke, not dyet by the intermission of due spaces
of time, has in it all that is excelleut in all formes of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
whatsoever. If the King be an affector of true
liberty, he has in Parliament a power as extensive as
ever the Romane Dictators was, for the preventing of
all publike distresses. If the King be apt to intrude upon
the common liberties, the people have hereby many
Democraticall advantages to preserve themselves. If
Warre bee, here is the Unitive vertue of Monarchy to
encounter it, here is the admirable Councell of Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy
to manage it. If Peace be, here is the industry and
courage of democracy to improve it. Let us now see
how Kings usually, governe without Parliaments especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
such as are ruled by Councell averse from Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
I need not speake of France, and other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,
where together with these generall Assemblies, all
liberty is falne to the ground; I need not travell further
then our stories, nay, I need not passe beyond our owne
Times, my discourse will be endlesse if I doe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:65723:13"/>
The wisest of our Kings following their owne private advise, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
conducted by their owne wills, have mistaken their best Subiects,
for their greatest enemies, and their greatest enemies for their best Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,
and upon such mistakes our iustest Kings, have often done things
very dangerous. And without upbraiding I may say, that this King by
the fraud of such as have incensed him against Parliaments, and his
most loyall people, hath so far been possest with a confidence in the
zeale of Traytors, that he hath scarse ever yet enioyed that grandour
and splendor which his Ancestors did enioy. He hath met in the field
with two contrary Armies of his own Subiects, and yet that Army
which he went to destroy, and advanced their colours against him, was
more loyall than that which himselfe commanded, and yet both were
more loyall than those fatall whisperers which ingaged them so one
against the other, if the whole Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> had been more
hearkened to, rather than some few malignants of the Popish, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall
faction, the King had sooner found out the fidelity of that whole
Kingdome, and the infidelity of that wicked faction. But as things then
stood, the King was as much incensed against them, as he is against us
now, and he that did then perswade him that the Scots were no Rebels,
seemed as great an enemy as he doth now that shall defend the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency
of Sir <hi>John Hotham;</hi> there was no difference at all betwixt that
ease of the Scots, and this of ours, the King attributed then as much to
his own conscience and understanding, as he doth now, and he attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted
as little then to the publike Votes of that Kingdome, as he doth
now to this, only in this, our condition is the more unhappy, because
that so fresh and memorable experiment doth not at all profit us, but
still by a strange kinde of relapse, the King seemes now the more firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to relie upon his own private reason, and counsell, the more cause he
hath to confide in publike advertisements, and the more he professes to
doe contrary: the maine question now is, whether the Court, or the
Parliament gives the King the better Councell; the King sayes, he
cannot without renouncing his own conscience and reason, prefer the
Parliaments Councell before the Courts; and that which the King here
calls Conscience and reason, can be nothing else but meere private opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion;
for if the Councell of the Parliament were directly opposite to
common understanding, and good conscience, and the Councell of
the Court were evidently consonant thereunto, there needed no such
contestation: For example, the Parliament conceives that such and
such ill offices have been done to frame parties; and unite forces against
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65723:14"/>
the Parliament &amp; the State, and therfore they desire that such Townes,
and Forts, and the publick <hi>Militia</hi> may be intrusted to the custody and
command of such Noblemen and Gentlemen as they conside in; the
Kings secret Court-Councell suggests against this, that this request
incloseth at reasonable intention in it, and that the ayme is to wrest
all power out of the Kings hand, that he may be forced to depose him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe;
the effect of this is no more but to let the King know, that they
are more wise and faithfull than the Parliament, and that hee may doe
royally to hearken to them in condemning the Lords and Commons
of most inexpiable, unnaturall, impossible Treason, for they must
needs love him better then the Parliament, but he cannot hearken to
the Lords and Commons without offering violence to his owne reason
and conscience; here we see the misery of all, if Princes may not be
led by their owne opinions, though infused by obscure whisperers, when
they scandall the loyalty of whole kingdomes without cause, rather then
by the sacred and awfull councels of whole Nations, they are denyed
liberty of conscience, and ravisht out of their owne understandings.
And yet if Princes may be admitted to prefer such weak opinions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
Parliamentary motives and petitions, in those things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
the Lives, Estates, and Liberties of thousands, what vain things
are Parliaments, what unlimitable things are Princes, what miserable
things are Subiects? I will enlarge my selfe no longer upon this end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
Theame: Let us look upon the Venetians, and such other free
Nations, why are they so extreamly iealous over their Princes, is it for
feare lest they should attaine to an absolute power? It is meerely for
feare of this bondage, that their Princes will dote upon their owne
wills, and despise publike Councels and Laws, in respect of their owne
private opinions; were not this the sting of Monarchy, of all formes
it were the most exquisite, and to all Nations it would be the most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirable:
Happy are those Monarchs which qualifie this sting, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
are those people which are governed by such Monarchs.</p>
            <p>I come now to the particularities of our own present case, for it may be
said, that though publik advise be commonly better than private, yet in
this case it may be otherwise; some men have advised the King, that the
Parliament hath trayterous designes both against his Person &amp; Crown,
and not to be prevented but by absenting himselfe, denying his influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
and concurrence, frustrasting and protesting against their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
is invalid and seditious, and laying heavy charges of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion
upon them, to this advise the King hearkens, so the Parliament re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65723:14"/>
and advises the contrary, and now in the midst of all our cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,
of gasping <hi>Ireland,</hi> and bleeding <hi>England,</hi> the Parliament seeing
that either they must make use of their legislative power and make
ordinance to secure some Forts and settle the <hi>Militia</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
in sure hands, and to prevent the seducers of the King, or
else two Kingdomes should probably bee lost, they doe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.
The King proclaymes to the contrary notwithstanding.
The question then as I conceive is this onely, whether or no the
King hath any just cause to suspect the Parliament of Treason (and
can make appeare to the world as some of his Papers mention)
wherein they have attempted or plotted any thing against his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
and Crowne, which was the onely motive why hee sought to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
himselfe from <hi>London,</hi> and to possesse himselfe of <hi>Hull,</hi> and to
frame such an impeachment against some of both Houses, if this
can be affirmed and proved, the Parliament shall be held guilty in all
their Votes, Ordinances and Commissions concerning Sir <hi>John
Hotham</hi> and the <hi>Militia, &amp;c.</hi> Although it be the first time that any free
Parliament was ever so criminous, but if this cannot bee prooved, it
must be granted that according to the Votes of Parliaments, the Kings
departure did by frustrating Parliamentary proceedings, in a time of
such calamitie and distresse greatly indanger two Kingdomes, and
whosoever advised the King to that departure, and to the charging
of Treason, since layd upon the Parliament (and all such as have
obeyed them, in seeking to prevent publicke mischeefes) are as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious
enemies to this State, as ever received their being from it.
The businesse of <hi>Hull</hi> is most instanced in, let that be first survayd, Sir
<hi>John Hotham</hi> is to be lookt upon but as the Actor, the Parliament as the
Author in holding <hi>Hull,</hi> and therefore it is much wondered at, that the
King seemes more violent against the Actor then the Author, but
since through the Actor the Author must needs be pearced, if the Act
be found Treason, let us consider of circumstances, the same act may
be treasonable or not, if such and such circumstances vary, for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
to possesse a Towne and shut the gates against a King is Treason,
if there be not something in the act or in the intention, or in the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie
of him that shuts the gates to qualifie and correct the nature
of Treason in that act.</p>
            <p>The first thing then to be lookt on is, that the King was meerely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed
entrance for that time, his generall right was not denyed, and
no defying language was given, no act of violence was used, though
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65723:15"/>
the King for divers houres together did stand within Musket shot, and
did use termes of defiance, and this makes the act meerely defensive, or
rather passive. And therfore how this should administer to the King any
ground to leavy guards at <hi>Yorke,</hi> many men wonder, or that it should
seeme the same thing to the King, as if hee had beene pursued
to the gates of <hi>Yorke.</hi> Did the King without any feare treate Sir
<hi>John Hotham</hi> as a Traytor in the face of his Artillery, and after to
enter <hi>Hull</hi> with twentie Horse onely unarmed, and continue such
a harsh Parley, so many houres, and yet when hee was in <hi>Yorke,</hi>
in a County of so great assurance, could nothing but so many bands
of Horse and Foot secure him from the same Sir <hi>John Hotham?</hi>
The next thing considerable is the Parliaments intention: if the
Parliament have here upon turned any of the Townesmen out of
their estates, or claymed any interest in it to themselves, or have
disseized the King, utterly denying his right for the future, or
have made any other use of their possession, but meerely to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
civill warre, and to disfurnish the Kings seducers of Armes
and Ammunition: let the State bee branded with Treason, but if
none of these things bee by any credit, though their enemies should
bee judges, the most essentiall propertie of Treason must neeeds
here bee absent in this act.</p>
            <p>The next thing considerable is the Parliaments Authoritie, if the
Parliament bee not vertually the whole kingdome it selfe, if it bee
not the supreame judicature, as well in matters of State as matters of
Law, if it be not the great Councell of the Kingdome, as well as of
the King, to whom it belongeth by the consent of all nations to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
in all extraordinary cases, <hi>Ne quid detrimenti capiat Respub:</hi> let
the brand of Treason sticke upon it, nay if the Parliament would have
used this forcible meanes unlesse petitioning would not have prevay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
or if their grounds of jealousie were merely vaine, or if the
jealousie of a whole kingdome can bee counted vaine, or if they
claime any such right of judging of danger, and preventing them
without the Kings consent as ordinary and perpetuall, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any relation to publike danger, let the reward of Treason be their
guerdon.</p>
            <p>But if their authoritie be so sacred, their intention so loyall, their
act free from offensive violence, and if the King might have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented
the same repulse by sending a messenger before hand, or by
coming without such considerable Forces in so unexpected a manner,
let not treason be here misplaced. Had <hi>Faux</hi> falne by a private mans
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65723:15"/>
Sword in the very instant, when he would have given fire to his trayne,
that act had not bin punishable; and the Scots in England tooke <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>castle</hi>
but by private authoritie, yet there were other qualifications in
that act sufficient to purge it of Treason, and he is not comprehensive
of the value of a whole State, nor of the vigour of our nationall union
which does not so interpret it; how much more unjust then is it that
the whole State of England shall be condemned of Treason for doing
such an act as this, when its owne safetie, wherein none can have so
much interest as it selfe, was so highly touched? Let not all resistance to
Princes be under one notion confounded, let the principles and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients
of it be justly examined, and sometimes it will be held as pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
and loyall to Princes themselves, as at other times it is distructive
and impious. Let us by the same test try the actions, intentions, and
authoritie of the Papists now in <hi>Ireland:</hi> and compare them with this
businesse at <hi>Hull,</hi> and we shall see a diametricall contrarietie betweene
them. Their actions are all blood, rapine, and torture, all ages, all
sexes, all conditions of men have tasted of their infernall crueltie. Their
intentions are to extirpate that Religion which hath indeavored so
long to bring them from Idolatry and Atheisme, and to massacre that
nation which hath indeavoured so gently to reduce them from poverty
and beastiall barbarisme. Their chiefe leaders in this horrid tragedy, are
Jesuites and meere Bandettoes, and the Authority of King, Parliament,
and Magistracy is the principall thing which they strike at, and seeke
to overwhelme in this deplorable deluge of blood, such a direct contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
then being betwixt the true Rebells in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the misnamed
Rebells here in England, the same men which condemne the one, if
they would be true to themselves, they ought to commend the other,
for we have had experience often in England, and other nations have
had the like, that Kings have marched forth amongst their enemies to
encounter with their friends, so easily are they to be flattered into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,
and out of errour to seeke the ruine of those which ayme at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but perdition. And yet questionlesse when <hi>Richard</hi> the second
was invironed with the Forces of <hi>Spencer,</hi> and his confederates, vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to sacrifice their blood in his quarrell, and in defiance of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse
trayterous Peeres, he which would have told him, that those
Swords drawne for him, were in truth drawne against him and
his best friends, and those Swords on the other side drawne against
him, or rather against his seducers were indeed drawne for him, should
have found but poore acceptance, for without doubt the King would
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65723:16"/>
have thought such a suggestion an abuse to his sences, to his reason, to
his conscience, and an impudent imposture, worthy of nothing but
scorne and indignation. And if it had beene further pressed that the
voyce and councell of the Peeres was the voyce and councell of the
major and better part of the Kingdome, whereas <hi>Spencers</hi> party
was but of inconsiderable fortunes, and his Councell was but pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate,
and might tend to private ends, it is likely the King at the last
resort; would have referred all to his owne will and discretion; but
I have now done with the businesse of <hi>Hull,</hi> and therein I thinke
with all objections against the Loyaltie of the Parliament, for the
same reason will extend to all their Votes and actions concerning
the <hi>Militia, &amp;c.</hi> and in summe all ends in this; if Kings bee so
inclineable to follow private advise rather then publique, and to
preferre that which closes with their naturall impotent ambition,
before that which crosses the same, are without all limits, then they
may destroy their best subjects at pleasure, and all Charters and
Lawes of publike safetie and freedome are voyd, and God hath
not left humane nature any meanes of sufficient preservation. But
on the contrary, if there bee any benefit in Lawes to limit Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
when they are seduced by Privadoes, and will not hearken
to the Great Councell of the Land, doubtlesse there must be some
Court to judge of that seducement, and some authoritie to inforce
that iudgement, and that Court and Authoritie must bee the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
or some higher Tribunall, there can be no more certaine
Crisis of seducement, then of preferring private advise before pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.
But the King declines this point, and saith, that hee doth
not undervalue the whole Parliament, or lay charge of Treason
upon all, he doth confesse that divers have dissented, and divers beene
absent, &amp;c. hee deserts onely, and accuses the faction and conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy
of some few in Parliament. Wee are now at last fallen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
an issue fit to put an end to all other invectives, let us sticke
close to it. The King promises very shortly a full and satisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
narration of those few persons in Parliament: whose designe is, and
alwayes was to alter the whole frame of government both in Church
and State, and to subject both King and people to their owne law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
Arbitrary power and government; a little of this Logicke is
better then a great deale of Rhetoricke, as the case now stands. If
the King will please now to publish the particular crimes of such,
as hee hath formerly impeached of Treason, and the particular
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65723:16"/>
names of such as now hee sets forth in those Characters, and
will therein referre himselfe to the strength of his proofes, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of his matter, it is impossible that any jealousie can cloud his
integretie, or checke his power any longer; Then it will appeare
to all, that he hath not left us, out of any disaffection to Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
or out of any good opinion of Papists, Delinquents, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Incendiaries, but that hee was necessitated to depart from us, that
hee might be the better able to preserve to us our Religion, Lawes
and liberties, and that none of his solemne oathes of cordiall love to
us hath wanted integretie and faith. This will satisfie all lovers of
Justice, that he gives not light credit to weake whisperers or maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
informers (whose ayme may bee to bring this Parliament to
some ignoble tryall, or to confound it without any tryall at all by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
aspertions and meere calumnious surmises) this will proclaime
his cander and sinceritie, and set a brighter luster upon his Justice,
then any oratory whatsoever. By the performance of this promise
he shall not doe onely right to himselfe, but also to the whole
kingdome, for the distracted multitude, being at last by this meanes
undeceived, shall not onely prostrate themselves, and all their power
presently at his feet, but for ever after remaine the more assured of his
good, whether to publike liberties and Parliamentary Priviledges.
Howsoever nothing but the awfull promise of a King could make us
thinke so dishonorably of Parliaments, or suspend our judgements
so long of them; for an Aristocracy in Parliament cannot bee erected
without meanes, and what this meanes shall be, is yet to us altogether
inscrutible, for the power of Parliaments is but derivative and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
upon publike consent, and how publike consent should be gained
for the erection of a new unlawfull odious tiranny amongst us, is not
discernable, the whole kingdome is not to bee mastered against con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,
by the Traine Band, nor the Traine Bands by the Lords or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butie
Lievtenants, nor they by the maior part in Parliament, nor the
maior part in Parliament by I know not what <hi>septem-virat,</hi> there is some
mistery in this which seemes yet above, if not contrary to nature, but
since the King hath promised to open it, we will suspend our opinion
and expect it as the finall issue of all our disputes.</p>
            <p>The maine body of the difference being thus stated, I come now
to the observations of some other severall obiections against this
Parliament, and exceptions taken against arbitrary power in all
Parliaments, and I shall observe no order, but consider them
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65723:17"/>
as I finde them, either dispersed or recollected in the Kings late Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Parliament being complayned against for undutifull usage
to the King above all former Parliaments, hath said,</hi> that if they should
make the highest presidents of other Parliaments their patterne, there would
be no cause to complaine of want of modesty and dutie.</p>
            <p>The King, because some Parliaments formerly have deposed Kings,
applyes these words to those Presidents, but it may iustly be denyed
that free Parliaments did ever truely consent to the dethroaning of any
King of England, for that Act whereby <hi>Richard</hi> the second was depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
was rather the Act of <hi>Hen.</hi> the fourth, and his victorious Army, then
of the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The Parliament is taxed of reproaching this Kings government, to
render him odious to his subiects, whereas indeed all the miscariages
and grievous oppressions of former times are solely imputed to the ill
Ministers and Councellors of the King, <hi>And all the misfortunes of these
times since November, 1640. are imputed to the blame of the Parliament:</hi>
the Kings words to the Parliament are, <hi>That the condition of his Subjects
when it was at worst under his government was by many degrees more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant
and happy then this to which the Parliaments furious pretences of
reformation hath brought them to.</hi> In this case the Parliament being
accused of so haynous crimes, did uniustly betray themselves, if they
should not lay the blame upon the Kings evill Councellors, the onely
enemies and interrupters of Parliaments. Neverthelesse the King
takes this as a way of the Parliament to let them into their franke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions
of him and his actions, and takes all things spoken against
his ministers, as spoken against himselfe, how miserable here is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
of the Parliament, eyther they must sinke under uniust charges,
or be censured for the reproachers of their king, nay they are unduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
if they tell not the King himselfe, that he ought not to onerate
himselfe with the blame of his Councellors.</p>
            <p>The Parliament, because it could not obtaine no equall Justice
from the Court-Caveleers, who are conceived to be the first moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
of those stirres and tumults which happened at <hi>Westminster,</hi> did
reserve the hearing of some of the contrary side it selfe, upon this it is
objected, <hi>that the Parliament incited those seditious; and protected the
actors in it,</hi> whereas they desire Justice yet, and that both sides may
be brought fairely to an equall hearing, and before such hearing they
desire that no parties may be condemned.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:65723:17"/>
And whereas the Parliament, upon those rude commotions, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
as unheard, and of that which is unproved, and never can be
proved, <hi>That they leavyed Warre upon the King, and drove him away,</hi> yet
they desire that that meer imputation may not draw any further oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition
to their proceedings, and the necessities of the State; for if the
King could not stay at <hi>London</hi> with safety, yet being now at <hi>York</hi> in
safety, he may concurre with the advice of his Parliament; the distance
of the place needs not cause any distance of affection, since the King
conceives <hi>He hath so few enemies, and assures himself of so many friends in
Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Parliament sayes, <hi>That none of its Members may be apprehended in
case of suspicion, where no information or witnesses appear, to make good the
Prosecution, without acquainting the Parliament, if leave may be convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
obtained.</hi> In opposition to this a case is put, <hi>Of a Parliament-man
that rides from</hi> York <hi>to</hi> London, <hi>and takes a purse by the way,</hi> the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
doth not priviledge Robberies so done; for though no such thing
be likely ever to be done, yet if it be, in that case the evidence of the fact
in that instant, allowes not onely the apprehending, but the casuall kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
of such a Robber: Who sees not many differences betwixt such a
case, and that of the five Members of the lower House, where neither
Witnesses, not Informers, nor Relaters, nor any particularity of crime
could be produced? and yet by the same act the whole House might have
been surprized: And all the world knows, That the impeached Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
still suffer by that Charge, and yet can obtain no right against any
Informers, though it be now converted to their disadvantage.</p>
            <p>The Parliament does not deny the King a true-reall Interest in any
thing held by him, either <hi>in jure Coronae, or in jurae Personae,</hi> yet meerly
because it affirms, That in the same thing the State hath an Interest Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont
in cases of publique extremity; by vertue of which it may justly
seize, and use the same for its own necessary preservation. Hereupon,
the King replies, <hi>That this utterly abolishes His Interest in all things, so that
by this device, He is made uncapable, either of suffering wrong, or receiving
right:</hi> a strange violented wrested conclusion; and yet the Kings Interest
in <hi>Hull,</hi> and in the lives of his subjects, is not such an Interest as in other
moveables, neither is the Kings Interest taken away from him; the same
things are still reserved for him, in better hands then he would have put
them. The Parliament maintains its own Councell to be of honour and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65723:18"/>
power above all other, and when it is unjustly rejected, by a King se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced,
and abused by private flatterers, to the danger of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
it assumes a right to judge of that danger, and to prevent it:
the King sayes, <hi>That this gives them an arbitrary unlimitable power to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>settle
the security of all mens estates, and that they are seduceable, and may
abuse this power, nay they have abused it;</hi> and he cites the Anabaptists in
<hi>Germany,</hi> and the 30 Tyrants at <hi>Athens.</hi> That there is an Arbitrary
power in every State somewhere tis true, tis necessary, and no inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience
follows upon it; every man has an absolute power over himself;
but because no man can hate himself, this power is not dangerous, nor
need to be restrayned: So every State has an Arbitrary power over it
self, and there is no danger in it for the same reason. If the State in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusts
this to one man, or few, there may be danger in it; but the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament
is neither one nor few, it is indeed the State it self; it is no good
consequence, though the King makes so much use of it, That the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
doth abuse power, because it may: The King would think it hard
that we should conclude so against him, and yet the King challenges a
greater power then Parliaments: and indeed if the Parliament may not
save the Kingdome without the King, the King may destroy the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
in despight of the Parliament; and whether then challenges that
which is most Arbitrary, and of most danger? but the King sayes, <hi>This
Parliament has abused their power.</hi> (I wish Kings had never abused theirs
more) And the Parliament answers, <hi>That this is but his nude avirment,
and in controversies that ought not to condemn private men, much lesse ought
Parliaments to fall under it.</hi> And as for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hooker,</hi> he does not say, That
the Anabaptists in <hi>Germany</hi> did deceive Parliaments with their hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie,
and therefore inferre that Parliaments ought no further to be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted:
the stirres of the Anabaptists in <hi>Germany</hi> conclude no more against
Parliaments, then the impostures of <hi>Mahomet</hi> in <hi>Arabia</hi> do. <hi>And as
for the 30 Tyrants of Athens,</hi> we know they were not so chosen by the
people, as our Knights, Citizens, and Burgesses are, nor created or cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
by any Kings Writ, as our Peers are; nor did they so meerly depend
upon their own good abearing, and the good liking both of King and
State, as our Lords and Commons now do; neither had they so many
equalls and Rivalls as both our Houses contain: we know their power
was not founded upon the consent of the Citizens, but the strength of
their Souldiers; neither were their Souldiers such as our Train Bands,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65723:18"/>
but meer mercinaries of desperate, or perhaps no Fortunes, whose Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue
was rapine, whose Trade was murther: I fear they were more like
our Cavaliers at <hi>Yorke,</hi> then the <hi>Militia</hi> at <hi>London:</hi> Were our new <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi>
any other our old Trayn Bands, or our new Lievtenants, and
Deputies, any other then the same Lords and Gentlemen, with very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
variation, which before were very well reputed of, both by King and
Commons, and not yet by either excepted against, or did the whole fate
of the kingdom depend meerly upon the new <hi>Militia,</hi> this new device
of an <hi>Aristocrasie</hi> might seem the more plausible; but as things now
stand, this new <hi>Aristocraticall</hi> Fabrick cannot seem to any impartiall
man, but as empty a shadow, and ayrie a dream as ever mans fancie
abused it self withall.</p>
            <p>The Parliament sayes, <hi>That the Kings power is fiduciary, and not to be
used against the Kingdom, but for it only:</hi> The King hereupon demands,
<hi>May any thing be taken from a man, because he is trusted with it? Or may
the person himself take away the thing he trusts when be will, and how he will?</hi>
Our case of <hi>Hull</hi> is not so generall, The things there remaining in the
Kings trust for the use of the Kingdom were Arms, and by consequence
of more danger, then other kinde of Chattels. And if I intrust my
cloak to anothers custody, I may not take it away again by force; But
if it be my sword, and there is strong presumption, that it may be drawn
upon me, I may use any means to secure it.</p>
            <p>The Parliament claims a right of declaring, and interpreting Law.
The King makes this question thereupon? <hi>Is the Law it self subject to
your Votes, that whatsoever you say, or do, shall be lawfull, because you declare
it so? Am I supream, and yet you above me? Must my power be governed by
your discretion?</hi> This is the Popes Arrogance, That all must submit their
understanding, and Scripture it self, to His declaring power: and a
case is put of the Irish Rebels, making themselves a major part in
Parliament, and so voting against the true Religion, &amp;c. In perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous,
uncontroverted things, the Law is it own interpreter, and there
no Judge is requisite, and the Parliament cannot be taxed to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
Law by the rule of their Actions; They have squared their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
according to Law, They may be censured, but they cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced
of any injustice. Tis true, In meer matters of State, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65723:19"/>
is not bound to strict presidents at all times, but in matters of
right, and justic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they have not deviated, either to the right hand, or to
the left: Howsoeve<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, In matters of Law and State both, where ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guity
is, some determin<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion must be supream, and therein, either the
K<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs power and t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ust must be guided by the discre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
or else the Parliament, and all other Courts must be overruled
by the Kings meer discretion; and there can be nothing said against the
Arbitrary supremacy of Parliaments, &amp;c. But farre more upon better
grounds, may be said against the Arbitrary supremacy of the King. As
for the Popes Arrogance, who undertakes to interpret Scripture where
it wants no interpreter, And in matters of meer opinion to usurpe over
al<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mens consciences; As if he had an infallibility in his sole breast. He
is not an instance so fitly to be alleaged against Parliaments, as Princes,
For slavish very probable, That if the Church had not submitted it self to
so <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a condition under one Man, but had been governed by some
generall Junto of Divines fairly elected, it had never swerved into such
soul idolatry, and superstition, as it has done.</p>
            <p>As for the case of <hi>Ireland,</hi> I conceive, tis improperly urged; For
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> are one and the same Dominion, There is as true
and intimate an Union betwixt them, as betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales;</hi>
And though by reason of remote situation, they do not meet in one, and
the same Parliament; yet their Parliaments, as to some purposes, are
not to be held severall Parliaments. And therefore, if the papists in
<hi>Ireland</hi> were stronger, and had more Votes in Parliament then the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants,
yet they would want authority to overrule any thing voted,
and established before in <hi>England.</hi> For the reason, why the minor part
in all suffrages subscribes to the major is, That bloud may not be shed.
For in probability, The major part will prevail, and else strife, and
bloudshed would be endlesse: Wherefore the major part in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by
the same reason ought to sit down and acquiesce, because <hi>Ireland</hi> is not
a severall monarchy from <hi>England;</hi> nor is that a major part of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
and <hi>England</hi> too; for if it were, it would give Law to us, as we now
give Law there; and their Statutes would be of as much vertue here, as
ours are there.</p>
            <p>The Parliament <hi>In case of extream danger, challenges an Authority of
setling the Militia in sure hands, and removing doubtfull persons; if the
King will not be entreated to do it of himself?</hi> The Kings sayes, <hi>This is to put
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65723:19"/>
His intrusted power out of Himself into others, and so to devest and disable
Himself for the protection of His people.</hi> This is a strange mistake. The
Parliament desires no removeall of that power which was in the King,
But that which was in such or such a Substitute? And how doe this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest
and disable the King? And if the King sayes, That He has a better
opinion of such a Substitute, then of an other, Though the Parliament
conceive otherwise, Then what does He but prefer His own private opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
before the most Honourable of all Councells, before the voyce of
the whole Kingdom? What higher Law then have we remaining then
the Kings will? And as for his account to God, will it be easie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for him
to pleade, That he used such an instrument of His own meer discretion
against publike advice if things prove unhappy, then that He followed
the most noble Councell, and such whose lifes, fortunes, and interests,
were most deeply concerned in it? And as for those absurde unreason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
incredible suppositions of the injustice, and treasons of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
as if they were lesse carefull of the publike good, then single
Rulers, Though it be spoken in derision, wise men perhaps may be not
so apt to laugh in applause, as in contempt of it. For how has the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
removed the rub of all Law out of its way, because it assumes
to it self to be higher then any other Court, and to be in declaring Law,
as farre beyond the Kings single countermands in Parliament, as other
inferiour Courts are out of Parliaments? Or how, has it erected a new
upstart Authority to affront the King, and maintain an Aristocraticall
usurpations, when the main body of the <hi>Militia</hi> is still the same as it
was, and such as the King professes no suspition of, and no alteration
is of the heads thereof, except only in some few popishly inclined, or
not publikely so honoured, and confided in as they ought? And when
the same Allegiance is performed, The same Supremacy of power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed
to be now in the King over the <hi>Militia,</hi> as has ever been? N<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y,
What ground can there be for this imaginary usurpation, when the
King professes, He fixes not that traiterous designe upon both, or either
House of Parliament, being most confident of the Loyalty, Good
Affectio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Integrity of that great Body? Is the main body of the
Kingdom loyall? Is the main body of the Parliament loyall? Is the
King true to Himself? And is all His great partie of Clergymen, Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers,
Souldiers, &amp;c. constant? And yet is there a machination in hand,
to introduce Aristocraticall usurpation odious to all men; which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65723:20"/>
Kingdom, Parliament, King, nor all the Royallists can oppose?
What a strange unlathomable machination, and work of darknesse is
this? <hi>But this is said to be done by cunning, force, absence, or accident.</hi> If it
be by cunning, Then we must suppose that the Kings party in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
has lost all their Law, policy, and subtilty, And that all the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
except some few are luld-a-sleep by <hi>Mercuries</hi> Minstrelsie; or
that some diabolicall charme has closed up all their various eyes. If it
be by force, Then we must suppose that our Aristocraticall heads carry
about them great store of that Serpents teeth which yeilded heretofore
so sudden and plentifull a harvest of armed men, being but cast into the
furrows of the earth, Though their armies have been hitherto invisible,
yet we must suppose, That they are in a readinesse to rise upon the first
Alarum beaten. If it be by absence, then we must suppose, That this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristocraticall
machination is easily yet to be prevented, for tis not a hard
matter to draw a full apparence together, and that we see has been done
lately by the order of the House it self. Nay, we see tis not the House,
but the opposite part that desires to scatter, and divide, and draw away,
and as much as in them lyes to hinder a full assembly: And therefore,
This is not the way. If it be by accident, Then we must be contented to
expect, and have a little patience; Fortune is not alwayes constant to
one certain posture, nor do the Celestiall bodies confine themselves to
one unaltered motion.</p>
            <p>The Parliament requests of the King, <hi>That all great Officers of State,
by whom publike affaires shall be transacted, may be chosen by approbation, or
nomination of the great Councell.</hi> The King takes <hi>this as a thing maliciously
plotted against him, as a proposition made in mockery of him, as a request
which He cannot yeeld to, without shewing Himself unworthy of that trust,
which Law reposes in Him, and of His descent from so many great and famous
Ancestors: He conceives, He cannot perform the Oath of protecting His peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
if He abandon this power, and assume others into it. He conceives it such
a Flowre of the Crown, as is worth all the rest of the Garland, not to be parted
with all upon any extremity of conquest or imprisonment; nor for any low sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did
considerations of wealth, and gain whatsoever. He conceives, That if
He should passe this, He should retain nothing but the Ceremonious Ensignes
of Royalty, or the meer sight of a Crown and Scepter; (nay the Stock being
dead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Twigs would not long flourish;) but as to true, and reall power, He
should remain, but the outside, the picture, the signe of a King.</hi> Could this
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65723:20"/>
be, If all Parliaments were not taken as deadly enemies to Royalty?
the substance of the request seems to be no more but this, That it would
please the King to be advised by Parliaments, rather then His own meer
understanding, or any inferiour Councellors in those things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
the liberties, and lifes of the whole people. And how could this
request seem equall to a demanding of the Crown, to a dethroning of
the King, and to a leaving of the Kingdom destitute of protection, if
Parliaments were not supposed mortall enemies to Princes, and Princes
not supposed, but openly declared enemies to Parliaments; if the King
choose such a man Treasurer or Keeper out of his own good liking only,
or upon recommendation of such a Courtier, here he is devested of no
power; but if it be upon the recommendation of the whole Kingdome
in Parliament, who in all probability can judge better, and are more
concerned, this is an emptying himself of Majesty, and devesting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
of Power. Ordinary reason cannot suggest otherwise hereupon,
but either Parliaments affect not Kings, nor their own good, nor would
make good elections, or else Kings affect not Parliaments, nor the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
good, and therefore they oppose such elections, meerly because
they are good: but let us observe the Kings reasons against Parliamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
elections; For first, <hi>He conceives them prejudiciall for the people:</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<hi>Dishonourable to himself.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man is by nature of restlesse ambition; as the meanest vassall thinks
himself worthy of some greatnesse, so the most absolute Monarch aspires
to something above his greatnesse. Power being over obtained by haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
mindes, quickly discovers that it was not first aimed at meerly to effect
Noble actions, but in part to insult over others; and ambitious men
thirst after that power which may do harm, as well as good; nay, though
they are not resolved to do harm, yet they would be masters of it,—<hi>Qui
nolunt occidere quenquam—Posse volunt.</hi> And yet let this power
be added, the minde still remains unfilled, still some further Terrestriall
omnipotence, a sharing with God, and surmounting above mortall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
is affected. Our Law has a wholesome Maxime, That the King
may onely do that which is just; but Courtiers invert the sense of it, and
tell him, That all is just which he may do, or which he is not restrained
from doing by Law. Such and such things Princes ought not to do,
though no Law limited them from doing thereof; but now those things
which by nature they abhorre to do, yet they abhorre as much to be limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65723:21"/>
from. That disposition which makes us averse from cruelty and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
we account a noble and vertuous disposition; but that Law which
shall restrain us from the same is stomacked at, and resisted, as a harsh bit
to put into our mouths, or bonds upon our arms. <hi>Antoninus Pius</hi> is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
renowned for communicating all weighty affairs, and following
publike advice a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> dapprobation in all great expedients of high concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
and he was not more honourable then prosperous therein. Had
he been a meer servant to the State, he coul<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not have condescended fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
and yet if he had done necessarily, what he did voluntarily, the
same thing had been in the same manner effectuall; for tis not the meer
putting or not putting of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw, that does after the nature of good or
evill. Power then to do such an evill, or not to do such a good, is in
truth no reall power, nor desired out of any noblenesse, but rather win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
arrogance; and as it is uselesse to men truely noble, so to men that
love evill for evill ends tis very dangerous. What will <hi>Nero</hi> more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spise,
then to condescend as <hi>Antoninus</hi> did? yet 'twere more necessary that
<hi>Nero</hi> were limited then <hi>Antoninus;</hi> for excessive power added to <hi>Nero</hi>'s
cruelty, serves but as Oyl poured upon flame. When Princes are as po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
as vicious, we know what Ministers swarm about them; and the
end is, That as vast power corrupts and inclines them to i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Councells
so they perish at last by Councellors worst of all. Tis pretended
that Princes cannot be limitted from evill, but they may be disabled
from doing good thereby, which is not alwayes true; and yet if it were,
the people had better want some right, then have too much wrong done
them: for what is more plain then this, That the <hi>Venetians</hi> live
more happily under their conditionate Duke, then the <hi>Turks</hi> do under
their most absolute Emperours. Neverthelesse, if we consider the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Trophees of <hi>Rome</hi> which it gained under Consuls, and conditiona<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
Commanders, we may suppose that no defect at all could be in that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular
and mixt government. And our neighbours in the <hi>Netherlands</hi>
are a good instance; for they being to cope with the most Puissant and
free Prince of Christendom, being but the torn relique of a small Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
yet for their defence, would not put themselves under a <hi>Dictatorian</hi>
power, but they prepared themselves for that so terrible encounter, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the Conduct of a Generall much limitted. Neither have those
straitned Commissi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns yeelded any thing but victories to the States, and
solid honour to the Princes of <hi>Orange;</hi> and what more, the mightiest Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:65723:21"/>
of our age have atchieved or enjoy'd, besides the filling of
a phantasticall humour with imaginary grandour. I speak not this
in favour of any alteration in <hi>England,</hi> I am as zealously addicted
to Monarchy, as any man can, without dotage: but I know there
are severall degrees of Prerogatives Royall, some whereof have
greater power of protection, and lesse of oppression; and such I
desire to be most studious of: In some things I know tis dangerous
to circumscribe Princes, but in others there may be great danger in
leaving them to their pleasure, and scarce any hope at all of benefit;
and amongst other things, the choice of publike Officers, if the State
have (at least) some share therein with the King, what considerable
inconvenience can happen thereby to the State or King, is not in me
to foresee: but if it have no share, experience sufficient teacheth us
what great disasters may happen. And so for the disusing and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solving
of Parliaments; if the Parliament divide some part of that
power with the King, I see great good, but no harm at all that can
ensue, either to weaken the Crown, or disturb the subject there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.
But it will be said in the next place, <hi>If this disables not the
King from protecting the Subject, yet it diminishes his own Right, and
leaves him but the shadow of Royalty.</hi> This is grounded upon a great
mistake; for some men think it a glorious thing to be able to kill, as
well as to save, and to have a kinde of a Creators power over Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects:
but the truth is, such power procures much danger to ill Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
and little good to any; for it begets not so much love as fear in
the subiect, though it be not abused; and the fear of the subject does
not give so perfect a Dominion as love. Were <hi>Hannibal, Scipio<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
&amp;c.</hi> the lesse honoured or beloved because they were not independ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent?
surely no, they were the lesse feared, and for the same cause the
more honoured and beloved. Or were <hi>Alexander, Pyrrbus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</hi> the
more honoured or beloved, because they were independant? I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
the contrary, and that they had lived more gloriously, and died
lesse violently, if a more moderate power had rendred them lesse inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
in their own thoughts, and lesse feared in other mens. Was <hi>Caesar</hi>
the private man lesse successefull in his Warres, or lesse dear in all his
souldiers eyes, or lesse powerfull in his Countrey-mens affections,
then <hi>Caesar</hi> the perpetuall Dictator? No, if the Imperiall Throne of
the World added any thing to <hi>Caesar,</hi> 'twas not excellence, nor true
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65723:22"/>
glory, 'twas but the externall complements of pomp and ostentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and that might perhaps blow up his minde with vanity, and fill
the people with <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, it could not make <hi>Caesar</hi> a nobler, gallant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
greater <hi>Caesar</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he was. I expect no lesse then to be laught
at at <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourt, and to be h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld the author of a strange paradox, by those
men which stick not to say, That our King is now no more King of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> then he is King of <hi>France,</hi> because his meer pleasure there,
is not so predominant in all cases of good and evill whatsoever: but
I regard not those fond things which cannot see in humane nature
what is depraved in it, and what not, and what proceeds from vain,
and what from true glory; and wherein the naturall perfection of
power and honour, differs from the painted rayes of spurious Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty
and Magnificence. To me the Policy of <hi>Scotland</hi> seems more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite
in poynt of prerogative, then any other in <hi>Europe,</hi> except
ours: And if the splendor, and puissance of a Prince consist in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding
religious, wise, magnanimous, warlike subjects, I think
the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> is more to be admired then the King of <hi>France;</hi>
and that he is so, to the meer ingenuity of Government, I ascribe it.
But some will allow, <hi>That to follow the pattern of</hi> Antoninus <hi>freely,
and voluntarily, as he did, is not dishonourable in a Prince; but to be
under any Obligation or Law to do so, is ignoble.</hi> And this is as much
as to say, That Law, though good, yet <hi>quate<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> Law is burthenous
to mans nature; and though it be so but to corrupted nature, in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
as it retains from nothing, but that which nature in its purity
would it self restrain from; yet corrupted nature it self is to be
soothed and observed. I have done with this point: 'twas spoken
in honour of <hi>Hen. 7.</hi> That he governed his subjects by his Laws,
his Laws, by his Lawyers, and (it might have been added) his subjects,
Laws and Lawyers by advice of Parliament, by the regulation of
that Court which gave life and birth to all Laws. In this Policy is
comprized the whole act of Soveraignty; for where the people are
subject to the Law of the Land and not to the will of the Prince,
and where the Law is left to the interpretation of sworn upright
Judges, and not violated by power; and where Parliaments super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intend
all, and in all extraordinary cases, especially betwixt the
King and Kingdom, do the faithfull Offices of Umpirage, all things
remain in such a harmony, as I shall recommend to all good Princes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:65723:22"/>
The Parliament conceives that the King cannot apprehend any
just fear from Sir <hi>John Hotham,</hi> or interpret the meer shutting of
<hi>Hull</hi> gates, and the sending away of Arms and Ammunition in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
to both Houses, to be any preparation for Warre and Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
against him at <hi>York,</hi> and therefore they resolve to raise Forces
against those Forces which the King raises to secure himself from Sir
<hi>John Hotham. The King hereupon charges the Parliament of levying
Warre against Him, under pretence of His levying Warre against them.</hi>
This is matter of fact and the World must judge whether the Kings
preparations in the North be onely sutable to the danger of Sir
<hi>John Hotham</hi> or no; and whether the Parliament be in danger of
the Kings strength there or no: Or whether is more probable at this
time, that the King is incensed against the Parliament, or the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament
against the King: or that the King is more intentive to assayl
the Parliament, or the Parliament the King. 'Tis true, the King
abjures any intention of making Warre against his Parliament; but
what he intends against the malignant party in or out of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
is not exprest: and the King abjures invasive Warre against
them; but whether he think not himself first invaded already, is not
exprest; and the specifying of a faction in Parliament of some few
malignants, secures none; for none can plead force, and none ought
to plead folly in Treasons of this nature, and the major part of
the Houses can neither plead absence or dissent; and those which
can, must not be their own purgators. Besides, the act of Sir <hi>John
Hotham</hi> is disputable; the King adjudges it Treason, the Parliament
adjudge it no Treason; and the King has not declared whether he
will refer this to the tryall of the sword only, or to some other tryall;
and if so, To what kinde of tryall the judgement of a Parliament
shall be submitted: If we call another Parliament to judge of this,
so we may appeal in <hi>infinitum;</hi> and why another should be cleerer
then this, we cannot imagine: If we could constitute a higher
Court for this appeal, so we might do in <hi>infinitum</hi> also; but we
know no higher can be imagined: and if we appeal to a lower, that
were to invert the course of nature: and to confound all Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
for ever; if we call all the Kingdom to judge of this, we do
the same thing as to proclaim Civill Warre, and to blow the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet
of generall confusion: And if we allow the King to be the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65723:23"/>
sole, supream competent Judge in this case, we resigne all into his
hands, we give lifes, liberties, Laws, Parliaments, all to be held at
meer discretion? For there is in the interpretation of Law upon the
last appeal, the same supremacy of power requisite, as is in making
it; And therefore grant the King supream interpreter, and tis all
one, as if we granted him to be supream maker of Law; and grant
him this, and we grant him to be above all limits, all conditions, all
humane bonds whatsoever. In this Intricacy therefore, where the
King and Parliament disagree, and judgement must be supream,
either in the one or other, we must retire to ordinary justice, And
there we see, if the King consent not with the ordinary Judge, the
Law thinks it fit, that the King subscribe, rather then the Judge.</p>
            <p>And if this satisfie not, We must retire to the principles of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
and there search, whether the King or Kingdom be to be
lookt upon as the efficient, and finall cause, and as the proper Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
of all power. Neither is the oath of supremacy indangered
hereby; for he that ascribes more to the whole universality, then to
King; yet ascribes to the King a true supremacy of power, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
above all particulars: Nor is our allegiance temerated, For
when the Judge on the Bench delivers Law contrary to the Kings
command; This is not the same thing, as to proceed against the
Kings person, upon any judgement given against him. The King
as to His own person, is not to be forcibly repelled in any ill doing<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
nor is He accountable for ill done, Law has only a directive, but no
coactive force upon his person; but in all irregular acts where no
personall force is, Kings may be disobeyed, their unjust commands
may be neglected, not only by communities, but also by single men
sometimes. Those men therefore that maintain, That all Kings are
in all things and commands (as well where personall resistance ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companies,
as not) to be obeyed, as being like Gods, unlimitable,
and as well in evill, as in good unquestionable, are sordid flatterers.
And those which allow no limits but directive only, And those no
other but divine and naturall; And so make all Princes as vast in
power as the Turk, (for He is subject to the directive force of God,
and natures Laws;) and so allow subjects a dry right without all
remedy, are almost as stupid as the former. And those lastly, That
allow humane Laws to obleage Kings more then directively, in all
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65723:23"/>
cases where personall violence is absence, and yet allow no Judges
of those Laws, but the King Himself, run into absurdities as grosse
as the former.</p>
            <p>I come now to those seven doctrines, and positions, which the
King by way of recapitulation layes open as so offensive—And
they run thus:</p>
            <p>1. <hi>THat the Parliament has an absolute indisputable power of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring
Law, So that all the right of the King and people, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends
upon their pleasure.</hi> It has been answered, That this power
must rest in them, or in the King, or in some inferiour Court, or
else all suites must be endlesse, and it can no where rest more safely
then in Parliament.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>That Parliaments are bound to no precedents.</hi> Statutes are not
binding to them, Why then should precedents? Yet there is no obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
stronger then the Justice and Honor of a Parliament.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>That they are Parliaments, and may judge of publike necessity
without the King, and dispose of anything.</hi> They may not desert the
King, but being deserted by the King, when the Kingdom is in
distresse, They may judge of that distresse, and relieve it, and are
to be accounted by the vertue of representation, as the whole body
of the State.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>That no Member of Parliament ought to be troubled for treason,
&amp;c. without leave.</hi> This is intended of suspicions only, And when
leave may be seasonably had, and when competent accusers appear
not in the impeachment.</p>
            <p>5. <hi>That the Soveraign power resides in both Houses of Parliament,
the King having no negative voyce.</hi> This power is not claimed as ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary;
nor to any purpose, But to save the Kingdom from ruine,
and in case where the King is so seduced, as that He preferres dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
men, and prosecutes His loyall Subjects.</p>
            <p>6. That levying forces against the personall commands of the King,
(though accompanied with his presence) is not levying warre against the
King: But warre against His authority, though not person, is warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
the King? <hi>If this were not so, The Parliament seeing a seduced
King, ruining Himself, and the Kingdom could not save both, but
must stand and look on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:65723:24"/>
7. <hi>That according to some Parliaments, they may depose the King?</hi>
Tis denyed, That any King was deposed by a free Parliament fairly
elected.</p>
            <p>To stand in comparison with these, I shall recite some such posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
as the Kings papers offer to us; And they follow thus.</p>
            <p>1. THat regall power is so derived from God and the Law,
as that it has no dependence upon the trust, and consent
of man; and the King is accountable therefore to God and His
other Kingdoms, not to this; And it is above the determination
of Parliaments, and by consequence boundlesse.</p>
            <p>2. That the King is supream indefinitely, <hi>viz.</hi> As well
<hi>universis,</hi> as <hi>singulis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. That the King has such a propriety in His Subjects,
Towns, Forts, &amp;c. As is above the propriety of the State, and
not to be seized by the Parliament, though for the publike safety.</p>
            <p>4. That so farre as the King is trusted, He is not accountable
how He performs, <hi>So that in all cases the Subject is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medilesse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. That the being of Parliaments is meerly of grace, So
that the King might justly have discontinued them, and being
summoned, they are limited by the writ, and that <hi>ad consili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi>
Only, and that but in <hi>quibusdam arduis,</hi> And if they
passe the limits of the Writ, they may be imprisoned. That if
the King desert them, they are a voyde assembly, and no honour
due to them, nor power to save the Kingdom, That Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
priviledges are no where to be read of, And so their repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentation
of this whole Kingdom is no priviledge, nor addes no
Majesty, nor authority to them. That the major part in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
is not considerable, when so many are absent, or dissent.
That the major part is no major part, Because the fraud, and
force of some few over-rules them. That Parliaments may do
dishonourable things, nay treasonable: Nay, That this hath been
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65723:24"/>
so blinded by some few malignants, That they have abetted trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
in Sir <hi>John Hotham,</hi> Trampled upon all Law, and the
Kings prerogative, And sought to inslave the whole Kingdom
under the Tyranny of some few, And sought the betraying of
Church, and State, And to the same erected an upstart Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
in the new <hi>Militia,</hi> and levyed warre upon the King, under
pretence that He levies warre upon them. That Parliaments
cannot declare Law, but in such and such particular cases legally
brought before them. That Parliaments are questionable, and
tryable elsewhere.</p>
            <p>These things, we all see, tend not only to the desolation of this
Parliament, but to the confusion of all other, And to the advancing
of the King to a higher power over Parliaments, then ever He had
before over inferiour Courts. Parliaments have hitherto been San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuaries
to the people, and banks against Arbitrary tyranny; But
now the meer breath of the King, blasts them in an instant; and
how shall they hereafter secure us, when they cannot now secure
themselves? Or how can we expect justice, when the meer impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
of treason, without hearing, tryall, or judgement, shall sweep
away a whole Parliament; nay all Parliaments for ever? And yet
this is not yet the depth of our misery, For that private Councell
which the King now adheres to, and preferres before Parliaments,
will still inforce upon our understandings, That all these doctrines,
and positions tend to the perfection of Parliaments; And all the
Kings forces in the North, to the protection of Law and liberty.
I finde my Reason already captivated, I cannot further—</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:65723:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:65723:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
