<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some observations made upon the root Cassummuniar, called otherwise rysagone, imported from the East-Indies Shewing its nature and virtues, and its usefulness above others as yet written of, in apoplexies, convulsions, fits of the mother, the griping of the gutts, with probable conjectures of its fitness to cure many other distempers; and its being the most proper corrector of the Jesuits powder, rendring that ... harmless. By John Peachie, Doctor of Physick.</title>
            <author>Peachi, John, fl. 1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56772</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P938AA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220360</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831764</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36231</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A56772)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36231)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2052:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some observations made upon the root Cassummuniar, called otherwise rysagone, imported from the East-Indies Shewing its nature and virtues, and its usefulness above others as yet written of, in apoplexies, convulsions, fits of the mother, the griping of the gutts, with probable conjectures of its fitness to cure many other distempers; and its being the most proper corrector of the Jesuits powder, rendring that ... harmless. By John Peachie, Doctor of Physick.</title>
                  <author>Peachi, John, fl. 1683.</author>
                  <author>Pechey, John, 1655-1716, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst, at the Bible and Three Crowns, at the lower end of Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page mutilated, affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36231:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME
OBSERVATIONS
Made upon the ROOT
CASSUMMUNIAR,
Called otherwiſe
RYSAGONE,
Imported from the <hi>Eaſt-Indies.</hi>
SHEWING
Its Nature and Virtues, and its Uſefulneſs above others
as yet written of, in Apoplexies, Convulſions, Fits of
the Mother, the Griping of the Gutts, with probable
conjectures of its Fitneſs to Cure many other Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers;
and its being the moſt proper Corrector of the
Jeſuits Powder, rendring that Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5+ letters">
                  <desc>•••••…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and Harmleſs.</p>
            <p>By JOHN PEACHIE, Doctor of Phyſick.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <bibl>Epictetus.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> at the
Lower end of <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:36231:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:36231:2"/>
TO THE
Right Worſhipfull
<hi>Sir Jonathan Keate,</hi>
BARONET:
A True Patron of Piety,
Vertue and Learning.
<hi>J. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humbly dedicateth the Enſuing Obſervations, in
teſtimony of his grateful reſentment of
his Favours, with apprecation of all
Grace and Happineſs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:36231:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36231:3"/>
            <head>OF THE
VERTUES
OF
Caſſummuniar.</head>
            <p>TO give a Deſcription of the Herb, its place,
its growth, whether it beareth any flower,
or Seed, is not in my power, having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
no account along with it from my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
Factor to the Honorable the <hi>Eaſt-Indy</hi> Company:
Only thus much is moſt certain, it is a Plant eſteemed
even by Princes themſelves, ſome part of what I have,
being taken out of the King of <hi>Golcondaes</hi> Garden,
one of the greateſt, and wealthieſt Princes in <hi>India,</hi>
and the Prieſts, who are the <hi>Brackmannes,</hi> of the <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagorean</hi>
Sect of Philoſophers, do many and great
Cures with it, for which they are ſo much eſteemed
not only by the Natives, but alſo forreign Merchants
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36231:4"/>
that reſide there, the Engliſh themſelves preferring
them before their own Country men, when they labour
under thoſe diſeaſes that reign in the <hi>Eaſt-Indys.</hi>
They are very excellent Botaniſts, admirably skilled
in the nature, and uſe of Plants, and having an extra-ordinary
variety of them have improved Galenical
Phyſick to a very great height. I do not underſtand
that they are acquainted with any of the Chymical
waies of ſeparating the pure, from the impure parts:
or underſtand the uſe of Minerals: but as they are
nouriſhed by the produce of the Earth, ſo they are cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
by the off-ſpring thereof, not feeding upon any ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
killed for their uſe, fearing they ſhould eat ſome of
their Anceſtors; becauſe they hold a tranſmigration of
ſouls. This root though it might ſerve to aromatize
their diet, and is certainly a good ſtomachical, yet they
uſe it only medicinally, and that in ſo homely a way
as is becoming ſuch plain, and ſimple men, unacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
with the Confectioners or Apothecarys Art; they
cut the Root tranſverſe, or croſs-waies, and having ſo
done, they dry it in the Sun with great care, and when
they have ocaſion to uſe it, grind it betwixt two ſtones,
adding water to it, after the manner of Painters grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
their Colours: being reduced hereby into the
conſiſtency of an Electuary they adminiſter two or three
drams of it at a time to their patients.</p>
            <p>As to its qualities it is moderately hot, and very
aſtringent, it conſiſteth of very fine parts, wrapped up
in, and tied to an earthy matter; and may be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
amongſt your Aromata or Spices. It exceedingly
recruiteth the animal and vital Spirits, and may well
be imagined by its taſte, colour, and ſmell, to be an
aperitive medicine. But by the experience I have had of
it, I find it admirably to agree with the animal ſpirits,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36231:4"/>
and a proper remedy against theit irregularities
With Spirit of wine I have drawn a good Spirit from
it, and with the remaining <hi>faeces</hi> made a very good
extract, and conceive its extract made with fountain-water,
might be better than the powder in the bloody
flux, for which it is an excellent remedy. The Spirit
is good to mix with cordials, and is a very good me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine
outwardly uſed: and will lay ſcents better than
any thing yet ſound out.</p>
            <p>It is matter of no ſmall grief and trouble to any
perſon endowed with pitty or compaſſion, to ſee how
many perſons labour under Apoplexies, Falling-ſikneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
Convulſions, and convulſive-motions, Fits of the
Mother, which diſeaſes have ſuch ſtupendious ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes,
that they do aſtoniſh the beholders, Nature
ſeeming to be in an earth-quake, and in its laſt agony:
and by the frequent aggreſs of ſo dreadful a Diſtemper,
thoſe endowments which diſtinguiſh us from irrational
creatures are in a great meaſure loſt; our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
that great Light very much darkned our memory,
that excellent Repoſitory, broken, and like a Sieve lets
through moſt, if not all the ſpecies preſented to it, ſo that
our fitneſs to ſerve either God or Man is very much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired.
And yet notwithſtanding all the Boaſts of Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,
and the ſingular and prudent management of Gale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,
with the help of what medicines Nature or Art hath
yet preſented, ſcarce one of a hundred hath proved
a trophy of their Victory over ſo obſtinate a diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per;
I mean not thoſe whoſe diſeaſe doth ariſe from
any fault in the firſt waies, as children which have,
wormes, or the nerves diſſeminated in the ſtomach,
being affected with ill matter therein conteined, of
which an eaſy way of cure doth effect the deſired end
<hi>viz.</hi> By evacuating and diſcharging nature by Vomit
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36231:5"/>
or Purges: but when the diſtemper hath its riſe from
the head, and is of long continuance and duration;
The way of cure Iuſe is firſt generals as Bleeding, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits,
or Purges ordinarily uſed in this caſe. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
where the diſtemper is in the head originally; I
uſe to cut off the hair, and uſe a fomentation of the
ſpirit night and morning. As for internal remedies:
℞ <hi>Caſſummuniar. pulv. ℥ii conſerv flor. Betonic.
℥i cum ſyrupo Pae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>: q. s. fiat electuar. s. a. Capiat
q. N. M. ter in die horis medicis ſupbibend. ℥iiii
ſequentis. Julapii ℞ aq. florum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iliae, ceraſor. nigr: an
<abbr>lb</abbr>. Spirit. Lavendul. Compoſit. Math. ℥iii. ſyrup.
Paeon. q. s. Miſce.</hi> I ſhall not give Inſtances of thoſe
many who have had their Fits hereby leſſened and
abated, and very many cured. I could inſtance in a
Gentlewoman, who had a concuſſion of her head, which
ſhe laboured under for half a year in the Country, after
a fall down ſtairs with her head foremoſt, coming up
to <hi>London</hi> was cured by a decoction, and electuary
made of this root, to mine, as well as her admiration,
and liveth now free from any ill effects of that ill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident.
I was called to a Gentlewoman that had
hyſterick. Fits with unuſual ſymptoms, accompanied
with as great oppreſſions, and debility in her Spirits
when her Fits went off, as when upon her, as ſhe appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended.
The Medicines uſed I find upon the file to have
been only theſe: ℞ <hi>Caſſummuniar. pulv. ℥s Conſerv.
flor. boragin. ℥i cum syrup Paeon, q. S. M. fiat
electuarium, capiat. q. N. M. ſuperbibend cockl.</hi> viii <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent.
Julapii. ℞ aq. atriplic.</hi> ℥vi <hi>puleg. spirit Lavend.
composit. Mat. an ℥i M.</hi> The common plaſter to the
navil, and a nodul of <hi>Galbanum;</hi> in two hours her
Fits ceaſed, and with the uſe of the ſame Remedies ſome
few daies, ſhe was ſo far cured, that they have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36231:5"/>
theſe twelve months, the occaſion of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper
not proceeding from any paſſions of the
mind.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of it drunk with black-cherry water
every new, and full of the Moon, I conceive may be a
ſoveraign preſervative for them, who have had the
common ſymptoms that are forerunners of that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
diſeaſe the Apoplexy, or been once attacqued by it,
and eſcaped it, for prevention of the ſecond Fit, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
mortal. To conclude this head; the greateful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
as well as the uſefulneſs of it, to prevent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions,
looſeneſs, and gripings in children, maketh
me commend this medicine to Country Gentelwomen,
to Midwives, and Nurſes, and the rather becauſe
of its ſafety, and but one incovenience can attend the
uſe of it, which is its binding quality, which is rarely
a prejudice, where the Medicine diſcuſſeth wind, as this
doth. They may boil it in their water-pap, their
milk, or what elſe they think fit to give the child. I
prefer it before any other Galenical or Chymical Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine,
for that I have obſerved, that by the nauſeouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of ſpirit of Amber, and ill contexture, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency
of Diaſcordium, Methridate, and <hi>Venice</hi>-treacle,
they have oftentimes brought Fits inſtead of hindering
them. The decoction of it in a little Ale, or Wine, and
Water, is very uſeful for the Mother when layd, or boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in her caudle to prevent Fevers, and after-pains, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
it will promote ſweat, and diſcuſs wind.</p>
            <p>The Griping of the guts, a diſeaſe no leſs torturing,
than mortal, hath reigned excedingly in <hi>London</hi> for
theſe many years laſt paſt: and notwithſtanding the
endeavours of our learned Doctors, and ingenious Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,
our bills of mortality inform us, that a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of perſons die of it every week, though more in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36231:6"/>
               <hi>July</hi> and <hi>Auguſt</hi> than at other ſeaſons of the year. This
deſeaſe is many times Epidemical in the <hi>Eaſt indies,</hi>
and this Root was ſent me with high commendations of
the ſuccesful uſe of it by the Brammenees in this malady,
and indeed this remedy hath convinced me of the truth
of Doctor <hi>Willis</hi>'s aſſertion, that the nervous part is
principally affected in this diſtemper. By the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
it is diſtinguiſhed into the bloody and unbloody
Flux, in the latter, the matter is ſometimes wateriſh,
and ſometimes mucous, to which may be added that
which is called the dry Gripes. The method I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
in all is alike: only where there is a Fever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned
with, or conſequent to the diſeaſe, I uſe Fountain-water
for the vehicle. When called to a patient, bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
being premiſed, if the age, temper of the patient,
and ſeason of the year require it, I uſe Doctor <hi>Syden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi>
purge. ℞ <hi>Tamarind ℥s ſol. ſennae. mundat.</hi> ℥ii
<hi>Rhei</hi> ℥iſs <hi>coquantur in aq fontanae q.s. Colatur. adde Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae,
ſyrup. roſar. ſolutivi an.</hi> ℥i <hi>M. fiat potio.</hi> At night
when the purge hath done working. ℞ <hi>rad. Rhyſagon.
pulver.</hi> ℥ſs <hi>cum ſyrup. corallior. q. s. fiat bolus hora ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi
ſumendus. Repetatur ſexta qua<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hora.</hi> After it I give a
large draught of the decoction of the ſame Root ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
with ſyrup of Couſlips, and ſometimes fifteen drops
of the <hi>Laudanum Liquidum</hi> deſcribed by Doctor <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denham</hi>
in his excellent book of Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
upon acute Diſtempers.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Syden.</hi> Pag. 255.</note> This Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod
I uſe till its declination to the better, and then the
caſe is ſo eaſy, I need not inculcate any thing further a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
it.</p>
            <p>I uſe this Root as a corrector of the inconveniences
that attend the peruvian bark, and commonly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe
three parts of the bark, and one of the Root <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummuniar.</hi>
And though I have alwaies after generals,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36231:6"/>
as the bitter potions, vomits, or bleeding as the caſe
requireth, proceeded to the uſe of that bark, and that
as frequently, as most have, having had the honour of
many perſons of greateſt eminency in the Univerſity of
<hi>Oxford</hi> one year under my care, together with many
others ill of quartans, yet never can charge, that bark
in any one of my patients with any damage, which was
the reſult of its adminiſtration, being thus corrected.</p>
            <p>A very Eminent <hi>Eaſt-india</hi> Chyrurgion aſſured me,
he had uſed this Root in Melancholy Hypocondriack,
and the Scurvy, with great ſucceſs, of which I can ſpeak
nothing from my own experience. I conceive that a deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
of this Root in Fountain-water, (ſeeing it ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eneth
the animal ſpirits, helpeth ſeparation of what
is inconvenient from them, promoteth Sweat, and a
good circulation of the blood) may be of great uſe
in Fevers, to prevent Deliriums, which hath frequently
a fatal ill event attending it. I look upon it as a thing
very probable, that this Root may be ſerviceable in
many other diſeaſes, and do not doubt, but its own
harmleſs, as well as uſeful nature will excite ingenious
and learned Phyſitians (of which this Nation and City
aboundeth in as many as any in the world,) to make a
higher and greater improvement of it, than I have, or
can. If what I have written may tend to the publick
advantage, I have my end: and could wiſh, that all
Phyſitians would ſo far conſult the good of mankind,
as to communicate what they have ſingular to the world,
that ſo noble a Science might be completed, and health
be the better preſerved and reſtored: for that of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi>
is moſt true in Phyſick: <hi>Multa egerunt, qui ante
nos fuerunt ſed non peregerunt, multum adhuc reſtat,
multumque reſtabit, neque ulli nato poſt mille ſecula
praecidetur occaſio aliquid adhuc adjiciendi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:36231:7"/>
This root may be had at Mr. <hi>Bartletts</hi> Druggiſt in
<hi>Biſhopgate</hi>-Street, or at my Apothecaries on <hi>Rhederiff</hi>
wall. Mr. <hi>Bartlett</hi> hath as I ſuppoſe a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity
for preſent uſe. And if it hath the deſired ſucceſs
(of which do not doubt) I preſume more will be import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in a year or two.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
