<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvhipper vvhipt being a reply upon a scandalous pamphlet, called The whip, abusing that excellent work of Cornelius Burges, Dr in divinity, one of the Assembly of Divines, entituled, The fire of the sanctuary newly discovered / inserti authoris, Qui Mockat, Mockabitur.</title>
            <author>Quarles, Francis, 1592-1644.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56846</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Q121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210654</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20534364</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20534364</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109428</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A56846)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109428)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 230:E13, no 16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvhipper vvhipt being a reply upon a scandalous pamphlet, called The whip, abusing that excellent work of Cornelius Burges, Dr in divinity, one of the Assembly of Divines, entituled, The fire of the sanctuary newly discovered / inserti authoris, Qui Mockat, Mockabitur.</title>
                  <author>Quarles, Francis, 1592-1644.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] imprinted :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLIV. [1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Quarles by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Place of imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Title within double line border.</note>
                  <note>This item can also be found as the third part of Wing Q113 (The profest royalist) which appears at reel 224:4.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665. --  Fire of the sanctuarie newly uncovered.</term>
               <term>Whip.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-05</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109428:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VVHIPPER VVHIPT.</p>
            <p>BEING A REPLY Upon a scandalous Pamphlet, CALLED THE WHIP: Abusing that Excellent Work of CORNELIUS BURGES, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> in DIVINITY, one of the Assembly of <hi>DIVINES,</hi> ENTITULED, <hi>The Fire of the Sanctuary Newly discovered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Incerti Authoris.</p>
            <p>Qui Mockat, Mockabitur.</p>
            <p>Imprinted, M. DC. XLIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:109428:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109428:2"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>SACRED MAJESTY</hi> OF KING CHARLES, My most deare and dread <hi>Soveraigne.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>SIR,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Epleased to cast a gracious eye upon this Book, and at Your leasure (if Your Royall imployments lend you any) to peruse it.</p>
            <p>In Your Three Kingdoms, You have three sorts of people: The first, confident and faithfull; The second, diffident and fearfull; The third, indifferent and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>The first are with You in their <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, Purses,</hi> (or desires) and <hi>good wishes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The second are with You neither in their <hi>Purses,</hi> nor <hi>good wishes,</hi> nor (with their desires) in their <hi>Persons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109428:3"/>
               <hi>The third are with You in their</hi> good wishes, <hi>but neither in their</hi> Persons, <hi>nor</hi> Purses, <hi>nor</hi> Desires.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In this Booke, these three sorts are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented in three</hi> Persons, <hi>and presented to the view of Your Sacred Majesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You shall find them as busie with their</hi> Penns <hi>as the Armyes are with their</hi> Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stols: <hi>How they behave themselves, let the</hi> People <hi>judge: I appeale to</hi> Cesar. <hi>Your Majesties honour, safety and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, The Churches Truth, Unity, and Uniformity, Your Kingdomes Peace, Plenty and Felicity, is the continued ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his</hi> Devotion, <hi>who is</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your Majesties
Most Loyall Subject,
The Replyer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109428:3"/>
            <head>THE WHIPPER VVHIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here came, by chance, to my un-enquiring hand, a <hi>Pamphlet</hi> called <hi>The Whip;</hi> whose Pharisai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>Author</hi> pretended a transcendent <hi>Zeale</hi> to my first eye; but, after a leafes perusall, I found his flame so extreamly hot, that his Religion seemed (for want of due stirring) burnt too; and so much tasted of the <hi>Brasse,</hi> that no Orthodox <hi>palate</hi> could relish it, nor a well-grounded <hi>Conscience</hi> digest it: The name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse Author had an <hi>Vtopian</hi> spirit; and the Government he best affected, was <hi>Anarchie:</hi> He was a <hi>Salamander;</hi> his very dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling was in Fire: His Heart was a sink of <hi>Ignorance;</hi> his Spleen, a spring of <hi>Gall;</hi> a <hi>Shemei,</hi> a <hi>Rabshekah:</hi> his <hi>mouth</hi> ran <hi>bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> and <hi>malice;</hi> and his <hi>Pen</hi> slow'd <hi>venime,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>object</hi> of this fiery Pamphlet, was the orthodox &amp; most excellent work of Doctor <hi>Cornelius Burges,</hi> a man of singular parts; and, at this time; a worthy Member of the <hi>Synod,</hi> or <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly</hi> of Divines; entituled, <hi>The Fire of the Sanctuary newly discovered,</hi> or <hi>A Compleat Tract of Zeale,</hi> and printed by <hi>George Miller</hi> and <hi>Richard Badger, anno</hi> 1625. which, this <hi>Pamphleters</hi> unlearned <hi>Pen</hi> hath so poorely answered, so impiously malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, so maliciously calumniated, that I have thought good to east away some Inke upon him, (not in vindication of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, whose Conscience, enlightned by the Scriptures, needs no <hi>Champion)</hi> but to rectifie the abused <hi>vulgar;</hi> who, by the help of such Pneumaticall Fantasticks, have turnd their <hi>leaden</hi> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109428:4"/>
into <hi>Quick-silverd</hi> Zeale, which hath swallowed up and devoured their duty to their <hi>betters,</hi> their faire demcanour to their <hi>equalls,</hi> and their charity to all <hi>Relations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This unworthy <hi>Pamphleter,</hi> in the Progresse of his more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy work, against this worthy <hi>Member,</hi> uses that method, which <hi>Beelzebub</hi> the prince of Flyes prescribes him; who, like a <hi>Fly,</hi> buzzes through his whole <hi>Larder,</hi> blowing here &amp; there; but leaving such fruitfull corruption, that, in short time, his whole store, nay (if possible) the very <hi>Bread of life,</hi> moulded by the hand of heaven, which hee hath set apart in his margent, would grow unsavoury.</p>
            <p>He begins at the <hi>Dedication</hi> Epistle, repeating the Doctors <hi>words,</hi> then poysoning them with his owne <hi>Calumnies;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, if your Patience (equall Readers) will admit me, by the name of a <hi>Replyer;</hi> you shall have all woven together in one <hi>Loome:</hi> Wherein I purpose not to load your eares with those his frivolous <hi>preambles</hi> and <hi>impertinences,</hi> which would swell this <hi>Pamphlet</hi> beyond your Patience; but, suddenly to rush in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the List.</p>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges <hi>Dedication Title.</hi> To the Right Honourable, WILLIAM, Earle of PEMBROKE, &amp;c.</head>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Calumniator.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Popery, and Superstition at the first dash! Dedication is a meer Popish</hi> Ceremony, <hi>begun by the Antichristian</hi> Hierarchy, <hi>derived from</hi> deo <hi>and</hi> dicatio, <hi>which is a vowing to God: It was first used when</hi> Steeplehouses, <hi>or</hi> Meeting-places <hi>were built, which Papists call</hi> Churches, <hi>dedicating them to</hi> God; <hi>or to those they honoured as much,</hi> Saints, <hi>whereof some of them are now roring in hell; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which pretence, they juggled</hi> holynesse <hi>into them, more then into</hi> Barnes <hi>or</hi> Stables: <hi>Now this Book the Doctor dedicates to the Earle of</hi> Pembroke, <hi>whereby he secretly acknowledges him ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a</hi> God, <hi>or a</hi> Saint; <hi>If a God, he</hi> blasphemes; <hi>If a Saint, he</hi> lyes; <hi>for he was a</hi> Courtier, <hi>and preferd the King before the</hi> Elect;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109428:4"/>
                     <hi>whereas Saints imitate God, and should be no</hi> Respecters of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; <hi>in whose eyes, Kings and Subjects are alike.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Replyer.</head>
                  <p>When <hi>Ignorance</hi> hath shot forth her shady leaves, how quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Impiety</hi> budds! and, then, how suddenly <hi>Rebellion</hi> blossoms! Ignorance first taught thee a false <hi>Etimologie</hi> of a word; then, Impiety suggests a slight estimation of a <hi>Church;</hi> and then, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion insinuates a disreputation of a <hi>King.</hi> Now, one lash more at schoole, would have helpt all this, by curing that Ignorance, and letting you know, that Dedication is derived from <hi>De,</hi> (here taken <hi>perfectivè)</hi> and <hi>dicatio,</hi> (which is an offering or a presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation) which two words, joyned, carry the sense of a full or totall <hi>presentation</hi> of this Book to whom he presented it. Now <hi>Cal.</hi> where's the Blasphemic? or where's the Lye? Let them even both returne to the base mouth from whence they came; And that one lash more which might have cured thy Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in time, might save <hi>Gregory</hi> some labour; and thee, some paines, in an undedicated <hi>Meeting-place.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>D. Burges in the Epistle Dedicatory.</head>
               <p>It <hi>(viz. this Treatise)</hi> speaks of Fire; But such, as was made to warme, and not to burne any thing, unlesse stubble.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I knew what temper your</hi> fire <hi>(your zeale) had, (luke-warme Master Doctor) apt to receive warmth or</hi> flame <hi>according to the times.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Rep.</head>
                  <p>It is the devils custome to leave out halfe the Text: Let mee supply your defect, <hi>Cal.</hi> To warme solid hearts; Not to burne any thing but such <hi>stubble</hi> as you, and then the sentence is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:109428:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges.</head>
               <p>Here is no ground for an Utopian spirit, to mould a new Common-wealth; no warrant for Sedition to touch the Lords Anointed, so much as with her tongue; No occasion administred to <hi>Ishmael</hi> to scoffe at <hi>Isaac;</hi> no Salamanders lodge themselves here.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An</hi> Utopian <hi>spirit is a word of your owne coyning, whereof I confesse my ingenious ignorance. But I perceive, this opinion which you pin upon</hi> Pembrok<hi>'s sleeve, admits rather of an old</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish <hi>Government, then of the moulding of a New, by an holy</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: <hi>It makes such an</hi> Idol <hi>of your King, (whom you falsly tearme the</hi> Lords Anointed) <hi>that it brands that hand with the aspersion of</hi> Sedition; <hi>and that tongue, with the guilt of</hi> Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, <hi>that touches him; whereas Kings are but</hi> men, <hi>and wicked Kings but</hi> Beasts, <hi>in Gods eye, and the</hi> righteous <hi>have Gods power, and may touch them; nay, and</hi> scourge <hi>them too; But, I feare, your Zeal burnes now onely to light your Doctorship to a</hi> Deanery: <hi>What you meane by</hi> Salamanders, <hi>I know not.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>You professe <hi>Ignorance, Cal.</hi> in the beginning and ending of your learned speech, and discover <hi>Treason</hi> in the whole Body: The first Ignorance you professe, is, of an <hi>Vtopian spirit,</hi> wherein I thus informe you: It is a <hi>fanaticall</hi> spirit, even your owne spirit, by which you pray <hi>Nonsense</hi> by the houre, preach <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> by the halfe day, and ejaculate <hi>blasphemies</hi> every minute. Your last ignorance is, of the <hi>Salamanders;</hi> wherein I thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct you. They are the <hi>fierie spirits</hi> that dwell within your flaming bosomes, by which ye <hi>murther,</hi> under the pretence of piety; <hi>rob</hi> by way of Religion; and fling <hi>dirt</hi> in the face of Majesty by colour of zeale: No wonder, <hi>Cal.</hi> those spirits are unknowne to you, when ye know not <hi>of what spirit</hi> ye are: As for the body of your speech, we leave it to the judgement of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:109428:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges.</head>
               <p>But here's a flame that will lick up all angry wasps, and inflamed tongues that presumptuously and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare speak evill of dignities, and of things they understand not, railing on all not so free as themselves to foame at the mouth, and to cast their froth on all that are neare, without difference.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This your</hi> Flame, <hi>Courtly Master Doctor, lights us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that your saintly Patrone had then some remarkable</hi> Living <hi>in his Gift; or power, to make you one of the Kings</hi> Chaplains, in ordinary; <hi>strengthned, with the hopes whereof, you thus magnisie dignities, that is,</hi> Kingship, Lordship, <hi>and</hi> Bishopship: <hi>And I am verily perswaded, if</hi> Amaleck <hi>or</hi> Esau, <hi>(whom God cursed) were in being, your linsy-</hi>woolsy <hi>Zeale would endeavour to vindicate them from that</hi> Curse; <hi>Or if</hi> Caiphas, <hi>the High Priest, were placed in office here, you have a</hi> Pensill <hi>to paynt his</hi> Wall <hi>white enough, for</hi> Paul <hi>to curse.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cal.</hi> I feare you are one of those angry <hi>wasps</hi> the Doctor's Zeallicks up, and his Pen (now above 19 yeares old) discoverd your <hi>nest,</hi> being a <hi>faction</hi> now in power, and prophesied of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 1500 yeares since; whose mal<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pert, sawcy, and slovenly <hi>Tenets</hi> were well known to him, to be the <hi>Ivie</hi> of the true Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox and <hi>Primitive</hi> Religion, whose ambitious and fiery spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, (hating all Government both in Church and State, casting their foame and froth in the face of <hi>Majesty</hi> and <hi>Hierarchie,</hi> without respect of honour or place) his conscience (enlightned and instructed by the holy Scriptures) hated with a perfect ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and used his best meanes to suppresse and quench.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges, in his Preface.</head>
               <p>My sharpnesse against some Democraticall Anti-Ceremonians
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109428:6"/>
is not meant to weak Consciences, joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with pious, sober, and peaceable courses.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marke, whilst this sharp Doctor would boast of a vertue called</hi> Moderation, <hi>he turnes Advocate to that detestable sinne of</hi> Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmnesse: <hi>As if he should have said,</hi> My sharpnesse against the enemies of Popery, extends not to them, that are not too active and zealous of Gods glory. <hi>Doctor, this Fire will hardly make your</hi> Pot <hi>boile.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Rep.</head>
                  <p>Mark how this bitter Calumniator acts his owne part to the life; at one breath, both wresting the <hi>words,</hi> and wronging the <hi>person:</hi> And how it offends him, (whose glory is to set weak Consciences upon the <hi>Rack)</hi> to see another, fearfull of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a <hi>weake</hi> Conscience: <hi>Cal.</hi> This Zeale will make your pot boyle into the <hi>Fire.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges.</head>
               <p>But I speak to such as keep a frantick coyle about Ceremonies, and think they never take their levell right, but when, with every bolt they shoot, they strike a Bishops Cap sheire off his head, and yet are more fantasticall, ignorant, proud, self-will'd, negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and deceitfull in their particular Callings then many whom they despise and condemne to Hell for carnall men, forsooth, as any observing eye may easily discerne.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So, Master Doctor; I now call both the</hi> Parliament, <hi>and the whole</hi> Assembly <hi>of Divines to witnesse, you are either a</hi> Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>or a</hi> Turnecoate: <hi>When you reade this clause, remember your own late</hi> Votes, <hi>and tell me, what</hi> Mettle <hi>your Conscience is made of. Tell me now, in sadnes, Doctor, Are they ignorant, proud, self-willd, negligent, and deceitfull in their Callings, that inveigh
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109428:6"/>
against</hi> Ceremonies, <hi>forsooth? that endeavour to strike off a</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops <hi>Cap, forsooth? Once again, I say, remember your own</hi> Votes <hi>and blush: Nay, if, with the</hi> Satyre, <hi>you can blow hot and cold with one Mouth, you are no</hi> Divine <hi>for me, forsooth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>You triumph <hi>Cal.</hi> too much before the victory, and crow too considently upon your owne <hi>Dunghill:</hi> I justifie the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor in what I know: you condemne him, in what you know not: What his <hi>Votes</hi> were, or how, or when made, it matters not to me, but his opinion (declared to all the world) proclaims him no lesse then <hi>Orthodox:</hi> I look upon him as a <hi>Divine,</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely; not as an <hi>Assembly-man,</hi> relatively: The Satyres <hi>hot</hi> breath warmed his fingers, which else had been too cold: The Satyres <hi>cold</hi> breath coold his Breth which else had burnt his lips: The first was <hi>Breath;</hi> The last, but <hi>Winde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges.</head>
               <p>Touching the Carriage of Zeale towards Princes, my CONSCIENCE witnesseth with me, in the sight of God, that I have spoken nothing, but what in my judgement is the Truth, without sinister or base intents.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Clause stands like a</hi> Pander <hi>to keep the doore, till you have committed your spirituall</hi> Fornication <hi>within; and to anticipate your beleeving Reader, whilst you basely flatter Princes; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, you have engaged your Conscience, and attested God concerning that your</hi> opinion, <hi>we shall hereafter understand; which in his due place, you shall not faile to heare of.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>How like a snarling <hi>Cur</hi> you gurne before yee bite: <hi>Cal.</hi> as you have acted your first part, in shewing your <hi>teeth;</hi> so, anon, we shall expect your second part, in clapping your <hi>tayle</hi> betwixt your legs, and shamefully <hi>running</hi> away.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:109428:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nor doe I touch on that, presuming to teach my Betters (but rather as men use to do, when they go for Orders, or a Benefice) to give accompt.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>Doctor, It is the property of Dogs to baule at <hi>Beggers,</hi> or Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, who come empty Isanded; but to fawne upon their <hi>Feeders,</hi> and wag their flattering tayles at those, from whose well furnisht <hi>Trenchers</hi> they expect some scraps: No, you presume not to teach your Betters; Tell me, Doctor, who sent you? Whose <hi>Embassadour</hi> are you? Come you in your own name? It seemes you do: He, in whose Name you should come, knowes no <hi>betters:</hi> The Truth is, <hi>Christ</hi> sext you; but <hi>Antichrist</hi> (from whose <hi>surrogates</hi> you had your Orders) signed your <hi>Commission:</hi> Christ sent you to <hi>Preach,</hi> and Antichrist bad you take a <hi>Benifice</hi> by the way; which (speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your Betters) you here craftily insinuate in your <hi>Simile:</hi> Iesuites beg not, but point yee where the <hi>Box</hi> stands.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your sawcy Impudence,</hi> Cal. <hi>Votes</hi> Modesty <hi>a vice, and</hi> rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se, <hi>Zeale: Our blessed Saviour sayes,</hi> Give unto <hi>Cesar</hi> those things that belong unto <hi>Cesar; and Saint</hi> Paul, Honour to whom Honour belongs, <hi>commanding</hi> all things to be done decently and in order: <hi>Which is too neate a Doctrine for your nasty spirits: God, who is no Respecter of persons inmatter of</hi> Iustice, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands you not, to disrespect persons, by way of</hi> manners: <hi>Diet for Princes and Pesants require</hi> severall <hi>dressings: When Saint</hi> Paul <hi>said to that heathen King</hi> Agrippa, Beleevest thou the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets? I know thou beleevest; <hi>have not you blasphemy enough to traduce the Apostle of a</hi> courtly <hi>lye? I feare, your</hi> Rabseka-spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>would have lent him courser</hi> language. <hi>And as for the</hi> Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice <hi>you say the Doctor insinuates in his</hi> Simile, <hi>you might have charitably translated it into two or three</hi> Sequestrations, <hi>and then it had been tolerable.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:109428:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>And yet I would teach withall: I meane, the boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous Multitude; who, ever prefer the rough Channel before the temperate shore, and think no man prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches well in a Prince his Court, but he that is so fierie and rude (plaine as they call it) as with his Thunder shakes the very house: And if he cast no squibs in a Princes face, or preach not like a Privy Councellor, they say he hath no holy Fire in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>How this temporizing Doctor still courts <hi>Preferment!</hi> In his last Clause, he Craftily insinuates for a <hi>Benefice;</hi> and in this, as grosly for a Court <hi>Chaplainship,</hi> wherein, he openly discovers how his silken Conscience stands qualified for such imployment, being more ready to sowe <hi>Pillows</hi> under Princes Elbowes, then denounce <hi>Judgments</hi> against their sins; declaring himself a profest enemy against the, boysterous <hi>multitude,</hi> who love the rough <hi>Channell;</hi> And who are they? Even those <hi>Nathanian</hi> spirits that dare tell the King, <hi>Thou art the Man;</hi> and professing himself a Friend to such as love the temperate <hi>shore;</hi> And who are they? Even such as flatter Princes into the <hi>flames</hi> of hell. A fit Doctor to consult and vote in the <hi>Assembly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is one part of the devils office,</hi> Cal. <hi>to accuse man toman, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> Office, I fear, you rather execute under him, as his</hi> Child, <hi>then u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surp from him, as a</hi> Stranger: <hi>Gods servants must wear Gods</hi> live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Meeknes; They must reprove with wisdom, sobriety, &amp; mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; especially, the</hi> sacred <hi>persons of Kings: God was more in the</hi> still voyce <hi>then in the</hi> thunder: <hi>Squibs, taunts, and Raylings are none of Gods</hi> wayes; <hi>but love, temperance, and moderation: If your house have a</hi> slaw, <hi>or an unsound</hi> pillour, <hi>will you, straight fire it; and, not rather prop it, and, by degrees, strengthen it, for after service? Gods fire, (that appeared in the</hi> bush) gave
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109428:8"/>
light; but, burnt not; But your Zeales have no patience, demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing and consuming, even from the <hi>Cedar</hi> that growes in Lebanon to the <hi>Hysop</hi> that is upon the wall: If such fire become the Assembly, then take out <hi>Burges,</hi> and put in <hi>Peters.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges.</head>
               <p>If men dislike a Book in this Age, their Censure is usually, It hath no salt in it: A discourse of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture should have salt good store, for all sacrifices must be seasoned with salt; So is this, but intended to sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son onely, not to fret any, unlesse by accident.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But if salt hath lost it's</hi> favour, <hi>wherewith shall it be seasoned? So hath yours, Doctor; Your</hi> Sacrifice <hi>then will quickly stinck: You are a very bad Phisition for the soul; Your</hi> kichen <hi>Phisick (for you have no other) were good to keepe a healthfull soul in a good state; But when</hi> feavors <hi>of lust,</hi> dropsies of <hi>drunkennesse,</hi> plurisies <hi>of Blood,</hi> faint fits <hi>of Lukewarmnesse, &amp;c. accost the soul, your seasoned</hi> Brothes <hi>will faile: sometimes the disease will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire vomits, purges, phlebotomy, cautherizing, scarifying, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, &amp;c. But, I feare, your end is rather to cure your own</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, <hi>then your patients</hi> distempers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>I fear, <hi>Cal.</hi> some of the Doctors <hi>salt</hi> hath fretted your chapt fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; which, perchance, you strive to wash out with your own <hi>vineger,</hi> which so much troubles you: you name some diseases in others, but forget your own, both <hi>acute</hi> and <hi>chronicall,</hi> the <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaca passio,</hi> the tumour of the spleene, the petulancy of the tongue, the <hi>Cold Fits</hi> of uncharitablenesse: The first, second, and fourth of these are inward and habituall; and, I feare, incureable; but for the third, the <hi>Beadel</hi> of Bridewell will be your best Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitian.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:109428:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges.</head>
               <p>Thus have you my Apology (if it be one) as a smal skreen to hold between you and the fire, if you think it be too big, or too neare, and that it would heate you too much.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doctor, Your</hi> Apology <hi>is as needlesse as your</hi> work: <hi>Your Fire (whereby (I take it) you meane your Zeale</hi> newly discovered) <hi>is but an</hi> Ignis lambens, <hi>or as rotten wood, shining in the dark; Or if it be a true Fire, it is but of</hi> Juniper, <hi>which rather serves to</hi> perfume <hi>a princes chamber, then to</hi> warme <hi>a Christians heart; and so dul, that it requires, rather, a paire of</hi> Bellowes, <hi>then a</hi> Sk<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eene.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>I hope, <hi>Cal.</hi> It is not such a fire as yours, called <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> which entices poor soules, (wandering in the dark,) to breake their necks; But (as you have excellently, (although against your will) tearmed it) a fire of <hi>Iuniper;</hi> No perfume, sweeter; no Coales, hotter; This Juniper fire sends up sweet perfumes of <hi>Comfort</hi> to the broken heart, and contrite spirit; but threatens the fiercest of Gods <hi>Iudgements</hi> to the Rebellious and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent soule.</p>
                  <p>Here, Reader, be pleased to pause a while, and to understand, our <hi>Calumniator</hi> hath done with the Doctors <hi>Preface,</hi> intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now to set upon the body of the <hi>work</hi> it self; wherein, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes not his <hi>Task</hi> progressively, but selectively; whether, he drives at one subject, collecting what he findes scattered through the whole book; or whether his wit can onely daunce after a <hi>Pipe</hi> of that nature, I cannot resolve you; You have it as I found it: This I perceive, by his stragling <hi>Method,</hi> that it was <hi>leape yeare</hi> in his Braynes, as well as in his Kalender; And so, we begin againe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:109428:9"/>
The Fire of the Sanctuary uncoverd.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 3. pag. 39. lin. 13.</head>
               <p>It had not been lawfull for <hi>Elijah</hi> to put those Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters to the sword, if he had not been able to plead speciall Commission from God, as he did.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take heed Doctor, you run not your selfe out of the</hi> Assembly <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> Ely house: <hi>What speciall Commission had our</hi> Parliament <hi>to do the like? Yet how many thousand more have perisht by the sword, at their Command? Are not they wise, and truly religious, and holy</hi> Merchants <hi>for Gods Glory, and blessed Agents for our Kingdomes</hi> Reformation? <hi>And would they do such an act, and stand guilty of such a</hi> Fratricide, <hi>so horrible a slaughter, had they not a</hi> Warrant <hi>for it? Come, Doctor, It is wisdome to retract and change a mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opinion: It is a good</hi> bargaine, <hi>to change for the better, and get</hi> 400. l. per. annum. <hi>to boot, and God knowes what be sides.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>You ride, <hi>Cal.</hi> upon the surer horse, as the case stands now: Take heed of the Kings <hi>plunderers.</hi> The Parliaments Authority is <hi>inscrutable,</hi> and too great a <hi>mistery</hi> for a private mans Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; But if the Doctors opinion be firmly grounded on the word of God, my <hi>Confidence</hi> of his Piety is such, that neither feare of <hi>Prisons,</hi> nor hope of <hi>Fortunes,</hi> are able to divert, or to corrupt him: But, <hi>Cal.</hi> it had been better worth your paines, to have refuted his opinion, by the strength of holy Scripture, then pinned your <hi>implicite</hi> faith upon the Authority of men, though never so learned or religious, being the self same <hi>Error,</hi> we cry down, in Popery.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 3. pag. 40. line 21.</head>
               <p>He that being under authority will rather resist then suffer, makes the Cause suffer by his resistance, and so
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109428:9"/>
in stead of standing zealously for it, he doth in effect raise forces against it.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A high and desperate</hi> Malignancy! <hi>A Doctrine most dangerous and damnable! not onely contrary to the</hi> practice <hi>of all Churches, that labour for a</hi> Reformation, <hi>but directly opposite to an</hi> Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance <hi>of Parliament also. If this Doctrine be permitted from the Pen of an Assembly man, without</hi> punishment <hi>or publique</hi> Retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, <hi>our Cause wil carry warme</hi> Credit; <hi>and his bosome a strange</hi> Conscience: <hi>If this</hi> Clause <hi>be sound, we are at a weekly cost to much purpose; If unsound, our Assembly hath a sound</hi> Member.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>No question, <hi>Cal.</hi> that Malignant <hi>Doctrine</hi> hath been the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and received <hi>Tenet</hi> of former dayes; neither do I know any Religion so opposite to it as the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which holds it not venial, but meritorious, not onely to resist but also to depose the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Supreme Magistrate; But we are better taught by Scripture, &amp; not alone commanded, but also find it frequently exemplifyed unto us by holy men, to give all <hi>passive</hi> obedience to the power of our Princes, whether good or bad; without which Gods true Religion, would, surely, want that honorable Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of holy <hi>Martirdome,</hi> which formerly it had; But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the yeare 1642. brought new inspirations and revelations with it, or whether the thousand six hundred and forty one yeares before it, slept in the darknes of this point, deluded by false <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slations,</hi> the Doctor (if you repaire to him) no question, can ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you a satisfactory accompt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 3. pag. 41. line 20.</head>
               <p>Zeale may stand with suffering and fleeing, but not with Resistance, which is <hi>Flat</hi> REBELLION; And no good <hi>Cause</hi> calls <hi>Rebellion</hi> to aid.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:109428:10"/>
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here's more Water from the same</hi> Ditch, <hi>but a little more stincking, through the addition of this odious word</hi> REBELLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON: <hi>What</hi> Malignant <hi>Devil haunted this Doctors Pen? Nay, in those <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alme dayes, when that base tearme</hi> (REBELLION) <hi>was hardly understood, but in our Prayers</hi> Confessive; <hi>Nay, scarce then; A</hi> word, <hi>more fit for those that can submit to the inordinate power of a Prince, and crush Religion in a Common-wealth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>How now, <hi>Cal.</hi> Does your shoe pinch you there? Dare you resist who have liberty to <hi>flee?</hi> Can you resist, and not <hi>rebell?</hi> Can you <hi>do</hi> the Act with a good Conscience, &amp; not <hi>heare</hi> of the Action without impatience? How willingly can a dog <hi>foule</hi> the roome, and how loath to have his nose <hi>rubbed</hi> in it? Did not I tell you, in the <hi>Preface,</hi> (where you shewed your teeth) that you would clap your tayle between your legs anon, and <hi>run</hi> away? He whose enlightned judgment there called his God to witnesse, hath condemned your <hi>Cause,</hi> styled you by the Name of <hi>Rebell,</hi> and branded your actions with the style of flat REBELLION: His Conscience, then, had neither Feare to <hi>pinch</hi> it; nor Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to <hi>enlarge</hi> it; nor could his Merits aime at any <hi>By-respects</hi> for his maintayning of so known a <hi>truth,</hi> so doubly fortified both by the <hi>law</hi> of God and Nature: REBELLION is a <hi>Trade</hi> the Devil is free of: It is both <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Devil</hi> too: No won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>Cal.</hi> to see you run so fast; You know who drives you: Nay, he hath driven you so far beyond your senses, that you hold him onely <hi>loyal,</hi> that rebells; and him <hi>rebellious,</hi> onely, that sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>D. <hi>Burges cap.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 45. <hi>lin.</hi> 20.</head>
               <p>I think no wise man doubts, that even in the purer times of the old Church in <hi>Israel,</hi> corruptions grew in Ceremonies as well as in the substance of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and yet pry into the Scriptures never so care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, we shall not finde any of the most Zealous
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109428:10"/>
Saints fall on fire for Ceremonies, which is worth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A true</hi> Chip <hi>of the old block</hi> Canterbury, <hi>who after he had fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarized the name of the Altar, in the common care, (not daring to bring in</hi> Transubstantiation, <hi>with a full Tide) innocently left out those words in his</hi> Service book, <hi>which onely made the difference betwixt a Sacrifice, and the</hi> Sacrament; <hi>so that, but one step more, and the</hi> work <hi>had been fully done. So this our Doctor (not daring to urge</hi> Ceremonies <hi>too loud, lest the Godly should heare him) sets the peaceable</hi> Custome <hi>of the former Saints betwixt him and the danger of all good mens</hi> Censure. <hi>He made the example of the Saints the</hi> wall <hi>by which his</hi> creeping <hi>Popery might hold, for feare of falling; who, (had not this blessed</hi> Parliament <hi>dropt down from heaven, to crush these Superstitions in their</hi> Rise) <hi>had been, by this, as perfect a</hi> Proficient <hi>as the worst; had had his</hi> high <hi>tricks, his</hi> low <hi>tricks, and perchance, his Merry tricks too, as well as his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>How you wonder at a <hi>sparke</hi> of fire, <hi>Cal.</hi> when just now your eyes dazled at the <hi>flame</hi> I Did not the Doctor, in his <hi>Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> as good as confesse himself an enemy to <hi>Anticeremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans?</hi> did not your self taxe him of rank <hi>Popery?</hi> and yet, what a busines now, you make of his <hi>creeping</hi> Ceremonies? The lyar, <hi>Cal.</hi> and the malitious, sometimes, are alike forgetfull; But, to the purpose; If you loved the <hi>substance</hi> of Religion more, you would have more lamented that sea of Christian <hi>blood,</hi> that hath been shed about these <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> then I find you do: We contend, so much, about the shell, that, I feare, we have lost the <hi>Kirnell:</hi> But this know, <hi>Cal.</hi> so long as you traduce your <hi>brother,</hi> and thus abuse your spirituall <hi>father,</hi> neither the love of God, nor the God of love abides in you.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>D. <hi>Burges cap.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 66. <hi>line</hi> 14.</head>
               <p>Again, let such as be Zealous sticklers for Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craticall, or Aristocraticall discipline, consider how ill
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109428:11"/>
the Church can be governed by one policy, and the Common-wealth by another.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Our Doctor is growne a</hi> Machiavilian; <hi>and forgets that Piety is the best</hi> Policy; <hi>We, living under a</hi> Monarchicall <hi>Governement in the common-wealth, how he pleads for a</hi> Hierarchicall <hi>governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Church? consequently, dissallowing</hi> Democraticall <hi>or</hi> Aristocraticall <hi>Discipline, which our gratious</hi> Parliament <hi>is now setting up; But't is no wonder to heare him, that hath so Zealously pleaded for the</hi> Robes <hi>and vanities of the whore to apologize for her</hi> governement; <hi>and, by consequent, for the</hi> whore <hi>her self also!</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>When Ignorance and Folly meet, how malice domineeres? How this government, by Bishops, erected in the Apostles dayes approved by <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Disciple, and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> the Disciple of <hi>Polycarpus, Ignatius,</hi> and all those first <hi>Planters</hi> of the Gospell; submitted unto by the whole <hi>Primitive</hi> Church; confirmed by <hi>Lucius,</hi> the first Christian King in this Island; afterwards, established by so many <hi>Acts</hi> of Parliament, (as yet unrepealed,) and freely and personally exercized by so many godly and learned <hi>Martyrs;</hi> how this Government sticks in ignorant <hi>Cal's</hi> stomack? whose forgetfull malice, would make the Doctor an enemy to the proceedings and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes of <hi>Parliament,</hi> whose writings were printed so many yeares before this <hi>Parliament</hi> was dream'd of: As for his plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the <hi>whore,</hi> this know; had the popish <hi>Strumpet</hi> found no better friends then he, she had wanted that retrograde Mercy of a <hi>Third part,</hi> when the Protestant Matrone must be content but with a <hi>Fift.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 3. pag. 68. line 20.</head>
               <p>It was long since the Zealous Complaint of a Holy Man, that men could no sooner get up their names in the world, and be able readily and confidently to muster up a few places of Scripture, nothing to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109428:11"/>
purpose, but they thought themselves sufficient to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter <hi>Moses</hi> himself, setting upon him as furiously as <hi>Dathan</hi> or <hi>Abiram</hi> ever did: Happy were this age, had it none of that Temper.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But has that holy man no name, Doctor? or, was it your own self? The man we know not, but his Intentions are apparent; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to conclude none able for the Ministry, but such as have first their</hi> Ordination <hi>from your popish Bishops, from whose imposition of hands, they presently receive the</hi> spirit; <hi>till then, being neither called nor qualified: brave Iuggling! when the laying on of</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaicall <hi>hands must enable a drunkard, or a whore-master, or worse, to preach the sacred</hi> Word, <hi>and administer the holy</hi> Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>who now, by the virtue of this</hi> Hocas pocas, <hi>hath a capacity to forgive sins, being (though formerly very ignorant) now gift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more or lesse, according to the</hi> gift <hi>he brings; where they that are called by the secret</hi> working <hi>of Gods spirit, inwardly, enlightned by knowledge, and especiall</hi> Revelation, <hi>and able for Interpretation (though never gifted with tongues) were not permitted to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize their ministeriall</hi> Function: <hi>but imprisoned, persecuted, and pilloryed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>True, <hi>Cal.</hi> you hit the intention right; and have so plainly discovered yours too, that every fool may reade it; and (being converted by you) approve it, too: wherein, you intimate, how needlesse, Ordination and Learning are, to qualify a <hi>Minister;</hi> and, that any, who finds himself gifted, may execute the <hi>Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> office. Tel me, <hi>Cal.</hi> may any, that hath skill to make a shoe, a hat, or a suite, professe the <hi>Trade,</hi> till he be made free? Your <hi>Halls</hi> say, no: Why? he hath skill in the <hi>Mistery,</hi> and his <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiship</hi> is served! what hinders him, he cannot practice? His Master must make him free, and he must performe the City <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony.</hi> And shall the calling of a Minister be undertaken by every unexamined <hi>tagrag?</hi> Shall every <hi>Coblor, Feltmaker,</hi> or <hi>Taylour</hi> intrude into that honorable calling, and be judges of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109428:12"/>
their own sufficiency? and leave their lawfull <hi>Trades</hi> for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable <hi>Professions,</hi> according to their own humerous <hi>Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies?</hi> Our bodyes, <hi>Cal.</hi> expect the help of the most <hi>rationall</hi> and authoriz'd Phisitians; but our soules can be content with every <hi>Emprick,</hi> and accept of every Theologicall <hi>Mountibank:</hi> As for our Bishops you tearme <hi>Popish,</hi> How many of them have lately forsaken (for their Conscience sake) their <hi>lively-hoods,</hi> and fled from the Popish <hi>faction</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> hither, where, instead of charitable reliefe, they are thrasht and tribulated, with another Flayle?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 3. page 70. line 11.</head>
               <p>The next way we can possibly take to the best Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation is by prayers and teares.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I see, the Doctor loves to sleep in a whole skin, and far enough off from</hi> Resisting to blood: <hi>Tis true, Prayers and Teares, are said to be the</hi> weapons of the Church; <hi>And happy it were if such weapons could prevaile: But where</hi> Entreaty <hi>findes defect,</hi> Compulsion <hi>must make supply; If Prayers cannot,</hi> Swords <hi>may: If Teares may not,</hi> Blood <hi>must.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>Let them <hi>perish</hi> by the sword, that take up the sword; And let them that <hi>thirst</hi> for blood, guzzle <hi>blood</hi> untill they burst: <hi>David,</hi> that fought <hi>Gods Battailes,</hi> commanded by Gods own mouth; nay <hi>a man after Gods own heart;</hi> yet his hand (that was in blood,) must not build the <hi>Temple;</hi> And shal we expect, by blood, a <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> of the Temple? The stroake of a <hi>Poleaxe</hi> is not accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, where the noyse of a <hi>Hammer</hi> was not warrantable.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 4. page 79. line 4.</head>
               <p>When many people are demanded their Reasons of divers opinions, which they stoutly stand unto, is not their answer thus? Because the contrary is against the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109428:12"/>
word: Being pressed to shew wherein, they reply, We are but ignorant People; we cannot dispute with you, but so we are taught by Reverend men, if you talk with them they will be able to satisfie you to the full.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Do, Doctor, offend those</hi> little ones, <hi>and despise Gods</hi> Blossomes: <hi>All have not learning to maintaine their Opinions, by</hi> Argument, <hi>and</hi> Sophistry. The battail is not alwayes to the strong, nor the Race to the swift: <hi>The perswasion of a Conscience is an able proofe; and the opinion of holy men a strong Refuge: Better to stand cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiously (though ignorant) in a</hi> Good Cause, <hi>(as some do) then to maintaine Error (as you do) with learned</hi> Impiety.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>Hence it is <hi>Cal.</hi> your <hi>Cause</hi> is stronglyer defended by the <hi>Sword,</hi> then by the <hi>Pen,</hi> whose Ignorant <hi>Patrons,</hi> can better thrash then plead: Tis confest, the perswasion of a wel-grounded <hi>Conscience</hi> is a good proof to the party so perswaded; but here it sticks, not able to <hi>convert</hi> a brother. Review those world of <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> of both sides published, and weigh them; In those of the <hi>one</hi> side, you shall have the full consent and <hi>Harmony</hi> of Scriptures; strict <hi>precepts,</hi> commanding; holy <hi>Examples,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming; and all, undenyable prest, and learnedly urged home to every <hi>Conscience</hi> that is not seired; On those, of the <hi>other side,</hi> what <hi>Wresting</hi> of Scriptures? What <hi>allegorizing</hi> of plaine texts? What shuffling? What faultring? What <hi>obscurity</hi> of stile? What Rhethoricall <hi>pretermissions</hi> of things materiall? What pasquills? What invectives? What raylings? What bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternesse? Enough to discover a <hi>Bad Cause,</hi> and to disparage a <hi>Good:</hi> But, <hi>Cal.</hi> your unmaintain'd <hi>Opinions</hi> are pinned upon the <hi>Authority</hi> of men: Say, where's the <hi>Papist,</hi> now? Is not <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite</hi> Beliefe one of our greatest Quarrells with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> even unto this day? Did not our Saviour himself con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the old Pharisees, for their <hi>Traditions?</hi> If this be not <hi>blind</hi> Zeale, that Scripture is Apochrypha, which said, <hi>Without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109428:13"/>
the mind is not good. Pro.</hi> 19. 2. No, <hi>Cal.</hi> such Zeale is the mother of all <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Heresies,</hi> being guided by the opinion, we conceive, of those <hi>men,</hi> who are subject to <hi>Error,</hi> because but men: I advise such to keep their eares <hi>open;</hi> and their mouthes, <hi>shut.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 4. page 82. line 12.</head>
               <p>I wish it were no breach of Charity, to compare the stirrs of our Brownists, Anabaptists, and Familists, and all the Rabble of such Schismaticall sectaries (who may truly be tearm'd Puritanes) with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerate action of those rude Ephesians, <hi>(Acts</hi> 19. 32.) If there be any difference, it is onely in this, that these mad <hi>Martin marre prelates</hi> professe in their words, that they knew God; but in their works, they deny him.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All that hate Popery and Popish</hi> Prelates, <hi>are, in our Zealous Doctors esteeme,</hi> Brownists, <hi>Anabaptists, and schimaticall</hi> Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>which he brands with that (now almost forgotten) stile of</hi> Puritanes; <hi>all, far honestci men then himself; whom (compare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to those rude Ephesians) he makes (according to the Kings unworthy</hi> Declarations) <hi>the Authors of all these</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, <hi>calling that worthy man</hi> Martin marre-prelate, <hi>mad, for touching the apple of his eye, the idolatrized</hi> Hierarchy. <hi>A Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant of the right stamp, and coyned at the Kings own Royall</hi> Mint?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>Once again, good <hi>Cal.</hi> (if it will not too much prejudice the progresse of your <hi>wit)</hi> correct the frailty of your <hi>Memory;</hi> and remember, the doctors book, which you so soundly answer, was Printed in the yeare 1625. which was a little before this unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py <hi>Commotion;</hi> which, you say, he fathers upon the Brownists and Anabaptists, and schismaticall sectaries, according to His Majesties <hi>Declaration:</hi> Truly, <hi>Cal.</hi> your malice may rather brand him for a <hi>witch,</hi> then a Malignant; but your discretion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109428:13"/>
may hold him rather for a <hi>Prophet,</hi> then either; that, so long since, foresaw this: Indeed, in that poynt, he jumps word for word with His Majesties <hi>Declaration:</hi> and, if the King speake <hi>true,</hi> the Doctor speakes not <hi>falsely:</hi> For what His Majesty writes, now, by way of <hi>history,</hi> our Doctor delivered then, by way of <hi>Prophesie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 4. pag. 137. line 20.</head>
               <p>Such as make a great blaze when prosperity, credit, Peace and Preferment are Bellowes to blow it; but are so carried about as hay in a whirlwind with the blast of Time, that they wil be ready to fire that which before they maintained, if the wind turned never so little about, &amp; through fears or hopes, wil be of any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and temper, that the strongest faction embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, resolving to go no further then a faire wind and weather, and a calme tide will carry them; And if any storme arise, presently to make to the shore, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent perill of life and goods; Such Zealots I say as these never had any Coale from the Altar, to kindle their Sacrifices; they never knew what it is to aime at the Glory of God.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your Doctrine is good, had it been as well followed; Say Doctor, who was he, that a little before this Parliament (when our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the</hi> Scots <hi>made their first approach into this kingdom, and whom a little after, the King Injuriously Proclaimed</hi> Rebels) <hi>in his Sermon at</hi> Magnes <hi>Church by London-bridge, flew in their faces, vilified them with opprobrious tearms, stiled their designe,</hi> Rebellion, <hi>proclaimed them</hi> Robbers, Ravishers, Traitors, <hi>and the</hi> disturbers <hi>of the Churches Peace, called their Doctrines</hi> schismati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, new fangled, <hi>and</hi> seditious, <hi>brought in to refine us, (with this addition)</hi> God will not be beholding to the Divel to sweep His Church; <hi>And not above a month after, at the beginning of thu Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in another Sermon at the same place, out of this</hi> Text Act.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109428:14"/>
17. 30. (And the times of this Ignorance God winked at, but now commaneth all menevery where to repent) <hi>took an occasion to eate his words,</hi> &amp; contradict <hi>every thing he formerly delivered? Who was the cowardly cur then? according to your own phrase</hi> pag. 138. line 3. <hi>Who is the</hi> Sheeps-heads <hi>now according to your own tearme?</hi> pag. 139. line 23. <hi>Who turned his</hi> Fiddle <hi>to the Base of the</hi> times? pag. 147. line 1. <hi>Who is guilty of</hi> Parasiticall basenes? pag. 147. line 18. <hi>Who is the</hi> Whiteliverd Christian to be turned out <hi>among</hi> dogs and hell-hounds? pag. 182. line 11. <hi>Doctor, now you have told us</hi> what he is, <hi>the whole parish of</hi> Magnes <hi>can tell you</hi> who it is. <hi>Who was it that was so active for the oath</hi> Ex Officio, <hi>so eager for the two shillings nine pence so contentious with his parishioners? The Clergy can witnesse the first, the City can te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stisie the second, Magnes can attest the last: Yet all this was done by way of zeale.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cal.</hi> First your tongue is no slander, Secondly your profession gives you a <hi>Patent</hi> under the broad <hi>Seale to lie:</hi> but to spoyle your jest, if any such man was, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>? True, Saint <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> was the Doctors Church at that time, and if any slipt into, and abused his pulpit, and himself, no question but the Doctor is as much <hi>troubled</hi> for it as you are <hi>pleased</hi> with it: But who ever you taxe (if you play not the Poet) he may, in spite of your bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternesse, justify his seeming <hi>Contradiction,</hi> and <hi>eate</hi> his words as harmelesly as a <hi>Potato pie</hi> in Lent: Whether the Seots were <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> or no, was no matter of <hi>Faith,</hi> but <hi>Opinion;</hi> The object of opinion is <hi>Reason,</hi> and it alters with <hi>Reason;</hi> When His Majesty proclaimed them <hi>Rebels,</hi> (being a matter of fact and <hi>state,)</hi> was it not reason for him to own it? But being pleased, by <hi>pardon</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiously to take off that odious <hi>imputation,</hi> it had been neither reason, manners, nor safety not to approve of it. When a ship hath made a voyage with <hi>one winde</hi> into New-England, will you blame it for returning back with a <hi>quite contrary?</hi> No wise man <hi>Cal.</hi> will do it, unlesse you, or such as you were in it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:109428:14"/>
               <head>D. Burges cap. 4. pag. 93. line 13.</head>
               <p>It is then a cleare case, that a Christian is not bound to reprove, or discourse of Religion to known or su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected scoffers: If he testify in secret to his God, his dislike of such Varlots, avoide needlesse societie, and unnecessary commerce with them, and in his soul, secretly mourne for their dishonouring God, he hath done his duty.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By your leave, Doctor, Your zeale here smells a little too much of the</hi> Coward: <hi>Did your dying Saviour endure the base</hi> Scoffes, <hi>and bitter</hi> Taunts <hi>of the Iewes, for your sake, and is your</hi> Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>so dainty, not to abide a little</hi> jeering <hi>for his sake? Will your zeale sell Gods honour for the impatience of a</hi> Scoffe? <hi>Were it your own case, I feare, Your wit would finde</hi> spirit <hi>enough, either to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne it, or retort it: But you will away, and complaine to God in a</hi> Corner: <hi>Mettal to the back! Doctor, He that refuses the vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Gods honour, denies him; And he that denies him at</hi> Court, <hi>him will God deny in his</hi> Chamber: <hi>Can you heare your</hi> Soveraigne <hi>abused and be silent? perchance (as the case now stands) you can, and make one for company, too, if you feare not his prevayling</hi> power. <hi>But can you heare your bosome</hi> friend <hi>injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously reviled, and lend him no</hi> Apology, <hi>but run away; and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper in his eare a tedious</hi> Complaint? <hi>If this you can, you are no friend for me: This (if your zeale belie not your conscience) must serve Gods turne, nay more, you have done your duty too.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>Have you not an inhibition, <hi>Cal.</hi> to cast <hi>Pearles</hi> before <hi>Swine?</hi> Are you more tender of Gods glory, or more wise to propagate it, then <hi>David,</hi> who accounted it his duty to keep his mouth <hi>close whilest the wicked were before him? Cal.</hi> your zeale tasts a little too rank of the mother; a <hi>Bellings-gate</hi> zeale, where the <hi>Revenge</hi> is often more sinfull then the <hi>Offence:</hi> Perchance you'ld spit in the offenders face: That zeale is a strange <hi>fire,</hi> that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109428:15"/>
produces such <hi>moist</hi> effects: <hi>Cal.</hi> your Religion is too rhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick: Sure, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> had a good quarrell, to draw his sword, yet the action had too much <hi>rashnesse</hi> in it (as well as blood) to be accepted: Where the party <hi>offending</hi> is not capable of reason, or the party <hi>Vindicating,</hi> hath no capacity of discretion, the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not <hi>warrantable:</hi> Better to beare the hazzard of some <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour,</hi> then to have it indiscreetly vindicated.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 7. pag. 262. lin. 22.</head>
               <p>The supreame and soveraigne Prince, who hath none between him and God, representing the person of God, executing his office, and in this respect, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his name, to whom he onely is accountable for all his actions, by way of Summons and command, this person, I say, must in all things, and at all times, be handled with all humility and due respect of that high place he holdeth; so as all may be taught not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spise, but to honour him, the more, by the carriage of those that are, in case of necessity, to treate with him in the name and busines of his God.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How now, Doctor? None between him and God; Onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptable to God for all his</hi> Actions? <hi>Sure, Doctor, You are now besides your text: Shall whole kingdomes, then, depend upon his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant</hi> pleasure? <hi>So many millions of soules lye open to the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of his arbitrary</hi> will? <hi>Is he not bound to his own Lawes? not limited by his Coronation</hi> oath? <hi>May he alter establisht</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>by the omnipotence of his own vast power, and turn Gods Church into a Rout of Infidells; and our Liberties, into a tenure of Villanage? Is this your Zeale for Gods glory? The man hath overwhelmed his Iudgement in the deep gulph of flattery, and lost himself in his own Principles: Can he represent Gods person, that commands what God forbids? Doth he execute Gods office, that forbids, what he commands? If this be zeale, or common Religion,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109428:15"/>
let me turne</hi> Amalakite, <hi>or any thing that is not, this. No, no; Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, (saving your private engagements, and expectations,) Kings are no such persons as our late Idolatry hath made them: The trust of Kingdomes is put upon them; which, so long as they faithfully discharge, they are to be honoured and obeyed; but, once being violated, their Covenants are broken; and they are no longer</hi> Kings; The safety of the people, is the supreme Law; <hi>and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were not made for the good of</hi> Kings, <hi>but Kings, for the good of</hi> People.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>How this Doctors loyalty, good <hi>Cal.</hi> offends you! If he would <hi>temporize</hi> as you do; abuse and slander <hi>Scripture</hi> for his own liberty, as you do; fly in the face of <hi>Majesty,</hi> as you do; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to introduce a new <hi>Government</hi> in Church and State, as you do; <hi>Blaspheme</hi> God and the King as you do, he were then a holy, a <hi>well-affected</hi> man, a Saint, or any thing that's good; But now his <hi>Conscience</hi> is directed by the Scriptures, his Judgement <hi>enlightned</hi> by the Scriptures, his words warranted by the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> especially in a Case of such Consequence, Away with him; He is a disaffected person, a Malignant, and what not, that's Bad? But concerning <hi>Kings,</hi> Know, They represent Gods <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> whether good or bad; If good; they represent him in his <hi>Mercy;</hi> If bad, in his <hi>Iudgments:</hi> Christ hath a Rod of <hi>Iron,</hi> as well as a <hi>Golden-</hi>Scepter; a <hi>Nebuchadnezzer,</hi> as well as a <hi>Iosiah;</hi> a <hi>Nero,</hi> as well as a <hi>Constantine:</hi> We must stoope to <hi>both:</hi> He that submits not to the power of a <hi>bad</hi> King, Kicks against Gods Judgments; But he that resists, snatches Gods <hi>Rod</hi> out of his hand; and, refusing Correction, falls into DAMNATION: We must submit to the <hi>Higher</hi> Powers. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. And who are they? <hi>Whether it be to the King, as Supreme, or unto Governours that are sent by</hi> HIM. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. 14. From whence necessari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this followes; That <hi>Power</hi> which he warrants not, we have no Warrant to <hi>obey;</hi> and, Those <hi>Ordinances</hi> his power signes not, we have no Commission to <hi>observe;</hi> As for your slighting and deposing Kings, the <hi>Current</hi> of the Scriptures runs strong against you, and all the <hi>examples</hi> of Gods children (through the whole book of God) bend another Course, They know no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109428:16"/>
of Kings but by <hi>death;</hi> no determination of Passive obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, but by <hi>fire:</hi> But whether our <hi>Translation</hi> of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures be the same with former Ages; or whether some strange light hath darted <hi>inspirations</hi> into these our later dayes, (which the Apostle denominated perillous) I leave to the learned <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod;</hi> who, I hope, will at length consult us into a <hi>Religion,</hi> which shall need no future <hi>Alteration;</hi> or that Alteration no further <hi>effusion</hi> of Christian blood.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. <hi>7.</hi> pag. <hi>272.</hi> line <hi>19.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>God made a Law to all, Not to revile the Gods, nor curse the Ruler of the people; which Law prohibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not onely Imprecations, and seditious Raylings, (which is a hellish impiety, though it be but in word onely, be the Prince never so impious) but even all rude, bitter, and unseemly speeches, although in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to himself alone, much more, in publique, or in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places behinde his back.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What paynes the Man takes to pick out</hi> Texts <hi>to countenance his</hi> Idolatry-royall! <hi>True, Kings are called</hi> Gods: <hi>But what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes? They shall dye like</hi> men: <hi>Concerning which</hi> dying <hi>not a word; because it is so opposite to a</hi> Living, <hi>which is the onely</hi> Butt <hi>he aymes at: But marke the</hi> Doctrine <hi>his Court-ship raises from his well chosen</hi> Text, Though Princes be never so impious, yet to reprove them roundly <hi>(which in his language is seditious rayling, rude, bitter and unseemely speeches)</hi> is a hellish impiety; <hi>and, in his King-clawing Iudgment, must neither be done in publique, nor yet in private. How ready are such</hi> Officers <hi>to light Princes to the Devill!</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cal.</hi> If he light Kings to the Devil by <hi>his poynt of Doctrine,</hi> you take a speedy course to send his subjects after him, by <hi>your use of exhortation:</hi> But mark your own words, you first inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate that he makes him a <hi>God;</hi> then, conclude, He lights him to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109428:16"/>
the <hi>Devil:</hi> You that can so suddenly make Contraries meet, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile the <hi>King and his two Houses:</hi> The <hi>issue</hi> then of all, is this; You say, He makes the King a God, by <hi>flattering Idolatry;</hi> and, I say, you make his subjects, Devils, by your <hi>flat Rebellion: Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> whom you confide in, tels you, That Princes (though most wicked in their Government) yet in respect of the dignity of their places, their name and Credit must be spared; But see, a greater then <hi>Calvin; Elihu,</hi> the moderatour betwixt <hi>Iob</hi> and his miserable Comforters <hi>(Iob</hi> 34. 18.) saith, <hi>Is it fit then to say to a King, Thou art wicked? and to Princes, yee are ungodly?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, a greater then <hi>Elihu, Solomon</hi> (whom yee blasphemously lesse Credit then either, for his <hi>partiality,</hi> being a King) sayes, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 8. 4. <hi>Where the word of a King is, there is power, and who shall say unto him, What dost thou?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. <hi>7.</hi> pag. <hi>274.</hi> line <hi>19.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>God hath engraven so large and fayre a Character of His Imperial Image in their foreheads <hi>(viz.</hi> of Princes) as must be sacred in the hearts of all, and binde not their hands onely, but tongues also to the good behaviour, and that for ever. Nor is this carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age onely due to good princes, but universally to all.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>Sacred? <hi>a little further: nay, then make him</hi> Almighty <hi>too: and even, fall down and worship: Make him your graven Image, your</hi> Dagon, <hi>and hoyst him up for a God; but be sure the</hi> Ark <hi>be away: Nay, though an</hi> Idolator, <hi>an</hi> Infidell, <hi>sacred too: Make him your</hi> Bell <hi>and</hi> Dragon; <hi>but you do well to binde his subjects hands to their good behaviour, for feare some</hi> Daniel <hi>be among them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>How now <hi>Cal.</hi> Is your fornace so hot? you forget that he is <hi>Gods Vicegerent,</hi> you make so bold with; Remember, <hi>there be birds of the Ayre,</hi> and <hi>things with wings;</hi> Had you lived in <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzers</hi> dayes, you would have sav'd him much Fuell,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109428:17"/>
and his Officers some labour: Questionlesse, your fornace had consumed the three passively <hi>obedient</hi> Children, and been too hot for the <hi>fourth</hi> to walke in.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 7. pag. 277. line 17.</head>
               <p>Invectives (though but against an equall, or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour) are ever odious, but against a Prince, intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If</hi> Invectives <hi>be so intolerable, let Princes be so wise as not to give occasion, and</hi> deserve <hi>them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>If all should have according to their <hi>deservings:</hi> I feare, <hi>Cal.</hi> the <hi>Psalme of Mercy,</hi> would scarce advantage thee.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 7. pag. 278. line 6.</head>
               <p>An indefinite Reproofe of sin in publique is enough; If this serve not to reforme a Prince, forbeare; More will make him worse.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kings are past Children, to be whipt on others backs. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will shew you some</hi> Prophets <hi>that feared not to rouze the very persons of Kings, by</hi> name; <hi>and rattle them soundly, and before their people too: But, Doctor, you have either no</hi> Commission, <hi>or are afraid to</hi> execute <hi>it: You flee to</hi> Tharshish, <hi>when you should go to</hi> Nineveh; <hi>You whisper softly, lest they should chance to heare yee; and give your Royal Patients no Phisick but Cordials, for feare it</hi> work <hi>and make their queazy stomacks sick.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>actions</hi> of Prophets, which had immediate <hi>Warrants</hi> from heaven, are no presidents for <hi>later times;</hi> neither durst those couragious Prophets speak before speciall <hi>Commission:</hi> Did <hi>Eliah</hi> stir to reprove King <hi>Ahab</hi> till God had given him charge to go? 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. 17, 18. <hi>Amos</hi> prophesyed not against King <hi>Amaziah,</hi> till God especially commanded him: <hi>Ordinary</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs must not be copied from <hi>extraordinary</hi> Embassages; but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109428:17"/>
from their usuall <hi>Sermons,</hi> which in their reproofs, were for the most part, <hi>indefinitely</hi> uttred to all, in generall; by name, to none. But you, that have fresh <hi>Influences</hi> of the spirit, may Boanarge it where and when ye please, and play the <hi>Bedlems</hi> in divinity; But remember what is said to those that <hi>exceede</hi> their Commissions, <hi>Who hath required these things at your hands?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 7. page 280. line 18.</head>
               <p>What shall they answer unto God, who being but private persons discontented, shall take upon them, <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei</hi> like, to revile and traduce their Soveraigne behind his back, and presume to make every Taverne and Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bench a Tribunall, whereat to accuse, arraigne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the sacred and dreadfull person of the Lords An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyted (whom they ought not to mention without a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reverence) and to censure all his Actions, before their Companions as confidently as if he were the vassal, and they the Monarch: Hath not former experience told us, this is the high way to all Treasons and Rebellions?</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When Princes offend their God in suffering, or</hi> partaking <hi>with Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, shall subjects be afraid to offend them? Shall Gods</hi> name <hi>be abused and torne in pieces with their execrable</hi> oaths <hi>and blasphemies, and shall their dainty names be held so precious, as not to be spoken of; or (as our Doctor saies) not mentioned without a holy</hi> Reverence? <hi>Shall Gods most sacred and just</hi> Commands <hi>be despised and slighted by them, and shall their prophane</hi> Injunctions <hi>not be unperformed, without</hi> presumption? <hi>their unlawfull Commands not violated with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> Rebellion? <hi>Weigh these things with the</hi> balance <hi>of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and you shall finde, that you either want true</hi> Zeale; <hi>or your Zeale a right object.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cal.</hi> review your owne <hi>Argument;</hi> and you will (with the help of some reasonable discretion) find it (TEKEL) weighed in the <hi>Balances,</hi> wanting in weight; In case, thy Prince should offend his God, in wounding and tearing his holy Name by oathes and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109428:18"/>
                     <hi>Blasphemies;</hi> Put case, he should justle Gods sacred <hi>Lawes</hi> out of the Land; violate them in his countermands; prophane his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with <hi>Idolatry,</hi> or <hi>Barbarisme;</hi> will this warrant thee to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour him, whom God hath commanded thee to <hi>serve?</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell against him, to whom God hath commanded thee to be <hi>subject?</hi> to disobey him, whom God hath commanded thee to <hi>honour?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he offends his God, wilt thou aggravate the offence, in offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him? and rebell against God, in rebelling against him? Weigh these things well; and let thy own conscience (if not brib'd with partiality) be thy <hi>Iudge.</hi> Thinkest thou this rabble of rebellious and seditious <hi>Rakeshames,</hi> that style themselves by the name of <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Seouts, Weekly Intelligencers, &amp;c.</hi> but, indeed, a pack of <hi>Alebench</hi> Whistlers, <hi>decayed</hi> Captaines, and <hi>masterlesse</hi> Journy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that want more <hi>haires</hi> then vices; and, for <hi>Thirty</hi> pieces of Silver, betray the <hi>Lords Anointed;</hi> for halfe a Crowne a week, fly in the face of Gods <hi>Vicegerent;</hi> and, under a pretence of <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> sell themselves to all wickednesse; that, like <hi>Sampsons</hi> Foxes joyne tayle to tayle, and carry fire-brands about to set the gallantest <hi>Kingdome</hi> in the world on a light flame; thinkest thou that these are pleasing to the God of <hi>Peace?</hi> Thinkest thou, these brazen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd <hi>Monsters,</hi> with their meditated <hi>lyes,</hi> malicious <hi>scandals,</hi> printed (and shamefully permitted) in their seditious <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> are pleasing to the God of <hi>Truth?</hi> Thinkest thou, these undecent and preposterous actions, tending to the <hi>confusion</hi> of well-establisht Lawes, and to the <hi>disturbment</hi> of a long setled Government, are pleasing to the God of <hi>Order?</hi> Thinkest thou, that they, and their <hi>Abettors</hi> will passe unpunisht? No; <hi>Cal.</hi> If our King faile in his duty to God; and we, in ours to him; God will keep us still di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in our affections so, that we shall joyne in nothing, but in drawing down <hi>Iudgements</hi> upon the whole land; which, without <hi>Accomodation</hi> (the King alwayes <hi>living</hi> in his Royall Posterity, and the Parliament <hi>never dying)</hi> will perpetuate us in <hi>blood,</hi> till the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Ruine</hi> both of Church and State.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 7. page 282. line 16.</head>
               <p>If good People should discerne some Errors, (and those not small) in Princes, the best Patterne they can
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109428:18"/>
propound themselves is, that of <hi>Samuel</hi> (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 35.) mourning and praying for <hi>Saul,</hi> not for Forme onely but heartily, and fervently indeed; and the worst they can pitch upon (unlesse they proceede to open Treason) is that of common Newesmongers and seditious spirits, who cannot make a Meale, spend a Fire, drink a Pint, or drive away one hower, without some pragmaticall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, and censure of Princes, and their State-Affayres.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nay Good Doctor; we have had many</hi> Samuels <hi>(or as good) that have</hi> fasted <hi>and</hi> prayed, <hi>at least these twenty moneths, That God would be pleased so</hi> turne the Kings heart, and bring him back to his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>but God hath stopt his eares against us, and will not be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. And, since God hath made his pleasure so openly known through the whole Land, (nay through the world too) that his Majesties heart is fully resolved and knit to Popery and Superstition; shall we subjects (whom it so much concernes) be afraid to</hi> communicate <hi>the businesse to one another? Your conscience, Doctor, is growen a great</hi> Royalist; <hi>but your tender</hi> Zeale <hi>of your Princes honour will hardly stop our mouthes or close our eares; Our Case is so, that our discourse of him, and</hi> States-matters <hi>too, cannot be too pragmaticall (as you call it) We must, now, take advantage of those his</hi> faults, <hi>which our Fasts, Prayers, and Petitions could not redresse; And, since his cruell</hi> Course <hi>of life, and soild</hi> behaviour <hi>will not be a perfect</hi> white, <hi>we must die it into a</hi> sadder colour; <hi>and these his</hi> Crimes, <hi>which our</hi> teares <hi>cannot wash sairer, (for the comfort of ourselves and Children) our reports (for the countenance of the</hi> Cause) <hi>must make fouler, for the</hi> exasperating <hi>of our Confederates, and</hi> encouragement <hi>of our souldiers; so, that by this christian</hi> Stratageme, <hi>through, the enterchange of</hi> newes <hi>(which you condemne) we may facilitate our own</hi> designes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cal.</hi> Your christian stratageme is but the modest tearme of a <hi>devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish project,</hi> or, in plainer English, a peece of <hi>errant knavery;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the father of your contrivements receives much <hi>glory;</hi> and the God of Truth, no lesse <hi>dishonour:</hi> Read that <hi>statute</hi> which God
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109428:19"/>
made, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19. 16. <hi>Thou shalt not go up and down as a Talebearer among thy people;</hi> where, in the end of the verse, he signes it with <hi>I am the Lord.</hi> The <hi>falsenes</hi> of the Tale doubles the sinne; the <hi>base<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> of the end trobles it; the <hi>person</hi> damnifyed (being a King) makes it, quadruble; the persons <hi>venting</hi> it, (being subjects) makes it terrible; but the <hi>place</hi> where it is commonly vented (being <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits)</hi> makes it horrible; and by the <hi>ministers</hi> of the Gospel too; and in the <hi>name</hi> of the God of truth too, almost impardonably <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable;</hi> Now <hi>Cal.</hi> Tell me how you like your <hi>Christian stratageme;</hi> No wonder, if your <hi>Samuels</hi> were not heard: Tis well for you, Gods Eares were closed against their prayers: Had he not been deafe in <hi>Mercy:</hi> and mercifull to <hi>admiration;</hi> and admirable in <hi>patience;</hi> they, surely, had been heard in <hi>Iudgement,</hi> to the terrible example of such unparalleld <hi>Presumption.</hi> How often have your solemne <hi>Petitions</hi> set <hi>dayes</hi> apart, for the expedition of your <hi>Martiall</hi> attempts in a <hi>Pitcht field,</hi> or for the <hi>raising</hi> of a Seige? How often have your solemnities been shewed in plentifull <hi>thanks givings</hi> for the blood of those thousands, whose soules (without infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) you cannot but conceive, in one day, dropt into the flames of Hell! What Bells? What Bonefires? What tryumphs? And yet, for the successe of your oft propounded, and (sometimes) accepted <hi>Treaties</hi> of Peace, what one blessed <hi>hower</hi> hath been sequestred? What <hi>Church</hi> doore hath been opened? Which makes me feare (and not without just Cause) your <hi>Fastings</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> have been rather to <hi>Contention,</hi> then to Unity; and that they have rather been attractive for <hi>Iudgements,</hi> then for mercies, upon this blood-bedab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Kingdom.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 7. pag. 284. lin. 1.</head>
               <p>As for such as will not take out this Lesson, let their eyes, their tongues, their teares, their sighs, their coates, their prayers be what they will be, their Carriage sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth not of Zeale for God, which thus casteth dirt and Myre upon the face of his Vicegerent, and tendeth to the taking away the life of his life in his subjects hearts, in which all good Princes desire as much to live, as to enjoy their Crownes; And if it be not lawfull
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109428:19"/>
thus to smite at their Persons, with the tongue onely, shall that be thought Zeale for God, which seekes their deposition from that Crown, which once a just free and absolute Title of Inheritance hath set upon their heads?</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doctor, you are very confident of your own learning, and definitive</hi> Judgment, <hi>to tye every mans Zeale to your</hi> Rules: <hi>and it seemes, you are more tender in flinging</hi> Dirt <hi>(as you tearme it) in your Soveraignes face, then in preserving his soule from the</hi> flames <hi>of Hell: Neither do I conceive it a thing so heynous, to take his Subjects hearts from him, as to</hi> unite <hi>them in the superstitious Bonds of Popery: And as for your</hi> deposing <hi>him from the Crown, (which you falsely call his absolute Inheritance) if he break the</hi> Covenants, <hi>whereby the Crown is set up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his head, he</hi> dissolves <hi>his own Authority, and our Obedience; and himself is become his own</hi> deposer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cal.</hi> It is not the Doctor, that prescribes Rules to anothers <hi>Zeale,</hi> but the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> from whence he drawes his infallable prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and Conclusions; And whereas you censure him for more prizing the <hi>cleannesse</hi> of his soveraignes face, then the <hi>wel-fare</hi> of his soul, your malice wrongs him in your <hi>hop-frog</hi> confutation; wherein, you make a wilfull preterition of that poynt, whereof you censure his neglect, in the wrong place. And whereas, you turne Deposition upon the <hi>default</hi> of Princes, know, kingdoms are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Copyholds,</hi> nor <hi>Leases;</hi> subject, either to <hi>forfeiture,</hi> or <hi>Reentry:</hi> Kings have, from God, their power of <hi>reigning;</hi> from Man, the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony of <hi>Coronation:</hi> To God they must give account, (not man) on whose pleasure their <hi>Titles</hi> absolutely depend.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 7. pag. 288. line 4.</head>
               <p>In fine, <hi>David</hi> thought him <hi>(viz.</hi> that slew <hi>Saul)</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of no Reward but death; and of this, so worthy, that instantly he gave order for his execution, with this sharp sentence uttered, Thy Blood be upon thine own head, for thine own mouth hath testified against thee, saying,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109428:20"/>
                  <hi>I have slaine the Lords Annoynted;</hi> A memorable example, and an Argument unanswerable against all King-killers, and deposers of absolute Princes, absolutely annoynted by just title, as here with us.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here, revereud Doctor, Your</hi> Simile <hi>limps: First,</hi> David <hi>was a</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; <hi>and, (knowing the Crown so neare his head,) spared that life, which he knew so neare a</hi> Period; <hi>not willing to dabble his</hi> Conscience <hi>in such needlesse blood: Secondly, (being confident himself was the next</hi> successor) <hi>commanded present Execution, to terrify his new</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects <hi>from the like presumption: Thirdly, (Though you deny it) our Kings hold not their Crownes by such an</hi> absolute <hi>Title, as those of</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Jerusalem.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>Is the Doctors <hi>Simile</hi> lame, <hi>Cal.</hi> Sure, 'twas your ill usage made it so: But say, was <hi>David</hi> a Prophet? Had he speciall <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations?</hi> then, doubtlesse, his wayes and actions were the best pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidents for us, to follow: But was he a Prophet? Then, sure, he knew it a heynous sin, to take away the life of Gods <hi>Vicegerent</hi> (though an Idolater) Had he speciall Revelations? then, questionlesse, he knew death a just Reward for killing the Lords <hi>Annoynted</hi> (though a wicked King.) But did this Prophets heart <hi>smite</hi> him, for cutting off his Soveraignes <hi>skirt?</hi> then, sure, God will not let him go <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smitten,</hi> that takes his Crown from off his head, or power, from his hand: But, <hi>Cal.</hi> how truth will be confest by your unwilling lips! which intimate, the Prophets conscience had been <hi>dabbled in blood,</hi> had the deed been done, and his subjects <hi>guilty of presumption,</hi> that should do the like: And, whereas you deny our Kings so <hi>absolute</hi> a power, or title as the Kings of former times, you should have done to better purpose, to shew, <hi>who</hi> limited it, and <hi>when;</hi> for your own single <hi>assertion</hi> is not Classicall.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 7. page 290. line 2.</head>
               <p>Authority is ever one of Envies eye-sores: Subjection a yoake, that Humane Nature loathes. Although Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours cannot help it, nor durst complaine, Liberty, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty is every mans desire, though most mens ruine.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:109428:20"/>
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When Authoritie is put into a</hi> Right <hi>hand, Subjection is no Burthen to a</hi> good <hi>heart: But when</hi> Tyrannie <hi>usurps the Throne of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, then the people may suspend Obedience, and cast off the yoke of their Subjection: We that</hi> are received into the liberty of the sons of God, and made heires of an everlasting kingdome, <hi>have too much priviledge to be enslav'd to men, or made</hi> vassals <hi>to perpetual bondage: If desire of holy</hi> Liberty <hi>be our labour here, eternall Soveraignty shall be our</hi> Reward <hi>hereafter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>He that <hi>gives</hi> Authority, knowes not <hi>where</hi> to place it: The people were pleased with goodly <hi>Saul;</hi> God was pleased to choose little <hi>David:</hi> Tell me, did the burthen-threatning hand of <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> the son of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the king of Israel and Judah; or <hi>Ieroboam</hi> (the rebellious subject of <hi>Rehoboam)</hi> who <hi>made Israel to sin,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the <hi>Scepter?</hi> By your <hi>marks,</hi> neither; In Gods <hi>wisdome,</hi> both: The one, to crush the liberty of the too proud subject; The other, to exercise the consciences of his chosen people: In both, to work his secret pleasure. But <hi>Guild-hall</hi> hath wiser counsel; and your Conventicling <hi>wives</hi> are fitter Judges for the setting up, or pulling downe of <hi>Kings;</hi> for <hi>regulating</hi> the power of the good, or <hi>limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the prerogatives of the bad: But, 'twere fitting, first, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epistles, or to vote S. <hi>Peters</hi> works APOCRYPHA; who, both, instruct us to submit to the Authority of kings, good or bad; But, indeed, the Liberty of the Subject had been a <hi>strong</hi> plea, had not His Majesty spoiled their jest, and granted all <note n="*" place="margin">1 Trienniall Parliam. 2 Starchamber. 3 High Commission. 4 Shipmoney. 5 Coat and Conduct money. 6 Monopolies. 7 Forrests. 8 Tunnage and Pound. 9 Regulate the Clerk of the market. 10 Knighthood money. 11 For the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this Parl.</note> 
                     <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions;</hi>  and the <hi>Badge</hi> of slavery had been unanswerable, had not our glorious Saviour honoured, and worne it upon his seamlesse <hi>Garment:</hi> The God of glory endured what we despise; and shewed that example, we scorn to follow.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>D. Burges cap. 7. pag. 307. line 14.</head>
               <p>For my part, I am so farre from taking away Prayer from preaching, that I could wish not onely more prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in some places, but more Prayer also in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and I meane, onely that Prayer which is allowed too: In performance whereof (if the fault be not in them who undertake it) much more good will be done, then
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109428:21"/>
will be acknowledged by some, who magnifie preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, rather then adorne it; Yea, I will adde, more then by some mens preaching, admired by so many.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is very much, Doctor, you durst so openly wish more</hi> preaching <hi>in those daies, when your dumb-dog-Bishops silenced so</hi> many; <hi>and most of all,</hi> themselves: <hi>Nay, you are not ashamed to wish more</hi> Prayer <hi>too: What a</hi> Lot <hi>is this, among so many</hi> Sodomites I <hi>But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this,</hi> Lot was drunk: <hi>Our Doctor, being afraid to be thought too righteous, put in one her be that spoiled his whole pot of</hi> Porrage: I meane <hi>(sayes he)</hi> that Prayer which onely was allowed: <hi>And what Prayer was that? even that</hi> English Masse-book, <hi>which (God be thanked) the sacred pietie of</hi> Souldiers, <hi>and the holy boldnesse of</hi> Inferiour <hi>Christians, hath most blessedly taken away. This is that</hi> Prayer, <hi>our Doctor desires onely should be used; This is that</hi> Prayer-book, <hi>our preaching Doctor deifies, and prefers before</hi> some <hi>mens preaching (and who were they, in those Episcopal daies, who knowes not?) admired by so many. This is that</hi> Prayer-book, <hi>that</hi> Prelacie, <hi>which this temporizing Doctor hath now extred into</hi> Covenant (in the presence of Almighty God) <hi>to suppresse.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>It seems <hi>Cal.</hi> this Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> is your <hi>maine</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell here; and Bishops, by the <hi>Bye:</hi> Tell me, who composed that <hi>Book?</hi> In whose <hi>Reigne</hi> was it composed? and what <hi>Authority</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it? Were not those blessed Martyrs the <hi>composers?</hi> they, who gave their bodies to the flame, in the defence of the true <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion, and in defiance of that superstition, whereof you say it is a <hi>Relique?</hi> Dare you vye piety with those Martyrs, that are so dayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of your <hi>passive obedience?</hi> They composed it; You defie it: Was not this detestable book composed in that pious Saints dayes <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. of holy memory, when the Protestant <hi>Broome</hi> swept cleanest? and when the cruelty of that bloody <hi>Religion</hi> was but newly out of breath, and fresh in Memory? This blessed <hi>Saint</hi> allowed it; You despise it: Was not this book, ye so revile, confirmed by <hi>Act</hi> of Parliament (in those dayes) the <hi>Members</hi> whereof were chosen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong those that were (excepting the blessed Martyrs) the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est <hi>sufferers</hi> under the tyranny of that barbarous <hi>Religion,</hi> whereof,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:109428:21"/>
you say, it favours? The Authority of this great <hi>Council</hi> confirmed it: You condemne it: Did not the <hi>Phoenix</hi> of the world, and of her Sexe Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of everlasting Memory, (in whose dayes God so smiled upon this kingdom) and that <hi>Monument</hi> of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and wisdom, King <hi>Iames,</hi> of never dying memory in all their <hi>Parliaments,</hi> establish it? Yet, you revile it: Did not your self, in your oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> sweare to maintaine the King in his esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished <hi>government,</hi> in Church and Common-wealth? Yet, in this particular, you violate it. Ponder all this, <hi>Cal.</hi> and, then, reviewe your own <hi>words,</hi> and if you blush not, you are brazen-fac'd.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 7. pag. 309. line 21.</head>
               <p>If they can pick out some boldfac'd mercenary Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick, that by the help of a <hi>Polyanthea,</hi> or some English Treatise, can make a shift, five or six times a week, with his tongue, and teeth, to throw over the Pulpit a pack of stolne wares, which sometimes the judicious hearer knowes by the mark, and sends it home to the right ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>Pag. 310. line 15.</head>
               <p>Or if the man hath been drinking, feasting, or riding, that so no time is left to him to search so far as a naked Commentary, Postel, or some Catechisme, yet adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures on the sacred businesse of preaching, carrying to the Pulpit a bold face, instead of savory provision, and thinks it sufficient, that the people hear Thunder, though they see no Raine, and, that loudnesse will serve, for once, instead of matter; because (if he be earnest) silly women, and some ninnyes more will count him a very zealous Preacher, and impute his want of matter to his wisdome and desire of edifying, not to his want of study, or ability, and say, <hi>He preaches to the Conscience: He stands not upon deep learning: He reproveth sin boldly, that is to say, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens,</hi> therefore they love him: not theirs, otherwise, they would abhor him.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:109428:22"/>
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And such a deale of</hi> Trumpery, <hi>that my pen tyres before it come to the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>adious</hi> Journies <hi>end of his invective speech; wherein, I have so much charity left to excuse him; in that, he personates some Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, whom his malice conceives no better then</hi> fooles; <hi>Who, indeed, though they make no</hi> flourish, <hi>quoate no</hi> Fathers, <hi>repeate no sentences of</hi> Greek <hi>and</hi> Latine, <hi>and preach not</hi> themselves <hi>(as our learned D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. doth) yet edifie the simpler sort of people more in two howers, then he with his neate</hi> Orations <hi>and quaint</hi> stile <hi>doth in five</hi> Sermons, <hi>ushered in by his Popish</hi> Lettany. <hi>These are those men who (in his last clause, he covertly saith) are</hi> admired by too many, <hi>and whose preaching lesse edifies then the superstitious</hi> Common-prayer book: <hi>Doctor, leave your gibeing, and presume not too much upon your</hi> learning <hi>and</hi> wit, <hi>which God hath given you, as a sharp knife to cut your own Throat, And deride not those whose</hi> Defects <hi>of learning are so bountifully sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed with</hi> Inspirations <hi>and Revelations of the</hi> spirit.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>Take heed, good <hi>Cal.</hi> you merit not the Honour to be called the <hi>Dunces Advocate:</hi> These are the men, that carry their <hi>Provaunt</hi> Sermons up and down the Country, and in their people-pleasing <hi>Lectures,</hi> cry up <hi>Liberty,</hi> and prate down Government; cry up the Spirit, and beate down <hi>Learning;</hi> cry up Sedition, and preach down <hi>Authority.</hi> But tell me, <hi>Cal.</hi> where were all these Edifyers, these inspyred <hi>Pneumasticks,</hi> when the daring Pens of <hi>Fisher, Campion, Harding,</hi> and other learned <hi>Hereticks</hi> breathed forth their threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings against the true <hi>Protestant</hi> Church? when as the hot mouthed Challenges of <hi>Romes Goliahs</hi> thundred in our English <hi>Host,</hi> where, where were all those <hi>long-winded</hi> Lecturers? Which of them took up the <hi>Sling?</hi> What one amongst them threw down his <hi>Gauntlet?</hi> Who among so many, struck one blow in the just defence of the true <hi>Reformed</hi> Religion? Or tell me, without blushing, where are they that did it? These, that bravely rusht into the <hi>Lists,</hi> defied the Enemy, grappled with him; nay, laid him on his <hi>back;</hi> tore the Crown from the bold <hi>Strumpets</hi> head, and snatcht the <hi>Cup</hi> of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son from her trembling hand, what <hi>Palme,</hi> or what <hi>Reward</hi> have they, I shame to tell: These, like undaunted <hi>Champions</hi> endured the <hi>Brunt,</hi> in dust and sweate, and stoutly undertook the <hi>Cause;</hi> whilest they, like Trouts, all day betook them to their <hi>Holds,</hi> and now, in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:109428:22"/>
the dark night of Ignorance, prey upon the Churches <hi>Ruine:</hi> They fish in <hi>Waters,</hi> which themselves have troubled. These, these are they, <hi>that lead silly women Captive, and creeping into Widowes houses, devoure them under a pretence of long Prayer;</hi> Learnings <hi>shame,</hi> Religions <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> the vulgars <hi>Idols,</hi> and the <hi>Bane</hi> of this our (late glorious) now miserable Kingdom.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>D. <hi>Burges cap.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 319. <hi>line</hi> 22.</head>
               <p>God made a Law, that every word of an Accusation should be establisht by two or three witnesses: This Law is revived by the Apostle in the Gospel, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the Case of Ministers. <hi>Against an Elder receive not an Accusation, but under two or three witnesses.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 19. By an Elder, meaning a Minister, as Saint <hi>Ambrose, Epiphanius</hi> and others rightly do expound it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>Pag. 129. line 9.</head>
               <p>It were therefore a most uncharitable, and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Course upon a bare Accusation of an Enemy, to condemne a Minister, before himself be heard, and a competent number of Witnesses of worth produced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How now Doctor, doth your Guilt begin to call for more</hi> witnesses? <hi>Are you tormented before your time? The</hi> Law <hi>(you speake on) would in these dayes, be needlesse: Our Ministers faults are now writ in their</hi> foreheads, <hi>and as apparent as the Sun at noone, whose leud and looser</hi> Conversations, <hi>are impudent</hi> Confessions, <hi>and visibly manifest, enough without farther</hi> Witnesses: <hi>Our Crime-discovering</hi> Century, <hi>is both</hi> Witnesses <hi>and</hi> Jury, <hi>and the pious</hi> Composer <hi>thereof, a most sufficient Iudge: But some there be so</hi> craftily <hi>vitious, that they can keep their words and Actions from the eyes and eares of Men: For such, I hold a reasonable Presumption,</hi> Evidence <hi>enough; Others there be, whose vices want no</hi> Witnesses, <hi>but, perchance, their Witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sses, (as the too partiall world expounds it) want</hi> worth <hi>and</hi> Credit. <hi>Some measure worth by a visible</hi> Estate; <hi>some, by unimpeachable</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty <hi>of body, or behaviour; others, by a religious</hi> demeanour <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to establisht canstitutions; whereas, for my part, If a poor</hi> handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:109428:23"/>
                     <hi>man, or whose</hi> Infirmity <hi>denies him a through-pac'd honesty, or whose piety is a little zealously</hi> refractory <hi>to establisht</hi> discipline; <hi>nay, be he a convicted</hi> Anabaptist, <hi>or</hi> Blasphemer, <hi>or what not? (in case it be for the</hi> Cause) <hi>that brings an</hi> Accusation, <hi>or appears a</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse <hi>against a Malignant Minister, I question not, but such a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse may be</hi> valuable.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Law</hi> denyes it, <hi>Cal.</hi> But now the Law's <hi>asleep,</hi> all actions are <hi>arbitrarie:</hi> But the ground of that <hi>Law</hi> was very just; for, as <hi>Theodoret</hi> in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. sayes, <hi>Because Ministers touch sinners to the quick, it exasperates many against them;</hi> in respect whereof, their Accusations require many witnesses. <hi>Eutichianus</hi> an ancient Bishop, about the yeare 276. after Christ, (if Bishops retaine any credit more then a Turk) <hi>Ep.</hi> 8. <hi>Episc. Syri<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> admonishes, to weigh well the <hi>Accusation</hi> of a Minister, because the faithfull execution of his <hi>Office</hi> gaines him many enemies. He also proceedeth to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enable all <hi>Heretiques,</hi> all <hi>suspected</hi> of Heresie, <hi>excommunicate</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, <hi>Malefactors, Theeves, Sacrilegious, Adulterers,</hi> that seek to <hi>Witches,</hi> or <hi>Conjurers,</hi> and all other <hi>Infamous</hi> persons. In the 3. Councel of <hi>Laterane (Vide Append. Concil. Lat.</hi> 3. <hi>par.</hi> 50. <hi>cap.</hi> 69.) It was decreed, That upon an <hi>unproved</hi> accusation of a Clerick, his owne <hi>single</hi> oath should free him. It was agreed in the 7. Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Carthage,</hi> that all <hi>servants, Stage</hi> players, <hi>uncleane</hi> persons, <hi>wanderers,</hi> all that came <hi>uncalled,</hi> all under 14. yeares of age, and all that the Accuser brings from <hi>home</hi> with him, shall be rejected, as <hi>Witnesses,</hi> against a Minister. Another Decree of <hi>Analectus,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes the <hi>Accuser</hi> to be a witnesse, or the witnesses to be such as are <hi>revengefull,</hi> and must be cleare of all suspition. In a Synod at Rome, about <hi>Constantines</hi> time, it was decreed, No <hi>Deacon</hi> should be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned under 44. able witnesses: Such tender care was, alwayes, had of the accusation of a <hi>Minister.</hi> But now <hi>Cal.</hi> your <hi>Tenets</hi> can (in favour to your new fashiond pieties) qualifie <hi>secret</hi> whorema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, <hi>open</hi> blasphemers, and such as your <hi>selfe;</hi> nay, one single <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuser</hi> (and a sorry one too) will doe the feat.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>D. Burges cap. 7. pag. 232. line 20.</head>
               <p>But what? is every tatling Basket-maker, or Butcher, or mincing Shee a fit Judge of a (Ministers) doctrine,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:109428:23"/>
and meet to reprove and confute him for it? Is that Zeal, which catches at pieces of sentences, and then runnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and gives out, that he preaches false doctrine, contradictions, or Invectives, to shame him to his flock?</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doctor, if some of your Coat (I name no bodie) were as tender of your</hi> Lives, <hi>as ye are of your</hi> Doctrines, <hi>you would have fairer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports: But your bent is to bring the vulgar to beleeve your words without</hi> Examination; <hi>and, then, you'ld preach them into what</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <hi>ye list. Could you but once work them to</hi> Implicite <hi>faith, the Kingdome of</hi> Antichrill <hi>were more then halfe set up: The horse that winces, is galled somewhere, or we account it the trick of a</hi> Jade, <hi>that feares riding. God hath commanded all</hi> to search the Scriptures; <hi>and will ye take</hi> Pett <hi>if we examine the</hi> Doctrine <hi>you raise from thence? Did our</hi> Saviour <hi>storme, when the</hi> Sadduces <hi>reproved his words? How often were his Doctrines traduced, as</hi> false? <hi>How often was his</hi> Authority <hi>questioned? nay more, denyed? Yet he reviled them not. Doctor, stroke downe your stomack; The closer you follow</hi> Christ, <hi>the cheerfullier your</hi> flock <hi>will follow you: But know, in things so neare concerning us, our mouthes shall be as wide as the faults, be they of</hi> Potentates, Generals, <hi>or</hi> Princes: <hi>and if they doe not what our Conscience tels us is their</hi> duties, <hi>they shall not faile to heare ont.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cal.</hi> I think Ignorance hath given thy tongue a <hi>Bribe,</hi> thou play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est her <hi>Advocate</hi> so well: Both of their lives, and doctrines, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters must give account to <hi>God,</hi> and his subordinate <hi>Authoritie;</hi> and not to you: <hi>Cal.</hi> you forget the Calling of a Minister: He is your spirituall <hi>Father: Cham</hi> was cursed, for discovering his fathers na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse. Put case, your Minister should shew his nakednesse in some <hi>Error;</hi> either, of life, or doctrine; it were more modest piety for you to cover it with your <hi>silence,</hi> or to recover it by your <hi>prayers,</hi> then to upbraide Him with it. Had you searcht the Scriptures as you ought, you would as well have condemned the <hi>saucines</hi> of the Sadduces, as the <hi>mildnes</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> whose high <hi>Authority</hi> need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no Credit among men; but our poor Ministers (whom the least breath of a <hi>Mechanicks</hi> mouth, is able (now) to ruine, and undoe both wives and children, without compassion) have reason to be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:109428:24"/>
moved with such affronts: But, <hi>Cal.</hi> perchance, you vindicate your own naturall father, whilst you revenge your self upon your spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall; from whence, ariseth this doctrine; <hi>You have more love to the flesh, then to the spirit:</hi> No question, <hi>Cal.</hi> your fancynesse is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall, and feares not to be exercized upon the Sword, as well as Keyes; Your Prince hath found it; Your Generall hath found it; whose slow designes cannot agree with the Constitutions of your too fiery spirits, your discontents have found unbridled tongues, to propagate your liberties, although by blood; But the Synod, (whose consultations are to settle peace in our distemperd Church) can go their own paces, without petition or complaint, from whence, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riseth this doctrine; <hi>You love your own safeties above the glory of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 7. page 335. line 21.</head>
               <p>I wright this, to clip the wings of those Batts, and Reremice, that are ready to fly in the Ministers face upon all occasions, with false accusations, fancy Reproofs, and proud Censures of his Ministry, desiring to be teachers of Law, understanding neither what they say, nor whereof they affirme.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doctor, you still harp upon the same string: But do these Batts, these</hi> Reremice <hi>trouble you? Then walke lesse in the</hi> Dark; <hi>(You know my meaning) But you now pick a Quarrell against your fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named</hi> Reprovers, <hi>That</hi> they desire to be teachers of the Law, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding neither what they say, nor what they affirme. <hi>How your Orthodoxe nose swells at that! If ye would be oftner in your</hi> Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, <hi>there would be the lesse roome for them: But tell me, Doctor; If a</hi> Smith <hi>or a</hi> Tinker <hi>should happen to be gifted, and strike a Naile of</hi> edification <hi>into the spirituall foot of an unregenerate brother, and thereby save his soule, would it trouble you, because the Smith was not called? would it grieve you, because the Tinker had no</hi> Ordination <hi>from a</hi> Bitesheepe? <hi>If a good deed be done, true piety will never blame the hand that did it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cal.</hi> You have twice together, out of your <hi>sinck</hi> of bitternesse bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out your naucious <hi>malice</hi> upon the Dr. in these dark words,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:109428:24"/>
                     <hi>(I meane no body,</hi> and <hi>You know my meaning)</hi> which like the <hi>flatus hypocondriacus</hi> (fuming from your spleene, the <hi>Receptacle</hi> of all base humors) troubles and distracts your head. But, in His Name I defye both them, and thee: And, as for your <hi>Tub-preachers,</hi> you so much defend, I perceive by your <hi>Metaphor,</hi> they edify the cleane contrary way; Concerning whom, this onely. When the great <hi>Block</hi> of Religion is removed, then such <hi>Buggs</hi> appeare: Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, like an <hi>Easterne-wind,</hi> brings in such <hi>vermine:</hi> When <hi>Ieroboam</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled against his lawfull <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> and dispossest him of the Crown of <hi>Israel,</hi> he made Priests of the <hi>lowest</hi> of the people, which were not of the house of <hi>Levi.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. 31. And this became <hi>sin</hi> unto the house of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> even to <hi>cut</hi> it off, and to <hi>destroy</hi> it from off the face of the earth. 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 13. 34. But your <hi>Tubbists</hi> have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enough, and understanding too, sufficient for an Auditory com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed of such as you, whom Ignorance cannot injure.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Burges cap. 7. page 360. line 11.</head>
               <p>If he that seemes religious, will yet be idle, false, undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, and stub borne, raile at Ceremonies, Bishops, and Common-Prayer, disdaine to be corrected, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his fault; that man or woman will never have any true Religion in him, till with a Cudgel all these Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfits be beaten off.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Cal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As our Doctor hath, formerly, in his severall</hi> Clauses <hi>and</hi> Chops <hi>of Zeale set down the particular</hi> Items <hi>of his ill-affected and malignant opinions; so in this last, he hath comprehended all in a</hi> Summa Totalis: <hi>And, to conclude marke one thing, right worthy to be observed; and then,</hi> farewell; <hi>He, that hath buzz'd so long about the Roome, like a</hi> Flesh-Fly, <hi>hath now discover'd himself to be a</hi> Hornet, <hi>with a sting in his Tayle: He hath, at length, turn'd the weapons of the Church into a</hi> Cudgell; <hi>and changed the peace of the Gospel into</hi> Club-law.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="counter-reply">
                  <head>Repl.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cal.</hi> If the Doctors <hi>Inventory</hi> please thee not, the fault lies in thy own Ignorance, that knowest not how to prize such <hi>Iewels;</hi> Grains are fitter for Grill, then <hi>Pearles:</hi> Our Doctor, whom you revile, is neither <hi>Fly,</hi> nor <hi>Hornet,</hi> but a painfull <hi>Bee;</hi> who, though he carry a sting in his Tayle for such <hi>turbulent</hi> spirits as you, yet he hath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:109428:25"/>
honey in his <hi>Bag,</hi> for such as shall deserve it: Think not his <hi>Zeale</hi> cruell, because, it mentions a <hi>Cudgell;</hi> A Cudgell drawes no blood, as your encouraged <hi>Swords</hi> have done: If Iustruction wil not do, <hi>Correction</hi> must; but <hi>Love,</hi> in both; If Saint <hi>Paul</hi> cannot perswade <hi>subjection to higher powers,</hi> Nor <hi>Solomon obedience to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majesty, Pauls</hi> Rod is for the <hi>stubborne</hi> heart, and <hi>Solomons</hi> Scourge for the <hi>fooles</hi> back.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="original_tract">
               <head>HEB. 6. 4, 5, 6.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is impossible for those who were once enlightned, and have tasted of the heavenly gift, and were made partakers of the holy Spirit,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And have tasted the good word of God, and the powers of the world to come;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If they shall fall away, to renew them again unto Repentance: seeing they crucifie to themselves the Son of God afresh, and put him to an open shame.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>To the Readers.</head>
            <p>NOw the businesse is ended. If you look upon this <hi>skirmish</hi> with a generall eye, you wil see nothing but (as in a Battail) smoak and confusion: But if you mark every ones particular behaviour, you wil easily distinguish betwixt a <hi>rash fierie spirit,</hi> and a <hi>truly valiant.</hi> In the <hi>Doctor,</hi> you shall find a <hi>David,</hi> fighting Gods defensive <hi>Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes,</hi> without sinister respects, or private <hi>passion:</hi> In <hi>Cal.</hi> you shal see the son of <hi>Nimshi,</hi> matching furiously, and hewing downe the <hi>Priests</hi> of Baal, yet neverthelesse a great worshipper of <hi>Calves:</hi> In the <hi>Replyer,</hi> you may behold <hi>Ionathan</hi> comming a <hi>Reserve</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> though perchance shooting his arrowes sometimes <hi>wide,</hi> and sometimes <hi>open:</hi> It lyes in you, Readers, now, to judge, and give the <hi>Palme:</hi> For the Doctors part and mine (would <hi>Cal.</hi> durst make the third) we both resigne our shares: Let Truth be crowned with the Victory, and the God of Truth, with Glory.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
