<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse upon prodigious abstinence occasioned by the twelve moneths fasting of Martha Taylor, the famed Derbyshire damosell : proving that without any miracle, the texture of humane bodies may be so altered, that life may be long continued without the supplies of meat &amp; drink : with an account of the heart, and how far it is interessed in the business of fermentation / by John Reynolds ...</title>
            <author>Reynolds, John, of Kings-Norton.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-05">2004-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57186</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10543</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12386125</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12386125</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60848</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A57186)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60848)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 225:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse upon prodigious abstinence occasioned by the twelve moneths fasting of Martha Taylor, the famed Derbyshire damosell : proving that without any miracle, the texture of humane bodies may be so altered, that life may be long continued without the supplies of meat &amp; drink : with an account of the heart, and how far it is interessed in the business of fermentation / by John Reynolds ...</title>
                  <author>Reynolds, John, of Kings-Norton.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.W. for Nevill Simmons ... and for Dorman Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Humbly offered to the Royall Society"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Taylor, Martha, b. 1651.</term>
               <term>Fasting --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fasting --  Physiological effect --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60848:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60848:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Discourse upon Prodigious
ABSTINENCE:
OCCASIONED
By the Twelve Moneths FASTING
OF
<hi>MARTHA TAYLOR,</hi>
The Famed <hi>Derbyshire</hi>
Damosell:
Proving That without any Miracle, the Texture
of Humane Bodies may be so altered, that Life may
be long Continued without the supplies of
MEAT &amp; DRINK.</p>
            <p>With an Account of the Heart, and how far it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teressed
in the Business of Fermentation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Iohn Reynolds.</p>
            <p>Humbly offered to the
Royall Society.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, by <hi>R. W.</hi> for <hi>Nevill Simmons,</hi> at the Sign of the
three Crowns near <hi>Holborn</hi>-Conduit: and for <hi>Dorman Newman,</hi>
at the Chyrurgeons Arms in <hi>Little Brittain.</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60848:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60848:2"/>
            <head>To the deservedly Famous, and my
Honoured Friend, Walter Needham, Doctor of
Physick, as also a Member of, and Curator
Elect to the Royal Society.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T were a Solaecism of the first magnitude to
entertain you with any thing like a Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative
of the Superennial Fast, under all the
Havooks and depraedations whereof the
<hi>Derby-shire</hi> Damosell hath hitherto been
sustained, though emaciated thereby into the
ghastliness of a Skeleton, to the great astonishment of the
<hi>Vulgus.</hi> Your correspondencies are so faithful, and your
Circumstances so advantageous, as wholly to supersede the
necessity of my engaging in, and the possibility of my grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
you, by such a <hi>Province.</hi> However, indulge me,
while bemoaning my self, the liberty to tell you, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the <hi>Phaenomena's</hi> attending this prodigeous Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinence,
my own thoughts have been so miserably ravel'd,
and my scanty intellectuals so much overmatcht thereby,
<pb facs="tcp:60848:3"/>
that I could not with any Complacency look into those, nor
with any delight consult these. A just reverence to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<hi>Theologues,</hi> asserting a total Cessation of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,
forbad me to immure my self in any such supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Asylum: and a praejudicate opinion of humane bodies
in this Animal State, allowed me not to <hi>Eurefuge</hi> my flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuating
mind in Physical Causes clubbing together, by an
Anomalous C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pulation, to engender so great an Heteroclite.
While thus lost in the Chaos of confused apprehensions, and
smarting under the <hi>Hirricano</hi> of my own tumultuary
thoughts, I hurry away to a very Worthy and Compassionate
Friend, who with a little deliberation runs through the
Diagnosticks of my Malady, pitieth my case, and after
some sharp Conflicts, with his own Modesty, affords the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief
of a Philosophical <hi>Elixir</hi> (for so I call the ensuing
Discourse) wholly transferring the right, which he had in
the happy results of his own contemplations, upon me.
Now (Sir!) what by much importunity I extorted from
him, for my own private satisfaction, I make bold to
tender the world a view of, under the Countenance and
Protection of your great Name, which is not only able to
secure it from the Critical Pharaphrases of an Envious Age,
but also to command it the Iustice of an unpraejudicate
perusal with such as know your worth. To my own grief,
I have found it much an Anodyne; or as a pleasant Lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labie
to my whimpering fancy; the issue of all hath been
rest: not knowing, but it may minister the like seasonable
relief to others, who have not Wit and Philosophy enough
to start any greater Objections, than my self; I judged it
worthy to travail the World. The confidence wherein I
seek to entitle you to the Patrociny of it, is no less than an
assurance of your benign Nature, singular Ingenuity, and
obliging goodness, which have begotten and pupil'd in me,
that perswasion, ever since I had the happiness and honour
<pb facs="tcp:60848:3"/>
to know you. Besides your clearer Intellectuals, and your
vast acquaintance with Natures Recondite Mysteries, made
it wholly incongruous to adopt any other the object of this
Dedication. I do still remember with the deepest resent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of a grateful heart, the happy distinction betwixt
parts Spermatique and parts Haematique, wherewith in pity
you relieved me, when anxiously enquiring, upon a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
account, after the <hi>principuum individuationis</hi> in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
bodies: a Notion (as to me it seems) more able to
rescue the Grand Article of our Creed concerning the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection
of the same individual Body from under suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,
and the many gross<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> absurdities, that some Phyloso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phasters,
and half-witted Atheists, would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain clogg it
with, than any offerture of Humane Reason, that I ever yet
had the happiness to meet with! Here (methinks I could
break forth into an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and congratulate my great,
though late felicity, that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) as
<hi>Origen,</hi> in one sense or other calls it) the Principle main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
a Numerical Identity in Humane Bodies, through
the whole series of Vicissitudes, Changes, and Sanctorian
Transmutations; betwixt the Vterine Formation, and the
Vltimate Reunition of soul and body, should, after many a
tedious search, and frustraneous disquisition, at last be
suggested by an hand able, in the maintenance of it, to
grapple with any Contradictor. In this you have satisfied not
only my reason, but my curiosity too; and therefore (Sir,)
so great is my opinion of your skill <hi>(absit omnis adu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationis
suspicio!)</hi> that whatever <hi>Dogma</hi> steps abroad
with your name written upon it, I could almost surrender
up my self as a perfect Captive to it (were I not a Man,
and which is more, a Protestant) upon an implicit faith!
But I have, I know not well how, digressed, and stept asid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
into things heterogeneous to the purport of this Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
Address. I therefore return to my ingenious friends
<pb facs="tcp:60848:4"/>
Discourse, upon which, were my judgement in these matters
worth any thing, I could afford to be liberal in the bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
of my Encomium's. But as 'tis shrouded under your
Patronage, so 'tis submitted to your Censure: (this I am
bold to do, knowing the Author, so much an Admirer of
you, that he cannot reluctate) whether more worthy your
pity or your approbation, none can better judge, than your
discerning and deserving self. Therefore such as it is, I
leave it to your Mercy; and beg leave to tell you, that I
should presently fall out with my self, did I not, upon
a faithful Scrutiny, find my self in the number of those
that really love and honour you.</p>
            <closer>Farewell.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60848:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OUR requests to take into conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
the so much fam'd prodigious
Twelve Moneths Abstinence of the
<hi>Derby-shire</hi> Maid, having the force of
commands, have produced these
lean results of the imposed Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
It cannot be unknown to a
Person of your large endowments and hot pursuit
after substantial Science, that both Divines, Medicks,
Historians, yea, Poets and Legenders have presented
the Learned World with a great variety of wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tinents, some whereof I shall briefly recite, as
well to reserve your sliding time for more Noble Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments,
as to manifest that our contemporary <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>se,</hi>
is not so sing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lar as some may imagine.</p>
            <p>Most certain it is, that the<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Acts 7. 22.</note> Learned <hi>Moses</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 34. 28.</note> fasted
40. dayes, and as many nights whilst he abode on the
Burning Mount; the great<note n="c" place="margin">1 King. 19. 8.</note> 
               <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jah,</hi> went as long in the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of a meal, and no less was the Fast of the
<note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 4. 2.</note>holy Jesus<note n="e" place="margin">August. in Epist. 86. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Sword<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Austin</hi> reports, that in his time one
survived 40. dayes fasting: but most strange is the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60848:5"/>
Story fathered on<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> l. 14. c. 45.</note> 
               <hi>Nicephorus</hi> of three Brethren af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted
by persecution into a Cave, where they
slept 373. years, as was known by the Coin they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
when they awaked. The Learned<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> l. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Fernelius</hi>
saith, he saw a pregnant Woman that lived two
moneths without meat or drink.<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. hist. p. 914.</note> 
               <hi>Zacutus Lusitanus</hi>
reports, that at <hi>Venice</hi> there lived a man that fasted
40. dayes, another there 46. dayes; and from <hi>Langi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>
and <hi>Forstius</hi> (two considerable Writers) another
full three years, and that with just stature, good ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit,
free countenance, and youthful<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wit. The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<note n="i" place="margin">Sennert. pract. l. 3. par. 1. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cl. 2. c. 2. de lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>â abstin. p. 383.</note>
               <hi>Sennertus</hi> is copious in such stories; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates
from <hi>Sigismundus</hi> and <hi>Citesius</hi> (a person he saith
worthy of credit) that the people of <hi>Lucomoria</hi> inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting
some Mountains in <hi>Moscovy</hi> do every year dye
in a sort, or rather sleep or freeze (like Froggs or
Swallows) on <hi>Novemb.</hi> 27. and so continue in that
rigid state till <hi>April</hi> 24. in which time they use no eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation,
save only that a tenuious humor distilling
from their nostrils is presently condens'd by the
ambient cold, much like to Isicles, by the which those
patent Pores are precluded, and the most endangered.
Brain fortified against the fatal assaults of brumal
extremities. The same <hi>Sennertus</hi> rehearses a Story of
a Virgin at <hi>Padua</hi> (from <hi>Viguntia</hi> Professor there)
who <hi>anno</hi> 1598. was afflicted with a Fever, then a
Tumor, then Arthritick pains, and pains in the Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle,
and whole abdomen, then with vomiting and
nauseating of food, till at last she could take no food
for two moneths, then after another fit of vomiting,
purging and bleeding, she fasted eight moneths, and
after a little use of food<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> she fasted two moneths
more. And to be short, he stories it of three persons
that fasted each two years, one three years, another
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60848:5"/>
four, one seven, another fifteen, another eighteen,
and one twenty, yea one twenty nine, another thirty,
another thirty six, and one forty years. Famous is the
story (perhaps fiction being Poetical) of<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ubi supra. Plutarch. in Symp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; l. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in orb: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Epimenides</hi>
(whose words St. <hi>Paul</hi> is thought to cite in his Epistle
to <hi>Titus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) whom some report to have
slept 17 years, some 77 years together; but enough
of story, those that are desirous to read more, are
referr'd to <hi>Marcellus Donat. l. 4. de med. hist. mirab.
c. 12. Schenk. l. 4. observ. Guaguinus, l. 3. hist. Franc.
Petrarch. l. 3. de mirabil. c. 22. Portius de hist. puellae
German. Uspergensis in Chron. Lentulus in hist. admir.
Apol. Baccius l. de vini nutritione. Bozius l. 11. c. 4. de
signis eccl. Fulgosius, l. 1. c. 6. Lessaeus, l. 9. hist. Scot.
Favorinus apud Gellium, l. 16. c.</hi> 3. and especially <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetus</hi>
that wrote a particular Tract to solve the <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena</hi>
of this Prodigy.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, it would be our ambition to advance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the same noble work, were it not our duty to
serve those awhile that blot all these stories with one
dash of unbelief: that pen certainly drops blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
that dares to rase the sacred Records; and that
uncharitableness which presumes to write <hi>falshood</hi>
upon all humane testimonies, they that assent to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
not confirmed by <hi>Autopsia</hi> are unfit to converse
in humane Societies; for how can I expect that any
body should believe me, whilest I my self will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
no body? 'tis an argument of an empty brain to
presume to comprehend all things, and thereupon to
reject those things from an existence in the world,
that have not their science in its intellectuals. Many
things forreign and strange may well be admitted on
good testimonies, sith, the most obvious objects are
scarce pervious to the most eagle-ey'd Philosopher;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60848:6"/>
witness the mistakes discovered by <hi>D. Cartes, Gassen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi>
&amp;c in <hi>Aristotle</hi> himself, one of the most sublimated
wits in all the Republick of Natural philosophy;
and likewise the spots in <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> those
mirrours in medicine, modestly pointed at by our
famous <hi>Harvey, Glisson, Willis,</hi> &amp;c. but further to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
these incredulous persons, 'tis affirmed that
some of these Abstinents have been<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> watch't by the
most wakefull eyes and jealous ears, to detect their
fraud, if guilty of any; as was that Maid that refus'd
all food except only water, for three years, by <hi>Bucol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi>
with whom she abode for twelve dayes, at
the command of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Emperour, so that
<hi>Apollonia Schrejerana</hi> was taken by the Senate of <hi>Bern,</hi>
and put into the Hospital of their Town, and there
watch'd till they were satisfied in the truth of her to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
abstinence.</p>
            <p>But enough to these that cut the knot to save the
labour of untying it; yet I may not step aside to
those in the contrary extream, that believe a century
of such reports with a faith almost as miraculous as
these miracles themselves, for so they seem to them:
but Sir, as 'tis humane infidelity to disbelieve all such
reports, because some are false, so 'tis superstitious cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
to believe all because some are true. Some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
as scant in their reading, as they are in their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels,
are ready to deem every thing strange to be a
monster, and every monster a miracle; true it is, the
fast of <hi>Moses, Elijah,</hi> and the Incarnate Word, was
miraculous, and possibly of some others; yet why
we should make all miracles, I understand not; for
what need have we now of miracles? Sith such su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural
operations<note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 22.</note> are for them that believe
not, not for them that believe, as witnesseth that<note n="n" place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 3.</note> coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestial
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60848:6"/>
Philosopher St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and thence we inferr,
Beings are not to be multiply'd without necessity.
Moreover, to what end are such miracles wrought?
certainly, the infinitely wise Operator labours not for
nought, therefore these Abstinents, if miraculous,
should confirm some Doctrine rejected, or refute some
Errour received, enfranchise some Saints oppressed,
subvert some Wickedness exalted, foretell some ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
events and issues of Providence to be
performed, or for some other end, at which miracles
have been usually level'd; but not a Gry of these
from most of our Abstinents; moreover, the fast of
our Blessed Saviour and his <hi>Prodromi</hi> procur'd not
the least detriment to their health, but 'tis otherwise
with most of these.</p>
            <p>Near of kin to these Miracle mongers are those
that suppose these pretended Fasters to be invisibly
fed by Angels; but 'tis incredible that such a favour
should be shewn to persons of no known sanctity, as
some of these (reported to be <hi>Ethnicks)</hi> were; more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,
either this food was visible, or invisible; if
visible, 'tis strange, that vigilant observers, and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
suspecters, could neither discover the ingress at
the fore-door, nor the excrementitious egress at the
back-door; but if 'twere invisible, then altogether
incongruous to our bodyes, and therefore miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous;
of which before. Neither is it of easie credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,
that food should be supply'd by Doemons pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessing
them; for we read of no foot-steps of such a
possession i'th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> story, and 'twould be strange if the
Devil should grow so modest as to content himself
with a single Trophy of a captivated rational; and as
strange, that a cloven foot should make such inrodes
and not leave a doubled yea redoubled impression.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60848:7"/>
Cousin-germanes to these are the presumers that the
Fasters are dead, and acted by Daemons; but this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
is also incongruous not only to their transmigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
from feeding to fasting without any shew of a
dissolution, but also to their regress from fasting to
feeding, (as it hapned to some of these) and health
again.</p>
            <p>And as for the admirers of occult Philosophy who
resolve these phrases into the effects of occult qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,
we only repose, that though an antipathy to
this or that food, and possibly to all food, may cause
abstinence, yet without food I cannot understand
how it gives sustenance; but others attribute all this
to the influence of coelestial bodies, whose operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
I deny not to be great on sublunary wights, yet
'tis not imaginable that this universal cause diffusing
its energy so promiscuously, should now and then in
a Century, here and there in a Countrey produce
such stupendious effects, without some universal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration
and predisposition of Bodies to determine
its general efficiency to the production of such a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy;
but as the former affect darkness, and these
an invisible light, we leave them to their retirements,
whilest we hunt the more perceptible prints of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
progress in these anomalous productions.</p>
            <p>By this time, Sir, I hope you'l grant that the old
inconvenient and tottering building is in a measure
demolish'd, the rubbish removed, and the ground
cleared; let us now propound the necessities and
conveniencies, the ends and uses by our new building
to be supply'd and attained, and then we'll fall to
the architecture it self; I mean, let us consider, what
the defect of aliment doth require for the support of
humane life. 1. The Natural Evacuations by Urine,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60848:7"/>
Stool, Salivation, Terms, and Transpiration, are so
lavish, that without reparation by feeding it seems
impossible to avoid a sudden dissolution. 2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>, How
shall natural heat be preserved from extinction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
a constant feeding on the radical moysture? and
how shall this Oleaginous humour be secur'd from
a nimble consumption, if it receive not additions
from frequent feeding? 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, How shall Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
be continued in the blood without new addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
of Chyle? and how shall Chyle be added, if
no food received? 4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, How shall there be a supply
of vital spirits, and consequently of animal, without
food and fermentation? 5<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, How can life consist
without sleep? and how shall we attain sleep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
ascending fumes to the brain from ingested
food?</p>
            <p>For a foundation I shall premise a few severals;
1. The long finger of powerfull Providence is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly
to be observ'd in the production of these
wonderfull effects; though these be not advanc'd
to the Zenith of divine Miracles, wrought by the
immediate hand of Omnipotency, yet the first cause
must be acknowledg'd in the proportioning, marshal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
dividing, uniting and actuating of concurrent
subordinate second causes for such Heteroclite pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions;
<hi>Plato</hi> himself could say, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and
the admirable D. <hi>Willis</hi> acknowledges, that Natures
Parent orders natural<note n="o" place="margin">Si hujusmodi limitatiosis causa inquira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imus, quod naturae pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers pos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> primoge to cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ta lem spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itus salis &amp; s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris copiam quae pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> eadis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times corporum stam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ibus, se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>camenti s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ret. <hi>Willes de ferment. p.</hi> 48. 49</note> Principles as to their quantity
and mixture, and consequently as to their opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>2. 'Tis very evident that when higher causes shall
disjoyn what Nature usually conjoyneth, and <hi>vice
versâ,</hi> and exalt one Principle and depress another,
then very astonishing results appear upon the stage
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60848:8"/>
of humane bodies; such is the stupendious voracity
of some <hi>Helluo's,</hi> the monstrous digestion of your <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thophagi,</hi>
the strange metamorphosis of your sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neans
into midnight melancholy, and of lucid intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuals
into piceous mopishness, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Now to supply the defect of food in its most
usefull restauration of what by daily Evacuations
the body is depriv'd of; as I need not compute the
vast expence of the Microcosme by stool, urine, spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
and terms, these being vulgarly known, so nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of the transcendent loss by transpiration, rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned
by<note n="p" place="margin">Sanctor. de staticá medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a.</note> 
               <hi>Sanctorius</hi> to preponderate all the rest;
all which exact constant additions to be made by
aliment, without which the body would quickly be
depopulated. But 1. let it be considered, that this
person (as 'tis most credibly reported) emptyes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
by urine or stool; and 'tis probable next to
nothing by salivation or transpiration, not by sali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
through a considerable defect of drinks; nor
by transpiration, because wanting food there's a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial
defect of fermentation in the blood, and thence
of natural heat, and so by the coldness of the parts
the pores are precluded, and the diaphoresis impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;
whence it will follow, that where the parts are
duely warm, and the pores patent, there the more
active principles are apt to take flight, yet where the
parts are cold, and the pores cork'd up, there 'tis
otherwise; as generous Wines and subtile spirits left
in open Vessels, will quickly bid adieu to their more
volatile and brisk Principles; yet if shut up in safe
Vessels, these Fugitives are imprisoned and kept to
their daily offices: the same is verifi'd ina queous
humours, which (our Kitchens as well as Laborato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
experiment) quickly evaporate through intense
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60848:8"/>
subjacent heats, but not without, and so 'tis here.
Thus these plentifull evacuations being suppressed,
restauration by food is rendred less necessary. Yet
lest you should dread from this hypothesis a suffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating
mass of excrementitious humours to assault the
heart, &amp;c. I therefore subjoyn, that a defect of nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritious
assumptions must needs precede a defect of
humours: moreover, the blood commands much of
these remaining humours for its own chariot-use;
neither may it seem dissonant to reason that the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle
and some of the intestines are us'd as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle
of the more tartarous and terrestrial faecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies;
as Embryo's though they receive large quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities
of liquid nutriment, yet there's seldom observ'd
the least excretion by the fundament, but a reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of a quantity of excrementitious terrestreities
in the intestines during their whole abode in their
maternal cells; likewise in fermenting liquours the
more active principles do precipitate the more slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gish
to the bottoms, chinks and walls of their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents;
further it cannot be denyed, that by expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
there is a considerable evacuation, as appears
both by the heat of our breath, and its moisture,
which is discovered by the reception of it into any
concavous Body. But 2. admit that there is some
waste either by salivation or transpiration, yet these
being small, produce only a lingring consumption,
which doth often consist for many years with a decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
life: such as our Virgins is.</p>
            <p>2. How shall natural heat be preserved, if not fed
by Oyl, continually supply'd and renew'd by aliment?
There are Sir, divers opininos touching humane ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles,
and therefore it highly concerns us to proceed
cautiously; it cannot be deny'd that there is a poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60848:9"/>
heat more or less in all humane bodyes, which is
the <hi>calor mixti,</hi> remaining when we are dead and key-cold;
such as is the heat of Sulphur, Arsenick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
(though in a great allay) this appears from chymical
operations on mans blood, by which 'tis forc'd to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
its endowments with spirits and volatile
Salts in great quantities, and some Sulphur also. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
it must be granted, that there is an actual heat
abiding in us whilest we live, and somewhile after
death; this is obvious to the sence of feeling it self:
this is the heat (as I conceive) joyn'd with the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenite
humour to which <hi>Aristotle</hi> ascribes life it
self. But yet Sir, I am somewhat doubtfull, whether
this heat be properly cal'd <hi>calor vivens,</hi> though the
great<note n="q" place="margin">River. instit. med. l. 1. Sect. 4. c. 3. de ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lido innato. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Arist. de respir.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Riverius</hi> term it so; or an immediate cause of
life, though an <hi>Aristotle</hi> himself pronounce it so: For
certainly Holy Writ ascribes life to the blood, <hi>the
blood is the life thereof:</hi> and death to a dissolution of
the <hi>compositum, the body returns to the dust, and the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
to God that gave it.</hi> But of this dissolution (I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose)
the soul is not ordinarily the cause, but the
body; and what part of the body may more justly
be challenged to be the Parent (if I may so phrase it)
of death, than the blood, which is in a famous sense
the parent of life? So then,<note n="r" place="margin">Willis de mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis coavuls. <hi>p.</hi> 175. Netdham de form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctu, <hi>p.</hi> 138. Ioweri dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribae, <hi>p.</hi> 115. Ferael. de ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. l. 2. c. 7.</note> most killing distempers
must arise from the excessive multiplication, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption
or depravation of the blood, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious
effects thereof; yet mistake me not, this hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
not other parts of the body, bowels and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours
to be often peccant, as undoubtedly they are
by infecting the blood, and receiving infections mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bifick
from it. Moreover, this heat continues some
hours without life, even after the dissolution;
and as it is without life, so is life often found
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60848:9"/>
without it, as not only in some Vegetables, as Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuce,
Hemlock, Cucumbers, &amp;c. but in Animals,
as Frogs and Fish, which are said to be actually cold,
and the Salamander, reputed cold in a high degree.
This heat may possibly be but the effect of matter
and motion, <hi>i. e.</hi> of the blood, or before it of the
seed impregnated with active principles, which
through their activity and heterogeneity suffer mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
collisions, or fermentations, whence ebullition,
and thence this heat, which is by circulation not only
promoted, but also convey'd to all parts of the
body, and by the same causes preserved, which pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly
may prove the summe of<note n="s" place="margin">Riverius ubi supra.</note> 
               <hi>Riverius</hi>'s implanted
and influent heat. These things presupposed, 'twill
not be impossible to guess that this heat is no such
Coelestial fire, as the most famous <hi>Fernelius</hi> would
have it, but only the igneous result of the combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
and commotions of the most active elementa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
Principles; and if there be any other heat, it may
prove to be (according to the conjecture of great
<hi>Riverius)</hi> the product of the immateriate soul; but
of that I understand little, only this is unquestion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
that the caelestial Soul chooseth for its more
immediate organs, the most subtiliated, spirituous,
and active parts of matter, such as the vital
and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
spirits, and the heat before mentioned, which
seems to be of the same Genius, and all but the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick
productions of various fermentations, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colations
and distillations in the humane Engine:
Wherefore, I shall crave leave to dismiss this fire till
we come to discourse of Fermentations.</p>
            <p>And so I pass on the next flame, which is the
<hi>Biolychnium,</hi> or the actual flame of the blood kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
in the heart, asserted both by Antients and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derns
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60848:10"/>
of astonishing titles, and tremendous venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
which devouring flame, if once kindled, will
quickly depredate all the oleaginous aliment, if not
renewed by frequent and plentifull assumptions; but,
therefore 'tis greatly suspected to have no existence
in our bodyes, because in these Jejunants it must
needs extinguish for want of Sulphureous supplyes,
and produce death to those that have liv'd long
enough to help to entombe it. 'Tis strange to me,
that provident Nature should require such vast sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes
both of meat and drink, out of which to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract
a small quantity nutritious juice; which with
divers Ferments, Colatures, Emunctories, and rapid
motions, it endeavours to exalt and defecate, and
yet after all should expose what she hath attain'd of
purity and activity, and consequently of noblest use
by her unparallel'd artifices, cost and toil, to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provident
disposal of wastfull flames; for indeed
flames are great wasters, as appears in the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Balsom of Sugar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> no less wonderfull
it is that a flame should continually burn in the heart,
and yet the fleshy walls thereof not boiled, roasted,
nor so much as a fuliginous or cineritious colour im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.
But lest Sir, you should be confident that
this perennial slame scorns an extinction by these
few drops, I therefore commend to your observation
those numerous and plentifull buckets that are poured
thereupon by the dexterous hand of the very learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and<note n="t" place="margin">Needham de format. foetu. <hi>p. 129, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> candid Dr. <hi>Needham.</hi> But yet lest you should
be so far praepossessed by the determinations of vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
antiquity, as to reject this new Doctrine, and
avowedly maintain this unseen fire, I shall therefore
adde: 1. That this Flame can be but small through
the defect of bodily exercise, and freer ventilations,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60848:10"/>
(these fasters being mostly close Prisoners) as also of
strong fermentations; therefore the less the Lamp,
the less Oyl will sustain it. 2. Through the defect
of heat the pores are bolted, and transpiration re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained,
whence a scarce credible quantity of moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture
is retained, which returning both by Veins and
Lymphaticks, gives no contemptible quantity of food
to this fire. 3. Through the restraint of Transpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
the igneous particles are secur'd from their
excursions, to the great increase of intestine heat;
for in feeders the loss of transpiration often kindles
in the blood a feaverish fire. 4. The Air (as impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated
sometimes especially) entring by the mouth,
the nose, and pores in parts passing the various
concoctions, may be converted into a humour not
altogether inept to preserve the lingring life of this
dying flame. 5. In pituitous bodies the abundance
of flegme through the various concoctions which it
undergoes in the body, may become usefull in the
room of more proper aliment to this analogous Lamp
in its Table-supplyes; which flegme though some
reject as excrementitious, yet I suppose they do it
only when consideration is from home, of its useful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
in the mastication of our food, wherein (as
some say) lyes the first concoction; at least therein
lyes the main preparation for the grand concoction
in the ventricle; the constant mixture of our food
with our spittle in the Jaw-mill, may enforce some
considering men to think, that 'tis nearer of kin to
our natural moisture than hath been formerly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged.
6. The colliquation of the parts of
these emaciated bodies may yield Oyl to these Lamps;
as 'tis usually affirmed in Hectick feavers; besides, if
fire be nothing but an innumerable host of sulphurous
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60848:11"/>
atomes breaking the Prisons of their former com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions
with other heterogeneities,<note n="u" place="margin">Willis de Fermeat, <hi>p.</hi> 66.</note> then certainly
all fire is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for nothing of that Sulphur re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,
it leaves only the heterogenious Principles,
with which it was combin'd. 7. 'Tis probable that
the moisture of these jejune bodies is much not only
condens'd by their cold, but also loaded with ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restreities
through the non-reception of aliment im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>egnated
with active Principles; whereby 'tis ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
more durable in this flame. As Oyls the more
impure, thick, and clammy they are, the less fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
they burn, but the more tenuious and spirituous,
the more nimbly do they flame and expeditiously
consume. As my face and hair did sadly experiment
upon the unexpected and suddain conflagration of a
quantity of the Oyl of Turpentine, as I not long since
drew it from the fire; I dare say, the Turpentine it
self would not, or rather could not have serv'd me so.
8. This moisture being drawn from more jejune Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
(as air, flegme, and lympha)<note n="x" place="margin">Willis de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>br. <hi>p.</hi> 103.</note> is the less impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated
with intro-sulphurous particles, and therefore
less inflamable;<note place="margin">Willis de Fer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 8 66. French's Art of Distillation, <hi>p.</hi> 148.</note> as in oligophorous Wines, where the
spirit and sulphur are greatly exhaled, and with a
quality abundantly dilated, there fire slowly burns.
9. 'Tis probable, that the crasis of these bodies is so
altered by the predominancy of fixed Salts not due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
actuated by powerfull fermentations,<note place="margin">Ioh. Baptist. Porta. Card. de sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitate.</note> that they
much retard the consumption of Oyl by this vital
fire;<note place="margin">Ludovic. Vives i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> l. 21. c. 6. de Civitat. Dei Augustin.</note> as if Quicklime, Soap, or other saline concretes
be added to Wax or Tallow, they will (say Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists)
make a candle of far greater duration than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary.<note place="margin">Guido Panci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollus.</note>
Strange is that story of St. <hi>Austine,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports
a Lamp to be found in the Temple of <hi>Venus,</hi>
that no storms could extinguish. Yet much more
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60848:11"/>
strange was that Torch, reported to have burnt
1550 years in the Tomb of <hi>Tullia, Cicero's</hi> daughter,
which being expos'd to the Air, by the opening of
the Tomb, was quickly extinguish'd: Now if our
humours should chance to attain the disposition of
these antient Oyls, they might supply the <hi>Byolychni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi>
long enough. 10. Or if these fixed Salts should
attain fluidity, as 'tis probable they have done, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
some of these Abstinents were of melancholick
complexions,<note place="margin">Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ert. pract. l. 3. pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 1. Sect. 2. de lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ga absti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tià.</note> then the sulphurous parts of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours
would be so fettered and oppressed thereby,
that they could not so quickly burst from under the
yoke into violent flames, but by degrees and leisu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably
as they could disentangle themselves; from
whence will arise a more durable though less force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
fire. Lastly, it seems probable, that extraneous
particles of fire may be convey'd into a body, and
therein lodged, which shall afterwards cause heats to
kindle therein. That igneous particles pass from one
body to another seems a matter of daily experience:
for 'tis not easie to demonstrate how our bodies are
warm'd by their approach to the fire, if there be not
fiery effluviums from the burning matter that enter
our bodyes; and that these fiery atomes thus lodg'd
in a foreign body, may afterwards by water, air, or
the like, break forth into a considerable heat, is very
imaginable; as in Quick-lime, which before 'tis burnt
is not at all subject to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mbustions by air or water;
but when it hath endured the Kill-fire, then 'tis rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily
kindled by the addition of almost any humidity;
which humidities may not be supposed directly to
contribute to the kindling of the atomes, but to the
dissolving of the Concrete, and thereby the disen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangling
of the Atomes, whereupon they fly out into a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60848:12"/>
considerable heat; like whereunto is that Powder,
boasted by Chymists, to take flame in your hand by
the only addition of Spittle.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Art of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Thus Sir, having ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd
a slender repast for your antique lamp, I crave
leave to attend the more modern Hypothesis of fam'd
fermentation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, How shall Fermentation be continued in
the blood without the addition of chyle? and how can
chyle be added without food assumed?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> It is the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
of ingenuous <hi>Henshavius</hi> that fermentation is
caused by the addition of chyle to the blood in the
heart, like that of Wine by the adding of Must, from
whence doth arise (he saith) a necessity of frequent
feeding:<note place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. de form. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> p. 132. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> de s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. p. 113.</note> which the excellent D. <hi>Needham</hi> seems much
to approve: and both the incomparable <hi>Willis</hi> and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious
<hi>Castle</hi> cite <hi>Hogeland</hi> for ascribing heat to a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation
in the heart,<note place="margin">Cast<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'s Chym. Gal. p. 81, 82.</note> like to that which happens up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the pouring of Spirit of Nitre on Butter of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony.
<hi>R.</hi> Now Sir, to help us out at this dead lift al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so,
I shall take notice of the several opinions of the
Learned touching the causes of fermentation.
1. There is a ferment placed in the heart it self by
the great <hi>Willis</hi> and his <hi>Hypaspistes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lis de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. p. 24, 25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 101, 102, 113.</note> the dexterous ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomist
Dr. <hi>Lower,</hi> with Dr. <hi>Castle,</hi> and other renowned
Assertors of fermentation. This Sir would serve us
eximiously,<note place="margin">Low<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Diatr. p. 121, 124. Castle's Chym. Gal. p. 81, 82.</note> to supply the defect of new chyle, if it
were but sufficiently evinced; but I must confess in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuously
though (as 'tis not unknown to you)
I have laboured to advance the antique glory of
the heart, yet I cannot satisfie my self, though I
would, that there is any such implanted ferment
therein; for I find not this ferment confirmed
by any experiment, or other sufficient evidence, but
<hi>(absit invidia verbo)</hi> too precariously asserted: nor
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60848:12"/>
any necessity assigned for such a ferment; the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
of fermentation being sufficiently demonstrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
without it; and though the honour ascribed to
the heart may seem to require it, yet I cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
of conferring honours, which infer a necessity
of multiplying Beings above what the <hi>opus</hi> and <hi>usus</hi> of
Nature createth. Neither can I conceive where
this ferment should be nested; it must be either in
the walls of the heart, or in the chambers thereof;
in the walls (saith Dr. <hi>Castle</hi> from <hi>Severinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Danus,</hi>
D. <hi>Cartes</hi> and <hi>Hogeland)</hi> are mechanick spirits, semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
salts or ferments; but yet <hi>(pace tanti viri)</hi> the
heart by its carnous fibres, membranes, colour and
consistence seems to be but a muscle, as our worthy
Dr. <hi>Needham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. foet. 132.</note> and acute <hi>Steno</hi> affirm; and if so, how
a ferment should be there generated any otherwise
than in other muscles,<note place="margin">Ste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o de Muse. &amp; Gland.</note> I do not understand; it hath not
the Parenchyma of the Liver, Spleen, or other parts
which are colatures to the blood, whereby they ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily
separate, and having separated retain what may
conduce to constitute ferments; but the walls of the
heart seem only like other muscles to receive blood
for their own private use, but none for a publick
stock. Moreover, if there were such a salt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
it is a wonder it doth not discolour the ruti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
fibres; as the salt in the Spleen manifestly
doth, but leave it of the same hieu with other non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fermenting
muscles; neither are there any cavities
within these walls capacious enough to contain these
mechanick spirits for publick offices; nay it is
observable that the heart is more firm, fast, hard,
and less stor'd with porosities than other muscles:
neither in the auricles, or venticles can these spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
keep quiet possession, by reason of that impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
torrent which many times in every minute
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60848:13"/>
washeth both flores and walls; and though these ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities
have their cellars, yet by the so frequent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strictions
of the omnimodous fibres causing the systole,
there's not only a mixture of the blood at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom
with that on the top, but also a violent extru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
of both made in the same pulsation: neither
in dissections is there any considerable difference
found betwixt that in the heart, and that in the
veins, as famous <hi>Harvey</hi> observeth. Yet with a <hi>non
obstante</hi> to these premises I must tell you, I opine
that fermentation may not abusively be ascribed to
the mechanick structure and operations of the heart,
though not enriched with an innate ferment, of
which hereafter more seasonably.</p>
            <p>2. It is not unknown that several liquors are self-sufficient
to command a fermentation, and that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective;
as Wine, Cyder, with other like spirito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulphuro-saline-fluids,
as also fruits of a more crass
consistence, as Apples, Pears, Plumbs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereof
many are advanced, by lying, to a greater perfection
after pull'd from their Mothers Breast; and it is at
least a violent presumption that the blood confected
by such self-fermenting bodies, and they exalted
greatly by the various additional concoctions, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colations,
and (as it were) distillations in the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendently
exquisite, and proto-laboratories of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
bodies is crown'd with the same Diadem of
self-fermenting principles: and indeed an ordinary
analysis of blood according to the rules of Pyrotech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
will discover all those principles of Spirit, Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur,
Salt, Water and Earth, lodg'd in its embraces
which are sufficient to elaborate fermentations:
which is further confirm'd in that when some of the
innate fermenting principles, as suppose Salts begin
to languish, several artificial ferments prove highly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60848:13"/>
useful;<note place="margin">De ferm.</note> under this notion (saith the sagacious <hi>Will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>)</hi>
are the fixed Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts of Vegetables, Chalybeats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of
such Soveraign efficacy.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, after various disquisitions touching the
use of the Spleen, some exalting it to the honour of
sanguifying for the lower belly, others depressing
it to the vile use of a sink, 'tis now by many upon
consideration of its colour, site, and vessels resolv'd
to be a colature, wherein the more black and fecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
juice is sever'd from the blood, and being there
reserved it becomes a ferment to the scarle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> liquor;
even as a small parcel of dough reserv'd in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aline
condiment grows acid, and so arrives to the dignity
of a levain, or ferment to the new farinaceous mass.
The principles which in this bowell are supposed to
be regent, are salino terrestrial, which by over long
abode attain fluidity, and so become acetous, like
Spirit of Vitrioll, Nitre, and of other saline con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes,
and that which renders this the more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable,
are the sowre belchings of hypochondriack
persons, the whiteness of their tongues, the soreness
of their throats, the excess of their appetite, and the
emaciating of their bodies: all which seem to proceed
from a preternatural acidity: and <hi>vice versa,</hi> when
the Spleen hath lost its ferment, then the blood
grows too insipid as appears in Cachexys, Ascites,
Tympanites, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> These things premised, 'twill be
no difficulty to prove that the blood is fermented
by the Spleen: 'tis but very lately that I added
Spirit of Vitrioll to a small quantity of the recent
blood of a Patient, which caus'd a visible fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and such a coagulation that it became almost
of the colour and consistence of our table Mustard,
only there remain'd some perfect black parts, but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60848:14"/>
no red ones: from whence I conjecture, that 'tis an
acid humour which causes such a black s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>diment in
the urine of many hypochondriack persons, and
that the same humour it is that coagulates the blood
often, if not alwayes, and renders it so unapt for
circulation: wherefore by the way, I would offer
it to your consideration, whether that sort of Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
and Melancholy which is rooted in blood more
than sufficiently hot, florid, and fluid (as oft-times
they are) can ascribe its origination to a meer acidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
or to fluid Salts: and consequently whether it
be not a misapplication of the nitrosulphurous Plants
which renders them of late suspected of impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy?
for to what end should these Plants be given
to those persons whose blood exceeds with salt and
sulphur already? yet in the colder more chachecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
Sorts of Scurvy and Melancholy nothing possibly
may be found more proper; for 'tis well known
that fixed salts and fluid salts, or (which is the same
thing) acid spirits do highly ferment, and cause a
considerable heat; as lately discover'd it self to me
in the preparation of Tartarus Vitriolatus, whence
I further conjecture that those preparations of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lybs,
Corall and other saline concretes which rob
them of their salts, or (which is the same thing)
that glut them with acidities so plentifully as to leave
no capacity to receive more acids do spil them <hi>eo
nomine</hi> of their fermenting vertue. But lest I
should seem to transgress whilst I intend searcely to
digress, I return to remind you that you have a
third ferment which in these Abstinents is presume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
to be highly useful, for several of them (not
to say all) were Spleneticks before they were Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinents.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60848:14"/>
Fourthly, 'Tis probable that the seminal humours
in these Virgins may by a long abode in their vessels
grow acid, and thereby supply the blood with a
more than ordinary ferment. Here are two things
supposed, the first is that the seed is impregnated
with salt, and that is prov'd by the many arguments
of the Philosophical Dr. <hi>Ente,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the other is that the
seed by its principles may elaborate the blood, this
is evident in females whose seed being grown fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundate
and vegete; it so levains the blood, that
except it purge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by menstrual terms it exposes
to innumerable diseases; but much more manifest in
men by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruption of their Beards, the greatning
of their voice, the heating of their blood, essemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
desires, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> These things being evidently so,
'twill much strengthen our Hypothesis to observe
that most of these Damosels fall to this abstinence
between the age of fourteen and twenty years when
the seed hath so fermented the blood, that various
distempers will probably ensue without due evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations;
except in our case, wherein through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
of fermenting food we are enabled to bear the
excess of these so much the better.</p>
            <p>Fifthy, There are several other innate ferments
placed by nature in humane bodies, as the Learned te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie,<note place="margin">De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
as that ascrib'd by Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> to the brain, for the
freeing the spirits from the entanlemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of other
principles to which they were married whilst they
abode in the blood, that so the brains distilla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion
might proceed the more prosperously; likewise
that in the reins, which is like Runnet to Milk, to
precipitate the serosities, that the ureters may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate
them as useless, burdensome excrements.
There are many more assign'd, yea more than can
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60848:15"/>
be numbred,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. c. 20. p. 139.</note> if Dr. <hi>Willis's</hi> Doctrine be true of a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation
through the habit of the body, caused by
the concurrence of arterial blood and nervous juice;
but these I lightly pass over, because I conceive they
are not immediately intended for the elaborating of
the bloody mass; yet I may not forget them, because
working upon the blood, 'tis not to be doubted but
the veins derive somewhat of their vertue with the
retrieved blood.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, But to approach yet nearer to our mark,
I affirm that though there be no edibles received, yet
it follows not that there's no sort of new chyle to
renew the bloods fermentation: for First, In these
cold bodies there must of necessity be a far greater
quantity <hi>(consideratis considerandis)</hi> of pituitous
humours than ordinary: for if transpiration be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed
to our bodies but a very small time, what a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundance
of flegm doth presently oppress us: which
flegm being led into the mouth by a great variety of
salivating ducts, and thence conveyed into the Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle
may take off the acidity, the edge of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite,
by which they tolerate their abstinence with
the greater patience; and also suffer a sorry conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
which is much advanc'd by the attendance of
all the concoctive forces to subact this sluggish mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
which is other bodies are variously diverted by
the great variety of food frequently admitted.
Secondly, 'Tis probable that some of these Fasters
were more than ordinarily addicted to flegm before
their abstinence, which is usual with those whose
concoctions are low, and with these 'tis more than
an even lay they were not very high, which must needs
be augmented by the defect of urine and stool, which
if granted, adds somewhat to our purpose. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60848:15"/>
The air receiv'd continually into the Stomach by
the Mouth and Nose, and also into the blood more
directly, though sparingly by the pores, and virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
if not formally by the Lungs, may contribute
much to this humour, but more to the fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the blood: that the air is impregnated with
Salts,<note place="margin">Apolog. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. p. 93.</note> the Learned Dr. <hi>Ente</hi> affirms and ascribes vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
as also the production of various animals
thereunto, as the worthy <hi>Willis</hi> doth frost and ice:
and 'tis asserted by Chymists that Caput Mortuum's
lixivated, if expos'd to the open air for a good
space they shall re-attain their saline principle: and
that salts cause fermentation in the blood, hath
been already noted. Yet one step further I
may advance upon good ground, and that is,
these salts may much renew the ferment of the
stomach also in lieu of other condiments.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over
the Liver being an ample bowell, instructed
with a great variety of vessels, enrich'd with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
traffique from most of the Corporations in
the Microcosm, so curious in its elections and colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
of the sulphuro-saline commodities so diligent
in reconding them in a peculiar Cell, and thence
transmitting them to the intestines upon all occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
these severals, I say, considered, it may be rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally
inferr'd, that 'tis not only helpful to the guts
in their excretions, but also in their fermentations,
whereby the chyle is rendred not only more fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiscible
in the blood, but also more fermentesce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t
thereunto. Yet Sir, lest this lean meat should not satisfie
your more delicate pallat, I must advertise you, that
the blood in these persons must needs be sparing, and
therefore the lesser chyle may ferment it, especially
considering that their fermentations are but small, as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60848:16"/>
appears by the smalness of their heat, and therefore
pray do your self the right, not to expect an account
of robust ones.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, The heart it self contributes much to
this fermentation. 'Tis acknowledged by all that
the circulation of the blood being a rapid motion
through the indefatigable pulsation of the heart adds
much to the fermentation; we see that motion
given to Wine, Ale, Cyder, or Cream of Milk though
sufficiently fermented, will yet without a new fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
give a new fermentation. But Sir, lest you
should mistake me when I stumbled at an innate fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
in the heart, and yet stood upon't that fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
may be ascribed thereto, let me unbosome my
self, that you may see what the heart contributes
thereunto. First, The heart is as it were a cistern in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
which the bloody veins, milky veins, and water
veins, or lymphaeducts by mutual consent deposite
their multiform juices. Secondly, It hath the force
of a Mill by its quaquaverse fibres continually busied
in their constrictions and dilatations to grind and
make small the more crassy particles of the juices.
Thirdly, Of a Mortar wherein the more exact mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of these different juices is highly promoted.
Fourthly, Of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inne expelling the blood suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
subacted, and then to the further execution of
its Offices, but too too troublesome; and by the way,
the burden of the blood may be one cause of its pulsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
for 'tis said, if a live heart be taken out of the
body, the prick of a Pin will renew its pulsation.
Fifthly, Of a Pump to give motion and according to
the sanguiterious ducts to the several parts distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution
of this juice adapted to nutrition.<note place="margin">Walaeus i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Meth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Sixthly, Of
a Loom wherein the blood is fermented. Seventhly, Of a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60848:16"/>
kind of Philosophical Furnace, wherein a spirital <hi>Bio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lychnium</hi>
is kindled, I intend only a heat perchance
caused only by the motion and fermentation afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said.
Eighthly, Of a Pelican to rarifie and exalt the
vital spirits. Ninthly, of an Alimbeck (not vulgar)
whereby the spirits receive a kinde of separation
(though yet they run with the blood) which being
condensed in the Refrigeratory of the habit of the
body (as the learned <hi>Walaeus</hi> expresseth it) are the
more easily subject to the brains Philtration, and the
nerves preservation. Tenthly, of a potential Philtre,
whereby there's made such a fegregation of homoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous
particles into their proper classes, as renders
the blood much more obedient to the colatures, and
emunctories of the body; as runnet in the milk po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentially
separates the whey, and prepares it for an
actual separation by the sieve; and in chymical pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations
the acid liquor, or diluteing large quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of weakning water, provoke a kinde of fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
whereby the suspended atomes in the strong
Menstruums are precipitated, and so prepa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red for a
more facile separation: so that indeed all the Engines
in Natures shop depend mainly upon the right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e,
texture, and operation of the heart. From which it
seems apparent to me (which yet I submit to clearer
minds) that the heart is further serviceable to fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation,
and other offices of Nature, than meerly
Pump-like to conciliate motion: which may be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
confirmed by the site of the heart in the centre
of the body, as also by it's firmest muniments by which
'tis garrison'd on its back by the spine, on its face
by the sternum, on its sides by the ribs, under its feet
by the diaphragme, and over its head by the canopy
of the pyramidall thorax, and lastly by its bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>-coat
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60848:17"/>
the Pericardium; and which is not nothing, the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
fabrick with various camerations, the ret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>form
fibres and various passages, the uniform procedure of
Nature in the formation of the hearts of Animals,
whilest often it sports it self in the building of other
parts, and its primogeniture, as appears by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>vesi-cula palpitans</hi> first formed in Egges (according to
the renowned <hi>Harvey)</hi> the rudiment of the heart, and
the bloods constant flux and reflux to and from the
heart, even then when the liver and lungs (though
famous bowels) are pass'd by unsaluted in the circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
of Embryo's; as also Natures great care to
supply the defective passages of those <hi>viscera</hi> by <hi>fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramen
ovale</hi> in the septum of the heart, lest the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course
of the blood with the heart should be impeded,
which hole is yet afterwards precluded when the Infant
is midwiv'd into a new World; much of this curiosity
of Nature about the heart, seems utterly unnecessary,
if it serv'd only for motion; but we are sure that
God and Nature do nothing frustraneously. Neither
am I yet satisfied, that the whole of the bloods mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
is to be ascribed to the hearts pulsation; for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringius</hi>
affirms that in live dissections the blood strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
circulates a long time after the left ventricle hath
lost its pulse; yea though the heart be taken out,
yet presently is not the motion of the blood destroy'd;
which seems to be confirm'd by the experiment upon
Frogs, which leap so nimbly, and swim so freely after
their hearts are exempted, that they cannot be known
from unwounded Frogs that exercise in their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;
the story whereof that most dexterous Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist
D. <hi>Needham</hi> hath published;<note place="margin">De format. foetu<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> moreover, if a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gature
be apply'd to a Vein or Artery, whereby the
pulse is intercepted with the undulation of the blood
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60848:17"/>
also, yet the blood beyond the bond runs its course
towards the heart; and which is so much the more
strange, because 'tis the motion of a heavy body
contrary to its natural tendency, upward. Moreover,
if the pulse of the heart were the only cause of the
motion of the blood, why then is not the menstrual
blood thrust into other parts as well as into the ute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine?
sith the other parts equally with these receive
the constant force of the hearts even pulsations and
impartial distributions; likewise we see that the ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
spirits in the nerves, with their juice, the Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha
in its ducts, the Chyle in its thoracicks, the Seed
in its seminals, the Urine in the ureters, and the
Flegme in its pituitary Vessels are all in motion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the force of any such Engine to give the origen
thereto. Whereupon I am apt to conjecture, that
Nature hath furnished several parts with an attractive
power, the blood with fermentation, and several
Vessels with a kinde of Vermicular motion of their
own (no doubt excited by the nerves) the Porta with
Asinus in the Liver, which serves for a Pump, and
the Cava (or one part it) with a pulsifick energy
(by which blood is thrust into the right ventricle, as
the learned <hi>Walaeus</hi> asserts) by which the motion of
humours is promoted; and consequently that the
rareness of the structure, unweariedness of the pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations
of the heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are designed to some higher
ends, than meerly, and as such, to give motion, though
that it doth with an Emphasis.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, How can Spirits both vital and animal be
prepared and separated without food, and frequent
fermentations? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. I. Whether there be a flux of animal
spirits through the <hi>genus nervosum</hi> seems yet not fully
resolv'd; and if no flux then the waste is small, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60848:18"/>
a small reparation may supply a small waste; but I
confess, I understand not how Narcotick fumes, nor
redundant humours restagnating in the brain can
cause an Apoplexy, Epilepsie, Palsie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the whole
body, if there be no flux of spirits from the brain; nor
how the hurt from a Coach in the seventh Vertebre
of the back (mention'd by great <hi>Galen)</hi> could cause
a Palsey in three singers; nor why we anoint the
Vertebres of the back for Palseys in the extreme parts,
if there be no flux of spirits. 2. Supposing a flux
of animal spirits through the nervous systeme, yet
(according to the Doctrine of famous Dr. <hi>Wharton)</hi>
much of the nervous juice separated by the glandules,<note place="margin">De. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
is returned by the veins and Lymphaticks, and so not
lost, though ense<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bled by its peregrination; and more
yet deposited (according to Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> the great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former
of Physick) by the extremity of the nerves in
the habit of the body, is again retriv'd by the Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaticks,
which serving in our Abstinents little or
nothing to assimulation (only somewhat to the che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing
of the implanted spirits) is the more plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
return'd and so the loss (thus far forth) less con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable
than ordinary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. 'Tis apparent that there's
a decay of these spirits, as well as an obstruction in
most of these Abstinents, as witnesseth their great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability
to motion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. The fermentations mentioned
before, though small may contribute something to
the encrease of these spirits; for Chymists know
that there are few juices so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, so sterile, but by
the help of fermentation may yield a not contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
spirit. 5. Those spirits that pass from the brain
to the extremity of the body, and thence returned
as before by the Lymphaticks, and that more for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
and plentifully being reflected by the impervious
cold and constipated skin seem rather tyred than ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hausted,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60848:18"/>
which may by the small ferments afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned,
the contritions mixtions, and exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of the heart, and the perpetual motions of the
scarlet liquor be rarifi'd and volatiliz'd to do at a
dead lift further good service. 6. 'Tis notorious,
that sents do hugely affect the brain; as to instance
in Apoplexies, hysterical passions, and in some sort of
Syncopes and Cephalalgies common practice doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate;
so then if feeding animals perceive such
strange alterations by odoriferous exhalations (as of
<hi>Assa faetida, Galbanum, Verrucae Equinae,</hi> &amp;c. which
according to the prodigious invention of the most Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophical
Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> are able to restrain the most
violent explosions (like those of Gunpowder, than
which none more violent) of the Nitro-sulphurous
atomes with which in spasmodick distempers the ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous
juice is impregnated, (and by which it's reduc'd
to the greatest disorders) why may not these Absti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents
be reliev'd by such enriched fumes also?</p>
            <p>Fifthly,<note place="margin">Aristot. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. c. 3.</note> without sleep no long life, and without food
no sleep; for say the Ancients, sleep is the binding
up of the first Sensorium,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Galen. de sympt. caus. c. 8. &amp; de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. c. 4.</note> or common sence caused by
the food digesting in the stomach, elevating its fumes
to the brain, which there condensing stop the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages
of the animal spirits, whereby they are detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
from their just visitations, whence the senses are
disenabled for the execution of their offices. <hi>R.</hi> 1. 'Tis
not certain that sleep is absolutely necessary to life,
for we read of many that liv'd waking:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. de med. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. hist. p. 23, 24, 25. l. 5. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholog. l. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. cap. c. 16. l. de Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia.</note> 'Tis said
that <hi>Ramus</hi> studied Philosophy so uncessantly, that
he became blinde, or deaf, or both, through defect
of sleep. <hi>Bhasis</hi> watched so long at his study of
Physick till at last he could not sleep at all; likewise
a Doctor of the Law studyed so indefatigably, that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60848:19"/>
he never laid his eye-lids together for four months;
yet all recovered by the use of Hypnoticks. The
most inquisitive Galenist <hi>Fernelius</hi> reports a certain
man to have surviv'd 14 moneths waking. The grave
<hi>Heurnius</hi> relateth a story, from (he saith) a truly
learned man <hi>Ierom Montuus,</hi> of a Noble Matron that
lived 35 years without sleep, nor hurt thereby; and
of another that lived 10 years waking. <hi>Seneca</hi> reports
that <hi>Maecenas</hi> lived three years without sleep, and
at last was recovered by musick. 2. But I affirm not
that our Jejunants are Vigilants, and therefore adde,
that though these persons receive no external food,
yet airy condensations and concretions, the flegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick
humours, colliquations of the parts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> afford
matter for such vapours, and so much the more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully,
because they are environ'd with a thick wall,
whose very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>revises, and much more gates, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
out-lets, are so close shut up and barricado'd,
that these troops of Exhalations that were wont to
be dispersed, are now crouded together, which as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saulting
the brain may do much to bind up her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
sense. 3. It seems probable by Apoplectical
Dormitators that a cold humour lodged in the brain
is a great causer of sleep; and why such a humour
may not lodge in a sufficient proportion in these con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stipated
brains to procure intermitting sleeps, I see
not. 4. 'Tis apparent that Narcoticks, as <hi>Opium,</hi> and
in their measure, Wines, Tobacco, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> provoke sleep,
not by any cold quality, for they are all prov'd to be
hot, but ('tis probable) by adding such a ferment to
the blood, as renders the spirits separated in the
brain more torpid, ignave, and consequently inept
to motion, and the execution of their offices; or,
(which is almost the same thing) as renders the blood
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60848:19"/>
inept for separation of spirits in the brains Alembick,
whence the wearied spirits for want of fresh sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies
are be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>almed and quiescent. So then if the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours
in the bodies of these Abstinents should haply
partake of these Narcotick sulphurs, they may prove
somniferous without the elevation of fumes from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesting
food. But Sir, lest you should be startled at
this unphilosophical discourse, in representing sleep
rather as a non-emission of spirits from the brains,
than a non-immission of them to the brain from the
external sences, and consequently as a negation of
action rather than of passion, I crave leave to minde
you, that I am not only deficient in the beard, but
much more in the brain of some very great Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers
who rank not only the external sences but the
first internal or common sence in the predicament
of passions; which I confess I cannot understand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
I know, that when devout persons are taken
up in divine services, though their eyes be wide open,
and presented with various objects, yet they see them
not, because they mind them not; likewise when dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
Students are intent on their books, they hear not
the Clock that strikes at their ears; and sound sleepers
with lethargical persons feel not the pulling and
haling of their friends that would awake them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
From whence I conjecture, that though objects act
<hi>ad ultimum virium</hi> upon the external sences in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printing
their species, yet that causeth not sensation,
except there be an actual attendance of the sensitive
spirits upon the sensible objects, a framing of their
effigies or species, and a conveyance thereof to the
understanding. Can you imagine that <hi>Columbus</hi> his
journey to the <hi>Indies,</hi> his surveying that unknown
World, and returning a map thereof to his own
Countrey-men, was a meer passion of his, and only
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60848:20"/>
the action of a novel Jig of American Atoms? or
<hi>Camden</hi>'s perambulation through all the Coasts of
this Island, with his observations thereon, which he
digested into a valuable volume, was meerly his suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering,
but wholly the doing of subtile spirits, and
aethereal globules magically charm'd into a once hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
combination. But to return, 5. Cold juices, as of
Housleek, Lettuce, Violets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will conduce to our
sleep, and 'tis not to be doubted but the Juices in
these bodies may be cold enough to effect the same.
6. The animal spirits in these persons being but lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guid,
are the less active, and consequently can give
the fewer repulses to the insinuating courtships of
somniferous causes. 7. The spirits of these languish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
('tis probable) are scant and defective, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
easily tyred by their constant operations, and
consequently easily perswaded either by a command
of the Heaven-born Soul, or an Exhalation from
the earthy body to yield to this temporary death.
8. Great security of minde, pleasing Fancies, either
from Imagination (such as some of these are said to
be swell'd withall) or from the sences affected by
Musick, dropping waters, gliding Rivers, whistling
winds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are usuall promoters of insensation. By
all which you may perceive that there are more doors
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our Bedchambers than one.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir, to satisfie your curiosity, I have travel'd
somewhat an unbeaten, yet not altogether unpleasant
path, and that I might not return these fruits of my
travels as jejune and sterile as the Countrey visited,
I have therefore taken a slight view of some of the
Monuments of Antiquity, as also of the stately su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstructures
of the new modell that occurred in our
Journey; yet there is one thing remaining that should
have been premised; and that is an exact history of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60848:20"/>
our Damosell, but that you cannot expect, because
you did not demand, and I suppose you did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
because you knew I was unable to perform;
yet that I might not seem to build on the sands, I
shall present you with a short Narrative receiv'd
since I began this Discourse, from a person of known
ingenuity and honesty, and therefore most worthy
of credit.</p>
            <p>
               <q>This Abstinent is one <hi>Martha Taylor</hi> a young
Damosell, born of mean Parentage, inhabiting not
far from <hi>Bakewell</hi> in <hi>Darbyshire,</hi> who receiving a blow
on the back from a Milner, became a prisoner to
her bed for several dayes, which being expired,
she obtained some enlargement for a time, but by
encreasing distempers was quickly remanded to
her bed-prison again; where continuing some time,
she found at last a defect in her Gula, and quickly
after a dejection of appetite, so that about the
22. of <hi>December, Anno</hi> 1667. she began to abstain
from all solid food, and so hath continued (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
something so small at the seldome ebbings of
her distemper as is altogether inconsiderable) till
within a fortnight before the date hereof, which
amounts to thirteen months and upwards; as also
from all other sorts both of meats and drinks, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
now and then a few drops of the Syrup of
stew'd Prunes, Water and Sugar, or the juice of a
roasted Raisin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but these repasts are used so
seldom, and in such very small quantities, as are
prodigiously insufficient for sustentation; she eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuates
nothing by urine, or stool, she spits not that
I can hear of, but her lips are often dry, for which
cause she takes water and sugar with a feather, or
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60848:21"/>
some other Liquids, but the palms of her hands are
often moist, her countenance fresh and lively, her
voice cleer and audible, in discourse she's free, her
belly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ap'd to her back-bone, so that it may be
felt through her Intestines, whence a great cavity
is admitted from the <hi>Gartilago ensiformis</hi> to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,
and though her upper parts be less emaciated
(though much too) yet her lower parts are very
languid, and inept for motion, and the skin there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iled with a dry pruriginous scurf, for which
of late they have washed them with milk; she
sleeps so sparingly, that once she continued five
weeks waking: I hear nothing of any extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
previous sanctity, though since her affliction, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
confin'd to her bed (which lyeth in a lower
room, by the fire-side) she hath learn'd to read,
and being visited so plentifully by the curious from
many parts, as also by the Religious of all perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,
she hath attain'd some knowledge in sacred
Mysteries, but nothing of Enthusiasm that she pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
unto. And lest she should prove a Cheat,
she hath been diligently watch'd by Physitians,
Surgeons, and other persons, for at least a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night
together, by the appointment of the Noble
Earl of <hi>Devon;</hi> as is already publish'd by Mr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins</hi>
B. of D. that is, Ballad-maker of <hi>Darby,</hi> whose
Ballad (they say) doth much excell his Book.
Likewise several other persons at other times have
been pleas'd to watch for their own satisfaction,
who detecting no fraud, have given the account
above mention'd, which was for the main confirm'd
to me by a Sophy, the renown of whose wisdom
hath often made <hi>England</hi> to ring, who assured me,
that he had an exact account of her.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60848:21"/>
This story being born thus out of due time, it
may seem necessary to make some reflections there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from
on the precedent discourse. And 1. her Age
confirms the probability of a ferment in the semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.
2. An antipathy to meat was not the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of the Tragedy, but an inability to swallow.
3. Her assumptions of Liquors, though seldom and
slender, contribute not only to a petite concoction
in the Ventricle, but also to a fermentation in the
Heart. 4. Her restrained Evacuations by Urine
and Stool adde much to her moisture, as well as
to our trouble to render the assumption and non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evacuation
consistent: to the performance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
let it be remembred, that in this respect she
was formerly compar'd to Embrio's, who use no
excretion by the fundament, but retain in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testines
the more crass feculencies, till the time of
their exclusion the uterine embraces; which is the
rather to be admitted, because she, as well as they,
receives nothing but liquids; only in this she dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers,
they evacuate by the Urachus into the Allan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toides
their urinal excrement, but she hath no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion
of Urine at all: the defect whereof may
yet be supply'd by these three advantages which
she hath above them, as is her expiration, extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
transpiration in the palms of her hands, and
the far smaller quantity of Liquors that she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives.
5. Her non-excretion, and the driness of
her mouth, argue the remanding of the humours to
the further services of Nature. 6. The Atrophy
of the parts, and inability to motion, seem to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue
a defect of nervous juice and animal spirits;
which weakens the necessity of our giving a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60848:22"/>
account how Nature may be compleatly sustain'd
in the absence of food. 7. Her impetiginous Erupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
argue the saltness of her blood, which addes the
greater probability to the several saline Ferments
mentioned before. 8. Her sparing sleep shews not
only the no-necessity of the ordinary measures of
healthfull Dormitators, but also that sleep may be
conciliated otherwise than by the powerfull medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation
of fuming food. 9. There's no cause from
any antecedent sanctity to ascribe this mirandous
production to miraculous causes. 10. Her abode
in a lower Room doth accommodate her with a
moister Air, which is more generative of humours,
11. Her propinquity to the Fire conduceth to the
extraneous reception of igneous Atoms. 12. Her
non-pretensions to Revelations, and the constant
visits she receives from persons of all forms, may
serve to occlude not only the mouths that are so
unevangelical as to cry her up for a Miracle, but
those also that are so unphilosophical as to cry her
down for the cheat of a Faction.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, should I take my hand from the Table,
did I not suspect that some one may possibly reply
upon me, and say, If I take it to be possible to
live without food, 'tis a wonder I fall not my self
to this piece of frugality; I therefore adde, though
with this jejune Table one may possibly live, yet
it follows not that I can, for according to the old
Saw, <hi>that which is one mans meat is another mans poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son:</hi>
And even in Physick 'tis affirm'd by that noble
Philosopher <abbr>Esq</abbr> 
               <hi>Boyle</hi> (a worthy Fellow of the
Royall Society, of whose admirable designs I would
you should know that I am a great admirer) that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60848:22"/>
some medicines as particularly,<note place="margin">Scept. Chym. p. 251.</note> Salt of Amber is
effectual for Epileptical Children; not so for adult
Epilepticks; and the deserving Dr. <hi>Castle</hi> affirms,
that <hi>Mercur. dulc.</hi> is more safe for children, than
grown persons, especially if irrigated with acidities.
But Sir,<note place="margin">Chym. Gal. p. 26.</note> I finde my self launching into a wide Sea,
I shall therefore tack about to do my Devoire, and
crave your acceptance of this slender Offering,
and your <hi>quietus est</hi> for the present, giving you
assurance that in so doing you may hereafter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>King-Norton.</hi> 
                  <date>Feb.
25. 1668.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Observant Servant,
<hi>Jo. Reynolds.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
