<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of Francesco Redi concerning some objections made upon his Observations about vipers written to Monsieur Bourdelot ... and Monsieur Alexander Morus : printed in Italian at Florence, 1670 / now made English ; together with the sequel of New experiments upon vipers, and a dissertation upon their poyson ... written in French by Moyse Charas ; now likewise Englished.</title>
            <title>Lettera di Francesco Redi sopra alcune opposizioni fatte alle sue Osservazioni intorno alle vipere. English</title>
            <author>Redi, Francesco, 1626-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58326</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R663</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5968</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13219834</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13219834</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98525</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A58326)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 436:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of Francesco Redi concerning some objections made upon his Observations about vipers written to Monsieur Bourdelot ... and Monsieur Alexander Morus : printed in Italian at Florence, 1670 / now made English ; together with the sequel of New experiments upon vipers, and a dissertation upon their poyson ... written in French by Moyse Charas ; now likewise Englished.</title>
                  <title>Lettera di Francesco Redi sopra alcune opposizioni fatte alle sue Osservazioni intorno alle vipere. English</title>
                  <author>Redi, Francesco, 1626-1698.</author>
                  <author>Charas, Moyse, 1619-1698. Nouvelles expériences sur la vipère. Suite. English.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. for John Martyn ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Lettera di Francesco Redi sopra alcune opposizioni fatte alle sue Osservazioni intorno alle vipere.</note>
                  <note>"A continuation of the new experiments concerning vipers" (p. [37]-112) has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Redi, Francesco, 1626-1698. --  Osservazioni intorno alle vipere.</term>
               <term>Snakes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98525:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A
LETTER
OF
<hi>FRANCESCO REDI</hi>
Concerning
Some Objections made upon his
OBSERVATIONS
About
VIPERS:
Written to
Monſieur <hi>BOURDELOT</hi> Abbot,
and Lord of <hi>Conde</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>Leger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And
Monſieur <hi>ALEXANDER MOR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in <hi>Italian</hi> at <hi>Florence,</hi> 1670.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now made Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with
The SEQUEL of NEW EXPERI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS
upon <hi>VIPERS,</hi> and a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertation
upon their <hi>Poyſon:</hi> Serving for
a Reply to a Letter written by Signor
<hi>Franciſco Redi</hi> to M. <hi>Bourdelot,</hi> and M. <hi>Morus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>Moyſe Charas.</hi>
                  <hi>Now likewiſe Engliſhed.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> for <hi>John Martyn</hi> Printer to the <hi>Royal
Society,</hi> at the <hi>Bell</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls Churchyard,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:98525:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:98525:2"/>
                  <head>A LETTER OF
FRANCESCO REDI,
Concerning ſome Objections made
upon his Obſervations about Vipers.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Written to
Monſieur <hi>BOURDELOT,</hi>
AND
Monſieur <hi>ALEXANDER MORUS.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIRS,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ROM your liberality I have
received the Book entituled
<hi>NEW EXPERIMENTS</hi>
upon <hi>VIPERS,</hi> learnedly
compoſed by thoſe noble <hi>Virtuoſi,</hi> who du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
ſome months had met in the Houſe of
M. <hi>Charas</hi> for that purpoſe. I have read
it over more then once with great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment,
plainly finding that thoſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
perſons have not ſcrupled by their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
labours to confirm the Truth of
thoſe Obſervations, which I alſo had made
touching <hi>VIPERS,</hi> until the year 1664.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98525:3"/>
And indeed I think my ſelf much obliged
to their ingenuity, and do frankly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
that whatever worth that rude and
plain piece of mine may have, it hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
it from the honourable teſtimonies,
given to it in <hi>France,</hi> where all the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
Sciences and Arts do highly floriſh, to
the admiration of thoſe that profeſs them
in the other parts of <hi>Europe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I intreat you, Sirs, that you would do
me the favour to repreſent upon occaſion
theſe my candid and cordial ſentiments,
and withall to declare the high eſteem I
have for that Book<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the authority of which
is ſo venerable with me, that, having found
therein ſome few things directly contrary
to my own Experiments, I have often
doubted of my ſelf, and been almoſt ready
to believe, that I dream'd when I made,
and when I wrote them. But ſome of my
Learned Friends, that were frequently
preſent at thoſe my Operations, have laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
at me for that proneneſs of my belief,
and between jeſt and earneſt aſſur'd me,
that thoſe Experiments had by no means
ſo ſucceeded with me in a dream. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
which, without any regard to
their aſſeverations, I reſolved to iterate
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98525:3"/>
and reiterate them, and that with ſo great
and careful diligence, that I ſhould greatly
injure my ſelf and Truth, if I ſhould not
freely and candidly tell you, that all thoſe
four or five Experiments, which to thoſe
Gentlemen in <hi>France</hi> have not ſucceded,
do ſucceed with me in <hi>Italy</hi> without fail,
as they were formerly recorded by me; on
the contrary, thoſe will not ſucceed with
me that have been made in <hi>France</hi> and are
contrary to mine.</p>
                  <p>And ſince you may perhaps have the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity
as to deſire to know of what kind
they are, I ſhall here give you a brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
of them; aſſuring my ſelf, that it
will be acceptable to all the Lovers of
Truth, but eſpecially to the Authors of
the Book of the <hi>New Experiments,</hi> who
have been induced to write by no other
motive then the ſole deſire either to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
or to find the Truth of a matter ſo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
of which ſo many underſtanding men
have written.</p>
                  <p>In my Letter then of the <hi>Obſervations
about Vipers,</hi> addreſſed to the Illuſtrious
<hi>Lorenzo Magalotti,</hi> ſpeaking of the Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
of thoſe creatures, both what it is, and
in what part of the Body it reſideth, I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98525:4"/>
(as I affirm ſtill) that the Poiſon
of a Viper is nothing elſe then a certain yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowiſh
liquor, which lodgeth in the veſicles
that cover the greateſt teeth of the Viper;
and that that Juice is not only poiſonous,
when it is ejected by the live Viper when
ſhe biteth, but alſo when 'tis collected
from a dead Viper, and even ſuch an one
that hath been dead many days, provided
it be made to paſs into a wound, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
there. Moreover, I added, that this
ſame liquor, when taken down into the
ſtomach, is not deadly, no not ſo much as
noxious. And this was my opinion, which
hath been confirm'd to me by innumerable
Experiments, made with the greateſt exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
I could employ.</p>
                  <p>But the Authors of the Book of the <hi>New
Experiments</hi> do reſolutely write, That
that above mention'd Liquor is not poiſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
but a meer and a moſt innocent <hi>Saliva</hi>
or Spitle. Thence they go on to affirm for
an undoubted and experimented Truth,
that the Viper hath no part of her body,
neither limb nor humor, able to poiſon;
and that all her poiſon conſiſts in the ſole
imagination of the Viper, irritated and
made angry by the <hi>Idea</hi> of vengeance, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98525:4"/>
ſhe hath conceived in her head; by the
means whereof the ſpirits being put into a
violent motion, are darted through the
Nerves, and at times through the Fibres of
the cavities of the Teeth, by which cavities
thoſe ſpirits are carried to infect the blood
of the animal, by the opening made with
the biting teeth. In ſhort, they conclude,
that if a Viper be not angry, and have not
that vindicative imagination, her bitings
do never poiſon, but are very innocent,
cauſing no miſchief at all to him, in whom
they are made. For theſe are their words;</p>
                  <p>Pag.<hi> 36. </hi>in the Engliſh Verſion,<hi> Theſe
conſiderations, ſupported by many Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
made by Us, and to be related hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
have induced me to call theſe Glands</hi>Salival,<hi> and to aſcribe to them the very ſource
of that yellow liquor, which hath been ſo much
decried, and withal ſo little known; and it
nothing elſe, but a pure and a very innocent
Spitle. I hope that thoſe who ſhall take the
pains of examining after me, theſe Glands,
and this Juyce of the Gums, will not ſtick to
give me their ſuffrages.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Item p. 105. 106. <hi>But not to ſtay upon
principles ſo ſlightly eſtabliſhed, and ill main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd,
for aſmuch as we have on our ſide a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98525:5"/>
great number of Experiments, upon which
we are grounded: We ſay, that this Juice is
nothing but a pure and plain </hi>Saliva,<hi> of which
we have already obſerved the uſe; and that
this Juice contributes nothing to the venomouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of the Biting, ſince being taſted and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
(as we have often experimented) it
doth no hurt to man or beaſt; and ſince alſo,
being put upon open wounds, and upon inciſions
made in the fleſh, the ſame being rub'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,
and mingled with the blood, it annoys
nothing at all; notwithſtanding the judgment
of a Perſon very intelligent, and particularly
in this ſubject of Vipers, who aſſures to have
made a great number of Experiments, which
being contrary to ours, the great opinion we
have of the abilities and the ſincerity of that
famous man, hath obliged us to employ the more
care and exactneſs, and to confirm our ſelves
by a very great number of Experiments, which
have alwayes been found alike in the truth we
here aſſert, and of which we ſhall make evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
and irrefragable proof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Item p. cog.<hi> We conclude therefore, that the
imagination of the Viper, irritated by the </hi>idea<hi>of revenge, which ſhe had framed to her ſelf,
gives a certain motion to the ſpirits, which
cannot be expreſſed, and puſhes them violently,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98525:5"/>
through the Nerves and their Fibres, to the
cavity of the teeth as into a funnel, and that
from thence they are conveyed into the blood
of the animal by the opening, which they have
made, there to produce all thoſe effects, of
which we endeavour to give a reaſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Item pag. III.<hi> However this be, we muſt
herein agree, that this irritation in the fanſie
or in the ſpirits of the Viper, is the main cauſe
of the activity and piercingneſs of its venom,
and that without it the biting would not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
ſuch ſurpriſing effects, as thoſe are, of
which we have related ſo many examples.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Item pag.<hi> 138. Theſe Experiments will
prove on the one hand, that the yellow liquor
contributes nothing to the poyſon; and on the
other, that theſe incenſed ſpirits, aſſiſted by
the openings, which the great teeth had
made for them, are the ſole and true cauſe
thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe ſentiments they confirm by ſome
Experiments, all which conſiſt in this, that
they had drop't a quantity of that yellow
liquor into the wounds of a Pigeon, a Dog,
and ſome Pullets, which yet dyed not of
it; and that having cauſed a Pigeon to be
bitten by a Viper not enraged, the animal
received thence no hurt at all. For they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98525:6"/>
ſay<hi> pag. 115. We alſo made a trial upon a
Pigeon, which we wounded under the wing
and in the Leg in the ſame moment of time;
and we let into each wound ſome of this yellow
liquor, which juſt afore we had drawn from
the gums of two enraged Vipers; then we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned
the skin well, to encloſe the ſaid liquor,
and we bound both wounds over with a band,
that nothing might run out. We can aſſure,
that the Pigeon felt not any inconvenience
from it, and that we even found upon the
wound, made in the Leg, a coagulated drop of
the juice, round, and of the ſame colour as we
had put it there, and the blood of the wound
dryed, and that, ſoon after, both wounds were
dried up, and healed of themſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pag.<hi> 116. We alſo made the like Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
upon a Cat, which we purpoſely wounded
in the Leg, but he received no harm at all by
it: We have alſo often experimented it on Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets,
and other Pigeons, but alwayes with the
like ſucceſs, and without any offence to the
Animals.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ibid.<hi> The ſame Trial hath been thrice
made at three ſeveral times, and even twice
in one day upon a Dog, whom we had wounded
on purpoſe towards the bottom of the Ear,
where he could not lick his wound; and no
miſchief at all followed upon it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98525:6"/>
Ibid.<hi> We cannot but add here an Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the mortal effect of the Enraged Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
without any intervention of the yellow
liquor. We made a Viper ſeveral times to bite
upon a ſlice of bread, by preſſing every time
its jaws againſt the bread; and we did this ſo
often, that not only that juice was altogether
exhauſted, but the blood began to come out of
the Veſſicles. At the ſame time we vexed
the Viper, and made her bite a Pigeon in the
moſt fleſhy part; and we obſerv'd that indeed
the effects of the venom of the biting were
not ſo quick, the Pigeon not dying but an hour
and an half after it had been bitten; but then
we found alſo, that the teeth of the Viper were
in a manner covered with the crums of the
bread, from the force of her having bitten at
it, and that that had hindred them from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
a deep entrance; and that having half
ſtop't up the pores of the teeth, a good part of
the angred Spirits could not come forth; ſo
that the death of the Pigeon could not follow
ſo faſt, though yet it hapned without any mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of the juice, which had been altogether
emptied.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pag.<hi> 138. The wound made by a Viper
not vexed, whoſe Jaws were held in, and
whoſe teeth were at the ſame time thruſt into
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98525:7"/>
the body of a Pigeon, which alſo was accompanied
with ſtore of the yellow juice, and yet not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
with any ill accident.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To theſe Experiments I have nothing
elſe to oppoſe, but thoſe very many ones,
that were made by me in the year 1664. and
recited in the above-mentioned <hi>Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
of mine <hi>about Vipers,</hi> and thoſe alſo that
I ſhall recite hereafter, made likewiſe by
my ſelf, not with a deſire to confirm the firſt,
but indeed to diſcover the Truth. And,
that I may not be put often to repeat ſome
things, I ſhall premiſe ſome General Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations,
made by me at the time when I dealt
in Vipers.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A viper more eaſily kills a Pigeon, a
Pullet, a Turky-cock, a Squirrel, a Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſe,
and generally all ſmall Birds and
Animals, than a great Animal, as a Sheep,
a Deer, a Horſe, a Bull; yea theſe greater
ones and thoſe that are of an hard skin, very
often a Viper kills not at all.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. According to the bigneſs of the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
bitten, and according to the place where
the Viper biteth, death follows ſooner or
later; eſpecially according as the place
wounded is a clear texture, or thick ſet
with veins and arteries; or thoſe veins and
arteries are very ſmall or big.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98525:7"/>
3. If from the wound of a Viper much
blood iſſueth, it ſometimes happens, that
the Animal nor only dyeth not, but does
not ſo much as feel any great inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It doth alſo not ſeldom fall out, that
an Animal bitten by a Viper ſuffers grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous
Symptoms from the poyſon, which
bring it near death, but yet kill it not;
but the creature without any help of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick
and by the ſole work of nature reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Thoſe Animals that are bitten of a
Viper dye a little ſooner, than thoſe, into
the wounds of which hath been on purpoſe
conveyed that yellow liquor, which by
art hath been fetch't out of the baggs of the
teeth of that Viper.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. 'Tis neceſſary, that great dexterity
be uſed in making the ſaid liquor to
penetrate into the wound; becauſe, if the
wound be narrow, it pierces difficultly;
if large, it cannot be otherwiſe but it will
bleed, and with that blood the ſaid liquor
will turn back, and ſo the poiſon come out
again.</p>
                  <p>I had then provided a good number of
Vipers which I cauſed to be brought me cut
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98525:8"/>
of the Kingdome of <hi>Naples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and having in
this moneth of <hi>May,</hi> 1670 wounded ten
Pigeons of the bigger ſort in the thighs, I
put into them ſome of the yellow liquor
freſhly taken out of the mouth of the live
Vipers; and all theſe Pigeons, ſome within
the ſpace of one hour, ſome in half an hour,
and ſome in two hours, died. This Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment
I repeated upon ten Chickens, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
wounded in their thighs, with the ſame
event that had befallen the Pigeons.</p>
                  <p>Then I cut off the heads of twelf Vipers,
and all the heads being cut off, and the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
quite dead, I thence extracted the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
and cauſed them to be put into the
wounds of eight Turtle-doves, all which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in the ſpace of half an hour.</p>
                  <p>In the month of <hi>June,</hi> having killed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
other Vipers, and gather'd out of the bags
of their teeth and their gums all the yellow
and viſcous Juice that was there, I anointed
therewith ſome beeſom-rods, ſharpn'd like
arrowes, and immediately I pricked with
them ten young Pigeons in the more fleſhy
part of their cheſt, leaving them fixed in the
wound; and the Pigeons ſurvived not above
two or three hours. But leſt it ſhould be
doubted; whether theſe Pigeons died not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98525:8"/>
of the wound it ſelf, enraged by the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures
of thoſe rods, I made a trial upon
four other Pigeons with rods not infected
with that poyſonous liquor; but none of
them dyed, though the wounds became pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent.</p>
                  <p>I alſo took eight heads of Vipers, cut off
ſix hours before, and, the Vipers being quite
dead, I cauſed eight Turtle-doves to be
bitten by them in the thigh, and not one of
them eſcaped.</p>
                  <p>Moreover I made the heads of fifteen
Vipers to be cut off: and put them into a
glaſs-veſſel well cover'd, having laid them
upon one another, that ſo they might remain
moiſt. Four dayes after, I ſtruck with thoſe
heads five young Cocks, and five great Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons
in the thigh, and they all after a little
while died. The like fell out with other
Viper-heads, which having been killed ſix
dayes before, had in all likely hood loſt all
choller and thoughts of revenge. And to
prevent all Objections that might be raiſed
on this occaſion, I ſhall not omit to relate
to you, that about the beginning of <hi>Auguſt</hi>
when two of my Vipers, that alone were
left me in a box, died of themſelves of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
I cauſed two Turtle-doves to be ſtruck
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98525:9"/>
by them, which alſo, like the former, dyed
in leſs than an hours time.</p>
                  <p>But I may go further. I had collected
in a glaſs all the poiſonous liquor of the
heads of two hundred and fifty Vipers, to
make various Experiments therewith upon
occaſion. But being by much buſineſs hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred,
I delayed to accompliſh my deſign:
Whence that liquor turn't firſt into a glew,
colour'd like amber; then in 30 dayes it
became altogether dry and friable, ſo that
it could eaſily be reduced to powder. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
pulveriſed, I had a mind to try, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
that powder, let into a wound, did
keep the force of poyſoning; and I found
that really it did ſo, all thoſe Pullets, Pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and Turtle-doves, into the wounds of
which I had put ſome thereof, dying of it in
a little while.</p>
                  <p>Having made this Experiment, I began
to doubt, whether that poyſon of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes
of the King of <hi>Macaſsar</hi> in the Iſland
of <hi>Celebes,</hi> which commonly are called the
arrowes of <hi>Bantam</hi> in <hi>Java Major,</hi> were not
the poyſon extracted out of the mouth of
ſome Viper, or of ſome other Viper-like
ſerpent, and perhaps of a more maligne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
becauſe of the diverſity of the Climate.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98525:9"/>
I am not much averſe from believing this to
be ſo; and it may be confirmed by what I
have read in <hi>Pliny, viz.</hi> That the <hi>Scythians</hi>
did infect their Arrows with a Viperin poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.
His words are, <hi>Scythae ſagittas tingunt
Viperinâ ſanie &amp; humano ſanguine: irremedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abile
id ſcelus mortem illicò levi tactu aſſert.</hi>
And this was perhaps extracted by <hi>Pliny</hi>
out of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who in h<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Book, intitul'd
<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſoon after deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth
the proceſs of preparing it, which I dare
not affirm to be the true one, or to requi<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e
ſo many circumſtances and cautions. And
who knows, whether the Arrows of <hi>Hercules,</hi>
of which the Fables alledge that they were
imbued with the blood of an <hi>Hydra,</hi> were
not infected with this poiſon of Vipers? So
'tis believed by <hi>Diodorus Siculus,</hi> when he
ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.
And <hi>Ovid</hi> gives the name of Viper to the
<hi>Hydra,</hi> when in his ninth Book of <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morph.</hi>
he ſaith;
<q>Pars quota Lerneae ſerpens erit unus Echiánae.</q>
And afterwards;
<q>
                        <l>—Capit inſcius heros,</l>
                        <l>Induitur que humeris Lerneae virus Fchidnae.</l>
                     </q>
To which may be added, that <hi>Philoctetes,</hi>
the Heir of the Bow and Arrows of <hi>Hercules,</hi>
being gon in the Grecian Navy to the <hi>Trojan</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98525:10"/>
War, and having unawares wounded himſelf
(as <hi>Servius Grammaticus</hi> relates, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Aeneid)</hi>
with one of his Arrows in the foot; was left
among the Grecians in the Iſle of <hi>Stalimene,</hi>
by reaſon of the violence of the pain, and
the intolerable ſtench of the wound. Whence
<hi>Sophocles,</hi> alluding, it ſeems, to the kind of
poiſon, in a Poetical way and phraſe rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth,
that <hi>Philoctetes</hi> was left in that Iſle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
he had been bitten by a Viper. His
words are;
<q>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>: That is</l>
                     </q>
                     <hi>O Son of </hi>Achilles,<hi> I am he, whom thou mayſt
have heard to be the poſſeſsor of the Herculean
Arrows, the Son of </hi>Paean Philoctetes:<hi> whom
the two Armies and the King of the Iſle of </hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalene<hi>ſhamefully left lying here, pining away
by a cruel diſeaſe, ſtruck by the fierce bite of a
murthering Viper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Cicero</hi> himſelf in his ſecond Book of
the <hi>Tuſculan Queſtions,</hi> and in his Book <hi>De
Fato,</hi> and many other Writers do follow this
opinion, <hi>viz,</hi> That <hi>Philoctetes</hi> was bitten by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98525:10"/>
a Viper. And poſſibly all of them had an
eye not only to this place of <hi>Sophocles,</hi> but
alſo to what <hi>Homer</hi> ſaid before, in his ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth
Book of <hi>Iliads.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And though againſt this conjecture it may
be ſaid, that the poiſion of Vipers is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable
in reſpect of what Poets do write
of the Arrows of <hi>Hercules,</hi> which by them
are ſaid not only to have the force of killing
without fail, whether the wound be ſmall or
great, as happen'd to the Centaure <hi>Chiron</hi>
and to <hi>Neſſus;</hi> but alſo that the blood of
their wounds was become ſo peſtiferous as to
infect any live body whatſoever, touched
thereby, and that with ſuch violence, as to
make the fleſh fall off from the bones: which,
<hi>they add,</hi> was experimented by <hi>Hercules</hi> to
his great miſchief, when his Shirt was tinged
with the blood of <hi>Neſsus;</hi> whence <hi>Ovid</hi>
ſaith,
<q>
                        <l>Victa malis poſtquam eſt patientia, reppulit
aras</l>
                        <l>Implevit que ſuis nemoroſam vocibus Oeten;</l>
                        <l>Nec mora, letiferam conatur ſcindere veſtem;</l>
                        <l>Qua trahitur, trahit illa cutim (faedumque
relatu)</l>
                        <l>Aut haret membris, fruſtra tentata revelli,</l>
                        <l>Aut laceros artus &amp; grandia detegit oſſa:</l>
                     </q>
This is a Poetical Fable; whence, I am apt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98525:11"/>
to believe, is raiſed that relation concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Arrows of <hi>Macaſſar,</hi> of which 'tis
ſaid, that they kill one in that very moment
he receiveth the ſlighteſt wound thereby, and
that alſo in the ſpace of half an hour the fleſh
of the killed perſon becomes ſo putriſied,
that it falls off from the bones in many pieces,
whence do exhale ſuch virulent ſteams, that
if they light upon any ordinary and not enve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomed
wound, they mortally infect it, and
without fail kill the Patient.</p>
                  <p>I do here affirm, that I have made many
tryal's with thoſe Arrows of the Indians; but
have not found them in <hi>Tuſcany</hi> of ſo fierce
and malignant a nature, as hath been related.
The Dogs I wounded with them, dyed ſome
of them in ſix, others in ſeven, others in
twelve, others in twenty four hours. And
their fleſh was not putriſied, nor fallen in
pieces, nor did their blood or exhaled ſteams
at all kill other wounded Animals. But I
have often obſerved, that, if one intends to
ki<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l with theſe Arrows, it is not enough to
make a ſimple inciſion of the fleſh, but he
muſt by art make them ſtick a while in the
wound (which is like to what happens in
putting into wounds the powder of the dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
yellow liquor of Vipers:) Whence it is
that thoſe Savages make of Wood the ſharp
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98525:11"/>
ends of thoſe Arrows, imbue them with poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
and then joyne them to the Arrow ſtick
in ſuch a manner, that thoſe ends ever remain
in the wound, whether the Arrow do break
or be drawn out; as came to paſs in the Siege
of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to thoſe Heroes of <hi>Flandres, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dofred</hi>
and <hi>Robert,</hi> of whom that great Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin
Poet thus ſingeth:
<q>
                        <l>Soſpingeva il monton, quando è percoſſo</l>
                        <l>Al Sig. de Fiaminghi il lato manco,</l>
                        <l>Si che travia s' allenta, è vuol poi trarne</l>
                        <l>Lo ſtrale, e reſta il ferro entro la carne:</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>That is,
<hi>The Engine diſcharged<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the left ſide of the
Flandrian Princes was ſo ſtruck, that they were
thruſt out of their way, and when they would
draw out the Arrow, the Iron ſtuck within
their fleſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is therefore neceſſary, that the Arrows
do ſtick for ſome time in the wound, if they
ſhall kill: Whence I underſtand not, how
the vulgar comes to fanſy, that the Blades of
Swords may be envenomed. I do well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
that with the yellow liquor of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
and with other things eſteemed veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous,
I have ſometimes ſlightly tinged Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cets
for letting of blood, and with them have
cut the vein of ſome Animal or other, but
death hath not followed upon it. Let ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98525:12"/>
men rather beware of the Tents of
Chirurgions; for 'tis too hard to cauſe
death by poiſon'd Lancets or other ſuch Iron
inſtruments. Hence it ſeems to me to ſavor
of the fable (though the caſe be different)
that <hi>Pariſatis</hi> the old Queen of the Perſians,
did poiſon her Daughter-in-law by the hands
of her Carver, poiſoning the one ſide of the
Knife, and therewith cutting aſunder a
Fowl, of which he gave to the young Queen
to eat that part, which the poiſoned ſide of
the Knife had envenomed, eating the other
part himſelf.</p>
                  <p>I could never ſee the truth of what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
of poiſons killing by a meer and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaneous
contact, or by vicinity alone;
as that Stirrups, Sadles, and Benches have
been poiſoned, and thereby proved mortal.
Let him believe it that will; I cannot. And
what a certain modern Writer relateth for a
great truth, concerning a prodigious acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
hapned by a kind of Serpents bred in
the Indies, I muſt leave to himſelf, who ſaith,<hi>After I have ſpoken of theſe Serpents, I preſume
it will not be unacceptable to give an account of
the ſtrange effect they produce. If perchance it
happen, that they paſs over a cloath or ſhirt dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in the Sun, there is wont to be bred in the
Kidneys of thoſe that uſe this cloath, a certain
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98525:12"/>
kind of Serpents, which little by little growing
up do encompaſs the whole body, and when their
tayl reaches their head, to conjoyn the circle,
then death is unevitable: Wherefore, to avoyd
this miſchief, they kill them with Razors and
Lancets, to prevent their growth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You have found above mentioned three
perſons, wounded by the Arrows of <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi>
namely <hi>Chiron, Neſſus,</hi> and <hi>Philoctetes.</hi>
The two firſt dyed ſuddenly; the third, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
a long ſickneſs eſcaped. If the caufes of
this difference were to be given (whether it
be an Hiſtory or a Fable) I ſhould ſay, that
<hi>Neſſus</hi> and <hi>Chiron</hi> dyed, becauſe they were
wounded whilſt <hi>Hercules</hi> was yet living, by
Arrows freſhly envenomed; beſides that
<hi>Neſſus</hi> was pierced through his heart, as <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
hath it,
<q>
                        <l>Jámque tenens ripam miſſos cùm tolleret ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</l>
                        <l>Conjugis agnovit vocem, Neſſóque paranti</l>
                        <l>Fallere depoſitum; quò te fiducia, clamat,</l>
                        <l>Vana pedum violente rapit? Tibi, Neſſe bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formis</l>
                        <l>Dicimus, exaudi, nec res intercipe noſtras.</l>
                        <l>Si te nulla mei reverentia movit; at orbes</l>
                        <l>Concubitus vetitos poterant inhibere paterni.</l>
                        <l>Haud tamen effugies, quamvis ope fidis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinâ,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="24" facs="tcp:98525:13"/>
Vulnere, non pedibus, te conſequar. Ultima
dicta</l>
                        <l>Re probat, &amp; miſſâ fugientia terga fagittâ</l>
                        <l>Trajicit; extabat ferrum de pectore aduncum:</l>
                        <l>Quod ſimul evulſum eſt, ſanguis per utrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
foramen</l>
                        <l>Emicuit, miſtus Lernaei tabe veneni.</l>
                     </q>
But <hi>Philoctetes</hi> was wounded long after the
death of <hi>Hercules;</hi> whence 'tis credible, that
thoſe Arrows had loſt much of their poiſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
force, even as the powder of the yellow
liquor looſeth of its force, and the Arrows of
<hi>Macaſſer</hi> by length of time grow languid;
which though they poiſon and kill if one be
wounded therewith, yet do they no hurt at
all, if their poiſon be ſwallow'd and taken
into the ſtomach. Which Experiment I have
tryed upon two Doggs, to whom I gave to
ſwallow two pieces of fleſh covered with
the powder of the ſcrapings of ſuch Arrows;
as alſo upon ſeveral Chickens, to whom I
gave the water to drink, wherein thoſe ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings
had been a long time infuſed.</p>
                  <p>But, to return after this long digreſſion
to the main thing; you may by the above re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
and often repeated Experiments, ſee,
that the po<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſon of the <hi>Italian</hi> Viper conſiſts
not in an imaginary <hi>idea</hi> of anger raiſed to
revenge, but rather in that yellow liquor,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98525:13"/>
which is voided out of the bags of the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
teeth of Vipers; which juyce if it chance
to be ſpilled in the mouth and upon the
Pallat of thoſe animals is able to envenoin
the ſpittle which moiſtens their throat.</p>
                  <p>I ſhould think it very well worth while
for thoſe learned Authors of the book of
the <hi>New Experiments,</hi> that they would
pleaſe to make their Experiments anew.
And if they ſhall find them conform to thoſe
they have already publiſhed, and really con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to mine, then we may unanimouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
that we have lighted upon a truth hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
unknown; which is, That the Poiſon
of the <hi>French</hi> Vipers conſiſts in an imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<hi>Idea</hi> of a revengeful anger; but that of
the <hi>Italian</hi> ones hath its ſeat in that yellow
liquor, ſo often mentioned by me. But if on
the other ſide, the <hi>French</hi> Experiments
ſhould not hold, then it may be affirmed,
that the <hi>French</hi> as well as the <hi>Italian</hi> Vipers
are of one and the ſame nature; and have
the ſame kind of poiſon.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore if in <hi>Italy</hi> the Viper in poiſon
certainly lodges in that yellow liquor, it
will be no untruth in me to affirm, that if by
biting, a Viper ſhould have loſt all that juyce
reſiding in thoſe bags, and that alſo which
may be furniſht by the neighbouring parts, it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98525:14"/>
will, I ſay, be no untruth in me to affirm,
that the ſubſequent bitings will not be mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal:
which is the thing I have theſe many
years aſſerted, and do ſtill aſſert, although
the aboveſaid Authors deny it, giving out
that one only Viper, being vexed and ſwell'd
with choller, is able to kill as many animals
as she bites; they truſting to one Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
in which they ſay there died five young
Pidgeons by the biting of one only Viper. <hi>We
hope</hi> (ſay they, p. 137.) <hi>that among the many
Experiments thoſe of the five Pidgeons, bitten
one after another, by one and the fame viper ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated
every time, and of which the laſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
died firſt of all, when the viper was moſt
vexed, and moſt exhauſted of its yellow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor,</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I am willing indeed to believe the fact to
be true; but for the confirmation of it I wiſh
they had cauſed many more ſuch Pidgeons,
and many other animals, of different kinds
and bigneſſes, to be bitten of the ſelf ſame Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
which had killed thoſe five ones, to ſee
whether that angry and cholerick poiſon had
an infinite power. For when I examin'd this
matter, I choſe about the beginning of <hi>May</hi>
a Female Viper, one of the biggeſt and luſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt,
and vexed her to bite ten Chickens one
after another, in the right thigh; of which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98525:14"/>
the firſt, ſecond, and third died almoſt in an
inſtant; the fourth ſeemed only to be ſick;
but the fifth and all the reſt did not only not
dye, but were not at all ſick; and yet every
time the Viper did bite, I angred and madded
her exceedingly. In the moneth of <hi>June</hi> I
repeated the experiment in five tame <hi>Ducks,</hi>
bitten by one and the ſame Viper, which alſo
immediately after bit three young <hi>Turtle-Doves.</hi>
The firſt wounded Duck dyed three
hours after; the ſecond, five hours after; but
the reſt eſcaped. 'Tis true, that the firſt
wounded of the Turtles dyed, but not the
other two. Of twelve <hi>Ring-Doves</hi> at one
time there dyed but four; but the next day
of twelve others there dyed ſix. Of five <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets</hi>
there dyed three<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of three <hi>Lambs</hi> the
two laſt lived, the firſt of them dying two
hours after it had been bitten.</p>
                  <p>I ſhould be too tedious, if I ſhould relate
to you all the other experiments: Wherefore
I ſhall go on to add, that having written in
my<hi> Obſervations, </hi>that that yellow liquor was
not conveyed to the bags of the teeth from the
bladder of gall, I did ſuggeſt, whether it
might not be diſgorged there by certain ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral<hi>Ductus's, </hi>that might be inſerted at the
head of them: which did appear the more
probable, becauſe that in all Vipers at the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98525:15"/>
bottom of thoſe veſicles I had always found
two glanduls, which had not, that I knew,
been obſerved or deſcribed by any body.
Whereupon the Authors of the<hi> New Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>do affirm, that they could never ſee
ſuch Glanduls as I had named; but that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
of them they had found two others,
which they call Salival, thus by them deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed,<hi>p. 31, 32. I believed at firſt, following
Signor </hi>Redi,<hi> that there might be Salival veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels
in Vipers, as there have been lately found in
Man and divers other Animals; ſo that after
many re-ſearches made with ſufficient attention
and patience, in many Vipers heads I diſcovered
at length ſuch Glands, proper to forme this
juyce, and to convey it to the Bags; and after I
was well perſwaded of it my ſelf, I ſhewed them
to divers of thoſe knowing Phyſitians, that had
met at my houſe the laſt year. Theſe perſons had
a mind to ſee them with their own eyes; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
I had well examined the parts which I ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
them, they not only found them true, but they
alſo ſaw there a greater number of ſmaller veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels
then had appear'd to me, of which ſome that
are Arteries and Veins paſs above the Glands,
and others that are Lympheducts run below; ſo
that they judged, that I could confidently aſſert
and deſcribe theſe Glands which I call Salival,
and which they had acknowledged together with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98525:15"/>
me; though </hi>Signor Redi<hi> durſt not ſpeak poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively
of them, becauſe he had not diſcovered
them; neither had they been deſcribed by any
Author of their knowledge, nor by any one of
mine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And pag.<hi> 35. As to the ſmall Glands, which</hi>Signor Redi<hi> hath obſerved at the bottom of the
Veſicles that contain this juyce, I can ſay, that I
have with great care and diligence ſearched af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
them, and that 'tis true, I have there found
the appearances of Glands, but having opened
them, I ſaw nothing in them but ſmall teeth that
were faſtned there, without finding any thing of
a Glandular nature there, nor that did in the
leaſt approach to the ſhape, ſubſtance, or quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of the Glands which I have been deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing,</hi>&amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I do not at all wonder that thoſe Writers
have not found thoſe Glanduls I named, I ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
they went about to ſearch them within
the Veſicles of the teeth, and at the bottom of
them: Whereas I never ſaid that they were to
be found within them, I ſaid they were to be
found <hi>Sotto'l fondo</hi> (under the bottom) of
thoſe bags, and in good <hi>Tuſcan</hi> language, tis
another thing to ſay <hi>nel fondo,</hi> (in or at the
bottom) another <hi>Sotto'l fondo</hi> (under the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom.)
And therefore when they <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ought them
where they are to be met with, they eaſily
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98525:16"/>
found them, and they are the ſame which they
deſcribe, neither are there any other conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable
glanduls to be diſcovered in the heads
of Vipers. Nor could I at all write that thoſe
Glanduls lay in the bottom of the Veſicles, if
I was of opinion that the yellow liquor did
run into them after it had paſſed through the
Salival Conduits, which yet I imagined might
have their origin from, or connexion with
thoſe two Glanduls ſeen by me, and therefore
muſt needs be in a ſcituation a little diſtant
from the Veſicles, and not in the bottom of
them. Now whether theſe Glanduls have this
office and this uſe, I intend not now to ſpeak
of, let it be what it will, 'tis too inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
a matter to make any more words of it.</p>
                  <p>I confeſs, that the dangerous experiments
which Vipers have, made them ſo diſpleaſing
to me, and even ſo odious, that I reſolved
not at all to meddle any more with them; but
that I was tempted thereto by a great deſire
I had experimentally to learn, whether the
volatil Salt of Vipers, Chymically prepared,
were endowed with that preſent and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
vertue of curing the bitings of Vipers, as
the ſaid Writers affirm. For my <hi>Genius</hi>
keeps me from much truſting to thoſe things,
that have not been made out to me by Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment;
although I do not preſently reject
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98525:16"/>
them as falſe before Experiment, but rather
being deſirous to know whether they be true,
I put them to tryal: But neither do I acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſce
in one or a few experiments, but I love to
ſee more and more, being ever apprehenſive
leſt I ſhould be deceived; as it often hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd
to me, when I have been ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide
in one haſty experiment. And to ſay truth
in the moneth of <hi>June</hi> there wanted not much
but that I had impoſed upon my ſelf in the
tryal of an experiment, which I am going to
relate to you, and which done I ſhall eaſe you
of further trouble.</p>
                  <p>Having read them in the Book of the<hi> New
Experiments, </hi>that the Head of a Viper, being
eaten of an animal, bitten by another Viper,
did certainly cure the wound; and the thing
being by me looked upon as very uſeful, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent,
and admirable, I had an eager deſire to
try it my ſelf, that I might ſpeak of it with
more confidence, although thoſe learned men
had made theſe two following experiments of
it,<hi> viz. </hi>pag. 120. <hi>We had alſo a deſire to find
whether a Viper being eaten by an animal, which
ſhe had bitten before, would be cured of that bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.
We therefore cauſed to be ſlightly broiled
the head of a Viper, which had on it a part of the
neck, newly ſever'd from the body; and we cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
a Dog to be thrice bitten at the ear, by a well
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98525:17"/>
enraged Viper, in ſuch a manner that the blood
came out at the three pricked places. We ſoon caſt
before him the head and neck; broiled, and yet
hot. The Dog, that was hungry, and felt not ſo
ſoon the effects of the bitings, immediately ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
on the head, bruiſed it between his teeth, and
ſwallowed it down. After which we ſtay'd a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
while to ſee, whether the three bitings would
prevail over the devour'd head and neck<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the
Dog was free, except ſome blewneſs and a little
Tumour he had at the places bitten, but which
little by little vaniſht in three or four days. We
made alſo a Dog to be bitten three times in the
ſame place, and without broiling the head of the
ſame Viper that had bit him, we caſt it before
him, hoping that he would eat it, becauſe he had
not eaten any thing for many hours before; but
the Dog would not touch it. Upon that we bruiſed
and ſtamped that head in a mortar, and ſo cram'd
it down the Dogs throat, rubbing alſo the bitten
places with the blood of the ſame Viper; which
done, we expected the ſucceſs, which was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that
this head, raw and bruiſed, and if you will, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
by the blood of the Viper, being applied to the
part bitten, had produced the ſame effects with
the former, which had been ſlightly broiled; in
regard that this Dog was ſafe, excepting thoſe
inconveniencies the former ſuffer'd, and was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
that as ſound as if he had never been bitten.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98525:17"/>
If theſe two Experiments had been made before
that Gentleman, above diſcours'd of, was bitten
by a Viper, we ſhould have been in much leſs anx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iety
for his preſervation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And a little before (pag. 119.) they had
ſaid:<hi> We have tryed, that having cauſed to be
bitten at the thickeſt place of the ear, by a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
vexed Viper, a young Cat, very lean,
that had but juſt before eaten the Eggs, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix,
and all the Guts of a Viper; the biting had
almoſt no effect, and there appeared nothing but
a very little ſwelling, and a very inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
lividneſs in the part bitten.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And pag. 154. <hi>It is very certain, that the
Head of a Viper, broiled and ſwallowed, healeth
the biting of that Animal. The Heart and the
Liver may do the ſame. Reaſon and Experience
have confirm'd it; and therefore in an urgent
occaſion theſe parts may be very beneficially em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And pag. 156. <hi>We believe, that the Liver
ſwallowed is capable to heal the biting of a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
like the heart, fleſh and other parts, of which
we have ſpoken; and that it may much facilitate
the delivery of Women with Child, as doth the
Liver of Eeles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hereupon I reſolved to imitate thoſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,
and having given a Vipers head half
boiled to a chain'd young Dog, I cauſed him
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98525:18"/>
immediately to be bitten by an other Viper
in the right ear, but the Dog dyed not, nor
did he appear to me to have any other incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience
than that he ſtood as 'twere amazed,
and looking grim, and melancholly, for four or
five hours ſpace. I ſoon reiterated the ſame
Experiment upon another Dog, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
been forced to ſwallow the head of a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
raw and bruiſed in a Mortar, gave no
ſign of any great poiſon, and had very little
and almoſt no ill enſuing. Whence I was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
to reckon this Experiment among things
proved and true, when a doubt coming into
my mind, obliged me to cauſe two other
young Dogs to be bitten in their ears, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
they had not eaten the counter-poiſon
of a Vipers head, yet dyed not. Whence the
ſuſpicion being increaſed in me, I cauſed to
be brought me the raw head of a Viper, and
crammed it into the throat of a young Pullet,
and then had its left thigh bitten by a Viper;
whereupon it preſently fell to the ground,
and in a little more then the eight part of an
hour died. Whence the ſuſpicion growing
ſtill greater, about ten a clock in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
I made a Capon to eat two raw heads of
Vipers, and afterwards about twelve a clock
I made him ſwallow two others, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
loſing any time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I cauſed him to be once
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98525:18"/>
bitten by a Viper in the thigh, and the Capon
immediately dyed, without finding any good
in the four ſwallow'd heads. The next day
I prepared for two young Dogs a diſh of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-heads
parboiled, but they would not eat
them, and we were forced to cramm them
down: Soon after, the leſſer of the two Dogs
was bitten in the thigh near the groin, and the
bigger in the tongue; and they both dyed. And
in the like manner dyed eight Chickens, two
Kitlings, two young Hares, and ſix Turtle-Doves,
likewiſe bitten by Vipers, and Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qued
not only by their heads, both raw and
boiled, but alſo having their wounds waſhed
with the Viper-blood. And I remember, that I
cauſed thoſe 6 Turtle-Doves to be bitten not
by the heads of live Vipers, but by thoſe of
dead ones, and ſuch as had dyed two days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.
Moreover, I continued for three days
ſucceſſively to cram two ſuch other Doves
with Viper-ſleſh, and gave them no other
drink then the broth of that ſleſh; and yet
they could not eſcape death, being bitten by
a Viper.</p>
                  <p>Whence I am inclined to believe, that in
<hi>Tuſcany</hi> the ſleſh of Vipers is no help or reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
at leaſt no conſiderable one, to Animals
bitten by Vipers. Mean while I refer my ſelf
to the Learning, Experience, and Authority
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98525:19"/>
of thoſe noble perſons, to whom I do moſt
willingly ſubmit this or any other opinion of
mine, and with whom I would never entertain
a controverſie. For I ſhould apprehend leſt
it might befall me, what <hi>Marcus Tullius</hi> was
wont to ſay of <hi>Cato,</hi> viz. That it was not leſs
troubleſome to him to anſwer to the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of <hi>Cato,</hi> then to his ſtrongeſt arguments.</p>
                  <p>For the reſt, I earneſtly intreat you, <hi>Sirs,</hi>
that you would pardon the rudeneſs of this
my Letter, ſufficiently appearing to have
been written by a perſon full of buſineſs, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
then enjoying leiſure; and that you would
pleaſe only to regard the naked truth, which
without any paſſion I did undertake to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:98525:19"/>
                  <p>A CONTINUATION
Of the
NEW EXPERIMENTS
CONCERNING
VIPERS:
TOGETHER
With a Diſcourſe touching their Poyſon:
By way of Reply, to a Letter written by
Signor <hi>FRANCESCO REDI,</hi>
to Meſſieurs <hi>BOURDELOT</hi>
and <hi>MORUS;</hi> Printed at <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi>
1670.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>MOYSE CHARAS.</hi>
Engliſh'd out of French.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi>Printed by<hi> T. R. </hi>for<hi> John Martyn </hi>Printer to the<hi> Royal
Society, </hi>at the<hi> Bell </hi>in S.<hi> Pauls Churchyard,</hi> 1673.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:98525:20"/>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:98525:20"/>
                  <head>A CONTINUATION
Of the
NEW EXPERIMENTS
CONCERNING
VIPERS.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>Finiſht in the Preſs at</hi> Paris, <date>
                        <hi>Auguſt</hi> 4. 1671.</date>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Believed, I had ſufficiently eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd
my opinion touching
the <hi>Poiſon</hi> of <hi>Vipers</hi> by abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
of Experiments, ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by Reaſons, heretofore
made publick: But there hath ſince appear'd
at <hi>Paris</hi> a Letter of Signor <hi>Redi,</hi> in which
he oppoſes my ſentiments: And he being a
perſon, whoſe merit hath acquir'd him a great
reputation among the Learned, that Letter
of his hath not been without making ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
in the minds of many, and in ſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
of thoſe, that had reliſh'd my opinion, in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98525:21"/>
favour of which they ſeem'd to have already
declared themſelves.</p>
                  <p>I might indeed have defended my ſelf as to
that which is againſt me in that Letter, ſoon
after it appear'd; having reaſons ſtrong and
numerous enough to maintain and juſtifie all
I had advanced in my writing: But I thought
it better to deferr it till Spring, to the end
that after I ſhould have made New Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and the more aſſur'd my ſelf of all, I
might, by a renew'd knowledge of the truth,
afterwards the better perſwade the publick
thereof. It will therefore appear by this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel
of Experiments, here ſet down, that I am
ſo far from changing my Opinion, that I have
reaſon to be more ſtrongly than ever confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
in what I embraced at firſt.</p>
                  <p>I do herewith ſincerely declare, that when
I publiſhed my book, my chief aim was,
faithfully to relate all the truths I had diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd,
and not to offend Signor <hi>Redi,</hi> whom I
exceedingly eſteem and honour for his rare
Talents, and whoſe friendſhip I hope to have
a ſhare in; ſo far was I from pretending to
do any thing that might make him write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
my Book, or from fore-ſeeing that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
I ſhould have occaſion to labour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
my ſelf againſt him: Which yet I ſince
found otherwiſe, by the Letter he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98525:21"/>
againſt me, and even without honoring
me with a Copy of it, wherewith he hath gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
many perſons at <hi>Paris</hi> and elſewhere, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
after I had had the advantage of ſome Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terary
Commerce with him, as I might eaſily
juſtifie.</p>
                  <p>I can beſides proteſt, that when I reſolved
to contradict certain points of his firſt Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
it was in a manner againſt my will, and
becauſe I could not at all diſpenſe with it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
I would have baffled my ſenſes, and that
light I ſaw my ſelf, together with a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of witneſſes. I can alſo aſſure, that I
ſhould now be very ready to un-ſay what I
have affirm'd upon this ſubject, and to agree
with him, if I were not altogether perſwaded
of the contrary in the main things he hath
written againſt my Sentiments.</p>
                  <p>After theſe Proteſtations, being well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
as well by Reaſon, as by many new Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments
newly made, that I have aſſerted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but what is true; I found<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſably
obliged to maintain it, and to
render a good office to the publick, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring
to ſhew that 'tis very difficult reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably
to oppoſe any thing to the contrary.</p>
                  <p>The difference between Signor <hi>Redi</hi> and
me conſiſts chiefly in this, That he Pretends,
the Jellow Liquor contain'd in the Veſicles
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98525:22"/>
of the Gums of Vipers, to be the only and
true ſeat of their Poiſon; That this juyce is
not venomous when taken at the mouth, but
that it is ſo when let into the wounds made
by a Viper whilſt ſhe is alive, and even in
thoſe, which ſhe may be forced to make ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
days after ſhe is dead, provided that yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
liquor do intervene; That the ſame li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
drawn from a live Viper, as well as that
of a dead one, is always venomous if let into
wounds, and mingled with the blood of the
Animal wounded, whether it be uſed when li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid,
or after it is dryed and reduced to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;
and that it generally kills all kind of
Animals into the wounds of which it ſhall
have been intromitted.</p>
                  <p>But I, who of all theſe points can admit of
none but that of the innocence of the yellow
liquor when taken at the mouth, and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
my ſelf to all the reſt; do ſay, That the
Poiſon of a Viper is no where but in her enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
Spirits; that the yellow juyce as well of
a live Viper, and even a vexed one, as of one
that is either newly dead, or hath been ſo for
ſeveral days, contains in it no poiſon at all,
neither in the biting, nor taken inwardly,
nor put into wounds, nor mingled with the
blood, nor any other way wherein it may be
uſed; that it kills nor infects any kind of ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98525:22"/>
and that it is nothing but a meer and
innocent <hi>Saliva.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The queſtion muſt principally be decided
by matter of Fact; though it may alſo be
cleared by very pertinent reaſons. I am far
from accuſing Signor <hi>Reds</hi> of unfaithfuleſs in
his Experiments; though they were not made
in publick as mine, and that ſome thing might
be ſaid as to the formalities of the biting, and
the uſing of the yellow liquor: His reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
is too well grounded to be blamed; and
this is the conſideration which troubles me
moſt. Mean time I ſee the contrary to what
he hath advanced againſt my Book; and the
truths which I there oppoſe are ſo clearly
ſeen in my Experiments firſt and laſt, as well
in thoſe I have made only in the preſence of
ſome curious perſons, as in thoſe I have late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
made in publick, and before a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of Phyſitians and other perſons very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent
in theſe matters. So that I can no<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
ought any longer to hide thoſe truths, which
are the chief inducement of writing this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
                  <p>We need not wonder that Signor <hi>Redi,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
made all his Experiments by order and
at the expence of ſo great a Prince, who is as
curious as he is Munificent, had Vipers and
all ſorts of Animals in far greater number than
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98525:23"/>
I had; I, who did all from my ſelf, at my own
charges, and with a meer deſire to diſcern
truth from falſhood. Nor do I think, I was
obliged to multiply expences when the truth
was found ſufficiently clear'd up, and all the
by-ſtanders acknowledged, that I had made
ſufficient tryals for every Experiment. For
ſince he hath contented himſelf with having
made ſome of the yellow liquor to be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
by one only Man, one only Duck, one
only Kid, thence to know and to aſſure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
of its innocence when ſwallow'd, without
making a greater number of Experiments;
He muſt not blame me for having candidly
bounded my curioſity, after I had in divers
things made many more Experiments, then
he mentions he hath made upon this ſubject;
as appears by what he writeth <hi>p.</hi> 17, &amp; 18. of
his firſt Letter. I find therefore, that he hath
no great cauſe to complain of me (as he doth,
under the name of <hi>thoſe Illuſtrious Authors,</hi> to
whom he aſcribes my Book in his Letter) for
not having vouchſafed to make Experiments
enow to confirm the truth of the Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
about Vipers, contain'd in his firſt Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of 1664. He had not, I ſay, great cauſe
to ſpeak of it after ſuch a manner, ſince I did
do ſo but in imitation of him, and becauſe he
had in the ſame Letter advanced and aſſured
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98525:23"/>
particulars, which required not I ſhould
make more tryals then thoſe I have deſcribed
in my Book: Although I can aſſure to have
made more then I have recited. He knows
very well, that about the end of pag. 23. of
his firſt Letter he uſed theſe words.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Equel veleno ſhizza tutto fuora, ſe non al
primo, almeno al ſecondo morſo; ſi che il terzo (epiù
volte l'ho eſperimentato) non è velenoſo:</hi>That is,<hi> And that poiſon iſſues all out, if not at
the firſt, at leaſt at the ſecond biting; ſo that
the third </hi>(which I have often experimented)<hi>is not venomous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if, becauſe of the reſpect I bear to the
writings of a perſon of ſo high a reputation, I
thought among divers other Experiments,
that having made one and the ſame Viper, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
time vexed, to bite five ſeveral Pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
which all died, and even the laſt of them
ſooner then the reſt, I might ſtop there; I
think Signor <hi>Redi</hi> hath nothing to reproach
me with. He had aſſured in his firſt Letter,
and aſſures the ſame in his latter, That all the
poiſon did lodge in the yellow liquor, and
that this poiſon was all exhauſted if not at
the firſt, yet at leaſt at the ſecond biting, and
that he had often experimented that the third
was no more venomous: So that, if I was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded,
that all the yellow Liquor muſt be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98525:24"/>
come out by the ſecond biting made upon the
ſecond Pigeon, and if, after that, I have ſeen
dye three other Pigeons by the freſh bitings
of the ſame Viper that had bitten the two firſt;
I do not think that Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath right to
accuſe me for not having done enough: He
might rather have done me that juſtice as to
acknowledge, that I had done more then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to maintain my Reflexions, and that I
was obliged from that time to ſeek the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
elſewhere then in the yellow liquor, in
regard it did no longer intervene, according
to him, in the three laſt bitings, and that the
three laſt Pigeons were as ſoon, yea ſooner,
dead then the two firſt, of the death of which
he could charge the yellow liquor. If I could
not find, no more then Sign. <hi>Redi,</hi> in all the
body of the Viper, any other viſible or pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
part that was venomous, and that
might juſtly be declared to be the ſeat of the
poiſon, and the true cauſe of the death which
enſued upon the three laſt bitings; he muſt
not wonder, if I have ſought and found it in
the <hi>vexed Spirits,</hi> and if I have grounded my
ſelf upon the beſt evidence, I could get from
Experiments and Reaſon.</p>
                  <p>But ſince the chief motive of my tryals hath
been the deſire of exactly knowing the Truth
concerning thoſe matters; having ſeen that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98525:24"/>
Sign. <hi>Redi, pag.</hi> 31. of his laſt Letter hath
deſired I would make new experiments after
his Objections againſt me: To be the more aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured
of all, I have been willing to give him
that ſatisfaction, in giving it to my ſelf. For,
in the moneth of <hi>May</hi> laſt, in the Chymical La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boratory
of the Royal Garden, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
of two or three hundred by ſtanders,
both Phyſitians and others, capable to judge
of it, and worthy to be credited; from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
many live Vipers, ſent me out of <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phine,</hi>
and divers parts of <hi>Poitou,</hi> I choſe a
great Femal-Viper, that was luſty enough
notwithſtanding the great way ſhe came, and
having open'd her jawes, I very carefully
cleared and ſqueezed out of them at ſeveral
repetitions, all the yellow liquor contained
in the bags of her gums, and that alſo which
might be diffuſed about the neighbouring
parts, with a fine piece of linnen cloth wound
about the handle of a pen knife: Which done,
I took the ſame Viper with Pincers about hér
neck, and angred her in making her to faſten
her teeth into the end of her tail, and in preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
from time to time her neck with thoſe
Pincers; and immediately after I preſented
to her five Pigeons and two Pullets one after
another, to bite them in the moſt fleſhy part
of their Cheſt, having irritated her every time
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98525:25"/>
of her biting. I purpoſely wounded alſo
ſix Pigeons and Pullets in divers places, in the
preſence of all the company, and let into the
wounds ſome drops of the yellow liquor,
drawn from the Veſicles of newly enraged Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.
I laid both ſorts a part; and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
parted about an hour after, before
which time, five of the Pigeons and Pullets,
that had been bitten, were dead, and the two
remaining died about an hour after; but the
Pigeons and Pullets, which I had wounded,
and in whoſe wounds I had put in ſome of the
ſaid juyce, ailed nothing, but that there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
ſome lividneſs, at the place wounded,
and ſuch an one as might have been there
from the ſole wounding them, and without
any concurrence of that liquor. Two days
after, I ſhew'd the company the ſame woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
Pullets and the ſame Pigeons, which
were very well, and had their wounds almoſt
perfectly healed up, only there remain'd a
little blewneſs about the wounded parts. I
would then have wounded the ſame animals a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
in other places, and intromitted freſh
yellow liquor: ſome alſo of the by-ſtanders
propoſed to let into one of theſe creatures
ſome of this yellow liquor by that way of
Transfuſion, that hath lately been made in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> of ſome ſtranger blood
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98525:25"/>
into the veins of men, that ſo this juyce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
mingled with the blood by the ordinary
circulation, it might be able to diſcover what
ever it could do. I readily complied with
their motion, whereupon the intromiſſion of
this liquor was attempted upon one of the
ſame Pigeons that had been wounded two
days before. One Phyſitian and two Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions
did the work one after onother, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
both the inciſion and the ligature of the
moſt diſcernable veſſels of the right wing:
But they let the Pigeon looſe ſo much blood,
that it dyed ſoon after. Seeing this, I ſaid,
that the Pigeon dyed only from the loſs of its
blood, and not from the letting in of the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
liquor; and that it would be neceſſary,
one only Chirurgion of the Company ſhou'd
make a new operation upon another of the
ſame Animals, that had been wounded 2 days
before, and upon whom that yellow Juyce had
alſo been tryed. The Operation was made
accordingly at the ſame time upon a Pullet,
which did not only eſcape again, but was ſeen
the next day and the following days by the
whole company to be very well; as were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
the other animals that had been wounded
again at the ſame time, and received of the
yellow liquor, though without the way of
transfuſion. Yet true it is, that one of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98525:26"/>
Pigeons, that had been the ſecond time woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
was found dead ſome time after its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
wounded, in a cloſe earthen Furnace, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
hot, and ſtanding cloſe by ſuch another,
where I then diſtilled ſome ſpirit and oyl of
Tobacco, and the death of which ought to
be imputed to the piercing vapors of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillation,
or to the exceſſive heat of the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace
in which it had been ſhut up, which
was found ſo hot, that the heat of it could not
be endured by ones hand; beſides that being
cloſed, almoſt no air could enter.</p>
                  <p>Which being thus paſſed, yet foraſmuch as
the reputation of Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> had acquired
him much eſteem and favour from many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
in <hi>Paris,</hi> I perceived ſome of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
yet inclined to doubt, whether this yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
Juyce were always innocent. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
having by me 4 Dogs of different bigneſs,
I preſs'd thoſe that ſeemed moſt to doubt,
that they would transfuſe or cauſe to be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed
ſome of that reputed poiſonous liquor
into all thoſe Dogs, or at leaſt into one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of them; but how inſtant ſoever I was,
no body would undertake it. It was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged,
that thoſe Animals were too Robuſt
to Succumb under ſuch an operation, ſince
the Pullet, that had endur'd it, and twice felt
the yellow liquor, had eſcaped as well as the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98525:26"/>
other Animals, that had been wounded again
at the ſame time with it, and that had alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
into them ſome of that liquor. Which
obliged me to proteſt, it was not my fault that
it was not experimented a freſh, and to pray
the company to take the refuſal of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
for an acknowledgment of the innocence
of the yellow liquor.</p>
                  <p>But not being ſatisfied herewith, I refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
the matter to the next day, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to have ready new Animals, of a leſſer
ſize than thoſe Dogs; the more amply to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie
the innoxiouſneſs of that Juyce by new
intromiſſions thereof into wounds.</p>
                  <p>I had then prepar'd ſix Pigeons, and two
Carlings; and engaged a perſon whom I knew
moſt favourable to Signor <hi>Redi,</hi> to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
the inciſion, and intromit the yellow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
as he ſhould think beſt. He made ſuch
wounds as he pleaſed, and he did even ſever
the skin of the fleſh round about the wounds
he had made, and ſo far, that I could not hold
to tell him ſmiling, he did more than Signor
<hi>Redi</hi> himſelf ſaid in his Letters he had done;
and added, <hi>Boni eſſe paſtoris tondere, non de
glubere,</hi> A good Shepherd did Sheer, not Flea
his Sheep.</p>
                  <p>One of the Catlings was bitten in the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilagineous
part of the Ear, without any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98525:27"/>
of blood at the place of the biting;
and it eſcaped. The other, which was much
leſs, and a very noted one by the blackneſs
of its colour and by having her ears cut off,
was purpoſely wounded on the upper part
of her neck behind, and alſo at the lower bone
of the hinder part of the head; its skin alſowas
ſeparated from the fleſh round about the
wound, and on both ſides, almoſt as far as to
the fore part of the neck: And then as much
of the yellow liquor as they would was put
into both ſides as well as into the wound.
This Cat held down her head, by reaſon
doubtleſs of the pain ſhe endured by having
in a manner been flead alive; feeling alſo ſome
pain in two other places, where ſhe had been
wounded and flead. Some of the by-ſtanders
began already to mutter, and ſaid, I ſhould be
caſt, and the Cat would certainly dye; yet
notwithſtanding the Cat did not dye, though
ſhe was very little and taken out from under
her dam; and ſhe was ſhew'd to the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
24 hours after, ſound and ſafe, although
ſhe had neither ſuck'd nor eaten any thing all
that time. And 'tis remarkable enough, that
this very Cat, having been returned to a Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar
to whom ſhe belonged, and being grown
big, hath yet to this day the hind-part of her
skull uncloſed at the place of her wound;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98525:27"/>
and notwithſtanding all that, &amp; the falling off
of ſome fleſh and skin, that were ſever'd from
the places where ſhe was flead, ſhe is very
lively and full of play, and very divertiſing
mimick geſtures.</p>
                  <p>The ſix latter Pigeons, that had been woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
at the ſame time, and received of the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
liquor, were likewiſe produced; and they
were yet kept five or ſix days with the other
Pigeons and Pullets that had been twice
wounded before; among which was that alſo
on which the transfuſion had been imitated.
At laſt they were killed, roſted, and eaten,
in good company, of which were ſome of
thoſe that ſaw them wounded; and that found
them very good and ſavoury meat.</p>
                  <p>Amidſt all thoſe Experiments I omitted not
to try, whether the heads of Vipers newly
dead, having yet their necks on, with all their
yellow liquor, would be able to kill Animals,
by making them to be bitten by them. I tryed
it upon Pigeons and Pullets, by thruſting the
teeth into them as deep as I could. I employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
alſo to the ſame purpoſe ſome whole Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
which I had found dead among the live
ones in the barrils, and which abounded in
the yellow liquor. But this was always with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any inconvenience to the Animals bitten,
ſo far was it from killing them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:98525:28"/>
I here paſs by many other Experiments
made at my houſe, in the preſence of ſeveral
Phyſitians, that did all agree in making out the
innocence of the yellow liquor, and in aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing
the poiſonouſneſs to the enraged ſpirits.</p>
                  <p>Yet I muſt not leave here un-mentioned,
what was done by three young Phyſitians, who
being perſwaded of the truth of my Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
as well concerning the innocence of the
yellow liquor, as that of bitings made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the angred ſpirits, cauſed their fingers to
be bitten, to ſtrifes, by a dead Viper having
yet all her yellow liquor, and that ſo deep,
that the blood of it appeared to all: But they
found no other inconvenience by it, but what
they might have felt from prickings made by
a needle.</p>
                  <p>I had certainly made a far greater number
of Experiments if I had not obſerved, that
Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> himſelf had already made many
for me, and for the maintaining of my Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
and among others that of <hi>pag.</hi> 26. of
his firſt Letter of Obſervations, where he
ſaith,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Si mori un pollaſtro morſicato, </hi>&amp;c. That is,<hi>There dyed a Pullet bitten by a Viper, the points
of whoſe teeth I had cut off; and out of whoſe
veſsicles I had ſqueezed out all that ill juyce that
it there.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:98525:28"/>
For, ſince by his own confeſſion, there dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
a Pullet by having been bitten by a Viper,
the points of whoſe teeth he had deſignedly
cut off, and all whoſe yellow liquor (which
he calls the ill juyce, and will have to be the
only ſeat of the poiſon) he had carefully
preſs'd out of the veſicles of her Gums; He
hath no more ground then I, to charge the
death of the Pullet upon a liquor, which was
there no more, nor upon the points of the
teeth, which he had cut off. And he cannot
avoid to accuſe with me the vexed ſpirits of
the Viper, and to fall into my opinion, <hi>viz,</hi>
That the venom of the Viper is not a groſs
matter, but ſomething inviſible and ſpiritual.</p>
                  <p>And to ſhew again, that Signor <hi>Redi</hi> hath
laboured, without being aware of it, to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
my Sentiment, and that at the ſame time he
manifeſtly contradicts himſelf, by deſtroying
in his laſt Letter his firſt Propoſitions, which
is, <hi>That all the venom of the Viper iſſues at the
firſt, or at leaſt at the ſecond biting, and that the
third is venomous no more,</hi> as he aſſureth to
have often experimented; to ſhew that, I ſay, I
ſhall alledge the words of pag. 33, 34, and
35. of his laſt Letter, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Su'l principio di maggio ſcelſi una vipera, </hi>&amp;c.
That is,<hi> About the beginning of </hi>May<hi> I choſe a
Femal-Viper, one of the biggeſt and luſtieſt, and</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:98525:29"/>
                     <hi>vexed her to bite ten Chickens, one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
in the right thigh; of which the firſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
and third died almoſt in an inſtant; the
fourth ſeem'd only to be ſick; but the fifth and all
the reſt did not only not dye, but were not at all
ſick; and yet every time the Viper did bite, I
angred and madded her exceedingly. In the
moneth of </hi>June<hi> I repeated the Experiment in
five tame Ducks, bitten by one and the ſame Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
which alſo immediately after bit three
young Turtle-Doves. The firſt wounded dyed
three hours after; the ſecond-five hours after;
the reſt eſcaped. 'Tis true, that the firſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd
of the Turtles dyed, but not the other two.
Of twelve Ring-Doves at one time there dyed
but four; but the next day of twelve others there
dyed ſix. Of five Rabbets there dyed three;
and of three Lambs the two laſt dyed; the firſt
of them dying two hours after it had been biten.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe ſeveral Experiments directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to the firſt aſſertion of Signor <hi>Redi,</hi>
were capable to perplex any other head but
<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is. For firſt, he hath ſeen, that of ten bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets
bitten one after another by one only Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
the three firſt dyed ſuddenly, and the
fourth was ſomewhat ſick; He hath ſeen, that
of five Ducks and of three Pigeons, bitten one
after another by a ſingle Viper, the two firſt
Ducks dyed, as alſo one of the Pigeons, which
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98525:29"/>
had been bitten even after the five Ducks: He
alſo ſaw once, that of twelve Pigeons bitten,
four dyed; that another time of twelve there
eſcaped but the moiety; and that of five Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets,
likewiſe bitten, there were but two that
evaded dying.</p>
                  <p>I cannot but be amazed, that all theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments
have not been able to change his
opinion, or at leaſt to ſuſpend it. Nor do I
doubt but that the number of Animals that
d<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed would have been much greater, if the
bitings had been made in other places but the
legs. For, beſides that they have their bones,
nerves, and tendons, that are able to blunt
the point of the teeth at the firſt biting; they
have alſo their Muſcles, which are very viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous,
and therefore fail not to imbue the teeth
of the biting Viper, thereby ſtopping in part
their Pores, and even hindring them by that
v<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcoſity from entring far in the enſuing bites,
and I likewiſe doubt not, but that will come
to paſs more and more in the reiteration of
their bitings. Nor do I wonder, that the
Ducks did not dye ſo ſoon as the Pullets or
Pigeons, nor that there dyed leſs of them; for,
beſides the reaſons juſt now alledged, they
have their skin, bones, and all parts much
harder, and far more difficult to be pierced
by the Vipers teeth, than thoſe of Pigeons or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98525:30"/>
Pullets. Now I do not find any part mo<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e
proper to try divers bitings, then the fleſhy
part of the cheſt, which hath neither Nerves,
nor Tendons, nor bones near, nor that Viſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity
found in the Muſcles of the legs.</p>
                  <p>Mean time theſe Experiments made by
Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> himſelf, muſt oblige him, as far as
I can judge, to relinquiſh his firſt Aſſertion:
And if he will perſiſt to maintain, that the
yellow liquor is the true ſeat of the poiſon,
he muſt needs believe that liquor to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exhauſtible,
and that always there ſucceeds
ſome freſh, in all the bitings of a Viper; or,
if he will abandon his opinion, and aſcribe
the poiſon no more to the yellow liquor, he
muſt find out ſome other ſubject to aſſign it
to, except he pleaſe to take mine, and to
lodge it in the irritated ſpirits; in regard that
he cannot find it in the yellow liquor, which
is no more there, after the ſecond biting (as
himſelf aſſureth;) and which muſt yet more
evidently be wanting there, when deſignedly
he had with care taken it out of the bags of
the gums of the Viper that bit the Pullet, and
the bite of which was followed by the death
of the Animal bitten.</p>
                  <p>But if Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> ſhould now be in an humor
to alter his opinion, and to judge the yellow
liquor to be neceſſary in all the bitings of a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98525:30"/>
Viper (though that be an impoſſible thing;)
his opinion would never be received by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intereſſed
perſons, that have ſeen my firſt and
laſt Experiments; among which perſons there
are ſome, even of the moſt able, who, having
heretofore examin'd the <hi>Salival Glanduls</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the deſcription I gave them of it after I
had diſcover'd them, did there obſerve alſo
ſome ſmall <hi>Lymphatic</hi> Veſſels, more numerous
then thoſe that had firſt appeared to me; and
who, having ſeen the laſt Letter of Sign. <hi>Redi,</hi>
were willing to ſuſpend their Judgment until
the making of my new Tryals, which have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
confirm'd them in my firſt opinion.</p>
                  <p>For, not to ſpeak of this, that in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
of divers perſons, even of the beſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
at ſeveral times and places, in divers aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies,
&amp; even in the Conferences of the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot
<hi>Bourdelot;</hi> I have ſwallow'd ſome of the
yellow liquor taken out of the bags of the
gums of many live and enraged Vipers, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
finding the leaſt inconvenience from it,
no more then the Viper-catcher of Sign. <hi>Redi:</hi>
I can boldly aſſure all the world, that at no
time, in no place, there ever dyed any animal
of all thoſe I have wounded, or ſeen wounded
on purpoſe, and into the wounds of which
that liquor hath been intromitted, although
it had been drawn hot out of the Veſicles of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98525:31"/>
the gums of Vipers exceedingly vexed; ſo far
is it, that the Juyce of dead Vipers was able
to annoy any animal. I can alſo aſſure, that
never any head of a dead Viper, whether the
Animal were who<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, or that head only with
its neck, and though it abounded with that
yellow liquor, hath done any harm to man or
any other Animal, bitten by it.</p>
                  <p>The yellow liquor, which I ſwallow'd in
one of the conferences of the Abbot <hi>Bourdelot,</hi>
puts me in mind of Letter, which M. <hi>Des
Tapieres,</hi> a very curious, ſincere and able A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary
of <hi>Bourbon l' Archamband,</hi> had
written to him, which was there read, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
other things did relate, That in the year
1630. he had taken a Viper, whoſe crook'd
teeth he had cut, and that he carried her in his
boſom; and that after two or three days, a fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
taking him to approach her to his face,
preſſing her a little, ſhe bit him in his lip, and
thereby cauſed great pain to him; whereupon
he flung her to the ground and in his anger
cruſht her in pieces; that his lip and face
ſwelled; that a Ligature was made upon him;
that Treacle was given him, and ſome of it
applied to the bite; that at the place of the
wound there appear'd a little bladder,
whence iſſued two or three drops of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
of a dark yellow colour, and that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98525:31"/>
his face remain'd very pale for a moneth.</p>
                  <p>If my opinion be asked about this Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment,
I declare that there is nothing in it,
which I ought not to believe; and I add alſo,
that there hapn'd nothing in it, which agrees
not with the principles by me eſtabliſh'd and
maintain'd. For, although the great teeth
of that Viper had been cut, which might have
gone further, and mingled the enraged ſpirits
of the Viper with the blood of <hi>M. Tapieres;</hi>
yet they had not cut the point of the ſmall
teeth, which I ſhew'd in the ſame conference
together with the other neighbouring parts
in the teath of a live Viper, ſent to Monſieur
<hi>Bourdelot</hi> by the ſame Apothecary that had
been bitten: of which ſmall teeth I have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore
given the deſcription and figure, as
well as that of the upper and lower Jawes, in
which they are faſtn'd, as may be ſeen in my
<hi>Anatomy of Vipers,</hi> in the <hi>Section</hi> of the teeth,
and the third <hi>Cut</hi> of that Pook. For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
thoſe little teeth have not the length
nor thickneſs of the great ones; yet they have
the ſame ſhape and the ſame matter; for they
are bony, crooked, tranſparent, and very
ſharp; ſo that the vexed ſpirits may paſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
them as into ſmall Funnels, and through
their Pores, as they do thorough thoſe of the
bigger ones: But they cannot go very deep,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98525:32"/>
becauſe their ſmalneſs permits them not to
carry their openings as far as into the fleſh;
and all they can doe, is, to open the skin.
Now to reaſon upon the accidents that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell
<hi>M. Des Trapieres</hi> by this bite, as they
are ſet down in his Letter; I ſee nothing in
them that is not very natural, and very credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
For, although the angred Spirits had
entred by the openings made by the ſmall
teeth; yet they could not penetrate the fleſh,
nor mingle with the blood, becauſe thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertures
were not deep enough, and they
could do no more but to make their effort
'twixt the fleſh and skin; whence follow'd
the ſwelling of the lip and face, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
of the pale colour, which appear'd
there during a moneth; which accidents
might at firſt have been eaſily prevented by
one only doſe of the volatil Salt of Vipers,
which would have made the enraged Spirits
to tranſpire, that lodged between the fleſh
and the skin, and could find no entry to paſs
further. As to the little bladder, which was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
at the place of the bite, and the two or
three drops of dark liquor that iſſued after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
that was nothing but a little ſerous
moiſture that had been gather'd there from
the neighbouring parts, and that had been
cauſed by the compreſſion of the Ligature,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98525:32"/>
and by the bruiſing made by the teeth and
Jawes at the time of the biting, and without
any intervention of the yellow liquor, which
beſides its innocence, could not have entred
through ſuch ſmall apertures.</p>
                  <p>After ſo many Experiments, and upon ſo
many Reflexions which I have made, as well
on the yellow liquor, as on the irritated ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
of Vipers, I cannot comprehend, how
the Animals of Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> could dye all and
without any exception by the intromiſſion
of the yellow liquor into the wounds, he had
made in them, and by the biting of heads ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd,
or by that of entire Vipers that had
been dead ſeveral days. I have too many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments
to the contrary, and too many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,
to put it out of doubt, and to fix me in
my firſt opinion.</p>
                  <p>But, to the end that among the Truths by
me advanced, and conſiſting in matter of fact,
the publick may find wherewith to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied;
I thought my ſelf obliged to explain my
ſenſe upon theſe matters, and to form to my
ſelf the Objections, that may be made againſt
me.</p>
                  <p>I ſay therefore concerning the <hi>Tellow Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor,</hi>
That nothing can act from it ſelf, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to its nature, the diſpoſition of the
matter of which it is compoſed, and the force
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98525:33"/>
of its activity. For example, you will not
find in River Water, the taſte, ſtrength, nor
particles that are found in Wine, nor will
<hi>that</hi> inebriate like <hi>this:</hi> it hath not the acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
nor penetrancy of Urine, neither the
colour not bitterneſs of Gall: The Spirit of
Wine, that is freed from the aqueous parts,
which hindred the Wine from producing the
effects it was capable of, is much more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile
and ſtrong, then the ſame wine whence it
hath been drawn: The Volatil Salt of Wine
hath quite another penetrating force than the
Urine which contained it before its ſublima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
And not to go from my ſubject; the
volatil Salt of Vipers is very different from
the fleſh and bones of them, whence it hath
been extracted; and, though in ſmall quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
it will work more in a moment as well by
its odour as its piercing vertue, than ten times
as much of that matter, whence it hath been
drawn, could effect in many hours: The bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leous,
ſharp, ſalt and ſpirituous ſeroſity, that
is often form'd in our bodies, will ſuddenly
produce inflammations in the eyes, tumors in
the cheeks, gums, throat, and many other
parts, as alſo Puſtuls, St. Anthony fire, and
the Gangrene it ſelf; and all that it does by
the compoſition of its parts, and the force of
its activity; whereas the thick and viſcous
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98525:33"/>
Phlegme will do no ſuch thing, but chargeth
nature only by its weight, cold, and tenacity:
This Phlegme, I ſay, will ever be incapable
of working with quickneſs, and it cannot
produce any effect out very ſlowly, and in
proportion to its power, which is extreamly
confined.</p>
                  <p>So then, it is not the nature of the yellow
liquor, to paſs ſwiftly to remote parts, and
there to act with vigor and violence;
which is obſerved in the poiſon of a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.
I ſay, that a tough, viſcous, and
in a manner inſipid <hi>Saliva,</hi> cannot make any
great progreſs in a moment. I affirm beſides,
that 'tis impoſſible, it ſhould corporally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
into the holes made by the teeth, which
are very ſmall and almoſt inviſible, and that it
ſhould alſo paſs through the cavities of the
teeth, and much leſs through their Pores, if
any would have them paſs that way. I ſay
further, <hi>that</hi> although the teeth of a Viper
ſhould be all over imbued with that Juyce at
the time of her biting; the skin of the Animal
bitten, and the fleſh it ſelf, if need were,
would keep it out of the bitten place, and
hinder it from entring there; <hi>That</hi> though it
ſhould be able to enter, it muſt have a fit
place to receive it, a great paſſage to go
through, and a long time to arrive to the parts
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:98525:34"/>
remote; I ſay alſo, that though it were arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
there, (if that were poſſible,) it could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
act beyond the forces, which nature hath
reſtrained it to.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, if this yellow liquor were capable
of any conſiderable operation, it would not
fail to diſcover it either in whole or in part,
when 'tis ſwallow'd and got into the ſtomach;
where the place, the heat, and all things
would ſeem to concur <hi>either</hi> to make it fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
if its matter were diſpoſed for it, <hi>or</hi> to
reduce its power into action: For, by paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
out of the ſtomach into the inteſtins it
would infect the Chyle, and make of it a poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
which would be carried jointly with it
through the milky veſſels, and through the
Thoracique Ductus'<hi>s,</hi> ſo happily diſcover'd
by the illuſtrious <hi>M. Pecquet,</hi> to deſcend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Heart with the blood, the which is the
matter, on which the poiſon of Vipers does
ſo particularly exert its dominion. And this
way is much more eaſie and large, than that of
the opening, made by the teeth, by which
this juyce cannot ſo much as enter. I ſay this
further, that, if it were ſuch as Sign. <hi>Redi</hi>
makes it to be, it would, being taken at the
mouth and let down into the ſtomach, impreſs
upon the places of its paſſage, and thoſe of its
ſtay, ſome mark or other of its power, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98525:34"/>
if it did contain any <hi>Arſenical</hi> Salts,
which would not fail, ſoon to manifeſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
either by their taſte or by ſome other
effects: And yet all thoſe that ſhall taſte or
ſwallow this yellow liquor, ſhall never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
any malignity whether great or ſmall,
neither in the mouth, nor in the ſtomach, nor
elſewhere. I conclude therefore from all
theſe conſiderations, that this juyce contains
in it no part at all, that is able to diſſolve, or
coagulate, or diſcompoſe any part of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;
&amp; that it hath not any quality, manifeſt or
occult, to ſhew that 'tis capable of doing ſo.</p>
                  <p>I add moreover, that this juyce, as flat and
ſalivous as it is, is always found ſo yellow in
all parts of <hi>France,</hi> that it can hardly be leſs
colour'd than 'tis in <hi>Italy;</hi> and that they both
muſt have altogether alike qualities, or, at
leaſt, very near ſuch. And it would be to
no purpoſe, to alledge in favour of Sign. <hi>Redi,</hi>
that the diverſity of places and climate, or
that of aliments might be able to change the
nature of Vipers, and cauſe that manifeſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,
there is between his Experiments
and mine. For, although ſome diverſity may
be obſerved in other things, there can be
found none in this; and if there could be ſome
difference, it cannot be that the nature of the
yellow juyce, and that of the Spirits ſhould
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98525:35"/>
be <hi>quite</hi> changed; ſince we find in <hi>France</hi> the
ſame marks in that liquor, which Sign. <hi>Redi</hi>
hath found and deſcribed in that of <hi>Italy,</hi> and
ſince our Vipers, without any intervention
of that juyce, do kill as nimbly as his can do.</p>
                  <p>But I think it would be much, if in the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
liquor, or in the enraged ſpirits, there
could be obſerv'd any <hi>ſmall</hi> degree of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
ſtronger or weaker in <hi>Italy</hi> than in <hi>France.</hi>
For, I have by a great number of experiments
made it out, that all the Vipers of <hi>France,</hi>
though taken in very different places, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
ſuch as are ſix ſcore Leagues diſtant from
one another, have their poiſon altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
and do kill equally. Whence I inferr,
that the difference of the Vipers of <hi>Italy</hi> and
<hi>France,</hi> cannot be conſiderable; ſince <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiné,</hi>
which is a Province in <hi>France</hi> that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth
us with many of them, and is very
mountainous as well as <hi>Italy,</hi> borders upon
<hi>Picmont,</hi> which is the beginning of <hi>Italy;</hi>
and that the ſame <hi>Dauphiné,</hi> abounds in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
in its utmoſt extremity; and ſince alſo
all Vipers, we get from thence, have their yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
liquor always very innocent, though high
colour'd. And I can truly ſay, that thoſe
Vipers, that have ſerv'd me moſt both in my
firſt and laſt experiments, were moſt of them
ſent me out of <hi>Dauphiné,</hi> and that I was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:98525:35"/>
to make uſe of ſuch, as being commonly
bigger than moſt of thoſe that were ſent me
out of <hi>Poictou;</hi> that, at leaſt, which ſerv'd
me to bite the five firſt Pigeons, which I ſpake
of in my firſt Experiments; and that which
bit the ſeaven laſt Pullets and Pigeons, were
of thoſe of <hi>Dauphiné,</hi> and even of the bigger
ſort that could be procured.</p>
                  <p>And it would have been to no purpoſe to
have uſed any tooth of a Viper ſever'd from
the head, and much leſs to wipe it dry with
ſome bread crums, in hopes it ſhould kill any
Animal by pricking it therewith; ſeeing the
teeth, that had of the yellow liquor upon
them, without being ſeparated from the dead
heads, were not able to do any harm, no not
thoſe of live ones, without the concurrence of
the enraged ſpirits. And if ſometimes I have
made uſe of bread-crums, ſometimes of a ſine
linnen ragg, to wipe away all the yellow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
of the veſicles, that was never but in
live Vipers; to ſhew, that it was not that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
which did kill, but the vexed Spirits
only, entring by means of the biting.</p>
                  <p>We are not to imagine neither, that a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
teareth by biting, unleſs having made her
to thruſt her teeth into the fleſh of ſome ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal,
you do immediately after draw her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
by the reſt of her body: We are not, I
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98525:36"/>
ſay, to pretend, that a Viper doth, by biting
of her own accord, make any great opening,
at which the yellow liquor is able to enter.
For, ſhe doth no more but thruſt in her teeth
far enough, and preſently draw them out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
with as much eaſe as a Cat draws out his
claws when he will. Beſides, you cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
but two very little holes, which do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
ſeem as 'twere cloſed again by the fleſh,
and which would hardly be diſcern'd, if the
pain of the bite, or the accidents enſuing, did
not oblige us to look very narrowly to it.</p>
                  <p>We alſo never ſee, that the poiſon faſtens
it ſelf to the part bitten, nor that the evil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
by a mortification, or by a gangrene
there. For, if that were ſo, and if the venom
did lodge at the entry, it would be much
more eaſie to maſter it. I know alſo by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Experiments, that the poiſon never ſtays
at the place where it enters, but inſinuates it
ſelf very nimbly into the Veines, to mingle
with the blood; eſpecially if the bite hath
open'd for it a paſſage free enough to arrive
there. I know, that there it produces after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
thoſe troubleſome accidents, which
enſue upon the biting; and that laſtly it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
death, if it be not prevented by a quick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.
Which clearly ſhews, that a poiſon of
this nature muſt needs have diſpoſitions to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98525:36"/>
penetrate, very differing from thoſe that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
in a yellow liquor, that is incapable of
all ſudden motion and operation.</p>
                  <p>It would alſo prove an uſeleſs labour, to
ſuck at the place of the biting, in hopes of
getting out from thence a Juyce, which could
not enter there. And though I do not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
this way of ſuccours on ſuch occaſion;
yet I know, that all what the ſucking can do,
is, to fetch out again part of the enraged ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
that had enter'd by the openings of the
bite. I know alſo, that a ſpecifique reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
taken at the mouth, is far better.</p>
                  <p>I would be in vain, to object unto me the
example of the ſeed of Animals, which, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
its viſcoſity, ſerves daily to
propagate that <hi>Species</hi> which produces it;
and that it could in like manner come to paſs
in the yellow liquor to convey the venom in
the biting. For beſides that the ſeed is the
pureſt and moſt elaborat part which an ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
can produce; it is alſo accompanied
with ſtore of Spirits; and there needs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
the concurrence of many other means
as well to introduce and to receive it, as to
form and perfect the <hi>Foetus:</hi> There is more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over
neceſſary an aſſiſtance of abundance of
ſpirits from the mothers ſide; a juyce pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate
and proper for its nouriſhment and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98525:37"/>
increaſe, and a ſufficient time for the ſame.
Whereas the yellow liquor, <hi>that</hi> can paſs for
nothing but a juyce excreted out of the Sali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val
Glanduls, after it had been ſent thither
from the brain and the neighbouring parts,
and <hi>that</hi> is deſtitute of ſpirits and of all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
to act; wants alſo a paſſage ſufficient
to intromit it, and a place proper to lodge
in. And if you ſhould grant it an entry, and
a place to ſojourn in; it muſt have a much
longer time than the ſeed, of which I was ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.
But with all this time and all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
circumſtances, it would ſtill be incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
of working any thing at all perfect, and
periſh of it ſelf; without any remarkable
production.</p>
                  <p>If any ſhould ſay, That this yellow liquor
may have ſpirits proper and proportionate
to its nature, and that they are not wanting to
make the poiſon work at the moment of the
biting; but that, being drawn out of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicles,
and expoſed to the Air, thoſe ſpirits are
diſſipated, and thereby render it incapable
of all action: I anſwer, That, without ſtaying
upon what I have amply made out of its inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence
in all kind of uſes, Signor <hi>Redi</hi> himſelf
contradicts it, as I have mentioned above;
ſince he pretends, that the Juyce even of ſuch
Vipers as have been dead for ſeveral days, &amp;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:98525:37"/>
that is dryed to boot, ceaſeth not to inſinuate
its venom without any intervention of ſpirits,
when it is put into wounds. But, beſides all
that, many Experiments have evinced to me,
that death follows the biting without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention
of the yellow liquor, and then
when it hath been perfectly wiped away.
Moreover, it is well known, that 'tis the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of ſpirits, to be in motion, to faſten them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
to, and to follow the parts that have
moſt of them, as for example, the blood. It
is alſo to be noted, that the ſpirits, that do
inſinuate the poiſon, are not of the nature of
thoſe that follow the ordinary motion of the
blood of the animal; <hi>that</hi> they do not joyn
themſelves to it, as thoſe; and <hi>that</hi> neither of
them have any union with the yellow liquor;
which is but a meer excrement: But that the
<hi>Spirits,</hi> I ſpeak of, do form themſelves in the
moment that the Viper conceives the <hi>Idea</hi> of
revenging her ſelf; and they need not the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baraſment
of ſuch a dull and viſcous juyce,
which is not qualified to follow them, nor to
paſs through the imperceptible pores of the
teeth, which the ſpirits only can penetrate,
no more then they can any ways enter through
the holes, which the teeth have made. In a
word; the nature of a groſs, tough and viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous
juyce is not, to act, penetrate, and be
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98525:38"/>
wiftly carried to the moſt remote parts of the
body; but that belongs to ſpirituous ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,
to go and come where groſs corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
ones cannot. Theſe are the only ſpirits,
that can ſubvert the whole Oeconomy of the
body; they are they, that diſturb the circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
of the blood, and that corrupt it; they
are they, that ſtop the natural and animal ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
and hinder them from paſſing to the
parts of the body as they were wont to do;
and laſtly, 'tis by the let of them, that the
death of the Animal uſually enſueth the biting.</p>
                  <p>As to what may be objected, that 'tis very
difficult, ſo exactly to evacuate the yellow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor,
that there remain none at all; and that
it may very well come to paſs, that a little of
it intervenes in all bitings: I anſwer, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
that this is alſo againſt the opinion of
Sign. <hi>Redi,</hi> and which he hath renounced in
his firſt Aſſertion; the Salival Glanduls,
though many in number, yet are too ſmall and
have too little capacity to contain juyce e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to furniſh for that purpoſe; and that
that cannot be expected but from great ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals,
that have thoſe Salival glanduls and the
other parts far bigger: And though it were
poſſible, they ſhould ſufficiently furniſh, I
do maintain, that the impoſſibility of intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
that juyce, and its evinced innocence,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98525:38"/>
ought to ſuffice for confuting this Objection.</p>
                  <p>Yet this I ſhall here ſay in favour of Sign.
<hi>Redi,</hi> That I doubt not but that this yellow
liquor, as Salivous and Excrementitious as it
is, contains its Volatil Salt, as well as all the
other parts of a Viper, and all the parts of
Animals, and even all their excrements, and
that conſequently it is to be reputed ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.
But then, beſides that theſe ſpirituous
ſubſtances are never hurtful, they are yet too
intimately mixed and locked in with their
matter, and they cannot produce their effects
without being ſeparated from it; which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be but by a violent heat, and in veſſels fit
for it. I ſay therefore, that by art there may
be extracted a true Volatil Salt out of this
yellow liquor, &amp; even without any addition
or mixture of other matter; which may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
to be of the ſame nature with that of the
other parts of a Viper; and that 'tis ſo far from
being able to work like poiſon, that t'is very
proper and effectual to maſter all the ill acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,
which the bite of a Viper may cauſe;
of which I do accuſe the enraged ſpirits alone.
Since therefore Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath dried and
laid aſide the yellow liquor of two hundred
and fifty Vipers, and may eaſily obtain much
more of it; 'tis in his power to extract ſuch
a ſalt out of it, when he pleaſeth, to verifie
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:98525:39"/>
what I was juſt now ſaying: And if, to ſave
himſelf that labour, by reaſon of his other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant
occupations, he ſhall pleaſe to ſend
me a competent quantity thereof, I do with
all my heart offer my ſelf to prepare it for
him, thereby to let him ſee not only the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence
of this juyce, but alſo the great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,
that is hid in it.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the <hi>Bilious Breath</hi> of a Viper,
that may be charged to intervene with this
yellow liquor, and to envenom it; I am of
opinion, that that is nothing but a diſguiſe of
the enraged ſpirits. I aſſert, <hi>That</hi> the true
Breath of a Viper is ever innocent, how bili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
ſoever it be repreſented; <hi>that</hi> there iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues
not any ill ſcent out of her throat, nor
out of her guts, nor from the parts made to
void the excrements; <hi>That</hi> Vipers among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
marks are in this different from Snakes,
that <hi>theſe</hi> have their excrements and the parts
containing them very fetide and of a ſmell of
ſtinking Urine; whereas you cannot perceive
any ill ſmell in any part of a Viper; <hi>that</hi> the
Spirits which carry the venom are quite ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
thing than the breath coming from the
Lungs; <hi>that</hi> thoſe ſpirits have no union nor
correſpondence with the Bilious humour;
<hi>that</hi> they are not formed but at the inſtant of
the irritation; and laſtly, <hi>that</hi> they need no
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:98525:39"/>
ſuch thing as an excrementitious and uſeleſs
liquor, pretended to intervene, fit for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but to gard the paſſage of the place,
through which the vexed ſpirits have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</p>
                  <p>But the better to ſhew the impoſſibility of
the intervention of this breath, and to make
it appear, that it never contributes any thing
to the poiſon; you may take notice, that a
Vipers head cut off, ſeparate from the Lungs
and all communication with the Gall, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable
to yield any breath, and deprived
even of all that yellow liquor; yet failes
not to kill by its biting as long as 'tis alive,
if the animal have been provoked; juſt as
would come to paſs, if a bite were made by
the head of a Viper that is whole and alive,
if no remedy were applied.</p>
                  <p>Touching the Communication, that may
alſo be pretended to be between the bladder
of Gall and the yellow liquor, by reaſon of
ſome reſemblance of colour; I ſay, that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<hi>that</hi> my Sentiments in theſe matters are
very conform to thoſe of Sign. <hi>Redi; that</hi> we
have both of us juſtified the innocence of the
juyce contained in the Bladder of Gall; <hi>that</hi>
we have denied, there is any veſſel carrying
this better juyce into the veſicles of the gums,
to make that yellow liquor which is found
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98525:40"/>
there: and laſtly, <hi>that</hi> we have unanimouſly
contradicted the errors of the Antients about
this pretended channel; beſides this; I ſay,
the truth of what we have affirmed is very
eaſie to prove, by taſting the yellow liquor of
the Gall, which is very bitter and very ſharp,
though very innocent, and by comparing it
with that of the veſicles of the Gums, which
is very flat, though equally innocent. The
ſame may be yet better made out by diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
one or more Vipers; where, no more
than in Serpents and all other animals, you
will never find any veſſel, that carries<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this
bile of the Bladder of Gall to the Gums; and
you will there ſee nothing but veins and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries
filled With true blood. Of this there
will be no doubt, if you pleaſe only to taſte
it; for you will find nothing but the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
taſte of blood. To be yet more aſſur'd of
it, you may taſte all that runs out of the body
of a Viper when the head is ſever'd from her;
for you ſhall find no bitterneſs at all, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
taſt but that of blood. And beſides, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
amply verified, that the yellow liquor
comes from the Salival glanduls alone, and
having given a very exact deſcription of
them; I think it needleſs to ſay any more of
it, what ever the Antients may have written,
or the Moderns may ſay of that ſubject.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:98525:40"/>
To come now to the <hi>enraged Spirits</hi> of a
Viper, which I do aſſure to be the true and
only ſeat of the poiſon; methinks Sign. <hi>Redi</hi>
hath no reaſon to oppoſe my opinion, when
I do intereſs in it the imagination of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
or her <hi>Idea</hi> of revenge, for the formation
of thoſe Spirits. I might here alledge what
<hi>Van Helmont</hi> ſaith in his Chapt. <hi>De Tumul<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
Peſtis,</hi> viz. That not only the <hi>Idea</hi> and the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination
of terror are formed in the inward
<hi>Archeus</hi> of the perſon invaded by the Plague;
but that the Toad, which hath, <hi>as he ſaith,</hi> a
perpetual hatred againſt man, finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
taken, and hanged by one of his hind-legs,
and in a condition of dying, conceives an
<hi>Idea</hi> and an imagination of terror by the
ſight of the man, that often preſents himſelf
before his eyes, and whom he looks upon as
his capital enemy, and that the ſame <hi>Idea</hi> or
the ſame phancy of terror, which the Toad
hath conceived by this means, forms in him
ſuch impreſſions and qualities, as are perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
even after his death. Then this Author
will, that of this body, that dyed in thoſe <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas</hi>
of terror, mingled with the parts that
have iſſued thence, and with the wax that
ſhall have received them, you ſhall make Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſque's,
which being taken inwardly, and
carried about you, or applied, ſhall have the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:98525:41"/>
virtue of curing as well as preſerving from
the Plague, by mortifying by their Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique
quality the terror which the inward <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi>
of the perſon may have conceived of
this evil. Now ſince this Sentiment of <hi>Van
Helmont</hi> hath found place in the minds of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
men, yery capable to judge of it; who
have been thence induced even to make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
that preparation of Toads, which he
hath taught in the ſame <hi>Chapter,</hi> and which I
can aſſure I have my ſelf made to ſatisfie the
deſire of very able Phyſitians; having alſo
known many perſons giving great credit to
it, and carrying continually about them of
thoſe Trocheſques whilſt there was talk of
the Plague; methinks, that the formation of
the enraged ſpirits, which I aſcribe to the
<hi>Idea</hi> and imagination of revenge, conceived
by the Viper when ſhe is vexed, is incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably
more maintainable, and much eaſier to
be comprehended, as well as the entry of the
angred Spirits through the Openings made
by the Teeth; becauſe not only theſe Aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
are wont to be deep, but alſo becauſe
the teeth being hollow, ſerve for a Funnel to
intromit thoſe ſpirits, that accompany the
biting, and that produce afterwards in the
body bitten thoſe diſmal effects of vengeance,
which the Viper had conceived when ſhe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:98525:41"/>
felt the ill done her; And the letting in of
thoſe Spirits through the cavity of thoſe
teeth is ſo much the more eaſie, becauſe there
is alſo at the end of each great tooth a hole,
which, though very ſmall and almoſt undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable
by the eye, may yet be diſcerned by
a Microſcope, &amp; hath accordingly been late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſeen in ſome publick Aſſemblies at <hi>Paris,</hi>
in the preſence even of perſons very affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate
to Sign. <hi>Redi.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What ſhall we ſay of the imagination of
Fright and Conſtraint, that a Toad alſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes
in a <hi>Wecſel,</hi> which having ſeen and
been ſeen by that ugly animal, at a certain
ſeaſon of the year, and always in ſummer, can
not avoyd to run a pretty while round about
it making a continual ſhrill noyſe, as if ſhe cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
for help, whilſt the Toad remains move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
with his throat open; and which after a
long troubleſome motion is conſtrain'd to
come and render her ſelf into that throat.
The thing is too well known in divers places
of <hi>France</hi> to doubt of it; and I can aſſure to
have heretofore ſeen it my ſelf; and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
I had well obſerv'd and withal wondred
at the force of thoſe <hi>Idea's,</hi> appearing in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation
of the Weeſel, and in her being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained
to fall into the mouth of the Toad,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98525:42"/>
I had the ſatisfaction to kill the Toad in
that moment, and ſo to ſave the Weeſel,
which quickly run away, finding her ſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd
by the death of the animal, which was
followed by the extinction of thoſe <hi>Ideas,</hi> that
before had had ſo much power over her. This
effect cannot be adſcribed to the foam, nor
to any material part of the Toad, ſince the
Weeſel flyes from him naturally, and falls not
into his mouth but in ſpight of her teeth. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
that the foam of the Toad, which the
Weeſel failed not to meet with in his throat,
can work nothing, ſeeing the Weeſel ſaved
her ſelf immediately after the death of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal.
We therefore muſt needs ſeek for
the cauſe of all theſe effects in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</p>
                  <p>More-over, what will Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> ſay of
a mad dog, which, in the pervertion of all
his ſenſes and of all the ordinary functions
of his body, breaths after nothing but miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief,
and makes it his buſineſs to reduce
into the ſame miſerable condition all men
he ſees, and even his own maſter, as well as
all animals he can come near and bite? If
then the mad Dog hath the power to make
paſs the ſame <hi>Idea's</hi> and the ſame imagination,
which have ſeized on him, into all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:98525:42"/>
that he can come to bite, and into man
himſelf, though of a very different ſoul and
nature from his, by doing no more than with
the edge of his teeth to touch the ſuperfice of
the skin, and that through his coaths that
may retain and wipe off all the foam adhering
to the teeth, and lyable to be accuſed of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
a hand in the miſchief; as is very well
obſerv'd by <hi>Van Helmont</hi> in the ſame Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?
If, I ſay, this dog hath the power of
communicating his evil to all ſorts of animals,
from one to another, without a limit, and
without excepting any kind; Why ſhould he
think it incredible, <hi>that</hi> a Viper is able by
her biting to carry her enraged ſpirits into
the bodies of ſuch men and other animals as
ſhe can light upon; <hi>That</hi> theſe ſpirits are
capable to kill the animal bitten; and <hi>that</hi>
they effect this by the perturbation and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,
they introduce into the whole maſs
of blood; foraſmuch as they do manifeſtly
hinder its circulation, and the communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the natural ſpirits, that were wont to
be conveyed into all the parts? Conſidering
withal, that they do not extend themſelves as
far as thoſe of the bite of a mad Dog; ſeeing
none of the Animals bitten by a Viper, have
any venom diffuſible either by their biting,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:98525:43"/>
or otherwiſe, as long as they live, and that
they may be ſafely handled, and even with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
danger eaten after their death.</p>
                  <p>I ſay beſides, that if it be true, that a man,
who hath at all times the ſame ſpitle and the
ſame teeth, &amp; who hath them not pointed nor
ſhaped like thoſe of a Viper, is capable to
introduce the Gangrene, and to cauſe death
it ſelf by a bite made by him in a rage; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
another and longer bite, made by the ſame
man not enraged, is not accompanied with
any ill accident, and is healed like a ſimple
wound; This being true, I ſay, we ought to
think it neither ſtrange nor impoſſible, that
a Viper, which hath long and piercing teeth,
and which ſhews the force of her being vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by the nimbleneſs of her biting, ſhould
be able, by biting when enraged, to make
animals feel the mortal effects of her vexed
ſpirits.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall we ſay of the pricking of a <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantula</hi>
how ſlight ſoever? ſhall we declare it
to be exempt from the <hi>idea</hi> and imagination
of this little animal, ſince it impreſſes it ſo
ſtrongly and differently upon perſons that
have been pricked therewith, inſomuch that
it perverts in part the ſenſes and ſpirits,
conforms them to his ſtirring and skipping
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:98525:43"/>
nature, and conſtrains them at certain and
ſet times to continual dancing for ſeveral
days, and which having left a contumacious
leaven of the ſame <hi>idea's,</hi> faileth not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
the ſame effects every year, and, if you
may believe Authors, as long as the <hi>Tarantula</hi>
liveth, and until the ſame <hi>idea's</hi> be extinct by
its death. And though I doubt not but
that Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath ſeen very many examples
of perſons pricked by <hi>Tarantula's,</hi> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ſtore of them in <hi>Italy;</hi> yet I ſhall not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear
here to recite that of a <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier,
who hath been theſe four years among
the <hi>French</hi> infantry. This Souldier, whom
his Camarads call'd <hi>Tarante,</hi> becauſe he had
been pricked by a <hi>Tarantula,</hi> is ſtill to this
very day in the Royal Regiment of <hi>Rouſſillon.</hi>
He never failed to feel every year at a deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
time <hi>(viz.</hi> about the 24<hi>th</hi> of <hi>July)</hi>
the effects of that ſting, which he had receiv'd
before he came into <hi>France.</hi> He was always
ſure of the time about two or three days near
it. And when the <hi>ideas</hi> of the ſting were
found exalted to a degree capable to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
their effects, he began to dance, and
deſired to hear without interruption the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins,
which the Officers of that Regiment cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to be play'd for him out of charity; to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98525:44"/>
which he anſwer'd continually, keeping time
very well, without being tired, for three
days, eating and drinking, without interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of his dance; and being very impatient
of any diſcontinuance of the play of the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins,
and that the more, if the intermiſſion
was any thing long; for then he became alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
livid, and fell into grievous ſwound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.
He pleaſed himſelf whilſt he danced,
to have in his hands ſeveral naked ſwords,
one after another; to ſee about him many
Looking-glaſſes, to behold himſelf in them
dancing; to be environed with much people,
and, that he might hinder them from going
away, to take from them their Gloves, Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons,
and ſuch other things; being very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
to keep all he had taken from them unto
the fourth day, which being come, his ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſs
to dance abated, and at length quite
ceaſed; he remembring all he had done, and
knowing all that were about him, to every
one of whom he rendred very exactly and
without any miſtake all he had taken from
them, though he had to do with a thouſand
people. After which time, he paſs'd the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder
of that year, and the whole interval
of his Paroxyſines without any inclination
to dance. He was naturally melancholick,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:98525:44"/>
in appearance of no great parts, neither had
he learn'd to dance. He hath been ſeen thus
dancing every year by thouſands of people,
and particularly in the Camp Royal <hi>Anno</hi>
1670. where the King himſelf and the whole
Court ſaw him. And this hath been ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial
to him, that the ordinary time is paſt
this year without any aſſault of this evil,
which he had great apprehenſions of, finding
himſelf at that time engaged in a march,
and fearing he ſhould want Violins at the
time that the ſit ſhould take him.</p>
                  <p>Now ſince the pricking of this Animal,
though very ſmall, and in a manner like that
of a ſmall fly, being made even thorough
ſtockings or cloaths, is able to act equally
upon the body and the mind of the perſon
ſtung; as leaving behind ſuch long and
ſtrong impreſſions, and cauſing ſuch irkſome
returns; To what can we adſcribe all thoſe
different effects, if it be not to the <hi>idea</hi> or i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination
of the animal ſtinging, or of the
perſon ſtung. 'Tis needleſs, to alledge
here the effects of the <hi>idea</hi> or imagination of
Women with Child, nor of that of <hi>Jacob's</hi>
Sheep. I think I have ſaid enough to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
the poſſibility of the <hi>idea</hi> or imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of a Vipers revengefulneſs, for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:98525:45"/>
of angry ſpirits, ſufficient to impute
unto them all the venom, and to exclude from
it the yellow liquor.</p>
                  <p>After this, Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> muſt not wonder,
if I, <hi>who</hi> make profeſſion of Chymiſtry, (of
which I have the honour to read publick Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures
in the Garden Royal) <hi>who</hi> doe every
day exerciſe my ſelf in ſeparating the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
parts from the groſs ones in mixt ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimat
bodies; and <hi>who</hi> have not been able
to find in any corporeal and ſenſible matter
the true cauſe of the ſtrange and ſuddain pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions,
obſerved in the biting of a live
Viper; If I, after all this, I ſay, have thought
my ſelf obliged to ſeek for it in the <hi>Spirits;</hi>
if having found it there, I have abandon'd
his party, and communicated to the publick
the diſcovery I have made.</p>
                  <p>Yet I am not over-much ſurpriſed, that
Sign, <hi>Redi,</hi> being in this matter prepoſſeſs'd
by corporeal groſs things, ſtill perſiſts in his
ſentiment, ſince in the preparations, that do
altogether depend of my profeſſion, and
which I ought to know well, he rejects ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituous
ſubſtances, which he reliſhes not,
ſticking only to the more material, which
are the leaſt, and in very ſmall quantity;
which doth not keep him from believing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:98525:45"/>
them to be the beſt. You may ſee, what he
writeth of it about the end of <hi>pag.</hi> 76.
and at the beginning of <hi>pag.</hi> 77, of his
firſt Letter of Obſervations, in theſe
words.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In queſte nuè naturali Oſſervationi ho con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuinato
gran quantitá, &amp;c. </hi>That is,<hi> In theſe my
natural Obſervations </hi>I<hi> have ſpent a great
quantity of Vipers, making of them daily a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
great ſlaughter; and, to extract the ſubtile
from the ſubtil (if </hi>I<hi> may ſo ſpeak) </hi>I<hi> always laid
aſide and kept all their fleſh and bones, which
being dryed in a Furnace, and afterwards by a
quick fire with long and great labour burnt and
reduced to aſhes, </hi>I<hi> thence drew the Salt with
Fountain-water, and purified it, and reduced
it into a kind of Chryſtal, </hi>&amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe that know all the parts of which
the body of a Viper is compoſed, will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
wonder, that a perſon ſo judicious
and knowing hath not found, that the chief
and beſt part of a Viper conſiſts in its vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til
Salt, and that that Salt would not fail to
avolate and to be waſted by that preparation
or rather deſtruction, which Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath
uſed to extract the Salt of Vipers. They will
quickly ſee, that when he would draw the
ſubtil from the ſubtil (as he ſpeaks) he did
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:98525:46"/>
quite the contrary, and expelled and diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated
the volatil and better parts, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning
only the groſs, the fixed and the leaſt.
They will ſoon judg, that he ſhould not have
given himſelf all that labour and pain, which
he ſaith he hath taken, to ſucceed ſo ill in his
work; and that he had done much better,
with ſilence to paſs over his proceſs, then to
publiſh it. The way, by him taken, will
be found, I think, received from the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients,
who knew not, that all Animals a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound
in <hi>Volatil,</hi> and have little of <hi>Fixed</hi>
Salt: And his preparation, which is very
eaſie, would have pleaſed better in thoſe
times, eſpecially in <hi>Italy,</hi> then that great and
laborious Preparation of the Salt of Vipers,
which was made with ſo great an <hi>Apparatus,</hi>
and of which I have already given my
thoughts, when I diſcourſed of the Remedies
drawn from Vipers.</p>
                  <p>I alſo foreſee, that Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
any greater advantage by ſtriving to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
to himſelf the firſt diſcovery of the
<hi>Salival glanduls,</hi> which I found on both the
Temples of both Male and Female Vipers,
and which I have deſcribed and delineated
in my Anatomy of Vipers: For, he will not
be able to perſwade it to thoſe, who ſhall
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:98525:46"/>
ſee <hi>pag.</hi> 44. of his firſt Letter of Obſervations
the diſcourſe following;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Se non ſtimaſſi vergogna ſcriver ſenza al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra
riprova, &amp;c. </hi>That is,<hi> If I did not think
it a ſhame, to write, without other proof, what
came into my phancy, I might ſay perhaps, that
that yellow liquor is by no other way intromit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
into the above ſaid gums of the teeth but by
thoſe </hi>Salival Conduits,<hi> found out by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</hi>Thomas Wharton,<hi> and ſhewn in this
Court by </hi>Lorenzo Billini,<hi> a learned young man
and of great expectation, in other Animals be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
Man, and particularly in Staggs, and
Wood-peckers: Moreover that under thoſe
Gums there are two ſmall Glanduls, found by
me in all Vipers. Yet I would not have you
rely upon this thought of mine, becauſe it may
prove a Chimera, as I believe it to be one,</hi>&amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I cannot comprehend, how Sign. <hi>Redi,</hi>
after he hath ſpoken of the <hi>Salival Conduits</hi>
as of a thing that came into his phancy, and
by a <hi>perhaps,</hi> that is to ſay, not knowing it;
and who declareth, that he was aſham'd to
write of a thing without verifying it; who
exhorts his friend to whom he writes, not to
relye on his thoughts, and who adds, that it
may prove a Chimera; I know not, I ſay,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:98525:47"/>
how, after he hath written all this, he can
pretend to be the inventor of the <hi>Salival
Glanduls,</hi> and their Pipes: For <hi>pag.</hi> 55 and
56. of his firſt Letter ſpeaking of the yellow
liquor, he adds,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>E queſto veleno altro non è, &amp;c. </hi>That is,<hi>This venom is nothing elſe but that liquor, which
humects the Palat, and ſtagnates in thoſe gums
that inveſt the teeth, not transmitted thither
from the Bladder of Gall, but bred in the
whole head, and conveyed </hi>perhaps<hi> to the
gums by ſome Salival conduits, which </hi>perhaps<hi>are there inſerted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where the word <hi>perhaps,</hi> yet twice again
repeated, doth ſufficiently ſhew, that Sign.
<hi>Redi</hi> did ſpeak of the <hi>Salival conduits</hi> no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
than as of a thing he was not at all
aſſured of. And though he may ſay, <hi>that</hi> he
hath had thoughts of it ſooner than I, (who
have not medled with Vipers but ſome years
after his firſt Letter,) <hi>that</hi> what he had
written of it gave me from that time occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and a deſire to ſeek for thoſe Pipes and
the Glanduls that might convey thither the
yellow liquor; <hi>that</hi> the belief, he had of the
Generation of this juyce in the whole head,
induced me to ſearch for the Salival Glanduls
higher and farther off than the place <hi>under</hi> the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:98525:47"/>
bottom of the veſicles; and <hi>that</hi> I doubt
not, that himſelf might have found theſe
true Glanduls, if he would have taken pains
for it. I anſwer, that, ſince he hath <hi>not</hi> done
it, he ought not to be offended at my having
labour'd for him, and ſucceeded in ſo doing:
Neither hath he any right to deny, that I
have firſt found, deſcribed, and to the life
repreſented the two heaps of Salival Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duls
of a Viper with all their Veſſels, as well
for forming, as conveying the yellow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
into the Veſicles that cover the great
teeth.</p>
                  <p>As to what Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> ſaith of me, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the Authors of my Book, that I have
changed the words, <hi>under the bottom,</hi> into
thoſe, <hi>at the bottom</hi> of the veſicles of the gums,
and there ſought in vain for the two ſmall
Glanduls, which he aſſures to have found
there in all Vipers: I anſwer, that whilſt he
is critical as to the letter of the words, <hi>I</hi>
keep to the truth of the matter of fact: And I
can aſſure, to have ſearched with much care,
not only <hi>in</hi> the whole bottom of the veſicles,
but every where <hi>under</hi> the bottom of them,
but have not found any, whether great or
ſmall Glanduls, nor any thing of the colour
of a Glandul, nor that came any way near to
their form.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:98525:48"/>
I put it then for a truth, that there is not
to be found any Glandul neither <hi>in</hi> nor <hi>under</hi>
the bottom of the veſicles, and that <hi>under</hi> the
bottom there is nothing but <hi>the</hi> griſtly bone
that gives the ſhape to the noſe of a Viper;
<hi>the</hi> two ſharp ends of the two advanced
bones of the skull, to which the two great
teeth are firmly annexed; <hi>the</hi> conduit of the
ſmell, <hi>that</hi> of the hearing; ſome ſmall vein,
ſome little Artery, ſome little Nerve, the
extremity of a Muſcle, and the two ends of
the Salival Channels that diſcharge into the
veſicles; as you may ſee it in a manner de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
in the Anatomy made of it by
me.</p>
                  <p>After this, Signor <hi>Redi</hi> himſelf ſhews,
that it was impoſſible, there ſhould be Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duls
<hi>under</hi> the bottom of the veſicles, ſince he
ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 38. of his laſt Letter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ne io poteva mai ſcrivere, &amp;c. </hi>that is,<hi> Nor
could I at all write, that thoſe Glanduls lay in
the bottom of the veſicles, if I was of opinion,
that the yellow liquor did run into them after it
had paſſed through the Salival conduits, which
yet I imagined might have their Origin from or
connexion with thoſe two Glanduls ſeen by me,
and therefore muſt needs be in a ſcituation a
little diſtant from the veſicles, and not in the
bottom of them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:98525:48"/>
For ſince he ſaith, to have meant, that the
yellow juyce took its courſe thorough the
Salival conduits before its coming into the
veſicles; He cannot find a way long enough,
nor a diſtance great enough, for the need of
long conduits, from the place <hi>under</hi> the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom
unto that which is in the bottom of the
veſicles: For, there would have needed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but a little opening in the ſame bottom,
to receive the juyce iſſuing out of the two
little Glanduls he hath ſpoken of. And he
ſhews ſufficiently, that he cannot maintain
thoſe two ſmall Glanduls <hi>under</hi> the bottom,
where he would have them to be, ſince now he
will needs have them a little diſtant from the
veſicles, that he may find, in the intervall, a
ſpace ſufficient for the veſſels that are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
to the courſe of this yellow liquor. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
that it is altogether impoſſible for two
ſmall Glanduls to furniſh all that yellow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor,
which preſents it ſelf in the veſicles;
ſince the two great heaps by me found in the
two Temples and behind the Orbits of the
eyes of a Viper, can hardly furniſh each a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
a drop in the ſpace of 24 hours, after
the veſicles have been well voided. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,
it is very eaſie to judge by what <hi>Sign.
Redi</hi> ſaith in his Firſt Letter, that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
not, the Salival Glands were ſeated, as
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98525:49"/>
they are, on the two Temples, nor ſo near the
skull; ſince he ſaith, that what came into his
phancy, was, that the head of a Viper did not
convey that yellow juyce but by certain ſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val
conduits. For if he had been of another
mind, he would not have ſpoken but of glands;
or, at leaſt, he would have begun with them
before he had ſpoken of the conduits, which
ſhews alſo ſufficiently, that by this means he
hath as 'twere inverted the order of nature:
For, inſtead of placing the Glands cloſe to
the skul, and afterwards the ſalival conduits;
he hath begun with theſe, and would have
them immediately to receive the juyce of the
Brain, and to carry them to the veſicles of the
gums; and that his two pretended glanduls
are ſeated between the extremity of theſe
conduits, and the bottom of the veſicles;
though none be there, and it would be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
uſeleſs, they ſhould be there, becauſe
there are none but they that can at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
ſuck &amp; digeſt the humidities of the brain
and the neighbouring parts, and ſend them
into the veſicles of the gums by the conduits
appointed for this office.</p>
                  <p>But when Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> accuſes me of having
taken the bottom of the veſicles for that
which is <hi>under</hi> the bottom of them, and of
not having rightly underſtood, as he ſpeaks,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:98525:49"/>
the <hi>Toſcan</hi> tongue; I may ſay, that himſelf
hath not very well apprehended, nor duly
explained the <hi>French</hi> terms, uſed by me;
ſince he ſaith at the end of <hi>pag.</hi> 35. and at the
beginning of <hi>p.</hi> 36. of the ſame laſt letter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sovra de chi gli, Autori delle novelle experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
affermano,</hi> &amp;c. That is, Whereupon the
Authors of the New Experiments do affirm,
that they could never ſee ſuch Glanduls as I
had named; but that inſtead of them they had
found two others, which they call Salival,
thus by them deſcribed, <hi>p.</hi> 31.</p>
                  <p>For neither in all that he hath afterwards
taken the pains to tranſcribe out of my book
on that ſubject, nor in all the reſt of my <hi>Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
upon the Salival Glanduls, he can have
read; that I ſay to have found <hi>two Glanduls,</hi>
but, <hi>Glanduls;</hi> there being a great difference
in good French, between <hi>Deux Glandes,</hi> and
<hi>Des Glandes, two Glands,</hi> and, <hi>Glands.</hi> And
when, deſcribing the Glanduls, I ſay, that
they are ſeated on the two ſides of the <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuns,</hi>
I ſay afterwards, that there are many
ſmall ones joyned together, which may be
call'd <hi>Conglomerate Glanduls.</hi> And yet more;
I ſpeak of an <hi>Heap of Glanduls;</hi> ſo far am I
from ſpeaking only of one or two Glanduls, as
Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath repreſented me to have done.</p>
                  <p>And ſince, in hopes of better maintaining
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98525:50"/>
his cauſe, he hath given himſelf the trouble
of copying word for word, in his laſt Letter,
only the moſt general place of my Book, and
that which was the leaſt contrary to it, in my
<hi>Section</hi> of the Salival Glands. To ſhew there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
on my part, that the Glands, found by
me, are very different, and that even they are
quite another thing, than the two ſmall ones
ſpoken of by him; I thought my ſelf obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
to tranſcribe hither out of my book
what he thought not neceſſary for him. For
in the ſame <hi>Section, p.</hi> 30. (in the Engliſh ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<hi>p.</hi> 33) I ſpeak thus of the ſalival Glands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe Glands are found in all the heads of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
both Males and Females; they are ſeated
on both ſides, and joining to the skull, in the
hind-part of each round of the eyes, and at the
ſame height with them. There are many ſmall
ones joined together, which may be call'd </hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glomerate
Glands,<hi> that are eaſily diſtinguiſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
by their form and colour, which is different
from the Muſcles, neighbouring to them, and of
which there is one, that may be call'd </hi>Temporal,<hi>which in part covers them by its extremity.
This heap of Glands appears there of the bigneſs
of the neighbouring eye, and extending it ſelf
in length, continues its progreſs in the Orbite
of the eye, below and in part behind the eye.
Each Gland hath its little Lymphatique veſſel,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98525:50"/>
which parts from it as from a little Teat, and
goes diſgorging it ſelf into a greater veſſel, that
runs all along and under theſe Glands, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
into the Veſicle of the Gum, and terminates
in the midſt of the Articulation, which the root
of the great teeth makes with the advancing cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of the ſaid Orbite, and with the little Bone,
which by its other end is articulated in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
of the upper jaw. This principal veſſel, which
being conſider'd alone, is very little in appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
but is not ſo in effect, ſeeing it receives the
diſcharge of all the ſmall veſſels that come from
each Gland, empties it ſelf into the bag of the
gums, and carries thither that </hi>Salival<hi> juyce,
which may have qualities approaching to thoſe
of the </hi>Saliva<hi> or Spitle of man, or of the foam or
drivel of divers other Animals.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Nerve, which ſerves in the Noſtrils
to the faculty of </hi>Hearing,<hi> runs for ſome
ſpace along theſe Glands, which are alſo, as
I have already ſaid, ſmall Veins and Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But having well conſider'd the ſubſtance, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
&amp; ſcituation of theſe </hi>Glands,<hi> we judged their
formation not to be in vain; but that their
Uſe, in all likelyhood, was, to receive the
humidities both of the Brain, the Eyes, and
the neighbouring parts; and that their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge
was very convenient, and even very
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:98525:51"/>
neceſſary to the parts, which receive that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor;
as well for moiſtening the ligaments
of the great teeth, and to keep them in a
condition of bending at ſuch time when the
Viper will bite, as for bedewing and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
the teeth, which Nature hath formed and
ſet in the midſt of this Juice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the reſt, examining and taſting the
Glands as well as the Juice, we found a
taſte altogether like that of the Gums, which
Sign. </hi>Redi<hi> hath deſcribed; namely, very
near the taſte of the Oyle of Almonds, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
all bitterneſs, though it leave, a while
after, a little acrimony in the mouth, ſuch
as may be diſcern'd in all kind of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I could add here, what I ſaid of the
Salival Glands of <hi>Snakes,</hi> their difference
from thoſe of Vipers; and I could al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
that I believe my ſelf to be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
the firſt Diſcoverer of them. But
becauſe ſo prolix a Citation might prove
tedious, and that thoſe that deſire to have
more light therein, may eaſily find the reſt
in the above-cited <hi>Section</hi> of my Book, I
ſhall not tranſcribe it hither.</p>
                  <p>Mean time 'tis very eaſie to judge from
my whole Diſcourſe, and from the exact
Deſcription, made by me, of theſe <hi>Glands,</hi>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:98525:51"/>
and their neighbouring parts, that they
were not known to me by <hi>Phancy.</hi> Their
ſcituation very diſtant from that place
<hi>under,</hi> and even from the ſides of, the
<hi>bottom</hi> of the veſicles of the gums, ſhews
ſufficiently, that they are neither <hi>in</hi> nor
<hi>under</hi> the bottom of thoſe veſicles, as Sign.
<hi>Redi</hi> hath pretended; and their great
number makes it appear, that 'tis quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
thing, than the two litle Glanduls
he ſpeaks of, and which are not to be found
neither.</p>
                  <p>I intreat the Reader, well to conſider
thoſe I have diſcover'd, as they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented
in my <hi>third Cutt,</hi> as well in that
part where the Temples are of a Head cut,
mark'd C, (where their ſhape and ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
is repreſented to the life, as they
ſhew themſelves before they are ſever'd;)
as in the incloſure of a Vipers ſceleton,
which is there alſo exhibited; where he
may ſee them in their upper and lower
appearance, drawn out of the Head, and
by their ligaments faſtned to the hind-part
of the Eyes, and to the body of the Brain.
I came not to the full knowledge of them
till after much pains, and a very long and
particular ſearch. I did not content my
ſelf to ſeek a great while in the bottom,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:98525:52"/>
and under the bottom of the veſicles of
the gums; but, to find theſe Glands, I have
flead and diſſected a great number of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
heads, as dextrouſly and nicely as I
could; and I have uſed all means well to
examine them; among others, I cauſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
heads to be gently boyled in a little
water, <hi>as well</hi> to conſider the divers ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
of the skull, and to ſeparate all the
parts from it; <hi>as</hi> to remark well the form
and the connexion of theſe Glands, to draw
them out whole, and joined, as they are,
to the Eyes, and to divers bodies of the
Brain, to which the marrow of the Spaine
is annex'd; and to have all theſe parts en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire,
and ſuch as I have cauſed them to be
engraven.</p>
                  <p>Me thinks, that all theſe cares, follow'd
by ſo good ſucceſs, may well deſerve, my
Diſcovery of this great number of Salival
Glands with all their veſſels, ſhould not
be envied me by Sign. <hi>Redi;</hi> conſidering
I do ſufficiently appear to him incapable of
envying him any of thoſe ſine things, he
hath already found, or may find hereafter in
his curious re-ſearches.</p>
                  <p>There remains no more for me to do, me
thinks, than to ſatisfie Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> as well
concerning the Uncertainty, wherein he is
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:98525:52"/>
touching the Power of the Volatil Salt of
Vipers for the curing of their bitings; as
about the Objections, by him made againſt
my Experiments of the Head and Neck of
a Viper, for curing Doggs bitten by it, and
which I have alſo thought ſhould be effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
to cure men in the like caſe.</p>
                  <p>He oppoſes nothing to the Vertue of this
Volatil Salt, but that he remits the Reader
to the time he will take, Chymically to
prepare this Salt, and to make the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment
therewith. But he ſaith, that he
hath made many tryals with the Heads and
Necks of Vipers, and found firſt; That,
having made two great Doggs aforehand to
ſwallow, each the head and neck of a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
and, afterwards cauſed both of them
to be bitten by other Vipers, thoſe Doggs
dyed not: And that, having cauſed to be
bitten two other Doggs of the ſame big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
that had eaten neither head nor neck
of a Viper, they dyed neither. He ſaith
further, that having made a Pullet to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
one head of a Viper, and a Capon two,
and cauſed them to be bitten, they both dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
ſoon after. He adds, <hi>that</hi> having the
next day made ready ſome heads of Vipers,
he cauſed them to be forc'd down the throat
of two little Doggs, of which he cauſed
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:98525:53"/>
the leaſt to be bitten in the legg near the
<hi>anus,</hi> and the other, in the tongue, and
that they both dyed; <hi>That</hi> he made the
ſame Experiment upon eight Pullets, two
Kitlings, two ſmall Rabbets, and ſix Pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
even with rubbing the place bitten
with the blood of the Viper; <hi>That</hi> alſo
the ſix Pigeons were bitten by the heads of
Vipers, dead ſeveral dayes before, and that
all theſe animals dyed; <hi>That</hi> laſtly, he had
fed two Pigeons for there dayes with the
fleſh and broath of Vipers, and being bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
thereupon, they dyed likewiſe, this aid
notwithſtanding.</p>
                  <p>For Anſwer to all theſe Experiments, I
make uſe of the ſame <hi>Generals,</hi> that Sign.
<hi>Redi</hi> hath done againſt mine, which are to
be found <hi>pag.</hi> 16. of his laſt Letter; where
he ſaith: <hi>That</hi> a Viper more eaſily kills leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer
Animals by his biting, than great ones;
that, according to the bigneſs of the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
bitten, and according as the place
wounded is more or leſs provided with
veins or arteries; that, if from the wound
of a Viper much blood iſſueth, the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
not only dyeth not, but does not ſo
much as feel any great inconvenience; that
it alſo falls out ſometimes, that the Animal
bitten eſcapeth, after it hath endured ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:98525:53"/>
mortal ſymptoms; and that this may
come to paſs by the ſole aſſiſtance of Nature.</p>
                  <p>As to the two other <hi>Generals,</hi> which he
alledgeth in reference to the letting in of the
yellow liquor; I did not think fit to alledge
them here, <hi>both</hi> becauſe I agree not as to the
poſſibility of the fact, <hi>and</hi> that I have elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where
declared my ſelf ſufficiently about it;
as alſo that they make not to this purpoſe.
But I think it more material, to add here
two other <hi>Generals</hi> to thoſe of Sign. <hi>Redi,</hi>
and to ſay: That the biting is more or leſs
noxious, not only according to the place
bitten, but according to the degree of the
Vipers being vexed when ſhe is to bite, and
according as her teeth have more or leſs pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrated.
And reaſoning particularly upon
theſe experiments, I ſay, <hi>that</hi> the dogs which
I had cauſed to be bitten every one thrice, &amp;
were cured by making each of them ſwallow
the head and neck of a Viper, were of a very
midling ſize, <hi>that</hi> it is very difficult to found
a certainjudgment upon the great ones, which
Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath uſed, as 'tis alſo, to paſs it
upon them that had ſwallow'd the head and
neck of a Viper, and thoſe, that had not done
ſo, <hi>that</hi> all the other little animals, which he
employed, as well the Pullet and the Capon,
as the Pigeons, Catlings, Puppies, and little
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98525:54"/>
Rabbets, had not of themſelves ſtrength e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to reſiſt for a time the enraged ſpirits,
nor to find the effect of the remedy; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
that which was bitten in the tongue. For, I
firmly believe, that there is no animal, great
or ſmal, which being fiercely bit in the tongue
by a Viper well vexed, can avoid death, what
aid ſoever you miniſter to it, becauſe of the
nerves, veins &amp; arteries, diſſeminated through
the tongue; and becauſe that the angred ſpirits
finding a free entrance, produce there all the
effect they are capable of, with ſo much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
and nimbleneſs, that nothing is able to
ſtop them. But in all curable bites I ſhall not
eaſily be induced to renounce the help, which
may be given by the head, neck, heart, liver,
and divers other parts of a Viper (eſpecially
of her that made the bite) for the cure of the
animals that have ſufficient ſtrength to reſiſt a
while, and to expect the benefit of this kind
of remedy. I believe alſo to have great cauſe
not to exclude from it man himſelf; as alſo to
prefer the parts of the ſame Viper that hath
bitten, to thoſe of others; becauſe they muſt
needs have greater cognation and more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
with the vexed ſpirits, that iſſued from
her. Concerning which I think it not amiſs, to
impart to the publick an accident that hapn'd
in the Royal Laboratory of this City, whilſt
my laſt experiments were making.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:98525:54"/>
A young man that had made a good progreſs
in his ſtudies, deſirous to perfect himſelf in
both ways of Pharmacy, and chiefly addicted
to my courſe of Chymiſtry, was near me, in
the midſt of a great Aſſembly, on the 2<hi>d</hi> day of
my experiments. After I had made ſome, whilſt
I was entertaining the company, the fancy
took him, in imitation of me, yet without my
knowledge, to take a Viper with his hand, and
to ſeize on her head: which he did not with
that caution that is neceſſary, as not holding
her ſo faſt but that the Viper took her oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity,
and ſtruck one of her great teeth very
deep into the middle of the upper part of his
left fore-finger. Having been made acquainted
therewith, I remov'd, as much as I could, all
fear from his ſpirit, and adviſed him to betake
himſelf to the neceſſary remedies. The credit
he gave to the truths contain'd in my book, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
read by him, induced him to ſay, that if I
thought well of it, he would eat the head and
neck of the Viper that had bit him. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending
his courage, I ſeconded his good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations;
for, I cauſed ſlightly to be broil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
on coals the head and neck of the ſaid vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
and made him eat and ſwallow it hot, in
the midſt of the company, adding to it the
heart and liver broiled likewiſe. After which
I ſaid, I doubted not but what he had done
would be ſufficient to cure him; yet to be the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:98525:55"/>
ſurer, I would give him ſome volatil ſalt of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
eſpecially he being a perſon whom I did
much eſteem, and for whoſe health I had and
ever ſhould haue a great concern. I thereupon
immediately gave him a doſe a fifty grains of
this volatil ſalt, diſſolved in four ounces of
water, and aſſured him there was not any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
after this. The young man remained in the
midſt of the company, &amp; ſtirr'd not from the
place, till the meeting ended, and then he took
a little freſh air. He was afterwards a couple
of hours in the Royal Garden and the Labora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory;
during which time he now &amp; then found
ſome little ſickneſs about his heart; but being
come to his own lodging, he was ready to ſup
as he was uſed to do, and would have done it,
if I had not thought it better for him to take
another doſe of the ſame volatil ſalt, which had
ſo good effect, that the next day, after he had
dined well, he came again to our meeting;
which did much ſurpriſe all thoſe that had
been witneſſes of the bite. Since that time he
hath ever been very well. Now though his
wound appear'd much deeper then that of the
German gentleman, that was bitten the 1<hi>ſt</hi> day
of my former experiments; yet had he none
of thoſe grievous accidents, that befell <hi>him,</hi> &amp;
were by me deſcribed in my book: for he had
no other pain but that of the hole of the bite,
nor had he ſo much as a Fever. The wound
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:98525:55"/>
only rendred ſome drops of blood, by means
of the ligature, I caus'd to be made on the top
of his wounded finger, which did never ſwell,
and heal'd up as if it had been made by the
prick of a pin, without any Cicatrice appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
ſo far was it from a Gangrene, or Scar, as
ſome fancied he would have.</p>
                  <p>The thing hath been too publick, not to be
credited every where; and I think not, that
Sign, <hi>Redi</hi> himſelf will doubt of it; but rather
that all things have concurr'd together to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie
all I had advanced in my book, of which
he hath conteſted ſome particulars, and could
not reſolve himſelf about others. However,
if he have by him any remedies, more quick
and more ſure for the cure of the bites of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
the publick will be much oblig'd to him
when he ſhall pleaſe to impart them, as I very
willingly communicate theſe I have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.
I ſhall not ſpeak here of divers Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments
lately made upon Vipers by very
able perſons at <hi>Paris,</hi> which confirm not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the perfect innocence of the jellow liquor
that is in the veſicles of the Gums, but which
warrant at the ſame time my adſcribing the
venom to the enraged ſpirits. Theſe truths
will be better received from their hands, and
they will be much more advantagious to me,
than if I did attempt to publiſh them now.
For doubtleſs there will be found in them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:98525:56"/>
curious things, and they are like to be of
more importance than what I might be able
to ſay of them. Beſides that I am far from u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping
the honor due to others, and from at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing
to me the obligation, which the
publick will owe them for it.</p>
                  <p>For a concluſion of this diſcourſe; <hi>ſince</hi>
Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath not found in the whole body
of a Viper any other part but the jellow juice
to which he can aſſign its venom; <hi>ſince on my
part</hi> by the new experiments, he hath deſir'd
of me, I have ſufficiently juſtified the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence
of the jellow liquor in the Vipers of
<hi>France,</hi> and the great conformities, there muſt
needs be in the ſame with that of the Vipers
of <hi>Italy,</hi> aſſerting withal the venomonſneſs of
the angred ſpirits cauſing the death that enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
the bite; and <hi>ſince</hi> laſtly the Vipers of
<hi>France</hi> do kill as ſoon and in the ſame manner
as thoſe of <hi>Italy</hi> do, and even without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention
of the jellow liquor: Theſe
things being ſo, I eſteem, that Sign. <hi>Redi</hi>
would do very well, if, to ſatisfie <hi>on his part</hi>
the expectation of the publick, and without
adhering any longer to the jellow liquor,
which is ſo reaſonably conteſted, he would
take the pains to labour to find out ſome new
ſubject, that might be common to the Vipers
of <hi>France</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Italy;</hi> that might have
the ſame diſpoſition of matter, and the ſame
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:98525:56"/>
power of acting nimbly; and that might with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
be equally declared the true ſeat of their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom;
to the end that afterwards he might as ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly
exclude from it the enraged ſpirits, as I now
exclude from it the jellow liquor. But if on the
contrary it comes to paſs, that he can find none
other, I believe not, that for the future he hath
any ground to maintain his opinion, no more
than to conteſt mine.</p>
                  <p>Concluding this diſſertation I ſhall ſay, that
the contrariety of opinions, which is between
Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> and me, in the moſt eſſential things
of the Vipers poiſon, may alſo be obſerved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
another account about the ſame animal: For,
the more <hi>he</hi> expreſſeth <hi>p.</hi> 39. of his laſt letter, the
averſion and hatred he hath againſt it, the more I
eſteem it, and the greater pleaſure I take to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,
to examine, and to prepare it. Nor can I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently
praiſe the excellent qualities, which ſo
rare a ſubject poſſeſſeth, nor the admirable reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
which it furniſheth: Which are the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,
that have heretofore induced me, and
oblige me ſtill to call the Viper one of the chief
Pillars of Phyſick.</p>
                  <p>It may be, that for this once Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> will
not doubt but that a diſcourſe as rude as this,
compos'd among coals and furnaces, which I
have ſeldom quitted of late, is mine. He will
doubtleſs judge, that, if more underſtanding men
had put their hands to it, the reaſonings thereof
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:98525:57"/>
would be more ſubtile, the ſtyle more polite,
and the expreſſions more elegant; and the <hi>Greek</hi>
and <hi>Latin</hi> quotations would not have been ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
therein, both to ſtrengthen the arguments
thereof, and to adorn &amp; enlarge the volume. But
for all the contrarieties, which the different con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions
have bred between Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> and me,
I ſhall always have a very great and a very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interreſſ'd
eſteem for him; and ſo much the more,
becauſe I have great reaſon to conceive ſome
good opinion of my book, ſince it could deſerve
that ſo intelligent &amp; famous a perſon hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed
to read it again and again with pleaſure,
as he ſaith himſelf, that he hath taken the pains
of tranſcribing many pages out of it word for
word, and hath made it famous by his anſwer, and
by that alſo which a perſon of great parts, and a
high reputation hath made to it, addreſs'd to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
on this ſubject. I cannot but much glory in
it, and highly declare my ſelf his obliged. And
if it ſhould come to paſs, that the diverſity of
his experiments, the force of his arguments, or
the eſteem he hath acquired among the Learned,
ſhould carry the bell from me in the ſpirits of all
the world; the victory, which he ſhould thence
obtain, would not be much leſs advantagious for
me, then if the truth of my experiments, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied
by my reaſonings, had been able to bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance
or even to prevail over his Sentiments and
the writings of ſo Illuſtrious a Perſon.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:98525:57"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
