<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Second complaint being an honest letter to a dovbtfvll friend : about the rifling of the twentieth part of his estate.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R90</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17879</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12348779</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12348779</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59921</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A58471)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59921)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 875:48)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Second complaint being an honest letter to a dovbtfvll friend : about the rifling of the twentieth part of his estate.</title>
                  <author>T. R. Honest letter to a doubtfull friend.</author>
                  <author>H. W., Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Reade and burne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Caption title (p. [3]): To his much esteemed friend and kinsman Sir H.W. at his house in Westminster.</note>
                  <note>Dated (p. [8]) at London, 28. December. 1642 and signed: T.R.</note>
                  <note>First published in 1642 with title: An honest letter to a doubtfull friend ...</note>
                  <note>Title occasioned by "A complaint to the House of Commons and resolution taken by the free Protestant subjects of ... London and Westminster ..." of about 31 December 1642.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Possessory interests in land --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59921:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Second Complaint:</hi> BEING An Honeſt Letter TO A DOVBTFVLL FRIEND, ABOUT The rifling of the Twentieth <hi>part of his Eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reade and burne.</hi> M DC XLIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59921:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59921:2"/>
            <head>To his much eſteemed friend and Kinſman Sir H.W. at his houſe in Weſtminſter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe indiſpoſition of my body hath confined me to my Chamber, we muſt now therefore diſcourſe by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; your Petition for peace I ſee is not ſo happy as to finde ſucceſſe in Parliament, at which while I <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I began to conſider the reaſons, which are divers <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the perſons oppoſing it. Therefore you muſt firſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the oppoſors; and then the reaſons will be evident. It is not fit the Houſes of Parliament ſhould deny the obedient Citizens of London any thing, for that may bee diſtaſtefull to the City; nor yet grant the Requeſt of the Petition; for that may be diſtructive to the Profit of many Members of both Houſes, and to ſome even of the City it ſelfe. It was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſely done of my abortive Lord Major and his Zeelous Sectaries to attempt the ſtrangling of it in the birth, by committing ſome that were active about it; the Reaſons are Reformation of Religion, that is, aboliſhing the Booke of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> as Popiſh, though juſtified by the <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers Martyrdome</hi> under the popiſh tyranny, but that will make way for their new Doctrines and extemporary bablings, next the diſſolving of Biſhopricks and Deanries will repay the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney lent upon publique faith, for advancing the Lords warre, (for ſo they miſcall treaſon) &amp; to conclude, that being <hi>the Lords debt,</hi> it is fitteſt to be paid out of the Lords inheritance, then Biſhops being eradicated, Elders may grow up and flouriſh as in <hi>Suſannaes</hi> dayes. And it is Conſiderable, that the eſtates of Malignants, will be juſt rewards for the godly laborers in this harveſt, all which will be loſt by a beggarly accommodation.</p>
            <p>Touching the Houſes of Parliament which conſiſts of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 140. Lords, and 500. Commoners, of which not a fift part do attend in their ſeverall Houſes, ſome being voted out,
<pb facs="tcp:59921:3"/>others committed for not conforming their Conſciences to the ſence of the Houſe, and very many, diſliking the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and tumults, left the Houſe and repayred to the King, with whom a greater part I am ſure is then attend both Houſes, being come to preſerve their oathes of Allegiance which is perſonall to the King.</p>
            <p>Take (Sir) but a view of ſuch as fit and act the buſineſſe in the Houſes of Parliament, obſerve who among them have Commands and places of profit in and about this warre, then examine their ſmall eſtate, with the great debt and charge; the rich profit of their command with their poor Revenew. You may find the Earles of <hi>Northumberland, Pembrook, Rut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Salisbury, Holland,</hi> ſitting in the Lords Houſe; and in the Houſe of Commons Sir <hi>Edward Hales,</hi> Sir <hi>George Stone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,</hi> Sir <hi>Alexander Denton,</hi> M. <hi>Edw. Waller,</hi> M. <hi>Maynard,</hi> M. <hi>Thomas Cooke,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Hutchinſon,</hi> M. <hi>Philips,</hi> M. <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> and others, all voting for Peace, to preſerve the eſtates they have, not find them in the liſt of Officers to get mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. All men know my miſled Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> loſt the beſt of his eſtate in loſt <hi>Ireland,</hi> and his whole debt, and great Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt to his Nephew <hi>Shirley</hi> is to be paid out of a ſmall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder, hath not my Lord of <hi>Warwick</hi> ſould all he can, but yet his creditors take new promiſes for old debts, though he be reſponſall for 400000. pound <hi>prout per accompt?</hi> are the Lords of <hi>Peterborough, Stamford, Say,</hi> and <hi>Brook,</hi> neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous? their debts and charge preſſing? then their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are double; both Horſe and Foot. The Lords <hi>Haſtings, Rachford, Wharton, S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iohn, Mandevill, Feelding, Gray</hi> of <hi>Grooby,</hi> Sir <hi>Hugh Chamley,</hi> Sir <hi>Samuell Luke,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Merrick,</hi> Maſter <hi>Nathaniel Fines,</hi> Maſt. <hi>Martin,</hi> Maſt. <hi>Wingat,</hi> Maſt. <hi>Walton,</hi> Maſt. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> Collonell <hi>Venne,</hi> M. <hi>John More,</hi> and others, are men whoſe credit (as appears by Screveners bookes) is as great as their eſtates, not invited to Commands by the profit of the places, but by their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious zeale to the Cauſe, others of the Houſes (leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:59921:3"/>any water ſhould runne beſide their mill) preferre their Sonnes, Brothers, and neere Friends, to places and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of profit about this warre, as <hi>M. Pym</hi> his ſonne <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> Sir <hi>H. Mildemay</hi> his brother <hi>Anthony,</hi> my Lord <hi>Say</hi> his ſon <hi>Iohn,</hi> and others other friends, while ſome men of the Houſe have confeſt that the pay made them undertake the cauſe, and which of all theſe, ſave Sir <hi>Iohn Merrick,</hi> knowes ought of his place but the profit? Nay, many of them for the better ſervice fight by their Lieutenants, as they pay debts by their ſureties, and how many of them, ſave two or three which are taken priſoners, received a wound, or ſtruck one blow in the late battels of <hi>Edge hil</hi> and <hi>Branceford,</hi> what hopes then that theſe men wil give their Votes and 12. or 1500. <hi>l. per ann.</hi> for a barren peace? will my Lord Major ſubſcribe a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition that ſhall take away his toll, 12.d. for Paſſes out of <hi>London?</hi> or Colonel <hi>Mannering,</hi> the craſed Mercer, Captain <hi>Baſſe,</hi> the Lace-man, Captain <hi>Maſon,</hi> the Button maker, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Witherly,</hi> the Pewterer, Captaine <hi>Capcote</hi> the Broaker, Captaine <hi>Lee</hi> the Vintner, with the Cunnyskin-Captaine in Southwark, and divers other Debt-compounding-Citizens, their pay and protections againſt Creditors, and leave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves nought but a Gaole to live in? What can you hope for by your Petition that theſe men, and the like, can hinder?</p>
            <p>Now ſurveigh the Popiſh and beggerly Lords and Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers for and about the King, as the Duke of <hi>Richmond,</hi> the <hi>Marqueſſe Hartford,</hi> Earles of <hi>Cumberland, Darby, Lindſey, Bath, Dorſet, Bridgwater, Denby, Leiceſter, Devonſhire, North-Hampton, Cheſterfield, Briſtoll, Weſtmerland, Barkſhire, New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle, Carnarvon, Kingſton</hi> and <hi>Thanot.</hi> The Lords <hi>Mowbray, Mountague</hi> of <hi>Baughton, Daincourt, Shandoys, Spencer, Gray, Mohume, Dunſmore, Newarke, Seymore, Capell,</hi> and others: Then of the Houſe of Commons, Sir <hi>Chriſto. Hatten,</hi> Sir <hi>Iar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas Clifton,</hi> S. <hi>Guy Palmes,</hi> Sir <hi>Iames Thinn, Mr. Iames Coventry, Mr. Henry</hi> and <hi>Iohn Bellaſſey,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Fanſhaw,</hi> Sir <hi>Richard Lewſon,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Danby,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Packington,</hi> Sir <hi>Ric. Lee,</hi> Sir
<pb facs="tcp:59921:4"/>
               <hi>Charles le Groſſe,</hi> Maſter <hi>Catline,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Holborne,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bridgeman,</hi> Mr. <hi>Chadwell,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Stangwayes</hi> &amp; his ſonne, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>John Digby,</hi> Sir <hi>Edw. Deering,</hi> Sir <hi>William Widdrington,</hi> Maſter <hi>Venables,</hi> Baron of <hi>Kinnerton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rogers,</hi> Mr. <hi>Newport,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Alford,</hi> Mr. <hi>Whitmore,</hi> Mr. <hi>Chuchley,</hi> Mr. <hi>Edgcome,</hi> Sir <hi>John Stowell,</hi> Mr. <hi>Crooke,</hi> Mr. <hi>Nowell,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sutton,</hi> Sir <hi>Will. Oagle,</hi> Sir <hi>Wil. Poole,</hi> &amp; one hundred more then my paper will hold, men of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and known integrity, &amp; which of all theſe whoſe age &amp; health would permit, adventured not their lives and eſtates in this war with the King? Now let us examine their Religion, you ſhall finde them daily at Sermons and Service with the King, hearing and practiſing the ſame Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Liturgie, that ſaved our Fathers, and hath beene in our Church ever ſince the Reformation, and which we have vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the late Proteſtation to maintain, then (no doubt) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King nor they are likely to bring in Popery, nor bee Separatiſts.</p>
            <p>That they are men of Eſtates the Counties that elected them (if not the Kingdom) knows, and which of them hath any profit by the warre: which of them goes not himſelfe and ſervants to the warre at his own charge? Nay, which of them have not otherwiſe in a large manner contributed to the maintenance of the Kings Army, and that without any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of an Ordinance; yea, even againſt the Declaration of the Houſe? what would they land others then have done, had an Order of the Houſe directed it as on the other ſide? By this then you ſee they are neither Popiſhly nor beggarly; nor can have any reward or hopes of repaire out of the eſtates of the adverſe party.</p>
            <p>But they would induce arbitrary government: I pray what proofe is there of that? what one act hath the King done ſince the Commence of the Parliament that favours of arbitrary juſtice? whom he hath diſtrained, committed, or turned out of the Towne for not lending? Nay, what hath hee not done to aſſure us the contrary? Reade His Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:59921:4"/>obſerve his regall promiſes and Proteſtations, and then tell me what Chriſtian (that hath charity) or what man (that would be beleeved) will not beleeve him? Hath he not regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the Councell Table? damned the Sipwrits? ſuppreſt the high-Commiſſion and Martiall Court? Nay, hath he not left all things to be tryed by ſtrict proceedings of Law?</p>
            <p>Whom can arbitrary juſtice more prejudice, then thoſe now about and with the King? the Rich and wealthy men? ſurely then they will not be a meanes to induce that Law that ſhall undoe, &amp; inſlave them, their children, families, &amp; eſtates. Yet muſt we lend money, ſend horſes, and raiſe Arms againſt theſe popiſh and beggarly Cavalliers. For it is not againſt the King, that were Treaſon, and breach of our late <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> which is to defend his Majeſty, yet was the Kings Perſon in danger at <hi>Edge-Hill</hi> Battle, when the undiſtinguiſhing ſhot tooke ſome perſons about the King, but God did then, and I hope always will cover his head in the day of Battel.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe conſiderations, Sir, I cannot beleeve or feare the reducement of popery or arbitrary Juſtice; nor thinke my conſcience, perſon, or eſtate, tyed by the neceſſitous Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of both Houſes (for want of an act of Parliament) to pay, or let the twentieth part of my eſtate (which you know may come to three or foure hundred pound) be taken to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a war, wherein the perſon of the King (which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) may be hurt.</p>
            <p>I am ſure that while God promiſed the Scepter to <hi>Juda,</hi> he put the Law-giver between his feet, to let us know, That the legiſlative power is neither above or without the King. And I know the King by His Writs, doth call them to adviſe with him, not to reſolve without him. I will therefore keepe my hands from giving; and ſo preſerve my conſcience; I will faſt bolt my doores, and ſo preſerve my perſon and eſtate untill a ſtronger then I come. For I had rather others committed treſpaſſe in taking, then I treaſon in giving. And I am ſure that both Armies are not on the right ſide, but one, with all
<pb facs="tcp:59921:5"/>their voluntary maintainers and abetters, muſt, without Gods infinite mercie be guilty of the blood of all the men ſlaine on either ſide. I ſhall therefore, for my particular beleeve and follow the rule of the Apoſtle, to <hi>obey the King, for Hee is ſet over us by God,</hi> rather then runne with the new opinions and contrary doctrine of our militant Evangeliſts, Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> Dr <hi>Downing,</hi> Mr <hi>Marſhall,</hi> and <hi>Sedgwicke,</hi> whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſtart out of the way at a white Surpleſſe, but never boggle at garments <hi>rolled in blood.</hi> There are other things conſiderable with us Citizens alſo, as the returne of Sir <hi>Faithfull Forteſoue,</hi> Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Wagſtaffe</hi> and my Lo: <hi>Eſſex</hi> favourite, Captain <hi>Scrimpſhaw,</hi> unto the King, next the danger and jealouſie we are in, that even ſome of the great ones will follow, (for theſe are but harbengers,) and rather then come empty handed to their King, will make us their peace offering.</p>
            <p>Let us conſider the event of war, wherein we can yet boaſt nothing but our ſucceſſe at <hi>Wincheſter.</hi> But had wee had the day at <hi>Edge hill,</hi> and totally routed the Cavalliers, would that have determined the warre? I feare rather have called in all the Monarches of Chriſtendome, to maintain Monarchie, and then were we engaged like the Low Countries, in perpetuall blood. How great then is our ſtraight, for if we ſucceede wee undoe our ſelves. If the King by victory (or treachery of our Commanders) the labour is ſaved us then, for having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed his mercie, we muſt expect his juſtice.</p>
            <p>I have now, Sir, unboſomed my ſelfe to you my friend, let therefore my errors finde a friendly reproof, rectifying my miſtakes by your advice, which I ſhall take as Commands, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne you the thankfull acknowledgement of</p>
            <p>Read and burne.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your friend ane Kinſman T. R.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Milkeſtreete</hi> London, <date>28. <hi>December.</hi> 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
