<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the funeral of Sir John Buckworth, at the parish-church of St. Peter's le Poor in Broadstreet, December 29, 1687 by John Scott.</title>
            <author>Scott, John, 1639-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-08">2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58818</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2072</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14391</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13142454</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13142454</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97988</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A58818)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97988)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 751:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the funeral of Sir John Buckworth, at the parish-church of St. Peter's le Poor in Broadstreet, December 29, 1687 by John Scott.</title>
                  <author>Scott, John, 1639-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ..., and Thomas Horne ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Buckworth, John, --  Sir, d. 1687.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-05</date>
            <label>Melanie Sanders</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-05</date>
            <label>Melanie Sanders</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97988:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97988:1"/>
            <p>A
SERMON
Preach'd at the
FUNERAL
OF
Sir <hi>JOHN BVCKWORTH,</hi>
At the Parish-Church of
St. <hi>PETER's le POOR</hi>
IN
BROADSTREET,
<hi>December</hi> 29. 1687.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN SCOTT,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the Bishop's-Head in
St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard; and <hi>Thomas Horne,</hi> at the South-Entrance
of the Royal Exchange in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:97988:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Guil. Needham.
<date>Jan. 10.
1687.</date>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97988:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97988:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97988:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO MY
Lady Buckworth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN Obedience to Your Desires, I here
present You with the Discourse I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
at the Funeral of Your Excellent
Husband, and my never to be forgotten
Friend. And indeed considering how little
there is in it, I have no other Apologie
to make for the Publication of it, but
that I could not without some degree of
<pb facs="tcp:97988:4"/>
Incivility refuse it, being urged with the
concurrent Requests of Your Ladiship, and
the rest of those my worthy Friends his dearest
Relatives. Not that I altogether despair
of its having some good Influence upon So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
and Attentive Readers. There are
some Thoughts in it which are apt enough
to Inspire considering Minds with good
Affections and Resolutions. The Text,
I am sure, contains excellent Sense in it,
and the Argument is mighty Serious and
Momentous: and how meanly soever I
have managed it, some honest Reader, I
hope, may from hence take occasion to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
my defects out of his own Meditations,
and so to improve it to his everlasting Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.
And as for Your Ladiship, I
hope the perusal of it, instead of reviving
<pb facs="tcp:97988:4"/>
Your Sorrows for Your Dear Loss, may
be some way Instrumental to Animate You
with a firm and vigorous Resolution, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue
that Blessed State, wherein This, and all
Your other Losses here, will ere long be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly
repaired in a most joyous and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting
Fruition. And This, <hi>MADAM,</hi>
is my hearty Prayers as well as my hope;
who am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your Ladiships</salute>
Obliged and Faithful
Servant,
<signed>JOHN SCOTT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:97988:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97988:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ECCLESIAST. xi. 8.</bibl>
               <q>But if a man live many years, and rejoyce in
them all; yet let him remember the days of
darkness, for they shall be many.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Shall not trouble you with the various ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings
of these words; which (with a very
little difference) do all amount to the same
sence; <hi>viz.</hi> That supposing it should be a man's
good fortune to live very long, and exceeding
happy in this world; yet he ought to have
great care that the Joys of this Life, do not so
wholly take up and ingross his thoughts, as to
make him forget those <hi>days of darkness,</hi> which
must ere long succeed this delightsome Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shine;
which <hi>days</hi> will be <hi>many</hi> more, and of
much longer continuance than the longest Life
of happiness we can promise our selves in this
World. So that all the difficulty in these
words, is, what we are to understand by <hi>the
days of Darkness,</hi> which are here opposed to a
long Life of Joy and Rejoycing in this World?
And this difficulty will be easily resolved, by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97988:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
considering the foregoing Verse; <hi>Truly the light
is sweet, and a pleasant thing to the Eye to behold
the Sun;</hi> upon which it follows, <hi>But if a man
live many Years, i. e.</hi> supposing he should for
many Years injoy this pleasant spectacle of the
light of the Sun, yet let him remember those
days of Darkness, wherein his Eyes shall behold
the Sun and Light no more, wherein he shall be
laid up in a dark and silent Grave, whence the
light of the Sun is excluded, and where the
sight of the Eyes is extinguished; or as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses
it in the Third Verse of the next Chapter,
wherein <hi>those that look out at the windows are
darkened:</hi> So that we shall have neither visible
Objects, nor visive Organs; but be buried out
of sight in deep darkness and insensibility.
By <hi>the days of Darkness</hi> therefore is evidently
meant all that space of time between our Death
and our Resurrection, wherein our Bodies shall
lye mouldering in a dark Grave, utterly insen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible
of Good or Evil, till by the powerful call
of God they shall at length be roused up out of
this fatal slumber, into a state of Everlasting
Life and Activity: And these days, saith he, <hi>shall
be many,</hi> though they shall not run out to an
infinite duration, but at length conclude in a
general Resurrection, yet they shall <hi>be many,</hi>
many more in all probability, than any man
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97988:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
now alive can hope to live in this World.</p>
            <p>The words thus explained resolve into this
sence, That how long and happily soever men
live in this World, they ought to entertain
their thoughts with frequent remembrances
and considerations of their approaching Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.
Which is a duty so obvious to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences
of all men, as being founded on the
plainest and most conspicuous Reasons, that
the men of all Ages, and Nations, and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
have owned, and acknowledged it. Thus
the Heathen Philosophers teach, That our lives
ought to be a Constant Meditation of Death;
and that even in our most pleasant, and healthful
moments, we ought to look upon our selves as
Borderers upon Eternity; That we should still
take care to mingle our delights with the sad
remembrances of our Mortality, and not suffer
the Joys of this Life to divert our Thoughts
from that impending Fate, which ere long will
set an Everlasting period both to Them and
That. But the necessity of entertaining our
minds with frequent Remembrances of our
Latter end, is founded upon far more powerful
motives than a company of fine Sentences, and
pretty Sayings of Philosophers. For</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> It is necessary to moderate our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
to the World.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97988:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is necessary to allay the Gaiety
and Vanity of our minds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is necessary to put us upon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving
our present injoyments to the best pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It is necessary to fore-arm our minds
against the Terrors of Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> It is necessary to excite and quicken
us in our preparations for Eternity.</p>
            <p>I. It's necessary to moderate our Affections
to the world; while we are encompassed round
with the pleasures and delights of this world,
they commonly so ingross our minds, that we
shut our eyes against all futurities, and are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient
to think of any thing to come, unless it
be the continuance of this happy scene of things
which is at present before us; with which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance
we are exceeding apt to flatter our
selves, that so thereby we may heighten the
gust of our present enjoyments; to which the
consideration of their leaving us, or our leaving
them, would be apt to give a very ungrateful
farewel: and when our thoughts are wholly
intent upon these present goods; and upon the
prospect of their continuance, our affections
must necessarily run out towards them with an
immoderate ardour and greediness. For now
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97988:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
our flattering Imaginations represent them to
us as standing and permanent things, as a kind
of immortal heaven upon earth; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly
our affections pursue and imbrace them
as the best of goods; and are for dwelling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
them, and building Tabernacles in them,
there to make their final abode, as in their
highest and ultimate happiness. Now there is
no more effectual way to rouse mens minds out
of this flattering Dream of happiness, (from
which if they persist in it, the dire experience
of a woful Eternity will ere long awake them)
than frequently to entertain their minds with
the thoughts of their departure hence. For
when I set my self seriously to think of my dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
hour, that fairly represents to my deluded
mind, the true state and condition of all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
happiness. Here I plainly see that I am Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
at will to a thousand contingencies, in
every one of whose power it is to turn me out
of the World, and out of my Happiness toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
every moment of my life; and that when
I have erected this childish Castle of Cards, and
housed my self in it, as in an imaginary Fortress
of impregnable security; it is in the power of
every puff of wind to blow it down about my
ears, and bury me in its ruins. In every serious
prospect of my Mortality, I behold all my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97988:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
worldly enjoyments, which promised me such
mountains of happiness, standing round my
death-bed, mocking at all my foolish hopes, and
exposing my baffled expectations to scorn and
derision; and whilst in the anguish of my Soul
I cry out to them, O ye helpless impotent things,
what are now become of all your boasted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts?
you that promised to be a heaven
upon earth to me, why do not ye now help
me in this my last Extremity? why do not ye
quench my raging Thirst? why do not ye cool
my feaverish Blood? why do not ye ease my
labouring Heart, and quiet my convulsed and
tormented Bowels? All the Answer they return
is this, Alas poor deluded fool! 'tis not in us to
relieve or succour thee. But what will ye then
forsake and abandon me, and shall I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
left of all the mighty goods you promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
but only a Grave, a Coffin and a Winding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheet?
Alas, poor deceived wretch, we leave not
thee, but thou must leave us; being summoned
away by a fatal power, which we can neither
bribe nor resist: thy body must go down into
a cold dark Grave, and there lye utterly insensible
till the Resurrection; thy Soul must pass into
the Region of Spirits, whither we are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to follow thee, and where thou wilt have
nothing to live upon to all Eternity, but only
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97988:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Graces and Vertues of thy own mind. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel
then ye Treacherous Cheats and Impostors;
that promised so much, and now perform so
little; miserable Comforters are ye all, and
Physicians of no value. Such thoughts as these
the remembrance of our Mortality will be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
suggesting to us; and if such thoughts
do not cool and allay the heat of our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
to the world, we are incurably fond of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
deceived and abused by it.</p>
            <p>II. Frequently to remember our departure
hence, is very necessary to allay the Vanity and
Gaiety of our own minds; whilest we are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compassed
with the delights of this World, our
minds are generally too frolick and jovial to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
of any serious impressions: and if at any
time any good thoughts come in to visit us,
(as those two Angels did <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom</hi>) to warn
us of the dire Fate that hangs over us, our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
like the drunken <hi>Sodomites,</hi> are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently
all in an uproar, and will never be quiet,
till those unwelcome guests be thrown out that
disturb our Riots, and mingle harsh Discords
with our jovial Airs: and so long as we continue
in this light vain temper, there is nothing will
be grateful to us but frothy mirth, or loose
company, or gay Ideas of our selves, and of our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97988:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
own Wit, or Wealth, or Beauty, or Finery.
And thus we shall fool away our Lives in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
Vanity and Impertinence; in rolling about
from Vanity to Vanity, and never be Serious,
till we are forced to it by some woful experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.
But now to fix such a Roving and Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile
temper, and thereby to render it accessible
and hospitable to wise and good Thoughts, I know
nothing more necessary than the frequent
Remembrance of our Mortality: for as for the
future Worlds of endless Joy and Torment,
though they are in themselves the most serious
things in the World; yet being both Future
and Invisible, Vain and Sensual Minds are not
so capable of apprehending them with that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
of certainty that is necessary to render
them affecting and prevalent: But that we must
die, we are all as certain of as of our present
Existence; and therefore this, if any thing, must
move and affect us. If therefore together with
those gay Idea's that possess our Minds, we
would ever and anon mingle that of our Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality,
that would soon reduce our squandered
Thoughts, and make us Serious in despight of
our teeth. As for instance, when in thy night
Thoughts thou art priding thy self in the Pomp
and Splendor of thy outward condition, think
thus with thy self, Alas, within a little while
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97988:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
this Bed which now is as gay, and as soft as
the Sleep, and the Sins it entertains, must be
my Death-bed; here I must lye a languishing
sad Corps, which nothing in all this World can
help or ease: so that though now I should go
on to add House to House, and Lands to Lands,
even till I am become the Lord of all my Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon;
yet in that sad Hour all these will no
more be able to relieve me, than the Landskip
of them upon my Walls, or my Hangings:
then I may as successfully go to my Pictures,
and try to entertain my Mirth and Luxuries
with them, or to recreate my Ear with heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening
after painted sounds, or to gratifie my
Palate with the Image of a Feast; as to give my
self any ease or content with these gay things
I am now so proud of. And when at length I
have groaned away my fleeting Breath, I must
be removed from all my company &amp; attendance
into a dark, lonely and desolate hole of Earth,
where all my present Pomp must expire, and
be overcast with Everlasting Darkness. Again,
when in the Morning thou art entertaining thy
Vanity with thy Beauty, thy Wit, or thy fine
Cloaths, think thus with thy self, Alas, fond
Soul, all these gay objects of thy Pride, must
ere long convert to Rottenness and Corruption;
that curled Forehead must be bedewed with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97988:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
clammy Sweats; those sprightly Eyes must
wax as dim as a sullied Mirror; that charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Voice must grow as weak as the faint E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choes
of a distant Valley; and all those Lilies
and Roses on thy Cheeks must wither into the
paleness of Death, and shroud themselves in the
horrors of the Grave. Again, when in the
Afternoon thou hast been entertaining thy self
with Mirth, or Sport, or Luxury, go down
into the Charnel-house, and there survey a
while the numerous Trophies of victorious
Death: In these gastly Mirrors thou beholdest
the true Resemblance of thy future State: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
years ago that naked Skull was covered like
thine, with a thick fleece of curled and comely
Locks; those empty holes were filled with Eyes
that looked as charmingly as thine; those hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
Pits were blanched with Cheeks that were
as smooth and amiable as thine; that grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
Mouth did smile as gracefully, and speak
as fluently as thine; and a few days hence
thou must be Rotting into just such another
spectacle: And forty years hence perhaps here
may thy naked Ribs be found mingled with
these scattered Bones; and then should another
take up thy bald Skull, as thou dost this, he
will find it dressed in all the self-same horrors
of this Deaths-Head; with its Nose sunk, its
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97988:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Jaws gaping, its Mouth grinning, and Worms
crawling in those empty holes wherein now thy
Eyes roul to and fro in Amorous glances; and
a Toad perhaps ingendring in that Brain that
is now so full of sprightly Thoughts, and gay
Idea's. If with these, or such like Considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of our Mortality, we would now and then
entertain our selves, they would by degrees
wear off the Levity and Vanity of our Minds,
and compose us into such a degree of Serious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
as is necessary to qualifie us for those Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
and Religious Considerations, without
which we can never expect either to be made
good men here, or happy men hereafter.</p>
            <p>III. That we should frequently remember
our Mortality, in the midst of our
most happy Circumstances here, is highly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary
to put us upon improving our present
injoyments to the best purposes, considering
what use the generality of Men make of the
Injoyments of this World, It is really a great
question, Whether it would not be much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
for them, even in respect of this Life, to
be without them, than with them. For ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
they shrivel them into miserableness, or
melt them into Luxury. The former of which
impoverishes, and the latter diseases them.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97988:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
For if the former be the effect of a man's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperous
condition, it increases his needs; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
before, he needed only what he had not;
but now he needs both what he hath not, and
what he hath. His covetous desires treating
him as the Faulkner doth his Hawk, still lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
him off from what he hath seised, to fly
at new Game, and never permitting him to
prey upon his own Quarry. And if the latter
be the effect of his prosperity, that is, if it
melts him into Luxury, it thereby wastes his
Health, to be sure, and commonly his Estate
too; and so whereas it found him Poor and
Well, it leaves him Poor and Diseased. And
whereas it at first took him up from the
Plough, it at last sets him down at the Hospital.
And in general, while he is possessed of it, it
only bloats and swells him; makes him proud
and insolent, griping and oppressive; pampers
and inrages his Lust, and stretches out his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires
into an insatiable Boulimy; sticks his
Mind full of cares, and his Conscience of
guilts: And by all these woful effects, inflames
his Reckoning with God, and treasures up
wrath for him against the day of wrath.
All which arises from the want of a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
Remembrance of our Mortality. For
did we but often ruminate upon this, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97988:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
it is but a very little while that we have to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
the Comforts of this Life, and that within
a very few years, yea, perhaps a few days, we
shall be stript of them all, and be sent as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly
out of this World as ever we came in;
and when we are gone hence, of all the Goods
that we have left behind us, we shall have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
to live upon to Eternity, but only the
Good that we did with them, the Necessities
that we Relieved, the Oppressions that we
Eased, the Nakedness that we Clothed, and the
Hunger that we Satisfied: these indeed will <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
after us,</hi> and feed us with content and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness
to eternal Ages. But if we are destitute
of these, we shall ere long be Shipt off from all
our present enjoyments, and be Landed in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
World, upon a strange Inhospitable Shore,
and there be left miserable poor Wretches,
without so much as one drop of the Comforts
we now enjoy to satisfie our Tormenting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires,
or to quench our still raging Thirst after
happiness: Then we shall Wish a thousand and a
thousand times over, that instead of gratifying
our Luxuries with the mispence of our Wealth,
or feeding our insatiate Avarice with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual
increase of it, we had by doing works of
Piety and Charity with it, <hi>made our selves friends
of the Mammon of unrighteousness, that so when we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97988:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
failed, they might receive us into everlasting habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi>
and there entertain us with pleasure and
delight for ever. Well then, seeing that ere it
be long we must leave all these our present
possessions behind us; it highly concerns us,
while we enjoy them, to do all the Good that
we are able with them: and seeing we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
to carry nothing of them but the Good
we do with them along with us, to enrich and
maintain us in our Eternal condition; by doing
Good with our Wealth, we shall Convert and
Proselyte it, and make that an Offering which
others make an Idol; we shall make this Earth
Tributary to Heaven, and in a much nobler
Sense than the new Systeme of Astronomy
teaches, advance it into a Star, and a Celestial
Body: by this we shall transmit it into the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
World, as it were, by Bill of Exchange,
there to be repaid us, Ten Thousand fold in
Glory and Honour and Immortality, and Ten
Thousand Ages hence we shall be enricht with
the product of it, and receive a vast revenue
of Happiness from it for ever. Suppose now
that you were a Merchant in a far Country,
where you were allowed for an uncertain time
the benefit of free Trade and Commerce, in
order to your gaining a good Estate to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
you whenever you should be forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97988:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to your own Native Soil, would you be so
indiscreet as to lay out all the product of your
Merchandise in Building fine Houses, or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chasing
great Farms, when you know not how
soon you may be commanded to depart, and
to leave all these immoveable Goods behind
you, or rather would you not think your selves
obliged by all the Laws of Interest and Discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to convert all your Gain into portable
Wealth, into Money or Jewels, or such move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
Commodities, as when you depart hence
you might carry home along with you, and
there be able to maintain your selves in many
years ease and plenty. Do but think then, and
think it often, that here you are strangers,
and foreign Merchants; that you came hither
from another World, to which you know not
how soon you must return again; that all the
Wealth, the Houses and Lands, you gain by
your present Commerce, are immoveable
Goods, which you must leave behind ye when
ye go from hence, and that there is nothing of
them Portable, but what you lay out in Piety
and Charity; and that therefore it concerns
you, while you have opportunity, to store and
treasure up a plentiful proportion of these, that
so when you are Shipt off into the Eternal
World, you may carry such an Estate of them
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97988:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thither with you, as may suffice to maintain
you there in Glory and Happiness for ever.</p>
            <p>IV. That we should frequently remember
our Mortality, even in the midst of our most
happy Circumstances here, is highly necessary
to fore-arm our minds against the Terrors of
Death. Whilst we abound with the enjoyments
of this Life, we are apt to put far from us the
evil day, and with the rich Churl in the Gospel,
to promise our selves many years Ease and Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuousness
in this World: So that Death ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
steals upon us before we are aware, and
like a Thief in a frightful Vizor surprises in the
midst of a deep Security, and after we have
strugled with him a few moments to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
robs us of our Lives and our Happiness
together. And O how terrible must Death be
when it approaches a man under such Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances;
when the poor deluded wretch hath
been just Singing a soft <hi>Requiem</hi> to himself,
<hi>Soul take thy rest and ease, thou hast goods laid up
for many years,</hi> and many years to possess and
enjoy them; For Death now to pronounce
that fatal sentence, <hi>Thou fool this night shall thy
soul be taken from thee.</hi> Now when he thought
all was safe, and concluded himself secure of a
long Lease of Life and Happiness: Now before
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97988:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
he hath given himself the leisure to think of his
Dying hour, or to fortifie his Heart with any
wise or good Thoughts against the Terrors of
this terrible one, that is just now brandishing
its fatal shaft at his breast! How must it needs
blank and amaze and confound him? and what
a trembling horror must it strike through his
Heart, to see himself thus unexpectedly hurried
away, one part of him to the Grave, and the other
to Eternity, now when he thought himself
so securely possessed of a long enjoyment of the
good things of this Life. Wherefore as we would
be fore-armed against the Terrors of Death,
and enabled to abide his dreadful approaches
with a firm and constant Mind, it concerns us
now while we are surrounded with the Joys and
Pleasures of this Life, to entertain our Minds
with frequent thoughts and remembrances of
him; to retire now and then into the Charnel-house,
and there to read Lectures to our selves
upon the Skelitons and Deaths Heads, those
emblems and representations of our approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Mortality: and from them to take such
lively Pictures and Ideas of this King of Terrors,
as may render his grim visage and fearful ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses
more familiar to us, and give our
thoughts a more intimate acquaintance with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97988:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
him, and with the manner and method of his
approaches; with what an Army of Diseases
he is wont to lay Siege to the Fort of our
Life; and how in despite of all the resistances
of Nature, he plants and quarters them in our
Veins and Arteries, and Stomachs and Bowels,
and from thence infests us all over with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual
Anguish and Pain: how when he hath
tired and exhausted us with his continued Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries,
and worn out our strength with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted
succession of wearisom Nights to
sorrowful Days, he at last storms the Soul out
of all the out-works of Nature, and forces it to
retire into the Heart; and how when upon this
last retreat of Life he hath marked us for dead,
in a cold Baptism of clammy and fatal Sweats,
he summons our weeping Friends together, to
assist him in grieving us with their parting
kisses, and sorrowful adieus; and how at length
when he is weary of tormenting us any more,
he rushes into our Hearts, and with a few mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
Pangs and Convulsions tears the Soul from
thence, and turns it out to seek its fortune in
the wide world of Spirits, where it is either
seized on by Devils, and carried away to their
dark Prisons of Sorrow and Despair, there to
languish out its Life in a dismal expectation of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97988:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that dreadful day wherein it must change its
bad condition for a worse; or be conducted
by Angels to some Blessed Abode, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
in unspeakable Pleasure and Tranquillity,
till the great day of its Coronation with a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
Resurrection. If we would thus frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
survey our approaching Mortality in all the
Circumstances and Appendages of it, we should
hereby familiarize its Terrors to our Minds, so
that when ever it happens to us, our thoughts
which have been so long accustomed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse
with it, will be much less startled and
amazed at it, and the often remembrances we
have past upon it, will put us upon laying in
such wise and good Thoughts and Considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
as are best able to fortifie our minds
against it, and to inspire us with Courage and
Alacrity under it.</p>
            <p>V. And Lastly, Frequently to remember our
Mortality in the midst of our most happy Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances
here, is highly necessary to excite
and quicken us in our Preparations for Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity:
and hence it is that we are so often cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
upon in this Militant Estate to <hi>consider our
latter end, Deut.</hi> 32. 29. and by the examples
of the best men, are invited <hi>So to number our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97988:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
days that we may apply our hearts unto wisdom,</hi>
Psal. 90. 12. <hi>and to wait till our change comes,</hi> Job
14. 14. To which end also we are put in mind,
that <hi>Here we have no abiding City,</hi> Heb. 13. 14.
and that <hi>it is appointed for all men once to dy,</hi> Heb.
9. 27. and that <hi>our life is even as a vapour that
appears for a little time, and then vanishes away,</hi>
Jam. 4. 14. And to this purpose the Apostle
applies this consideration, 1 <hi>Cor. 7. 29, 30, 31.
Now this I say, brethren, (i.e.</hi> of our uncertain
abode and continuance here) (upon which he
exhorts us to compose our selves to a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency
as to the things of this World) <hi>it
remains, that they that have wives, be as if they had
none: and they that weep, as though they wept not:
and they that rejoyce, as though they rejoyced not: and
they that buy, as though they possessed not: and they
that use this world, as not abusing it: for the fashion
of this world passeth away, i.e.</hi> Since your time here
is so very short and uncertain, see you endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
beforehand to loosen your selves from
this World, and to put your selves into a fit
posture to leave it; for 'tis but a short Scene
of things, that will quickly be shifted, and then
there will an Eternal state of things succeed.
And indeed, since to Dy well is the last Act and
final Consummation of our Life; it must needs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97988:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
highly concern us, to arm and prepare our
selves for it beforehand, lest we lose the prize,
by stumbling just at the Goal; and after a long
Voyage, miscarry within sight of Harbour.
For in the hour of Death we throw our last
Cast for an Eternity of Happiness or Misery:
And how much are we concerned to throw that
well, upon which so vast a Stake depends? O
my Brethren, it is a most serious thing to Die, to
pass this dark Entry of Eternity, through which,
as we go right or wrong, we are made or
undone for ever: For to carry us right
through, 'tis not a few Death-bed sorrows, or
good wishes; 'tis not a few extorted Promises,
or forced Resolutions, or rack'd Confessions,
and Lord have mercy upon us. O no, to
Die well is an expensive Passage, which we shall
never be able to defray, unless we carry along
with us a very great stock of Spiritual Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.
We shall have need of a strong and
active Faith; of a Mind well furnished with
wise and good Considerations, of a deep and
large, and a tried Repentance, of an unrestrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
Charity, of a confirmed Patience, of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
Submission to the Will of God, and a
well grounded Hope of a blessed Eternity.
For without all these together, we shall be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97988:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ill accoutred to Die, and run a fearful ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard
of miscarrying for ever. And these are
such things as do not usually spring up like
Mushromes, in a night, and much less in the
disturbed moments of a Dying hour; but do
ask a much larger and serener Season to grow
and ripen in. But if whilst we are entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
our selves among the Joys and Pleasures
of this Life, we banish from our Minds the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
of our Mortality, and look upon
Eternity as a thing at a vast distance, this will
put us upon delaying and deferring our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration
for it. For in this temper we shall
be apt to conclude, that we have time enough
to come to begin and compleat our Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
and that we may safely indulge our
selves yet a good while longer, in the free in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment
of our own hearts desires, and sin on
at present upon this Security, that we will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
Repent hereafter; and by this easie
Train do men toule themselves on through the
several stages of their Sin and Life, till they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive
at their Death-bed, and then they begin
to think of Repenting in good earnest. But
then alas, what will they be able to do, when
their Thoughts are continually disturbed with
the care of disposing their Affairs in this World,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97988:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and the frightful prospect they have of the
other. When their Minds are distracted with
incessant Pain and uneasiness; so that it is not
in their power to consider so much as a quarter
of an hour together; when through the stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por
and indisposition of the Organs of their
Reason, they are not able to range their scatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and unwieldy Thoughts into any of those
sober Reflexions and serious Meditations, that
are necessary to the forming of a sincere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?
In effect therefore for men to refer
their Repentance to a Death-bed, is the same
thing as to retire into a Battel to Meditate,
or to set up a Closset to study Philosophy in,
in the head Quarters of an Army, where most
men are as capable of free and undisturbed
Contemplations, as they are of Repenting
amidst the Tumults and Hurries of a Death-bed.
And yet upon this dismal extremity do
men commonly cast themselves, through their
neglect of remembring their approaching
Mortality. Whereas did they but often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
and seriously reflect on it, they would
as soon dare eat Fire, as defer their Repentance
upon the uncertain hopes of futurity. For alas,
what is vain Man, that he should talk of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting
hereafter, when perhaps while the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97988:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
words are in his mouth, the earnest of Death
is in his Head, or Heart, or Bowels; when
for all he knows, he may be inflamed with a
Fevor with what he hath drank to day, or
stifled with a Surfeit with what he shall eat to
morrow; when he may expire his Soul with
his next Breath, or suck in his bane with the
next Air; and so many unlooked for accidents
may presently put an end to all his talk of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting
hereafter, and render it impossible for
ever? Now of what dismal consequence would
it be, should I be thus surprized? If while I
presume upon my future Repentance, I am
merrily Sinning on, I should all of a sudden
be hurried away out of the company of my
Jovial Associates, into that of houling and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
Spirits: And from my Songs and
Laughter, into weeping, and wailing, and
gnashing of Teeth. How would it blank and
amaze me to think, that ever I should be so
mad, as to run such a desperate hazard? How
dare we then talk of Repenting hereafter, when
we consider, that it is not in our power to
command so much as one moment of future
time? When for all that we know, the hope of
Eternity, which is now in our hands, may be
lost for ever, and drop through our Fingers
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97988:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
before to morrow morning? And that when
we lye down at night, and fall asleep securely
in our Sins, we do not know, but before the
next Twilight we may awake with horror and
amazement in Hell? Let us seriously consider
therefore, that the present time only is in our
power; and that as for the future, it is wholly
in God's: and that therefore when we defer
our Repentance to the future, we do, as it
were, cast Lots for our Soul, and venture our
Everlasting hopes upon a contingency which is
not in our power to dispose of. For all we
know, this may be the Evening of our day of
Trial; and if it be, our Life and Eternity de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends
upon what we are now doing. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
it highly concerns us, by all the regard we
owe to our own Everlasting safety, wisely to
manage this last Stake, the winning or losing
whereof may be our making or undoing.
Thus will the frequent remembrance of our
Mortality put us upon laying in good store of
Spiritual provisions against that great day of
Expence. For he who often considers the great
uncertainty of Life, the dreadful approaches,
the concomitant Terrors, and the momentous
issues and consequents of Death; must be
strangely stupified, if thereby he be not vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97988:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
excited, to fore-arm and fortifie himself
with all those Graces, and Defences, that are
necessary to render his Departure hence easie,
and safe, and prosperous.</p>
            <p>And now having done with the Text, I shall
only crave your leave to say a few words upon
this sorrowful occasion; <hi>viz.</hi> The Funeral of
our common Friend, Sir <hi>John Buckworth,</hi> who
perhaps while he lived, was a person as emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently
known, as ever any Merchant that trod
the Exchange of <hi>London.</hi> And indeed conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
the great share he had of Intellectual En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments,
He was a Gentleman that seemed
to have been mark'd out by Providence, to
make a considerable Figure among Men. For
First, Nature had inrich'd him with a clear bright
Mind, with a quick Apprehension, a prompt
Memory, a steady and a piercing Judgment,
together with a natural presence of Mind, and
fluency and readiness of Speech, which inabled
him upon all occasions easily to express his own
conceptions of things in very clear and apt
Language. All which Natural Indowments
he had vastly improved and cultivated, by a
long and curious Observation and Experience.
For as Nature had fitted him for an active
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97988:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Life, so Providence soon introduced him upon
the stage of Action. For as he was born a
Gentleman, so he was educated a Merchant;
which perhaps is one of the most advantagious
Academies in the World, to instruct the Mind
in the knowledge of Men, and the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of Humane Affairs. His Education fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished
him with a fair opportunity of seeing the
World, as well abroad, as at home; and of
prying into the Intrigues of Commerce, and
into the Manners and Interests of Men; whence
he drew so many wise and useful Observations,
as rendred him a Prince among Merchants, and
an Oracle of Trade; insomuch that he was
thought worthy to be chosen Deputy-Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
of that wise and great Company of the
Turky Merchants; and was perhaps as much
consulted by his Superiors, about the Interest
of the <hi>English</hi> Trade, and the Mysteries of
Commerce, as any one Merchant of this City
or Nation. Thus for his Intellectuals. As for
his Morals; I believe that all that knew him,
will allow him this Character, That he was a
Gentleman of great Integrity and Fidelity to
his Trust; of exact Justice and Righteousness in
his Commerce and Dealings: That he was a
studious and successful Peace-maker: And
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97988:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
great part of his Time, before he was called
up by his Prince, into a more busie and active
Station, being spent in Arbitrating differences
between Man and Man: in which he was so
expert, so impartial and prosperous; that I am
apt to think he cemented as many broken
Friendships, reconciled as many Quarrels, and
adjusted as many Differences, (which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
might have flamed out into destructive
breaches) as most of those blessed Peace-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
that are gone before him.</p>
            <p>Consider him in his respective Relations,
and there all that knew him I am sure will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
him to have been a Faithful, a Loyal and
useful Subject to his Prince, a kind and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
Husband to his Lady, a tender and a wise
Father to his Children, a prudent, careful and
benevolent Master to his Servants; and in a word,
a wise Counsellor, a faithful Friend, and a just
and diligent Correspondent. As for his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
he was a hearty Protestant of the Church
of <hi>England,</hi> which upon mature Judgment,
and upon thorow Information, he preferred
for the Loyalty of its Principles, the Simplicity
of its Doctrines, and the Primitive Purity of its
Worship and Discipline, before all the Churches
in the World; and what his Judgment was of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97988:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
our Church, he visibly exprest by his constant
attendance upon the Publick Offices of our
Religion upon the Lord's day, from which he
never absented, but when he was either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
by Sickness, or some very urgent and
unavoidable occasion; and in which he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
demeaned him with all the profound Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
and Devotion that outwardly expresses
a Mind inspired with a Pious Sense of its Duty,
and of the awful presence of the great Majesty
of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Thus he Lived, and as for his Death, though
it was accompanied with all the Circumstances
that could render a man fond of Life, and
make him play loth to depart, though he had
a plentiful Estate, a loving and beloved Wife,
dutiful and hopeful Children, and these all
of them happily disposed off and setled in the
World to his own Hearts content: To leave
all which at once, seems a very hard Chapter
to a mind not well resolved; yet all these to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
had no such effect upon him. Indeed
not long before his Death, though then in
perfect health, he seemed to have an Aboding
of his approaching Fate; for having to his
hearts desire, disposed of his only Son in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97988:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
(who was the last of his Children un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disposed)
he hath been often heard to say, That
now he thanked God, his business in this World
was finished, and that it was high time for him
to think of his Departure into the other: and
when soon after he was seized with his last
Sickness, he bore it with an invincible Courage
and Constancy; and though the last part of it
was extremely painful to him, he underwent
it without Complaint or Murmuring, with
a Mind that seemed intirely resigned to the
Soveraign Disposer of all Events. And when
he perceived the approaches of Death, and
found that he was going off this Stage of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,
he never shew'd the least sign of Regret
or Reluctancy, but took a solemn leave of his
Friends; and which was much harder, of his dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
Relatives, who stood lamenting and weeping
about him; and this with a Mind very serious
indeed, but in all appearance very calm and
composed. And finally he gave up the Ghost like
a brave Man and a good Christian, with a
firm and undaunted Mind, and as one that
had placed his main hope on the other side the
Grave, and did expect to exchange an uneasie
Mortal Life, for an Immortal one of Pleasure.
And therefore though I make no doubt after
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97988:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
all, but that as a Man, he had his Faults, (and
he that hath none let him cast the first stone)
yet I am sure he had his Vertues, and those
very eminent ones too: And therefore it will
highly become us who survive, in Charity to
cast a Vail over the one, and in Piety imitate
and transcribe the other; That so with him,
and all our other Christian Brethren departed
this Life in God's true Faith and Fear, we may
have our final Consummation in Bliss and
Glory, through Jesus Christ our Lord: To
whom with the Father, and Eternal Spirit,
Three Persons and One God, be ascribed all
Honour and Glory and Power and Dominion
for ever and ever. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
