<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sacellum Apollinaire a funeral poem to the memory of that great patriot &amp; statesman, George, late Marquis of Hallifax.</title>
            <author>Settle, Elkanah, 1648-1724.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-06">2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37372</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16412259</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16412259</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105375</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A59341)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105375)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1158:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sacellum Apollinaire a funeral poem to the memory of that great patriot &amp; statesman, George, late Marquis of Hallifax.</title>
                  <author>Settle, Elkanah, 1648-1724.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Wilkins, and are to be sold by R. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Settle by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Halifax, George Savile, --  Marquis of, 1633-1695 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105375:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105375:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sacellum Apollinare.</hi> A Funeral POEM TO THE MEMORY OF THAT <hi>Great Patriot &amp; Stateſman,</hi> GEORGE, LATE Marquiſs of Hallifax.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>—Sapiens dominabitur Aſtris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J. Wilkins</hi>; and are to be Sold by <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi>-Inn, in <hi>Warwick</hi>-Lane, 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105375:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105375:2"/>
            <head>A Funeral POEM, &amp;c.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AS HEAV'N it Self's on <hi>Empire</hi>'s Axis roll'd,</l>
               <l>(For <hi>God-Head</hi>'s but <hi>Dominion</hi> Uncontroul'd;)</l>
               <l>So the <hi>Crown'd Head,</hi> the Sublunary <hi>JOVE,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Does, in his Royal <hi>Orb</hi> of <hi>Glory,</hi> move;</l>
               <l>With all his <hi>Bolts of Fate,</hi> in his High Poſt</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Sovereign Pow'r,</hi> the Weilded <hi>Thunder</hi> boaſt.</l>
               <l>But, in the Higheſt tow'ring Flight of KINGS,</l>
               <l>'Tis the Great <hi>Stateſman</hi> plumes their <hi>Eagles</hi> Wings;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They</hi> Move the Great MACHINE, <hi>He</hi> Sets the <hi>Springs.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And thus, whilſt Pregnant EMPIRE's <hi>Labouring Head</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With ſome vaſt <hi>Off-ſpring</hi> Teems; the <hi>Stateſman</hi>'s Aid,</l>
               <l>To bring the Fair Divine <hi>Minerva</hi> Forth,</l>
               <l>Is call'd the Great <hi>Lucina</hi> to the <hi>Birth.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Counſel!</hi> 'Tis their Min'iſtring Ray,</l>
               <l>Thoſe Bright CROWN-<hi>Genij,</hi> Cheer th' <hi>Imperial Sway:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105375:3"/>The <hi>Harmony</hi> of WORLDS is only Theirs;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Empire</hi> but Guides, 'tis <hi>They</hi> that Tune the <hi>Spheres:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Counſel,</hi> in Church or State, the <hi>Warmth,</hi> by Whom</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aaron</hi>'s and <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Budding <hi>Wands</hi> both Bloom:</l>
               <l>Thus MONARCHY, what, tho' She Reigns <hi>Alone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis by her <hi>Argus</hi>-Eyes She Guards her Throne:</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Lights</hi> an Hundred, tho' her <hi>Hand</hi>'s but One.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of thoſe Rich <hi>Lights,</hi> Great <hi>HALLIFAX</hi> ſhin'd there;</l>
               <l>In <hi>Powr's</hi> whole <hi>Conſtellation,</hi> None more Fair:</l>
               <l>In <hi>Calms</hi> or <hi>Storms,</hi> in every varying <hi>Gale,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Furl'd, the Hoyſted, or the Slacken'd <hi>Sayl</hi>;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Helm</hi> to Manage, or the <hi>Mates</hi> to Cheer,</l>
               <l>No <hi>Pilot</hi>-Hand cou'd ever Worthier <hi>Steer:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>TRUST, the Magnetick <hi>Load ſtar</hi> of his Soul;</l>
               <l>And FAITH, and ZEAL, his <hi>Needles</hi> to the <hi>Pole.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Studied <hi>World</hi> was his Long <hi>Theam,</hi> and All</l>
               <l>The <hi>Politick Movements</hi> of the Mighty <hi>Ball:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105375:3"/>Yes, the <hi>Old World</hi> He had Fathom'd o're and o're;</l>
               <l>Nay, had there been yet <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown Globes</hi> t' explore,</l>
               <l>To give that <hi>Head,</hi> that <hi>Reach,</hi> thoſe <hi>Depths,</hi> their Due,</l>
               <l>He had ſtood a Fair <hi>Columbus,</hi> for the <hi>New.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In SENATES, There, with all his <hi>Brighteſt Beams,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not <hi>Michael,</hi> to th' Embattl'd <hi>Seraphims,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A Mightier <hi>Leading</hi> CHIEF: Oraculous <hi>Senſe!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Victorious <hi>Right!</hi> Amazing <hi>Eloquence!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All from that Cleareſt <hi>Organ</hi> ſweetly Sung:</l>
               <l>From that bold ENGLISH <hi>CICERO</hi>'s Silver Tongue,</l>
               <l>VVell might Great TRUTH, and Genuine <hi>Juſtice</hi> flow;</l>
               <l>For <hi>He</hi> Lookt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pward,</hi> when <hi>He</hi> Talkt <hi>Below:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Up to <hi>ASTRAEA,</hi> Heav'ns tranſlated <hi>Pride,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her Righteous <hi>Ballance</hi> his Great <hi>Standard</hi> Guide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In Redreſs'd <hi>Wrongs,</hi> and Succour'd <hi>Rights APPEAL,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No Hand, in the <hi>Judiciary Scale,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>More VVeigh'd and Pois'd, than <hi>HALLIFAX</hi> alone;</l>
               <l>Ev'n <hi>Half</hi> the Great <hi>Tribunal,</hi> was his Own.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:105375:4"/>But, in that more Exalted <hi>Patriot</hi>-Cauſe,</l>
               <l>The Moulding of thoſe <hi>Stamps Imperial,</hi> LAWS;</l>
               <l>Then, when the whole <hi>Divinity</hi> of <hi>Pow'r,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In her <hi>Collective Strength,</hi> that Lab'ring Hour,</l>
               <l>In her All-wiſe Conſulting <hi>Providence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sits, ſome New Fair <hi>Creations</hi> to Commence;</l>
               <l>In that <hi>High VVork,</hi> for the Great <hi>FIAT</hi> Fixt,</l>
               <l>No Hand like <hi>His,</hi> the Sovereign ELEMENTS Mixt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Fam'd GAMALIEL in the Great <hi>State-Schools,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus by unerring PRUDENCE Sacred Rules,</l>
               <l>No wonder, on that <hi>Card'nal Hinge</hi> He mov'd;</l>
               <l>In <hi>Pow'r-Craft</hi> Skill'd, that Bold <hi>Arts-Maſter</hi> prov'd:</l>
               <l>The Great <hi>Performing Part</hi> He had Study'd thro',</l>
               <l>And no leſs Learnt the Greater <hi>Duty</hi> too.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Publick Spirit,</hi> and the <hi>Active Soul,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>More Lively <hi>VVarmth,</hi> than e're <hi>Prometheus</hi> ſtole,</l>
               <l>Thoſe <hi>Champions</hi> both of <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Heav'n</hi>'s Juſt Right,</l>
               <l>Bound by their Great <hi>Indenture Tripartite,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:105375:4"/>Their equally divided FAITH muſt bring,</l>
               <l>Betwixt their GOD, their <hi>Country,</hi> and their <hi>King.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In <hi>Pow'r</hi> and <hi>Truſt,</hi> thro' his whole Life's long Scene,</l>
               <l>Never did <hi>Honour</hi> wear a Hand more <hi>Clean:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He from the <hi>Iſrael Prophet</hi>'s Copy drew;</l>
               <l>The Suppliant <hi>Naaman</hi> for his Grace might ſue.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diſtreſs,</hi> 'tis true, his Succour ne'r cou'd lack —</l>
               <l>But then her <hi>Laded Chariots</hi> muſt go Back.</l>
               <l>No <hi>Syrian Bribe</hi> was on his Shoulders worn;</l>
               <l>That <hi>Tainted Robe</hi> ſuch TRUTH and VIRTUE ſcorn.</l>
               <l>Thus, like the <hi>Eden Pair,</hi> Why is <hi>Truth</hi> drawn</l>
               <l>A <hi>Naked Beauty,</hi> in Tranſparent Lawn?</l>
               <l>Yes, 'till her <hi>Innocence,</hi> for Imp'ious <hi>Gold,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That Tempting, Falſe <hi>Heſperian Apple,</hi> Sold;</l>
               <l>'Tis from that <hi>Fall,</hi> Original <hi>Bluſhes</hi> came;</l>
               <l>'Twas <hi>Then</hi> She wanted <hi>Fig-Leaves</hi> for her Shame.</l>
               <l>A <hi>Bribe!</hi> That moſt loath'd <hi>Thought</hi>! Ev'n his whole <hi>Roof,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His humbleſt <hi>Menials,</hi> that Temptation-Proof,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105375:5"/>(So Fair their Leading LORD's <hi>Example</hi> ſtands)</l>
               <l>Oblig'd with Frank <hi>Full</hi> Hearts, but <hi>Empty</hi> Hands.</l>
               <l>His <hi>Favours</hi> in that <hi>Generous Current</hi> run,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Providence</hi> vouchſafes Her <hi>Rain</hi> and <hi>Sun.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>Favours</hi> Cheaper ev'n than <hi>Heav'n</hi>'s confer'd:</l>
               <l>For, though, like <hi>Heav'n,</hi> th' Imploring <hi>Pray'r</hi> He heard;</l>
               <l>Yet no <hi>Thanksgiving Offerings</hi> Return'd:</l>
               <l>To His Kind GRACE, no <hi>Gumms</hi> nor <hi>Incenſe</hi> burn'd.</l>
               <l>Ay, and 'twas Nobly Brave! What can more high,</l>
               <l>Than an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmercinary Greatneſs</hi> fly?</l>
               <l>If ought his <hi>Obligations</hi> muſt Defray,</l>
               <l>He rather choſe that <hi>Heav'n,</hi> than <hi>Man</hi> ſhould Pay:</l>
               <l>Yes, with a Fair <hi>Ambition,</hi> Juſt <hi>Diſdain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Scorn'd leſs than <hi>JOVE,</hi> his <hi>Golden Show'rs</hi> ſhou'd Rain.</l>
               <l>And well ſo High, that <hi>Fair Ambition</hi> tow'r'd;</l>
               <l>For <hi>HALLIFAX</hi> ſo <hi>Scorn'd,</hi> and <hi>JOVE</hi> ſo <hi>Show'r'd:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whil'ſt that vaſt <hi>Affluence</hi> Warm'd his <hi>Fruitful Soyl,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Till his <hi>Rich Glebe,</hi> and <hi>Loaded Harveſt</hi> Pile,</l>
               <l>With that <hi>Increaſe,</hi> that <hi>Milky Canaan</hi> flow'd:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Proſperity</hi> thus Reap'd, where <hi>Virtue</hi> Sow'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105375:5"/>
               <l>NATURE &amp; FORTUNE, <hi>Here,</hi> both <hi>Rivals</hi> join'd,</l>
               <l>Which to their darling <hi>HALLIFAX,</hi> more Kind,</l>
               <l>Should heap the Ampler <hi>Maſs: Nature</hi> her more</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Refin'd,</hi> and <hi>Fortune</hi> in her <hi>Courſer Oar.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>World</hi> but Smil'd, where <hi>Heav'n</hi> had Smil'd before.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Great Bleſſings,</hi> when by <hi>Greater MERIT</hi> ſhar'd,</l>
               <l>(Not Providence's <hi>Gift,</hi> but her <hi>Reward,</hi>)</l>
               <l>Are all <hi>Heav'n</hi>'s Faireſt <hi>Blazon,</hi> Nobleſt <hi>Pride</hi>;</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Eternal</hi> DISPENSATION <hi>Juſtify'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Righteous Diſtribution</hi> ought no leſs:</l>
               <l>So Great 'tis to <hi>Deſerve,</hi> and then <hi>Poſſeſs.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor in Proud <hi>Courts,</hi> nor <hi>States</hi> alone, that Great</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dictator</hi>; Ev'n in the DESPOTIC <hi>Seat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In His own narrower <hi>Domeſtic Sway,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>Houſhold</hi> Sweet <hi>Penates</hi> deckt ſo Gay;</l>
               <l>To VICE, like <hi>Hannibal</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſworn</l>
               <l>Eternal <hi>Foe</hi>; and VIRTUE's <hi>Champion</hi> born:</l>
               <l>To his own <hi>Filial Nurſery,</hi> ſo Kind</l>
               <l>A FATHER, with thoſe <hi>Leading Lights,</hi> He ſhin'd:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105375:6"/>
                  <hi>HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R,</hi> ſo Lovely by that <hi>Pencil</hi> drawn,</l>
               <l>The Early <hi>Phoſphor</hi> to their <hi>Morning Dawn:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So Fam'd his equally <hi>Paternal Care,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>T' Inſtruct the <hi>Great,</hi> and to Adorn the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>His Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to a</hi> Daughter.</note> 
                  <hi>Fair.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus BEAUTY's <hi>Toilet</hi> ſpread ſo all Divine,</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Cabinet Jems</hi> ſo Furniſht from That MINE;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Virgin,</hi> and the <hi>Bridal Coronet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Were, by Kind <hi>HALLIFAX,</hi> ſo richly Set;</l>
               <l>VIRTUE and INNOCENCE at that full View,</l>
               <l>As ev'n th' Original <hi>Eden Lanſchape</hi> drew:</l>
               <l>All her whole <hi>Hierarchy</hi> of <hi>Graces</hi>; not</l>
               <l>One leaſt Enamell'd <hi>Heav'nly Spark</hi> forgot;</l>
               <l>Each <hi>Star</hi> in the whole <hi>Feminine Renown,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From <hi>Caſſiopoea</hi>'s CHAIR, to <hi>Ariadne</hi>'s CROWN.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In the Rich <hi>Furniture</hi> of that Fair MIND,</l>
               <l>Thoſe dazling <hi>Intellectual Graces</hi> ſhin'd,</l>
               <l>To draw the <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Homage</hi> of Mankind;</l>
               <l>Nothing cou'd more than his firm FRIENDSHIP <hi>Charm:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cheerful,</hi> as <hi>Bridal</hi>-Songs; as <hi>South</hi>-Suns, <hi>Warm</hi>;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105375:6"/>And <hi>Fixt,</hi> as <hi>Northern</hi>-Stars: When e're He daign'd</l>
               <l>The Solemn Honour of his <hi>Plighted Hand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He ſtood a more than Second <hi>Pylades</hi>;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſhaken,</hi> as <hi>Immutable</hi> DECREES.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But, whilſt theſe vaſt <hi>Perfections</hi> I Recount,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Heights</hi> to which thoſe Soaring <hi>Glories</hi> mount:</l>
               <l>My <hi>Muſe</hi> thus rapt into that <hi>Cheerful Sphear</hi>;</l>
               <l>Is This her <hi>Wailing Dirge?</hi> her <hi>Funeral Tear?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For his <hi>Sad</hi> DEATH, to Draw his <hi>Glorious</hi> LIFE!</l>
               <l>Paint <hi>Lights</hi> for <hi>Shades,</hi> and <hi>Ecſtacies</hi> for <hi>Grief!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are Theſe the <hi>Melancholy Rites</hi> She brings,</l>
               <l>Fit <hi>Ayrs</hi> to Tune the <hi>Mournful Theme</hi> She ſings!</l>
               <l>Yes, the <hi>True Mourner</hi>'s in th' <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> Play'd:</l>
               <l>What's Preſent <hi>Grief,</hi> but Paſt <hi>Delight</hi> Diſplay'd?</l>
               <l>Counting what once was <hi>Ours,</hi> we need no more:</l>
               <l>To Sum th' <hi>Enjoyment,</hi> does the <hi>Loſs</hi> Deplore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beſides, What's all our Sable <hi>Cavalcade,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To the Great DEAD, our Darkeſt <hi>Funeral Shade?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105375:7"/>T' Illuſtrious <hi>Virtue,</hi> Grief's an <hi>Eaſy</hi> Debt;</l>
               <l>Her Glorious <hi>Amulet</hi> but <hi>Cheaply</hi> Set:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>She</hi> finds the <hi>Diamond,</hi> and <hi>We</hi> the <hi>Jet.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Learning, Wiſdom, Eloquence,</hi> Expire,</l>
               <l>And the <hi>Great</hi> SOULS, (Sparks of <hi>Celeſtial Fire</hi>)</l>
               <l>Back to Their <hi>Elemental Sourſe</hi> Retire:</l>
               <l>To ſuch <hi>Rich</hi> DUST, in vain we <hi>Pyramids</hi> Rear;</l>
               <l>For <hi>Mauſoloeum's</hi> are but <hi>Pageants</hi> there.</l>
               <l>What's a poor Short-liv'd Pile of <hi>Crumbling Earth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Mould'ring</hi> Tomb, t' <hi>Apollinary</hi> WORTH?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Worth,</hi> that ſo far from ſuch a <hi>Narrow Bound,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Spreads a <hi>Large Field!</hi> Moves th' <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Round!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fills every <hi>Tongue!</hi> Thus, what no <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rn</hi> contains,</l>
               <l>The <hi>World</hi>'s the <hi>Casket</hi> to thoſe <hi>Great</hi> REMAINS.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor let <hi>Poetick Vanity</hi> Rehearſe</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Boaſted Dreams,</hi> Her <hi>Miracles</hi> of VERSE:</l>
               <l>Think, in ſome poor <hi>Recorded</hi> EPITAPH,</l>
               <l>That Shallow Page of <hi>Braſs,</hi> or <hi>Marble Leaf</hi>;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105375:7"/>Or, in ſome more <hi>Voluminous Folio</hi> Pile,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Davideis,</hi> or <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Sweating Toil,</l>
               <l>Some Sacred WORTHY's <hi>Deathleſs Fame</hi> t' Enſtal;</l>
               <l>Rais'd by her <hi>Lyres,</hi> like the Old <hi>Theban Wall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No; when <hi>Great</hi> NAMES ne'r Dye; That <hi>Work</hi> alone,</l>
               <l>Is all a Fair <hi>Creation</hi> of Their <hi>Own.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>True GLORY Shines by her <hi>Own</hi> Lighted <hi>Beam:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis not the <hi>Muſe</hi>'s <hi>Song,</hi> but <hi>Muſe</hi>'s THEAM.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When in Great <hi>HALLIFAX,</hi> WIT's <hi>Pantheon</hi> fell,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Death</hi> now huſht that Silenc'd ORACLE<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>From Fair <hi>Eliza</hi>'s Hallow'd <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-School.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Helicon</hi>-Walls,</l>
               <l>Methinks, I hear a Fatal <hi>Summon</hi> calls:</l>
               <l>When, lo! the <hi>Delphick</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, <hi>who Dy'd the ſame Day.</hi>
                  </note> SEER, that <hi>Reverend Bard</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of Sacred <hi>Literature</hi>'s rich <hi>Fount,</hi> prepar'd</l>
               <l>Th' Expiring <hi>HALLIFAX,</hi> in <hi>Death</hi> to wait.—</l>
               <l>No leſs Attendant on his <hi>Funeral State,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fate</hi> to that ever <hi>Honour'd</hi> HEAD cou'd owe:</l>
               <l>LEARNING it ſelf muſt ſhake, at ſuch a <hi>Blow.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105375:8"/>
               <l>But, tho' with all this <hi>Mine</hi> of <hi>Learning</hi> ſtor'd;</l>
               <l>He <hi>Liv'd,</hi> and <hi>Dy'd,</hi> no Niggard of that <hi>Hoard:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Witneſs His own <hi>Long</hi> Pious <hi>Founded</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>His Free School Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Piles,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where <hi>Nurtur'd</hi> ARTS, by His <hi>Auſpicious</hi> Smiles,</l>
               <l>Tune their <hi>Young Voices</hi> to the <hi>Muſe's</hi> Song,</l>
               <l>Nerv'd by his HAND to <hi>Books,</hi> and <hi>Virtue,</hi> ſtrong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus, as th' Old <hi>Iſrael Patriarch,</hi> to his once</l>
               <l>Illuſtrious <hi>Twelve,</hi> HE to His <hi>Hundred</hi> Sons,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Fruitful</hi> CHARITY's Adopted <hi>Race,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(With all his Tendereſt <hi>Diffuſive Grace,</hi>)</l>
               <l>Doals, with a True <hi>Paternal Glory</hi> crown'd,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Living</hi> and His <hi>Dying</hi> Bleſſings round.</l>
               <l>Yes, from that <hi>Hand,</hi> this <hi>Scatter'd Bread</hi> muſt fall:</l>
               <l>He Furniſhes thoſe <hi>Numerous Pencils,</hi> all</l>
               <l>To <hi>Copy</hi> from <hi>His</hi> Great <hi>Original:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reſolv'd, if poſſible, Reſolv'd t' <hi>Inſpire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To this <hi>Young Nurſery,</hi> His <hi>Cheriſht Choire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His own Rich <hi>Soul,</hi> their <hi>Tranſmigrated Fire.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:105375:8"/>
               <l>But, why (if 'tis not a too <hi>Bold Offence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To dare <hi>Expoſtu'late</hi> with OMNIPOTENCE,)</l>
               <l>Why ſhould Prodigious <hi>Worth,</hi> from th' <hi>Orb</hi> it warm'd,</l>
               <l>Snatch'd from the <hi>Soyl</hi> it cheriſht, <hi>Eyes</hi> it charm'd,</l>
               <l>From its <hi>Deſerted Charge,</hi> unkindly Fly,</l>
               <l>Quit th' <hi>Earth</hi> it Bleſt, Impoveriſh <hi>Worlds,</hi> and Dye?</l>
               <l>No, the Kind <hi>Heav'ns,</hi> in Mercy, to Rebate</l>
               <l>That <hi>Mighty Loſs,</hi> the too keen <hi>Edge</hi> of <hi>Fate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have circled <hi>Virtue</hi> in a <hi>Fence</hi> ſo High,</l>
               <l>As ſtands ſo Safe, it knows not how to Die;</l>
               <l>But Founds its own Proud <hi>Immortality.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For, as ſome Lofty <hi>Cedar,</hi> long had ſtood</l>
               <l>The <hi>Land-mark</hi> of the <hi>Plain,</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Wood</hi>;</l>
               <l>Till the Dread <hi>Voice</hi> of <hi>Fate, Heav'n</hi>'s Angry <hi>Blaſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Bolt</hi> of the Deſtroying <hi>Thunder</hi> caſt,</l>
               <l>All the tall PRIDE lies <hi>Fal'n.</hi>—Yet ſtill ſome <hi>Shoot,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some tender <hi>Scyen</hi> from the <hi>Sacred</hi> ROOT,</l>
               <l>By' its <hi>Nutrimental</hi> PARENT-<hi>Succours</hi> fed</l>
               <l>Springs, Growes, Spreads, Flouriſhes; till th' Uprear'd <hi>Head</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:105375:9"/>Do's t' all its Great <hi>Original</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>IGHTS improve,</l>
               <l>A Second <hi>Pearch</hi> for the Fair <hi>Bird</hi> of <hi>JOVE.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So may Great <hi>HALLIFAX Himſelf</hi> Survive;</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Fall,</hi> and thus His <hi>Deathleſs</hi> Virtues <hi>Live.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>LIVE in His <hi>Fair</hi> SUCCESSION, ever Bleſt;</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt <hi>Honour</hi> Builds its own <hi>Rich PHAENIX</hi> Neſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
