<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lord Chancellor's speech in the Exchequer to Baron Thurland at the taking of his oath, 24 Jan. 1672/3</title>
            <author>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of, 1621-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-10">2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59479</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14981</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12430727</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12430727</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61943</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A59479)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61943)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 297:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Lord Chancellor's speech in the Exchequer to Baron Thurland at the taking of his oath, 24 Jan. 1672/3</title>
                  <author>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of, 1621-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672 [i.e. 1673]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thurland, Edward, --  Sir, 1606-1683.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61943:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
Lord Chancellor's
SPEECH
IN THE
EXCHEQUER,
TO
BARON <hi>THVRLAND</hi>
At the Taking of his
OATH,
24 <hi>Jan.</hi> 1672/3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1672</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:61943:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61943:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. Serjeant Thurland,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He King of his Grace and Favor,
hath made choice of you to be One
of the Barons of the <hi>Exchequer.</hi> He
designed to place you in a Court
of more profit, though not of more
Dignity; but your own Modesty
and Vertue hath chosen this Court,
where you thought you could serve the King best. And
I could not omit to mention it here to your Honor, it
being the greatest instance of a good Man, That he
had rather be found serviceable then rich. His Majesty
hath had large proof of your former Services; besides
He takes you upon the credit of that Recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
that hath justly the best place with Him, I mean
His Royal Brothers.</p>
            <p>Some few things it is fit I should here mention to you,
and leave with you as Admonitions, or rather Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances.
In the first place, you are to maintain the
<hi>Kings Prerogative;</hi> and let not the <hi>Kings Prerogative,</hi>
and the <hi>Law,</hi> be two things with you. For the <hi>Kings
Prerogative</hi> is <hi>Law,</hi> and the Principal Part of the <hi>Law;</hi>
and therefore, in maintaining that, you maintain the
<hi>Law.</hi> The Government of <hi>England</hi> is so excellently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwoven,
that every part of the <hi>Prerogative</hi> hath a
broad mixture of the Interest of the Subject; the ease
and safety of the People being inseparable from the
Greatness and Security of the Crown.</p>
            <p>In the next place, let me advise you, that you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint
your self with the <hi>Revenue;</hi> as also with the
<hi>Ancient Records, Precedents,</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of this Court.
For want of which knowledge, I have seen this Court
a most excellent <hi>Common Pleas,</hi> when at the same time,
I could not say so much for it as an <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third place, let me recommend to you, so to
manage the <hi>Kings Justice</hi> and <hi>Revenue,</hi> as the King may
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61943:3"/>
have most <hi>Profit,</hi> and the Subject least <hi>Vexation.</hi> Raking
for old Debts; the number of Informations; Projects
upon Concealments: I could not find in the Eleven
years experience I have had in this Court, ever to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
the Crown. But such proceedings have for the
most part delivered up the Kings good Subjects into
the hands of the worst of men.</p>
            <p>There is another thing I have observed in this Court,
that I shall mind you of, which is, When the Court
hearkens too much to the <hi>Clerks</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> of it; and
are too apt to send out <hi>Process,</hi> when the Money may
be raised by other ways more easie to the People. I do
not say, That the Kings duty should be lost, or that the
strictest course should not be taken, rather then that
be: But when you consider, how much the <hi>Officers</hi> of
this Court, and the <hi>Vnder-Sheriffs,</hi> get by <hi>Process</hi> upon
small Sums, more then the Kings duty comes to; and
upon what sort of People this falls, to wit, the <hi>Farmer,
Husbandman,</hi> and <hi>Clothier</hi> in the Countrey, that is
generally the <hi>Collector, Constable,</hi> and <hi>Tithingman;</hi> and
so disturbs the industrious part of the Nation, you
will think it fit to make that the last way, when no
other will serve.</p>
            <p>Give me leave also to mind you of one thing more,
which is in your Oath, <hi>That the Kings needs ye shall speed
before all other:</hi> That is, the business of the <hi>Revenue of
the Crown</hi> you are to dispatch before all other, and
not turn your Court into a Court of <hi>Common Pleas;</hi>
and let that justle out what you were constituted for.</p>
            <p>In the last place, let me conclude with what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns
all my <hi>Lords,</hi> the <hi>Judges,</hi> as well as you, let me
recommend to you the <hi>Port,</hi> and way of living suitable
to the dignity of your place, and what the King allows
you. There is not any thing gains more Reputation and
Respect to the Government, then that doth: And let
me tell you, <hi>Magistrates</hi> as well as <hi>Merchants,</hi> are sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
by <hi>Reputation.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
