<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ode on the King's birth-day by Tho. Shadwell ...</title>
            <author>Shadwell, Thomas, 1642?-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-05">2003-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2862A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10818</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12425277</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12425277</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61824</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A59439)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 297:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ode on the King's birth-day by Tho. Shadwell ...</title>
                  <author>Shadwell, Thomas, 1642?-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Saunders ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ode">
            <pb facs="tcp:61824:1"/>
            <head>ODE ON THE KING's Birth-Day,</head>
            <byline>By <hi>THO. SHADWELL,</hi> Poet-Laureat and Historiographer-Royal.</byline>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>HAil! Hail, thou Blest, thou most Auspicious Day,</l>
               <l>On which broke forth such an Illustrious Ray,</l>
               <l>As has o'er <hi>Europe</hi> since dispers'd his Light,</l>
               <l>And every Day still grows more Gloriously bright.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>The Hope of <hi>Europe</hi> dawn'd when he arose;</l>
               <l>Oh happy was that Morn;</l>
               <l>Blest was the Princely Womb did him disclose:</l>
               <l>Let Golden Letters this great Day adorn,</l>
               <l>Which brought Him forth whom by Heav'n design'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cho.</hi> The Vniversal Champion of Mankind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>First, <hi>Belgia</hi> felt His Influence,</l>
               <l>Which ere His Noon He amply did dispence;</l>
               <l>When groaning underneath the <hi>Gallick</hi> Pow'r,</l>
               <l>What <hi>Nassau</hi> first did raise, this <hi>Nassau</hi> did restore:</l>
               <l>And 'twas a Work of full as great a Weight,</l>
               <l>Of His who did Redeem, as His who did Create.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>Then <hi>Britain</hi> felt His Pow'rful Beams,</l>
               <l>Eclips'd, and in her last Extreams,</l>
               <l>He shed about His Heat and Light,</l>
               <l>And Vigour did impart</l>
               <l>To ev'ry English Heart,</l>
               <l>He soon dispell'd all Clouds of Night,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Britain</hi> now again shines bright.</l>
               <l>He invaded her with Liberty,</l>
               <l>And set the Laws and Gospel free.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cho.</hi> Oh <hi>Britain</hi> these great Acts He did for thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <pb facs="tcp:61824:2"/>
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Inflam'd by Him your Ancient Warlike Name,</l>
               <l>Which you had gain'd under Victorious Kings,</l>
               <l>Is now restor'd with Never-dying Fame,</l>
               <l>And loudly through the World your Valour rings,</l>
               <l>Which you had lost in vile inglorious Peace,</l>
               <l>Under soft Princes drown'd in Vice and Ease,</l>
               <l>He wak'd you from your sordid Lethargy:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cho.</hi> Oh <hi>Britain,</hi> These great Acts H' has done for Thee!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>Destroy'd be then that Vip'rous Brood,</l>
               <l>Who would their Mothers Bowels tear;</l>
               <l>Or would oppose thy <hi>Hero</hi>'s Good,</l>
               <l>By whom thou dost thy Honours bear;</l>
               <l>By whom our Liberties and Lives,</l>
               <l>Our Goods, our Children, and our Wives,</l>
               <l>Our Altars and our Fires defended are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>He does to thickest Crowds of Foes,</l>
               <l>His Sacred Breast for us expose:</l>
               <l>Oh may His Toyls and Dangers cease;</l>
               <l>And His Keen Sword give <hi>Europe</hi> Peace;</l>
               <l>That Circled in His Sweet <hi>MARIA</hi>'s Arms,</l>
               <l>He may be free from Rough Alarms;</l>
               <l>And in wise Sway His Mind employ,</l>
               <l>And all the Calm Delights of Peace enjoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>Blest be the Day which joyn'd this Royal Pair,</l>
               <l>The Wise and Valiant, with the Good and Fair.</l>
               <l>And on that Day may Heav'n for ever smile,</l>
               <l>On which they both espous'd this Happy Isle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Small Cho.</head>
               <l> Long may They Live in Happiness!</l>
               <l>Long may They Reign with Glory and Success!</l>
               <l>They one another, and We Them, possess.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Gen. Cho.</head>
               <l>Let Vs to Heav'n Our Praises loudly sing,</l>
               <l>For such a Gracious QVEEN, for such a Glorious KING.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for <hi>Francis Saunders,</hi> at the Blew Anchor in the Lower Walk of the <hi>New Exchange.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
