<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to the Amicable accommodation of the difference between the representer and the answerer</title>
            <author>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-03">2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59789</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37544</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16970225</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16970225</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105556</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A59789)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105556)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1159:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to the Amicable accommodation of the difference between the representer and the answerer</title>
                  <author>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Amery ... and William Rogers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXVI [1686]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Sherlock by Wing.</note>
                  <note>"Imprimatur, July 22. 1686. Jo. Battely"</note>
                  <note>An answer to "An amicable accomodation" by John Gother.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gother, John, d. 1704. --  An amicable accommodation.</term>
               <term>Jesus Christ.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:105556:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July 22. 1686.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>IO. BATTELY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105556:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN
ANSWER
TO THE
<hi>Amicable Accommodation</hi>
OF THE
DIFFERENCE
BETWEEN THE
REPRESENTER
AND THE
ANSWERER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
Printed for <hi>Iohn Amery</hi> at the <hi>Peacock,</hi> and <hi>William Rogers</hi> at
the <hi>Sun;</hi> both against St. <hi>Dunstan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetstreet.</hi>
MDCLXXXVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105556:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105556:2"/>
            <head>AN
ANSWER
TO THE
Amicable ACCOMMODATION,
Of the Difference between
The Representer and the Answerer.</head>
            <p>IN Answer to the Reply to <hi>Papists protesting against
Protestant Popery,</hi> our Author has <hi>amicably ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated</hi>
away the whole Book, excepting one
word called <hi>Misrepresenting;</hi> and therefore whereas he
expects Ten sheets from me in return, I must be forced to
compound with him for a much less number.</p>
            <p>We are likely at last to agree about the meaning of <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>representing,</hi>
which is a very common word, and easily
understood when men give their minds to it. Our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
Printed a double Character of a <hi>Papist Misrepresented</hi>
and <hi>Represented;</hi> the first being an accusation on Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants
for misrepresenting Papists; I examined every part
of his Character, and could not find why he called it
<hi>Misrepresenting;</hi> for it did not appear by his Characters,
that we had charged them with any Doctrines or Practices
(excepting some few things) but what they themselves
owned. We charge indeed their Doctrines and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices
with such guilt as they do not own; but this I told
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105556:3"/>
him did not properly belong to Representing but Dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting;
for while we agree about matters of fact, there is
no Misrepresenting on either side, and then we are no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise
Misrepresenters, than as all men are who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn
such Opinions and Practises, as others judge very
true and innocent; and thus Papists as much misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
Protestants, as Protestants misrepresent Papists; that
is, they equally differ from each other in their Opinions
and judgments of the same things; but who are truly
the Misrepresenters, is not to be decided by <hi>Character-making,</hi>
but by Reason and Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Well, our</hi> Accommodator <hi>is very willing out of civility
and for the sake of peace, to yield this point, That</hi> the
Title of a Papist Misrepresented,<note place="margin">Amicable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation, <hi>p.</hi> 6.</note> is not to be taken in its
strict and proper sence, as Misrepresenting signifies down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
Lying, or falsly charging of matter of fact; but in its
larger or less-proper sence, as it comprehends both Lying,
Calumniating, Mis-interpreting, Reproaching, Mis-construing,
Mis-judging, <hi>&amp;c. which I confess is a very great piece of
civility, that he will not charge us now with</hi> down right
lying, <hi>but onely with</hi> Lying <hi>and</hi> Calumniating, <hi>and several
other hard words into the bargain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There needs not many words about this matter, for
the short of the case is this: In order to reconcile our
people to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> he thought it necessary
to perswade them, that Popery is quite another thing,
than what they had been taught it is, which would at
once remove their prejudices against Popery, and beget
in them a great jealousie and suspicion of their former
Teachers; for men will not easily trust those who have
once deceived them.</p>
            <p>In order to this, he gives us a double Character of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist;
one he calls the <hi>Character of a Papist Misrepresented,</hi>
the other of <hi>a Papist Represented;</hi> which any man would
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105556:3"/>
guess, should be two very different and contrary things;
the first what a Papist is not, the second what he is; and
yet, when we come to examine them, every thing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most,
which can properly be called a Character, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presenting,
is the same in both; onely the Character of
a Papist Misrepresented tells you, what opinion Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants
have of Popery, and the Character of a Papist Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented,
tells us, what good thoughts Papists have
of themselves, and their own Religion; now whoever
doubted, but that Papists and Protestants differ very
much in their Opinions of Popery, as they do also in their
Opinions of Protestancy. And this is the onely pretence
for his charge of Misrepresenting, not that we charge
them with believing or practising, what they do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
or practice, but that we think worse of their Faith
and Practice than he thinks they deserve.</p>
            <p>And if this be all that he means by Misrepresenting,
we readily own the charge, that we have much worse
thoughts of Popery than he has; that we believe those
Doctrines to be erroneous, and those Practises to be sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
which he thinks very well of; and because I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved,
if possible, to be as civil as he is, in my Concessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and not to dispute about words, I am contented he
should call this misrepresenting, <hi>Lying, Calumniating,</hi> or
what he pleases, if he can prove that we condemn their
Faith or Worship unjustly; onely he must remember,
that this will engage him in a dispute, which he seems re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved
not to engage in. For he must not think, that
upon his bare word, we must be concluded guilty of that
misrepresenting, which he calls <hi>Lying.</hi> He should have
been very much afraid to accuse us of Lying, if he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved
altogether to <hi>represent,</hi> and not to <hi>dispute:</hi> For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
no wise man will give his Neighbour the lye, unless
he be well prepared to prove it against him. <hi>Misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105556:4"/>
was a civil term, because honest men may through
mistake <hi>misrepresent;</hi> but Lying is the fault of Knaves,
which as it deserves great punishment, so it ought not to
be charged upon men without great proof, much less
with none at all: And therefore he should not have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
up an obstinate humour against Disputing, just be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
he thought fit to charge us with Lying, but have
remembred what M. <hi>de Meaux</hi> says in his Pastoral Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<hi>p. 29. Those who bear false and scandalous witness a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
an innocent person, are condemned to the same punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
which the Crime of which they bear witness did deserve
had it been found true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to clear my self as well as I can; besides this, that
I am not conscious to my self of any <hi>misrepresenting,</hi> I
must tell him once more, that in a strict and proper
sence, to misrepresent relates only to matter of fact,
when we charge men with saying and doing what they
never said or did, as our <hi>Accommodater</hi> confesses; and in
this sence I have already proved, that we are no Misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presenters,
and at last, if I understand him, he confesses that
we are not; but then he tells us, that to misrepresent, in a
larger and less-proper sence, signifies also to put a false
construction on things: As for instance, to say that to
Worship Saints and Angels, and the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> as pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised
by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is to give the Worship of
God to Creatures; and that their Image-Worship is
what God has forbid in the second Commandment; that
their denying the Cup to the Laity is contrary to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution
of our Saviour, and their Latine Service is a
very unreasonable Worship, and destructive of the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
of the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now though we do not charge
them falsly in these cases as to matter of fact, for they do
Worship Saints and Images, and deny the Cup to the
Laity, and keep the Service of the Church in a Language
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105556:4"/>
unknown to the people, yet if through prejudice and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect
of due consideration, we should condemn these Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices
as contrary to the Laws of God, and injurious to
mens Souls, though they were not so. I grant even this
may be called Misrepresenting, for 'tis to call good evil,
and evil good, light darkness, and darkness light; and
whoever is guilty of this kind of Misrepresentation, is
guilty of a very great Sin, and does great mischief in the
World, not by falsifying matters of Fact, but as much as
in him lies, by changing the nature of things.</p>
            <p>And upon these terms the dispute of Misrepresenting
may be easily accommodated: Let him plainly confess,
that we are not Misrepresenters in the first sense; that we
do not falsly charge any Doctrines or Practices on the
Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which she disowns; that we do not
teach our People, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> believes or
practices, otherwise than she does, and we will give him
leave to call us Misrepresenters still, if he can shew that
we charge their Doctrines or Practices with such guilt as
they do not deserve.</p>
            <p>But it is by no means a sufficient answer to this Charge
to call us <hi>Lyars,</hi> which for ought I can see, is all we are
like to get in Answer from this man. Of all the several
projects for ending Controversie, the most effectual that
I ever yet heard of, is that which our Author hath set on
foot: for he would now insinuate, that he has vindicated
the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> from our Misrepresenting, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
matter of Fact, but the guilt we charge them with up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
those matters that are confessed by themselves. Now I
have shewn him as well as I could, that some of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed
Doctrines are false, and some of their confessed Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices
are unlawful, and that their best Apologies for them
are insufficient. What says the Accomodator to all this? He
answers, that all this is <hi>Misrepresenting,</hi> as that signifies
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105556:5"/>
               <hi>Lying.</hi> But how the dispute should be carried on upon
these Terms, otherwise then by giving him the <hi>Lye</hi> back
again, I do not comprehend? And therefore because nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
true Religion, or good Breeding, will suffer me to
carry on a Dispute at that rate, the Controversie should
seem even upon this account to be at end; and I give him
joy of the honour that he is like to get by it.</p>
            <p>And yet I think an indifferent Reader may observe
that his fastning the <hi>Lye</hi> upon us, for Misrepresenting
them in the less-proper sense, as he pretends we do, is
but an after-game to which he is reduced by the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of a bad Cause.</p>
            <p>The design of our Author in his Twofold Character of
a Papist, was to perswade our People, that we were Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>representers
in the first and most proper Sense; that we
had belyed the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with imputing such Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
to her, as she did not own; and this all men, that
ever I met with, understood to be the design of it: But
since he cannot make good his Charge against us, he will
now make good his Title of Misrepresenting in a less<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper
Sense, not that we misreport the Doctrines and
Practices of their Church, but that we unjustly condemn
them; and though we will rather allow him to call this
Misrepresenting, than dispute about a word, yet if this
be all he intended to acquaint the World, that Protestants
think worse of Popery, than Papists do, it was a
wonderful discovery; and he took as notable a way to
rectifie such mis-apprehensions. He disclaims all dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
and thinks to confute Protestant Misrepresentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
by giving onely a true Character of a Papist, with
reference to his Faith and Practice, out of the most au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick
Records of their Church: Now if the Misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentation
does not concern matter of Fact, but only mens
judgments and opinions about such matters, how can a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105556:5"/>
meer Character rectify such Misrepresentations? When
we know, what the Doctrine and Practice of the Church
of <hi>Rome</hi> is, and yet think very ill of it; Can the meer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating
what the Doctrine and Practice of the Church
of <hi>Rome</hi> is, cure our ill opinion of it? And yet this is all
the business of a Character to tell us, what a Papist is,
which might indeed reconcile us to Popery, had we dislik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
Popery onely because we did not understand it, or
took it to be something more formidable than it is, but
cannot cure such dislikes as arise from a true understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of Popery.</p>
            <p>He appeals to the Definitions of the Councils of <hi>Trent,</hi>
and the Bishop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Exposition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to vindicate
Popery from the Misrepresentations of Protestants; that
is, to show us what the genuine Doctrines of Popery are:
And how can this confute our Misrepresentations, unless
by Misrepresenting he understood Misrepresenting mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of Fact, charging such Doctrines on their Church as
were never decreed by their Councils, nor owned by their
most authentick Expositors? For the Authority of the
Council of <hi>Trent</hi> is nothing to us, any otherwise than as
we own it to be the Rule and Standard of the Romish
Faith; and therefore he can prove nothing against us
out of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> but onely that those are not
the Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which we say are,
and this cannot confute Protestant Misrepresentations of
Popery, unless our Misrepresentations consist in charging
them with such Doctrines as their Church and Councils
do not own.</p>
            <p>And therefore, though he is now willing to grant, that
we are not Misrepresenters, as that signifies, <hi>down-right
Lyers,</hi> who charge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with Believing
and Practising what she does not, yet it is apparent, that
this was what he intended in his Title of a Papist Misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105556:6"/>
to accuse Protestants of charging Papists with
such Doctrines and Practices as they do not own; and if
this be not the intent and design of his Book, there is a
great deal less Sense in it, then I thought there had been.</p>
            <p>For if by Misrepresenting he only meant, that we
reproach and calumniate the Doctrines and Practices of
the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and charge them with such guilt
as they do not deserve, not that we charge them falsly
with such Doctrines and Practices as they do not own,
(as he now would have it;) though I grant this may
be called Misrepresenting, if the charge be false, yet it is
not such a Misrepresenting as is confuted only by a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,
or by true Representing; it is wholly matter of
Dispute, as I have often told him; for he must not think
that we Protestants shall believe ever the better of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
because he professes to believe very well of it, in his
Character of a Papist Represented.</p>
            <p>If he will vindicate the Doctrines and Practices of the
Church of <hi>Rome</hi> from that guilt, which Protestants charge
on it; if he will justifie the Worship of Saints and Angels
and Images, Transubstantiation, the Adoration of the
Host, half Communion, Prayers in an Unknown Tongue,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> and prove us to be Misrepresenters, he must quit
his retreat of Character-making, and fairly dispute the
points in question, which is the way the generous Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates
of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have always taken, to defend
her, by the Authority of Scriptures, Fathers, Councils,
and here we are ready to joyn issue with them.</p>
            <p>And thus, for ought I see, this Controversie is at an
end, though he had not charged us with Lying; for
whatever he at first pretended, he grants now, that we
are not in a strict and proper sence Misrepresenters;
and thus farewel to Character-making, since Papists and
Protestants, who understand these matters are in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105556:6"/>
main agreed, what the Character of a Papist is, though
they differ in their opinions about him, which can never
be decided by Characters, but by Reason and Argument.
And yet our Author, after all his pretences to an Amicable
Accommodation, is unwilling the matter should end
thus, at least unless we will acknowledge our selves ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
much beholden to his good nature for it: Why,
what is the matter now? Have I not plainly proved,
that we are not Misrepresenters in the strict and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
notion of Misrepresenting? That we do not charge
the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with any matter of Fact, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Doctrines or Practices which she does not own?
And can we Misrepresent them, when we charge them
with nothing that is false;<note place="margin">P. 7.</note> Yes, he says, <hi>my principle,
that there can be no Misrepresenting, where there is an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement
in matter of fact, has more of the counterfeit
in it than true standard; is supposed to be certain, but
without the support of Authority or Reason:</hi> That is,
though we charge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with nothing
but what she her self owns; though we represent a
Papist just as a Papist represents himself, as to his Faith
and Practice, yet we may be Misrepresenters; and then
we may indeed be Misrepresenters for ought I know,
if we may Misrepresent, when we say nothing but what
is true.</p>
            <p>If he can make good this, I must acknowledge him
to be a man of Art; and therefore shall briefly examine
how he proves it.</p>
            <p>He says,<note place="margin">P. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Misrepresenting seems to stand in opposition to
Representing, and proper Representing being nothing more,
than the describing or shewing a thing, as it is in its self, as
many ways, as a thing can be shewn otherwise than it is in
its self, so many ways may it be properly Misrepresented.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105556:7"/>
This I agree to, and therefore let us proceed: <hi>Now</hi>
(says he) <hi>it is certain, that for the description to bear on
exact resemblance with the thing, it must not only agree
with it in matter of fact, but likewise in every other respect,
which it pretends to declare, as in motive, circumstance, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,
end,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The agreement in any one of these
being enough to quite change the nature of the thing, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
the matter of fact being still the same.</hi> And
this also I agree in, that motives, circumstances, intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
end, are all to be considered in representing; but I
want a reason, why he distinguishes these from the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of fact: for by matter of fact, I understand an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
cloathed with all its circumstances, without which,
it is impossible truly to represent any action: For cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances
alter the nature of actions; As suppose a man
be killed, this may be done by accident, or with design,
in heat of blood, or of premeditated malice, which makes
it, either Chance-medley, Man-slaughter, or Murder;
and therefore the consideration of these things falls
under the matter of fact, and are the proper matters
for a Jury to inquire into, who yet are judges onely
of Fact. And thus I understood matter of Fact,
when I asserted, that we did not Misrepresent the
Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in any matter of Fact; that we did
not onely charge them with nothing but what they
did, but that we truly Represented all the circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of what they did, as far as the moral nature of the
action is concerned in it, and indeed I know not, how
we can either Represent or Misrepresent any action
without its circumstances; we may tell what is done,
but the matter of the action is the least thing conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
in Representing, because it may be either good
or bad in most cases, according to its different circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105556:7"/>
and we cannot say, which it is, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering
all circumstances. As for instance, We do
not onely charge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with Praying
to Saints, and Worshipping Images, but we consider
what is the Doctrine of their Church about these mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
in what manner they do it, and with what cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances;
we admit of all the excuses and apologies,
and fair representations that they can make of it, and
then consider what the nature of the action is, and
what the Scriptures and Primitive Fathers declare it to
be.</p>
            <p>This, he knows, I did in the Book, which he now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
to answer. To put an end to this Dispute about
Misrepresenting, I told him, we did not like Popery, as he
and the Bishop of <hi>Condom</hi> had Represented it, and
shewed him our Reasons why we did not like it, as
to <hi>the Object of Religious Worship, the Invocation of Saints,
and the Worship of Images:</hi> And had he thought fit to
have considered these, we might have obliged him so
far, as to have confined the Dispute to his own Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters,
and the Bishops Exposition, in the other points
of Popery; but he says not one word about this, but
advances a new Paradox, that men may be Misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters,
though they do not Misrepresent any matter
of Fact, because they may Misrepresent the Motives,
Circumstances, Intention and End, as if this were not
to Misrepresent matter of Fact? Or as if we had Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>represented
them in this manner, when he had not, and
cannot give any one instance wherein we have done
so?</p>
            <p>This short account shews, how impertinent all his
examples of Misrepresenters are, who, as he says, did
Misrepresent without belying men in matter of Fact;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105556:8"/>
for though this is nothing to us, unless he could prove
us to be such Misrepresenters, which he has not once
attempted to do; yet the Examples he produces do
not prove what he brings them for, for all their Misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentations
are in matters of fact.</p>
            <p>Thus the ten Tribes suspected, that the Children of
<hi>Reuben</hi> and <hi>Gad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">22 Josh.</note> and the half Tribe of <hi>Manasseh,</hi> had
built an Altar for Sacrifice in the borders of <hi>Iordan,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-against
the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> whereas the true mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of Fact was, that they had built an Altar not for
Sacrifice, but as a witness and memorial of their right
to Gods Altar, to offer their Sacrifices and burnt Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
in the place which God should choose.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Eli</hi> thought <hi>Hannah</hi> had been drunken,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1. 13.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
she prayed in her heart, only her lips moving,
this was Misrepresenting matter of fact, for she was not
drunk. And surely he will grant, that the two wanton
Elders did foully bely <hi>Susannah,</hi> though she was alone and
naked in the Garden, and that they represented the fact,
quite otherwise than it was.</p>
            <p>And methinks our Author should grant, that the Jews
did misrepresent matter of fact, when they charged our
Saviour with being a Sabbath-breaker, a Glutton, a Friend
of Publicans and Sinners, unless he will say that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
was all this; for if he were not, then they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
him in matter of fact; and so they did the Apostles
and Primitive Christians, when they accused them as
Troublers of the City, and Movers of Sedition, that they
murdered Infants, and eat their Flesh; that they Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped
the Sun, and adored an Asses head for God; for
I suppose he will grant, that the matter of fact was
false.</p>
            <p>But still, says the Accommodater, they had some mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105556:8"/>
of fact, whereon their Accusations were grounded,
and which gave some colour and pretence to them.
Sometimes they had, and sometimes they had not: But
is not this a pleasant inference, that because those who
tell onely a piece of a story may misrepresent, therefore
those who faithfully relate the whole matter of fact, with
all the particular circumstances of it, may be Misrepresen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
also? If he can give any one example of this nature,
I will onely desire him to tell me the difference between
Misrepresenting and true Representing. Men who have
wit and malice enough, may put very spiteful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions
upon the most innocent and virtuous Actions,
by altering or concealing some circumstances, or the
end and intention of doing them; but this is to misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
the fact, to represent a thing done otherwise, or for
another end, than really it was; but if a man who tells
the whole truth, not onely what was done, but the end
why, and the manner how it was done, can be a Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>representer,
the honestest man in the world may be a Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>representer.</p>
            <p>When an action is truly and fairly Represented, men
may still pass a false judgment upon that action; may
think that evil and forbidden by God, which God has not
forbid, or that allowed and approved by God, which God
abhors; but this is not properly Misrepresenting, but
judging falsly, which differ just as matter of Fact and
matter of Law do in Civil Affairs. In all Causes Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal
and Civil, there are two distinct questions; what
the Fact, and what the Law is, what is done, and what
judgment the Law passes on such Actions: To falsifie in
matters of fact, is to Misrepresent the person and the
action; to give a wrong judgment, is to Misrepresent
the Law: and thus it is in our case: We are first to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105556:9"/>
what the Doctrines and Practices of the Church of
<hi>Rome</hi> are, and then of what nature they are, whether
true or false, good or evil: If we affix such Doctrines or
Practices on them, as they do not teach, or alter any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial
circumstance relating to them, then we are Misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presenters
in a proper sence, as misreporting matter of fact;
and this we utterly deny, and they can never prove that
we do thus misrepresent them, that as our Author misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presents
us, <hi>we usher in,</hi> with <hi>they teach this, they believe that,
they say this,<note place="margin">P. 12.</note> they affirm that, and under these preambles
charge the Papists for asserting and believing such Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
which they would sooner loose their lives than assent to:</hi>
Which he has boldly affirmed without giving one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
of it; but as for judging of their Doctrines and
Practices, we do indeed pass such a judgment on them,
as I doubt not but they will call Misrepresenting; but
whether it be so or no, is matter of Dispute, and must be
decided by appealing to Scripture and Reason; and we
are not ashamed of being called Misrepresenters by them,
when that signifies no more, than censuring and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
their Faith and Practise.</p>
            <p>But he has one example more of this Misrepresenting,
and that as he thinks a very nicking one, and that is
the Fanatical Misrepresentations of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi>
To this end he brings in a Dissenter charging the
Church of <hi>England</hi> with Popery, and several other ill
things, which is intended to serve more purposes than
one.</p>
            <p>Had he first proved us to be Misrepresenters, it had
been a very proper way to make us sensible of the evil
of it, to appeal to our own resentments of such usage.
But what if Dissenters Misrepresent the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
does this prove that the Church of <hi>England</hi> Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>represents
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105556:9"/>
the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> If we indeed Misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> we have less reason to complain
that the Dissenters Misrepresent us; but if we are no
Misrepresenters, we have reason doubly to complain,
both for being charged with Misrepresenting, and for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Misrepresented.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Answer to this long harangue, is
very short and plain; however the Church of <hi>England</hi>
be Misrepresented, whether by Papists or Fanaticks, we
justifie our selves either by denying matter of Fact when
that is false, or by confuting the Charge: We are not
afraid of Disputing with our Adversaries when that is
needful, but justifie the Doctrines and Practices of our
Church by Scripture and Reason, which is a more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
way, than meerely to complain of being Misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented,
without daring to right our selves; which is the
case of our late Character-makers. If the World will
be moved by their complaints, to believe that they are
Misrepresented, all is well, and they have what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired;
but if you will be so perverse as not to believe
that they are Misrepresented, though they tell you they
are, and will needs be a disputing the point with them,
they have done with you; for their business is not to
Dispute, but to Represent. The difference between us
in this matter, is no more but this: We are not afraid
of Misrepresentations, because we know we can defend
our selves; whereas they find they cannot defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,
and therefore have no other remedy, but to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
of being Misrepresented.</p>
            <p>And yet I must confess, this is as artificial a way
of saying nothing, as I have met with. Our Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modator
is very sick of this talk of Misrepresenting,
and knew not how to get rid of it, but by diverting
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105556:10"/>
the Dispute; and therefore though it be nothing to
the purpose, instead of proving that we are Misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters,
he desires us to consider, how the Dissenters
Misrepresent us: but we have considered that enough
already, and when there is occasion for it, will do so
again; our business at present is not with Dissenters, but
Papists, and we are not for pursuing every new Game,
but will keep to our old scent.</p>
            <p>It would be a pleasant Scene, could he at this time of
day, engage the Church of <hi>England</hi> and Dissenters in a
new Quarrel; but thanks be to God many of our Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters
are grown wiser now, and I hope more will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
day; whatever they have formerly suspected of our
inclinations to Popery, they find now that they were
mistaken in us; and whatever defects they may charge
our Worship with, I believe they will call it Popish
and Antichristian no longer; to be sure they will never
think us the more inclined to Popery, because a Papist
says so. While these Gentlemen lay behind the Curtain,
and acted the part of a <hi>Zealous Brother</hi> under several
disguises, there was much more danger of them than
now: They have laid aside their Vizards, and let them
now paint the Church of <hi>England</hi> how they please, and
the worse the better; for how mean an opinion soever he
seems to have of our Dissenters, they are too wise and
cautious to take Characters from open and professed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:105556:10"/>
The truth is, he has horribly abused our Dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
unless by Dissenters, he means only his dearly
beloved <hi>Quakers,</hi> with whose Cant he is as well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted,
as if he had been either their Master, or
Scholar. For he has drawn up such a charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the name of a
Dissenter, as no Dissenter ever made. It is a Popish
Character Fathered upon a Dissenter, for which
they are much beholden to him, that when he has
a mind to say things so spiteful and silly, that
he himself (tho' none of the modestest men) is
ashamed to own, he can think of no person so fit
to say them as a Dissenter.</p>
            <p>Did ever any Dissenter charge the Church of
<hi>England</hi> with making gods of dead men, because
we call our Churches still by the names of those
Saints to whom they were dedicated in the times of
Popery? For did not the Dissenters themselves do so
in the late times of Reformation? And do they scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
to do so now? If there were any difference, it
was only in not giving the Title of Saint to them,
and I suppose that does not alter the case; for if it
be <hi>Paul's,</hi> or <hi>Peters,</hi> or <hi>Mary's</hi> Church, it is much
the fame: But they were not so silly as to think,
that names which were used only for distinction,
without paying any worship to Saints, or erecting
any Altars to them, in those Churches which were
called by their names, made Gods of dead men.
The Bills of Mortality were the same formerly in
the Dissenters time, that they are now, and yet they
did not suspect themselves guilty of <hi>placing</hi> Mary
<hi>above Christ, or making a Goddess of her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:105556:11"/>
Did ever any Dissenter charge the Church of
<hi>England</hi> with Image-Idolatry, for having Pictures
in their <hi>Bibles,</hi> or <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> painted with
the Ten Commandments, without leaving out the
Second against Image-worship? especially when
these are things wherein the Church of <hi>England</hi> is
no otherwise concerned, than in not correcting the
extravagancy of Painters and Printers. And I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess,
I have always suspected, that these men, who
now charge us with the Image-Idolatry, of having
Pictures in our Common-prayer Books (which is a
very late invention) did secretly lay the design to
reconcile our people by degrees to the use of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures
and Images.</p>
            <p>The Dissenters indeed were never any great
Friends to Holy-days; but they never charged us
with worshipping Saints on those days, which they
saw we did not; nor do they now charge us with
worshipping the Bread, when we kneel at receiving
the Sacrament, (which is contrary to the publick
Declarations of our Church) but reject it, because
it was no Table-posture, and because it had been
abused (as they scruple not to say) to an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous
worship of the Host in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They have indeed objected against our Liturgy,
That it was taken out of the Mass-book, and have
been sufficiently answered as to that point; and we
know who they were that first started that Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">See Foxes and Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands.</note>
some Mass-Priests under the disguise of Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans.
But I never heard before, that they were
scared with the very names of Epistles, and Gospels,
and Colects, and Litanies, nor did they ever quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel
with retaining Popish Saints in our Calendar,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105556:11"/>
when we give them to place in our Prayers, which
is only an evidence what Reformation we have
made. I never knew before, that our Dissenters
thought the Mass-book as Ancient as St. <hi>Basil</hi> and
St. <hi>Chrysostom,</hi> or that they liked our Common-Prayer-Book
ever the worse, because it came in with
the Reformation of Religion, and has been altered
since several times for the better; whereas their
complaint is, that it is not yet altered enough.
Much less are they scandalized at the Thanksgiving
for discovery of the Plot, how great a Chimera
soever it be.</p>
            <p>Nor is there any dispute, that I know of, between
the Dissenters and us about the Power of Absolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
or the Ministerial power of forgiving Sin.
They and we agree, that Christ has left such a Power
in the Church, of remitting and retaining Sins, of
receiving in, and putting out of the Church, which
is the state of Pardon and Forgiveness; and we both
deny, that this is absolute and judicial, or not only
Ministerial. They know we oppose the pretence of
a Judicial Power to forgive Sins in the Church of
<hi>Rome,</hi> which we say is reserved for the great Judg
of the World; and it is very strange, they should
peremptorily charge us with giving the Power of
God to forgive Sins, to men, and yet at the same
time accuse us of not agreeing what this power of
Absolution is. Tho our Accommodator may make
bold sometimes to contradict himself, yet I doubt
the Dissenters will think themselves misrepresented
by such contradictions.</p>
            <p>But did ever any Dissenter charge us with encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging
a Death-bed Repentance, for not obliging
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105556:12"/>
men to Confession and Penance (which he calls <hi>to
Confess and Repent)</hi> in the time of their Health?
We teach men to confess their Sins to God, and to
men too when there is occasion for it, either to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile
themselves to their Brother, or to receive
Ghostly comfort and advice; and we teach them to
Repent of their Sins, and reform them in time of
Health, and show them what great danger there is
in a Death-bed Repentance, and how very seldom
it proves true; which is no great encouragement to
such delays. But how the Dissenters, who reject
Confession to a Priest, and the Popish Sacrament of
Penance, themselves, should quarrel with us for
doing so, is somewhat strange.</p>
            <p>But we pretend to <hi>a power of giving Absolution,
and never enjoyn it but in the last agony, which</hi> (he
says) <hi>is argument enough to conclude,<note place="margin">P. 25.</note> there's no obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
of Repenting amongst us, till death looks us in
the face.</hi> But he has not improved this Argument
so well as he might; for Absolution is never enjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
not so much as in the hour of Death; (for we
are only required to give Absolution, in case the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent
earnestly desire it) and therefore, according to
his reasoning, it follows, that we think Repentance
never necessary, not so much as in the hour of
Death. But other men, who have common under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,
would hence conclude, that we make a
great difference between the Sinners Repentance,
and the Priests Absolution; that the first is always
necessary, the other only in case of Church Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures,
or to give relief to afflicted Consciences, or
to dismiss penitent sinners in the peace of the
Church.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105556:12"/>
Do not Dissenters themselves allow converted
Priests, who are under the vow of Continency, to
Marry, if they cannot preserve their Chastity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
it? And has not our Accomodator then, put
a wise Objection into their Mouths against the
Church of <hi>England;</hi> which, if it be any Objection,
returns upon themselves? Neither they nor we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
to dispence with Vows made to God; but we
think no Vow can oblige men to Sin; and since all
men have not the gift of Continency, as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
says, If such Persons are ensnared in a rash Vow,
(it may be, while they were Children, or before
they understood their own Temper and Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on)
since we cannot think the Fornication of Priests
a more holy State than Marriage, we think it
more justifyable to repent of a rash Vow, than to
live in a constant state of Temptation and Sin.</p>
            <p>It is likely enough, as he says, that Dissenters
may complain of Persecution, tho they themselves
have been declared Enemies to an unlimited Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;
and it will be hard to find a medium between
a general Liberty of Conscience, and those restraints
which are laid on Dissenters.</p>
            <p>But it must be considered, whether the Church
or the State be chargeable with this. The several
Laws which have been made against Dissenters,
have been more for the security of the State, than
of the Church; have been occasioned by a restless
humour which has threatned the publick Peace;
and have been rarely executed but at the instance
of Civil Authority, to provide for the security
of the State; and I suppose he will not parallel
this with some other Persecutions. But to make the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105556:13"/>
Dissenters quarrel at the Assistance given to the
<hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and proffered to the <hi>French</hi> in their
Rebellion, and the hard usage of the Queen of
<hi>Scots,</hi> and the late Murder of <hi>Charles</hi> I. argues, he
matters not much what he says; and to charge these
Intrigues of State upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is to
forget that he is in <hi>England</hi> (and not at <hi>Rome)</hi>
where Kings make Peace and War, not the Pope
with his Council of Cardinals.</p>
            <p>And yet our Accommodator has kept the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
bit for the last. For he brings in the Dissenter
accusing the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for giving every
man a liberty of Judging, and yet requiring Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
to her own Constitutions, which the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
Sectaries among them challenge and practice;
and it is not very modestly done of them, to blame
that in us, which they do themselves. They all
judg for themselves, and therefore form Churches
and Communions of their own; and they will not
receive any into their Communion, without owning
their Faith, and submitting to their Order and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline;
and this is all that the Church of <hi>England</hi>
challenges, only with this difference, that being
established by Law, her Communion and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
is enforced by Laws. And what a mighty
Absurdity and Contradiction is this, that men
should be taught to use their own Reason and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
in Religion, and yet required to submit and
conform to a Church, whose Faith and Worship is
consonant both to Scripture and Reason.</p>
            <p>Well, but after all this Liberty granted by the
Church of <hi>England, Whosoever will follow her, must
shut his Eyes, stifle his Reason, and be led only by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105556:13"/>
the Nose.</hi> Why! What's the matter now? The
charge is no more but this, That in matters of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
and Decency; and such things as are left to the
Determination of Church Governours, as are
neither forbid nor commanded by God, we must
submit to the Determinations of Authority, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
private Judgement or Opinion we may have of
things. A great fault this, that tho every man
must judge for himself in good and evil, yet every
private mans Judgement must be over-ruled by the
publick Judgment in matters of Order and external
circumstances of Religion.</p>
            <p>Much of the same nature,<note place="margin">P. 31.</note> is his concluding
Charge, <hi>That we are a wavering and unsetled Church,
subject to continual Variations,</hi> because some Rites
and Ceremonies formerly used, are now laid aside;
And what then? Does the settlement of the Church
consist in external Ceremonies? Is it any fault in a
Church, which challenges to her self a Power to
appoint, and constitute, and alter external Rites, to
exercise this Power as She shall think most for the
Edification of the Church, which is the only Rule
of right and wrong in this Case, which may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
change with the Change and Alteration of times
and Persons, and other external circumstances of
Affairs?</p>
            <p>Now let every man judg, whether there were ever
such a Speech made for a Dissenterbefore, which in
every Point of it is directly contrary to his own
Profession and Practice: It is time for our Author
to have done with his Trade of Representing, for
no man would know what it was he Represented,
did he not take care with the unskilful Painter to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105556:14"/>
write over his uncouth Figures, what they are;
This is an Horse, and this an Ass. And thus this
hopeful design of Representing and Misrepresenting,
ends only in ridiculing the Church of <hi>England;</hi> a
Liberty, which if we needed it, is not mannerly for
us to use at this time; but we are contented they
should ridicule our Church, if they will permit us
truly to Represent theirs.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, Our Accommodator grants that
he is still in Arrears; and certainly, never any Bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
paid less in the Pound than he offers;<note place="margin">P. 35.</note> and this
is his Accommodating, which Merchants call Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding.</p>
            <p>In my Answer to his <hi>Reflections,</hi> I proved, that
what he calls the Character of a Papist Misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented,
has nothing of Misrepresentation in it proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
so called; for there was no matter of Fact misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported;
in his Answer, which he calls, <hi>Papists pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testing
against Protestant Popery,</hi> instead of justify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
his Character, he seeks out for new Misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentations;
this in my last Answer, I enquired the
reason of, <hi>Why, instead of justifying his own Misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentations,
which he had so unjustly fathered upon
us, he should hunt about to pick up some new Misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentations
for me to Answer.</hi> And the Reason he
now assigns for it, is, <hi>Because I had little to say a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
the former, except that they were not to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
Misrepresentations in a strict Sense.</hi> Now, the less
I had to say, it was the more easily answered, tho I
know not what more need to be answered to the
charge of Misrepresenting, than to prove that it is
false. But he says, <hi>he fathered his Misrepresentations
on no Body;</hi> and so much the worse for that, for a
general charge includes every Body.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:105556:14"/>
And yet he was as unfortunate in his new Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>representations,
as in his old ones. He brings in
the Arch-Bishop of <hi>York</hi> for a Misrepresenter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
the Misrepresentations he Transcribes out of the
Arch-Bishop, the Arch-Bishop cites out of Popish
Authors, and names the Authors where they are
to be found; but the Protester to make a Misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presenter
of him, conceals all these Authorities, and
sets down the Words as the Bishops own; and this he
did only <hi>to consult the Credit of the Prelate:</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 36.</note> In what
Sir? That he might have the entire Glory of being
a Misrepresenter, without being thought to steal out
of Popish Authors.</p>
            <p>But he saies, The Bishop is still a Misrepresenter,
in charging these sayings of private Doctors upon
the Church; But where does he do that? Yes, He
saies, <hi>He (that is, the Papist) must believe;</hi> but
does he say, The Church says thus, or only <hi>Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton?
Stapleton</hi> might be a Misrepresenter, in deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
this as the Faith of the Church, <hi>That we must
simply believe the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>whether it teach
true or false;</hi> but the Arch-Bishop does not Misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present
the Church in saying, that <hi>Stapleton</hi> saies
so. What is the Authority of private Doctors, is
not the Dispute; but, whether Protestants be Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>representers
for saying, That such Doctrines are
taught by such Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Case of Mr. <hi>Sutcliff</hi> (another of his Misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presenters)
is somewhat different. For, besides what
he cites from their own Authors, which is set
down by the Protester without taking notice that
he quotes his Authors for it; he many times charges
them with the Concequences of their Doctrines
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105556:15"/>
and Practices; not that he charges them with own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
such Consequences, but proves such Doctrines on
them, from what they do profess and own; and
such sayings as these the Protester sets down as
charged on the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in the first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
as her avowed Doctrine: When Mr. <hi>Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliff</hi>
only alledges them, as the just interpretations
and Consequences of her Doctrine, which differ just
as much as Misrepresenting and Disputing; as say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
what a Church professes to believe, and what
the consequence of such a Faith is. As to show this
by an instance or two: The Protester sets these Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions
down as Mr. <hi>Sutcliffs</hi> Misrepresentations.
<hi>That Papists speak what they can in disgrace of the
Holy Scriptures; That they give the Office of Christs
Mediation to the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>to Angels, and to
Saints; That by the Doctrine of Papists, the Devils
in Hell may be saved.</hi> Now indeed, had he said,
That the Papists teach this in express Words, he
had been a Misrepresenter in a proper Sense, for
they teach no such thing; but Mr. <hi>Sutcliff</hi> never
charges these Doctrines Directly upon them, but
saies, That <hi>they say, the Scriptures are obscure and
hard to be understood;</hi> and this is, <hi>to speak in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace
of the Holy Scriptures.</hi> That <hi>they teach, that
by the merits of Saints, Christians obtain their desires,
and are delivered out of Purgatory. And this is to give
the Office of Christs Mediation to the Virgin</hi> Mary,
<hi>and to Saints. That they teach, that the Devils in Hell
may have true Faith; and yet our Saviour saith,
Whosoever believeth in him, shall not perish, but have
everlasting life: So it follows by the Doctrines of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,
That the Reprobrates and Devils in Hell may
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105556:15"/>
be saved.</hi> So that he expresly distinguishes between
what the Papists teach, and what himself concludes
from such Doctrines, and therefore he does not Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>represent
the Papists; for he charges them with
owning no Doctrines but what they do own; but if
he be guilty of any fault, it is in reasoning and Dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting;
and there is no way that I know of, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute
such Consequences, but by Reason and Dispute;
the very Name of which is very uneasie to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presenter,
and there is good reason why it should
be so.</p>
            <p>And this I suppose may satisfie the Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
Why I charged him with setting down these
sayings of Mr. <hi>Sutcliff,</hi> seperated from the Reasons
of them; for how little soever he may think himself
concerned in his Reasons, yet it is of great Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
in the matter of Representing, to distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish
between the Doctrines of Papists, and what
is charged on them, only, as the Consequence of
their Doctrines. To charge them with teaching such
Doctrines as they do not teach, is Misrepresenting<g ref="char:punc"></g>
and therefore, had these sayings, which he Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed
out of Mr. <hi>Sutcliff,</hi> been charged upon the
Papists as their sayings, it had been Misrepresenting;
and this was the design of the Protester in quoting
these sayings, without giving an account upon what
occasion they were said, to perswade his Readers,
that Mr. <hi>Sutcliff</hi> had directly and immediately
charged these Doctrines upon Papists as expresly
taught by them, and then he had been a Misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senter
indeed. But since it is otherwise, it is plain,
Mr. <hi>Sutcliff</hi> was Misrepresented by the Protester,
but he did not Misrepresent Papists, as that signifies
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105556:16"/>
charging them immediately with such Doctrines as
they do not own.</p>
            <p>In the next place he charges me with translating
dishonestly,<note place="margin">P. 37.</note> for not rendring <hi>proper Deum,</hi> or for
Gods sake, in <hi>English,</hi> in the form of consecrating
the Cross. Now I confess, why this was not tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated
I cannot tell, and knew nothing of it, till
I was informed by him; had it been in a dispute
about the nature and reason of that worship which
they pay to the Cross, these words had been very
considerable; but it relating only to the manner
of consecrating the Cross, they signified nothing, as
any one will see, who consults the place. Especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
considering, that the whole design of that Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course
about the Worship of Images (against which
he has not one word to object, but this Omission)
was to show the evil of Image-worship, tho they
gave no Worship to the material Image, but only
worshipped God or Christ, or the Saints by Images;
and therefore I had no occasion at all to conceal the
<hi>English</hi> of <hi>propter Deum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In my Answer to <hi>Papists protesting against Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant-Popery,</hi>
I took occasion to examine the Bishop
of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Exposition in two very concerning
Points,<note place="margin">P. 38.</note> 
               <hi>viz. The Invocation of Saints, and Worship
of Images;</hi> our Accomodator, it seems, could see
no reason why he should engage in this Dispute,
and therefore thinks it sufficient to show, that my
Reasons for this Dispute are not cogent, and he
names two, such as they are; 1. That <hi>I know no
reason for all this Dispute.</hi> But this saying related to
the Dispute about the Bishop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Authority,
not about his Exposition of the Catholick Faith.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105556:16"/>
2. His second Reason is like the first; Because I said,
<hi>He was not satisfied with my bare telling him, That I
was not satisfied with his Religion; and therefore now
I would give him my Reasons for it;</hi> which he huffs
at, and says, <hi>he was never concerned with my not liking
his Religion.</hi> What pretty Reasons will serve to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse
a Man from Answering a Discourse which he
knows he cannot answer!</p>
            <p>The plain case is this, The Representer made his
Appeals, and put great confidence in the Bishop of
<hi>Condom</hi>'s Authority, whose business is to put the
softest sense he can upon the Doctrines of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil
of <hi>Trent;</hi> and such Interpretations of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Faith, as have been condemned by other very
Catholick Doctors. In my <hi>Reply</hi> to the <hi>Reflections,</hi>
I considered what this Bishops Authority is; and in
my last <hi>Answer</hi> I examined what the Protester had
returned in the defence of it, which our Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modator
now says not one word to: But yet I told
him, I knew no reason for this dispute, Whether the
Bishop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Exposition were to be the stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard
of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Faith; for if we should
allow this, yet Popery is a very corrupt Religion,
tho the Bishop of <hi>Condom</hi> were the Authentick Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positor
of it. And to show that it is so, I undertook
to examine that Bishops Exposition in those two
great Articles of the <hi>Romish</hi> Faith, the <hi>Invocation of
Saints,</hi> and <hi>Worship of Images;</hi> and how this should
be a Reason for our Accommodator to take no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
of it, I cannot imagine: Had he any zeal for
his Religion, and could have answered that Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course,
I believe all that I could have said would
not have hindred him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:105556:17"/>
To conclude this whole matter, He peremptorily
adheres to his first Title of a <hi>Representer,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines
all manner of disputation, tho in vindication
of the Bishop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Exposition, to which he
so often Appeals. The only point he sticks to is,
That <hi>to assent to the Catholick Faith, as expounded in
his Character, and by the Bishop of</hi> Condom, <hi>is suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
for any Man to be received into the Communion
of the Church of</hi> Rome. But both he and the Bishop
of <hi>Condom</hi> do not meerly Represent, but Reason and
Argue also; and I should have thought they had
been a little concerned to justifie their own Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentations
and Reasonings. But whether this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soning
and Disputing were agreeable to his design or
not, it was very necessary to ours. For when they
endeavour to soften the Doctrines of their Church,
and to abate a great deal of <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Popery, to
reconcile our people to them; it is necessary for us to
warn them of the snare, and to show them what an
ill thing Popery is in its best dress; and therefore I
as little desire that he should answer what I have said
to this purpose, as he cares for doing it: I never
writ a Book with a desire to have it answered; but
to inform those, who otherwise might be imposed
on. And I suppose our people will think never the
worse of any Book, because <hi>Papists</hi> decline the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spute,
who were never known to avoid Disputing,
when they thought they could get any thing by it.</p>
            <p>And thus I take a fair leave of the <hi>Representer;</hi>
for this matter, I think, is driven as far as it will
go: We have by his own confession, cleared our
selves from being <hi>Misrepresenters</hi> in the true and
proper sense of the Word; for we have not falsly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105556:17"/>
charged them with any Doctrines and Practises dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned
by their Church; and as for their <hi>Character
of a Papist Represented,</hi> tho' it falls very short of
what some great Divines among them, of equal
Authority with the Bishop of <hi>Condom,</hi> have thought
to be the Doctrine of the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> yet
we are willing to joyne issue with them upon their
own terms, and to shew them our Reasons, why we
cannot comply with this refined and new-modelled
Popery. But this is to dispute, and that does not
agree with a <hi>Representer,</hi> whose business is to make
<hi>Characters</hi> without any concern to defend them:
And I am not so fond of disputing, as to dispute with
him whether he will or no.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
