<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modest examination of the authority and reasons of the late decree of the vice-chancellor of Oxford, and some heads of colleges and halls concerning the heresy of three distinct infinite minds in the Holy and Ever-blessed Trinity / by William Sherlock ...</title>
            <author>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-10">2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14301</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12004696</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12004696</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52275</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A59831)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52275)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 878:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modest examination of the authority and reasons of the late decree of the vice-chancellor of Oxford, and some heads of colleges and halls concerning the heresy of three distinct infinite minds in the Holy and Ever-blessed Trinity / by William Sherlock ...</title>
                  <author>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Rogers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52275:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52275:1"/>
            <p>A
MODEST EXAMINATION
OF THE
AUTHORITY and REASONS
Of the Late
DECREE
OF THE
Vice-Chancellor of <hi>OXFORD,</hi>
AND
Some HEADS of Colleges and Halls;
CONCERNING
<hi>The Heresy of Three Distinct Infinite-Minds
in the Holy and Ever-blessed Trinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By WILLIAM SHERLOCK, D. D.
Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, Master of the <hi>Temple,</hi> and
Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majesty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
Printed for <hi>W. Rogers,</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> against St. <hi>Dunstan</hi>'s
Church in <hi>Fleetstreet.</hi> MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:52275:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52275:2"/>
            <head>A
MODEST EXAMINATION
OF THE
Oxford Decree, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O Man has truer Honour and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
for that Great and Learned Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
of the University of <hi>Oxford,</hi> nor
has paid more just Civilities and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects
to any of the Heads or Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
of it, as I have happened to be
acquainted with them, than my self;
which makes it very uneasy to me,
that there should be the least appearance of any Quarrel
or Disrespect on either side.</p>
            <p>I can despise a Thousand <hi>Jacobite</hi> Stories, even with
all the Additional Comments and Flourishes of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious
Animadverter; and justify my Neglect and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
to my self, who am most nearly concerned in it: For
many of those Stories I can only deny, because I know
nothing of them, but only this, that according to my
Principles and Inclinations, it was morally impossible
that I should say or do such things: And what I do
remember any thing of, is falsly reported; and yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52275:3"/>
be rectified without betraying the Privacies of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation,
as my Accusers have done, and reflecting
sharply upon some who have been old Friends, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
they are now; which are such hateful Vices, and
so destructive to the Innocent Freedoms of Conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
that nothing but absolute necessity can justify or
apologize for the least approaches to them. But the
Charge of Heresy is of a different nature, especially
considering my Profession, Character, and Station in
the Church, which will not admit of a Complemental
Silence: That if it should be thought too bold and
daring to enter the Lists with these <hi>Oxford</hi> Heads, that
force and necessity which they themselves have put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
me, and which a very modest man neither can nor
ought to resist, I hope will excuse it.</p>
            <p>But how come I to be concerned in this Decree,
which only censures one of their own Members, for
some Passages in a Sermon about the Trinity; which,
as it is said, <hi>gave just occasion of Offence and Scandal to
many?</hi> How many were offended, I can't tell; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
they had just cause of Offence, shall be examined
presently; but how much soever they were offended,
they did not think it deserved such a censure: For
when a Warm Zealot promoted a Petition to the Vice-Chancellor
for a Censure, he could persuade but one
Master of Arts to subscribe it.</p>
            <p>But though this Decree was occasioned by this <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>
Preacher, yet every one knew as soon as they saw
it or heard of it, that it was aimed against me: I'm
sure these Gentlemen knew very well what work there
has been made with <hi>Three Distinct Infinite Minds or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</hi>
The Animadverter had railed himself out of
breath, and then calls for a <hi>Decretum Oxoniense</hi> to help
him; which was the wisest thing he could do; for his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52275:3"/>
Reason will never do any hurt; but such a <hi>Decretum</hi>
might furnish him with new Topicks of Railing. It
happen'd as luckily for the purpose as if it had been
contrived, that this Preacher used some of the same
Expressions which I had done, and which the Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter
had charged with Tritheism, <hi>viz. Three Distinct
Infinite Minds and Spirits.</hi> This was an Opportunity
not to be neglected, to obtain his desired Decree:
Dr. <hi>South</hi> sollicited the Cause with such Zeal and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity,
as could not be resisted; and, as I am inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
prepared the way for it in a furious Sermon the <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi>
before, wherein he upbraided them, as being afraid to
condemn Heresy, <hi>Deism, Socinianism, Tritheism, lest they
should fall from Ecclesiastical Grace, and the door of Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
should be shut against them;</hi> which was a very civil
Complement both to them and to the Governors of our
Church. Some of the wisest Heads among them, and who
were most concerned in a Decree of Heresy, were absent;
others absented themselves; and some who were present
in the Convention, dissented, alledging, That their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
were Irregular, and not according to their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.
But some of the Animadverters Complexion and
Interest, with great Zeal over-ruled the rest, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree
was past, and printed in <hi>Latin,</hi> in these words:
<q>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52275:4"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="decree">
                           <head>In Conventu D. Vice-Cancellarii &amp; Prefectorum Collegio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
&amp; Aularum Vniversitatis Oxon. <date>Die Vicesimo
quinto Novembris. A. D. 1695.</date>
                           </head>
                           <p>CUM in Concione nuper habitâ coram Universi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
Oxon. in Templo S. Petri in Oriente, ad Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum
SS. Simonis &amp; Judae proxime elapsum, haec Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,
inter alia, publice prolata &amp; asserta suerunt, <hi>viz.
[There are Three Infinite distinct Minds and Substances in
the Trinity.]</hi> Item <hi>[That the Three Persons in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
are Three Distinct Infinite Minds or Spirits, and Three
Individual Substances.]</hi> Quae verba multis justam offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionis
Causam &amp; Scandalum dedêre:</p>
                           <p>Dominus Vice-Cancellarius &amp; Praefecti Collegiorum
&amp; Aularum, in generali suo Conventu jam congregati,
Judicant, Declarant, &amp; Decernunt, praedicta Verba esse
<hi>Falsa, Impia, &amp; Heretica;</hi> Dissona &amp; Contraria Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae
Ecclesiae Catholicae, &amp; speciatim Doctrinae Ecclesiae
Anglicanae, publice receptae.</p>
                           <p>Quapropter praecipiunt &amp; firmiter injungunt Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus
&amp; singulis, eorum fidei &amp; curae commissis, ne <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ale
aliquod Dogma, in Concionibus, aut aliàs, in posterum
proferant.</p>
                           <closer>Ex Decreto Domini Vice-Cancellarii &amp; Prefectorum
<signed>
                                 <hi>Ben. Cooper</hi> Not. publicus
&amp; Registrarius Vniversitatis Oxon.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:52275:4"/>
Whoever drew up this Decree, some Criticks say
he need not brag much of his Skill in <hi>Latin,</hi> having
transgressed the plain Rules of <hi>Grammar,</hi> in using <hi>Eorum
fidei &amp; curae,</hi> for <hi>suae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this <hi>Latin</hi> Decree did not satisfy the Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
but for the Benefit and Edification of <hi>English</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
he (as is easy to guess) Translates it, and adds a
notable Title, and a notable Remark to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Title is,</hi> An Account of the Decree of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity
of <hi>Oxford,</hi> against some Heretical Tenets.</p>
            <p>The Remark by way of Postscript is, <hi>It may be
noted, That the Propositions above-mentioned are
Dr. S—k's in his Discourse of the Trinity, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders
of it, and wrote against by the Animadverter,</hi> &amp;c.
which is as good <hi>English</hi> as the other is <hi>Latin:</hi> And yet
this did not satisfy him, till he had published this <hi>Oxford</hi>
Decree against Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> in one of the Weekly Prints.
<hi>Spectatum admissi!</hi> Certainly he thinks there is no stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
against this <hi>Oxford</hi> Decree; and therefore in the
first place let us briefly examine the Authority of it.</p>
            <p>He calls it, <hi>The Decree of the Vniversity of</hi> Oxford;
which is a mere Sham; for some Heads of Colleges
and Halls were never yet thought <hi>the Vniversity of
Oxford:</hi> But that Great and Learned Body, if they
will vindicate their own Rights, are more concerned in
this than I am. The Decree of an <hi>Oxford</hi> Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
is indeed <hi>Decretum Oxoniense,</hi> or a Decree of the
University of <hi>Oxford:</hi> This is what the Animadverter
called for, and this he would persuade the world he
has; but let the <hi>Oxford</hi> Convocation look to this,
which may prove an ill President.</p>
            <p>But I am inform'd (for I confess I know not their
Statutes my self) that this Decree of <hi>the Heads of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges
and Halls,</hi> is so far from being <hi>the Decree of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52275:5"/>
Vniversity of Oxford,</hi> that it is no Judicial nor Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative
Decree at all; not so much as for censuring a
Preacher, much less for declaring and decreeing Heresy.
Their Statutes refer such Censures to the Vice-Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor,
and Six Heads, Doctors of Divinity, and to one
or both the Professors of Divinity; but give no such
Authority to the General Meeting of the Heads, much
less to Heads, who are no Divines, nor Doctors in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity;
and some such there were in this Meeting. So
that this pretended <hi>Decree of the Vniversity of Oxford,</hi>
is no more than the private Opinions of some Heads;
and if that be so Venerable an Authority, I will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake
any day in the Year, to procure a Meeting of
twice as many, as Wise and Learned Men, to censure
their Decree. But supposing their Authority to be Just
and Regular, there is another very proper Question,
How far their Authority extends? Whether to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring
and decreeing Heresy? Whatever the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation
of the University may challenge, this was
never before pretended to by the Heads of Colleges and
Halls.</p>
            <p>All the Authority I can learn their Statutes give
them in such Cases, is to summon the Preacher, who
has said any thing in his Sermon contrary to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to require a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
recantation from him, or to forbid him ever to
preach again in the <hi>Vniversity:</hi> Whereas nothing of all
this was done; the Preacher not summoned to this
Meeting, nor his Name, as far as I can learn, once
mentioned in it; no Recantation enjoined, no Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition
of his Preaching again: But instead of this,
which was their proper Business, they declare and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree
Heresy, which so many Masters of Arts might
have done with as good Authority, where ever they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52275:5"/>
had met. And they ought, (notwithstanding all their
Zeal against Heresy) to have advised with men of Skill,
how far such an Irregular and Unstatutable proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
might affect them.</p>
            <p>The Authority of declaring and making Heresy,
may be of such pernicious Consequence to the Peace
of any Church, that it is not fit to be intrusted with
any Body of men less then a National Synod; for
otherwise we may have as many different and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
Religions, as there are Declarers and Decreers
of Heresy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Statute</hi> 1 Eliz. ca. 1. <hi>we find</hi> the power to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
determine, or adjudge any matter or cause to be Heresy,
<hi>restrained only</hi> to such as heretofore have been determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
ordered, or adjudged to be Heresy by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
of the Canonical Scriptures: Or by the first Four
General Councils: Or by any other General Council,
wherein the same was declared Heresy by the express
and plain words of the said Canonical Scriptures: Or
such as hereafter shall be ordered, judged, or deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
to be Heresy, by the High Court of Parliament
of this Realm, with the Assent of the Clergy in their
Convocation. And if the King could not grant a greater
Authority than this to his High Commissioner for Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical
Affairs, it is not likely that any other Body
of men have it; and my Lord <hi>Cook</hi> says, That this is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
to others, especially to Bishops in their adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng
Heresy, 3 <hi>Instit. pa.</hi> 40. and how they have obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
this Law in their Decree, they had best consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oxford Reasons</hi> have formerly had a very just Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration
paid to them, and will have so still, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
they are penned with the same strength and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;
but they have a greater Opinion of their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52275:6"/>
than I can find the rest of the world has, if they
think by a meer Decree, without pretending to give the
least reason for it, to silence all disputes, and to bear
down all Reasons, and all Authorities on the other
side</p>
            <p>But since these Heads are pleased to take part in the
quarrel, which one would have thought they need not
have done, had they not suspected the Success of their
Animadverting Champion; I accept this exchange with
all thankfulness. As for the Animadverter, he might for
me have writ on as long as he pleased, and have railed and
triumphed as much as he pleased, and the world might
have judged of him, and his performances, as they
pleased: His last Book I have read nothing of, and
could never persuade my self to read all his first Book;
there is such an Evil Spirit and such Venom in his
Writings, as is enough to give an Unchristian Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture
to those who read them: He resolved never to
answer any one but my self; and I resolved never to
read what he writ; and thus there was some hope to
see an end of this matter, when he grew weary of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
or his Bookseller of Printing. But now I hope to
meet with no new Animadverters, who shall all fare
alike with me; but with Men of Ingenuity and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,
good Learning, and good Tempers, who will
reason without Sophistry and Misrepresentations, weigh
Authorities in an equal Balance, and contend for Truth,
not for Victory; and then it is indifferent to me whether
I overcome, or am overcome; for Truth is better than
Victory, and will make an Honest Man triumph in
being conquered.</p>
            <p>Having thus considered the Authority of this Decree,
which the Animadverter so much glories in, let us now
examine the Decree it self.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52275:6"/>
These words, <hi>Three distinct Infinite Minds,</hi> and <hi>Three
Substances,</hi> as applied to the Three Persons of the Ever-Blessed
Trinity, are singled out in this Decree, and
parted from the Body of the Sermon, without any
thing to explain in what sense the Preacher used them;
and therefore we must conclude, that these Words are
absolutely condemned, as <hi>False, Impious, and Heretical:</hi>
That though a <hi>Mind</hi> in this place signifies <hi>an Intelligent
Person;</hi> and <hi>Substance a Substantial Person;</hi> and Three
Infinite Intelligent Persons, and Three Infinite Substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial
Persons, is the Catholick Faith; as I doubt not to
make appear; yet Three Distinct Infinite Minds, and
Three Substances, when they are used in no other sense,
than for three Intelligent and Substantial Persons, must
be condemned <hi>as Impious and Heretical.</hi> These are won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
nice Criticks, to make the same Doctrine, owned
and acknowledged to be the same, in one Form of
Words to be truly Catholick and Orthodox, and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Form of Words, which do and are intended to sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify
the same thing, <hi>False, Impious, and Heretical:</hi> This
is a strange Magical Power of Words; <hi>Hoc est Corpus</hi> in
the mouth of a Popish Priest, never were pretended to
make a more Miraculous Transubstantiation. I wish it
at last appear that these Gentlemen do really believe
Three Infinite Intelligent Persons, and Three Substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial
Persons in the Trinity; for let them distinguish as
subtilly as they please, an Intelligent Person is a Mind,
and a Substantial Person is a Substance, and Three are
Three; of which more presently.</p>
            <p>There may indeed be a very Heretical Sense put
upon these words: to say, That there are Three In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
Minds or Persons (for the Heresy is the same,
whatever the word be) wholly divided and separated
from each other, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Three Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52275:7"/>
Principlees, Independent on each other, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;
Three Unbegotten ones, without any relation
to each other, as Father, Son, and Spirit; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
Three Substances in the <hi>Arian</hi> Notion, for Three
distinct Kinds and Species of Substance; or Three Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
and Essences specifically different: All this, I say,
is False, Impious, and Heretical, and has been condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
as such by the Catholick Church. And could they
have affix'd any such Sense as this on the Preacher's
Words, they would have done well to have shewn it;
and then they had done very justly and religiously, in
condemning such an Impious Sense of these Words:
but to condemn Words, in themselves very Orthodox,
as Impious and Heretical, without giving the least In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation
wherein their Impiety and Heresy consists, is
a new way of proceeding, which they never learnt from
any of the Ancient Councils. But Party-<hi>Shibboleths</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
do the best Execution, the less they are understood.</p>
            <p>The Charge is drawn up as fully and emphatically as
it is possible. 1. That these aforesaid Words are False.
2. That they are Impious. 3. Heretical. 4. Contrary to
the Doctrine of the Catholick Church. And 5. In
particular contrary to the Doctrine of the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> as publickly received.<note place="margin">Judicant, declarant, &amp; decernunt, praedicta ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba esse falsa, impia, &amp; he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retica; dissona &amp; contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria doctrinae Ecclesiae Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicae, &amp; speciatim do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae Ecclesiae Anglica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, publice receptae.</note> This they
Judge, Declare, and Determine; and had
they Proved it too, they had done all at
once; but now the hardest part still re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains;
and men who will not take their
bare word for it, will judge all over again.
And I hope it will give no Offence to that
Great and Learned Body of the University of <hi>Oxford,</hi> to
examine the rash and hasty Judgment of some of the
Heads of their Colleges and Halls.</p>
            <p>In order to this, I shall briefly premise some few plain
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52275:7"/>
Observations, the more effectually to shew the Rashness
and Injudiciousness of this Decree.</p>
            <p>As 1. That no form of words is to be condemned as
<hi>False, Impious, and Heretical,</hi> which do not necessarily
and manifestly contain a <hi>False, Impious, and Heretical
Sense:</hi> Words may be new, unusual, inconvenient, and
want the stamp of Ecclesiastical Authority, which are
not <hi>False, Impious, or Heretical.</hi> These are very different
Crimes, to broach new Words, and new Heresies, when
the Words themselves are not manifestly Heretical.
And certainly such men ought to have understood this,
who take upon them to be Judges of Heresy.</p>
            <p>Nay, <hi>2dly.</hi> Such new forms of speech as are liable to
an Heretical sense, are not therefore to be rejected, if
they are of use to secure the True Catholick Faith, and
those who use them declare the Orthodox sense wherein
they use them. All learned men know, that the <hi>Homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousion</hi>
it self was charged with as many Heresies as any
other word can well be: Some charged it with <hi>Sabellia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nism;</hi>
others with a division and partition of the Divine
Substance; as if the Son's being begotten of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's
Substance, and so being Consubstantial, or of one
Substance with him, signified such an Efflux and Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
as divided the Father's Substance, and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
part of it to the Son: But when the Catholick
Fathers rejected these perverse and Heretical senses of
the word, and declared in what sense they used it, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position
to the <hi>Arian</hi> Heresy, and that it was the most
significant word which could be used to that purpose,
and which those subtle Hereticks, who equivocated in all
other forms of words, could by no means elude, the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi>
Council received it into their Creed; and <hi>Eusebius</hi>
of <hi>Caesarea,</hi> and some others, who at first scrupled the
use of that word, subscribed to it, when they were satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52275:8"/>
of its Orthodox signification. It is reasonable for all
men to consider this, who pretend to find Heresy in
words, Whether those who use them, own that Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
sense which they charge upon them; for otherwise
they may as well condemn the <hi>Homoousion,</hi> as False, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious,
and Heretical, as <hi>Three distinct Infinite Minds and
Spirits,</hi> if they have no regard to the sense of those who
use these words, nor to the end for which they are used.</p>
            <p>3. And if we will ever allow of Unscriptural Words
to explain and secure the Catholick Faith, (which none
but secret or open Hereticks ever quarrel'd at) there
may be the same reason and necessity for it in our Age,
that ever there was in any Age of the Christian Church;
and then it is as justifiable now, as ever it was. The
Church never had Authority to make a new Faith, but
always had, and always will have, Authority to declare
and explain the True Catholick Faith in such words as
are most aptly expressive of it, and necessary to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
the Arts and Evasions of Hereticks.</p>
            <p>This Apology the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers made for putting
the <hi>Homoousion</hi> into their Creed, as St. <hi>Athanasius</hi> declares
at large, in his Book <hi>de decretis Synodi Nicaenae.</hi> The <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
made a shift to reconcile their Heresy to all other
Forms of words, by the <hi>Homoousion</hi> detected their Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisy
and Heresy: This was too plain and express to
be evaded by equivocal senses, and therefore they could
never be reconciled to it; and the Catholick Fathers
thought that a very necessary reason for the use of it.</p>
            <p>Now if such expressions as these, <hi>Three distinct Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
Minds and Spirits, or Three Substances,</hi> be as necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
in our Age to detect and oppose <hi>Sabellianism,</hi> and to
secure the Catholick Faith of a Real, Substantial Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
(which is all that is intended by them) as the <hi>Homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousion</hi>
was at the time of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, to detect
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52275:8"/>
and oppose <hi>Arianism;</hi> this will justify the use of such ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions,
how novel soever they may be thought; and
what necessity there is for this in our Age, will appear
presently.</p>
            <p>4. It is a sufficient justification of any Unscriptural
Forms of words in Articles of Faith, that though the
express words are not found in Scripture, yet all that is,
and that is intended to be signified by those words, is
found in Scripture; for no words can be <hi>false, impious,
and heretical,</hi> which contain the true Catholick Faith,
as taught in Scripture: Thus <hi>Athanasius</hi> and the other
<hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers answer that <hi>Arian</hi> Objection against
the <hi>Homoousion,</hi> that it is not to be found in Scripture;
that though the word is not in Scripture, the Faith sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
by that word is; and thus St. <hi>Augustine</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
defends it in his dispute with <hi>Pascentius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. No Expressions can be said to be contrary to the
Doctrine of the Catholick Church, which have been
used by Catholick Fathers, either in the same or in equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent
terms, and contain that Doctrine which the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
Fathers always taught.</p>
            <p>Having premised this, let us now examine the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
which these <hi>Oxford</hi> Heads have made of these Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions:
<hi>There are Three Infinite distinct Minds and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances
in the Trinity;</hi> Item, <hi>That the Three Persons in
the Trinity are</hi> Three <hi>distinct Infinite Minds or Spirits, and
Three Individual Substances.</hi> That is, I suppose, as much
Individual Substances, as they are Individual Persons.</p>
            <p>It is evident, that all this relates only to the Notion of
the Trinity, and to the Notion of a Divine Person, and
of Three Divine Persons in the Trinity; and therefore
the Unity of the Godhead is not concerned in this, which
belongs to another Question, How these Three are One;
of which more when I examine the <hi>Heresy</hi> charged on
these words.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:52275:9"/>
1. But the first charge is, that they are <hi>false:</hi> I wish
they had told us what in them is false; but since they have
made no distinction, we must suppose they mean that all
these words are false. Is it false then, that each Person
in the Ever-Blessed Trinity is by himself in his own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
a Distinct, Infinite Mind, Spirit, or Substance? Is
not God the Father an Infinite Mind or Spirit? Is not
God the Son, the substantial Word and Wisdom of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
an Infinite Mind or Spirit? Is not God the Holy
Ghost, that Eternal Spirit, which knoweth the things of
God, as the Spirit of a Man knoweth the things of
a man, an Eternal Mind or Spirit? Or is not an Infinite
Mind and Spirit a Substance, the most real perfect Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance;
that is in the world, which gives Substance and
Subsistence to all other things? Is not the Father consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
as an Infinite Mind and Spirit, distinct from the
Son and the Holy Ghost; the Son distinct from the
Father and the Holy Ghost; the Holy Ghost distinct from
the Father and the Son? To deny any thing of all this, is
downright <hi>Sabellianism,</hi> and destroys a real substantial
Trinity, which is as Essential to the Christian Faith, as
the Unity of the Godhead is.</p>
            <p>The only Quarrel then, that I can imagine, against
these words is this; That tho the Father be a distinct Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
Mind, and the Son a distinct Infinite Mind, and the
Holy Ghost a distinct Infinite Mind, yet according to the
Catholick Form of Speech, we must not say that there are
Three distinct Infinite Minds, but one Infinite Mind or
Spirit or Substance: Now I grant that in the sense of the
<hi>Homoousion,</hi> or Consubstantiality, this is very True and
Orthodox, in which sense St. <hi>Jerom</hi> condemned <hi>Tres Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantias</hi>
or Three Substances; and St. <hi>Austin,</hi> who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
that the Father is a Spirit, the Son a Spirit, and
the Holy Ghost a Spirit, yet denied, that there are Three
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52275:9"/>
Spirits, but One Spirit; but when we apply this
to Persons, it is gross <hi>Sabellianism</hi> to say, that there are
not Three Personal Minds, or Spirits or Substances,
but only One Mind Spirit, or Substance; for then there
can be but one Person too, for one Personal Mind is but
One Person.</p>
            <p>Let us consider what a Mind is, and how we can
know whether there be but One, or more distinct Minds.
The Substance of a Mind I know nothing of, no more
than I do what the naked Substance of Body or Matter
is; but the true Notion of a Mind is a thinking Being,
and therefore where ever we find the Acts of Knowledge,
Understanding and Will, there is a Mind; and where
there are distinct Personal Acts of Knowledge and Will,
there are distinct Personal Minds.</p>
            <p>Now if we believe the Scripture, the Father knows
the Son, and the Son knows the Father; the Father wills,
and the Son by a distinct Personal act, wills with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and what the Father wills; the Father works, and
the Son works, and sees all that the Father doth, and
doth the same things.</p>
            <p>Thus the Fathers proved against the <hi>Sabellians</hi> the real
and substantial distinction of Persons in the Unity of the
Godhead, from those distinct personal acts which are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed
in Scripture to Father, Son, and Holy Ghost;
which having a mutual relation to each other, require
distinct Persons for their Subjects; and since all the instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
they give (as may be seen in <hi>Tertullian</hi> against <hi>Praxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,
Novatian</hi> in his Book of the Trinity, <hi>Athanasius</hi> against
the <hi>Sabellians,</hi> St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> St <hi>Austin,</hi> and all that have writ
on this Argument) are acts of a Mind, as well as of a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
they must prove (if they prove any thing) distinct
Minds as well as Persons; for if one singular Solitary
Mind may be the Subject of such distinct acts as necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52275:10"/>
suppose more than one, One Person may be so too;
and then there is no possible way left to confute <hi>Sabellia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nism,</hi>
or to prove a real Trinity of distinct substantial
Persons. It is very evident, that both the <hi>Sabellians,</hi> and
the Catholick Fathers in this Controversy understood the
same thing by Person, which we do by Mind or Spirit:
By Person the <hi>Sabellians</hi> meant such a Person as is true
and perfect God; and therefore the most real Substance,
an Infinite Mind and Spirit; and for this reason they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
Three Persons for fear of Three Gods, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
was, and is still the Objection against a real substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial
Trinity; for there is no danger, that Three Names, or
Notions, or Modes, should be a Trinity of Gods. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
this, the Catholick Fathers allow their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of a Person, and prove against them such a Trinity
of Persons as they rejected, each of which is true and
perfect God.</p>
            <p>Now since <hi>Person</hi> is the Catholick word, which long
Ecclesiastical use has made familiar, I should by no
means allow of any other word in this Mystery, could we
retain the old Catholick Faith, together with the word:
But when men make no more of a Person, than a meer
Mode, and a Trinity of Modes in one singular Nature,
and Substance, must pass for a Trinity of Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
which was the Heresy of <hi>Sabellius,</hi> who contended
for One Singular Solitary Nature or Subsistence in God,
and was not much concerned by what name you called
the Three, so they were not Three Substantial Subsist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Persons; for he never dreamt that there could be
Three Real Substantial Persons in One Singular Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
I say, when this Heresy is reviv'd under a new
Name, we are under a necessity of saying in more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press
words, what the Fathers meant by Person, if we
will retain the Catholick Faith, as well as the Word.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:52275:10"/>
Would Men but give themselves a little Liberty
of thinking, they would see how impossible it is to
find a <hi>Medium</hi> between a real <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Sabellia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nism,</hi>
however disguis'd. The Three Persons in the
blessed <hi>Trinity</hi> are either Three Substantial Persons,
or they are not; to deny them to be Substantial is
<hi>Sabellianism,</hi> whatever else we call them: There must
be either One singular solitary Substance in the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
or Three distinct Personal Substances: The first
is the fundamental Article of the <hi>Sabellian</hi> Creed,
and a direct Contradiction to the Doctrine of the
<hi>Trinity,</hi> for One singular, solitary Nature or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
is but One Person; for which reason the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellians</hi>
so earnestly contended for it, and the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi>
Fathers so vigorously oppos'd it: And if we
own Three distinct substantial Persons in the <hi>Trinity,</hi>
we must own Three distinct personal Substances;
for a distinct substantial Person must have a distinct
Substance of his own, proper and peculiar to his own
Person: that though the Father and the Son are of
one Substance, as the Son is begotten of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
of the Father, and consubstantial with him;
yet the personal Substance of the Son is no more
the personal Substance of the Father, than the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
is the Person of the Son, or the Son the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of the Father: and therefore there is a manifest
<hi>Sabellian</hi> Fallacy in it, which it is impossible to make
sense of, to say, That the Father is an infinite Mind,
the Son an infinite Mind, and the Holy Ghost an
infinite Mind; that the Father is Substance, the Son
Substance, the Holy Ghost Substance, and yet that
there are not Three personal Minds, or Three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal
Substances, but One singular Mind and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance;
for this is to be One and Three in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52275:11"/>
same Sense; which is not Mystery, but Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p>There has been a nice Dispute about the singular
and plural Predication, when we speak of God; that
since in the Unity of the Godhead there are Three
and One, what it is we may call Three, and what One:
This is the whole Pretence, as far as I can guess,
for the <hi>Oxford</hi> Censure, that Minds and Substances
are spoke of in the plural Number. Now this seems
to me to be a very plain Case, that if in the ever
Blessed <hi>Trinity</hi> there be Three and One, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
they are Three may be said to be Three; but
that wherein they are but One, must be said to be
but One; for otherwise Three are not Three, nor
One One; which must either destroy the Faith of
the <hi>Trinity,</hi> or of the <hi>Vnity.</hi> That there are <hi>Three
Persons, and One God,</hi> is the Catholick Language;
and therefore Three belongs to the Persons, and
One to the Godhead: And therefore whatever is
absolutely Essential to the Notion of a distinct
Person, may be number'd and distinguish'd with the
Persons; for whatever is included in the Notion of
a Person, though it be number'd with the Persons,
no more affects the Unity of the Godhead, than a
Trinity of Persons does. If then a Person be a
Mind, a Spirit, a Substance, Three such Persons must
be Three as distinct Minds, Spirits, or Substances,
as they are distinct Fersons; and Three such Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal
Minds, Spirits, or Substances, are as reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
with the Unity of the Godhead, as Three sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial
Persons; for the <hi>Three</hi> belongs to the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,</hi>
who are Three, not to the Godhead, which
is but One; of which more presently.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:52275:11"/>
As for that Phrase of <hi>Three individual Substances,</hi>
it seems more obnoxious, because <hi>individual</hi> may
signifie, and does in common use, more than barely
<hi>distinct,</hi> even <hi>a separate</hi> Substance, as all other indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduals
are; and an <hi>Individual</hi> carries with it a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
to a <hi>Species;</hi> and though the ancient Fathers
do indeed mention frequently a specifick Unity of
Nature in the Godhead, they did not confine the
Unity of the Divine Nature to this, which is a meer
Logical and Notional Unity: The Divine Nature is
no <hi>Species,</hi> for it is but One, and therefore the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
of the Godhead is the most real, essential, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divisible,
inseparable Unity.</p>
            <p>But how incautious soever the Expression is, the
Preacher seems to have had no ill meaning in it;
and therefore this might have been corrected, but
not so heavily censur'd, especially since <hi>Boethius</hi> his
Definition of a Person might have led him to it,
<hi>rationabilis naturae individua substantia,</hi> the <hi>individual
Substance</hi> of a rational Nature: And if this may be
allow'd a good Definition of a Divine Person, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
belongs to the Definition of a Person, may
be number'd and distinguished with the Persons.</p>
            <p>2. Thus much for the first Charge, that these
Words are <hi>false;</hi> the next is much heavier, That
they are <hi>impious.</hi> Now there are but two things
wherein the impiety of any Doctrine can consist,
either in teaching some Wickedness, or in reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and blaspheming the Deity. Now what Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
does this Doctrine of a real substantial <hi>Trinity,</hi>
a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Three infinite personal Minds, teach
us? unless to worship Father, Son, and Holy Ghost
with the most humble and devout Adorations, be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52275:12"/>
impiety. This indeed it does teach us, and this we
do, and this no other Notion of a <hi>Trinity</hi> can
teach us, or justifie us in doing: For is any other
<hi>Trinity</hi> but a real substantial <hi>Trinity,</hi> the Object of
a religious Adoration? can we without impiety, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctly
worship, as we do in our Litany, three distinct
Persons, who are not each of them distinctly in their
own Persons, infinite Mind and Spirit? is <hi>a Mode, a
Posture, a Somewhat,</hi> without any name or notion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
to it, the Object of Religious Worship? is it
possible in the nature of the thing, for any man, who
believes but one singular, solitary, divine Nature, to
worship three with a distinct worship, without any
conception of a real, substantial, distinction between
them? Can any man honour the Son, as he honours the
Father, as a distinct Object, and with distinct acts of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,
who does not believe the Son to be as truly and
substantially a Divine Person, as the Father is, and as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct
a Person from the Father, as <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> were
distinct Persons, tho not separate Persons, as they were?
Men may please themselves with subtil distinctions, but
they can never distinguish themselves nor others out
of their sense and feeling; and I appeal to all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
whether distinct Acts of worship do not require
distinct Objects, as really distinct as their Worship is?
whether they can distinctly worship, three Names, or
Modes, or Somewhats, when there is but one real sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial
Subject or Suppositum of them all? if they can,
their Devotion is as airy, subtil, and unintelligible, as
their Distinctions are.</p>
            <p>Does this Doctrine then of a real substantial Trinity,
of three infinite Personal Minds, reproach or blaspheme
the Deity? I do not now dispute with the Antitrini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian
Hereticks, who are professedly so, who charge
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52275:12"/>
the Doctrine it self with Blasphemy, but with those
who profess to believe a Trinity, but charge the
Doctrine of a real, substantial Trinity with impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
and therefore shall confine my self only to
them.</p>
            <p>Is it any Reproach then to the Ever Blessed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
to affirm, that each Person is by himself a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct
infinite Mind? is an infinite Mind then a Term
of Reproach and Blasphemy? does not an infinite
Mind signifie all the Perfections of a Deity? and
is this Blasphemy? I beseech you against whom? a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
Father, Son, or Holy Ghost? and is not each
of these Divine Persons a distinct infinite Mind? or
is it Blasphemy to say, what they are? or when each
of these Divine Persons is a distinct infinite Mind, is
it Blasphemy to say, that three Divine Persons are
three distinct infinite Minds? that is, will the Three
Divine Persons of the ever Blessed Trinity, when
each of them is, and is owned to be a distinct infinite
Mind, think themselves reproach'd to be call'd Three?
and if the Divine Persons will not think themselves
blasphem'd by this, there is no danger that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
Nature should: For the Divine Nature is whole
and entire in each Divine Person, and there is no
danger but three distinct infinite Minds must have
the same One Divine Nature, for Infinite, Infinite, and
Infinite, are but one and the same Infinite Nature.
But as I take it, the danger of Blasphemy is on the
other side: for if they deny the Three Persons of the
Trinity to be three distinct infinite Minds, which of
these Divine Persons, Father, Son, or Holy Ghost, will
they deny to be an Infinite Mind? for when we know
him, we must strike him out of the Trinity, as not
being true and perfect God: Or if they allow <hi>Person</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52275:13"/>
to signifie the same thing, when applied to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
to the Son, or to the Holy Ghost, then neither
of these Persons is a Divine Infinite Mind, or each of
them is, and then there are <hi>three,</hi> as there are three
Persons, or there is never a Divine Infinite Mind a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
them all; the Consequence of which is so blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous,
that I know not whether I may venture to
say it, for fear the Animadverter should serve me, as he
has done once already, to make these Consequences my
own Doctrine: But yet I will tell these Gentlemen,
what a bolder man, than I am, would venture to say
upon this occasion, that if a Divine Person, as a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
and as distinct from the other Persons, be
not an Infinite Mind, there is an end of the Christian
Trinity, in which every Person is true and perfect
God, which no Person is, who is not an Infinite
Mind; and therefore if any one Person, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
in his distinct personal Capacity, be not an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
Mind, he does not belong to the Christian Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;
and if all the Persons are in this respect alike,
that not any one of them, in his distinct Personal Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity,
is a distinct Infinite Mind, then there is no
Trinity at all; and if they will find a God, when
they have renounced a Trinity, it must be one singular
Divine Nature, which they themselves will not allow
to be a Person: And thus we have lost a Trinity, and
lost a God, who is a Person. This is plain sence, and
I fear, neither <hi>Thomas,</hi> nor <hi>Scotus,</hi> can help them out.</p>
            <p>But let us suppose (and I am sure they ought to
be thankful for such a Supposition, for their Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of a <hi>Person</hi> will not admit it, unless they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand
one thing by a Person when apply'd to the
Father, and another when apply'd to the Son, and
Holy Spirit; but I say, let us suppose) that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52275:13"/>
Nature is originally in the Person of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
or that the Father is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the
unbegotten, self originated God, as he certainly is,
and therefore a Divine substantial Person, who is es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentially
God: Now the very Name of Father is a
relative Term, and signifies that he has a Son, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten
of himself; and let any Man consider which
sounds most like Blasphemy, both against the Father
and the Son, to say, that the Father begets a Son,
who is his own perfect Likeness and Image, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press
Character of his own Substance (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>)
of the same Substance with himself, but distinct in
Substance, as Father and Son are, true and perfect
God, as his Father is, without any other the least
difference, but that one is the Father, and the other
the Son; or to say, that the Father begets no Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
at all, but only a Mode, or a Relation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
a Relative, in his own Substance: That the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
begets Filiation, not a Son, but Sonship; is not
this to ridicule the Divine Generation, and to make
Sport for Atheists and Hereticks: If God begets no
Substance, he begets nothing real, nothing substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially
distinct from himself, and therefore no sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial
Person; and then neither God is a true and
real Father, nor the Son a real Son, which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws
the whole Mystery of our Redemption, by
the Incarnation, Death, and Sufferings of the Son of
God: For God was not incarnate, if the Divine
Nature was not incarnate: And if there be but one
singular divine Nature and Substance in the Deity,
though they could find a Trinity of Persons in this
one singular Nature, the Incarnation of this one sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
Nature is impossible, without the Incarnation
of the whole Trinity. Men may wrangle as long
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52275:14"/>
as they please about these Matters, but it is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest
Contradiction to say, That the Divine Nature
is incarnate in the Son, and is not incarnate in the
Father and the Holy Ghost, when there is but one
singular Divine Nature and Substance in them all;
which is to say, that the same one singular Nature
is incarnate and is not incarnate; and <hi>is,</hi> and <hi>is not,</hi>
is a Contradiction, or there never can be a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.
And now I leave it to all impartial Judges
on which side the Impiety lies.</p>
            <p>3. The third Charge is <hi>Heresie:</hi> But if it be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
false, nor impious, I hope there is no Heresie
in it neither: However, they would have done well
to have given this Heresie a Name, that we might
have known where to find it, who were the first
Authors of it, in what Age of the Church it began,
and by what General Councils it was condemn'd:
For I can find no Heresie in these censur'd Words,
but the Heresie of a real substantial Trinity, the
Heresie of three substantial Persons, or of three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal
Minds and Substances; and I do not find any
mention of this Heresie in the ancient Records of the
Church, unless those who called themselves Catholicks
were these Hereticks; for this was always their Doctrine,
as some of our Modern Orthodox Zealots, and Heresie-makers
confess, and know not how to excuse them from
Heresie upon this account. Well! if this be the Case,
we must be contented to be Hereticks with all the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
Fathers, and the four first General Councils: but
these Gentlemen should have remembred, that the
Church of <hi>England</hi> requires them to expound Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
as the ancient Catholick Doctors expound it,
and receives the four first General Councils, where
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52275:14"/>
this Heresie is in great Perfection; and it had not
been amis, if some body had minded them, that the
Laws of <hi>England,</hi> as I observ'd before, forbid the
declaring any Doctrine to be Heresie, which is not
condemn'd for Heresie in the four first General
Councils.</p>
            <p>But let Fathers and Councils, Canons, or Acts of
Parliament say what they please, they have a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
and more venerable Authority than all of them:
The Animadverter has told them it is Heresie, and
has told them what Heresie it is, no less than the
Heresie of <hi>Tritheism.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I confess, I am much to seek what this
Heresie of <hi>Tritheism</hi> is. It is not <hi>Paganism,</hi> for the
Heathens did not stint themselves in the Number
of their Gods; they were <hi>Polytheists,</hi> not <hi>Tritheists,</hi>
even the <hi>Platonists</hi> themselves, though they own'd
a Trinity, a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or one Divinity, which exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
it self to Three, which was essentially distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish'd
from all created Nature, and from all their
Creature Gods; but they worshipped many Gods
besides, as the rest of the <hi>Pagan</hi> World did. <hi>Trithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ism</hi>
was never charg'd upon any Men but the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippers
of the Holy and ever Blessed Trinity, and
it was charg'd upon them from the beginning by
<hi>Pagans</hi> and Hereticks. The fear of this made <hi>Noe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>
and <hi>Sabellius</hi> deny three real substantial Persons
in the Trinity, and made <hi>Arius</hi> deny the true eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
Divinity of the Son, and Holy Spirit: But the
Catholick Fathers despis'd this Charge, and owned
three distinct real substantial Persons, each of them
by himself to be true and perfect God, but not
Three Gods, but One God: For thus the Scripture
had taught them to believe and speak, that there is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52275:15"/>
but One God, and there are Three, Father, Son,
and Holy Ghost, who have all the Perfections of
the Deity distinctly in themselves. So that this <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theism</hi>
is a Christian Heresie if it be one, and was
never charged upon Christians by Christians for se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
Ages, but only by Hereticks. The most Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox
Christians were always most charg'd with it;
and some to avoid this Charge, turn'd Hereticks,
and were condemn'd for such by the Catholick
Church.</p>
            <p>It is true, in the declining Monkish Ages of the
Church, we sometimes hear of these <hi>Tritheists;</hi> but
it is a very dark part of Story, and I never cou'd
find a satisfactory Account what their Opinions were,
or why they were call'd so: It is not improbable
but that they might fall into the Hands of some ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious
Animadverter, who by Zeal and Faction
might procure a new Name and Heresie to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed
them; for there is no new thing under the
Sun. But this has made me apt to suspect, that those
who have been charg'd with Tritheism, for profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
the Faith and Worship of the ever blessed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
have been the most Orthodox Believers; and
that those who have so minc'd the Matter as to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scape
the Charge of Tritheism from Hereticks, have
been Hereticks themselves: A real substantial Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
in which each Person is by himself perfect God,
has always been charged by Hereticks with Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theism,
for Three, each of whom is true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
God, they say are Three Gods; and yet this is
the true Christian Trinity: But though Men may
laugh at a Trinity of Modes, you shall never hear
them charge it with Tritheism; and what Hereticks,
who own but one personal God, cannot charge with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52275:15"/>
Tritheism, is no Christian Trinity; that is, has not
Three Persons, each of which is true and perfect
God: So far are those Gentlemen mistaken, who
think it a piece of Art and Prudence to avoid all
Expressions which Hereticks charge with Tritheism;
for then they must renounce all Words, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
and express the ture Catholick Faith.</p>
            <p>At least I think, this should warn all Men, who
are not disguis'd Atheists and Infidels under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession
of Christianity, to have a care of ridiculing
Father, Son, and Holy Ghost, to be reveng'd of
these Tritheist Hereticks, as the Animadverter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanely
does, who so often scoffs at me for my Three
Gods, who never own'd any other God than Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
Son, and Holy Ghost, and pities the <hi>Socinians</hi>
as an unequal Match for me, because they have but
One God, and I have Three; nay compares Father,
Son, and Holy Ghost to <hi>Pagan</hi> Gods, when he tells
the World, that I curse him <hi>by my Gods;</hi> which is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest
and impious Allusion to <hi>Goliath</hi>'s cursing <hi>David</hi>
by his Gods. Can he think that the Dispute about Three
Modes, or Three Minds in the Unity of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head
can justifie such Blasphemies as these, against
<hi>Father, Son, and Holy Ghost?</hi> or is this to be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
in a Christian Church? Whether I curse him
or not, (and I thank God, I curse no Man, but
pray for my worst Enemies) he may justly fear that
such Blasphemies will bring the Curse of the ever
Blessed Trinity on him; and that will be no
Jeast.</p>
            <p>No Man, who believes but One Divine Nature,
which is originally in the Father, and is substanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
communicated by the Father to the Son, as a
distinct subsisting Person, by an eternal and ineffable
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52275:16"/>
Generation; and to the Holy Ghost by an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
and substantial Procession from Father and Son,
can be a Tritheist, whatever inconvenient Expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
he may use, unless the Doctrine of the Trinity
it self be Tritheism.</p>
            <p>But let us consider the reason of this Charge a
little more particularly. They ask us, Whether
an eternal and infinite Mind be not ture and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
God? Yes, most certainly; and for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
we must assert, that the Son is an eternal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
Mind, because he is true and perfect God.
But if one infinite Mind is true and perfect God,
are not Three infinite Minds Three Gods? This is
easily answer'd, as far as we are concern'd to answer
these Men, only by changing <hi>Minds</hi> for <hi>Persons.</hi> Is
not an eternal, infinite Person true and perfect God?
and if every eternal Person, as a distinct Person, be
true and perfect God, are not Three such distinct
Persons Three Gods? The Objection is the same;
and let them but answer for themselves, and they
answer for us.</p>
            <p>But if each distinct Person, and each distinct Mind
is true and perfect God, why may not the Term
<hi>God</hi> be number'd and distinguish'd as Persons and
Minds are? Why may we not say that there are
Three Gods as well as that there are Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
or Three Minds? This is the true Difficulty,
which as much affects the Doctrine of the Trinity
it self, as any Terms or Expressions about it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Three Persons</hi> or <hi>Three Minds:</hi> Nay though we
give no Name to these Three, the Difficulty is the
same; for if we own Three, each of whom is true
and perfect God, why are not these Three three
Gods, when each of them is distinctly and by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52275:16"/>
true and perfect God? Now not to dispute
this Matter with the <hi>Socinians,</hi> which is not my
present Business, there is a very plain Account to be
given of this to those who acknowledge a Trinity;
why we may say that there are Three infinite Minds
and Spirits, each of which is true and perfect God,
and yet must not, and ought not to say, that there
are Three Gods.</p>
            <p>The Reason, why we may say, that there are Three
distinct infinite Minds, is, because there are Three,
each of whom is a distinct infinite Mind, and Three,
each of whom is a distinct Mind, are Three distinct
Minds; but the Reason, why we must not say, there
are Three Gods, is not, because there are not Three,
each of whom is distinctly, and by himself, true and
perfect God, as every infinite Mind is, for that is
Sabellianism; but because there is but one and the
same Divinity, or Godhead, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in them
all; and therefore though there are three distinct
Persons, or Minds, each of whom is distinctly, and
by himself (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) God, yet there are not Three
Gods, but One God, or One Divinity: And if they
will not allow, that the same One Divinity or God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,
may be entirely, and indivisible and insepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
in Three distinct Persons or Minds, there is an
End of a Trinity in Unity, of Three Persons and
One God. For if the whole Divine Nature cannot
subsist intirely, indivisibly, and inseparably, and yet
distinctly in Three, either there cannot be Three,
each of whom is distinctly and by himself God, or
there cannot be one God; whereas the scripture No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Unity of God, is not such an Unity as
is only is one Person, for then it could not enjoyn
the Faith and Worship of Father, Son, and Holy
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52275:17"/>
Ghost; but such an Unity as can be between Three,
when the same One Divine Nature, is wholly and
intirely communicated by the eternal Father, to the
eternal Son, and by Father and Son to the eternal
Spirit; without any Division or Separation; and that
which is communicated whole and intire, without
Division or Separation, makes no Number, for it is
but One still. A Mind, and Mind, and Mind, must
be three Minds, or Persons, by reason of their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct
subsistence, which belong to them as three;
but God, and God, and God, as some of the antient
Father speak, are not Three Gods, but One God,
because the same One Divinity <hi>(totus ex toto,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as both the <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Fathers speak,
concerning the Generation of the Son) is whole, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire,
indivisible, inseparable, in all Three; and Three
distinct, whole, inseparable, sames, how hard soever
it may be to conceive, as to the Manner of it, is the
most natural and intelligible Notion of three and
one; and this is the Catholick Notion of a Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
in Unity. I forbear prosecuting this any farther
here, because I shall do it at large elsewhere.</p>
            <p>4. The next Charge is, that it is <hi>Disagreeing and
contrary to the Doctrine of the Catholick Church.</hi> I am
truly sorry for this, because it must unavoidably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect
on their Skill in Antiquity, and the Doctrine
of the Catholick Church; but if the Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
has imposed upon them in this too, they must
thank themselves, and take what follows: I shall
not multiply Testimonies in this Cause at present,
because I have a Treatise by me, which is near fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished,
upon this very Subject, to give an Account
of the Judgment of Catholick Fathers, and Councils
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52275:17"/>
concerning a real and substantial Trinity, and what
their Notion of Thritheism is. The Matter appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to me so plain, and demonstrable, that I began
to be weary of it, as an unnecessary Work; but
this Decree has convinc'd me of the contrary, and
I now thank God, that I am so well prepared to
justifie the true antient Catholick Faith, against the
Pretences of those, who judge of the Doctrine of
the Catholick Church by Inspiration or Prophesie,
without knowing what the Catholick Fathers have
said about it.</p>
            <p>As Confident as these Heads are, of the Doctrine
of the Catholick Church; those, even of their Mind,
who have looked into the Fathers, are not willing
to stand to their Judgment in this Cause: Some of
the <hi>Ante-Nicene</hi> Fathers, they give up to the <hi>Arians,</hi>
and they know not what to think of the <hi>Nicene</hi>
Fathers themselves; they spoke incautiously, and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
very near upon Tritheism; nay, some of them,
they think, were down right Tritheists; and they
are in the right, for they were all so to a man, in this
modern notion of Tritheism, that I was glad to find,
they would own the Doctrine of the Catholick Church,
and put the Cause upon that issue.</p>
            <p>The present Dispute is about <hi>Three distinct in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
Minds, and Substances in the Trinity,</hi> whether
this be the Catholick Doctrine, or Catholick Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage;
now, I suppose, if it appear, that they own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
Three distinct Substances, both Name and Thing,
there will be no Dispute about three Minds, for
the Substance of the Deity can be no other, than
infinite Mind.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:52275:18"/>
Now this is a Wonderfull Dispute, when the
School-Men themselves own the Three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
to be Three Substances, though they say, they
are (not meer Relations without a Subject) but
<hi>relative Substances,</hi> and we say so too: That their
Substances, as their Persons, subsist in an insepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Union, and Relation, to each other: But <hi>relative
Substances,</hi> Substances, which are not absolute and
independent, but essentially related to each other,
as Father, Son, and Holy Ghost, are Substances still,
and three distinct Substances, as they are distinct
Persons.</p>
            <p>But this is not our present Inquiry, what the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
of the Schools is, but what was the Doctrine
of the Primitive Fathers.</p>
            <p>Now it is evident beyond all possibility of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial,
that the Catholick Fathers, one and all, did
assert Three substantial Persons in the Trinity, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
the Heresie of <hi>Sabellius,</hi> who owned but one
substantial Person, with Three Names, according to
his different Appearances: now besides, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible
to make sense of Three substantial Persons,
without three personal Substances, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
must signifie Three Substances; had not these
Fathers understood it in the Sense and Notion of three
Substances, they had not opposed <hi>Sabellius,</hi> whose
fundamental Principle was the one singular, solitary,
Substance of the Deity.</p>
            <p>They asserted indeed <hi>one Substance</hi> of the Deity
against <hi>Arius,</hi> but it was only in that sense, in
which <hi>Arius</hi> denied the <hi>One Substance:</hi> He owned
the Son to be a substantial Person, who had
a distinct Substance of his own, and this the
Nicene Fathers never quarelled with him for;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52275:18"/>
but he denied, that the Substance of the Son
was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of the Substance of the Father
but perfectly of a different Kind and Nature, as
not begotten of his Father's Substance, but made by
his Power. In Opposition to this Heresie, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
taught, not one singular Substance in God,
which is Sabellianism, but such an Oneness of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
as we know not how to express otherwise,
than by a specifick Sameness and Unity, tho' that
does not answer the compleat Notion of the Divine
Unity; but this is one Way the Fathers common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
express it, by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>genus,</hi> and such like Words,
as among us signifie the specifick Unity of Nature;
and therefore they tell us, that by the <hi>Homoousion</hi>
they only meant, that the Son was so of the same
one Substance with the Father, that he is <hi>God of
God, Light of Light, very God of very God;</hi> that is,
true and perfect God, as his Father is true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
God, considered in his own Person, as distinct
from his Father; that he is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> created
out of nothing, as all Creatures are, but is truly
begotten of the Substance of his Father, and in that
Sense Consubstantial, or of one Substance with him,
as all other Sons are Consubstantial with their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.
Now had not this been a very wise Dispute
on both sides, if the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> as well as the <hi>Arians,</hi>
had not allowed, that the Son had a Substance of
his own, proper and appropriate to his own Person,
and as distinct from the Personal Substance of the
Father, as the Person of the Son is distinct from the
Person of the Father, to contend whence he had
his Substance; of the Substance of the Father, or
created out of Nothing, when he has no Substance
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52275:19"/>
at all of his own, proper and peculiar to him as a
Son?</p>
            <p>One would think these two Extremes of <hi>Sabelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anism</hi>
and <hi>Arianism,</hi> both which were rejected with
equal Abhorrence by the Catholick Fathers, might
satisfie any Man what their Judgment was about a
Trinity in Unity. For if these Fathers understood
both these Heresies, and rejected them both, asserted
three substantial Persons, in opposition to <hi>Sabellius,</hi>
and one Substance, in opposition to <hi>Arius,</hi> the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
Faith must lie between these two extremes;
and yet it is demonstrable that there is but one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium
between them. If it be Haeresy to say, that there
is but One Personal Substance in the Deity, as <hi>Sabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi>
asserted, then three distinct substantial Persons
must have three distinct personal Substances: For this
is the direct contradiction to the <hi>Sabellian</hi> Heresie of
one Substance; If the <hi>Arians</hi> deny'd one Substance,
not in the <hi>Sabellian</hi> Notion of One Substance, but
as one Substance signifies perfectly the same Divine
Nature in Father and Son, then <hi>One Substance,</hi> as it
is asserted by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, in opposition to
the <hi>Arians,</hi> must signifie not one personal Substance,
but One Divine Nature, which is perfectly alike,
and the same in Father and Son. I challenge any
Man living (always excepting the Wonder-working
Animadverter) to shew me any Medium between the
One Substance, or the One Person, of <hi>Sabellius,</hi>
and the Three Substances of different Natures and
Species of the <hi>Arians,</hi> but only the true Catholick
Faith, of Three substantial Persons, or Three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal
Substances, of one and the same Nature, both
for kind, and by Generation and Procession.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:52275:19"/>
The reason of the thing is plain and evident,
which is the most I intend at present; for I shall
reserve Authorities, as I intimated before, for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
Treatise, which, if God permit, shall soon
follow this; and therefore St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> and the <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrian</hi>
Synod, under the great <hi>Athanasius,</hi> after the
Catholick Bishops were recall'd from Banishment, and
restor'd to their Sees by <hi>Julian the Apostate,</hi> shall
serve now.</p>
            <p>The Dispute is concerning <hi>One Substance, and
Three Substances,</hi> in the Deity; and it may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd
into these three Questions. 1. Whether the
Son, as begotten of his Father, have a Substance and
Nature proper to his own Person, which is not the
Personal Nature and Substance of the Father. 2. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Three such Persons, who have, each of them,
a pesonal Nature and Substance of his own, may
be call'd Three Substance. 3. In what sence then
they are one Substance? Whoever reads <hi>St. Hilary
de Syn. adv. Arianos,</hi> will find all these Questions
fully and expresly resolv'd, I shall give but some
few Instances of each.</p>
            <p>As for the first, he tells us,<note n="*" place="margin">Quod vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta in patre hic intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligitur sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantia sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificata; vita quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in Unige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nito, quae ex patre generata est èssentia intellecta—quod enim in utro<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vita est, id in utro<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> significatur essentia &amp; vita quae generatur ex vita, id est, essentia quae de essentia nascitur—natae &amp; gignentis essentiae, id est, vitae quae habetur &amp; data est.—</note> that <hi>Life in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
is Substance, and Life in the Son which is begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
of the Father, is Essence or Substance; and that
Life begotten of Life, is Essence born of Essence;
and owns this as a universal Maxim, which holds
true in all Births: That that which is born receives
a Nature of its own from the Nature,<note n="†" place="margin">Quia omnis nativitas quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> est, in naturam suam ex naturâ gignente consistit.</note> which begets,
and subsists in its own Nature;<note n="‖" place="margin">Ex natura enim generante naturam sumpsit genita natura.</note> that the begotten
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52275:20"/>
Nature receives its Nature from the Nature, which
begets: And giving an Account why Wisdom says
<note n="*" place="margin">sed quia Dei filius non cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralis partitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis est ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplo, sed ex perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto Deo perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, Deus natus est, idcir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co ait cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atam se esse sapientia; omnes in generatione sua corporales passiones excludens; at verò ut ostenderet, non creationis in se, sed nativitatis naturam esse, subjecit &amp; geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, ut cùm creatam se &amp; genitam confitetur, absolutam nativitatis suae intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam praestaret, dum indemutabilem patris naturam in creatione significat, &amp; legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam &amp; propriam ex Deo patre genitae suae naturae ostendit esse substantiam.</note>that she was both created and begotten: The first
he tells us, is to exclude all corporeal Passions from
the Divine Generation; that the Nature of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
suffers no change or diminution in the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
of the Son, no more than in the Works of
Creation; and by being begotten is signified, that
the Son receives his Nature not by Creation, but
by Birth; and has a legitimate and proper Substance
of his own begotten Nature from God the Father.</p>
            <p>Once more; In one of these Oriental Creeds,
they anathematize those who make the<note n="*" place="margin">Et siquis intempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralem uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geni<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i filii de patre substanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, ad innascibilem Dei essentiam referat, quasi filium patrem dicens, anathema sit.</note> Eternal
Substance of the only begotten Son of the Father to
be the unbegotten Substance of God, thereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
the Son to be the Father.</p>
            <p>This St. <hi>Hilary</hi> explains and approves, and acquaints
us with the<note n="†" place="margin">Dedisse superior definicio occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem haereti<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is videbatur, cùm tempus nativitatis filii negaretur, quia nef<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s esset si pater esset in tempore: in tempore autem esset, si filius tempori subdere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: ut per hanc opportunitatem temporis abnegati, sub filii nuncupatione pater, qui innascibilis esset, singularis at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> unicus, ipse sibi &amp; pater &amp; filius praedicaretur, quia ubi nascendi tempus excluditur, illic opinio videtur innascibilitatis admitti, ut natus non putetur, cujus nativitas non sit in tempore. Idcirco ne per hanc occasionem tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris abnegati haeresis unionis irreperet, &amp; haec impietas damnatur, quae audeat intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralem nativitatem ad unicam &amp; singularem innascibilis essentiae referre substantiam, cùm aliud sit intemporalem esse; aliud sit esse non natum; quorum unum habeat (licet extra tempus) nativitatem, aliud ipsum sibi, ad id quod est, solus at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> idem Autor aternus sit.</note> Occasion of this Decree, <hi>viz.</hi> The
Catholicks asserting the eternal Generation of the Son,
that he was begotten before all Time, and in no
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52275:20"/>
Time; some Hereticks took advantage of this, to
deny that there is any begotten Substance of the Son,
but only the unbegotten Substance of the Father,
and that under the denomination of the Son, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
who is undegotten, and but one singular
Person, is both Father and Son to himself: For
to be born in no time seems to signifie, not to be
born at all: this he calls <hi>The Heresie of Vnion,</hi>
or Sabellianism, which this Decree condemns, whereas,
as he adds, to be eternal, without any temporal begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
and to be unbegotten, are two very different
things; that which is eternal may be begotten, tho' not
in time; but that which is unbegotten, is the sole eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
Author of its own being, and all that he is.</p>
            <p>This I think is home to the purpose, to deny that the
Son has a begotten Substance, proper and peculiar to
himself as a Son; or to say, that the Son has no other
Substance but the unbegotten Substance of the Father,
is Sabellianism; and which ought farther to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
to say, that the Father and Son have not a distinct
Substance of their own, but that the unbegotten Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
of the Father is the Substance of the Son,
makes Father and Son but one Person: which shews
that these Fathers and St. <hi>Hilary</hi> never dreamt of
three Persons in one singular Substance. Now if the
three Persons in the Trinity are really distinct in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
and it is Heresy to say, that the unbegotten
Substance of the Father is the Substance of the Son,
any man would wonder, what Haeresie it should be
to say, that there are three distinct personal Substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
in the Trinity.</p>
            <p>But to put this Matter out of doubt, St. <hi>Hilary</hi> in
the next place expresly vindicates the Synod of<note n="*" place="margin">His<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nominibus (patris, &amp; filii, &amp; spiritus sancti) non simpliciter, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> otiosis propositis, sed signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantibus diligenter propriam uniuscujus<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nominatorum substantiam &amp; ordinem &amp; gloriam, ut sint quidem per substantiam tria—</note> 
               <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:52275:21"/>
for attributing a proper Substance to each Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
Person, and affirming, that they are Three
in Substance, which he renders by <hi>Three Substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi>
whereby he says, they did not mean Three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse
Substances of different Kinds and Natures, but
Three Substances, in opposition to the <hi>Sabellian</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie;
which reviv'd again after the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council,<note place="margin">Volens igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregata sanctorum synodus impieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem eam perimere, quae veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris, &amp; Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lii, &amp; Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti, nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num numero eluderet, ut non subsistente causa uniuscujus<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nominis, triplex nuncupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio obtinerer sub falsitate nominum unionem—Idcirco tres substantias esse dixeruntꝰ subsistentium personas per substantias edocentes, non substantiam Patris, &amp; Filii, &amp; Spiritus sancti diversitate dissimilis essentiae separantes.</note>
and gave these three Names to the Father, and by
a Trinity of meer Names, without a subsisting
Cause or Subject for each Name, destroyed the truth
and reality of Father, Son, and Holy Ghost; and
therefore they said, there were Three Substances,
thereby meaning three subsisting Persons; not divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
and separating the Substance of the Father, the
Son, and the Holy Ghost, by a diversity and dissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude
of Essences.</p>
            <p>So that St. <hi>Hilary</hi> thought, that Three Substances,
when they are not used in an <hi>Arian</hi> sense, to fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
a diversity of Nature, but only to signifie
Three substantial subsisting Persons, in opposition to
<hi>Sabellius,</hi> are very Catholick Words, and contain a
true Catholick sense: in this sense, and for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
same reason we use these Expressions of Three
distinct infinite Minds, and Three Substances: And
I hope these Heads will not take it amiss, if One
St. <hi>Hilary</hi> have more Authority with me than all
they together.</p>
            <p>3. As for <hi>One Substance,</hi> which was taught by the
<hi>Nicene</hi> Council, and inserted into their Creed, St.
<hi>Hilary</hi> very plainly and frequently tells us, in what
sense we are to understand it: that there is one Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52275:21"/>
of the same Kind and Nature, <hi>in genere na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,
&amp; secundum proprietatem naturae;</hi> not one Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
as that signifies one subsisting Person; but
as it signifies perfectly the same Nature, in every
thing alike, without the least difference or varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
that the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Idcirco autem u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiae, non utunus sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistat aut solus, sed ut ex substantiâ Dei natus, non aliunde subsistat, neve in aliquâ dissidentis substantiae diversitate subsistat.</p>
                  <p>Aut aliud hic testatur homousion, quàm ut una &amp; indissimilis duum sit secundum naturae propaginem essentia, quia essentia filii non sit aliunde; quae quia aliunde non est, unius recte esse ambo creduntur essentiae, quia substantiam nativitatis filius non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat, nisi de paternae autoritate naturae. Credamus &amp; dicamus esse unam substantiam, sed per naturae proprietatem, non ad significationem impiae unionis; una sit ex similitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, non ex solitudine.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Homoousion</hi> signifies one Nature per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
alike, and the same by Natural Propagation;
because the Essence of the Son is from no other
Cause, but the Essence of the Father; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
Father and Son may both be said to be of one
Nature or Substance.</p>
            <p>And for the sake of the Charge of <hi>Tritheism,</hi> which
the Anim adverter makes such a Noise with, it will be
necessary to observe, that St. <hi>Hilary</hi> gives the same ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
of the Unity of the Godhead, as he does of the
Unity of the Divine Substance aud indeed they must
be one in the same sense, for one divine Substance is
one God.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matizat nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eos, qui tres Deos di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt, quia secundum naturae veritatem, numerum nuncupationum substantia ista non recipit, nisi ut in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus &amp; Angelis solet—caeterùm in natura Dei Deus unus est, ita tamen ut &amp; filius Deus sit, quia in eo natura non differens sit; &amp; cùm Deus ex Deo sit, non potest non uter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Deus esse, quorum per generis differentiam non discernatur essentia. Numerus autem nominis in nuncupatione respuitur, quia non est in naturae qualitate diversitas, cùm igitur Anathema sit duos deos dicens, &amp; anathema sit filium Deum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negans, absolute ostenditur unius ad uttum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nominis unitatem de proprietate in differentis esse substantiae.</note> The <hi>Sardican</hi> Synod anathematiz'd those who
said there were Three Gods: And St. <hi>Hilary</hi> gives
this account of it, that speaking properly, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
Substance or Nature will not admit of the
plural Number, to say, that there are more Gods
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52275:22"/>
than One, excepting when, the Title of God is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
to Men or Angels, by way of Honour, not of
Nature: But in the Nature of God, there is but
One God; yet so that the Son is God, because he
has the same Nature, without any unlikeness or dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,
with his Father; and when there is God of
God, it cannot be but that each of them must be
God, because their Nature is not distinguish'd by
a different Kind or Species; and when he is anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiz'd,
who says there are two Gods, and he also
is anathematiz'd who denies the Son to be God, it
is manifest that the same Name of God, and One
God, is apply'd to both of them, upon account of
the same Nature, without the least difference or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Tamen ne rursum unius Dei praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam ac si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie suâ so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarii Dei velit affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiam, statim eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am hanc condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem, quae quia Deus unus est, unum ac solitarium Deum patrem, habentem in se nomen patris &amp; filii confitetur. Cum in generante parre &amp; nascente filio, Deus unus esset ob indifferentis ab invicem naturae substantiam praedicandus.</p>
                  <p>Cùm in damnatione sit, patrem &amp; filium duos Deos dicere, &amp; rursum anathema sit, filium Deum negare, substantiae diversae alterius ab alterâ opinio in praedicandis Diis duobus excluditur, non enim est alia praeter illam Dei patris, ex qua Dei filius Deus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporalis est natus, essentia.</p>
                  <p>Non enim religiosa unitas nominis ex indifferentis naturae essentia constituta perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam genitae ademit essentiae, ut unica ac singularis Dei essentia per unionem nominis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligatur: cùm utrius<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> essentiae nomen unum; id est, Deus unus, ob indiscretae in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> naturae indissimilem substantiam praedicetur.</p>
               </note>
And adds, that least the Doctrine of One
God should seem to teach that there is but one sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
Subsistance of one solitary God without his
Son; The same Synod condemns those also, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
pretence of owning but One God, profess only
One singular and solitary God the Father, under
the Name of Father and Son; whereas the Father
who begets, and the Son who is born, are to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd
One God, upon account of the same
Nature in both, without the least difference or vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:52275:22"/>
Were it not to shorten this Discourse, I could easily fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish
my Readers with Numerous Quotations to the same
purpose, out of St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> (to whom I now confine my
self, and particularly to his Book <hi>de Synodis,</hi> that these Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities
may be the more easily found all together) to
prove, That the Catholick Notion of One Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
and One God, does not signify One Personal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
nor One singular solitary God, who is but One Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son;
but there is One Divine Substance, and One God, as
the same Divine Nature is communicated whole and entire
by the Father to the Son, and by Father and Son to the Holy
Spirit, without the least difference, or change, or separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
Which I shall explain more at large elsewhere.</p>
            <p>Thus much for St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> who has always been allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
a Credible Witness of the Catholick Faith; for which
he suffered Banishment under <hi>Constantius,</hi> and is now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
for a Heretick by the <hi>Oxford</hi> Heads.</p>
            <p>But it is more wonderful to me, that men who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand
what <hi>Hypostasis</hi> signifies, and in what sense it
was used by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, should condemn the
Phrase of <hi>Three Substances</hi> in the Trinity, as False, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious,
and Heretical, when <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Three Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postases,
which is the Catholick Language, is neither bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
nor worse than Three Substances. In the <hi>Nicene</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil
it self, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are used in the same sense, and
both signify Substance: And <hi>Petavius</hi> owns, that all the
Ancient Fathers used <hi>Hypostasis</hi> in no other sense, but to
signify Substance; and then Three <hi>Hypostases</hi> are <hi>Three
Substances.</hi> And when afterwards they more nicely distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished
between <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they still used <hi>Hypostasis</hi>
in the notion of Substance, that which did actually sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist;
which is therefore often rendred by the <hi>Latins
extantia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to set aside other Observations, the <hi>Alexandrian</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:52275:23"/>
Synod under <hi>Athanasius</hi> is sufficient to put an end to this
Dispute.<note place="margin">Athanasii Ep ad An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochenses T. 1. p. 574 Et Concil. T. 2 p. 810.</note> When the Catholick Bishops were recalled
from Banishment by <hi>Julian,</hi> several of them stopt at
<hi>Alexandria,</hi> and met in Council to advise about the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
state of the Church: Among other things that fell
under consideration, there had a Dispute happened among
the Catholicks themselves, concerning the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whether they ought to say, That there
is but One Substance in the Trinity; or, That there are
Three Substances; for so it is plain that both sides under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood
<hi>Hypostasis</hi> in the notion of Substance. To compose
this Difference, the Synod called both Parties before them,
and examined them in what sense they used these words.</p>
            <p>As for those who said there were Three <hi>Hypostases</hi> in
the Trinity, they asked them, Whether by this they
meant, as the <hi>Arians</hi> did, Three <hi>Hypostases</hi> of a different
Kind and Nature, subsisting by themselves absolutely and
independently, as perfectly divided and separated from
each other, as other Creatures, and as the Children of
men are; or as those things which have different Natures,
as Gold, and Silver, and Brass? Or whether by Three
<hi>Hypostases</hi> they meant, as some other Hereticks did,
Three Principles, or Three Gods? All this they professed
they had neither said nor thought. And being asked
again, Why they then used those Expressions of Three
Substances? They answered, Because they believed in the
Holy Trinity, not a Trinity of Names, but a Real Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting
Trinity; a Father, who really and actually is, and
subsists; a Son, who in truth and reality is a substantial
subsisting Son; and the Holy Spirit, who actually is, and
subsists: That they never said, There are Three Gods, or
Three Principles, but owned the Holy Trinity, and but one
Godhead, one Principle, and the Son consubstantial to the
Father; and the Holy Spirit neither a Creature, nor of a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52275:23"/>
different Nature, but genuinely and inseparably of the
same Nature with Father and Son. All this was appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
of as very Orthodox. And then the Synod examined
those who affirmed, That there was but One Substance in
the Trinity, What they meant by it? Whether they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood
it, as <hi>Sabellius</hi> did, to deny the Real Subsistence
of the Son and Holy Spirit, to make an Unsubstantial
Son, and an Unsubsisting Spirit? This they also denied;
and told the Synod, that they thought <hi>Hypostasis</hi> signified
the same with <hi>Ousia,</hi> Essence, Substance, Nature: And
therefore they owned but one <hi>Hypostasis</hi> or Substance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
the Son is of the Substance of the Father, and by
reason of the Identity of Nature between Father and Son;
for they believed but One Divinity, and one Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
and not one Nature of the Father, and another dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
Nature of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. This
Explication also was approved by the Synod; and thus
this matter was reconciled: Those who taught Three
Substances in the Trinity, and those who believed but
one Substance, when they had given their several Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications,
were both owned by the Synod, and
owned each other for Catholick Christians, and both
Condemned <hi>Arius</hi> and <hi>Sabellius;</hi> though the Synod thought
it better to adhere strictly to the words of the <hi>Nicene</hi>
Creed; but soon after they distinguished between <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and then Three <hi>Hypostases</hi> (still in the notion
of Three Substances) and One Nature, was the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Language; which St. <hi>Basil</hi> gives a large account of,
<hi>Ep.</hi> 300. of which more elsewhere. So that <hi>Athanasius,</hi>
and those Glorious Confessors for the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith, in
the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> Synod, owned Three Substances in the
very same sense in which we now use those words, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
the true Catholick Faith; and if they knew what
the Doctrine of the Catholick Church was, our <hi>Oxford</hi>
Heads are out in their guess.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:52275:24"/>
5. The last Charge is, That <hi>Three distinct Minas and
Substances</hi> is <hi>especially contrary to the Doctrine of the Church
of</hi> England, <hi>publickly received.</hi> What they may mean
by <hi>publickly received,</hi> I can't tell; there may be some Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
too publickly received in the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
which are not the Doctrines of the Church; and I doubt
<hi>Sabellianism</hi> is one of them: But if they mean by <hi>publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
received,</hi> the Doctrine of our Articles and Creeds; this
is the very same with the Doctrine of the Catholick
Church. We make profession of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith every
Week, and that asserts a Real and Substantial Trinity, if
<hi>Athanasius</hi> understood it.</p>
            <p>The only pretence, I can guess, they had for this
charge, if they thought of any themselves, must be the
Form of the <hi>Athanasian</hi> Creed, which will not permit us
to say that in the Plural Number of all Three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
which it allows us to attribute distinctly to each di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct
Person in the Singular Number; we may say, the
Father is Almighty, the Son Almighty, and the Holy Ghost
Almighty, but must not say that there are three Almighties,
but one Almighty. But will they hence frame an Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal
Rule, That nothing must be said of the Holy Trinity
in the Plural Number, considered as Three? We will not
attribute any thing to the Holy Trinity in the Plural Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
which this Creed forbids; we will not say, there
are Three Almighties, Three Eternals, Three Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents,
Three Infinites, Three Gods, or Three Lords; but
this Creed does not forbid us saying, There are Three
Minds, or Three Substances; nay, it teaches us to say,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which as you have already heard, in the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Age, and more expresly in After Ages, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
Three Substances, and therefore must do so in this
Creed.</p>
            <p>The reason given in the Creed against this Plural Praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52275:24"/>
is, Because there is but One God, and therefore such
terms, as immediately and directly multiply the Deity
and Godhead, must not be exprest Plurally; and thus the
Plural Praedication of any Divine Perfections in the abstract
does; Three Omnipotents, Three Infinites, Three Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals,
which are Equivalent to Three Omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,
Three Infinities, Three Eternities; and they to
Three Deities, and Three Godheads, or Three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
Natures; but though we cannot distinguish be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the Person, and the Divinity, or Divine Nature of
that Person, for there is no Composition in God, or in a Divine
Person, as there is in Creatures; yet when the same Divine
Nature, communicated from the Father to the Son, and from
Father and Son to the Holy Spirit, subsists distinctly, tho in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>separably
whole and entire in Three; and that which really
and actually subsists, is Mind and Substance, with respect
to these Three Subsistencies, they are and must be Three
Minds and Substances, though with respect to the same<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
and identity of the Divine Nature, which is Whole, and
Entire and Inseparable, and therefore but One in all, they
are but One, not Three Gods.</p>
            <p>This is all the sense I can make of that known distinction
between Substantives and Adjectives in a Plural Praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
That we may say, there are Three who Create, but
not Three Creators; Three, who are Omnipotent, but not
three Omnipotents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that in these Adjective Praedications,
we consider the Divine Person, Mind or Substance, as a sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ject
of Jahaesion, and these Divine Perfections as Essential
Properties or Attributes, which may and must be numbred
with the Subjects in which they are; but Substantives have
a more absolute sense, and include pure nature, without
relation to different Subjects; and therefore to use them
Plurally, is to multiply Nature, to make more than One In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite,
Eternal, Incomprehensible, Omnipotent Nature,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52275:25"/>
and consequently to multiply Gods. But from this very
distinction we learn, that there are Three Suppositums or
Subjects (and then they will easily be owned to be Three
Minds and Substances) to which all the Perfections of the
Deity belong; for when these Divine Perfections are Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated
Adjectively, they must suppose a Subject to which
they belong; and they being such Perfections as can be
only in a Mind, they must suppose Three distinct Minds
to which they belong.</p>
            <p>Thus I have considered, with all possible brevity, every
particular of this Charge; and if these Decreeing and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resy-making
Heads will be just to me, they must own,
that as they and the Animadverter had ordered the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
it was impossible for me to do otherwise, unless I
would have been trampled on by every Scribler: This is a
good human reason; but I had a better reason for this than
any thing meerly Personal: They have condemned the
true Catholick Faith, even the <hi>Nicene Faith,</hi> which is <hi>the
Faith of the Church of</hi> England, for Herefy, and they have
exposed this Faith to the Scorn and Triumph of the <hi>Socinian</hi>
Hereticks, who already make their boast, That they have a
Decree against the real <hi>Trinit arians;</hi> and they only want ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
against the Nominal ones, and then their work is done to
their hands; tho I think, they have Decrees enow against
them; even all the Fathers and Councils which condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<hi>Sabellius,</hi> condemned them, and if all this be not enough,
the common Sense of Mankind, of which every Plowman is a
judge, condemns them: For Three Persons, who are not
Three distinct Minds and Substances, is not greater Herefy,
than it is Nonsense.</p>
            <p>In short, we have had these Gentlemen's Decree; and
now we expect their Reasons, which it had been much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
they had thought of first, and then we should have
escaped their Decree.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
