<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Honourable House of Commons, now assembled in Parliament the humble remonstrance of Iohn Smith, in behalf of the inhabitants of Margate.</title>
            <author>Smith, John, of Sandwich, draper.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3398</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12083595</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12083595</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53669</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A60490)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53669)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 580:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the Honourable House of Commons, now assembled in Parliament the humble remonstrance of Iohn Smith, in behalf of the inhabitants of Margate.</title>
                  <author>Smith, John, of Sandwich, draper.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Smith of Sandwich by Wing.</note>
                  <note>"A letter written by Iohn Smith, expenditor of sea works of the town of Margate, to the Right Honourable, the Earl of Warwick" on p. 1.</note>
                  <note>"The copy of a certificate from the mayor and jurats of the town of Dover" p. 6.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Margate (England) --  History --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53669:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>TO THE Honourable House of COMMONS, Now assembled in Parliament: <hi>The humble Remonstrance of</hi> Iohn Smith, <hi>in behalf of the Inhabitants of</hi> MARGATE.</head>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter written by <hi>Iohn Smith,</hi> Expenditor of Sea-works of the Town of <hi>Margate: To the Right Honourable, the Earl of WARWICK.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>KNowing your judgement, skill and experience to be great in Maritine affairs, and your Power and Place enabling to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse this our condition and heavy grievances, being a busines of that concernment, as the neglect there of may be of dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence to the whole Isle of <hi>Thanet,</hi> but surely, if not speedily provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, will bring suddenly an unavoydable destruction upon our town of <hi>Margate</hi> through want of timely repair of the Jettee works, the Sea there having of late done no little harm. I am the more bold to give you a short relation of our present state and condition, and what hath been formerly done touching the same, hoping your Lordship will not suffer us any longer to be wearied and wasted with a long and chargeable attendance, and we thereby be subjected to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent and sudden ruine; but you will afford us your assistance for the saving of us and our poor town: Be pleased to know, that above thirty years ago, sundry houses in <hi>Margate</hi> were taken away by the rage and outbreakings of the sea; whereupon the Inhabitants did sue to the Lord Warden of the Commissioners of Sewers, to have the town for the future secured against such outbreakings, and for that end
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53669:2"/>
desired fifteen able Yeomen of the country to take a view of the town, which was done accordingly, and thereupon all those houses &amp; lands which were in danger of the sea, were taxed and scotted for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and maintaining the works against the sea, which works upon the setting up cost near 2000. l. and these scots and assesments were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and paid for twenty five years, and thereby through the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of God much good hath come to the town &amp; whole Island there, there having not been any losse either of houses or lands, while the scot was continued.</p>
            <p>In the year 1641. I was made Expenditor of the works there, by the Commissioners of the Sewers, allowing me a scot of two shillings in the pound, of such houses and lands as were formerly scotted, and in danger of the sea, for the maintenance and reparation of the works, and 36. l. taxed, and to be levied out of the Peer, as appeares by the Scot. But upon my suit to the Chmmissioners, in respect I could not so well attend the same, as another, without neglecting my calling; Another was appointed, viz. one <hi>Iames Heniker,</hi> but he refused to take that office upon him, saying the same would undo him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I was constrained to continue still Expenditor: But upon my demanding a scot for the next year (for it was the custome to have one every year) for repairing the Sea works; some particular men moved the commissioners to have the scot given over, and that every man might defend himself against the sea: but I told the commissioners, that could not be, without laying the whole burthen upon a few for all, for thereby what any did for his own safety and defence, would be done and serve for others, which would prove the undoing of them that so did it, and yet not be able to keep up the works.</p>
            <p>Upon these differences, the Commissioners did wholly reject the said works, the best and greatest part whereof, having had no repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and maintenance, by violent rage of the sea hath been taken away since, as also many houses there and highwayes, by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breakings of the sea thrown down and carried away, to the undoing of many the inhabitants. VVherefore I; being Expenditor, for the prevention of the losse of the town, borrowed 200. l. for which I yet pay use, for defending a small part of that place, having for these four years last, spent more to defend my self and the town against the sea, than all the rents and profits of lands and houses will amount unto, and yet still subject and in danger to lose the whole, for neglect and want
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53669:2"/>
of a fuller reparation; so as if I be not speedily relieved herein, I shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be utterly undone thereby, besides the losse of the town, and endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering the whole Island, making way for our enemies entry there. Neverthelesse all this time have I had my Rents sessed to all assesments and taxes to the full, which <hi>I</hi> have paid, besides my free and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary contributions in the beginning of the warres, even beyond and above my ability: With the first <hi>I</hi> sent in all my Plate, being above 20. l. and upwards: Afterward, when my Lord of <hi>Warwick</hi> came to <hi>Sandwich</hi> he being set in the Town-hall with the Major and Brethren, and called the Townsmen before him, to the end to see and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand how willing the Townsmen were to subscribe for men and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; when the best and ablest man there did not subscribe for above five men, and yet most of the subscribers did not send in their monies, being forty shillings for every man; Notwithstanding, <hi>I</hi> did subscribe for six men, and according to my undertaking sent twelve pounds by a safe messenger of my own charge: but in regard the greater part of the subscribers did not send in their monies according to their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, my mony was returned back unto me, with which <hi>I</hi> bought a very good Gelding for the State, being the first man that bought any horse for the publike service there: seven moneths <hi>I</hi> kept this horse upon my own charge, which cost me five shillings a week at the least: when the Troop was made up, <hi>I</hi> furnished the Rider, of my own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per charge, with pistols, saddle, and all other furniture fitting, and likewise provided and gave the Rider sword, boots and spurs, with mony in his purse for his further incouragement, at which my doings some with us were not a little displeased; neither was <hi>I</hi> afterwards backward upon any occasion offered, to expresse my willingnes and readines to advance the service of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>But the eminent danger we were daily subject unto by reason of the outbreakings of the sea, the greatest and best part of the Jettee works being taken away; The which for want of due reparations, in <hi>January</hi> last I came up with a Petition subscribed near with three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score hands, thereby desiring an Order from the Parliament for some Tymber out of some Delinquents lands, to make up the sea-works, and to have the accustomed Scot continued for the preservation of the Town of <hi>Margate,</hi> which Petition, upon reading, was very well approved of, though I had attended five weeks before I could have the same read, but at length with much sollicitation I obtained the same;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53669:3"/>
And your Lordship, upon reading thereof, declared, how you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived 200 Tuns of Tymber would be too little for the work: and thereupon your Lordship, with the rest of the Committee, gave order to view the sea-works at <hi>Margate,</hi> but before I could procure the Gentlemen appointed to meet to view the same, I was put to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove twenty severall journies, to my no little travell and charge.</p>
            <p>The Gentlemen appointed for that purpose, promising to come to <hi>Margate,</hi> I provided a dinner of my own charge for them, but two only came, who told me they could do nothing of themselves without another: Thereupon I intreated them, though they wanted one of their number, they would give way to some Workmen to measure the works, whereupon workmen were sent for, so I procured three Carpenters, who measured 55 rods of work, which they cast up, and they conceived every rod of work would take up five tun and a half of tymber for single work, and double work would ask as much more; It was two moneths before <hi>I</hi> could get them together, after <hi>I</hi> was forced to make severall journies to <hi>Dover-</hi>castle to procure Major <hi>Boys</hi> Governour thereof to <hi>Margate,</hi> and going often thither for that purpose, <hi>I</hi> hapned to meet with Sir <hi>Henry Heyman</hi> a Parliament man, with whom I made bold to lay open our grievance to him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he was perswaded to go to <hi>Margate</hi> with me, and at my request he desired and gained Major <hi>Bois</hi> to go with him: Vpon view of the works, they found the same was gone to ruine, and that the Peer of <hi>Margate</hi> was the cause of the destruction of a great part of the Town, and this Peere was accustomed to pay scot to the said works, but for these four years and upwards hath not paid one penny, yet some particular men make a benefit of the Peer mony, which can be proved by very able witnesse.</p>
            <p>Our humble desire is, That there might be an account given every year to some Justices of the Peace there, the respective Mayors of <hi>Sandwich</hi> and <hi>Dover</hi> for the time being, and some of the Townsmen of <hi>Margate</hi> to be joyned with them for passing the accounts, and the one half of the profits of the overplus upon their accounts may be allowed for the maintaining the said works; and whereas our Scots were 2 s. the pound, we are willing for the ease of the town to take 12. d. the pound, and 1. d. the pound for goods shipt and unshipt, and 2. d. for every chaldron of coals from the buyer, and some other things mentioned for the ease of the houses and lands which are in danger as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53669:3"/>
aforesaid. And seeing the making up of the works will be a great charge, and if not timely done, will endanger the town; We desire to have Tymber from <hi>Hide,</hi> the Mayor there certifying that he hath wood will serve for that purpose (if order be given for the same) to the value of 100 Tun and upwards: And likewise if we may have Briefs granted for the free and voluntary collections of the well-affected in the Island and other adjacent Counties, it will much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the furtherance of the works, and ease of the Townsmen of <hi>Margate,</hi> for otherwise we shall not be able (without wronging the arrears of the scots, which will lie heavy upon the inhabitants) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the works, and to raise the 200. l. for which <hi>I</hi> am engaged, and crave allowance of. This done; And if <hi>I</hi> may have secured the Scots for hereafter at 12. d. the pound, and have the profits of the overplus of the Peer, and poundage of other goods shipt and unshipt, as in a schedule is set forth: <hi>I</hi> will engage my whole estate, both lands and houses in <hi>Margate</hi> which is worth near 1000. l. for upholding the sea-works there for ever; which not any man <hi>(I</hi> believe) in all <hi>Margate,</hi> nor in the whole Island will undertake to do.</p>
            <p>My Lord, <hi>I</hi> pray you consider of our present state and sad condition, <hi>I</hi> have been the larger in the relation thereof, for that <hi>I</hi> would have your Lordship not only informed of the truth thereof, and the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger we lie continually under, but likewise to let you see what trouble and charge <hi>I</hi> have been at, and how wearied and discouraged with at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, often waiting on your Honour and the Committee, with Councel; but hitherto all <hi>I</hi> could do, ineffectuall, my travel lost, and the fees and monies given my Councel, hath served to no purpose. By which doings and slow proceedings (if your Lordship afford not help) I shall be utterly disabled further to prosecute this good work, and every well affected will be discouraged either to ingage or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the same for the future; and what mischief may ensue thereupon, and how Malignants and disaffected will be imboldned who have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed us herein, I leave to your Lordships consideration. When Major <hi>Boys</hi> gave me his warrant for 24 Tuns of tymber, which came to 36. l. being the arreare for one yeare due by the Peere of <hi>Margate,</hi> the same was slighted: when afterwards your Honour issued another warrant to the same purpose (you being then at <hi>Wamouth</hi> castle) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the Majors warrant, the same was likewise disregarded and disobeyed by the Peer wardens of <hi>Margate,</hi> who would neither give
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53669:4"/>
us the tymber, nor mony in lieu thereof, but disposed the same as they thought good themselves, some to their private use, and selling some for signe posts, yea though we would have given them ready mony of our own for it, we could not have it, such is the malignancy and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection of these to this good and publike work. All which I hope your Honour will see timely remedied and redressed, and will not suffer us to be longer exposed to contempt, and such apparent destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, nor further wearied and wasted with a long and fruitlesse at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance. Therefore my humble request unto your Lordship and the rest of the honourable Committee of the Admiralty, is, That you will be pleased to give your order and present direction for what you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, and conceive fit to be done touching the whole busines: And thereby I, and many more shall have cause to blesse God for you, and shall ever be ready upon all occasions to expresse my thankfulnesse, and approve my self to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships in all respective obedience JOHN SMITH.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July 14. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="certificate">
            <head>The copy of a Certificate from the Mayor and Jurats of the Town of <hi>Dover.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO all Christian people to whom these Presents shall come: JOHN GOLDER Gent. Mayor of the Town and Port of <hi>Dover</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and the JURATS of the same, send greeting in our Lord God everlasting.</p>
            <p>Forasmuch as we hold it the office of Magistrates, and the duty of all other persons, to certifie and declare the truth, in all matters and things doubtfull or sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious, whereby wrongs and injuries may be avoyded, and truth take place and be manifested, especially being thereunto requested: Know ye therefore, that a great part of the Village of <hi>Margate</hi> in the Isle of <hi>Thanet</hi> in the said County, a Limb of this Town and Port, is in danger to be overflowed and ruined by the Sea, (the Works and Jetties about 25 years past made at the great charge of the then Inhabitants there by Scots granted and allowed by the then Commissioners of Sewers for those parts having been of late, for want of repaire, subverted and ruined by the rage and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Sea) and thereby divers houses overwhelmed, foot and horse-wayes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and other houses likely to be carried to sea, to the impoverishing of divers persons, and decay of the said Village, if some speedy course be not taken for the repaire and making of other Jetties there. In witnesse whereof, We the said Mayor and Iurats of the said Town and Port, the Seale of Office of Majorality of the same Town and Port have caused to be set and put, the four and twentieth day of <hi>December,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Exam. per me <hi>Fra. Raworth,</hi> Com. Cler. Vil &amp; Port Dover.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:53669:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN pursuance of your Lordships command, The Peere at Margate, and the defence made by the Works at the Shore for the defence of the Town have been sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed by Sir <hi>James Oxenden</hi> Knight, Major <hi>Boys</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Dover-castle, and <hi>Henry Crisp</hi> of <hi>Queeks</hi> 
               <abbr>Esq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>And we find,</p>
            <p>That about 25 or 26 years since, there was a peece of work added to the said Peer of <hi>Margate,</hi> which had proved very advantagious for the Peer, but desperately ruinous for part of the said Town.</p>
            <p>That before the making of the aforesaid new peece of Peerwork, it is not known to any man living that ever there was any work at the shore for the defence of any of the houses of <hi>Margate,</hi> or that there was any need of any such work; but since the making of that new peece of Peer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, there hath been as much Tymber-work set down by the Inhabitants at the shore for the defence of the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses there, as by credible relation hath cost them fifteen hundred pounds and upwards, the which is now wholly ruined by violence of the sea.</p>
            <p>Whereupon we conceive, that if the Peer be continued as now it is, the Town must suffer; and if the Peer do not continue as now it is, the Peer will quickly fail, and the Publique suffer for want of trade.</p>
            <p>The houses at <hi>Margate</hi> now in danger, are conceived to be near the fourth part of the Town, and will require fifty five rods of new work, which wil take up five tun and a half to every Rod of single work (by the judgement of the best experienced workmen) For which, they are hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble suitors to your Lordships.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Iames Oxenden,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Kt. Major</hi> Boys, <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                     </item>
                     <item>Henry Crisp, <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:53669:5"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I <hi>Humbly desire that You will be pleased to consider the great charges I have been at these four years, for the care of the Town of</hi> Margate, <hi>and that you will give me a speedy answer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>I was constrained to hyre 200. pounds, to keep up a small part of the Town for the preservation of it, paying interest for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>I have been eight moneths, since I got my Certificate from</hi> Dover, <hi>and three severall journies to</hi> London, <hi>and many jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies I made before I could get my Report; and long waiting with great charges, with Counsels and other expences, which hath cost me above six score pounds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>It is above an hundred pounds out of my way, by neglecting of my Calling, upon this businesse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>There is not one man in</hi> Margate <hi>alloweth me a penny to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my charges: I have waited these seven weeks in</hi> London <hi>with no little expenses; If I had set out twenty Light-horses on my own charge, it would not have put me more to misery: This publike busines hath cost me for my own self above 420. pounds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I desire your Honours that you will take some speedy course for Tymber and Monies, otherwise the Town will suddenly come to ruine. And that your Honours will be pleased to passe an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for continuing of the Scot, and for payment of the arreares due upon the same to the Expenditor</hi> John Smith, <hi>And that all such houses as are scotted towards the Sea, may be free from all other assesments. And that your Honours be pleased to send six Brasse peece of Ordnance, and Ammunition for the preservation of that part of the Kingdom in</hi> Margate, <hi>for it is a place of great concernment.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
