<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some considerations relating to the enlarging the Russia trade and the contract for importing tobacco into that countrey: humbly proposed by the contractors.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-03">2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4494B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218719</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830290</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830290</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34740</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A60783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34740)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2020:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some considerations relating to the enlarging the Russia trade and the contract for importing tobacco into that countrey: humbly proposed by the contractors.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tobacco --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  Russia --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34740:1"/>
            <head>SOME CONSIDERATIONS Relating to the Enlarging the RUSSIA TRADE, And the Contract for Importing <hi>Tobacco</hi> into that Countrey: Humbly Proposed by the Contractors.</head>
            <p>IT is observable, That Inquisitive and Disinterested <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Sir <hi>Ios. Child</hi>'s New Discourse on Trade; in the Preface, and also in <hi>Pag. 105.</hi> of the 2d. Edit. Printed 1694. As also a Discourse of Trade, Coyn and Paper Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. <hi>pag. 90.</hi> Printed 1697. supposed to be wrote by Mr. <hi>Polixfen;</hi> and the Discourse of the Publick Revenues and Trade of <hi>England,</hi> by the Author of the Essay of Ways, and Means. <hi>Part</hi> the 2d <hi>pag. 82.</hi> Printed 1698.</note> Persons, who have lately Publickly treated of Trade; have look'd upon the Trade of <hi>Russia</hi> as almost wholly lost to this Nation, either by ill Management or Negligence.</p>
            <p>Since therefore, the Observations of these Authors are also confirmed by our own Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience: It may be high time to find out some proper Methods to recover that Trade.</p>
            <p>It is an undoubted Truth, That Arts, Manufactures and Foreign Trades, make the greatest Improvement, where there are the greatest numbers of Hands and Stocks to carry them on, and where there are no Clogs or Barrs to Industry: Of this <hi>Holland</hi> is a sufficient instance; for tho' the <hi>English</hi> were the first Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverers of the <hi>Russia</hi> Trade, and had a Charter to incorporate them, and that confirm'd by an Act of Parliament, yet the <hi>Dutch</hi> without the advantage of any Company at all, but with a full liberty to every one to Trade to <hi>Rus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia</hi> have (with their numbers of Hands and largeness of Stock) drove the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> almost quite out of that Trade: They have encreased their Trade to Forty five and Fifty Ships, sent thither yearly; and we with our great Fines and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions have dwindled our Trade thither to Four or Five Ships yearly. They have for many Years (and do yet) engross all the most considerable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of <hi>Russia,</hi> as <hi>Masts, Pitch, Tarr, Pottashes, Deals</hi> and <hi>Firr Timber,</hi> and we (with our few Traders) drive no Trade at all in <hi>Masts, Pitch,</hi> and <hi>Tarr &amp;c.</hi> Nay, are often forced to buy our <hi>Pottashes</hi> at second hand from the <hi>Dutch.</hi> Surely, this consideration alone is of weight to make the entrance
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34740:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
into that Company as wide and easie as possible, that so by the encrease of Hands and Stock in that Trade, we may retrieve what we have lost for want of them, and what the <hi>Dutch</hi> by those very means only have gained from us.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Russia</hi> Company are at any Charge to support their Corporation, other Traders that come in, will help to bear it, and ease them: For sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose this Company do (one Year with another) expend 300 <hi>l.</hi> and trade for 20,000 <hi>l.</hi> Yearly, then the charge upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n the Trade would be 1½ <hi>per Cent?</hi> But if they admit others for a small Fine, the Trade will probably encrease to 200,000 <hi>l.</hi> (for the <hi>Tobacco</hi> Trade alone may be 150,000 <hi>l.</hi> of it) and then instead of paying 30 <hi>s.</hi> Impositions on every 100 <hi>l.</hi> according to the above supposition; they will not need to pay above 3 <hi>s.</hi> for 100 <hi>l.</hi> and this they must own will be a great ease to them: But the true reason why they so strenuously oppose the admission of others on easie terms, is this, That (as they are) they have but very few Traders, and those do so well understand one another, that they can manage that Trade, to as much advantage to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves as they please, without regard to the Publick good, but when others may Trade thither also, they cannot combine together, and tho' their Profits will be less, yet the Kingdoms will be greater by the encrease of our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portations; this is the only true Reason that makes them strive so hard for great Fines for Admissions, knowing that as that hath been, so it will always be an effectual means to keep Men out of their Company, few being willing to give a great Sum for liberty to drive a Trade they have not been acquainted with; and the Company have taken care to keep all Men but themselves as ignorant of the <hi>Russia</hi> Trade as possibly they could.</p>
            <p>It cannot well be imagined, that the whole necessary charge of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany can be above 300 <hi>l.</hi> a Year, for they seldom are at any expence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and here at home their charge is chiefly in Salaries to one another, and good Dinners; which charge they have raised yearly by Impositions on Goods Imported from <hi>Narve,</hi> which are mostly brought home by <hi>Eastland</hi> Merchants, and others not free of the <hi>Russian</hi> Company.</p>
            <p>A Liberty to Import <hi>Tobacco</hi> into <hi>Russia,</hi> hath been long wish'd for by all Men that understood and desired the wellfare of <hi>England,</hi> as knowing it would be better to us than Mines of Silver, by encreasing our Shipping and Seamen, and turning the Ballance of all Our Northern Trades in Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; that whereas we have hitherto been forced to send great Sums in Specie to pay for the Product of those Countries, over and above all our Exports: This would in a little time turn the Scales, and we should rather have Species from them, then send any thither.</p>
            <p>This so long wish'd for Liberty is now obtained at the expence of a great Sum by private Men, who are Strangers to the Trade of <hi>Russia,</hi> and have bought up several Parcels of <hi>Tobacco</hi> fit (as they are informed) for that Countrey, and they are ready to Export it thither, in case they may have Liberty to do it, and to run the hazard, whether they shall gain or lose by it; but they hope it will not be thought reasonable they should pay any great Fine, for their Admission into the Company, to drive a Trade of such great and certain Profit to the Kingdom,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34740:2"/>
and so doubtful and hazardous to themselves. For since they entred into the Contract with the <hi>Czar,</hi> for the Importing so great a quantity of <hi>Tobacco</hi> Year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into his Dominions, they have been mightily discouraged by the <hi>Russia</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, who alledge the Contractors have engaged in such an affair, as will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the greatest part of the Sum their Subscriptions amount to; and that if the <hi>Russia</hi> Company were concerned in it, they would chuse to lose One half, nay, Nine tenths of what they had Subscribed, rather than stand to the bargain. Such Discourses, with the other difficulties in the passing of the <hi>BILL,</hi> hath so discouraged the Subscriptions, that ever since those difficulties were made, there hath not been One penny Subscribed, tho the Roll hath lain open all the while, and there is not Subscribed one half so much, as may be employed in the <hi>Tobacco Trade.</hi> These are great discouragements from People who pretend to know so well the State and Nature of the Trade and People of <hi>Russia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It seems strange therefore, That the <hi>Russia</hi> Merchants should in their Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals demand a Fine of 500 <hi>l.</hi> and besides that, a certain Imposition of One <hi>per Cent.</hi> upon a Trade, that they are sure will be destructive to the Undertakers, tho they do acknowledge it will be very advantageous to the Nation.</p>
            <p>These Undertakers are willing upon their Admission into the Freedom of the Company, to bear their share of the Charge of the Company, by paying Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable Impositions to what other Traders pay; but to pay more, they think ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard for the Reasons mentioned above.</p>
            <p>How small soever the said Imposition of One <hi>per Cent.</hi> upon the Importation of Returns for Tobacco may seem, it will amount in Seven Years (the Term of the Patent) to above 10000 <hi>l.</hi> by a modest Computation; which Sum, as there will be no occasion for it to defray the necessary Charge of the Company; so it will discourage the Undertakers from proceeding on the Contract, while they see so little probability of advantage by it. Now to what end are the <hi>Russia</hi> Merchants so earnest for great Fines and Impositions, since they do not Trade in a Joynt-Stock, nor have Power to divide those Fines and Impositions among themseves? Certainly what they receive more than they spend, doth and must lie as a dead Stock by them, so that (as is observed before) their main Design by it, is to clog other Traders, and to keep Men out of their Company: For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the greater Trade is driven, the less need their Impositions be.</p>
            <p>Besides, as to their Act of Parliament, tho none of the King's Subjects can Trade to the Dominions of the Emperour of <hi>Russia</hi> without their Licence; yet is there not the least word therein-mentioned that gives them any Power to take Money, for such Licences.</p>
            <p>This Nation hath by this Grant from the <hi>Czar</hi> an opportunity to encrease its Stock 150,000 <hi>l.</hi> a Year (besides Employing some Thousands of the Poor in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacturing the <hi>Tobacco</hi>) and the World may think it strange if we hesitate or make difficulties about the embraceing and improving so advantageous an offer. And if we cannot make use of the Grant, we must part with it to those that will pay us for it: And the Nation may hereafter have time to repent the loss of so great a Jewel, which no Art nor Expence may be ever able to recover.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:34740:3"/>There is another National Advantage, That a great Trade to <hi>Russia</hi> would give us, and what the Dutch find by it, <hi>Viz.</hi> That all <hi>Naval Stores</hi> and other Commodities Imported from <hi>Russia,</hi> would be brought home in our own Shipping (the <hi>Russes</hi> having none) whereas all those <hi>Naval Stores</hi> from <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> and the Ports of the <hi>Baltick,</hi> are Imported chiefly in Shipping of those Countreys, which is a double Charge and loss to this Nation; besides the Dutch, by having an opportunity of being supplied with <hi>Masts, Deals, Hemp, Pitch</hi> and <hi>Tarr</hi> from <hi>Russia,</hi> need not depend on <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Denmark</hi> for them, and by that means can better keep those Two Princes in awe, with respect to Commerce, which we cannot do, having at this time our sole dependance on those Two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms for all our <hi>Naval Stores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, The Contractors for Importing <hi>Tobacco</hi> into <hi>Russia,</hi> are so far from engrossing to themselves any Profit, that may be thought will arise from that Grant, that they do yet keep open their Subscriptions for every one that hath a mind to be concerned with them therein, and they are willing rather wholly to lose that advantage they propose to themselves by the Contract, than that the Nation should be totally depriv'd of the <hi>Tobacco Trade.</hi> And therefore, in case they cannot be admitted into the entire Freedom of the <hi>Russia</hi> Company, to drive that Trade on equal Terms, with all other Members of the same, they are ready and do offer to part with it to the <hi>Russia</hi> Company, upon the repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Money they have paid and expended about it.</p>
            <p>And surely the <hi>Russia</hi> Merchants will not be (like the Dog in the Manger) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther carrying out <hi>Tobacco</hi> themselves, nor suffering others to do it, who would; since the doing of it will bring so many advantages to the Nation, which its humbly hoped, will be always preferred before the private Interest of Ten or Twelve Persons.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
