<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Davvnings of light wherein the true interest of reformation is opened in generall, and in particular, in this kingdome for the establishment of weaker judgements, and many other things impartially hinted, to a further discovery of truth and light in many of our present controversies : with some maximes of reformation / by John Saltmarsh ...</title>
            <author>Saltmarsh, John, d. 1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60972</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S477</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19463389</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19463389</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108857</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A60972)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108857)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1677:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Davvnings of light wherein the true interest of reformation is opened in generall, and in particular, in this kingdome for the establishment of weaker judgements, and many other things impartially hinted, to a further discovery of truth and light in many of our present controversies : with some maximes of reformation / by John Saltmarsh ...</title>
                  <author>Saltmarsh, John, d. 1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 104 [i.e. 106] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R.W. and are sold by G. Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 72-73 skipped in the numering; p. 95-98 repeated in the numbering.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-05</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-05</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108857:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108857:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DAVVNINGS OF LIGHT: Wherein the true interest of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation is opened in generall, and in particular, in this Kingdome, for the establishment of weaker judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: AND Many other things impartially Hint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to a further Discovery of Truth and Light, in many or our present controversies. With some Maximes of Reformation.</p>
            <bibl>1 Cor. 13.11.</bibl>
            <q> For now we see through a glasse darkly, now I know in part.</q>
            <bibl>1 Cor. 13.10.</bibl>
            <q> But when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part, shall be done away.</q>
            <p>By JOHN SALYMARSH, Preacher of Gods Word, at <hi>Brasteed,</hi> in the County of KENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for. <hi>R. W.</hi> and are to be sold by <hi>G. Calvert,</hi> at the black-spred-Eagle near <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:108857:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108857:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable, The <hi>Knights</hi> and <hi>Burgesses</hi> for the County of <hi>Yorkshire,</hi> in the Commons House of Parliament, <hi>viz. The Lord Generall</hi> Fairfax, <hi>Sir</hi> William Strickland, <hi>Sir</hi> Philip Stapleton, <hi>Sir</hi> Henry Cholmley, <hi>Sir</hi> William Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, <hi>Mr.</hi> Henry Darly, <hi>M.</hi> Hoyle, <hi>M.</hi> Alu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>M.</hi> Pelham, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Should exceed an Epistle, to speak of you in your severall spheres of activity, for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the cause of God</hi>; Some <hi>of</hi> yee have jeoparded your lives in the high places of the Field; Some <hi>of</hi> yee offered
<pb facs="tcp:108857:3"/>
your selves, willingly among the people. <hi>When the great</hi> work <hi>of God is finished, the names of those shall be sought for that have acted for him, and it shall be said,</hi> What honour and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity hath been done to <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for this? <hi>You that work both for</hi> God <hi>&amp; your</hi> Countrey, <hi>shall bee recorded both in the</hi> Chronicle <hi>of</hi> Heaven <hi>&amp;</hi> Earth: <hi>And</hi> ye <hi>are the more eminent in this, that ye have sate out the</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, <hi>and unfortunate</hi> fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings <hi>of so many</hi> (<hi>preserved through the power of Christ</hi>) They went out from ye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they were not of yee: <hi>And such is the quality of your employment, that ye may learne to be at once both</hi> Saints, <hi>and</hi> Statesmen, <hi>in this work: for the daily opening of the</hi> secrets <hi>of</hi> affairs <hi>before ye, both</hi> religious
<pb facs="tcp:108857:3"/>
               <hi>and</hi> civill, <hi>may make your house a</hi> Senate <hi>and a</hi> Temple; <hi>and the more spiritually ye work in State-affairs, ye act in a higher capacity then common Statesmen, or former Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My prayer is for ye,</hi> That ye may be stedfast and unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, alwayes abounding in the work of the Lord, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that your labour shall not be in vain in the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So prayes your Servant,</hi> John Saltmarsh,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:108857:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>To the Worthy and Eminent Committee in the County of <hi>KENT.</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have through the providence of <hi>God</hi> been seated in the influence of your government, where I have enjoyed, as others of that place have done, a <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>security,</hi> while many places of the kingdome hear the <hi>Alarms of War,</hi> and put on <hi>garments rolled in blood.</hi> The Lord, <hi>who is the mighty Counsellour</hi>; hath poured out a <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>wisdome</hi> and <hi>counsell</hi> upon you and so long as you act in the strength of him, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to him, you see you have sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for Wals and Bulwarks.</p>
            <p>You have much experience of God (as I have observed) in the conduct of your affairs, which hath not only been advantagious to the publick, and to the peace of your own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; but <hi>exemplary</hi> to others <hi>abroad,</hi> and the more you go on to involve your selves into the cause of God, the greater share you may look for
<pb facs="tcp:108857:4"/>
in the <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Happiness<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Successe</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>You know well (nor need I remind you) how the <hi>interest</hi> of your <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> is wrapped up in that <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>Parliamentary association,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> while you preserve (through the blessing of God) as you do, in that <hi>constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> you may expect to live by the same line of prosperity you have done. And so prayes,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant, <hi>Iohn Saltmarsh,</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:108857:5"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>To Mr. <hi>Tho. Fuller,</hi> the Author of a Book entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Truth maintained</hi>: at <hi>Oxford,</hi> or elsewhere.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS you accused me once of haste in my Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon your Book, so you may now charge a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay upon me for the Answer I am preparing to your second Treatise: my interruptions have bin many, yet the Truth I defend, I hope will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take you at length, though you set forth long before me: I shall deale better with you, then you have done with me, to let you see our usage on this side of <hi>Oxford</hi> hath more cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; for I shall fairly interpret the <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>candidly</hi> reject the
<pb facs="tcp:108857:5"/>
               <hi>bad</hi>: I could wish you would prevent me in comming over to our present <hi>Reformation,</hi> and so you may <hi>satisfie</hi> the <hi>question</hi> better. Yet, Sir, we might both do better to hearken to our learned Umpire, <hi>Mr. Herle,</hi> who tels us, <hi>How needlesse fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sputes were about Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, by how much Reformation is necessary.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:108857:6"/>
            <head>The Preparatory.</head>
            <p>I Have in this short discourse la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laboured to give you rather the <hi>spirits</hi> and <hi>extractions</hi> of things, then to write at large; and to point only to the <hi>advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> amongst us: for I saw so many plunged in the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies</hi> of our times, that it had been good <hi>some</hi> of them were either <hi>well out,</hi> or had never <hi>come in;</hi> for the disputes which only before <hi>warmed</hi> us, have now set us all on <hi>flame,</hi> and we have reasoned our judgements much beyond those <hi>boundaries</hi> in the Word, of godly peace, and edification: Discourses of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ought to be free and peaceably bold; for the <hi>soule</hi> is more at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty for debating, where the
<pb facs="tcp:108857:6"/>
lesse <hi>ingagement</hi> or <hi>interest</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, else the <hi>enquiries</hi> can be but narrow and impartiall: I hope I need make no larger <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> for my plain dealing with all. I have writ little <hi>conclusive</hi> or <hi>positive</hi>: Determinations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not the proper work of <hi>us</hi> that stand <hi>below,</hi> who only aime at oyling the wheeles in this great work; And whilest we are but on the way to Reformation, in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory conclusions, and finall inferences, there may be more haste then good speeed.</p>
            <p>I thought, that openings and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of this nature would help to a more solid and clear firmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the truths received; for there is nothing brings greater <hi>unsettlement,</hi> then arguing things halfe way: and therefore our <hi>Reverend Assembly</hi> are not
<pb facs="tcp:108857:7"/>
to be accused of any unnecessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry delay in things of so high consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
            <p>I have writ in expressions not popular, for we should not be too much the peoples, till the light we hold out were well quit of the vapours that darken it; not that I decline the multitude, save on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in order of time, and there are certain cautions in the VVord for not revealing or communicating too suddenly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hast thou faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have it to thy self before God,</hi> Rom. <hi>14.22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Take heed left by any means this liberty of yours become a stumbling block to them that are weak, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have yet many things to say unto you, but you cannot bear them now,</hi> Iohn <hi>16.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:108857:7"/>
               <hi>And he communicated only privately, with some that were of reputation,</hi> Acts.</p>
            <p>If I be thought by any to speak too favourably of things so gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally dissented from: I desire such to take notice in what capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city I write; not as one that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers positions to the world, but as one that would fain see what is the grounds or secret that the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and some amongst us are concen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red in this, to call all other <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> who may be found perhaps to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer but as the stronger and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Christians, who though <hi>one eat herbs, and another regard a day, do it</hi> both to the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="considerations">
            <pb facs="tcp:108857:8"/>
            <head>CONSIDERATIONS in REFORMATION.</head>
            <p>COnsider, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies of our times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst some, take up the application of them so whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as a few particular truths are made their only businesse, and the positive work of sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation little advanced; <hi>These ought we to have done, and not to leave the other undone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Consider, that the <hi>measure</hi> of grace is not equal in all, nor the degrees of <hi>light</hi> the same; and this hath ever brought forth in the practice of the <hi>godly,</hi> according to the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in Scriptures, an <hi>indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> and <hi>godly prudence</hi> towards
<pb facs="tcp:108857:8"/>
one another; and this would be a seasonable consideration in these times of <hi>Reformation,</hi> where all cannot bear the <hi>truths revealed</hi> to some; and in the <hi>establishment of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to come, where if all the <hi>truths</hi> be not setled that many desire, yet so much may bee setled as ought rather to bee the object of godly indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency &amp; praise, then scandall and murmuring; and to blesse God for our very removes from Popery &amp; Prelacy into the Reformation to come, yet so, as this be no caution against the peaceable testimony of those, for the greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancements in the worship or government of God, whom God shall stir up.</p>
            <p>Consider that the warres in
<pb facs="tcp:108857:9"/>
the severall States of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome, as <hi>Germany, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, Italy, Ireland, England, &amp;c.</hi> are but pieces of the great work, and preparatories, and fall in their severall degrees and orders into the designe of God for his Church, and the ruine of Antichrist, and are not to be lookt upon as pieces and splinters that brake out from confused troubles: <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when you hear of wars and rumours of wars,</hi> be not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, <hi>for the end is not yet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Consider, that unlesse we be a people more sanctified by the successe and meanes wee have, our enemies shall not fall through any divine favour to us, but through the provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their own sinnes, and then their ruine will scarcely
<pb facs="tcp:108857:9"/>
be our salvation, but they shall only have the precedency to be first in the judgement: yet here we may look up at the prerogative of Gods mercy working sometimes above sins and provocations, <hi>He went on frowardly in the way of his heart, I have seene his wayes and will heale him.</hi> And there is to this too a supplement in the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Representative of our <hi>State,</hi> or <hi>Parliament,</hi> though the body or people of the Kingdome be not so disposed as we could wish; and this sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a Kingdome in <hi>Iosiahs</hi> and <hi>Ezekiahs</hi> times, and may save ours.</p>
            <p>Consider, that our <hi>dayes of Fasts, &amp;c.</hi> as they ought to be exceedingly advanced, we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving experienced much by
<pb facs="tcp:108857:10"/>
them, so they may be possibly made to take up the <hi>reall</hi> and <hi>substantiall Reformation</hi> that ought to be, if our Ministers looke more to their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe, then Gods in them, and so the <hi>dayes</hi> and <hi>duties</hi> may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most devour the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse</hi> in the <hi>practise</hi>; for the <hi>reformation</hi> of a <hi>day</hi> is the easier duty, then that of a <hi>whole life,</hi> and sooner done: and it would be well observed, whether we rise up equally in this, that they bee not mistaken, as it were, for the occasional Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes of our weekly sinning? and then if people once think an extraordinary day the only remedy provided, they will soone grow remisse in their constant practice. This I speak that we keep not up a <hi>standing
<pb facs="tcp:108857:10"/>
sinne,</hi> with a <hi>standing remedy</hi>: that it may be considered, that <hi>God</hi> lose not any thing through mans <hi>additionall</hi> of <hi>circumstance</hi> in <hi>worship,</hi> and because I see the very <hi>formality</hi> of the <hi>duty</hi> is as much lookt upon by some as the <hi>duty,</hi> and the <hi>duty,</hi> as him to whom it refers, and carries almost the <hi>glory</hi> of our successe from <hi>Christ</hi> himself, at least is made by some indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctly a competitor in our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances: these things would bee rightly and clearly stated to the people, <hi>God</hi> and <hi>duties</hi> must have their right places; and that may not only keep many <hi>right,</hi> but save some from going <hi>wrong</hi> in this point: let us be as much in these <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinaries</hi> of <hi>humiliation</hi> as we can, so we hold up <hi>God</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:108857:11"/>
and <hi>Christ</hi> in their glorious <hi>preheminencies</hi> in them, and the people be taught to be as <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant</hi> in the power of godliness, as <hi>occasionall,</hi> &amp; to know <hi>Christ</hi> for the only <hi>power,</hi> both of the <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>deliverance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Consider, whether our <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations</hi> under so many <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stations</hi> and <hi>Covenants,</hi> be not <hi>equivalent</hi> to that excellent duty of our first <hi>Obligations</hi>; and whether the <hi>humiliation</hi> for this, ought not to be as <hi>solemne</hi> as the <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> and as <hi>Nationall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Consider, that our debates and disputes about <hi>worship</hi> and <hi>government,</hi> have not been assisted with any publick or particular acknowledgement of former and present supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious inclinations both in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery
<pb facs="tcp:108857:11"/>
and people, and with any publick or particular seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, for revealing his will in this present Reformation to us: thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may make us so long in seeking.</p>
            <p>Consider, whether all of Prelacy be removed, as well as their vitiousnesse and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitions, and that none of their pride, superciliousnesse, and self-seeking be left behinde in us, and any of our own Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, especially any that stand above others in place of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: and if so, let us en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the extirpation of it by vertue of our Covenant.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:108857:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108857:12"/>Dawnings of Light. Wherein the true Interest of REFORMATION is opened.</head>
         <div type="part">
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Interest stated.</head>
               <p>BEing to treat of the <hi>interest</hi> of the <hi>creature</hi> only,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.33.1 Joh. 5.7.</note> I shall not speak of the <hi>interest</hi> of the <hi>Creator,</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> himself,<note place="margin">Joh. 5.26. Rev. 8.22.</note> which is so deeply and unsearchably laid in his own <hi>Essence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 17.28. Jer. 23.23, 34.</note> each person in the <hi>Godhead</hi> subsisting in the same in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiinite <hi>onenesse</hi> or <hi>being,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.20</note> and so acting abroad adessentially,<note place="margin">Psal. 8.5.</note> and intrinsecally upon the creature.<note place="margin">Ps. 13 5.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:108857:13"/>
There is not any thing created, but it hath an <hi>interest,</hi> there is a <hi>naturall</hi> or <hi>physicall</hi> interest, that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists in such a <hi>being</hi> or <hi>cause,</hi> or in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall causes which are in consociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the producing and improving such and such effects; and this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est is strengthened and improved by the putting forth the effects and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is a <hi>political</hi> or <hi>civil</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest,<note place="margin">Judg. 16.17.</note> and that is the strength of every State:<note place="margin">1 Chron. 19.2.</note> as <hi>Sampson</hi> had his locks wherein his might lay,<note place="margin">Act. 12.20.</note> so there is no <hi>Kingdome</hi> or <hi>State</hi> but they have their locks,<note place="margin">2 Kings 18.39.</note> some <hi>complication</hi> where their power is twisted and takes root, and like vines cast out them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in severall veins and sinews of negotiation, and so acquire improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>But there is a <hi>Supernaturall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est,</hi> and that is it which I aim at in this place, or an <hi>intorest of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> this interest is considerable, either towards <hi>God,</hi> or towards <hi>men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The interest towards God is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created, divine,</hi> more <hi>immediate,</hi> more
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108857:13"/>
                  <hi>immanent,</hi> more <hi>pure,</hi> and <hi>primary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The interest towards man is more <hi>incorporated,</hi> more <hi>complicated,</hi> more <hi>circumstantiated,</hi> more <hi>secondary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These two parts, if well studied, might be exalted into a <hi>transcendent science,</hi> and it is pitty that now when severall <hi>Ages of Reformation</hi> draws on, few or none that I know, elder or more modern, that have much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into the mystery &amp; sublimity, whereas every variety here below is drawn up into <hi>systemes</hi> and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorismes,</hi> only this wanders incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly under the shadow of the science <hi>Theologie,</hi> which is so <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall,</hi> that there is not that perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction attained in it, as there might be, if like other Sciences it were taken in, or inclosed, and so studied; for then some whose <hi>spirituall ingeny</hi> might be of a complexion fitter for such or such a part in Divinity, would apply thither, when as now they wander up and down in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded <hi>wastes</hi> of Theologie, and like the Philosopher, who laying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self out to <hi>nature at large,</hi> sits down
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108857:14"/>
with a narrow satisfaction; whereas the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stronomer, or any other <hi>single scienced</hi> person, knows every star and circle, and variation, and hath a more exact and particular knowledge, then such an universall contemplation can give him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The increated Interest:</head>
               <p>FIrst then for the <hi>Interest of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> as it relates to <hi>God,</hi> I mean the <hi>supernaturall</hi> interest, or the <hi>increated</hi> interest: and we must know it lies radically in the <hi>counsels of God,</hi> and subsists in his <hi>power</hi> and <hi>infinity,</hi> and takes not degrees and improvements here below, as other interests <hi>naturall</hi> and <hi>politicall</hi> do: and therefore it is, that the <hi>Interest of Reformation</hi> rayes out in some ages gloriously at its very first rise, &amp; then when it seems to have the least in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement or complication below, but seemes rather to flow from <hi>new created springs</hi> and <hi>originals,</hi> so as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108857:14"/>
that scripture holds forth, <hi>Things which are seen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>are not made of things which do appeare:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and though some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times other contraries may seem to have anticipated all the <hi>interest,</hi> and taken up the advantages beforehand, yet on a sudden God lets out an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion of light, and spirit, and in a moment disinteresses and dispossesses all the former, and this appeares in that, <hi>when the people which sate in darknesse saw great light,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and to them which sate in the region and shadow of darknesse, light is sprung up:</hi> for as the appearance of Christ to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is implied to be momentary, <hi>As the lightning that lightneth out of the one part of heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 17.24.</note> 
                  <hi>shineth unto the other part, so shall also the Son of man be in his day:</hi> now the <hi>Son of man</hi> is thus in his <hi>day of Reformation,</hi> as well as <hi>Condemnation</hi>; and as in light there is not that graduall alteration, and propagation, and working for interest in the aire, but a transfusion and illumination in such an intermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate subject or body, because there is not in it any quality contrary, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108857:15"/>
that can put any impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to so immateriall a thing as <hi>light:</hi> So it is in the <hi>spirituall trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusions</hi> of grace and reformation, when the power and will of God car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries it and applies it irresistibly, effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caciously to such and such a season or State, or people; for God being as it were more <hi>immediate,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>distant,</hi> and intrinsecal in this work, he will not sometimes admit of any such grosse or inferiour artifice, and preparings, and consociations, which argues an impotencie in the agent and work: but as he is <hi>infinite,</hi> and the <hi>Creator,</hi> so he commands the <hi>creature</hi> to make room, and the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in an <hi>obedientiall</hi> and <hi>passive</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity opens and entertains his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spensations, this is then when he would make bare (as it were) his glory, and shew himself to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and put off the creature, and as it were devest himself of his interests here below, &amp; act more immediately upon the world, and then his <hi>light</hi> and <hi>dispensation</hi> is carried on without reluctancy or disputings in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108857:15"/>
there is a melting at his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, this divine work is sweetly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuated in that Scripture,<note place="margin">Psal. 97.4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>his light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings enlightned the world, the earth saw and trembled, the hills melted like waxe at the presence of the Lord:</hi> the earth trembles, <hi>the earth,</hi> or the most <hi>grosse</hi> and <hi>opace</hi> impediment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>hils,</hi> or <hi>high obstructions</hi> flow down, and are powred out, when God powres out himselfe in any strong activity upon them.</p>
               <p>The work of Reformation being of this nature in part, and such an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate efflux of God in Christ, we should rise into higher conceptions and contemplations concerning it, and find out the <hi>interest</hi> on which it turns, in the most spirituall motions and beginnings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The more spirituall effluxes of the Interest, with a Caution.</head>
               <p>ANd these are the very same which God brought his <hi>Dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations</hi> into the world by at first, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108857:16"/>
carried on his truths on a <hi>naked pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> witnesse all his <hi>miraculous actings</hi> for his Law and Church then under <hi>Moses</hi> &amp; <hi>Joshua,</hi> God carrying them on by a mighty hand, and after under several <hi>Judges,</hi> &amp; by such sudden light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of mercy, when all their own <hi>interest</hi> was lost &amp; overflowed by the enemies, as the Scriptures intimate; <hi>Then the Lord raised them up a Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jud. 3.15.</note> The sudden restoring of the worship under <hi>Asa, Jehoshaphat, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah, Josiah</hi>: And so the raising of the Temple under <hi>Cyrus</hi> and <hi>Darius,</hi> the expressions all hold out the <hi>most high,</hi> and <hi>divine risings,</hi> and <hi>actings,</hi> as those concerning <hi>Cyrus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezra 1.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The Lord stirred up the spirit of</hi> Cyrus, <hi>and then rose up the fathers of</hi> Benjamin, <hi>and</hi> Judah, <hi>with all them whose spirit God had raised to go up:</hi> and as these con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Artaxerxes,<note place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h. 28.18.</note> 
                  <hi>And the King granted me</hi> (<hi>sayes</hi> Nehemiah) <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the good hand of God upon me, and then I told them of the hand of my God which was good upon me:</hi> And in the time of <hi>Mordecai,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Esth. 9.1.</note> 
                  <hi>And in that very day that the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mies of the Jews
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108857:16"/>
hoped to have rule over them it was turned to the contrary, and the Jews had rule over them.</hi> And thus the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation under the Gospel was carried on by a <hi>pure heavenly work,</hi> and immediate concurrence;<note place="margin">Mark. 16.20.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord (saith the Scripture) working with them, and confirming the Word With signes following, and many of them which heard the Word beleeven, and the number of the men was about five thousand,</hi> all on sudden:<note place="margin">Act. 4.4.</note> Thus the <hi>Interest of Reformation,</hi> or the <hi>Gospel,</hi> lay then most in the <hi>naked</hi> and <hi>immediate power of God,</hi> subsist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his very omnipotencie, and so in divers ages to this; though in a particular account from <hi>Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall Story,</hi> we may soon be led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to some false experiments of this <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest</hi>; for it was a luxuriancie in some of them, to put down some <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous passages,</hi> or <hi>stories,</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are very questionable; for the <hi>mysterie of iniquity</hi> working higher every age then other, the <hi>learning</hi> of after times, partly in an <hi>easie</hi> and <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt piety,</hi> and partly in a <hi>policie</hi> to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108857:17"/>
preserve the reputation of so divine an <hi>interest,</hi> kept up many Legends to this day: But for <hi>later Centuries,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Gormanie, Scotland,</hi> and our own kingdom, God hath brought in himself according to the former Scriptures, <hi>with an high hand</hi> with <hi>signes</hi> and <hi>wonders,</hi> with raising and stirring up the spirits of his people, working even immediately by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; casting out the interest of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christianisme</hi> and <hi>Prelaecie,</hi> and place<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>his owne</hi> there, as at this day, we experience in the <hi>late opening of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and <hi>radiation</hi> upon this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, when the <hi>Prelaecy</hi> was at highest, and interweaving it self <hi>into Popery,</hi> and fastening its <hi>interest</hi> at the very foot of the <hi>Chair</hi> in <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>How the increated Interest works to be discerned below.</head>
               <p>THis increated <hi>interest</hi> of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel lying thus in the counsels, wisdom, and power of God, it comes abroad sometimes on the <hi>Wheele of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108857:17"/>
some omnipotency,</hi> when God hath a purpose to undo or dissolve the <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therings,</hi> and <hi>strong holds,</hi> the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the world, and to exalt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to the eyes of his people and his enemies, <hi>Wonderfull things did he in the land of Egypt in the field of Zoan</hi>: And here we may rise into this enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, How <hi>God</hi> may be discerned in such a work? though best <hi>by the Spirit, which searches the deep things of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>First, God, in making any clear discovery of this <hi>interest,</hi> must assume such Agents as may not seem to stand in the way of his <hi>omnipotency,</hi> I mean, by casting any <hi>shadow</hi> upon it, but they must be such as he may be seen in, even to a <hi>carnall</hi> eye, as the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitians of Egypt,</hi> who could then only discern God, &amp; but his <hi>finger</hi> neither, in the <hi>judgement of Lice</hi>;<note place="margin">Exo. 8.19.</note> of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture were those things he made use on, as <hi>Moses rod,</hi> and <hi>Aarons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 17.</note> both blossoming with miracles al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke, the <hi>Waters of Jordan, rams horns,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Josh. 3.15 16 17.</note> 
                  <hi>lamps and pitchers, a sling and a pible stone, the jaw bone ef an Asse, clay and spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Josh. 6.20</note> 
                  <hi>handkerchiefs and shadows,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 7.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>a</hi> Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108857:18"/>
                  <hi>or poorest family in</hi> Manasseh,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.50.</note> 
                  <hi>and he the poorest in his fathers house,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jud. 15.15</note> and thus <hi>the Gospel had its rise and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 9.6, 7</note> God <hi>choosing the base things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 19.12</note> 
                  <hi>the weak things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 5 15.</note> 
                  <hi>and foolish things, fishermen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 6.15</note> 
                  <hi>and Women,</hi> and <hi>laying</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side whatsoever might exalt it self,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.27, 28.</note> so as <hi>not many wise men after the flesh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1.16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>nor many mighty, nor many noble were called</hi>:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.26.</note> Nay, in the great and finall work for his Church,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.21.</note> his very word, which he cals (in the name of the world) <hi>the foolishnesse of preaching,</hi> shall be acted by that <hi>omnipotency,</hi> as all the power of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abylon</hi> seems only to fall at the noise of that: I dispute not here, what other <hi>concomitant</hi> God may annex, yet the Word car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the reputation; and it is most reasonable, in this way of the Lords working, that <hi>God</hi> should overthrow them by that, which they in their own wisdome reputed but <hi>foolishnes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:108857:18"/>
               <head>The Interest suffers no change from the creature.</head>
               <p>NOw this <hi>interest</hi> is only and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire in God, and the Designe works only below for compleating the body of Christ; and this body is made up of all <hi>nations and kindreds,</hi> and though in some nations where the <hi>Gospel</hi> is, God may not equally dispence successe or advancement to it, but may often in his own wisdom let the interest seem to dye out, as in our own Kingdom, and that of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he hath formerly done, and in that of <hi>Ireland</hi> of late; yet even then we must look at the designe of <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> as it is in <hi>God,</hi> and not in the <hi>creature,</hi> and not think so far below such a glorious businesse, as if the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing or wasting in any particular had put any stop to the work of God, as if any thing of the world had pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to disorder the <hi>uniformity</hi> of such a work, and <hi>should put God about,</hi> but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108857:19"/>
we must know that God hath fully and from eternity made up the glory of this businesse: and though there may be unevennesse on the worldly side of it, yet on the heavenly side of it there is none; as in former inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, not only when God dwelt in <hi>curtains,</hi> and in a <hi>Temple made with hands</hi>; but after, when he took up a more spirituall habitation in his people,<note place="margin">Acts 8.1.</note> for even then their <hi>Churches were scattered abroad throughout the Regions of Judea, and Samaria, except the Apostles:</hi> &amp; here the <hi>Spirit</hi> hints to us, how God sometimes locks up or layes up his <hi>interest</hi> in some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder, as here in the <hi>Apostles,</hi> when the rest were scattered, the <hi>word it self was hid in the root of</hi> Jesse, and <hi>the branch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 4.20</note> 
                  <hi>the tree in the vision had a stump left in the earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 19 18.</note> 
                  <hi>and God had seven thousand unknown to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, which had not bowed to</hi> Baal, and <hi>the woman which he lodged in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernesse, to whom he gave the wings of an Eagle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Isa. 55.5.</note>
                  <hi>My thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your wayes my wayes</hi>;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108857:19"/>
God hath divers ends in making o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertures of light, and withdrawing it, in Gods work there is nothing lost nor in vain, and when the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of man is not able to make any thing of disadvantages, the wisdom of God can. Christ is the same yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and to day, and for ever, nor in him is any variablenesse or shadow of change.</p>
               <p>I shall here for a further advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to this, make a discovery of such secret principles, as if clearly discus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, might prove of powerfull advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, to some present and succeeding controversies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>A right stating of the Churches Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, of great concernment to some present Controversies.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF the Churches Interest hath been alwayes below,</hi> (I speak now of the period from Christ) then this saves the birth of <hi>a new Ministery,</hi> or <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and all this may stand
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108857:20"/>
good: <hi>viz. Of receiving them out of mysticall Babylon, as the Jews did the golden vessels,</hi> then it would be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussed whether any such way of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> did strengthen that of a <hi>necessary</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>visibility,</hi> and <hi>whether it did as fully advance the Attributes of God: viz.</hi> his omnipotencie, &amp;c. and equally <hi>comply with the revealed designe of God</hi> in his word, of alwayes preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Church; and whether the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> or <hi>ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tacie,</hi> and the <hi>slaying</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>of the witnesses</hi> could stand with such <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> a Church-<hi>nterest,</hi> and <hi>how the temple of God,</hi> on which Antichrist sits, <hi>her golden cups or jewels,</hi> may be in the Spirits sense the true <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances</hi> in bondage, or only a <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> or <hi>resembling</hi>; and <hi>what <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the Tabernacle of God</hi> coming down may imply, whether such a continued <hi>inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st</hi> or no; <hi>and whether the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures themselves, being the Ark of Gods revealed will, be not the conserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of the Interest in such intervals,</hi> and <hi>whether th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> hur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h or Scriptures</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> be the fitter Subjects, according to Gods method and rule of working,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:108857:20"/>
for preserving and propagating such an interest.</p>
               <p>And if the Church hath alwayes had <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> an <hi>interest,</hi> whether this <hi>interest</hi> hath been alwayes the same from the first, because some do so quarrell that, and call it a going to <hi>Moses</hi> from <hi>Christ,</hi> a seeking for <hi>Gospel to the Law</hi>; and indeed, if some stronger labours were of this nature in full, not in broken Treatises, then as yet we have seen, they might heale many an objection about our <hi>Ministery</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> which for want of it, some may think lie too open: and here might be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the severall <hi>administrations</hi> God took up for such seasons, and how <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> far such <hi>administrations</hi> were inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be answerable to each other, both before the <hi>Law,</hi> and under the <hi>Law,</hi> and how <hi>the Law is fulfilled in</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>the Gospell,</hi> and <hi>whether there be not</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>a fulfilling by way of eminency</hi>; and if so, then <hi>whether there be any such spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall or particular relating in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances under</hi> Christ, Abraham, <hi>and</hi> Moses: and this done, the subject and circumstances of one <hi>Ordinance</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:108857:21"/>
which fals under so peremptory a precept (I mean <hi>Circumcision</hi>) will sooner clear up to the weaker judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>And in this it would be observed what latitude such proof allows, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Papists</hi> can take any of the same shadow to sit under for proving any thing of their <hi>Hierarchy, Ceremonies,</hi> and <hi>musick,</hi> to be a fulfilling of that part of the <hi>Law, the Priesthood and Service.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All these things deserve large and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> powerfull discourses, because from these such consequences spring up as may trouble our ages more then they yet have done, especially we being now laying our <hi>corner stones,</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to build</hi>: and this I should recommend to the pens of the most godly learned of our age, by way of speciall advancement to the cause of God at this present.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:108857:21"/>
               <head>The contemplation of this Interest ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry strengthening, and the higher, the more safe.</head>
               <p>I Intend at this time but to let out a glimpse of this <hi>Interest of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> to awaken us into a closer pursuit and enquiry after it, for I know not any that have taken pains in this, except godly <hi>Bucer</hi>; and he hath not pursued this Interest under this <hi>notion</hi>; nor higher then into the next organicall part of it, concerning the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> in its severall <hi>administrations</hi>; and believe it, if this part were rightly and supreamly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussed, and held forth in such <hi>ages</hi> as this, when God is casting out <hi>new beams</hi> every day to the <hi>world,</hi> till at length all be <hi>on a pure light,</hi> and our <hi>day</hi> be like the <hi>first day of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> when God said, <hi>Let there be light,</hi> as if all the <hi>stars</hi> and <hi>luminaries</hi> of heaven were disbanded, and let out from their <hi>Orbs, when the light of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108857:22"/>
Moon shall be as the light of the Sun, and the light of the Sun as the light of seven dayes:</hi> If this part, I say, of the the Reformation were methodically heightned and drawn into principles, and Aphorismes, it would raise up the soules of Gods people in all sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and would be a subliming and strengthening to faith, even the very <hi>substance of things hoped for,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and the evidence of things that are not seen</hi> and such a spiritualizing to the soul, that we might live in the same regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Apostle, <hi>whose conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation</hi> (as he sayes) <hi>was in heaven,</hi> in the same region with <hi>Enoch,</hi> who walked with God, and with all the <hi>blessed Saints</hi> &amp; <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> who stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died the science of this <hi>interest</hi> more then any; and therefore it is, that they stood firm &amp; higher then all the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er regions of Providence, even in a serene firmament all the time of los<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and tempests, and miscarriages, &amp; declinings,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.27.</note> 
                  <hi>as seeing him who is invisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> and <hi>looking for a City which hath foundations, whose builder and maker is God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:108857:22"/>
But this is not the <hi>interest</hi> we look so much after in this age, men are carried by <hi>lower</hi> and more <hi>naturall</hi> interests, which draw and entice the soule into the senses, and so <hi>incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates</hi> the contemplations and graces of the soul, and when we should live <hi>a life</hi> even <hi>hid wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h Christ in God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3.</note> we are <hi>hiding</hi> our life in the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, <hi>rising</hi> and <hi>falling, ebbing</hi> and <hi>flowing</hi> with the ordinary Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, not being able to attain to that <hi>spirituall consistencie</hi> of soule which the former agents in Reformation had, Nay, you shall see, that even the holy men of God, while they let themselves down into these outward Providences, they would often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline some degrees, as <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 27.1.</note> 
                  <hi>I shall one day perish by the hand of Saul:</hi> and as <hi>Paul, Sirs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 27.10</note> 
                  <hi>I perceive that this voyage will be with hurt and much damage, not only of the lading of the ship, but also of our lives</hi>; but when he had conversed more above, and had seen a vision from God, he then could say, <hi>Sirs, I now exhort you to be of good cheer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 27.22, 23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>for there shall be no
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108857:23"/>
losse of any mans life among you, for this night there stood by me the Angel of God, whose I am, and whom I serve.</hi> The reason that there are so many doubtings, and despondencies, and discouragements, is only this, Many look too much upon the <hi>naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of Reformation,</hi> not upon the <hi>supernaturall,</hi> and that which is the more <hi>hidden</hi> and <hi>secret,</hi> which though it be <hi>invisible,</hi> and not so discernable to a carnall eye, yet it is the only <hi>unchangeable, eternall</hi> &amp; <hi>sure interest,</hi> hid and involved in <hi>God himself,</hi> and in his <hi>power</hi> and <hi>wisdome</hi>; but the <hi>soul</hi> and <hi>spirit</hi> of man being in union and correspondencie with something more <hi>corporeall</hi> then it self, the body inclines after <hi>interests</hi> that are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal too, as <hi>outward power</hi> and <hi>forces,</hi> and <hi>successe,</hi> and <hi>excellencie of agents</hi> and <hi>instruments,</hi> and <hi>strength of contributions,</hi> and <hi>auxiliaries,</hi> and whatsoever may conduce to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing and propagating the cause below; and if once they look about, and see not the <hi>workings,</hi> the <hi>relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, advantages, contextures,</hi> and <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108857:23"/>
of things below</hi> as they expect, and saw usually before, they are presently cast down, and never on the wings of comfort, but when things have a strong and naturall interest, and are on wing too; as the <hi>weak Spouse</hi> could then only delight her self abroad, when she could see the <hi>floures appeare on the earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 2.12, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>and heare th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> singing of birds, and the vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce of the turtle, and see the figtree putting forth, and the vines with the tender grapes.</hi> These <hi>puttings forth,</hi> and <hi>blossoms,</hi> and <hi>outward appearance,</hi> and <hi>visibility</hi> of things is the support and only comfort of the <hi>Spouse:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Can. 5.4.</note> thus she was raised too, when she saw but her lover <hi>putting in his finger at the holes of the door.</hi> So it is with the <hi>Spouse</hi> now, with the Church and people of <hi>God</hi> now, they can only delight them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves <hi>abroad,</hi> in the <hi>Providences</hi> of God, then, and to look about towards <hi>Reformation,</hi> then, when the <hi>grapes</hi> appear, and the <hi>fig-tree</hi> putteth forth, and the <hi>singing of birds</hi> is come, when there is any <hi>chearfull budding and blossoming providence,</hi> and any <hi>musick
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:108857:24"/>
of successe,</hi> and advancement: this was <hi>Gideons</hi> errour, an overlooking and neglecting the <hi>spirituall</hi> and <hi>su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall</hi> interest, and fixing his eyes too much on the naturall: <hi>Oh my Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 5.</note> sayes he, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>God be with us, why th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all this befallen us? and where he all the miracles our fathers told us on? But now the Lord hath forsaken us, and delivered us into the hands of the Midianites:</hi> and yet we know, even then, the Divine and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural interest was working most strongly for their deliverance from the <hi>Midianites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I shall set down, before I take off my pen, my Observations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>naturall</hi> and <hi>politicall</hi> interest which Reformation hath in this age of ours, even that <hi>visible</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest which is undeniable and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: but yet with this caution, that I do not lay these open, as affirming any unquestionable, necessary suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, but as probable und deducible a successe as ever age had, because I know there may be withdrawings and retirings in God respectively to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108857:24"/>
a particular <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> and yet his Church have a fair and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent interest both there, and elswhere in other States and Kingdoms; for as a Nation is not dead in the funerals of a few persons, nor an house ruined in the falling of a pillar or tyle, no more is the <hi>Church,</hi> which is a <hi>catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, invisible, spirituall body,</hi> by any particular declination in such a <hi>City,</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> or <hi>Nation</hi>; though I must affirm this, That there is a most <hi>clear, visible, powerfull</hi> and <hi>mighty interest</hi> which <hi>Reformation</hi> hath in the <hi>Chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian world,</hi> and this <hi>Kingdom</hi> at this time, and if it succeed not here, I can accuse no want of <hi>supernaturall, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall,</hi> or <hi>political</hi> interest, for we are able enough in these, but I must accuse some speciall sinnes that have done it,<note place="margin">Isa. 59.2.</note> which have <hi>separ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ted betwixt us and our God,</hi> and <hi>have withheld good things from us,</hi> and made our God refuse to shew us the pattern, and his will, for here are conditionals implied, <hi>If the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>se of Israel sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> be ashamed of their iniquities,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ez. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>I will shew them the form of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>e:</hi> and ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108857:25"/>
                  <hi>If any man will do his will,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 7.17.</note> he shall know of the doctrine, whether it be of God or no.</p>
               <p>At what instant I shall speak con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a nation, and concerning a kingdome, to pluck up, and to pull down, and to destroy it,</p>
               <p>If that Nation, against whom I have pronounced, turne from their evil,<note place="margin">Jer. 18.7, 8.</note> I will repent of the evil that I thought to do unto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Severall secrets in the Interest. </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>1.</hi> The Interest in Christ.</head>
                  <p>THis Interest is laid up in Christ from all eternity, and here we may rise into most spirituall appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions concerning it, for though God causes the Interest to beam forth into the things below, yet it is in Christ like light in the body of the Sun; God doth so dispence himself into Christ, that there is not any thing of God stowes beside him, but all in him, and through him, <hi>All things
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:108857:25"/>
that the Father hath are mine</hi>: for Christ, as he was the <hi>Word,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 16.15</note> was <hi>With God in the beginning, and was God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 1.10.</note> 
                     <hi>without him was not any thing made that was made, in him was life:</hi> in these expressions the Spirit lets us see how God made himselfe over to Christ: And further,<note place="margin">Ephes. 1.15.17, 18.</note> 
                     <hi>He was the image of the invisible God, he is before all things, and by him all things consist,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note> and he is the head of the body, the Church, who is the beginning, being also the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ghtnesse of his glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Scripture opens this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie further yet: <hi>God was in Christ, reconciling the world unto himself,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.19.</note> and <hi>in him the fulnesse of the Godhead dwels bodily:</hi> and when Christ that <hi>eternal Word</hi> came to apply the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest neerer the creature,<note place="margin">Isa. 53.2.</note> 
                     <hi>He grew up before him, as a tender plant, and as a root out of a dry ground</hi>;<note place="margin">Pro. 8.22 30.</note> 
                     <hi>yet the Lord possessed him in the beginning of his way before his Works of old, he Was by him, as one brought up with him.</hi> The holy Spirit holds out the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie of laying up the Interest in Christ yet more, and writes to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:108857:26"/>
Church to comfort her in the <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the mystery of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 3.2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>and of the Father, and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hrist, in whom are hid all the treasures.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if we would see a further glimpse of this interest, sweetly opened by Christ himselfe, let us heighten our meditations upon these Scriptures, where Christ discourses with his Father, implying the spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall interest all the way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All mine are thine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job. 17.10</note> 
                     <hi>and thine are mine, and I am glorified in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, and as thou Father art in me &amp; I in thee, that they also may be one in us,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">21</note> 
                     <hi>and the glory which thou gavest me, I have given them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">23</note> 
                     <hi>I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rfect in one.</hi> So as now God being thus in Christ, and the Church adopted so near to that infinite Unity, of God in Christ, the Interest is unchangeably, and eternally preserved; and to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e all fast with the heavenly cordage of love,<note place="margin">Jer. 31.33 Ezech. 36.26.</note> God holds our himself in <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 8. Col. 1.19.</note> in an <hi>everl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sting C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>venant:</hi> And thus it hath <hi>pleased the Father, that in him should all f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lnesse dwell,</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:108857:26"/>
and all our Interest should be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured in him, even to that of grace and glory, that our life should be hid with Christ in God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>II.</hi> The Spiritual Interest in Allegory.</head>
                  <p>THat we may discern the Interest more nearly it is conveyed to us on the scene of Allegories, for God being invisible in himself, and more immediate approaches, makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self appeare through such expressions as the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thou shalt hide them in the secret of thy presence,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ps. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.20.</note> 
                     <hi>thou shalt keep them se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly in a pavilion.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cant. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>I sate down under his shadow with great delight.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov.</note> 
                     <hi>The Name of the Lord is a strong tower, the righteous run unto it and are safe, under the shadow of his wings will I make my refuge. Come my people,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isa. 29.20.</note> 
                     <hi>enter thou into thy chambers, and shut thy doors about thee, hide thy self as it were for a little moment:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Psal. 48.12, 13.</note> 
                     <hi>Walk about Sion, go round about her, tell the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:108857:27"/>
thereof,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isa. 22.23.</note> 
                     <hi>mark ye well her bulwarks, consider her palaces.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cant. 2.14.</note> 
                     <hi>My beloved hath a vineyard, &amp;c. he fenced it, and built a tower in the midst. And I will fasten him as a nail in a sure place. O my Dove, thou art in the clifts of the rocks in the secret places of the stairs.</hi> Thus God hides his interest in these Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories, <hi>Clefts,</hi> in <hi>Rocks,</hi> and <hi>secret places</hi> and <hi>chambers,</hi> and <hi>wings,</hi> and <hi>shadowes,</hi> and <hi>bulwarks,</hi> and <hi>palaces,</hi> and <hi>towers,</hi> and <hi>fences,</hi> and <hi>pavilions,</hi> and the <hi>secrets</hi> of his <hi>presence,</hi> for God is so indistant, and present with his, that they are safe in the midst of dangers, and he holds these <hi>invisible Sanctuaries</hi> over them: <hi>Lo, he goeth by me, and I see him not; he passeth on also, but I per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eive him not.</hi> Thus said <hi>Job,</hi> when his sight was dim with affliction, that he could not see into the Interest beyond the creature.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>III.</hi> The Recipients of the Spirituall Interests.</head>
                  <p>THose things which are of neerest capacity to the receiving of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:108857:27"/>
Interest, are first the <hi>Covenant,</hi> or <hi>eternall Paction</hi> and ingagement, wherby <hi>God</hi> stands bound of his meer free grace to his Church or people, and by this interceding act he and his people are brought together.</p>
                  <p>The next is the <hi>Scriptures of God,</hi> or the <hi>Word,</hi> whereby the interest is propagated, being the <hi>power of God unto salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The other is the <hi>Church of God,</hi> which is <hi>the Fountain sealed,</hi> the <hi>garden enclosed</hi> wherein all the sweets &amp; fragrancies of grace breath forth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>IV.</hi> The Recipients of the Interest.</head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Prophetical truths</hi> in the Prophets,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and the <hi>Revelation of John,</hi> are the severall orbs and spheres the <hi>Interest</hi> works in, and hence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the severall degrees of <hi>radiation</hi> that the <hi>truth of God</hi> casts out in the ages past, present, and to come. The <hi>operations</hi> &amp; <hi>fluxes</hi> of the Spirit,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of which there are, as the Apostle sayes, <hi>Diversities of gifts, &amp; diversities of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:108857:28"/>
administrations, inspirations, illuminations, instincts, motions, created powers</hi> and <hi>mights,</hi> for effecting <hi>successes, preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, deliverances, advancements, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The purer Ordinances of Praying, Preaching, Prophesying, Worship and Government, holy Treatises, Writings, Discourses, or any other Divine faculty, like a golden candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick conveying the heavenly light abroad.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>V.</hi> The Engines the Interest works by.</head>
                  <p>THere are certain <hi>created powers,</hi> &amp; qualifications <hi>spiritual, natural,</hi> and <hi>civil,</hi> which the infinite supreme Agent makes use on here below (as I hinted before) the <hi>vertues, gifts</hi> and <hi>graces,</hi> likewise the <hi>policie, power</hi> and <hi>authority,</hi> and <hi>consociations,</hi> all these <hi>God</hi> takes up, &amp; carries on his <hi>interest</hi> by them in States and Kingdoms, nor was there ever <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tion,</hi> but <hi>God</hi> set it on by such wayes of appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, either by <hi>eminencie of gifts</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:108857:28"/>
and <hi>inspirations,</hi> or by <hi>eminencie of power,</hi> and some of these he used more eminently at one time, then at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, as in <hi>Iosiahs</hi> and <hi>Asaes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Chron. 15.13.2 Kings, 23.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> when the <hi>coercive authority</hi> was the greatest wheel in the Reformation.</p>
                  <p>To conclude this, <hi>God</hi> improves Reformation by <hi>created meanes</hi> and <hi>entities,</hi> which are like wheeles and springs, and God moves by these, sometimes in the way of his <hi>omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie,</hi> sometimes more <hi>connaturally,</hi> and according to his way of moving, the improvements are; if he move in a connaturall way, he works with the creature little further then its own capacity, and then things may go slowly on, because he puts not out his hand to bring on the creature faster then its own strength will carry it: See this in <hi>Iosiahs, Asa's, Ezra's</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, in <hi>Edward</hi> the sixth's, <hi>Elizabeth's,</hi> where the Reformation went on gradually from one obstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to another.</p>
                  <p>God having thus laid in <hi>qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of severall orders for advancing his great work, they all work in their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:108857:29"/>
proper subserviency &amp; subordination, for the whole creation serves but this glorious end, that God may have his Church compleated through so many severall ages &amp; providences, according as he hath drawn it out in kis e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rnall Model or Idea, which is, his own wisdome or counsel; and when God is upon his work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, you may observe all the lower interests are set a going,<note place="margin">Judg. 5.20</note> 
                     <hi>The stars shal fight against Sisera in their course,</hi> thus shall the <hi>natural interest</hi> help on.<note place="margin">Ezra 1.1. Neh. 2.8. Ezra 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and <hi>Artaxerx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> shall send out commissions &amp; letters to their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and ministers of State; thus shall the <hi>politick interest</hi> help on. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Zechariah,</hi> the people of God, shall pray and prophesie, so shall the more <hi>spiritually-organicall means</hi> help on.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>VI.</hi> The Obstructions, and how removed.</head>
                  <p>THe Spirituall obstructions are <hi>intrinsecall,</hi> and <hi>forain,</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinsecall</hi>; the intrinsecall are <hi>malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:108857:29"/>
of nature, carnall reasonings, idolatrous, superstitious principles, principles of Atheisme, Libertinisme</hi>; there are but two wayes of removing these, by a Power spirituall, and a Power civil, or of Magistracie, and the disciplines and orbs where both these powers work, and influence; and here it would be well inquired how far this latter of <hi>Magistracie</hi> may be improved to remove the more spirituall obstructions, and to compell up to a Reformation, and how neer the <hi>interests</hi> of <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> are, seeing they were at first in one subject or person, and after in two, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be found any more in one, as the Papists &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>relates would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated them again: and its said, we clearly see not the right interest of Christian Magistracie by any pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical truth in the Gospel, and that which makes it so dark is this, that no nations were wholly converted in Christ's and the Apostles times, by which we might have experiments of their <hi>power</hi> in cooperating with the Apostles, and what the true subservi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:108857:30"/>
of such a power is to a spiritual interest, and in what latitude, is not yet clear to some. And surely here we are too low of late in our Treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, for we should first state the <hi>interest</hi> of <hi>Magistracie,</hi> as we find it in the Gospel, and under the Law respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, and then enquire into the secret of <hi>Gospel-propagation,</hi> and why the the Gospel begun below, and went up, and not as <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sar</hi> first, and so down? and whether it equally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect both administrations? and how far that Scripture that is not thought on in such case may be consulted? <hi>You are not c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>me un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> the mountain that burned with fire, but ye are come unto mount Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n</hi>?<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eb. 12.8.</note> And it would be clearly stated, whether spirituall perswasion, and conviction, and the Evangelicall Ordinances, be the onely <hi>mediums,</hi> or <hi>means,</hi> which were then imployed for carrying on the Gospel? and the auxiliary of <hi>miracles</hi> then annexed for compelling reputation? and now that of <hi>miracles</hi> cea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing, whether <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracie</hi> ought not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ply? These are yet not beaten out so in our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:108857:30"/>
discourses, as they might be.</p>
                  <p>The forain or extrinsecal obstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are, some Lawes, Customes, Traditions, Adversaries or enemies to truth, Confederations with Princes and States abroad, a people of forain interests in their own nation. These are removed by suspending <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tatutes, opening Pulpits, Presses, and letting out the holy dispensation of the Gospel freely, by State agencie, and vigilancie, and a kind of sending out <hi>Hushaies</hi> to sit at Councel table with <hi>Achitophels</hi>; and if this hath too much of <hi>David</hi> in it, yet the <hi>Iewes</hi> which dwell neer them may be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with for intelligence, as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did.<note place="margin">Neh. 4.12</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Instances of mixtures in Scriptures, as that of Corinth, those seven of Asia, the Parables improved, <hi>Mat 13.29, 30,</hi> of the Tares and Wheat.</head>
               <p>WHen these and such like are urged in case of separation,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:108857:31"/>
and mixt communicating in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; It would be further enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whether such a sense come up more directly or obliquely to the holy Spirit? and whether Church-corruptions, as <hi>Corinth's,</hi> and <hi>Ephesus</hi> &amp;c. were intended any more for Proofs, or Arguments, or Rules, then Personal corruptions, as <hi>Davids</hi> lusts, and <hi>Moses</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssions, and <hi>Peters</hi> fears? and whether all such examples be not rather set down as cautions, and written for our admonition, that <hi>we should n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t lust,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.11.</note> 
                  <hi>as they also lusted?</hi> &amp; further, whether the name <hi>Church</hi> be not sometimes to be taken in the same sense under the Gospel, as the Ark and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emple was tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> under the Law still for the places of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> though sometimes he was not so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>bly ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd whether the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pirit for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore not to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> them, because the fault was in some particular practices about Ordinances rather then in the <hi>essential,</hi> or <hi>first form</hi> of Church constitution, which they had perfecter then we? And whether this be a rule for the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:108857:31"/>
of Gods people, who are to go by the clear and visible Rules in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, according to which Churches are made up, or have constitution? And whether the Holy Spirit would have reputed them still Churches, had they gone on in the toleration of such corruptions, for all their first consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, as appears in that caution to Ephesus, <hi>Repent, or I will c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me unto thee quickly, and remove thy candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick?</hi> and whether the Parables of mixture of <hi>Tares</hi> and <hi>Wheat,</hi> and <hi>good Fish</hi> and <hi>bad,</hi> be so as may make for toleration of <hi>visible mixtures</hi> any where then in the world because they are <hi>shut up</hi> with the mention of the <hi>Worlds dissolution?</hi> And whether such <hi>Church censures</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrist hath provided against sinnes and scandals, import not an <hi>outward purity</hi> in all such as would pretend to be members of his <hi>visible body?</hi> These things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are the hinges of certain debutes amongst us, would be more fully opened.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:108857:32"/>
               <head>Separation enquired after.</head>
               <p>ANd for <hi>Separation,</hi> I find it not rightly stated: for, withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and particular communicatings apart of the godly, that separate only upon grounds, not so clearly or fully condemned in the Word, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, ought not to be presently reputed Schisme, or Separation, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by those that so withdraw, nor those from whom the pretended se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration is made, if we would study the common peace of Christians: and if this were rightly discussed, and the true Scripture principles made clear which bear it, there would be no such <hi>division,</hi> as there is <hi>separation,</hi> but it would be only a <hi>suspending</hi> one from another, as in the intervals of unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse under the law, till <hi>Christ had revealed even this unto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed it would be well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, seeing God reveales his <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uths</hi> in severall degrees in <hi>nations,</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:108857:32"/>
Whether such a national con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity be fully agreeable to such a method of <hi>Revelation,</hi> and that all ought to conform <hi>outwardly,</hi> that conform not <hi>inwardly</hi>? and whether such an <hi>unity</hi> may not have equally its inconveniences on the right hand, as <hi>formality hypocrisio, &amp;c.</hi> as well as the other on the left, <hi>errors, divisions,</hi> &amp;c. and yet all State inconveniencies must be taken in here, which may spring from the want of such a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity; alwayes provided that the rule in Scripture be fully consulted, lest we make Church businesse bend further toward the maximes of State, then there is just grounds in the word: and it would be well weighed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther such separation hath not foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation enough for more <hi>spiritual correspondencie,</hi> then some on all sides practise? and whether such differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in those that pretend all to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ought to be esteemed other than the severall complections and features of so many members of the same body? some are more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable then others. And here we
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:108857:33"/>
might do well to observe better that great engine of Sathans, which he useth against the people of God, that of severall <hi>titles,</hi> and notes of distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as of <hi>Presbyterial, Independent, Brownist, Anabaptist:</hi> For by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us thus under <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Apollos,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> he drawes us into <hi>scandal,</hi> and <hi>offence,</hi> and <hi>sidings,</hi> and <hi>parties,</hi> amounting almost to the disinteress<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and unclasping our selves one from another, and letting us out into these severall channels, and then our stream must needs slow more weakly against the banks of the common enemy, and the power of hell and darknesse. I conclude thus, that these Scriptures would be further searched.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now I beseech you &amp;c. that you all speak the same thing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. and that you be perfectly joyned together in the same same mind.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Let us therefore as many as be perfect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">15.</note> 
                  <hi>be thus minded, and if in any thing you be otherwise minded,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">16.</note> 
                  <hi>God shall reveale even this unto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neverthelesse whereunto we have already attained, let us walk by the same rule, let us minde the same things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:108857:33"/>
                  <hi>We then that are strong ought to bear the infirmities of the weake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>and not to please our selves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let every one of us please his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15.2.</note> 
                  <hi>for his good to edification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For one believeth that he may eat all things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 14.2.</note> 
                  <hi>another who is weak eateth herbs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let not him that eateth, despise him that eateth not.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In these Scriptures are almost the full latitude of Christianity: in the first, the <hi>perfect Rule of unity</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended; in the other, the severall degrees to this unity are opened, and commanded.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Christ's interests, and the Worlds.</head>
               <p>ME thinks, in stating severall controversies of late, we go not high enough, but we strive in the vallies, where the mist is thickest, whereas we might see better and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if we could go up higher, to the interest of <hi>Christ:</hi> the Disciples saw
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:108857:34"/>
more of him when he <hi>took them up with him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 9.</note> then they saw before.</p>
               <p>This <hi>interest</hi> would be well cleared and held forth in its <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuality,</hi> and abstracted from all other worldly interests which complicate with it: the Kingdom of Christ and the World are two, in their funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals, policy, lawes, governours, ends, designes, and the more the World insinuates any of its policy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of Christ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the more is the Kingdome of Christ darkned, and corrupted; and as it is in a civill State, the more of <hi>arbitrarinesse</hi> that comes in, the more is the <hi>established government</hi> subverted; so in <hi>Christs,</hi> whose government is more one and unchangeable, by how much a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in a spirituall notion, is more perfect, then a Kingdome in a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or worldly.</p>
               <p>And if we observe well, we shall see that the great <hi>mysterie of iniquity</hi> is no more then a <hi>meer spirituall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Worldly interests works much in mixed <hi>aggregations</hi> and <hi>counsels,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:108857:34"/>
authoritative power, in servile depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies</hi> and <hi>subordinations,</hi> in <hi>promis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us unity and conformity,</hi> and <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versality,</hi> in <hi>blinde</hi> and <hi>implicite obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> in falsely pretended <hi>antiquity,</hi> as appears in the <hi>popish</hi> and <hi>Prelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>licy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The interest of Christ is in a <hi>spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all freed me</hi> or <hi>priviledging,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 8.36. Act 6.5.</note> in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nction</hi> or <hi>knowledge,</hi> in <hi>consociations,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.22, 23.</note> in <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogentall unity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.19.</note> in <hi>directive</hi> and <hi>su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>intending,</hi> in <hi>perswasive,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.27.</note> and <hi>repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensive administrations</hi> or <hi>ordinances,</hi> and the government of Christ seems to be so framed, as neither Tyranny should get in at any <hi>consociation,</hi> nor Anachy or Libertinisme get in at any <hi>dissociation,</hi> or particular gathering, and at this beam we may weigh our controversies of this age.</p>
               <p>And they that argue for any <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of interests,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 31.43. Acts 15.2.3.</note> must look well to the spirituality of the Kingdom,<note place="margin">Acts 20.17.</note> and that God in this latter dispensation applies not so to the outward man,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.</note> as he did in the former, and that sim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plicity, paucity, pers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icuity, humility,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.25.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enity, and visible sanctity,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.1. Col. 3.12.</note> are the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:108857:35"/>
proper orbs, where the <hi>evangelicall light moves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet here I would be rightly understood, for I make but overtures for enquiry, while things are making to their constitution amongst us, which if once constituted, all ought to be either actively or passively obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Disputes for liberty improved.</head>
               <p>THere are great disputings now for <hi>Libert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and this springs from a mutuall jealousie in each party, the one fearing the others establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will endure no other interest near its own, and the more prevalent fearing the insinuations &amp; encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a <hi>tolerated interest</hi> that is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse from it.</p>
               <p>Now we should enquire here, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther these jealousies be the more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per passions of States, or Christians, and how far Christ, who is protector of his Church, is to be trusted with
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:108857:35"/>
the defence of his own government in such cases, and yet the true evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall latitude is not found out? Some plead upon such principles as would bring in an universall toleration, and while they would open a door only for themselves, they set in all promis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuously.</p>
               <p>Therefore it would be enquired here if all must be tolerated, for fear of persecuting the truth through ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance; then whether doth not this ground argue for a <hi>plenary Liberty,</hi> for all to propagate their interests equally with that, which is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly received <hi>truth</hi> of that place; for a <hi>truth,</hi> I conceive, may be no more <hi>suppressed</hi> ignoran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, then it may be <hi>persecuted</hi> ignorantly: and it was as great a sin, if not greater, in that <hi>Councel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 4.18</note> to charge the <hi>Apostles they should not teach the people in his name,</hi> as to <hi>whip them for the doctrine they taught.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, it would be further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired if such a <hi>Liberty</hi> be the <hi>Gospel way,</hi> what use of the reserves of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome and persecution, which
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:108857:36"/>
Christ hath made into such a glorious condition, as if he intended it as a blessed supplement to that of <hi>Liberty,</hi> and it would be enquired whether such a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lky way as that of <hi>Liberty</hi> be always consonant to the estate of the Church,<note place="margin">Can. 2.2.</note> being a <hi>Lilly among Thorns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it would be enquired too, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther such a <hi>Liberty</hi> be fully Christs minde, because the enemies of the truth, heathen Empires, and popish States as well as others are and have been abe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tors of it, and so it be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a State principle tolerating on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly those which either the necessity of some evill consequence or some <hi>State expedients,</hi> or the experienced inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of the tolerated Religion hath produced: and yet on the other side, it would be enquired further, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they that desire this <hi>Liberty</hi> be not such as are on the same funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals with us, and brethren in the Lord, and may be brought to meet with us in certain common principles, <hi>walking by the same rule,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.16</note> 
                  <hi>minding the same thing in that whereunto we have attained,</hi> and may not let out them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:108857:36"/>
unto mutuall peace and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, their dissentings, having a certain <hi>orbe</hi> or <hi>spheare</hi> allowed them, wherein they may move, that still upon occasion, we may all fall into one <hi>common society</hi> against the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>enemy</hi> of the Gospel, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> who though they lived other times at distance, yet were ever ready to relieve one another; and here I desire to know whether such severall motions as this, which agree in the same <hi>unity of faith,</hi> of <hi>mutuall edification,</hi> and contribute together to the same publick preservation; may not be with as little prejudice to the grand <hi>spirituall sphear,</hi> as in the <hi>naturall,</hi> wherein we see nature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in severall <hi>motions</hi> &amp; <hi>orbs,</hi> and yet all these (as occasion opens) mutually assisting the interest of the <hi>universe</hi> or whole.</p>
               <p>And here me thinks we should stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the latitudes of Christianity more then we doe: especially when the Scriptures holds it out to us, both in principles and practice: yet this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I must lay down, that all our
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:108857:37"/>
dissenting Brethren be as carefull o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their parts to study things that make for common peace,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.2. Phil. 3.15.16.</note> as they would have Authority carefull in acting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their particular peace.</p>
               <p>There is much arguing now against compulsive authority, in case of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the arguments run thus: 1. That it is a note of <hi>Persecution.</hi> 2. That it drives on the <hi>Popish</hi> and <hi>Prelaticall designe</hi> of <hi>Vniformity.</hi> 3. That it distracts and wounds ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>doubting consciences.</hi> 4. That it armes the enemies of the truth in their <hi>tyranny,</hi> from the <hi>Magazine</hi> of true <hi>Professors.</hi> 5. That it assumes dominion over the consciences. 6. That it intrudes into the place of God, and his Ordinances, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately influence on the soule. 7. That it was but judiciall and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall to the <hi>Jewes.</hi> 8. That it runs an hazard of fighting against God. 9. That there is no <hi>expresse com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> nor <hi>example</hi> in the Gospel for such compulsion. 10. That it is a means of keeping out <hi>truths</hi> that are yet to be revealed. 11. That the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:108857:37"/>
authority of the Magistrate in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, reaches onely to <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> transgressions; and to <hi>spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> as they come forth into the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, and so trouble the civill peace or government of the State. 12. That it makes <hi>Formalists,</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet here it would be enquired fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whether there be not the same morall and and judiciall equity, for the Magistrate to assist God in the designe of his Church now, as there was before. 2. Whether <hi>Heresies</hi> and <hi>Schismes,</hi> do not naturally bring forth such <hi>divisions,</hi> and <hi>distractions,</hi> as dash so on the power of the <hi>civill Magistrate,</hi> that they justly raise up that power against them. 3. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>pleaders</hi> for this compulsive power, do not over argue it, through indulgency, and the opposers argue it but half way, through jealousie; the one having it on their side at present, and the other against them: and whether a more moderate way be not the more <hi>Scripture-path viz.</hi> That the compulsive power may be
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:108857:38"/>
found in the Gospel-principles, sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with such <hi>Cautions</hi> and <hi>Rules</hi> from the word, as the <hi>Enemies</hi> and <hi>opposers</hi> of truth, may neither tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in an unwarrantable liberty, nor the weaker Christians have cause to complain of an unwarrantable au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, whose doubtings are expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced to wound their own soules, more then the soule of <hi>States,</hi> the <hi>Government.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Establishment of Reformation.</head>
               <p>IT hath not yet been far enough ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued according to the principles in <hi>Scripture,</hi> of what nature the <hi>esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishments</hi> ought to be under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel &amp; sure we ought more properly to advise with him that hath the <hi>keys</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> and knowes best how to <hi>shut</hi> and <hi>open,</hi> for else we may shut so fast, that we may be forced to have our doores broken open from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; as of late under <hi>Prelacy</hi> (we sadly experience) who had shut up all with so sure an establishment, that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:108857:38"/>
a truth could not get in but by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; and thus <hi>Rome</hi> and those Princes of <hi>Bondage</hi> under her, as the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> &amp;c. make use of their <hi>keyes</hi> in all their dominions for shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out, so as the <hi>Gospel-truths</hi> have no visible entrance but by force, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse God bring them in at some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther door yet unknown to us, as he seems to intend: now whether the establishment ought to be such under the Gospel as may universally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept all but what is received, or such as may contrive some holy <hi>prudenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all way,</hi> for trying any <hi>new revealed truths</hi>; if such be offered clearly from heaven by the hands of men, we finde that in Arts &amp; Sciences the <hi>Sistemes</hi> are not such as will admit of no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement:<note place="margin">Bacon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> the profoundest agents in nature are led daily on to new <hi>experiments,</hi> and the <hi>Aristotelian magistrality</hi> hath been found no lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hinderance to young travellers in the <hi>regions</hi> of <hi>nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that which may carry us on further in this enquiry, is the possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of not seeing all at once,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:108857:39"/>
strenghened by experience in our <hi>own</hi> and <hi>others reformations</hi>; yet here we must enquire too, whether <hi>Kingdomes</hi> ought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it so loose in their decrees, and whether the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science of <hi>Nations</hi> or <hi>Parliaments</hi> are to remain still in such a constant potentiality to new degrees, and whether such a way would not keep a <hi>Kingdome</hi> alwayes tottering and uncertain? Yet further, whether the <hi>potentiality</hi> of acquiring <hi>new degrees</hi> of this nature, would not bring such an alteration as were rather <hi>perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive,</hi> then <hi>corruptive,</hi> or <hi>destructive</hi>? and if so, whether these <hi>jealousies</hi> may not be saved? we see, that in the bodies <hi>naturall</hi> and <hi>spirituall,</hi> there is a <hi>potentiality</hi> to any <hi>perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive alteration,</hi> as in the <hi>aire</hi> to <hi>light,</hi> and in the <hi>soul</hi> to degrees of <hi>illumination,</hi> till they come to the <hi>statu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of the fulnesse of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:108857:39"/>
               <head>The advancers out of Babylon.</head>
               <p>IN our commings out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> we have many <hi>fellow travellers</hi> that pretend as well to leave her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde as we; and these are called <hi>Hereticks, Schismaticks, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, Separatists.</hi> Now before wee be too far engaged in this, being they are such as pretend to come from the same <hi>point of advancement,</hi> or <hi>setting forth,</hi> it would be well enquired how <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Prelacy</hi> come to oppose them so directly, and <hi>their interests</hi> to be so inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stent, if they be all enemies to the truth: I finde Christs maxime tend to another sense, <hi>How can Sathan cast out Sathan</hi>?<note place="margin">Mat. 12.16.</note> yet here again, I finde that Sathan may appear as well an Angel of <hi>Light</hi> as <hi>Darknesse,</hi> and <hi>Heresies</hi> may walk abroad, as well in <hi>white</hi> as in <hi>black</hi>; and that some <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> are as inconsistent and destructive to one another, as <hi>vices</hi> and <hi>vertues.</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:108857:40"/>
However, they pretend with us to come out of Babylon, so it is possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they may only mistake their way in their going out: yet we must ask further in such cases, where <hi>popery</hi> &amp; <hi>Prelacy</hi> agree with us thus <hi>in uno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertio</hi> (as appears in this one experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of calling the others <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schismaticks</hi>) whether a godly jealousie may not do well? for it is possible, to cast out the <hi>courser part</hi> of <hi>popery</hi> and <hi>Prelacy,</hi> and yet hold it by a <hi>finer thred,</hi> as it hath been to this <hi>age</hi> in our <hi>partial Reformations,</hi> when at first <hi>popery</hi> was cast out only by the head, and so gradually still holding it by some parts, for it is harder casting out a <hi>mysterie</hi> then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one conjectures at the first sight,<note place="margin">Rev. 17 5</note> for <hi>popery</hi> being a <hi>mysterie</hi> in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits sense, hath something more then a <hi>visible traine</hi> of Hierarchy <hi>courts</hi> and <hi>ceremonies,</hi> there is something more <hi>spiritual</hi> in it, their mixed <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> their <hi>tyrannie,</hi> their <hi>magistrality,</hi> their <hi>universality,</hi> their <hi>implicite obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> with others, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now it would be enquired what
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:108857:40"/>
                  <hi>interest</hi> or <hi>remainder</hi> these may have left behinde, for it is possible for <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie</hi> to leave such <hi>roots</hi> and <hi>stumps</hi> in the ground where it hath planted so deeply, &amp; to work again upon these <hi>hidden</hi> and <hi>occult dispositions,</hi> for the <hi>Man of sin rose by such interests</hi> at first, and this the holy Spirit had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served betimes, saying,<note place="margin">1 Thess. 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>the mysterie of iniquity doth already work, defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, compliancies,</hi> and <hi>ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stasies,</hi> as we have seen, are easily obtained, when the <hi>man of sin</hi> hath such <hi>invisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble interests</hi> and <hi>agents</hi> layed in to work by; nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as the grosser or more visible <hi>ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ts</hi> the only meanes to actuate this Kingdom back againe towards <hi>Rome</hi> so often (as we expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience) but these more <hi>secret</hi> and <hi>mercuriall engines</hi> which I have na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <p>First for their <hi>unity,</hi> it hath such cold principles as freeze and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geale <hi>multitudes heterogenially</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the <hi>worship of God,</hi> and then puts the name of <hi>Schisme</hi> upon all the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> that will not come into the dark with them,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:108857:41"/>
where all colours are like.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Their <hi>tyrannie</hi> reaches to the most <hi>spiritual cruelty,</hi> That of compelling soules under the <hi>penaltie</hi> of <hi>martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Their <hi>magistrality,</hi> in obtruding the decrees of their counsels, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility, with <hi>Anathema's,</hi> their <hi>Lording</hi> it over the <hi>heritage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Their <hi>universality,</hi> in holding out their religion for <hi>Catholick,</hi> because the <hi>ten horns have given their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to the Beast,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v. 17.17</note> though no longer then <hi>untill the words of God shall be fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Their <hi>implicite obedience,</hi> wherein all <hi>light</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> is denied to the people, but such as streams through their <hi>ministery</hi> &amp; <hi>dispensations,</hi> which must needs be of their own colour, and will never be purer, comming so; Now these and such like would be enquired into further; and our <hi>ministery</hi> may do well, a little more then they do, to set upon this part of discovery of the interests of <hi>popery</hi> and <hi>prelacie</hi> in their <hi>magistrality, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> and <hi>implicitie obedience</hi> (as their
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:108857:41"/>
Covenant oblieges them) for this I take to be the more <hi>spirituall part</hi> of it, and little studied, and thus they shall be more faithfull to their <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> which ingages them to a <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall extirpation</hi>: and now that we are upon <hi>reforming,</hi> or <hi>refining,</hi> the extractions must not be only of the grosser, the <hi>government, supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ceremonies</hi>; but of the more es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sential, and formal, and vertual parts of <hi>prelacie</hi> and <hi>popery</hi> in the things I named; only we must take heed, that in such extractions, the <hi>purer spirits</hi> doe not exhale with the other, and therefore in such <hi>spirituall experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> the furnace must be chimically heated, for it is possible that <hi>Gods unity, order,</hi> and <hi>subordination</hi> may go out with the other, if the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions be more violent, then the <hi>word of God,</hi> and <hi>Apostolical practices</hi> will endure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:108857:42"/>
               <head>The severall Interests of REFORMATION in this Kingdome.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I. The Supernaturall Interest.</head>
                  <p>THe supernaturall interest ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in those many great and eminent mercies since the first opening of Heaven upon this Nation (I reckon now from our own late epoche of Reformation.)</p>
                  <p>And first in that designe of calling a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and engaging them against the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and so to have turned back the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> in its first advancing, a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe</hi> not unlike that of <hi>Herods,</hi> of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:108857:42"/>
killing <hi>Christ</hi> in the cradle; and here <hi>God</hi> let in some glimpses, and cast in some jealousies into that great <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel,</hi> which rescued it from such an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and for all the <hi>State Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice</hi> of <hi>Court Declarations,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences; suspitions sprang up in the hearts of people, and though armies are levied by <hi>prerogative,</hi> and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down, yet God takes off their <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> and <hi>successe,</hi> both in their <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings</hi> and <hi>skirmishings</hi> with <hi>Scotland,</hi> and this is made by <hi>Providence,</hi> a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of calling a <hi>Parliament</hi> again, so as this inter designe of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, served onely to land us upon clearer discoveries.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Parliament</hi> is summoned, and excellent Members elected by a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt commonalty,<note place="margin">Psal. 29.3.</note> 
                     <hi>So as the voice of the Lord is upon the Waters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now all things worke and turn upon <hi>heavenly engines,</hi> and the <hi>long design</hi> of <hi>keeping</hi> of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> is turned into a necessity of a <hi>Trien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>all one,</hi> and further, to that of an everlasting one, by an act of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation: <hi>and God hath fastened it as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:108857:43"/>
a raile in a sur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> place,</hi> and now <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> moves some degrees on.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Votes and suffrages</hi> begin to disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teresse <hi>Properie</hi> and <hi>Prelacie, Gods voice is upon the waters again,</hi> Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon Petitions from <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Countries</hi> for <hi>Reformation,</hi> a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over-powring still in the <hi>voices</hi> and <hi>votes</hi> for <hi>Reformation,</hi> both in the <hi>house,</hi> and elsewhere, Papists and popish cast out of <hi>Interest,</hi> and place in the great Counsell, the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive losing many <hi>State-advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and the <hi>Prelacy</hi> many <hi>Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The contrary <hi>designes</hi> of <hi>Jesuites</hi> and <hi>Prelates</hi> disappointed, and all turned into designes for <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Vnity</hi> with <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>severall plots</hi> defeated and discovered, which were still counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining.</p>
                  <p>That of bringing up the Army from the North at first.</p>
                  <p>That of bringing the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> to the doors of the Parliament.</p>
                  <p>That of betraying the <hi>Militia of City</hi> and Parliament, and surprizing all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:108857:43"/>
The several endeavours of betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cities, Towns Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</p>
                  <p>The corrupting Parliament Agents, and getting interests in their severall counsels and forces.</p>
                  <p>The attempts of unclasping us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to several parties.</p>
                  <p>The restoring a <hi>Parliament from the day of small things,</hi> in the generall defeatures, not long since.</p>
                  <p>The preserving the most famous <hi>City of London,</hi> which hath been like <hi>Ezekiels potters house,</hi> the place where all the <hi>wheels</hi> of Reformation moved.</p>
                  <p>And to all these, an <hi>assembly</hi> of many godly and eminent men for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing the <hi>Temple,</hi> voting out Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy and Superstition in the places where they sate voting not long since to establish it, with <hi>Oathes</hi> and <hi>Lawes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The severall successe of Battels at <hi>Keinton, Newbery, York, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Protestations</hi> and <hi>Covenants,</hi> like heavenly cordage to fasten both Parliament and Kingdomes, and make them the more <hi>stedfast and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:108857:44"/>
in the work of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The many severall preservations and successes of late, as that of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>castle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus the supernaturall interest hath wrought, and things have been as it were created and supported, by that naked <hi>power, and wisdome</hi> of <hi>God in Christ,</hi> which carried on his <hi>Church</hi> with <hi>signes</hi> and <hi>wonders,</hi> in the times of its first rising.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The spirituall Interest.</head>
                  <p>THe next interest I finde <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to have in this <hi>Kingdome</hi> is <hi>spirituall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And first the many interrupted assayes formerly by godly Divines and others in the reign both <hi>Qu. Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, Treatises, Dayes of <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>seeking God,</hi> the seed time of which light we now enjoy, <hi>light is sown f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> the righteous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The many assemblings of private
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:108857:44"/>
Christians, in latter times, their <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall contributions</hi> then of <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>humiliation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now the means of grace pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out so effectually in <hi>Preaching,</hi> and <hi>prophes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing,</hi> and prayer amongst us.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>effectual door</hi> which is opened of late, and a seeking to <hi>Sion</hi> with our faces thitherward.</p>
                  <p>The return of the <hi>banished, persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, godly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The daily seekings to heaven, in solemn humiliations.</p>
                  <p>The Gospel lightning from <hi>many Treatises, Discourses, Expositions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>sending out labourers</hi> into the harvest, the springing up of many young Prophets, as if this generation were the Seminary for the next: and to these <hi>spirituall subsidiaries</hi> in our own <hi>Kingdome,</hi> the <hi>prayers,</hi> and <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contributions</hi> of all other <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches</hi> of <hi>Germany, Geneva, New-England,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> with the Churches in <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>low Ireland,</hi> these all fall in with us into the <hi>spirituall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe</hi>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:108857:45"/>
of <hi>Reformation,</hi> we are engaged in.</p>
                  <p>This spirituall interest reaches to every <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God, to every <hi>minist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ation,</hi> to every <hi>grace,</hi> to every <hi>spirituall facultie,</hi> or power that makes towards Heaven or God, in <hi>this Kingdome,</hi> or other <hi>reformed States.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Interest is yet stronger in the Propheticall part of it, the <hi>fifth An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> now pouring out his violl on the <hi>seat of the beast</hi>: and here I dare fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Expositors to this, That <hi>Babylon</hi> is falling in the near parts of it; and for the time of the totall ruine, the Prophesie runs strongly, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters too, that is not much above six years.</p>
                  <p>To these, the meltings and dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings of <hi>customes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cant. 2.17</note> 
                     <hi>traditions, supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> for the <hi>day breaks and the sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes fly away.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The enemies filling up the <hi>measure,</hi> and <hi>Ephah,</hi> by their daily <hi>sinnes, ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries,</hi> and <hi>provocations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The work of God upon <hi>Sion</hi> and <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> or his people, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:108857:45"/>
wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s or tribulation.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nding spirituall remedy</hi> of many godly Divines, in the conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of an Assembly who like <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur,</hi> hold up the hands of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Politick or Civil Interest.</head>
                  <p>THe power and acting of the <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Supreme,</hi> in a Kingdome <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchically</hi> constituted, as this would soon give the <hi>Reformation</hi> a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and spreading Interest, as we see in one <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> and <hi>Constantine,</hi> and an <hi>Edward,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi>; therefore Princes are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>nursing Fathers,</hi> and <hi>nursing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> to the Churches of Christ: yet though we want this <hi>Interest</hi> for the present, and the <hi>personall actings</hi> of a King, yet wee have in the meane time a supplement, a <hi>Parliamentary regall power</hi> of two Kingdomes: A strong <hi>fundamentall</hi> in the work of <hi>Reformation,</hi> and a <hi>power</hi> very agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:108857:46"/>
to the constitution of both, and very naturall, for the propagating Reformation in this Kingdom, and this improved by Associations, and Covenants.</p>
                  <p>The present power, armies, and successe in most of the parts in this Kingdome, but the West; and yet some strong Interests there to.</p>
                  <p>The consideration with other <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant States</hi> and <hi>Churches,</hi> (though I could wish it more) the commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and troubles abroad, in <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> in States of <hi>Italie, Germanie, Spain, Franc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> whose engagements gives them not time, to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to our disadvantages &amp; distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; God making them to hear a <hi>rumour of war in their own land.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Further Searchings.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I. Non-comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nion, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Excommunication.</head>
                  <p>SEeing there is such a difference amongst us, concerning <hi>Non-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> and <hi>Excommunication,</hi> that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:108857:46"/>
the first is not so proportionable, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dequate, and powerfull as the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: now, that which may be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable here, is, whether it appear an Ordinance or no, and then all such consequences are saved, and the objections are but imaginary; for if it be an Ordinance, and spititually strenghened and armed from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: it is all one whether you call it <hi>Non-communion,</hi> or <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>: nor is it the weaknesse of any thing on the worldly side of it, that ought to make us prejudge it for no Ordinance, because there may be an heavenly and spirituall supplement to make up whatsoever may be suspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>II. Nationall and Congregationall.</head>
                  <p>That which makes the difference here, is, a disputing about the fittest subject for Church ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and we differ here in point of latitude and qualification; for on the one side, it is thought that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:108857:47"/>
a people nation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nts of all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>; on the other side, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly congre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; if we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, we shall see that such quali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ations are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ated by both, and such cautions, as the Ordinances are, but neither prosti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by the one, nor the other, but a due regard had to the predisposing, and preaccommodating to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, which are of a pure and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly constitution.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Concerning the Model in Scriptures.</head>
                  <p>THat which makes the controversie here, is the consideration of Gods way of policy at the first with his Church, under the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and <hi>Temple,</hi> which were all so exactly &amp; compleatly sent down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, with laws, and cautionary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, for the just observance, and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:108857:47"/>
to these under the Gospel the noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Scripture, of Kingdom, City, Family, Officers, Offices, Church-censures, Administrations, Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with many things of spirituall policy, both in principles and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, with necessary inference from Gods first method: On the other side, all this is acknowledged, yet in a little more latitude, and godly prudence is let in, for making up some<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hing where there is not a defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency suspected: but no clear prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples or rul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s revealed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pretended Heresies, Divisions.</head>
                  <p>AS we should not go about to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse or defend any errour, clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convicted, so not to condemn any thing for errour, which seems not to beare up equally to our received principles: and here wee must ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, that there are many, who when the notion of errour or heresie is abroad, are only Pentioners to the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:108857:48"/>
multitude, and measure the errour or heresie, by those that are for it or against it, and are resolved however to write that way that they see the most condemn; and these are such, who though they do not kindle, yet they blow the fire amongst us: and I have observed, that these do so overwrite a cause, that at length they improve an errour, and arme it more against the truth then it was before, by charging things on the wrong side of it, as we have seen of late: and thus while we think to gain, by letting in such a promiscuous stream of opposers, we rather lose: as in the case of some present controversies, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plain that they are rather op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed then convinced, and bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n down, then writ down: &amp; certainly, that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> makes us on all sides so far from peace, and issue, or successe: the more we dispute, is our intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perancy and unnaturall heats, in which we spend as much paper as in the cause it self: and I am sure in some differences I could name, the truth stands by, while we wrangle
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:108857:48"/>
beside it, and the dust that we raise in arguing, makes the truth lesse discern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; and that which is considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble amongst us here, is the exceeding prejudice received against <hi>difference of judgement, and divisions,</hi> not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering that it is Gods secret or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine for discovery, as well of truth as errour, and for advantaging the one, as well as disadvantaging the other. To instance in our late debates about <hi>Government,</hi> it will appear that truth is improved, and hath received ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> those very principles that seemed to oppose it; and I am sure in the case of the Antinomians, that errour about Free-grace hath drawn our Divines into more study<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and preaching it then before, and stating it clearer; and the very Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies almost of all times, have acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> advanced some particular Scripture truth. And that very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie about the Ministery recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from Bishops, hath brought forth some advantage amongst many of the godly, even a deep humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, because it came to us with a mark
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:108857:49"/>
of the beast with it: and let not any jealousie or fear of derogation or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement, cause us to fold it up without any Nationall contrition or acknowledgement, now in a season when we are laying new spirituall fundamentals, as in that late <hi>Act for Ordination:</hi> let the Prelates own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes of connivence, whose princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples dare not look the Light in the face.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Selfe indulgency: with the right use of Heresies and Errours.</head>
                  <p>FIrst, it is impossible but <hi>Heresies</hi> and <hi>Errours</hi> should be, though there be a <hi>woe</hi> upon the Authors and Abettors, so as one would think this prediction of Christ should coole us in the heat of our tumults about them, and we should make no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at that which Christ hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red us so long before hand to receive; yet here we should do as the <hi>Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> did, when their Lord had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:108857:49"/>
them of a treachery to befall him, every one said, <hi>Master is it I?</hi> this reflective disposition, or selfe-jealousie I finde much wanting in many, while every one rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>its ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at his own door, and will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther search his house himself, nor suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer another to go in without opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and thus all count their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons truth and will not do so much as suspect their own judgements, which was not the <hi>Disciples</hi> practice; and so we are forced to confute one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, while no man will confute him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and thus differences are inflamed.</p>
                  <p>And be it, that the things we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn for <hi>Heresies</hi> and <hi>Errours,</hi> be so, then there is this left us, to work up to Gods designe in such cases, and to turn them into advantages for the truth, and such a work is next to Gods, who takes in every sinne and distemper, and makes it act some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to his glorious ends, <hi>He hath commanded light to shine out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Are they Anabaptists, as they call them? Let it provoke us to awaken
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:108857:50"/>
the Scriptures more for what we do; let us study the substance of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant more, let us study Scripture inference and deductions more, let us study the correspodency of the Seals under both dispensations more, and we shall gain this, to be able to do, what we do, upon clearer and stron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger principles.</p>
                  <p>Are they Brownists or Separatists as they call them? Let it stir us up to look to our Fundamentall truths better, to our Ministery, to our Churches, to our Practices: and sure while these controversies involve us more into the Scriptures, we shall only come forth more refined and clearer in judgement and practice; and what we might possibly have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in under the notion of Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Authority, and so have enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our selves implicitely to the truths we professe, we shall now give up unto God <hi>a more reasonable sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Are they Antinomians, as some cal them? or these that cry down Law, or duties? Let us draw this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:108857:50"/>
to seek out how the riches of Free grace are offered, and how the Law is established by the Gospel, and what power of it is annulled, &amp; how Christ is to be advanced above all, and how he is all in all, and the true Fountain in whom our life is hid; and that our being in him, and he in us, is the cause of all graces and duties in us: and that our life now in grace ought to be in conformity to that we shall live hereafter in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, where being filled with Christ, we shall only live to the obedience and praise of him, for that work of justification and redemption we had by him: and let us study to give du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties their right origination, order and end, Prayer, Repentance, Obedience, &amp;c. as gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s that flow from Christ into his, and back again from his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Christ; and that we interpret all Scriptures that concern either Christ, or the Law, or Sin, or Obedience, or Duty, into the glory of God in Christ, that all our conclusions may exalt him, whom God had in designe only to exalt, <hi>To be a Prince and a Saviour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:108857:51"/>
And thus we should drive on Gods ends more then we doe, in making every thing serve his glory, and our own edification, and not dash our selves meerly one against another, and go out only in vapours of heat and opposition, which too many do.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Trials of God amongst us.</head>
                  <p>THat which is an argument of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and distraction to carnall judgements, ought to be the only confirmation and strengthening to Gods people, who live in a higher region, and stand on the vantage ground above the men of the world, and see how the designes of Heaven are managed, and are able to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern that in the creature, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are not, even a providence work which shines sorth in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture of things and affairs, like the Sun beams on the wall and first let it be no wonder that God is in the midst of troubles and tumults, <hi>I will
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:108857:51"/>
shake all Nations,</hi> sayes God, and then it follows, <hi>the desire of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (or Christ) shall come before me</hi>;<note place="margin">Hag. 2 7.</note> and when he was with <hi>Israel</hi> he was in a <hi>cloud</hi> and <hi>fire</hi> at one time,<note place="margin">Exo. 19 9.</note> in <hi>lightning</hi> and <hi>thunder</hi> at another;<note place="margin">1 Kin 19.12.</note> and when with his Prophet, <hi>there went a whirlewinde and fire before kim,</hi> and the Spirit of God which knowes Gods manner of presence best, sets him forth thus,<note place="margin">Psal. 50.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Our God shall come, a fire shall devoure him, and it shall be very tempestuous round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him:</hi> when he was with <hi>Gideon</hi> and his people, it was so, as he could see little of him, <hi>If the Lord be with us, why then is all this befallen us?</hi> when, <hi>with his people in captivity,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Judg. 6.1</note> it was so as the Prophet could say, <hi>Can these dry bones live?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eze. 37.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> When with his Disciples, it was so, as <hi>there was no comelinesse in him, he was not desira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>: when with his Apostles,<note place="margin">Isay 53.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> he strook the <hi>room with a whirlewinde,</hi> and <hi>enlightned it with fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>See Gods method and goings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore amongst his people, and you shall trace him now in the same spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:108857:52"/>
and providentiall impressions.</p>
                  <p>First, in our <hi>Parliamentary</hi> &amp; <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Assembly,</hi> and the rising of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to <hi>build the Temple of God</hi>; so it was before, when the Temple in type was raised, <hi>and the Lord stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel the sonne of She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathiel, Governour of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua the son of Josedech the high Priest,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>and the spirit of all the remnant of the people, and they came, and did work in the house of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the beginnings of the war, when a few Delinquents drew in so great a party to the Kings party, &amp; when so many revolted from the work; so it was before in that of <hi>Gibe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> which got in the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> to their quarrell against all <hi>Israel.</hi> And in that of <hi>Abijah</hi> and <hi>Jerobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> when <hi>Jeroboam</hi> was <hi>four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thousand men more then Judah:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Chron.</note> 
                     <hi>but there were gathered to them vain men, the children of Relial, who thought to withstand the kingdom of the Lord, with whom was a great multitude, and golden Calves, who cast out the Priests of the Lord But
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:108857:52"/>
with Abijah was the Lord God, and the Priests which minister unto the Lord, and they which burn sacrifice morning and evening, and which soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded trumpets to cry alarm against ye, O children of Israel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Contributions brought into the work of the Lord, as the Plate, Money, Jewels, Levies, Loanes.<note place="margin">Neh. 7.</note> So it was before, when some of the chiefe of the Fathers gave unto the work, and the rest of the people, twenty thousand drams of gold and silver.</p>
                  <p>In the divers successe the enemies had in the proceding of this War: So it was before when the <hi>Sons of Belial in Gibeah</hi> involved a whole Tribe into their quarrel,<note place="margin">Judg. 20.</note> and got the better of it in divers battels.</p>
                  <p>In the battels and victories we had in many places, as <hi>Edge kill</hi> &amp; <hi>York,</hi> where our multitude did not deliver us. So it was before in <hi>Gideons,</hi> when God took off his Army to three hundred, and then gave him the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse against his enemies.</p>
                  <p>In other particular deliverances of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:108857:53"/>
besieged places, as <hi>Bradford, Hul, Lime, Glocester.</hi> So it was in <hi>Ziph.</hi> in <hi>Keilah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m. 23.</note> in <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> when God caused <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Senache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ib</hi> to hear a rumour of war to divert them from the siege.<note place="margin">Isa 36.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>In our divisions about some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture truths, in our murmurings and disputings, and our wayes of conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation by an Assembly. So it was before amongst the Brethren, till a Councell at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> reconciled them: So amongst the <hi>Grecians</hi> and the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> till the Brethren were called together to consider of it.</p>
                  <p>In the discoveries of Conspiracies and Plots against Parliament, and City, and Armies. So it was with <hi>Israel,</hi> when <hi>Elisha</hi> discovered the councels of the <hi>Syrians</hi>: So with <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> when <hi>Sanballats</hi> and <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iabs</hi> plots were revealed: So with the <hi>Iewes,</hi> when <hi>Hamans</hi> was disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and defeated: So with <hi>Abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons,</hi> when <hi>Achitophels</hi> was tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>d into folly. <hi>The Lord is known by the judgements that hee executes: the wicked is snared in the works of their own hands.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:108857:53"/>
In stirring up the younger sort in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to attempts against the Armies and enemies of God. So it was before, when <hi>Ahab</hi> said, <hi>By Whom? And he said, Even by the young men of the Princes of the Provinces.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g. 20.34.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>In raising up new Armies after dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfitures and losses; as in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rout we had throughout the Kingdome not long since, when our Southern, Western, and Northern Armies were scattered. So it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when <hi>Israel</hi> had losse after losse in their way to <hi>Canaan,</hi> and still re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruited by the power of their God.</p>
                  <p>In carrying on the cause through windings &amp; turnings through losses and victories, making us a mutuall scourge to one another, dashing us both in pieces, and repairing us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and thus keeping up a standing affliction amongst us, till his work be finished on Mount <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion, &amp; his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on his enemies. So it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when <hi>Israel</hi> and <hi>Iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h</hi> were engaged against each other: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o it was with <hi>Ionahs</hi> ship, when they rowed hard to shore, but they could
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:108857:54"/>
not, <hi>for the winde blew and was tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestuous against them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>God standing in these times.</head>
                  <p>THey that would see God in this work, must consider the <hi>spiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> of the <hi>designe,</hi> and Gods way of <hi>mysterious acting,</hi> and not let them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves down into the creature, and think that the breaking of an Army, or a Party, breaks Gods designe; for it remains the same <hi>yesterday</hi> and <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>day,</hi> and <hi>the same for ever</hi>; and God takes in miscarriages, disadvantages, and improbabilities, and seeming impossibilities, and treacheries, and enemies workings, and makes them all work into his purpose: He took in a treacherie at the compleating of the spirituall designe of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a <hi>Iudas</hi> must accidentally, though wofully, help in the work of our salvation. So that if we would but study Gods designe concerning his Church and method, and rise up
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:108857:54"/>
higher then the creature &amp; the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures method in our conceptions, and look on the other side of it, we should not be at such losses and stands, and in such despondencies and discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements as we are: And while we grasp at the creature too fast, either at Agents, or Armies, or Counsels, God many times (as we experience) drawes them either off from us, or us from them.</p>
                  <p>Again, we must look at <hi>Gods stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> amongst us: He is not now as he appeared to <hi>Israel</hi> on the Mountain, <hi>with a clear paved work of a Saphire under his feet</hi>; but he is now as he was before in the visions, he stands <hi>in the bottome among the Mirtle trees, on a red horse,</hi> so shaded as none but his own can see him; <hi>His spirit</hi> is in the <hi>wheeles,</hi> and <hi>one wheele</hi> within a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: He walks in the midst of the seven golden Candlesticks, yet none but a Disciple sees him. The work of Church providence is intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and perplexed; so it was when the <hi>Iewes</hi> were his people, and now it is when the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:108857:55"/>
too: so it was in the <hi>first part</hi> of his <hi>work</hi> about his <hi>Church,</hi> and so it is in this <hi>second p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rt</hi> of his <hi>work</hi> too; for it is all but <hi>one work,</hi> only in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall complexions and methods, to <hi>Israel</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="maxims">
            <head>Maximes of REFOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MATION.</head>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s engagement for deliverance.</head>
               <p>WHen the people of God are under any spirituall or civill oppression, God will be sure to be mindefull of them, designing some course for their deliverance, not in the way of his common providence, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the engagement that he hath laid upon himself by covenant: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd in this his season of thoughts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, their sighes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of soul do move him and put him on, and actuate his wisdome into experiments.<note place="margin">Exod. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3, 34, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>And the childre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Israel sighed by reason of bondage, &amp; they cried, &amp; their cry came up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:108857:55"/>
God and God heard their groaning, and remembred his covenant, and had respect unto them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Eminent workin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</head>
               <p>When God sets himself to deliver a people, he comes towards some of them in some eminent working, and engages them to go before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Come therefore, and I will send thee unto Pharaoh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>that thou maist bring forth my people.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Disp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rehand.</head>
               <p>When God intends actually to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large a people, he layes in dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons beforehand into the hearts of the Princes and Elders, so that all their motions shall fall easily into such conjunctures as tend that way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And they shall hearken unto thy voice, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u shalt come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exo. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>thou and the Elders of Israel.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Gods designe upon obstructions.</head>
               <p>When the Lord is upon the work of enlargement and bringing out his people, he often allowes the obstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which their enemies cast in,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:108857:56"/>
and yet goes on to make up his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious designe of their impediments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I am sure the King of Epypt will not let you go,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exo. 3.19.</note> 
                  <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, not by a mighty hand.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Mutuall concurrences.</head>
               <p>The Lord in the great designe of leading forth his people, acts both the Elders and Ministers into mutuall concurrences and strengthnings of each other, that the failing of each may be made up by the others sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And Aaron shall be thy spokesman unto the people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exo. 4.16.</note> 
                  <hi>and he shall be to thee in stead of a mouth, and thou shalt be to him in stead of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Some experiments eccentrick to Gods time.</head>
               <p>There are oftentimes certain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments which the people of God make in their way to deliverances before the fulnesse of time come: But still there is such a want of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondency in the things they look for, that they make no proceeding, but faile, being eccentrick to Gods time of successe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:108857:56"/>
                  <hi>He supposed his brethren would have understood how that God by his hand would deliver them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 7.25</note> 
                  <hi>but they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood not.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Successe through disadvantages.</head>
               <p>When God stirs up a people to go out from bondage, he gives the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my the liberty of obstructing and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and drawes forth his people through many windings and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; so as their passage is not even and direct, but their successe is made up of disadvantages, of contrarieties, and improbabilities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He brought them out,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 7.36.</note> 
                  <hi>after that he had shewed signes and wonders in the land of Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The season of seeking God.</head>
               <p>When tidings of publick calamity are abroad, then is the season of seeking God, and enquiring after sin, and putting God in minde of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants and engagements that hee stands in to his people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And they said unto me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 1.3, 4, 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that are left of the captivity there in the Province, are in great affliction and reproach; the wall of Hierusalem
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:108857:57"/>
also is broken down: and it came to passe when I heard these things, that I sate down and wept, and prayed, and I said, I beseech thee O Lord remember now these are thy servants whom thou hast redeemed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Relations for advantaging the cause of God.</head>
               <p>We must observe all our relations in publick times, and see how we are placed for advantaging the cause of God, and we must put forward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very engagement, still keeping an eye upon him for directing our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes to his own ends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prosper I pray thee thy servant this day,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 1.11</note> 
                  <hi>and grant him mercy in the sight of this man: for I was the Kings Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>When to impart th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appearances of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</head>
               <p>That which will exceedingly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the spirits of people to publick endeavours, is a wise imparting the severall preparations that God hath made, and the appearances of God to the rises and beginnings that are attempted; for men are the easilyer
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:108857:57"/>
drawn to engage there, where they see God ingaging first.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then I told them of the hand of my God which was good upon me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 2.18</note> 
                  <hi>as also the Kings words that he had spoken unto me, and they sayed, let us rise up and build: so they strengthened their hands for this good work.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Treating with few, and a just survey.</head>
               <p>In the first designing of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is good treating only with few at first, and that in secret, and to take as just a survey of the necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as you can.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I arose in the night,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>I and some few men with me, neither told I any man what God had put in my heart, to do at Jerusalem: neither was there any beast with me, save the beast that I rode upon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Let your enemies see your interest.</head>
               <p>When the enemies of God are beginning to plot against the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of Reformation, the safest is to let them see the interest you rest on, and that your judgement and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:108857:58"/>
resolution is seated higher then to bee easily taken downe with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, or scandals, or practices.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But when</hi> Sanballat <hi>the Horonite,<note place="margin">Neh. 2.19 20.</note> and</hi> Tobiah <hi>the servant the Ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and</hi> Geshem <hi>the Arabian heard it, they laughed us to scorn, and despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed us, and said, what is this thing that you do, will you rebell against the King? Then answered I them, and said unto them, the God of Heaven he will prosper us; therefore we his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants will arise and build: but you have no portion, nor right, nor memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall in</hi> Jerusalem.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Holy preparations, foundations, for Reformation.</head>
               <p>In the work of Reformation, your beginnings and foundations, must be layed in prayer and holy preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the works of God must be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced in the wayes of God, and Reformation must go up in sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then</hi> Eliashib <hi>the High Priest rose up with his Brethren,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>the Priests, and they built the sheepgate, they sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, and set up the doors of it even
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:108857:58"/>
unto the tower of Meah, they sanctified it unto the tower of Hananell.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Watching with both eyes.</head>
               <p>In the practices of the enemy, we must watch with both eyes, one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, &amp; the other towards the work we have to doe; though God is able to fortifie the weakest proceedings, and shade them from violence: yet we must not so tempt God for extraordinaries, as we take not the ordinaries he provides us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neverthelesse we made our prayer unto our God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 4.9.</note> 
                  <hi>and set a watch against them day and night because of them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The time of the strongest conspiracies.</head>
               <p>The times of the enemies strongest &amp; most effectual conspiracies, is then, when the work of Reformation ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in some successe and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But it came to passe, that when</hi> Sanballat and Tobiah,<note place="margin">Neh. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians, and the Ammonites, and the Ashdodites, heard that the wals of</hi> Jerusalem <hi>were made up, and that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:108857:59"/>
the breaches began to be stopped, then they were very wroth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>When Reformation is violent.</head>
               <p>When a people are superstitiously principled,<note place="margin">2 Cro. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and Nationally conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, reformation is but violent, and formall, and they turn only by a power from without, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And yet for all this,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 3.10.</note> 
                  <hi>her treacherous sister Iudah hath not turned unto me with her whole heart, but fainedly, saith the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>How people coole.</head>
               <p>When the people are all on a flame in Reformation, they coole as soon upon intermissions, and obstructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for such heats are but moods and passions. <hi>O Ephraim what shall I do unto thee</hi>?<note place="margin">Hos. 6.4.</note> 
                  <hi>O Iudah what shall I do unto thee? For your goodnesse is as a morning cloud, and as the early dew it goeth away.</hi> As in the time of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah,</hi> when they killed <hi>Baals</hi> Priests one day, and would have killed <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> the next.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Dispensations of right principles.</head>
               <p>That a Reformation which is last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:108857:59"/>
must bee sure to abound with dispensation of right princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and there must such courses be projected, as the light may be disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed amongst the people, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests must be sought for,<note place="margin">2 Cro. 17.8, 9.</note> by laying in good principles to work out the bad.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And with them he sent Levites, and they taught in Iudah,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Carnall reasonings in Reformation.</head>
               <p>Take heed of carnall reasonings in Reformation, they will soonest weaken the hands, for there is scarce any Reformation but it will hold out some parts which may offend the darker side of judgements or opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, there was so much in <hi>Ezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> as might have stumbled some, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the very Serpent which <hi>Moses</hi> set up was broken down; and so much in <hi>Christs,</hi> because he put down <hi>Moses</hi> and the Law, which God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self had given, though he did but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed fulfill it, and so much in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, because they were men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out learning, which turned back the Pharisees and Rulers that they could
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:108857:60"/>
not believe in him; and so much in ours now, because old customes, and old laws, and old traditions are bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken down.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The designe of Fixation.</head>
               <p>In times of Reformation, there must be an eminent designe amongst many others, and that is the designe of fixation, which must be advanced by all spirituall and civill meanes: This Kingdome hath most need of that, for they have still changed Religion with the change of succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors: and yet this designe of fixation must be so cautionary and provisio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, as may let them out to higher degrees of Reformation, this was <hi>Israels</hi> and <hi>Iudahs</hi> case,<note place="margin">Hos. 64.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> a <hi>recovering</hi> and <hi>backsliding</hi> with the succession of good and bad Princes? <hi>Oh Iudah what shall I do unto thee? for your goodnesse is as the morning cloud, and as the early dew it goeth away.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Reformation times.</head>
               <p>Reformation times prove often very hard and expensive times, and times of murmuring; yet that should not make for discouragement, but redresse.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:108857:60"/>
                  <hi>And there was a great cry of the people: some there were that said,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 3.4, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>We have morgaged our lands: some also that said, We have borrowed money. Then I consulted with my self.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In publick engagements particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar interests must be laid by, and the yoke of oppressions taken off, and the cause of God must take up all: they that build their own houses and the Temple together, are no fit workmen for a spirituall fabrick.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I rebuked the Nobles and Elders,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>and said unto them, You exact usury, restore</hi> I <hi>pray you, unto them their lands and their vineyards.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>A sad Preferment.</head>
               <p>They that are called out to the publick, ought to let all their designs and endeavours run in such a chanel as may flow thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther, and not to stream back, or aside, in any other course. It is a sad preferment to be enriched w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> the calamity of Church or State, and to build up your own ship with the broken planks of the Kingdomes vessels; or to settle your own inheritance, before the publicks.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:108857:61"/>
                  <hi>But the former Governours were chargeable unto the people,<note place="margin">Neh. 5.16 17.</note> and had taken of their bread and wine, besides forty shekels of silver: but so did not</hi> I, <hi>because of the fear of the Lord</hi>; I <hi>also continued in the work of the Lord,</hi> I <hi>also continued in the work of the Lord, neither bought we any land.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>No hearkening to pretences.</head>
               <p>It is no safe hearkening or turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aside to the pretences of those whom you are not assured of to be cordiall in the work: Such only make out either to stand in your way, or to break the strength of your applic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to the publick.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then Sanballat and Geshem sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t to me, saying, Come let us meet together: bug</hi> I <hi>sent, saying,</hi> I <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> doing a great work, why should the work cease whilst</hi> I <hi>leave it?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Imaginary dangers.</head>
               <p>The fears and jealousies, and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary dangers, are usually the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances of the enemy, nor ought they to be reckoned further into the common work, then cautious for strengthening; they that account
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:108857:61"/>
them as other serve not so much the designe of God, as the Enemies:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For they all made us afraid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 6.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>that we might do so, and sin, and there they might have matter for an evil report.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Astonishment from God.</head>
               <p>The more that God is sought to, the more of astonishment will the successe have in it, and the more wonder and fear will it shed upon the hearts of the despisers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now therefore, O my God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 6.9.10, 16, 17.18.</note> 
                  <hi>strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en my hands, and, O my God, think thou on Tobiah. So the wall was fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, and they were much cast down in their own eyes, for they perceived that this work was wrought of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Secret workings.</head>
               <p>The greatest hinderances, are the secret and inward workings by such who hold correspondency with some without: and if the work be Gods, there will be many of these: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore relations, alliances &amp; dependen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ought to be carefully lookt to; for the Enemy winds in at these, to betray and act by.<note place="margin">Neh. 6.1.18,</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Nobles of Judah sent many
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:108857:62"/>
letters unto Tobiah, and the letters of Tobiah came to them, and there were many in Judah sworne unto him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he was the son in law of Sheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah. Heavenly instruments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the safest and most harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the work of God, to imploy such agents as have much of God in them: Heavenly work is the best set on by heavenly instruments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then I gave my brother Hanaeniah the Ruler of the Palace, charge over Jerusalem, for he was a faithfull man, and feared God above many,</hi> Neh. 7.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Publick designations.</head>
               <p>In publick designations to place or imployment, it is good ordering and disposing men abroad, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their nearest relations and interests.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And appoint watches of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of Jerusalem, every one in his watch, &amp; every one to be over against his own house,</hi> Neh. 7.3.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Originations.</head>
               <p>In the proceedings of the business of God, he hath his speciall times of working, of new beginnings, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:108857:62"/>
originations: for God is never at such a losse, but he knowes where to begin: and therefore we fall ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry short of Gods designe, in doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and despondencies, seeing that he is so immediate and infinite an Agent as he is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And my God put into my heart to gather together the Nobles and the Rulers, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Gods Treasurers.</head>
               <p>Gods work is of that nature, that drawes out the strength and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of all sorts, and God only seems to lay up provisions amongst his people for such a time: Men are but treasurers for God, and must o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their coffers, when providence puts the key into their hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And some of the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iefe of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers gave unto the worke, and that which the rest of the people gave, was twenty thousand drams of gold, &amp;c.</hi> Neh, 7.72, 73.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Also we made ordinances for us to charge our selvs yearly for the service of the house of our God,</hi> Neh. 10.32.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Scriptures openly consulted.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:108857:63"/>
It is the surest way, to consult the Scriptures of God, and finde out the minde of him in every part of our way to Reformation; and to draw out those principles there, which the people are to work by: The more light the multitude see from thence, the more firmly and faithfully will they walk.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And Ezra opened the book in the fight of the people day by day, from the first day unto the last day he read in the book of the law of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The mixed, or Neutralists.</head>
               <p>There ought to be a godly and faithfull care in the times of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, to discriminate and sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate those that are mixed or Neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists, for they are such as stand in the way; and if the businesse flow into their orbe of negotiation, there it sticks and is retarded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In those dayes saw I also Jewes that had maried wives of Ashdod, of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and Moab: and their children spake half in the speech of Ashdod, and could not speak in the Jewes language: And I contended with them, and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:108857:63"/>
smote them,</hi> Neh. 13.23, 24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Prayer beforehand.</head>
               <p>When we expect God down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst us to do some great thing for his Church, then should be the sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of our holy assemblings &amp; meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: and it is a signe of Gods imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate following, when he sends out a spirit of Prayer and Supplication beforehand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then returned they unto Jerusalem, and all continued with one accord in prayer and supplication.</hi> Act. 1.12, 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Publick appointments.</head>
               <p>In publick appointments there is much godly prudence in selecting those that are not experimentally known amongst us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore of those men which have accompanied with us all the time, must one be ordained to be a witnes,</hi> Act. 1.21</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Resort and consociate.</head>
               <p>When evident dangers and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions are in the way, then it is good for the people of God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort and consociate, and to make the maine part of their designe a communicating of the state of their
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:108857:64"/>
affairs to God, for they relate most to him, and it is the fittest to impart to him those impediments what he can only remove.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And being let go they went unto their own company, and when they heard that, they lift up their voyce to God with one accord, &amp;c.</hi> Acts 4.23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Differences composed.</head>
               <p>Differences amongst the godly are best healed, and composed by the godly, and meetings or gatherings of the people of God are remedies very agreeable to the distemper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There arose a murmuring of the</hi> Grecians,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. 6.1, 2</note> 
                  <hi>against the</hi> Hebrews <hi>Then the twelve called the multitude of the Disciples together.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Spirituall provid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce.</head>
               <p>When once the Gospel hath been admitted, there must be a spirituall providence used, not only for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating, but strengthening and establishing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heard that Samaria had received the word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cts 8.14</note> 
                  <hi>they sent uato them</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> John.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>An eminent Agent.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:108857:64"/>
If there be any one agent whom God hath eminently engaged and prospered in his work, there ought to be an eminent care for his preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and accommodation, least the light fall out if the candlestick be broken.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And they watched the gates day and night to kill him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 19.24, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>then the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples took him by night, and let him down by the wall in a basket.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Gracious seasons.</head>
               <p>When the Lord gives any gracious seasons to his people from troubles or persecutions, those times must be only Spirituall, else the people of God come not up to his ends in the mercies received, and it may be just with God to break off such seasons, when they are no better acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then had the Churches rest and were edified,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 19.31.</note> 
                  <hi>walking in the fear of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Care in communicating.</head>
               <p>Where any thing is acted by any of the people of God, by a more then ordinary light, there ought to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:108857:65"/>
be much care in communicating and clearing up to the mindes of darker Brethren, the reasons and grounds of such actings, and no such dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings or contendings as may rather ravell out a controversie, then guide into any orderly information.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And when</hi> Peter <hi>was come up,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 11.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>they of the circumcision contended with him. And</hi> Peter <hi>rehearsed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> matter from the beginning, and expounded it by order unto them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The whole counsels of God.</head>
               <p>It is godly prudence, to prepare people in their way to reformation, with telling them as well of the Crosse as the Crown, and to open the true constitution of things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and this i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to publish the whole counsels of God, and to lay in a principle of patience, and premoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before any thing come to passe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They returned again,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 14.22.</note> 
                  <hi>and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the soules of the Disciples, and exhorting them to continue in the faith, and that through much tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation we must enter into the kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:108857:65"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
