<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse made by the Ld Bishop of Rochester to the clergy of his diocese at his visitation in the year 1695 : published at their request.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Rochester. Bishop (1684-1713 : Sprat)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-03">2003-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5031</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39999</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18595896</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18595896</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108092</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A61157)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108092)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1102:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse made by the Ld Bishop of Rochester to the clergy of his diocese at his visitation in the year 1695 : published at their request.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Rochester. Bishop (1684-1713 : Sprat)</author>
                  <author>Sprat, Thomas, 1635-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. Jones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In the Savoy [London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVI [1696]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title page reads: The Ld Bishop of Rochester's discourse to his clergy, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Pastoral theology --  Anglican Communion.</term>
               <term>Visitation sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-12</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108092:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108092:1"/>
            <p>THE
L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rochester</hi>'s
DISCOURSE
TO
His Clergy, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108092:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108092:2"/>
            <p>A
DISCOURSE
Made by the L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Bishop
OF
ROCHESTER
TO THE
Clergy of his Diocese,
AT
<hi>His Visitation in the Year</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>Published at their Request.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the SAVOY:</hi>
Printed by <hi>Edw. Iones,</hi> MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:108092:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:108092:3"/>
            <head>A
DISCOURSE
MADE BY
The L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Bishop of Rochester
TO THE
CLERGY, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>I Can scarce think it worth my while, or
yours, (my good Brethren,) that I
should now spend much time in any
long general Exhortation, to your Diligent
and Conscientious performing the Duties
incumbent on you, as you are <hi>the Ministers
of GOD, duly called according to the Will of
of our Lord</hi> Christ, <hi>and the Order of this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>Did I find, there were here any absolute
need to use many Words, towards the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing
your Care in the several Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108092:4"/>
of your Holy Calling; yet, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suaded,
I my self might well spare my own
Labour, and your Patience, on this Subject;
since all that kind of wholesome Advice has
been already so very sufficiently, and so much
better given you, in Arguments deduced
out of the Holy Scriptures, and most fitly
applied to this Purpose, by the venerable
Compilers of our Public Liturgy, in the
Forms appointed for the Ordering of Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons
and Priests.</p>
            <p>There, you know, this Work has been so
wisely, and so fully, long ago, done to a
Bishop's hands; there all the Parts of your
weighty Office are so judiciously laid before
you; the high Dignity, and great Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
of it, towards the Salvation of Mankind, is
so substantially urg'd; the blessed Fruits, and
everlasting Rewards of well-attending it, and
the extreme Dangers of neglecting it, are so
justly amplified; the Necessity of adorning
your Doctrine by an innocent, virtuous,
and pious Life of your own, towards the
rendring it efficacious on the Lives of others,
is so pathetically inforc'd; that, I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
the very best Charge, a Bishop could
give to his Clergy, were to recommend se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108092:4"/>
to all their Memories, as I now do
most affectionately to yours, those very same
Questions and Answers, those very same Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises
and Vows, as you ought to esteem them,
where-with every one of you did most so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly
charge his Conscience, at the time of
your Admission into Holy Orders.</p>
            <p>I profess, I cannot, nor, I believe, can the
the Wit of Man, invent any more proper
Method of Instruction to Men in your Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances,
from a Man in mine, than to
exhort you all to a continual Recollection
of, and Meditation upon, those many and
great Obligations, you then seem'd volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily
and cheerfully to lay on your selves.</p>
            <p>Whence there could not but ensue (by
GOD's Blessing,) a firm Resolution in
your Minds to endeavour the performance
of them, and a Holy Perseverance in those
Endeavours, and in Conclusion, the happy
Effects of all on your selves, and the Flocks
committed to you: That by thus <hi>Meditating
on these Things, and giving your selves wholly
to them, your profiting may appear to all; and
that by taking heed to your selves, and your
Doctrines, and continuing in them, you may
both save your selves, and those that hear you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:108092:5"/>Wherefore seeing that, which else had
been a Bishop's proper Business in such
Meetings as this, I hope, is, or may be so
easily shorten'd for me, by you your selves,
by your having recourse to a Rule so well
known, and so obvious to you, in a Book,
which ought scarce ever to be out of your
hands; I shall the rather, at this time, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely
omit the prescribing you many Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions,
touching the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>substance</hi>
of the Duties of your Sacred Function.
Instead of them, I shall only offer you some few
familiar Considerations, which may serve as
so many friendly and brotherly Advices, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning,
chiefly, the <hi>Manner</hi> and <hi>Way</hi> of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming
some of the principal Offices of
your Ministry.</p>
            <p>And, I trust in GOD, that if these Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices
shall be as carefully examin'd, and, if
you find them useful, as industriously obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
by you, as they are honestly intended
by me, they may, in some sort, enable you
to do laudably, and with Commendation,
the same Things, which, I hope, you already
do, without just Exception.</p>
            <p>Only, in this place, let me premise once
for all, that whatever Instructions I shall now
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108092:5"/>
give you, I intend them not only as Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
to you, but especially to my self. As
indeed, in all Matters, that come under De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation,
he ought to be esteem'd no good
Counsellor, who is very ready and eager in
giving, but averse from receiving the same
Counsel, as far as it may be also proper for
himself.</p>
            <p>The first Advice I presume to set before
your view, shall relate to the <hi>Manner</hi> of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
your part, in all the ordinary Offices of
the Public Liturgy.</p>
            <p>As to that, it is my earnest Request, that
you would take very much Care, and use
extraordinary Intention of Mind, to perfect
your selves in a true, just, sensible, accurate
becoming way of Reading, and administring
them as you have occasion.</p>
            <p>A Suggestion, which some perhaps, at
first hearing, may think to be but of a slight
and ordinary Concernment: Yet, if I am not
much deceiv'd, it will be found of exceeding
Moment and Consequence in its Practice;
and of singular Usefulness towards the raising
of Devotion in any Congregation piously
inclined: When your weekly, or rather daily
labours of this kind shall be thus performed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:108092:6"/>
I mean, not with a meer formal or artificial,
but with such a grave, unaffected Delivery
of the Words, as (if the defect be not in
our selves,) will, indeed, naturally flow
from a right and serious considering of their
Sense.</p>
            <p>I pray therefore, take my Mind a-right in
this particular. I do not only mean, that
you should be very punctual in reading the
<hi>Common Prayer</hi> Book, as the Law requires;
that is, not only to do it constantly, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely
in each part, without any maiming,
adding to, or altering of it, that so <hi>Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,
Prayers, Intercessions, and giving of
Thanks, may be made,</hi> by you, <hi>for all Men:
For Kings, and for all that are in Authority;
that we may lead a quiet and peaceable Life in
all Godliness and Honesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you do not so, you are liable to a Legal
Punishment and Censure. But my aim now
is, not meerly to prevent that, or to provide
only against your breaking the Law. What
I intend is something higher, and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent;
something, that you cannot be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish'd
for, tho' you do it not; but, if you
shall do it in any reasonable Perfection, it will
redound to the unspeakable Benefit of your
Congregations.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:108092:6"/>The purpose then of this my plain Motion
to you is, in short, to beseech you all to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy
much serious Pains, in practising the
public and private Reading of all your Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
as the Use of any of them shall occur,
distinctly, gravely, affectionately, fervently;
so as every where to give them all that Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour,
Life and Spirit, whereof they are
capable: Which certainly is as great as in
any human Writings whatsoever; if we be
not wanting to them in the Repetition.</p>
            <p>The Truth is, whatever some may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
to the contrary, such a compleat and
consummate Faculty of reading the <hi>Common
Prayer, Quam nequeo monstrare, &amp; sentio tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi>
is of so great difficulty, as well as use,
that I am fully convinced, it very well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves
to have some place among our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
Studies; at least in the first Initiation
into our Ministry, if not throughout the
whole course of it.</p>
            <p>I could heartily wish, it were altogether
needless for me to lay so much stress on this
Advice as I do. Yet, I hope, I may do it
without Offence; since it is not with design
of censuring any particular Mens Failings or
Deficiencies, but only for the public Good;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108092:7"/>
that we may all strive to attain not only to
a Mediocrity, but to an Excellency in this
kind: Which, in my small Judgment, can
never be done, unless we shall make this Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
a Business by it self, and assign it a special
Place among our other Ecclesiastical Studies.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denied, but the Church it
self has provided for this with all imaginable
Circumspection; having solemnly enjoin'd
every Clergy-man, besides the Times of his
public Ministry, to read some very conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Parts of his Office, once a day, at least,
to himself, except he shall be excused by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dispensable
Business.</p>
            <p>By which wise Injunction, tho', no doubt,
the Church intended primarily to produce
and increase, in the Minds of all its Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,
a frame of Spirit perpetually serious
and devout: Yet, if that be also accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied
with a proportionable Regard to the
Manner, as well as to the Matter of our
Public Prayers, this other Advantage of
well-reading, what is so often to be read, will
follow of course, and by necessary Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
            <p>It seems indeed to me, that the very way
of performing all the outward Acts of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108092:7"/>
has so wonderful an Influence towards
obtaining the inward Effects of it, on our
Hearts and Consciences, that I cannot but
think, we can never be too laborious in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring
and exercising our Thoughts, and
even our very Voices, in private, for a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic
Service of so great Importance.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, we generally value and esteem
Preaching, as our great Privilege and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.
And so far we are in the right. But
we are not so, if we look on the reading of
Prayers only as our Task and Burthen; and,
as such, shall be willing to get rid of it alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
or to get thro' it in any undecent
Manner, with such Heaviness or Precipitation,
as, in any Affairs of worldly Interest, we
would never be content with.</p>
            <p>A preposterous Custom, which, if due Care
be not taken, may be very prejudicial and
mischievous to our Church, by quenching
the Spirit of Devotion in our own People,
and giving occasion to our Adversaries to
throw Scorn and Contempt on our other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise-incomparable
<hi>Liturgy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Consider, I pray you, How can we expect
that others should revere, or esteem it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to its true worth, if we our selves will
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108092:8"/>
not keep it so much in Countenance,
as to afford it a fair Reading? If we will
not do it so much common Justice as to
contribute, as much as lies in our Power,
that it may have an impartial Hearing, equal,
at least to any other Divine Ordinance? If
we shall refuse to lay as much weight on
those Devotions, which our whole Church
has injoin'd us to pour out before the
Throne of Grace, for the People, as we do
on those Discourses, which we make, on our
own Heads, to the People?</p>
            <p>Wherefore, I say again, this very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable
Skill of devout and decent Reading
the Holy Offices of the Church, is so far
from being a perfunctory or superficial Work,
a mean or vulgar Accomplishment, or a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate
lower Administration, only fit for
a Curate; that it deserves to be placed
among your Ministerial Endowments of
greater Superiority and Praeeminence; as
being one of the most powerful Instruments
of the Holy Spirit of GOD, to raise and
command Mens Hearts and Affections: of
the Holy true Spirit of GOD, I say; which,
tho' in our inward Ejaculations, or private
Supplications towards Heaven, it often <hi>helpeth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108092:8"/>
our Infirmities, and maketh Intercession for us
with Groanings that cannot be uttered;</hi> Yet, in
the public Worship, is most frequently
pleased to operate by such Words, and
Sounds, as are express'd with the best Ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance.</p>
            <p>So that now, with a just Assurance, I may
assert this to be a very proper Qualification
of a Parochial Minister; that he has attain'd
to an habitual Faculty of setting forth the
public Prayers to all their due Advantage, by
pronouncing them leasurably, fitly, warmly,
decently; with such an Authority in the
Speaker, as is, in some degree, suitable to
the Authority of what is spoken.</p>
            <p>Thus much I may safely say, that the
Reader of the Prayers; if he does his part,
in the manner I have mention'd, by such a
vigorous, effectual, fervent Delivery of the
Words and Conceptions, put into his Mouth
by the Church it self, may give a new en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livening
Breath, a new Soul, as it were, to
every Prayer, every Petition in it: He may
quicken and animate those Confessions, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercessions
and Thanksgivings, which, when
read coldly, and indifferently, with irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
Carlesness, or ignorant Flatness, will
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108092:9"/>
seem to some to be but a dead Letter: He
may make every Hymn, every Psalm, every
Lesson, Epistle and Gospel, to become well
nigh a new Sermon; at least he may give,
to the old standing Text of the Bible, a very
good clear Exposition, even by his very way
of reading it to the Congregation.</p>
            <p>This, upon Experience, you will find to
be apparently true. For if, as is usually ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served
by Men of Learning, in printed
Books, the very accurate and critical pointing
of the Copy is one of the best kinds of good
new Commentaries on any old Author;
how much more, in all the Offices of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion,
would that, which consists not only
in good Pointing, and observing all due
Stops, but in so much more besides, I mean
a good, distinct, forcible, yet easie, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced
reading of every Prayer, and Portion
of the Holy Scriptures; how much more
would all this really serve for a good new
Paraphrase and Illustration of every Sentence
in them!</p>
            <p>It is indeed almost incredible, how quite
another thing the daily morning and evening
Prayers will appear; what new Figures and
Beauties, and hidden Treasures of sacred
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108092:9"/>
Eloquence, they will continually discover,
when thus pronounc'd; how much apter
they will be to kindle in us, and our Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,
all manner of Heavenly Affections, of
Spiritual Grief, and Contrition, of Love and
Gratitude, of Faith, Hope, and Charity,
and Joy in the Holy Ghost; When the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
of the Tongue shall be tuned, as it
were, to the Harmony of the Matter;
When the Zeal of the Reader shall keep Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
with his Voice; and his Voice shall be adap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to, and varied together with every Sense
and Expression; When by long Use, and Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the best Masters, or the best we can
come at, we shall know familiarly how to
give every Word and Sentence its due poise;
Where to lay a greater or smaller weight on
every Clause, according to its natural or
spiritual Force; where to be quicker or
more vehement, where slower and more se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date;
how to observe equally all Pauses and
Distances; how to avoid Monotonies
on the one hand, and immoderate Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
and Depressions on the other; Yet,
where to use the same Tones, where to rise
or fall in the right place: When, I say, the
Reader shall be throughly expert and vers'd
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108092:10"/>
in practising these, and many more such
natural Decencies of Pronouncing; tho' they
may seem but light, and petty things, taken
singly, and a part, yet all together, in their
full united Power, they will be found to
have an admirable Concurrence towards the
creating, augmenting, well tempering, and
well-governing of Devotion.</p>
            <p>Had I time, it were easie to exemplifie this,
in every Office of our Church. Give me
leave only to mention one Instance within
the compass of my own Knowledge, which
perhaps may not be unworthy your special
remarking: Tho' I doubt not but many of
you have met with several Examples of the
like nature.</p>
            <p>It was immediately after the Happy Resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, when, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with the Rights of the Crown, and
the English Liberties, the Church, and the
Liturgy, were also newly restored; that a
noted Ringleader of Schism in the former
times, was to be buried in one of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal
Churches of <hi>London.</hi> The Minister of
the Parish, being a wise and regular Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist,
and he was afterwards an eminent Bishop
in our Church, well knew how averse the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:108092:10"/>
Friends and Relations of the Deceased had
always been to the <hi>Common Prayer;</hi> Which,
by hearing it so often call'd a <hi>low Rudiment,
a beggarly Element,</hi> and <hi>Carnal Ordinance,</hi>
they were brought to contemn to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,
that they shunned all occasions of being
acquainted with it.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, in order to the Interment
of their Friend, in some sort, to their Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction,
yet so as not to betray his own Trust,
he used this honest Method to undeceive
them. Before the day appointed for the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,
he was at the pains to learn the whole
Office of Burial by Heart. And then, the time
being come there being a great Concourse of
Men of the same Phanatical Principles, when
the Company heard all delivered by him
without Book, with a free Readiness, and
profound Gravity, and unaffected compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
of Voice, Looks, and Gestures, and a
very powerful Emphasis in every part; as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
his Talent was excellent that way; they
were strangely surprised and affected: Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing,
they had never heard a more sutable
Exhortation, or a more edifying Exercise,
even from the very best and most precious
Men of their own Persuasion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:108092:11"/>But they were afterwards much more sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised
and confounded, when the same Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
who had officiated, assured the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal
Men among them, that not one Period
of all he had spoken was his own;
and convinc'd them by ocular Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration,
how all was taken Word for
Word out of the very Office ordained for
that purpose, in the poor contemptible Book
of <hi>Common Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence he most reasonably inferr'd, how
much their ill grounded Prejudice, and
mistaken Zeal, had deluded them, that they
should admire the same Discourse, when
they thought it an unprepared, unpremedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated,
Rapture: which they would have abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated,
had they known it to be only a set
Form prescribed by Authority.</p>
            <p>And from the same Observation, we also
may as justly infer, that all the Coldness and
Dulnes, which too many, such abused and
wanton Spirits, have complain'd they find in
set Forms, is not really in the Forms them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves;
in ours it is far otherwise. If there
be any colour for the Complaint, that can
only proceed from a cold, flat, supine, insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid
manner of repeating them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:108092:11"/>Upon the whole Matter it is most certain,
that, in the public Worship of GOD, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
can be more grave, or moving, more
lofty, or Divine, either in the confessing, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioning,
or praising part, than where the
Thoughts and Expressions are strictly weigh'd,
and prudently reduced into standing unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable
Forms: Provided also, those very
Forms be not pronounced in a formal way;
but that they be assisted, inflamed, inspired,
as I may say, with such a present Ardour,
and sprightly Zeal in reading them, as will
always make them seem to be extempore:
Extempore, I mean, in the new, ready, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement
manner of their Pronunciation; but
set Forms still, in the solid Ripeness of the
Sense, and the due Choice, and deliberate
ordering of their Phrases and Figures; Which
are the peculiar Advantages of set Forms:
And therefore, so spoken, they will, in all Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
produce a far more real, unfeigned, and
durable Devotion, than all the other meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extempore,
raw, and indigested Effusions
ought to pretend to.</p>
            <p>I should crave your pardon, that I have
dwelt so long on this first Head of Advice.
But it appear'd to me so very material, that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108092:12"/>
I could not hastily pass it over: Especially
since what I have now said on this Subject,
may concern in common all your public Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrations,
and is equally applicable, not
only to the well-performing the daily mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
and evening Prayers throughout the
Year, both of ordinary Days and <hi>Sundays,</hi> and
extraordinary Fasts and Festivals; but also
to the Offices of Baptism, Matrimony, and
the Holy Communion; and indeed to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
other part of our established Liturgy:
In all which, as the Reader officiates better
or worse, so most usually is their Benefit and
Efficacy more or less on the Minds of the
Hearers.</p>
            <p>Nay, I will now make bold to go farther,
to apply the Usefulness of this Counsel, not
only to the Praying Part, but also to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Part of your Office, I am next to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider,
which is that of Preaching.</p>
            <p>I am verily persuaded, that the Sermons
preached every <hi>Sunday</hi> in this one Kingdom,
by the Church of <hi>England</hi> Clergy in this Age,
are more excellent Compositions of that kind,
than have been delivered, in the same space
of time, throughout the whole Christian
World besides.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:108092:12"/>Only let me take the Freedom to suggest,
that perhaps it would add much, tho' not
to the solid and substantial Part of such Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses,
yet to their just popularity, and
more general Acceptance, and to the greater
Edification of our Hearers, if we would uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally
addict our selves a little more to this
Study of Pronunciation: By which Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages
alone of the Freedom, and life of their
Elocution, we know the Preachers of some
other Nations do seem to reign and triumph
in the Pulpit, whilest their Sermons, as far
as we can judge by those we have of them
in Print<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are not comparable to the English.</p>
            <p>An Observation, which, methinks, may
rouze our Preachers to out do them in this
kind of Perfection also: I mean, in a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
comely, modest, yet undaunted force
of Pronunciation: Not such as is full of
over-Action, and mimical Gesticulations;
which, though some Parties may admire
for a time, and to serve a Turn,
yet the serious Temper of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
will never long approve or admit of.
But I intend such a steddy composed, severe,
decent, lively, and apposite managing your
Voices and Gestures in the Pulpit, as is best
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108092:13"/>
accommodated to the Gravity and Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity
of the English Genius, and is also
agreeable, as much as may be, to the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity,
Power, and height of the Message
you bring from Heaven.</p>
            <p>The next great Duty then of your Priestly
Office, which comes in our way, being that
of Preaching, I shall begin with one short
Admonition, which, I confess, I am almost
ashamed to give; and yet it may be very
expedient, that it should be given; not, I
declare, as a Correction to any of you here
present, for any thing past, but only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
to the future, and for the sake of those
who as yet are less experienced Preachers,
and young timorous Beginners.</p>
            <p>The Caution, in plain Terms, is this, that
every Person, who undertakes this great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,
should make it a master of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
and and Conscience, to preach nothing but
what is the Product of his own Study, and
of his own Composing.</p>
            <p>I would not be mistaken, as if I should
hereby condemn the Reading of the Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies;
which were composed by the Wisdom
and Piety of former Times, and have been
ever-since allowed, nay recommended, by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108092:13"/>
our Church, in some Places, and upon some
Necessities to be used. I am so far from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
so, that I rather wish from my Heart
we were furnish'd with a larger Stock of such
learned plain, and orthodox Discourses.</p>
            <p>There can be no manner of hurt, nay
there is very great reason, that, upon some
urgent Occasions, a Preacher should have
liberty to take something out of that public
Treasury, which was laid up for that end,
and has the Stamp of Authority upon it to
make it current. My Purpose is only to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suade
you from all unjust Rapine of this kind,
from all under-hand dealing with the private
Stores of particular Persons.</p>
            <p>As to that, I dare avouch, it is far better
and more advisable, even for the rawest
Practiser, to exhibit but very mean Things
of his own, at first, than to flourish it in the
best of other Mens Sense and Oratory. For
he, who does never so ordinarily at first,
provided it be from himself, may, and will
do better, and better in time, by GOD's
Assistance, thro' fervent Prayer, and indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable.
Attention to reading, and hearing,
and practising to preach. Whereas this sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did
borrowing, this shameful, I had almost
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:108092:14"/>
said, sacrilegious purloining from other
Mens Labours, is an utter irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable
Enemy to all manner of Growth
and Improvement in Divine Learning, or
Eloquence.</p>
            <p>I will not now insist on the meaness of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
and perpetual fear, that must attend the
Consciousness of this Guilt, lest it should
be, some time or other, discover'd; or on
the shame and contempt that often happens
to such Pilferers upon the Discovery. But
besides all this, in Truth, when once Men
have indulged themselves in this easie, but
despicable and shuffling Commerce, they sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
or never give it over; nay, at last, they
can very hardly give it over if they would.</p>
            <p>Thence will succeed such a visible decay
of Parts, such a neglect of all serious Studies,
such a desuetude, and unaptness for regular
thinking, such Emptiness of Invention and
Memory, such a Diffidence of their own
Style, Understanding and Judgement; that
they, who at first made bold with others
Sermons, perhaps meerly out of Idleness,
will at length be forced to do it out of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
It will unavoidably happen to this
kind of Thieves, as most commonly it does
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108092:14"/>
to all others; they steal so long in their
Youth, and Strength of Age, because they
will not work, that in their old Age, they
are compell'd to steal on, because they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
work.</p>
            <p>But enough, or too much of this. I know
to whom I speak; to those, who, for ought
I could ever observe, or hear, do not only
Preach, but themselves compose what they
Preach. Yet I thought it became me to
give this Intimation, seeing, in my own
small Experience, I have been forced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Orders to some Persons, because I found
them peccant in this very Crime. I was at
first exceedingly amazed to hear them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
most excellent Sermons, whilest I found
their Gifts of Nature, and Abilities of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
and Knowledge, were far from being
passable. But my Wonder was soon over,
when I manifestly discover'd, that nothing
but their Ignorance was their own, their
Sermons belonging of right to their Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>Now then, my Brethren, that we may
come into the Way again, after this unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
Digression, in making our Sermons,
great regard ought to be had to the Words,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108092:15"/>
and to the Matter; great to both, tho' not
equally great to both.</p>
            <p>Your Words and Style should be simple,
expressive, weighty, authoritative: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
tho' not without some true Art, yet
not very artificial; and rather void of all
Ornament, than over-adorn'd; but as much
Scriptural as may be without Affectation;
and as easie, familiar, and intelligible as pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible.
And Perspicuity is always possible.
Nay it is almost impossible, that ones Words
should not be perspicuous, when his Thoughts
are clear, and untroubled, and the Thing
to be spoken of is throughly understood.
When the Matter is well invented, digested,
and ordered in the Mind, it very rarely hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens,
but the fittest and most expressive
Words will occur to the Fancy and Tongue
of the Speaker. <hi>Verba non invita sequentur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, since your Matter must, of course,
be either Doctrinal or Practical; where it
shall be meerly Doctrinal, there it may suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
for your common Auditories, and, in good
Truth, for all other, from the lowest to the
very highest, that it be plain, sound, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial,
ancient, catholic; seldom or never
curiously drawn out into the fine Threads of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:108092:15"/>
Dispute and Speculation, or, as the Apostle
terms them, <hi>Oppositions of Science falsly so
called.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were indeed, much to be wished, that
the agitating of all manner of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies
could be utterly excluded from the
great Work of saving Souls, which is your
special Work. Yet, because in times so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate
from the Primitive Purity, and in
this militant State of the Christian Church,
it cannot be expected, that you should teach
aptly, or oppose Schism and Heresie solidly,
without touching sometimes, and entring
upon some Walks of Controversies; Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the best way, in these inevitable Cases, is
never to meddle with such obscure Subtilties,
out of Spiritual Pride or Ostentation, but
meerly out of Necessity; and then only
with the most necessary Parts of them; and
then also that you be ever sure to keep close
to <hi>the Form of sound Words</hi> used in the Church,
and to contain your selves within the known
Bounds of Scripture Determinations, in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
controverted Point, to deliver the Faith
to your People, as <hi>it was once deliverd to the
Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:108092:16"/>As little a Lover then as I am of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versial
Divinity in the Pulpit, yet I cannot
be faithful to you, or to our Mother the
Church of <hi>England,</hi> if I do not recommend
two sorts of it to be seriously studied by you:
But I must still say, rather to be studied than
preach'd; tho' preach'd too upon reasonable
Occasions.</p>
            <p>The first kind is that of the Controversies
between us and the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For
we are not yet so exempt from Fear on that
Quarter, that we should securely lay aside,
and suffer to rust on the Walls, those very
Arms, which, to the immortal praise of the
Parochial Clergy, were so successfully mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
by them, during the last great <hi>Crisis</hi> of
danger from the Popish Interest.</p>
            <p>I the rather mention these, because they
are still almost in every Mans hands; and
perhaps a judicious summ, and full Epitome,
collected out of them all, would be as use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
a Body of Controversies on those Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions,
as any is yet extant.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, that you may preserve your
own, and the Souls under your Care, from
Infection, and be able to convince Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayers,
I exhort you all, according to your
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:108092:16"/>
several Stations and Opportunities, to be still
conversant and prepared in those very same
Arguments against the Papists: Yet, let me
say also, not only now in those.</p>
            <p>For there is another sort of Controversies,
or rather blasphemous Doctrines, reviv'd in
this Age, and which seem, indeed, to be the
most cherish'd and darling Tenents of the
loose and Antichristian part of the Age; I
mean those execrable Opinions against the
Incarnation and Eternal Godhead of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
the Satisfaction of his Meritorious Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,
and Death, and the very Being of
the Ever-blessed Trinity: Which being all
of them the peculiar and distinguishing Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations
of Christianity, whatever they,
who so directly oppose them, may at first
pretend, yet they cannot but really tend to
the Destruction of the Primitive Faith in
Christ, and the Introduction of another Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
new, and therefore abominable.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, to maintain no less than the
main Fundamental Points of our <hi>pure and
Vndefiled Religion,</hi> you are now most zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously
to apply your Thoughts to the serious
Study of those Divine Mysteries. Yet, if
you please to take my Judgment, after you
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:108092:17"/>
shall be never so well furnish'd with Weapons
defensive, or offensive, of this nature, you
should very rerely brandish, or so much as
shew them in your ordinary Pulpits; never
but when you cannot avoid it without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying,
or deserting the Orthodox Truth.
And whenever you shall produce any of
them in such Auditories, even then, it
were best done in a calm, positive, and
didactical, rather than in a sharp, wrangling,
or contentious way. But always take along
with you, what I said before, to wade no
farther in them, in your popular Sermons,
than as the Scripture Light primitively ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
shall plainly lead you.</p>
            <p>This may suffice, at present, touching the
doctrinal and speculative part of your
Preaching. As to the other, which is the
Practical, in that I need not forewarn you
to proceed with such reserve, or restraint.
In the greatest abundance of that, if ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged
with any tolerable Prudence, there
can hardly be any manner of excess. Most
assuredly the less controversial, and the more
practical your Pulpit Discourses are, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
they must be, and the more profitable.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:108092:17"/>Now, my dear Brethren, the Subject of
this part of your Sermons, being, as you
cannot but know, so comprehensive and
vast, as to take in the whole compass of all
our Spiritual and Moral Duties; I say of
Moral also; For, let none be deceived, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Preaching is of marvellous use where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
it is subservient to the inspired Doctrine
of Christianity, and does not strive to justle
that, which is its Principal, quite out of the
Pulpit: But, I say, the Matter of your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical
Preaching being in it self so large, as
to extend to all the Precepts and Promises.
both of the Law, and the Gospel; to all
the Temptations and Corruptions of the
World, the Flesh, and the Devil; whereof
the one ought to be the eternal Argument
of your Exhortations, the other of your
Reproofs and Admonitions: Here it is espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially,
that I would beseech you all, with a
Brotherly Tenderness, and oblige you, with
a Fatherly Authority, to lay out the whole
stress, and bent of your Souls, to draw all
your Studies, all your Learning, Human or
Divine, all your Eloquence, all your Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
all your Zeal this way: This being
the great Work you have chosen for the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:108092:18"/>
of your whole Lives, and for which
we all were so peculiarly dedicated to the
Service of GOD, and his Church: And let
me add, this being the great Purpose, for
which <hi>all Scripture</hi> seems to have been <hi>given
by Inspiration of GOD:</hi> That it may be <hi>profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction.</hi>
There is the chief end of all the Doctrine
you are to teach. But what follows? <hi>For
Instruction in Righteousness; that the Man of
GOD may be perfect, throughly furnished to
every good Work.</hi> There is the great Design
of all the Practice you are to inforce.</p>
            <p>I have dispatched what I thought proper
now to say on this Head of Preaching, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less
you will suffer me to name one very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious
Caution; which yet I cannot think to
be ever the less necessary, for being so
very obvious.</p>
            <p>The Caution is, that in all your Sermons,
where you have Occasion to praise any Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
or dispraise any Vice; in all your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations
of what is bad; you would always
separate the good Person from the good
Thing, and always distinguish the Sinner
from the Sin: That is, That you would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:108092:18"/>
put any one Virtue, never any one Vice,
you are to deal with in the Pulpit, into the
Habit or Countenance of any one Member
of your Congregations, so that they may
be known thereby: In a word, that you
would utterly shun, and abhor all Personal
Flatteries of the Good; and all Personal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections
on the wicked.</p>
            <p>As to the first of these Extremes, that of
Flattery, I need only mention it here. That
is seldom thought worthy of such plain Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
Congregations, as yours generally are:
'Twere well, if it were as much excluded
out of all other Religious Assemblies of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
Quality.</p>
            <p>It is indeed great pity, that such glosing
and deceitful Language should at last, in
any measure, take Sanctuary in the Church;
when it had been so long, in all Ages, by
common Consent of wise and good Men,
judg'd fit to be banish'd out of all other well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constituted
Societies. Has it not been always
found, by Experience, that a flattering
Tongue is so far from increasing the Virtues
of the Good, and the Great, that it rather
serves to deprave the real Worth they might
have before? So that, as the Psalmist says,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:108092:19"/>
the Men <hi>who flatter with their Tongue, have</hi>
not only <hi>no Faithfulness in their Mouth,</hi> but
<hi>their very Throat is an open Sepulcher.</hi> But,
above all, it is most unbecoming the Pulpit;
where Men would seem to speak as from
GOD, and with Authority, which nothing
can more debase or prostitute than Flattery.</p>
            <p>As to the other Excess, that of secret Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections,
and malicious Insinuations against,
or open Defamations of Persons, I would
absolutely dissuade you from the very Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,
and Suspicion of it. I would intreat
you all, in <hi>the Bowels of our Lord Christ,</hi> that
you would never, on any Occasion, or Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
not even on the greatest Provocation,
do that Affront to the Honour and Modesty
of the Pulpit, as to make it a Place for any
Rudeness, or Scurrility whatsoever. Surely
nothing can be more disgraceful to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
of your Profession, or more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive
to Edification, or more unbeseem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Gravity and Charity of a <hi>Church-of-England</hi>
Divine, than to make an Ordinance
so sacred; and the Word of GOD handled
in it, become instrumental to your own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
Passions, Animosities, or Revenges.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:108092:19"/>I am now arrived at the next great Duty
of your Holy Office, which is that of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chising;
not so much to recommend to you
the Duty it self; tho' I might do that most
earnestly and vehemently, and with some
kind of Episcopal Expostulation and Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension,
if any where it should be totally
neglected. But that I would not here so
much as suppose.</p>
            <p>I cannot doubt but we are all of one
Mind, touching the inexpressible Advantages
of this Ordinance in general; we especially
who have lived in these Times. We cannot
but be abundantly convinced of it by a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
and dear-bought Experience: Since it is
evident, that the far greater part of the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous
Looseness of Opinions, and profane
Enormity of Manners, which overwhelm'd
the whole face of the last Age, and has too
much descended on this, did remarkably
proceed from the notorious defect, or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal
Omission of Orthodox Catechising,
during the Calamities and Confusions of the
great Rebellion.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, touching the imminent Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity
of restoring, or, I may well hope ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
among you, of continuing this first
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:108092:20"/>
part of Christian Discipline, I make sure ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
we are all agreed.</p>
            <p>The only Thing, to be debated, is the
Manner, how this Holy Exercise may be so
put in use, that the blessed Ends, which, I
am assured, we all aim at alike, may be
attained.</p>
            <p>Without all Controversie then, the first
Practice of your regular Catechising, in all
your Churches, ought to be in the very same
Order, and on the same Materials, which
the Church Catechism has traced out, and
the Law has injoin'd.</p>
            <p>I would therefore desire you all to begin,
or rather incourage you to go on, plainly
and literally in that way, with a strict Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinement
of your Catechumens, as they may
be called, to that very compendious Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction;
to have your Youth throughly
versed, and instructed perfectly in all the
Questions and Answers there prescribed.
This ought by no means to be left undone
in the smallest or poorest of your Country
Cures; where the highest Capacities are not
at first above, and the lowest can scarce be
below, this kind of plain Information.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:108092:20"/>But in greater Towns, where the Youth
are somewhat better educated, and so should
be more capable of Improvement, there,
supposing still you never omit the other
more simple way, you may, by degrees,
with a sober, and discreet Pace, proceed
farther; I will not say, by inlarging the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations,
but by raising the Building higher
on the same compass of Ground.</p>
            <p>And this I have known done with very
remarkable Fruit, and Benefit to the Learners,
in a familiar Method, whereof I will only
trace out to you the imperfect Draught<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
which, by Time and Custom, you may easily
advance, and complete. The Method is
this, That to every Article, and every Clause
of it, in the Church Catechism, after they
have learnt them by Heart, you should an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex,
at first, some such Texts of Scripture,
as may suffice to prove the Matter contain'd
in them, and do it in the fewest Words,
and clearest to the Purpose. These Texts
you should induce your young Disciples to
repeat often, and perfectly without Book,
together with each Article, and should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
to let them understand, by a very brief
Exposition, how evidently each Scripture
proves each Article.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:108092:21"/>Then, by degrees, after they shall be made
intimately acquainted with that first Sett of
Texts, you may more securely add other
Quotations out of the Bible, somewhat lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
but still tending to the same Purpose;
and when you have explain'd them, in the
like manner, but more copiously, you may
cause those also to be learnt as exactly, and
repeated as readily as the former. And the
same Course you may begin, and go through
with again, still adding more Texts,
and more distinctly dividing the Parts, and
Members of the several Articles, as often as
you shall find it practicable, or conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</p>
            <p>Thus, whilest you do not over-burden
tender Minds, but softly instil these Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
into them, Drop after Drop, the
Children, you have undertaken in this way, so
very little out of the common Rode, and many
also of riper Years, who shall be present, and
attentive, will, beyond their own, and even
your first Expectation, come to have trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured
up, almost unawares, in their Minds,
a little Body, as it were, of Orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity:
which cannot but be all Orthodox,
all Primitive, as being, without mixture,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:108092:21"/>
purely collected out of the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>With the Scriptures, by this means, their
Memories will unperceivably be filled; yet
not so as only to fit them to cant with unsea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonably,
in common Discourse, but so as to
instruct or confirm their Judgments, and
teach them to apply properly, what they
shall there read, to every part of a sober Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians
Belief, or practical Duty.</p>
            <p>In this great Article of Catechising, I
would offer one honest Direction more. It
is, that you should not so much aim in it at
the length of the Exercise, or at the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
changing of your Thoughts and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions,
as at the sound Bottom, on which
you build your Discourse, and the solid,
unmovable Ground of each Doctrine,
whereon you fix your Explanations; tho'
your Performance each time be the shorter,
so it be not unreasonably short, and tho'
your Words, and Phrases, may happen fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
to be the same, and repeated more
than once.</p>
            <p>In truth, I would, if I durst, offer some
such Advice also as to your Preaching. But I
know the common Vogue is against my real
Opinion in this Matter. And therefore I
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:108092:22"/>
must handle this point the more tenderly.</p>
            <p>It is indeed a very great Burden, that the
Humour of the People, and our own too,
in some measure, has laid on our Profession:
Such as, I think, no other Calling, or Way
of Life, were ever willing to lay on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves;
no, nor any other Nation, that I
know of, has exacted in so high a degree,
from their Clergy; that you should twice or
once a week, at least, always present your
Auditories with new Sermons; and those
also to be composed with the Care and Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy,
almost of Elaborate, and Complete
Treatises.</p>
            <p>Whereas I am sure, in the business of
Catechising, and most probably, the same
will be found true in Preaching also, that a
sound, substantial, well-collected, and well-woven
Provision, of Plain, Instructive, God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
and Devout Discourses, altered, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased,
according to the Teachers growing
Abilities, and used over, and over, tho' in
the same Desks, or Pulpits, would be more
edifying, and sink deeper into the Minds,
and Consciences of the Hearers, than all
the greatest Afluence, and Redundance of
new Words, and Phrases multiply'd, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchanged,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:108092:22"/>
which the most fanciful, copious
Catechist, or Preacher can devise.</p>
            <p>I have known some very learned and pious
Men, and excellent Preachers, and zealous
Lovers of our Church, and Country; whose
Welfare and Prosperity they wisely judg'd to
be inseparably join'd; I say I have known
these Persons affectionately declare their
Wishes that some such Order, as this I shall
subjoin, were observed by the greatest part,
if not by all our Parochial Ministers.</p>
            <p>That, on the very entring into their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry,
or at any time afterwards, if they
have not done it before, they would set them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
to draw out the general Lineaments,
and larger Members of a whole Years, or
perhaps a two Years Course of Catechisms,
and Sermons: following therein the annual
Method of our Churches Devotions, or any
other Scheme they shall approve, and form
to themselves; provided it comprizes all the
main Points of Christian Doctrine, and
Practice.</p>
            <p>That on this Stock they should set up;
and, in the first, and second Year, begin to
fill up the void Spaces, and lay the first Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours,
towards the finishing, as well as their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:108092:23"/>
Sufficiency will then allow; still collecting,
and conveying all the Streams of their useful
Reading and Learning into those common
Receptacles and Channels; and so successive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Preaching them on, as the Year turns round.</p>
            <p>That ever after, in the whole Progress
of their Ministry, they should still be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to, or cutting off from, or polishing those
first imperfect <hi>Ideas;</hi> altering the Method,
and Shape of the whole, if needful; infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,
or increasing the Arguments, Illustra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
and Amplisications, if Wanting; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serting
new Doctrines before-unobserved,
making new practical Inferences before-un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched,
as their Judgements, or Light, or
Experience shall improve; but especially, still
drawing more, and more, over all, a new
beautiful Skin, and the lovely Features of
Scripture Language: And then, without
Scruple, or Disguise, should preach them
again, and again, so corrected, augmented,
and in some part renewed.</p>
            <p>And I have heard these very wise Persons,
some of them most excellent Fathers of our
Church, often conclude, that, by this, or
some such Method, any Preacher, tho' of
no extraordinary-bright Endowments at first,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:108092:23"/>
yet of an honest Mind, clear Sense, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied
Industry, and judicious Learning,
would, in process of time, in all likelihood,
have by him in store, a complete, domestic,
Course of sound, well-compacted, affecting
Sermons; that, by GOD's Blessing, might
with the just Advantages of Delivery, be of
far greater use to his Conscientious Hearers,
than all that pompous Novelty, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit
Variety, which some others may boast
of.</p>
            <p>I say counterfeit Variety. For so indeed
it is often, upon tryal, found to be. And
now I have faithfully told you the Opinion
of those Great Men, I will presume, under
so safe a Shelter, to disclose my own Thoughts
in this Business; yet still with all deference,
and candour towards any, who may differ
from me in this Particular.</p>
            <p>We have lived in an Age, when the two
Gifts, as they are wont to be call'd, of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore
Praying, and Extempore Preaching,
have been more pretended to, and magnified,
than, I believe, they ever were before, or,
I hope, ever will be again, in this Church
and Nation. Yet, for all I could ever learn,
or observe, the most sudden Readiness, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:108092:24"/>
most profuse Exuberancy, in either of these
Ways, has been only Extempore in Shew
and Appearance, and very frequently but a
cunningly-dissembled Change of the very
same Matter, and Words often repeated,
tho' not in the same order.</p>
            <p>As to that of Extempore Praying, which
therefore too many mistake for Praying by
the Spirit; it is manifest, that the most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised,
and most redundant Faculty, in that
kind, is, in reality, only Praying by the
Fancy, or, the Memory, not by the Spirit.
They do but vary, and remove the Scripture
Style, and Language, or their own, into as
many Places, and Shapes, and Figures, as
they can. And tho' they have acquired ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
so plentiful a Stock of them, yet still the
same Phrases, and Expressions, do so often
come about again, that the Disguise may
quickly be seen through, by any attentive
and intelligent Hearer. So that, in plain
terms, they who think themselves most skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
in this Art, do really, all the while, only
pray in set Forms disorderly set, and never
ranged into a certain Method. For which
Cause, tho' they may not seem to be set
Forms to their deluded Auditors, yet they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:108092:24"/>
are so in themselves; and the very Persons
who use them most variously, and most arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially,
cannot but know them to be so.</p>
            <p>This, my Brethren, seems to be all the great
Mystery of the so much boasted Power of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore
Praying. And why may not the
like be affirm'd, in great measure, of Extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore
Preaching, which has so near an Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
with the other? Is not this also, at the
Bottom, only a more crafty Management
of the same Phrases and Observations, the
same Doctrines, and Applications, which
they had before provided, and composed,
and reserved in their Memories?</p>
            <p>Do but hear the most voluble Masters in
this way, once or twice, or perhaps oftner, as
far as their Changes shall reach, and at first, no
doubt, you will be inclined to wonder at the
strange Agility of their Imaginations, and
compass of their Inventions, and Nimbleness
of their Utterance. But if you shall attend
them calmly, and constantly, the Vizour
will be quickly pull'd off, tho' they manage
it never so dextrously: You will at last find,
they only walk forward, and backward, and
round about: One, it may be, in a larger
Labyrinth than another; but in a Labyrinth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:108092:25"/>
still; through the same Turnings and Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
again, and again, and, for the most
part, guided by the same clue.</p>
            <p>The Explanations, perhaps, of their Texts,
the Connexions, and Transitions of the Parts,
and some sudden Glosses, and Descants, and
Flights of Fancy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may seem new to you.
But the material Points of Doctrine, and the
common Places, to which, upon any Loss,
or Necessity, they have recourse, these they
frequently repeat, and apply, to several Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
with very little Alterations in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
oftentimes not in the Words. These
are the constant Paths, which they scruple
not to walk over, and over again, 'till, if
you follow them very close, you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
amidst all their Extempore Pretensions,
they often tread in the same Rounds 'till they
have trodden them bare enough.</p>
            <p>But, GOD be thanked, the Church of
<hi>England</hi> neither requires, nor stands in need
of any such raptural (if I may so call it)
or Enthusiastical Spirit of Preaching. Here
the more advised, and modest, the more
deliberate and prepared the Preacher is, the
better he is furnished, by GOD's Grace, to
deliver effectually our Churches solid Sense, its
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:108092:25"/>
fixed Precepts, its unalterable Doctrines. Our
Church pretends not to enter into Mens
Judgements; meerly by the Affections;
much less by the Passions to overthrow their
Judgements. The Door, which that strives
first to open, is of the Understanding, and
Conscience: It is content, if by them, a Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage
shall be made into the Affections.</p>
            <p>I have detain'd you the longer on this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,
because I am perfectly convinced,
that although one, or two Preachers in an
Age, or perhaps some few more, Men of
extraordinary Parts, Assurance of Mind, and
Volubility of Tongue, may, by long use,
make a remarkable Blaze, for a time, in this
sudden, unstudied Way: Yet, if it should
ever become the general Custom of the whole
English Clergy, it would produce little more
than Ignorance and Confidence in many of
our Preachers, and tempt many of the Laity,
who presume themselves to be equally gifted,
to think they had an equal Right to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry.</p>
            <p>But what need I say any more of this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?
It is confess'd on all hands, that if an
Extempore kind of Preaching had been uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally
put in use among us, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:108092:26"/>
of our Reformation, the whole
Church of Christ had been much impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished
thereby, had been deprived of the
best Treasury of Sermons, that ever it was
inrich'd with, since the Apostles, and their
Successors, and the primitive Fathers Times.</p>
            <p>There is still behind one solemn Duty
more, belonging to all of us, wherein I
would willingly suggest one serious Word of
Counsel: And it concerns the <hi>Office of
Visiting the Sick.</hi> I would not doubt, but
herein you generally do your Parts, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently,
piously, and prudently. But there
are some Things in this, as well as in the
others before-mentioned, touching the <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>
of doing it, whereof the Observation may
be of a peculiar and signal Benefit to your
selves, as well as to your Spiritual Patients.</p>
            <p>If you please to consult the Rubricks re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating
to this Office, you will find, you are
more left to your own Liberty in this, than,
I think, in any of the rest. For this Duty of
Friendship, and Charity, being supposed to
be more in private, the Rule it self in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy
seems to give way to, nay to direct
some occasional Admonitions, and Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:108092:26"/>
to which I do not remember, it does
equally impower you in any of the rest, out
of the Pulpit.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, to prepare your Thoughts,
and to replenish your Minds throughly for
this Work not only of Ministerial Duty, but
of Compassion, and Brotherly Love, you
shall not only do well to furnish your Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories,
with a plentiful Store of pious, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,
affectionate Expressions, out of the
Book of Psalms, and other practical and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votional
Parts of the Holy Scriptures first;
and, next to them, out of our own Liturgy;
and all these to be casually used, as shall be
most proper: But principally I would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suade
you, to have some good, sound Body
of Casuistical Divinity, of your own studying
I mean, to be always at hand, that is, in
your Hearts, as well as Heads.</p>
            <p>You can scarce imagine, unless you have
try'd it, as, I hope, some of you have, of
what unspeakable Use this Divine Science of
Cases of Conscience will be to you upon any
sudden, unforeseen Emergency in such
Ghostly Visits.</p>
            <p>Indeed the being a sound, and well-expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced
Casuist is also a most excellent Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:108092:27"/>
towards all the other Ends of your
Ministerial Office; there being no kind of
Skill, or Proficiency in all your Theological
Studies, that more becomes a Divine of the
Church of <hi>England;</hi> whose highest Spiritual
Art is to speak directly from his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science
to the Consciences of those under
his Pastoral Care: and this at all times; but
most especially when they are on their Sick-Beds:
When Mens Consciences are usually
most awakened, most managable, most truly
tender, and capable of the best Impressions.</p>
            <p>So that I say it again, and can never say it
too often, one of the most necessary Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,
and Instruments of your sacred Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,
which you are always to carry about
with you, in your own Souls, (for there it
is best lodged; thence it will be drawn forth,
on all Occasions, with the quickest Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,)
is such a firm Sense, and general
Scheme of the primitive, uncorrupt, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,
Casuistical Divinity: Such as, on the
one side, is purged from the Spiritual Crafts,
and Equivocations of the Jesuits, and, on
the other, is freed from the Narrowness and
Sourness of Enthusiasm.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:108092:27"/>I told you even now, it highly concern'd
you all to be well stock'd with plenty of
good Matter for present Use, in the Visita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Sick; and that for your own
Sakes as much as theirs. And, in truth, so
it is. A Clergy-man can, no way better,
have his own Affections, and Passions regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated,
tempered, soften'd, mortified, sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
than by frequently performing this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
in a right Godly manner.</p>
            <p>By thus often seeing Death before our Eyes,
in all its ghastly Shapes, we cannot, if it be
not the Fault of our own Insensibility, but
be the better accustomed, and made skilful
to teach the whole, and the healthful, how
to prepare to meet that <hi>King of Terrors.</hi> By
these Spiritual Anatomies of the Dying, (if
I may be allowed to use so bold a Metaphor,)
we cannot but be made more expert in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the inward Frames and Constitutions
of the Living, and to apply the properest
Remedies to the Diseases of their Souls.</p>
            <p>And, to instance now only in one Duty of
such a faithful Spiritual Physician, that of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving
and refreshing the Conscience through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
searched and purged, and of comforting
and restoring the true Penitent, What, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:108092:28"/>
you, can be a more God-like Work
among Men, than for us to be humbly ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable
in that, which GOD owns to be
<hi>His</hi> Work, to be skill'd in <hi>not breaking the
bruised Reed, and not quenching the Smoaking
Flax?</hi> To be instrumental in performing our
Lords own Office, under the Parable of the
good <hi>Samaritan, in binding up the wounded
Spirit, and pouring Wine, and Oyl into it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What can more adorn your Evangelical
Ministry, than a soft, melting, compassionate,
Fellow-feeling, merciful Habit, and Dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition
of Mind, and, as the Scripture styles
it, <hi>the Ornament of a meek Spirit?</hi> Or, Where
can such a blessed Temper be more seasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
practised, or sooner learn'd and increas'd,
than in the Chambers of sick and dying Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons?</p>
            <p>Now, my dear Brethren, having all along
insisted, that, for the furnishing and inriching
your Minds with Spiritual Knowledge, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the due performing these, and all other
Offices of your Holy Profession, you should
make the Holy Scriptures the principal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
and indeed the only final Center of all
your Studies; that your Doctrine should
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:108092:28"/>
never swerve from that unerring Rule; your
very Words, Language, and Style, should
every where tast of, and overflow with those
living, and inexhaustible Streams of Truth,
and Godliness; it may be expected, that, for
the Sake only of the younger Divines among
you, I should add a Word or two, touching
the <hi>Manner,</hi> and Method, of your studying
these sacred Writings. It is indeed a Business
too large to be drawn within the narrow
compass of the Conclusion of such a Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course.
But since a true, at least a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
Understanding of this Blessed Book,
ought to be the Beginning, and End of all
our Spiritual Studies; and because I may
speak to some, whose Circumstances in this
World are not so plentiful, as to enable them
to purchase large Libraries; yet their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry
is by no means to be discouraged,
nor their Zeal, in pursuing this Holy Skill,
abated; I will open to you my own simple
Apprehensions in this Matter, with Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission
still to better Judgements.</p>
            <p>My Opinion is, That altho', without
question, all manner of Secular, or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical
Learning, can never be more useful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
employ'd, than in this search, and is all
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:108092:29"/>
little enough for it, and too little to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat
it; yet, when all is done, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
it self is the best Expositor, the best
Commentator on it self.</p>
            <p>It is apparent, that the whole <hi>New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
is so to the whole <hi>Old Testament;</hi> that
being the real Light of the others figurative
Darkness, and Mysteries; the very Consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
of the others Prophecies, and <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows
of good Things to come.</hi> But I will
also aver, that every Part, every Book, every
Sentence almost, both of the <hi>Old</hi> and the
<hi>New Testament,</hi> well-compared, and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously
set one over against the other, in
their right View, and Reflection, cannot but
prove, by GOD's Blessing, an inestimable
Explanation of each other: If a due and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate
Care, I say, be taken to interpret
their difficult Texts, by others of their own,
that are easier; and to collate their Words,
Phrases, and Sense, that may seem dark, or
doubtful in some Places, with the same, or
the like in other Places, where they are clearer
and more intelligible.</p>
            <p>I cannot forbear, as I go along, to declare
my Meaning a little fuller in this Matter, by
one special Instance. For, consider, I pray,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:108092:29"/>
how is it possible for any, the most learned,
or sagacious Student in Divinity, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
the true, and genuine Sense of the Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
and Divine Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
he has been also throughly conversant
in the Writings of <hi>Moses?</hi> Or where can
there be found a clearer, a more Spiritual,
and more illustrious Commentary on the
whole Ritual Part of the Pentateuch, than
the Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like also may be proved of all other
Portions of the Holy Book of GOD. And
indeed to manifest, what mutual Brightness,
and Splendor, the Scripture gives to and
takes from it self, by comparing its several
Parts, I need only urge the frequent Practice
of our Saviour himself, and the inspired Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
of the Gospel, in thus expounding the
Old Law by the New, and the New by the
Old.</p>
            <p>So that now I may with greater Freedom
propound my humble Conceptions in this
Matter; That where Multitudes of Fathers,
Councils, Schoolmen, Histories are wanting,
(which are all very beneficial Helps, where
they can be had, but, where they cannot be
come at,) if a Clergy-man shall resort im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:108092:30"/>
to the Fountain it self, first, and
always imploring the Assistance of that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
Spirit, by which the Scriptures were
written, and then, with a sincere Love of
the Truth, and Resolution to live according
to it, without which GOD will neither
hear our Prayers, nor bless our Endeavours;
and also with an humble Heart, a devout
Mind, and unquenchable Fervour of Spirit,
and a right unbyass'd Judgement; join'd
with a sufficient Skill in the Original Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages,
and in those other Introductory Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;
which no Man in Holy Orders, if it
be not the Bishop's Fault, as well as his own,
can possibly be altogether to seek in: And
if withal he shall be assisted with some of the
ancient, and some few of the modern sound,
and Orthodox Commentaries; he will, in all
human Probability, by an incessant, daily, and
nightly meditating upon, and revolving in
his Mind, the Divine Text it self, become,
in time, tho' not perhaps, as <hi>Apollos</hi> is said
to have been, <hi>Eloquent, and Mighty in the
Scriptures, yet a Workman that needeth not to
be ashamed, rightly dividing the Word of
Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:108092:30"/>The more to incourage your Studies in
this Method, if you shall be necessitated to
it, give me leave to present you with one
Example of a great Divine, and Bishop, in
the Time of King <hi>Charles</hi> the First, who was
one of the most Eminent Confessors then,
and survived those Calamities, to die in
Peace and Tranquillity, several Years after the
Return of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second.</p>
            <p>In the common Persecution, which then
happened to the whole Episcopal Order, this
Reverend Person was exposed to a more than
ordinary Degree of popular Malice, and
Rage; so that, without ever being once
brought to his Tryal, he was closely impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned
in the <hi>Tower,</hi> for almost twenty Years,
and was not only despoil'd of his annual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue,
and Personal Estate, in the first Fury
of the Civil Wars; but was also plunder'd
of most of the Collections of his former La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
and a very considerable Library.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, being thus laid up in Prison,
without any prospect of Liberty, having also
a numerous Family to maintain, so that he
was not able, in any sort, to repair the Loss
of his Books, and Papers, he betook himself
to this course of Study. Well-knowing, that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:108092:31"/>
he could have no faithfuller Companion for
his Solitude, nor surer Consolation in his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions,
than the Holy Scriptures, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
himself to them immediately, with little
other help, but what he had within himself,
and the best Prints of the Originals in the
Learned Tongues, and their Translations in
the Learned, and Modern, in both which he
was a great Master.</p>
            <p>Thus however he firmly, and vigorously
proceeded so far in the single Study of the
Scriptures, that long before his Enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
he had composed a great Mass of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations
on divers Parts of the Bible.
What is become of them, I know not.
If they are either imbezill'd, or suppress'd,
no doubt, it is to the great Damage of the
Church; since the Native Thoughts of a
Great Man are generally, at least, as good
as the most Artificial.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you will say, he might be able to
do all this by the Strength of his Memory,
and the Variety of Learning he had laid up
in it before-hand: And I make no doubt but
those were an exceeding great Assistance to
him.</p>
            <p>But what was very remarkable, and for
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:108092:31"/>
which I am bold to produce him as an
Instance worthy your Imitation in this
Particular, I know, he was often heard
to profess solemnly, that in all his former
Studies, and various Reading, and Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations,
he had never met with a more
useful Guide, or a surer Interpreter, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
his Paths in the dark Places of <hi>the lively
Oracles,</hi> to give Information to his Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
in the obscure Passages, or Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
to his Conscience in the experimental
Truths of them, than when he was thus dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
by Necessity, to the assiduous Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation
of the Scripture alone, and to weigh
it by it self, as it were, in the Ballance of the
Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>Had I not been already so tedious, there
is one Particular behind, on which I ought
most justly to have expatiated, which now
I can only name; And it is that touching the
<hi>Manner</hi> of your Conversation; that it be
such, as may render you <hi>Vessels,</hi> not only
<hi>sanctified,</hi> but <hi>meet for your Masters Vse,</hi> and,
as St. <hi>Paul</hi> also adds, <hi>Vessels of Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would therefore recommend to Men of
your Character, not only the Innocency, and
Sincerity, but (as much as human Frailties
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:108092:32"/>
will allow,) the Comeliness, and the Amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleness
of every Word, and Action of your
Lives: That you especially would not only
strive <hi>to follow whatsoever Things are true, or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest,
or just, but</hi> moreover <hi>whatsoever Things are
pure and lovely, and of good Report;</hi> that you
would <hi>think on these Things, not only if there be
any Virtue, but if there be any Praise of Virtue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From you, my Brethren, it may well be
expected<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that your Behavior should not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
be unblameable, but, if I may be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
so to say, something more than strictly
unblameable, and that not only to those with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
but also towards them who as yet are
without; that you should not only keep
your Minds clean, your Hands unpolluted,
your Tongues well-govern'd, your whole
Course of Life spotless, and upright, and
your Consciences undefiled, but also <hi>your
Consciences void of Offence,</hi> and that <hi>towards
Men,</hi> as well as <hi>towards GOD:</hi> That you
may be not only exemplary in your Families,
in your Parishes, in the Neighbouring Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
in the whole Church of GOD, to the
Gentry, to the Laity, to your Brethren of
the Clergy, to the Commonalty of our
Communion, for your Justice, Modesty,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:108092:32"/>
Sobriety, Prudence, Quietness, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
to Superiors; but that you would
exercise, and extend all these Virtues, and
also your Humility, Long-suffering, good
Will, good Wishes, Condescention, and
Affability, even beyond the Church it self,
to the very Enemies of it: That towards all
Men you would sweeten the Gravity of
your Behaviour, and soften the Strictness of
your Conversation, with the Gentleness,
and Suavity of your Manners: That you
would take special Care, as never to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinately
in the wrong, so, when you are sure
you are in the right, even then never to be
too rigidly, austerely, or morosely in the
right: That by all reasonable Respects,
mild and winning Converse, and not only
by a ready Return, but by a chearful Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention
of all Christian good Offices; and
even by making your very Oppositions, and
Contentions with those, that differ from
you, if you shall happen to be forced to any,
as humane and friendly, and <hi>easie to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated,</hi>
as possible; by all this you may do
your part <hi>to put to silence the Ignorance of
foolish and unreasonable Men.</hi> Who knows
but you may convert, and gain some of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:108092:33"/>
them? Who knows, but by your thus <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing</hi>
not only <hi>Righteousness, and Faith,</hi> but
<hi>Peace and Charity;</hi> by your being not only
<hi>apt to teach, but gentle to all Men, and patient,
in Meekness instructing those that oppose them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves;</hi>
who knows, but by these Means <hi>GOD
peradventure will give</hi> the fiercest Adversaries
of our Church <hi>Repentance to the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the Truth?</hi> Most certainly by these
Means, or by no other, in all human Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</p>
            <p>I cannot now enlarge, as I would, on this
most necessary and seasonable Argument.
But unquestionably by thus keeping your
selves free from haughty Censoriousness, and
untractable Peevishness, and sullen Darkness
of Life, and Manners; And by excelling in
the contrary Virtues, you will, in the best
way, teach and convince all that dissent
from you, how unworthy such a Pharisai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
Garb, and Disposition is of the true
Christian Liberty, or Severity.</p>
            <p>In short, by such a grave, sedate, decent,
charitable Course, and Colour of your
whole Lives, you will do your selves, and
especially the Church of <hi>England</hi> most
Right. For our Church it self, wherever
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:108092:33"/>
she is set in a true Light, cannot but be
found to be most of this sweet, meek, and
truly pacific Temper, of any Church in the
Christian World.</p>
            <p>I conclude therefore. Whoever among her
Sons, and Members, much more among her
Teachers, and Fathers, as you, and we are,
shall not do their utmost, to attain to this
gentle, obliging, charming Manner of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation,
which our Church prescribes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
all Men, Adversaries as well as Friends,
I must repeat what our Blessed Saviour said to
his Disciples, on the like Occasion, <hi>they know
not what Spirit they are of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is one or two short Requests more
I am to make you, which chiefly respect
me, as your unworthy Bishop; and then I
shall give ease to your Patience.</p>
            <p>One is to intreat, that you would be
exceeding watchful, and indeed religiously
serupulous, for whom you give Certificates
and Testimonials. For what some of you,
perhaps out of good Nature, or good
Neighbourhood, or an Easiness, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
able to resist Importunity, may at first
think to be only a Matter of Form, is not
so to me. I have scarce any other way pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:108092:34"/>
of being rightly informed, from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,
of the good Lives, or sufficient Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of the Persons, but only by yours,
and the like Testimonies. The Law of the
Land appoints that Method to me, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most
confines me to it. Whereas, if you
make this to be only a Business of private Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,
or Partiality, not of public Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and Conscience, I may chance to be
led into very mischievous, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
irreparable Mistakes; only by that,
which you may esteem but as a piece of
Bashfulness, and good Breeding: I may be
induced to lay Hands on the ignorant, and
unworthy, meerly by the Authority of your
Names, the subscribing of which you might
think to be only an Office of common Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity
and Modesty.</p>
            <p>My next and last Request to you, at this
time, shall concern your Curates. This it
may suffice only to intimate to you. I
know, I need not spend many Words on it
in this Assembly; because there is but a very
small inconsiderable Number of Pluralists
in my Diocese. I am persuaded, they will
be found upon Inquiry the fewest of any in
<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:108092:34"/>I cannot but say, I could be very well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
there were more: Especially if all, so
qualified, would be rigorously true to the
Church, in their Choice of Substitutes, where
they cannot always reside themselves.</p>
            <p>For, as I will frankly own, I never yet
heard an invincible Objection, against the
prudent Allowance, and moderate Use of
Pluralities; but only some plausible popular
ones against the Abuse of them; which we
are as much offended with as any others can
be: So, I verily believe, were this Legal
Indulgence to the Clergy so carefully obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
every where, as, among divers other
good Ends of it, to furnish us with a Race
of painful, learned, Godly Curates; who,
by this way of Probation, may make, and
shew themselves worthy to be promoted to
a higher Charge; there Pluralities would
be so far from being a Scandal, or Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,
that they would conduce to the
Strength, and Defence, as well as they do
to the Ease, and Ornament of the Church
of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great Obligation then I am to lay
upon you; you, I mean, whom it does at
present concern, is this, That you would be
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:108092:35"/>
very unmovably faithful to me, to your
selves, and to the whole Church of GOD,
in the Persons, whom, on just Occasions,
you shall offer to me to be your Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates.</p>
            <p>I do not only intend, that you should ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
Own, or Patronize any, as your Curates,
who really are not so, that, under that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,
by false Titles, they may slip into
Holy Orders. But I speak of such Instances
where you really have need of, and the
Law allows you to have Curates. In such
Cases, it is my earnest Intreaty, that you
would not only keep all the Legal Times of
your own Residence, and Hospitality; and
not only afford your Curates a liberal Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
in your Absence; Liberal, I mean,
not only for their own Livelihood, but for
their continuing some kind of Hospitality
too, to the Poor at least: But that you, you
especially, who are of greater Age, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,
would watch over your Curates
as your Fellow-Labourers, your Friends, your
Probationers; for whose Improvement, in
Divine Learning, Godly Conversation, and
Abilities of Teaching, you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or I, must be
answerable to the Great Shepherd of our
Souls.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:108092:35"/>But it is high time to dismiss you. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech
Almighty GOD to assist, and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
all your Labours, to His Glory, and
your own Comfort in the Great Day of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.
Towards the obtaining which Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
Ends, you can never think of any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
or indeed of any other Means, than by
living up<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in your private Conversation, to
the Religion you profess, and teach others;
and, in your public Office, by defending
and supporting the Church established by
Law in this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>A Religion, and a Church, that well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves
all this at your hands; being in its
Faith most Primitive, in its Orders most A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolical;
in its Discipline most Moderate;
in its Charity most Diffusive; in its Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
most Spiritual as to the Substance;
most decent as to the Circumstances. In
few Words, in its Interests it is inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
united with the Laws and Rights, with
the Well-Being, I had almost said with the
Being, of the English Nation and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
In its Principles, it is irreconcilable
with the Interests of Popery, and the only
impregnable Defence against its Return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
this Land: Which, it is much to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:108092:36"/>
that the Dissenters will not see, and
are therefore Dissenters, since it is evident,
the Papists themselves have always seen it
but too well.</p>
            <p>What then remains? but that as Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
as English-Men, as Church-Men, we
should all make it our principal, our only
great Concern, and pray to <hi>GOD the Father
of Mercies,</hi> that all others of our Character,
throughout the Nation, would make it
theirs; to represent to the World the true
Excellencies of such a Religion, and such a
Church, by our Doctrine and Example,
with Industry, and Vigilance, with Stedfast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
and Courage, <hi>in Meekness of Wisdom,
and with Zeal according to Knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if we shall all, in this Manner, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote
our selves to this Work, we may then
be assured, that the same Promise, which
our Lord Christ, in some of his last Words
on Earth, made to his whole Church,
will be eminently made good to this, the
purest part of it in these latter Ages of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity,
that <hi>He himself will be alway with it
even to the End of the World.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:108092:36"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
