<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An admonition concerning a publick fast the just causes we have for it, from the full growth of sin, and the near approaches of God's judgments : and the manner of performance to obtain the desired effects thereof, which ought to be other than our Common Forms, and with stricter acts of moritication than is usual amongst us : with an abstract of Mr. Chillingworth's judgement of the state of religion in this nation in his time : and of a letter from the Hague concerning two sermons preached there in the French church at which were present divers of the English nobility.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-09">2003-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19528</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11761456</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11761456</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48699</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A61415)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48699)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 550:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An admonition concerning a publick fast the just causes we have for it, from the full growth of sin, and the near approaches of God's judgments : and the manner of performance to obtain the desired effects thereof, which ought to be other than our Common Forms, and with stricter acts of moritication than is usual amongst us : with an abstract of Mr. Chillingworth's judgement of the state of religion in this nation in his time : and of a letter from the Hague concerning two sermons preached there in the French church at which were present divers of the English nobility.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
                  <author>Chillingworth, William, 1602-1644.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Stephens who is known as Socrates Christianus. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fasting --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Judgment Day --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fasts and feasts --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>God --  Love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-08</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48699:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48699:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ADMONITION CONCERNING <hi>A Publick FAST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Just <hi>CAUSES</hi> we have for it, from the full <hi>Growth</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> and the near <hi>Approaches</hi> of God's <hi>Judgments;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND The <hi>MANNER</hi> of Performance, to obtain the desired Effects thereof;</p>
            <p>Which ought to be other than our Common Forms; and with stricter Acts of Mortification than is usual amongst us.</p>
            <p>With an <hi>ABSTRACT</hi> of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>'s Judgment of the State of Religion in this Na<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on in his time.</p>
            <p>And of a Letter from the <hi>Hague</hi> concerning two Sermons Preached there in the <hi>Fr<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nch</hi> Church, at which were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent divers of the <hi>English</hi> Nobility.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year M DC XCI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:48699:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48699:2"/>
            <head>To the Queen.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce the Authority of your Majesty hath appeared so particularly in a most Necessary Appointment of <hi>a Publick Fast and Humiliation to be Observed in most Devout and Solemn manner for Supplicating Almighty God for Pardon of our Sins, and Imploring his Blessing,</hi> &amp;c. not once, but <hi>every Month during the War.</hi> It may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed, that what is sincerely endeavoured, that so Necessary and Pious a Command may happily obtain its desired Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, cannot fail of a Favourable and Benign Construction with a person of so much Piety and Sense of Religion: though to those Naturals or Animals, in whom the God of this World hath blinded their Minds, it cannot but seem Foolishness and Canting, as must all Truth to those, who are both Ignorant and yet Conceited: and though to such as are Big with the Wisdom of the World (which is Foolishness with God) <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome things in it may seem Rude and Presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous: For true Piety could bear even the Railing of a <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei</hi> in a time of Humiliation; and Christian Wisdom can easily discern and distinguish between Height of Fidelity and Affection in the plain Words of Truth and Soberness, and that Malice and Falsehood, which are always ingredients of Railing and Presumption. Even Civil Prudence, consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the irreparable Mischiefs, which are daily wrought in the Courts and Councils of Princes by Treacherous Flattery, will not only permit and allow, but favour and encourage Serious Liberty and Freedom of Speech upon just and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary occasion in persons of unspotted and undoubted Fidelity
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48699:3"/>
and Affection: But Christian Wisdom much more; and especially in Times of Account, which call for Humiliation, Repentance, Reformation, and Judging our Selves; and for Publick Humiliation, and particular Confession of Publick and known Sins and Offences, with their Circumstances of Aggravation, and carefull Search to discover them. Which is the only way to lay a sure Foundation, and to be raised up by the Mighty Hand of God.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, <hi>Madam,</hi> presuming that I write to a person more Illustrious by such Great Virtues, than any fading, earthly Honour or Majesty can make you, besides what I have said in Common to all, I shall out of Fidelity and great Affection humbly represent to your Royal Consideration some few things more particularly relating to your self.</p>
            <p>I will not here recount the Great Things which God hath done for the Gradual raising of your Glory, nor tell you that the Eyes of all the World are upon you, and what Great Things they Hope and Expect from you: But this I may say in the Name of God, That his Eyes are upon you; <hi>the Eyes of the Lord,</hi> (which) <hi>run to and fro throughout the whole Earth, to shew himself strong in the behalf of them, whose Heart is perfect towards Him:</hi> (2 Chron. 16. 8.) That to whom much is given of them, much shall be required; and, That if you justly <hi>expect</hi> from your fellow Creatures, <hi>whom You imploy,</hi> Fidelity, Zeal, and Activity, proportionable to the Favours You confer, and the Trusts You repose in them; much more are You obliged to perform all these to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lord of all in the full Improvement of all t<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ose Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Talents of Honour, Authority and other Advantages, which he hath conferred upon You, for His Honour and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and with so much the more Vigor and Resolution, by how much the greater are the Difficulties which occur. <hi>The Highest pitch of all is the least Sacrifice that you can offer</hi> to Him.</p>
            <p>And therefore I will not, I may not tell you, <hi>That the Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, as well as the Calm of Peace, will be necessary for this:</hi> or, <hi>That your Resolving on it Inwardly before God, will be accepted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48699:3"/>
by Him,</hi> though you defer the Actual Performance till that Leisure and Calm, which you may never see, nor are ever like to see, while Difficult Duties are declined, neglected or deferred. For this would be to deceive You after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the False Prophets of old? and to expose You and Your Affairs to the Treacheries and Abuses of <hi>Dissolute and Depraved men,</hi> who <hi>be always truer to their Vices than to their Masters.</hi> But on the contrary, this I may be bold to affirm, that when by actual Discountenancing and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracing of Vice, and Encouraging of Virtue <hi>by distinguishing Marks of your Favour;</hi> and by a visible beginning of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming your Court and your People, and particularly that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which of all others should need it least, it is once understood that you are setled in those Noble Purposes, this will make the Execution of them Easie to you,</hi> and detect the Falsity of such dilatory Doctrines: and would have done so sooner if more Faithfull Advice had not been withstood by such as perverted the Right Ways of the Lord, and mis-led those they should have directed therein. For <hi>God hath wrought in the midst of us a Mighty Deliverance; and was ready to perfect and stablish that which he hath wrought for us.</hi> But it is now apparent that something there is, which doth <hi>stop that Course of Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings</hi> that, seems I cannot now say, but once did seem, <hi>ready to flow in upon us.</hi> And we have now another Count to cast up. We may and ought to recount the <hi>Mercies</hi> and <hi>Favours</hi> of God to us: But we have now, also an Account of his <hi>Judgments</hi> and <hi>Frowns</hi> to reflect upon: And this should lead us back to enter into another Account, <hi>viz.</hi> of Our <hi>Sins and Provocations.</hi> For that Course of <hi>Blessings,</hi> which for some time was only stopp'd, was afterwards turned to a Course of <hi>Crosses</hi> and Disappointments, or of a Mixture of Mercy and Judgment, and is now at last turning, it may be feared, to <hi>severe Judgment,</hi> Confusion, and Destruction, unless very speedily prevented, by strict and impartial Inquiry into the Causes, by truly Noble and Heroick Resolutions thereupon, and by a vigilant and vigorous Execution. For <hi>the King</hi> himself, if I, and many others, be not mistaken, hath already
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48699:4"/>
suffer'd some Diminution in some Essentials of his Majesty, Honour, and most Prevalent Powers and is in Danger to fall lower, from being a Glorious Instrument of God for Good and Happiness to this and many other Nations, into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable and despicable condition of being an occasion of Confusion and Misery: only there seems a door of Hope still open for him, upon one Consideration, if the Opportunity be not neglected; of which more presently: but first I think fit to say something briefly concerning <hi>The present State of Things in the World, and what may be expected from it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In matters of Prudence, none but weak and dull, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved Souls will expect Mathematical Demonstrations and Sensible Evidences, for all their Actions: God by his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath purposely so ordered the Course of things, that his Rational Creatures, Mankind, should be often necessita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a Close Application of their Minds, and a kind of <hi>Spiritual Discerning,</hi> in the Management of their own Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. This Faculty, as may be perceived by Experience, if well disposed, and carefully observed, extends much farther in many-things than men are able easily to demonstrate to others, and yet even in those often discerns very right. But such Indications may sometimes be observed from a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of various Circumstances as are Sufficient Principles of a Moral Demonstration. My pre-apprehensions of our own Occurrences have hitherto proved true in the Event; and I have now some Indications to help me.</p>
            <p>It is very apparent that there have been very few <hi>Princes</hi> or <hi>Great Men</hi> in the World for some years, or rather Ages, who have manifested in their Course of Life any great and just apprehension of the Business of Man upon Earth, much less of the Proper Business of Princes, and Persons under their Circumstances; But have generally both by their Example and their Management, been more subservient to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Darkness, than to the Kingdom of Light; And their Courts, Armies, Navies, and all their great Meetings, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally little other than Seminaries and Nurseries of Pride, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, Covetousness, Injustice, Oppression, Luxury, Impiety,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48699:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Prophaneness, and all manner of Vice and Wickedness; where Souls in great numbers have been trained up and habituated to all the Diabolical Qualities of that dismal crew: and so deceived and abused have they been by False Prophets and other Instruments of that Kingdom, appearing great in the World in pomp and grandure, magnifick Names and Titles, the superficial Ornaments of Literature and Wisdom of the World, (all directly contrary to the Simplicity of the Gospel) that they have believed it must be so, and cannot be otherwise; we must not expect Armies of Saints; and so have plainly given over all Care of Reformation of those things, as Impracticable, Platonick or Phanatick-Phansies.</p>
            <p>It is likewise apparent that <hi>the People</hi> in all places, even where hath been, or still is the greatest Profession of Religion, (both Laity and Clergy) are most grievously degenerated and corrupted; a great part with the most gross Vices, and scandalous Sins; others of more consideration and sense of Reputation, some with Atheism and Infidelity; others with Formality or Superstition; some with Hypocrisie and Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and most of the very best with over-valuation of the things of the World, and with Pride of some Worldly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, of Birth, of Estate, Favour with Great Men, Wit, Learning, Apparel, Attendance, or some such Hobby-horse or other, over-looking divers necessary Christian Virtues, and even to despise and be ashamed of Christ himself in his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, if appearing in the genuine form of their Master; so that a Genuine Compleat Christian is rare to be found in the World, especially among those who have the greatest share of it: and the Sins both of Princes and of People seem to have over-grown all the Methods of the Divine Providence for their Amendment.</p>
            <p>And it is also apparent that such are <hi>the Posture and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Humane Affairs at this time in Europe,</hi> as are plain Indications that Almighty God by his Providence is produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing some <hi>Great Alteration</hi> in this part of the World very suddenly. And what this is like to be is well and carefully to be considered. Nor is it any presumption to do this soberly;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48699:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
but so far from that, that to discern the Signs of the Times is a plain and necessary Duty; the Neglect or Non-observance whereof is condemned in the <hi>Jews</hi> in the like case, by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and before by the Prophets.</p>
            <p>The present <hi>Posture</hi> of Affairs is a State of <hi>War,</hi> which is <hi>one of God's Judgments,</hi> for the Punishment of Princes and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and such as the present Sinfull State both of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and People hath justly deserved, and we may therefore reasonably conclude hath provoked. This War is between <hi>two great Parties,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Turk</hi> on the one side, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror and the Confederates on the other: And most Princes and States are concerned in it. And if we consider <hi>the Motions</hi> of this War, it was <hi>begun</hi> by the <hi>French</hi> King in secret Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy with the <hi>Turk</hi> and the late Kings of <hi>England,</hi> without any Colour of Justice, merely to gratifie a Proud, Haughty, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solent, Luciserian, Domineering Humour, and <hi>carried on</hi> with barbarous Cruelty, even upon his own Subjects, and Devasta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abroad. But the Divine Providence at last interposed, and put a Hook in his Nostrils, deprived him of the Assistance of both his Confedarates, and turned the Strength of one of them against him; and thereby gave an offer of Mercy, and a fair Opportunity to the Confederates to have been the Instruments of his Judgments against that Wicked Insolent Invader, had they wisely improved that Divine Favour, for the Service of God and the Reformation and Good of the People.</p>
            <p>But they have all been insensible of, and unhappily neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their Duty; and have likewise in a great measure lost that fair opportunity put into their hands; so that the Favour of the Divine Providence seems in some sort to have forsaken them, and gon over to their Enemies for the Punishment of this and all their former Sins and Miscarriages, and Unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableness for his Service. And indeed whether we consider the Provocations of God's Judgments by this Neglect under such Circumstances, or the present State of Affairs (which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not here particularly observe) both present us with too just reasons for some apprehensions, That that cruel and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Tyrant may now be made the Terrible Instrument of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48699:5"/>
Divine Vengeance, for purging these Countries of that Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness, which they would not reform; and for casting out such unprofitable Servants; unless it be prevented immediately by some extraordinary and vigorous Means of Reformation.</p>
            <p>For, as all <hi>the Judgments of God</hi> are for Punishment of Sin, and Reformation of Manners; so the Common <hi>Sinfull State</hi> of all Nations in these parts, and the <hi>General Commotions</hi> of all, are a plain Indication of <hi>some Great Judgment coming up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all,</hi> who do not prevent it by speedy Repentance, and some notable Reformation. And because the Judgments of God are frequently executed not onely upon Persons, but in a special manner also upon such Things, as have been much abused to his dishonor or disservice, <hi>the Great Work,</hi> which all these Commotions overruled by the Holy Providence of God tend to, may in all probability be, not onely the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment of the Persons of all degrees, but the putting down or abolishing of all that Rule, Authority and Power in the World, which hath been so abused, unprofitable and disser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to their Great and proper Master, to make way for that Glorious Kingdom and Blessed <hi>Theocracy,</hi> which shall never be destroyed. This was begun, and should have been done by the Confederates against that Insolent Tyrant and common Oppressor, had they well considered their Business and subjected their Power to Their Sovereign, and used their Authority in subservience to this Great Work, first by Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of themselves and of the People subjected to them. But they not considering, but neglecting this principal Part, the present Posture of things seems to theraten, That they may be first suppressed and the Sins and Wickedness of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves and their People punished, by Him, and Himself at last for all his Insolence and Wickedness by some extraordinary Judgment. Yet possibly there is not any of them all, but if they shall in time open their Eyes, and without any sinister Designs to set up themselves, apply their Power sincerely and by direct and proper Means to promote the Service of GOD in this Great Work, they may be received and well rewarded, both with Honour here, and Happiness hereafter.</p>
            <p>Of all the Confederates, none hath been more highly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48699:6"/>
by an Extraordinary Providence than King <hi>William;</hi> but in my apprehension, none hath more failed than he, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering his circumstances, in the Duty incumbent upon him; nor is any in greater danger both in that respect, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the present State of his Affairs, which I take to be in all respects the Consequence of that. Onely there seems to be yet, as I said, a door of Mercy and Favour open for him, in as much as it is now apparent, that it was not wholly his Fault, but partly his Unhappiness, in that he had no better Guides to direct and admonish him; and if he yet be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and resolute to doe what he ought, though now more difficult, and therefore to be performed with so much the greater Resolution, possibly he may recover in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure his former Prosperous Condition; though I doubt that He may suffer such loss, as may be just matter for a longer Sorrow and Repentance; and that he that hath troubled both Him and us shall bear his Judgment, whoever he be, unless he prevent it by some proper and eminent Works of Repentance.</p>
            <p>Many things more I had to have said: but this first Work is of so great Importance, that unless it be instantly and effectually provided for, it will be in vain to think of far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther applications. Nay our very Fasting and Humiliation, and all the Prayers in the World, will avail nothing, unless the Troublers of <hi>Israel</hi> be brought forth, and the Accursed thing be removed. If this were once well resolved upon and concluded, it would not be hard to detect greater Troublers of our <hi>Israel,</hi> than those who are now in danger of their Lives; and soon to put things into such a posture of Security, as the King need not fear Confusions in his Absence, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise may be feared.</p>
            <p>Yet one thing there is most peculiar to your self that however ought not to be omitted upon this oceasion; and that is <hi>the manifest Judgments of God upon your own Royal Family, and</hi> upon so near a Relation as a <hi>Father;</hi> and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments both <hi>Spiritual,</hi> of strong Delusions; and <hi>Temporal,</hi> of just and deserved Exclusion from the Government of these Nations. The due Consideration whereof will easily disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48699:6"/>
several Obligations upon you. 1. The Consideration of such Unhappiness of so near a Relation (which is matter not onely of particular Humiliation, but of continual Grief and Mourning) requires great Seriousness in all your beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and Circumspection lest Prosperity make you forget it, and thereby offend God, and so bring Evil upon your self. 2. The Consideration of the Provoking Causes requires, first, your Humiliation under them, and that you be content and willing, and desirous that they may be plainly and fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected: first, that you may avoid them, and all partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation in them, lest you be overtaken and involved in the Judgments of God upon them: but, secondly and principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the Glory of God, and manifestation of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness of his Judgments: for should you offer to hinder this, as it would tend to the Scandal of his Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, so it would certainly provoke him to detect all some other way to your greater Shame and Confusion, and bring the same Judgments upon your self. Secondly, It requires your utmost Care and Circumspection all your life long to avoid them, that you abhor them, come not near them, lest they lay hold on you: for of all they are the most dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous for You, by reason of the Participation in so great a Store of Guilt, and the Warning given you by such Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the special Temptations you are like to meet with.</p>
            <p>There is <hi>an Iniquity</hi> in that Family, <hi>which might be traced</hi> a great way <hi>back into Scotland;</hi> but King <hi>James</hi> I, came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England</hi> by the Favour of Providence, in a State of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. And therefore we need look no farther back for this purpose. By and under the same Favour have all his Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors come to the Throne, and your self in particular: but they all forseited it, and that You may not, is this plain Advice written. <hi>His great Sins,</hi> which have most ensnared his Posterity were, 1. <hi>Great Injustice,</hi> and a very wicked Design by a <hi>Mystery of Iniquity</hi> to subvert a Noble Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Government, which God had intrusted him with, and he had sworn to mainian; and, 2. <hi>Abuse and Prophanation</hi> of Religion to serve his Unrighteous Design. To give a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular account of each of these would be too long for this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48699:7"/>
place. But there are two <hi>Effects</hi> thereof which have ever since been very pernicious to his Posterity and to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and at the present are the greatest occasions of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Danger to Your Government, above all other. The one is, <hi>False Notions concerning the Constitution of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Prerogative, and the Rights of the People,</hi> which cost your Grandfather his Head, and your Father his Crown, and at present mislead many worthy and honest Persons, to be your Adversaries, who would otherwise have been your loyal and faithfull Subjects; and would be much more mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous to you, if you should by that Faction, Flattery, or any Temptation be once possessed with them. They are in their original, a Mystery of Iniquity, a wicked Imposture, and such as the Vengeance of the Righteous God has pursued, and still will, till they be eradicated; and it concerns you much to be very carefull to avoid them, and that the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions and Stumbling-stones be removed by some deliberate Acts of King and Parliament, and of a Convocation: for they will otherwise prove a Root of Bitterness to the whole race of the Authour. Your Government is Just and Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, let but the Execution of it be so too, and God's Blessing will be upon it. The other is, the <hi>Overspreading of Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Formality,</hi> which all Governours are obliged to use their utmost Care and Endeavours to reform, but You dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that you may also discharge your self of the Guilt of your Ancestors; I might say trebly, <hi>viz.</hi> also out of Gratitude for the special Mercies and Favours you have received. Nay it is your special Business, as much to suppress that, as to cast out Popery, without which you cannot prosper.</p>
            <p>That God will bless your Majesty, and that you may be faithfull to him, and to the Trust reposed in You, and may flourish in all Grace and Virtue and Prosperity, is the hearty Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Loyal and Faithfull Subject,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48699:7"/>
            <head>AN ADMONITION Concerning A PUBLICK FAST, TO Implore the Mercy and Favour of GOD for the Averting of his Judgments, and the Recovering of his Blessing.</head>
            <p>BEcause I have heard that we are like to have a Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for a Publick Fast; or however, because I am certain we have great need to have one, at least for the use of those who desire to be found Mourners in secret for the Abominations that be done in the Land; I have thought fit, as an Act of Duty to God, and Charity to my Country, to publish this brief Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning the present just <hi>Causes</hi> we have for it, and that manner of <hi>Performance</hi> of it, which must be observed if we expect any good effect thereof. I did formerly, upon occasion of the Fast, <hi>Jun.</hi> 5. 1689. publish a Paper <hi>Of Humiliation,</hi> of which one of the Scoffers of the latter Times, at a Coffee-House scoffingly said, He supposed that would do more Service than 20000 Men in <hi>Ireland.</hi> But how long did we afterwards see more than 20000 Men lie near the Enemy there, and do nothing at all! Not dare to attack them,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48699:8"/>
though one would think encouraged enough with so great and easie Success then so lately in <hi>England!</hi> But of the Invisible Powers, which attend and interpose in the Affairs of Men, such bruitish Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals have little Sense or Apprehension. And therefore it is not unlikely that this may meet with the like Entertainment: But I am perswaded that they shall proceed no further, and that their Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety will very shortly meet with a due Correction, if not before by the Hand of Governors, by the Hand of Providence and the Sword of an Enemy in the midst of them.</p>
            <p>And therefore, leaving them to their own severe Mistress, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, There are two great <hi>Causes to provoke us to an extraordinary Humiliation</hi> at this time. 1. <hi>The Fulness and Ripeness of Sin. 2. The near Approaches of a terrible Judgment.</hi> Concerning <hi>the former</hi> to say nothing of other Evidences of its Maturity, this one I think is sufficient, <hi>When it is become past Remedy by Humane Means, it must needs be ripe for the Judgments of God.</hi> And then certainly is it past all Humane Means, when it hath either so infected the Governors and Ministers that they will not, or is become so prevalent that they cannot or dare not correct it, or punish it as it ought. And this is plainly our Case. Rarely hath any Prince been more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admonished of a Special Duty, and of the dangerous Consequence of the Neglect of it than King <hi>William</hi> hath been, and in due Time: And as rarely any more plainly admonished of his Fault when committed, and of the Mischiefs thereby incurred, than he bath been again and again. Never was <hi>Parliament</hi> more plainly admonished of a foul Fault in the beginning of so great a Work, than our Convention was of that-in their Order for the Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, (which hath proved a Root of Bitterness ever since) but so senseless in such matters is this Generation grown, that I doubt we have some Doctors, who do not understand it to this Day. Nor ever were Parliaments more provoked to their Duty by plain-deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than ours have been again and again. Lastly, never were <hi>Bishops</hi> more honestly and plainly told of their Duty, nor more justly and homely reproved for their most shameful Neglect, than ours have been. But alas! here's the Root of all our Evil. Their Unfaithfulness to God, whose special Service was their proper bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness; Unfaithfulness to Kings, whom they have magnified above measure, and more slattered for their own Advantage, than faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully admonished for the Service of God, and been more forward to conspire with to subvert the Rights of their Country, than to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48699:8"/>
admonish them of their Duty both to God and Man, to be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors of the Right of the meanest Subject. Their Neglect of their Episcopal Authority for Reproof and Correction of the Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Sins, especially of Great Men, against the Laws of God; and on the contrary, Abuse of it for punishment of Sober and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientious People with the utmost Severity for any breach of their own Canons, or Laws made for their Advantage; hath been the greatest <hi>Inlet</hi> of all our Mischief, of the Bruitish and Carnal Sins of the Nation: And again, their earnest and endless pursuit of Preferments, and mis-imployment of what they get, hath been the great <hi>Incentive</hi> to those <hi>Animal Sins</hi> of Covetousness and Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which have betrayed the Nation, and been the immediate Means to bring the Judgments of God so near to us, as they are at this time. Nor is this all: But besides their Unprositableness in that great Place and Advantage, which they had to have done good in the Parliament, they have not only heretofore been the Principal Obstructors of many good things, which have been proposed and begun in the House of Commons, but have of late laid aside a Bill for the necessary Reformation of Manners, and preventing the approaching Judgments of God, which was drawn at the Request of some of them, without offering any other in the place of it. And besides, some of them have not only in private obstructed the good Effect of those faithful Admonitions, which have been given to the King, by misrepresenting the Person to him who sent them, as if the Truth and Weight of the Admonitions had not been the only thing to be regarded, whoever was the Instrument; but have at last even from the Pulpit, in the Face of the World, encouraged the King to Security in Neglect of that great Duty, which had been so earnestly pressed in those Admonitions for his own Good; and done it in such a manner, as never any of the false Prophets of old, (except only their Pretence of special re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation or the great Enemy of Mankind could have done more subtily and plausibly: Which though of sad Consideration in other respects, yet may give the more hope of <hi>the Kings Case,</hi> that there is in it so much the less of Fault as there is more of Unhappiness, in that he hath been so unfaithfully dealt with by those about him. And if with this we take. into the Consideration the Bishops Excuse, why they did not offer the Bill in the House of Lords, <hi>viz.</hi> Lest a thing of that Nature should be ridicaled and contemned, and Religion with it. I suppose no serious Man but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48699:9"/>
will acknowledge all this to be sufficient Evidence of the Prevalence and full Maturity of Sin and Wickedness in this Nation.</p>
            <p>And now concerning the near <hi>Approaches of God's Judgments</hi> upon the Nation. Every Affliction or Calamity upon a Person or Nation is not presently to be reputed a Judgment or Punishment of Sin. Some may be for the Glory of God, and some for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of his Creatures. But when we see notorious and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Sins followed with proportionable Calamities and Afflictions, then we may safely conclude them <hi>Judgments;</hi> especially when we see Afflictions after Afflictions, or Interchanges of Afflictions and Mercies, and the Afflictions more and more increasing, but the Provocations no whit abated, but either still increasing, or Men more and more hardned in them, and insensible of God's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that is a dangerous Sign that some terrible Judgment is not far off. But when in such Case a particular Calamity is as visible as a Cloud in the Air, and as likely to fall upon a Nation, as such a Cloud to break into a Storm, (as when you see <hi>Jerusalem</hi> encompassed with Armies) then the Approaches of that Judgment are very near. And whether this be not the Case of this Nation at this time, deserves our very serious Consideration speedily. Of the Ripeness and Maturity of the Sins of the Nation I have given suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Evidence before: It remains thereof only to consider what <hi>Prospect</hi> there is <hi>of any particular Calamity</hi> visible, which may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably or possibly be approaching this Nation. And if we look back for most part of these Thirty Years last past, there has been a Storm in brewing, often ready to break out very terribly both upon these and some Neighbour Nations; but it hath pleased God that it hath as often blown over, and served only for so many Warnings. And it was within these three years that we were in very great Danger, we and our Neighbours too; and it pleased God to give us as great, and a very extraordinary Deliverance. But how little good Effect it hath had upon us, may be understood by what is said already; to which I will add only this, that as we prophaned our Thanksgiving for our Deliverance with a frothy Complement to the Instrument, so do we now make a sport and a Trade of the Approaches of God's Judgments; a matter that hath more of Sin and Provocation in it, than this Sensual Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is apprehensive of and a very ill Sign of a dangerous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Certainly God, after so great a Manifestation of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in our Deliverance, expected other and more substantial
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48699:9"/>
Returns than such a Formality; and when we notwithstanding neglected our Duty, he was graciously pleased the first year to correct our Neglect only with a Suspension of his Blessing; all things were at a stand with us, nothing prosper'd or succeeded: But when we still continued our Neglect, he proceeded one degree fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to a smarter Chastisement by a shameful Bafflle of our Fleet at Sea, through the Unfaithfulness or Fearfulness (so suitable a Punishment) of some employed in that Service; to say nothing of other Misfortunes elsewhere. And now we are come to the third year without any Amendment, and with a bolder and brisker At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of a Powerful and Active Adversary, very early, and with good Success, in the View, in a manner, of the King himself; and perhaps not without some Error committed through Fearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, if not Unfaithfulness in some of his Council of War. And if we well consider how Powerful, Active and Forward our Adversary is, how distracted our Allies are abroad, how divided we our selves are at home; how unfaithfully, or unwisely, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>successfully our Affairs are managed both at home and abroad, we have reason to fear the Approaches of a very terrible Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment very near. And if things be well examined, we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend not only a <hi>Proportionable</hi> but a <hi>Suitable</hi> Judgment in all, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulness, Fearfulness of God's Enemies, and adhering to Dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory wicked Councils, punished with like Unfaithfulness, Fearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of our Enemies, and like Dilatory Counsels in those we em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy. And for the nearness of the Approaches of Judgments, at the very instant, while I am writing this, are we alarm'd with a terrible beginning of a Fire breaking out in the Royal Palace at <hi>Whitehal.</hi> Certainly, we have great Reason to believe that the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment of Bishop <hi>Usher</hi>'s Prediction is very near, and that we may soon be taught what Monsieur <hi>St. Jean</hi>'s <hi>Thunder under Ground</hi> did import, by a sudden Resurrection and Eruption of the Plots, which the Unsaithfulness and Deceitfulness of some have so politickly buried, if not prevented by a very speedy Alteration of our Ordering of things so as may be both more for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Service of God, that we may recover his Favour and Blessing, and better for the Security of the Nation, which his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Blessing alone can help and lead us to.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Recovery</hi> of which, (which is my next business) we must</p>
            <p n="1">1. First consider the <hi>Majesty of God,</hi> with whom we have to do, in respect of which the greatest Majesty upon Earth is Ten
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48699:10"/>
Thousand times less than the faintest Shadow we can behold, and the greatest Monarch but a Butterfly; nay, less than the meanest and most despicable Animal. He is a God of infinite Mercy indeed, but withal of absolute Justice and Holiness, and very terrible in his Judgments against obstinate and incorrigible Sinners.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We must next consider the <hi>sinful State and Condition of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> the <hi>Universality</hi> of it, having overspread all Orders, our Kings, our Nobles, our Priests and our Prophets, and all Ranks and Degrees of our People. The <hi>Growth and long Continuance of it,</hi> and the <hi>Impudence and Obstinacy</hi> of it, out-facing all Humane Authority, and standing out without Remorse against the various repeated Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Methods, both of Judgments and Mercies, to bring us to Repentance and Reformation: And the great <hi>Danger,</hi> it is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain fallen into by reason of our unprofitableness upon so late and great a Mercy and Deliverance as our last was.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And when with such Considerations we are affected with such a sense of our Condition as is meet, and a sincere internal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, we must speedily apply our selves to give Glory to God, by serious and solemn <hi>External Actions of Humiliation;</hi> appointing of Days for the purpose, afflicting our Souls in strict <hi>Fasting and Mortification, confessing</hi> the Sins of the Nation, of our Kings, and our Priests, and our Prophets, and all sorts amongst us, plainly and truly with great Seriousness and sense of the Evil of them, and the Justice of all the Judgments we either feel or fear, with humble and earnest Supplications and Deprecations. But this, if it be done to purpose, had need be done in another manner than is usual in the Forms of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and with more strictness in the Acts of Mortification than is usual amongst u.</p>
            <p>When Publick Sins and manifest Judgments require Publick Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, then to neglect it is a great Aggravation of the Sin and Provocation of Judgment: To appoint a Day, and not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve it with the greatest Seriousness, Solemnity and Strictness, is to lose our Labour, prophane a Sacred Duty, and add a greater Aggravation and Provocation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But if all thus far be performed never so well and exactly, yet there remains <hi>one thing more,</hi> which if neglected, will certainly not only frustrate the Effect of all the rest, but convert it to the highest Aggravation and Provocation. And that is the Removal of the Accursed Thing, whatever it be, and <hi>Reformation</hi> of what is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48699:10"/>
amiss, instantly, if it be such as may be done instantly. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to set about it, and do what may be done toward it; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly, and then pursue it with great Resolution and Constancy till it be throughly accomplished; Banish all false Prophets, who have deceived us into Neglect and Procrastination of so important and necessary a Duty, and thereby brought us into so much Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief and Danger; and make Examples of Notorious Scandalous Persons; and by doing all that can be for the present, declare both to God and Man a firm Resolution to go thorough with it, by the Blessing of God, whatever Difficulties occur in the way. No Difficulties or Dangers must stop or stay us: It is for our Life And there is no greater Danger than in the Neglect or Delay of so indispensable a Duty. We must remember in this case, as well as in many others, that Warning of our Saviour, <hi>He who will lose his Life,</hi> (or what else is most valuable) <hi>for my sake, shall save it: But he who will save it</hi> (thinks to secure it by neglect or transgression of his Duty or Respect to me) <hi>shall lose it,</hi> and certainly find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self mightily mistaken in his Policy. Nor must we rest in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Performance of this part of our Duty: For the Judgments which threaten both the King and the Nation at this time, if I mistake not, are very great, and require the Zeal of <hi>Phinehas</hi> to avert them, and pacifie the Wrath of God.</p>
            <p>And here I must take notice of a matter, which deserves to be well consider'd, though I doubt few ever think of it, and that is of <hi>Giving Glory to God in respect of his former Judgments,</hi> and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is necessary for <hi>cleansing of the Nation from the Guilt and Pollution of the former Sins,</hi> of which it is not yet purged as it ought to be. We have these thirty years past rather politickly than religiously kept every year the 30th of <hi>January,</hi> as the Day of <hi>the Martyrdom of King</hi> Charles <hi>the First:</hi> But it ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider'd, Whether ever we have taken care to <hi>give God the Glory of his Judgments in that very thing.</hi> It was an extraordinary thing for a King to have his Head cut off, at his own Door, by his own Subjects. But however, if we have had more regard to the Dead King than to the Living God, and to his Hand and Judgments in it, that will prove such a piece of Hypocrisie, as may concern the Church of <hi>England</hi> to look to it in time, lest God by his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments set it out to their Shame or Confusion. And for the <hi>late K.</hi> James, if we can satisfie our selves with our Acquests, and take no care to manifest to the World the Justice of our own Proceedings
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48699:11"/>
in the late Revolution, certainly we ought in Gratitude to God to have given him the Glory of his Justice as well as his Mercy in it, by publick Examination and Justice upon some of the notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Criminals. And I doubt not but the Judgments of God will reach those Prophane Politicians, who have studiously smothered and covered such Works of <hi>Secrecy and Darkness,</hi> as ought for the Glory of God to have been set in the Light, as well as obstructed Justice upon more apparent Criminals. And besides, this is a thing that does so greatly concern the King in respect of his Duty to God, that as it is a shame to all his Bishops and Doctors and Chaplains about him, if they have been all so unskilful in their own Profession, or so unfaithful to him, as that none of them hath admonished him, and endeavoured to make him sensible of the Importance of it; so I doubt it will be imputed to the filling up of the measure.</p>
            <p>But whatever be done by the Church and the State for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of any Publick Judgment or Common Calamity, there is that which may be done by <hi>Private and particular Persons,</hi> which may both help towards that, and may procure Safety and Exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to themselves out of it: Which I shall comprize in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Particulars.</p>
            <p>The First is, to <hi>try and examin</hi> their own ways, <hi>and turn</hi> to the Lord by <hi>Repentance</hi> and effectual <hi>Reformation</hi> of whatever is amiss, and be sure to cast out every <hi>Root of Bitterness;</hi> leave no matter for the Fire of God's Judgments to take hold of. If we will escape Eternal Judgments, we must beware of such deadly Sins as procure them. And if we desire to escape Temporal Punishments, we must be careful, and vigilant, and circumspect to <hi>avoid</hi> and <hi>cleanse</hi> our selves from every Sin. For every <hi>Sin</hi> shall receive a just Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pense of Reward, and the <hi>Sinner</hi> shall suffer Loss, though he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self may be saved, so as by Fire. There is a Chastning of the Lord, by Weakness, and Sickness, and Death, even of those who shall not be condemned with the World; and for that purpose that they may not; which as we would avoid, we must carefully avoid all Sin; or, if we fall into any, be careful speedily to <hi>cleanse our selves</hi> from it; which is not to be done without Trouble. We must judge our selves, if we will not be judged of the Lord. We must afflict our Souls. For though it be the Blood of Christ and the Spirit of God only which can perfect our Cleansing, yet is there something to be done by us in the use of Means, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operation
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48699:11"/>
with the Grace of God: As 1. Serious Consideration both of the Majesty, Holiness and Justice of God, and of the Evil of Sin. 2. Serious use of the Means of Humiliation, and of the Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Expressions of it for the more Solemn Acknowledgment of the Sin, and the Glory of God, in the sight of Men and Angels. 3. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution and Actual Reformation, so as to abolish the Sin, as much as may be, by Restitution, Reparation, Satisfaction, and Practice of contrary Vertues. 4. Application to God by Supplication and Faith in our great Propitiation, with Acts of Mercy and Charity to others. Th<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and such as these We must do through the Grace of God for our Cleansing.</p>
            <p>The next is to take great <hi>care to be of the number of those whom</hi> the good Archbishop <hi>Usher</hi> hath told us, <hi>God will hide</hi> in the Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of his Hand, and under the Shadow of his Wings: And to that end often peruse and ruminate upon that excellent Prophesie, and like excellent Description of Sanctification printed with it; and study, and strive, and pray earnestly, and above all things, to have that Holy Work wrought, and indelibly imprinted in their Hearts; and to give it growth by continual Exercise and Labour of Love for the Honour of God and Good of his Creatures, till that Noble Generous Christian Property, of exerting our Faculties for the Common Good, make us almost forget our selves, and carry us beyond all Private Respect: Which yet is no more than we see imprinted in the Nature of a poor Animal; a fearful Hen, which will fly at a Kite and a Mastiff for the safety of her Chickens, from which she would otherwise fly as fast to save her self. What Brutes are we, who will not out of our selves for the God of our Lives, and the Centre of our Happiness!</p>
            <p>The third is, to look out into the World; behold and <hi>consider well the deplorable state and condition of this Nation; and indeed, of all the Reformed Churches,</hi> by reason of the full Growth of Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, and the Terrible Judgments of God, which threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them, and seem so near approaching after so extraordinary a Mercy lately afforded them, and a Day of Salvation, which they seem to have neglected, without any Sense of the Duties, which such a Divine Favour and Opportunity required; that so they may become Mourners in secret, as well for the Indignities offered to God and our Saviour, and the Abuse of a most Holy and Excellent Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as for the Calamities, which we have great reason to fear are coming upon them, for Just Punishment of all that Wickedness,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48699:12"/>
which no Means could prevail with them to reform; and may be the better fitted to perform their Part in a Publick Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The Fourth and Last is to do what they can for the <hi>Reformation of others,</hi> and thereby for the averting <hi>or mitigating of the Judgments of God.</hi> The Zeal of one <hi>Phinehas</hi> turned away the Wrath of God from the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> that he did not destroy them. And besides it was imputed to him for Righteousness; and he obtained thereby a Blessing upon himself and his Posterity, <hi>Numb</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 11, 13. <hi>Psal.</hi> 106. 31. and many such, tho private Persons, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> even of the Lower Ranks of Men, might do much Good to the Nation; and especially to themselves, and their own Families. This may, and must be done by these <hi>Means.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By well ordering <hi>their own Families,</hi> if they have any; and that 1. By <hi>Daily Prayers</hi> in their Families; for which purpose there are many good Books to be had, to help them who need. 2. By Religious Observance of the <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> taking care that all of their Family frequent and reverently attend to the Publick Worship of God, and employ the rest of the Day in Reading, and other Religious Employment. 3. By Instructing, Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing, Reproving, and Correcting such as may need or give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion for it; and discharging from their Service and Employment such as are incorrigibe. Of which more presently.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By Admonishing and Reproving their Familiar <hi>Friends and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> and <hi>such at they converse with,</hi> as occasion may serve or require; <hi>Thou shalt in any wise rebuke thy Neighbour that thou bear not sin for him,</hi> Lev. 19. 17. and using their best Endeavours, that the obstinate, who will not be reformed by such means, may be punished and corrected by the Magistrates and Governors. Wherein if they may seem to lose their Labour through the Unrighteousness of those in Authority, yet their Labour will not be in vain in the Lord: And besides, if they be constant and unmoveable in the Work of the Lord, they will animate one another; and the Importunity of many will by degrees, by God's Blessing, prevail against the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteousness of such Judges.</p>
            <p>This is a Duty of greater Weight and Obligation than most Men are sensible of: And the Neglect of it hath given great Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to the Growth of Sin and Wickedness amongst us to that Maturity and Fulness it is come to, and to the present Unhappiness of the Nation: And therefore now under our Circumstances is it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48699:12"/>
so much the more to be put in Execution with Zeal and Vigour against all (tho they be as thy Right Hand, or thy Right Eye) by whom the Offence cometh, they must not be spared; thine Eye shall not pity them, neither shalt thou spare them, neither shalt thou conceal them; so shalt thou put the Evil way from the midst of thee; however from thy self, and deliver thine own Soul, if it cannot longer be kept off from the Nation. But could such a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Zeal be raised, but in the <hi>Despised People,</hi> it would be no little Ground of Hope still. And why should it not? We see it in some Particulars upon occcasion; and may see it in more, if they be but rightly informed. There is not less reason for it against Debauchery than against Popery; it is not less injurious to our Religion, nor less dangerous to our Nation; nay, it is believed by many Men of Learning and Knowledge of Affairs, that it is one of the Bastard Brats of Popery, and the most pernicious of all, produced by their Councils, and faustred by their Agents, that they might unman us, and expose us to the Wrath of God, and the Fury of our Enemies. All therefore who have any Zeal or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation against Popery, ought to turn it mightily against this. First, to resent the Abuse put upon them by the <hi>Midianites,</hi> and their own Folly and Madness so easily to be led into the Snare, as at the same time that they are so warm against the Papists, to be through want of Consideration, their very Instruments to promote their Designs for the Destruction of this Nation; and at the same time that they profess so much Zeal for the Protestant Religion, to offer greater Indignities to it, than any Adversary possibly can: And upon such Considerations bethinking themselves well, first de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberately and resolutely with Indignatión and Zeal breaking through those Enchantments, and mending their own Manners; in the next place give their Zeal as full Vent against Debauchery as they would against Popery; and against all such infatuated and inchanted Tools of theirs, all debauched People, wherever they meet with them in their Debaucheries, as they would do against any Priests or Jesuites, who could never hurt us, were we not first weakned and exposed by our Sins and Wickedness. Consider how they would take it, if a Man to their Face should reproach their Father, or their Mother, their near Relation or intimate Friend, their great Benefactor, or their Master, Lord, or Prince, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himself ill affected to their Country; and know, that, if they have any thing of Manhood or Generosity in them, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48699:13"/>
done to God, the Supreme Monarch of the World, and, the Father, Lord, and great Benefactor to us all, and to our most Holy and Excellent Religion, the only compleat means of all Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness both here and hereafter, are Provocations Ten Thousand times greater and more reasonable to exert it to the utmost, and to treat all Prophane and wicked People accordingly; that so that Impudent Prophaneness and Leudness, which at present fills all places, should not dare henceforward to appear abroad, or in our Streets. This might, for ought I know, were it well considered and encouraged, save the Nation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By a general (tho implicit) Reproof of the corrupt Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Age, and a kind of bearing Witness against them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring a Disallowance and Abhorrence of them, that is, by avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and <hi>abstaining from all Communication</hi> either with the scandalous Persons, or with the corrupt manners thereof.</p>
            <p>That we should avoid all Conversation with <hi>Evil and Scandalous Persons</hi> there are divers considerable Reasons: Because 1. It may be a Temptation to us to corrupt our Manners in divers respects. 2. It may give Advantage to the Evil Powers, which reside and rule in them, to hurt us. For there is a secret Spiritual Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of Good or Evil in Company, such as it is, which few Men observe, or are sensible of, 3. It may be scandalous to us, if it be intimate or familiar, which is a thing we ought carefully to avoid. 4. Our Holy Religion and Profession may be affronted by them in our Presence, of which we ought also to avoid all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions. 5. We ought to express and manifest our Resentment and Indignation against their wicked and scandalous Actions and Practices, for the Honour of our Religion, and to shame them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Repentance and Reformation: But familiar Conversation with such is an implicit deserting of our Profession, disowning of Christ, and prostituting our Religion in an unworthy Compliance, and a means to make them secure in their Evil Courses. For these and the like Reasons we ought at all times to avoid them, unless when we have any hope or design of doing good to them, but more espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially under such Circumstances, lest we be Partakers in their Sin, or tainted by them; lest we be Partakers in their Punishment, and suffer with them; and that we may assert and vindicate the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Religion, and shame them into Repentancc and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:48699:13"/>
By this means may the meanest Person many times have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to give a tacit Reproof, and such as by the Blessing of God may prove very effectual, to the greatest. And every one ought to do it as they have occasion, without regard to their own worldly Interest or Benefit to be had by them, or to the Worldly Dignity of the Person, without respect of Persons. For to neglect it for Private Interest, is to prostitute Religion, and apply to the Devils Instruments, instead of dependance upon God for Supplies, (if we really need them) and his Blessing. And to do otherwise out of respect to any such Person, be his Degree what it will, is to prefer a wicked Creature before our Creator and Redeemer, to prefer external Temporal Honour, before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, intrinsick, and eternal, and to shew more respect to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of God, who dishonour him, and despise his Laws, than to God himself upon whom we depend. Both which, whatever Men think of them, are more wicked and prophane than I can here set out as they deserve, and are ready means to provoke God, whose Cause is thereby deserted, to desert them who do so, and leave them to have their part with such Company, with Insidels and Unbelievers. It is so in the meanest Christian, and therefore let those of higher degree look to it, how they will answer the Transgression of this Duty to God, when they are called to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for it, which may be sooner than they expect. It is that which every one ought with great Care to observe, who desires to be found faithful to God, and to be preserved in the Common Calamity by his special Favour. The meanest Servants ought to avoid such Masters and Families; and if by mistake they fall into them, to manifest their Dissatisfaction, get leave to be gone; and if that cannot be had, to fly with <hi>Moses</hi> into the Wilderness, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than abide with such wicked <hi>Egyptians:</hi> Every Tradesman to despise their Custom, and every Artist, Mechanick and Labourer their Service or Employment, and all to avoid so much as to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute them, or shew them any respect, which would be to be Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of their Evil Deeds: Be they who they will, who have so lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Discretion, or Command of themselves, as to contemn and affront even the Laws, Government and Religion of the Nation, and all the sober People of it, they ought to be slighted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spised by the-very Footmen, Carmen, and all sorts of People; and if they offer to draw their Sword, or injure any, to be trod in the Dirt, as the Pests of the Nation, and Instruments of all our
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48699:14"/>
Unhappiness; only <hi>Magistrates,</hi> and Men in Authority, which is God's Ordinance, must not be affronted, but left to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, if those who have power over them will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>the Manners of the Age,</hi> besides those gross and scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous sins, there are divers others, which must be avoided and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and cleansed, if we would endeavour to purpose to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scape the Fire of God's Judgments. Such are 1. All secret Sins, secret and mean in their Commitment, and concealed from the View of Men. God will certainly find these out, and manifest his All-seeing Providence in the severe Punishment of them, if not prevented by a timely and thorough Repentance and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. 2. Such as in their own Nature are not apparent and distinguishable enough to be corrected by Humane Laws, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure or Cognizance; which are many and various: As, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse of Aliments</hi> in indulgence to the Appetite, wherein a great part of the People of this plentiful Nation are guilty of Excess to their own Hurt, but especially those bruitish <hi>Epicures,</hi> who glory in their shame, and turning their Paunches into Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hils by a modish Foolish Term, of eating Well, would recommend a beastly ravenous Action: <hi>Ease</hi> and <hi>Luxury, Sports,</hi> and <hi>Idle and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Employments, Loss of Time,</hi> and divers great <hi>Advantages,</hi> without Benefit to others, or to themselves: Abuse of the Talents of <hi>Estates and Wealth,</hi> which ought to be employed for the Honor and Service of God, and the Good of Men, to Vain-glory and Ostentation in Apparel, Buildings, Furniture, Attendants, and such like Pomps and Vanities, which the ancient Christians so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly renounced at their Baptism, and as carefully avoided ever after; and, (which doubles the Sin) even to Emulations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond proportion, which draw many other Mischiefs after them, to themselves, their Families, and many other, by the means next to be mentioned: Covetousness, and Ambition, and insatiable Greediness and pursuit of things of the World, and the cursed Fruits thereof, Frauds, Cheats, Exactions, Extortions, Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, Breach of Trust, Faction and Treacheries against King and Country, for Pensions from Foreign Princes, and Preferments at home. 3. Such as are covered, and palliated, and patronized by Modes, Fashions, Customs of the World, and pretence of Necessity for the management and promotion of Trade, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of divers are mentioned already in general, and need not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:48699:14"/>
These, though spread over this Nation, (to say nothing of other Protestant Countries) are most rife and notorious in this <hi>Great City,</hi> which give great Cause to fear some special Judgment upon it. And though I have always been a Friend to it, yet I think my self obliged to bear my Testimony against the Iniquity thereof in one notorious Part, and that is <hi>Abuse of Apprentices</hi> after great Sums of Mony received with them. I my self have had no less than four Sons, as soberly Educated and as well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed as most, before they came to be Apprentices, and who behaved themselves afterward without any great Extravagancies, placed here to suitable Trades, with no little Pains and Charge, yet after all ruined and undone by the Iniquity and Wickedness of their Masters and their Partners. But I have seen the Judgments of <hi>God</hi> upon two of them already; and to him I have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my Cause with the other two. This I write upon my own sad Experience, and could say as much of my own Knowledge in the case of some others. Of which I have written heretofore in a Paper, Entituled, <hi>Relief of Apprentices,</hi> and mention it now as a Common Cause worthy of Consideration, amongst others, of the Magistrates for averting the Judgments of <hi>God</hi> from the City.</p>
            <p>And while I write this of a Case wherein I my self have been so much concerned, I cannot but be sensible of the case of some others which I often see and hear of, and in Faithfulness to God and to the State, and Charity to the poor People, take notice of it upon this occasion: And that is the <hi>Pressing of Men,</hi> and send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out of the Realm, to Sea, or beyond Sea, by Force and Violence against their Wills. I cannot find, or learn upon En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, that there is any Law or Statute, since those made in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. are expired, for the Pressing of Mariners and Sailers, much less of Land-Men, And if there be not, I am sure it is contrary to a Principal <hi>Fundamental Right of the People,</hi> whose Goods, much less their Persons or Liberty, cannot be touched but by Order of Law and their own Consent in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and would frustrate the principal Design and Reason of the <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> Act, and render it ridiculous and contemptible in Cases of greatest Exigence, and most needing its Relief. The <hi>Rights of the Poor,</hi> ought to be preserved inviolable, as well as of the Greatest: And they who can be content to see their own Rights violated in the meanest of their Countrimen, while their own Persons and Estates are untouched, do not deserve to have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48699:15"/>
them preserved; and may expect that they or their Posterity may, by the just Judgment of God, be deprived of them. Nor can I see any Reason, why the Poor of the Land, who enjoy so little of it, should be frighted from their Employments, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from their Families, Friends, and the Trades and Labours to which they have been used, to hazard their Limbs and their Lives against their own Wills, to defend and maintain the Superfluities and Grandeur of the Rich? Or how the Death of such in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice being forced against their Will, tho by Law, unless they first forfeit their Right by their own ill Behaviour, can be excused from Murder in the sight of God? Nor Lastly, How we can expect that either such should do any Great <hi>Service,</hi> or that the <hi>Blessing of God</hi> should be with us in the use of such unreasonable Means. If we enquire into the <hi>Methods of our Ancestors</hi> in such Case, we shall find them more just and reasonable, more prudent and honourable, and more prosperous and successful, when Men of Honour and Interest covenanted with the King to bring in their several Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, raised them among their Tenants and Neighbours, and led them themselves; so that there was a mutual Love and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence between the Leaders and Soldiers. But <hi>this mode of Pressing,</hi> if I be not much mistaken, is a novel Invention, a base Project of the Authors of Ship-Mony, put on now, even while a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is in being, to the Prejudice of the King, as well as of the Nation, to furnish such Officers with prest involuntary Soldiers, who have little Interest of themselves to raise Volunteers, and whom few are willing to serve under. And since it is done while a Parliament is in being, which could have given Authority for it; it may justly be looked upon as no ordinary Abuse to the King himself, but as one of the Treacherous Policies of some Evil Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to prejudice his Government and Cause; make his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment offensive and suspected by the People, and his Cause seem absurd, while his Authority is abused to violate the Rights of the People, which he came to preserve, and in a Fundamental Point, and contrary to his Coronation Oath; and thereby to justifie or excuse the Miscarriages of his Predecessor: For all this it plainly and directly tends to. It is true, there is a <hi>Necessity</hi> that Men must be had: But Necessity will not excuse Injustice to the Poor, with so great Violation of Common Right, and when without either it may be supplied. Let not such be excluded from the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, who are able and willing to serve in their own Persons, and have Interest and Reputation to bring in Seamen and Soldier
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48699:15"/>
Let the Salaries, Pay and Profits of Great Officers, especially who sit at home, and are out of danger, be reduced to Moderation, and those who venture all, have a proportionable Encouragement, both by good Pay while in Service, and of Good Provision in case they be disabled, and we shall want no Men, nor need any Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing: And let but good Discipline be exercised, as it ought to be, in respect of the Manners of Officers as well as of Soldiers and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and we shall not want God's Blessing.</p>
            <p>But to leave these things to the Consideration of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and of the City, of the Evil Manners before mentioned, those which are <hi>Secret Sins,</hi> only by Secrecy in the Commitment, and as they are concealed from Men, but otherwise are well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough known to all to be Sins, though they have not so much of Scandal as those which are openly committed; yet may they have other Aggravations, which may equal that, and require no less Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of judging our selves, if we would not be judged of God. As to the rest, which either in their own Nature are not so pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, or easily discernible from what is Lawful; or by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Opinion and Usage of the World are reputed Lawful and Harmless, nay commendable; and some perhaps excused and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronized in opposition to Popery, it is to be considered, 1. That some are condemned as wholly unlawful, not only by the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Practice of all the ancient Christians for many Ages, and comprehended in that ancient Solemn Renunciation required of all admitted into the Society of Christians by <hi>Baptism,</hi> viz. Of the Devil and his Works, the World and the Pomps, Glory and Vanity thereof, and the Flesh and its Lusts and Desires; but also by the express Doctrin of the Holy Scripture, both under such <hi>General Comprehensive Names,</hi> as <hi>the Flesh,</hi> Gal. 5. 17. <hi>Lusts of the Flesh,</hi> Gal. 5. 16: 2 Pet. 2. 18: 2 John 2. 16. <hi>The Old Man,</hi> Eph. 4. 24. <hi>The Natural Man,</hi> I Cor. 2. 14. <hi>Desires of the Flesh,</hi> Eph. 2. 3. <hi>Works of the Flesh,</hi> Gal. 5. 19. <hi>Provision for the Flesh,</hi> Rom. 13. 14. <hi>Mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Flesh, and the things of the Flesh,</hi> Rom. 8. 5, 6, 7: Gal. 6. 8. <hi>Walking after the Flesh,</hi> 2 Cor. 10. 2: 2 Pet. 2. 10. <hi>Minding earthly things,</hi> Phil. 3. 19: Col. 3. 2, 5: James 3. 15. <hi>Being of the World,</hi> John 15. 19: 17. 14, 16. <hi>Love of the World,</hi> 1 John 2. 15: 5. 19. Ja. 4. 4. <hi>Lusts of the World,</hi> Tit. 2. 12. <hi>Wisdom of the World,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 19. <hi>The Course of the World,</hi> Eph. 2. 2. <hi>Conformity to the World,</hi> Rom. 12. 2. <hi>Inordinate Affection,</hi> and <hi>Evil Concupiscence,</hi> &amp;c. with weighty Admonitions of their provoking the Wrath of God, and exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48699:16"/>
from the Kingdom of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by <hi>more particular Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters,</hi> Directions and Injunctions, as against <hi>Covetousness,</hi> which is again and again called Idolatry, and such as both brings down the Wrath of God, and excludes from Heaven (which should make People more cautious against it than usually they are) and divers Branches of it, as Defrauding, Exacting, Oppressing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> against Pride, Vain-glory, Boasting, Ostentation, Pride of <hi>Apparel,</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly that of Women, (in whom it is more pardonable than in Men) prohibited in very express Terms by the two chief Apostles severally, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 9. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 3. and yet so agreeably, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares it to be a resolved Point and positive Injunction, which yet we see frustrated in our Times by some, just as the Pharisees did by the Law in our Saviours time; and against others, some of them noted before, but all too many to be here more particularly noted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That there are others, which being Lawful, or more excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sable at other times, are apt to be the less taken notice of, yet are not only unlawful and inexcusable at such a time as this, but greatly offensive and abominable to God, and highly provoking, as impious and Prophane, under such Circumstances, as may be perceived by the great Indignation expressed in the Prophet <hi>Isa.</hi> 22. 12. against such upon like occasion, as <hi>Iniquity,</hi> which should <hi>not be expiated till they should die</hi> for it. And indeed, as it is a terrible thing to fall into the Hands of the Living God; so there can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be a greater Provocation, than such Behaviour as dectares or Implies a Contempt or Neglect, Carelesness or Unconcernedness at the Approaches or Appearance of the Judgments of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a Nation, by any particular Person. It is very like and the ready way to fix the Decree against such a Person to be certainly involved in it.</p>
            <p>Now therefore to prevent, and avert the Judgments of God from themselves, and, as much as in them lieth, from the Nation; all who in order thereunto desire indeed to have no Fellowship with any such Evil Manners, Customs or Fashions, and to keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves unspotted of the World, must apply themselves seriously to such further <hi>Means</hi> as these, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To abstain and withdraw themselves, as much as their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances will permit, from all unnecessary <hi>Diversions, Business and Imployment</hi> in and about the Matters, and Conversation with the Men, of the World; and <hi>retiring,</hi> apply themselves to Prayer, Reading, Meditation and Watching; and frequent the <hi>Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:48699:16"/>
of God with all Reverence as often as Opportunity may be had.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To abstain from all <hi>Acquest</hi> of the things of the World in any unfitting manner or unreasonable measure, both which are very common; but be content with just, and honest, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable <hi>Gains,</hi> according to the real Worth, not appearance of things, reasonable Rents as Times will bear, and moderate Fees, according to the real Merit of Labour, Skill, and Time, without occasioning more Expence than needs; and likewise, to pay to the full value of Commodities, and Desert of Labour, Skill and Time: nay, to abstain from all <hi>Pursuit of some, of Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> not only after the greedy and ambitious manner, and by the indirect means, which are usual; but from all, considering more the Account, which must be given, and the Incumbrance, than the Profit and Honour; unless out of Charity to Men, and Love to our Country, to prevent the Intrusion of Evil Men for their own Advantage, and to the Disservice of King and Country; which is now so common as may justifie that which otherwise would be inexcusable. Out of which Case, for a Man to be well qualified and ready to serve his Country when he is called to it, is sufficient. And lastly, to abstain not only from Pursuit, but from <hi>Acceptance</hi> of others, of insignificant (as our later Reigns have made them) and burdensom <hi>Titles of Honour.</hi> Which Men of true Vertue and Wisdom will at no time seek; especially when by the Prodigality of Princes they are thrown, and by the Vices of Nobility trodden in the Dirt, and made rather Badges of Flattery, Servility, Treachery, Vanity and Degeneracy, than Ensigns of Vertue, and of Merit by noble and generous Service and Atchievements, the only substantial Grounds of Honour: And Men of Great Piety will not easily accept at such a time as this. Besides, I am perswaded never any Man was made better by them, nor many who were not made some way worse; and that the whole Nation at this time is much the worse, almost un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, and in great Danger of Ruin and Confusion by some aspiring ambitious Persons, if they be not speedily taken down: But sure I am they are unsuitable for Times of Fasting and Humiliation, when they who have them, ought in a sort to depose and lay 'em a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side during such Circumstances. And since now a <hi>Publick Fast and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation</hi> is appointed by the Queen to be observed Monthly, <hi>in most Devout and Solemn manner,</hi> it is but fit and necessary that the <hi>House
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48699:17"/>
of Lords</hi> be admonished of a Great Disrespect both to God and to the King upon the like occasion the last year; (though touched before in the <hi>Reflections upon the</hi> then <hi>late Action at Sea,</hi> where the unhappy state of our Clergy and Church was more fully dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursed, and therefore is spared here:) For I believe it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern them not only to have more regard to the Eyes of Men that are upon them, for their own Honour and Reputation, but to the all-seeing Eye of Him, who hath said, <hi>Them who honour me, I will honour; but they who despise me shall be lightly esteemed,</hi> lest if through their Fault (amongst the rest) the Sun and the Moon be darkned, the Stars also fall from Heaven; and lest he again shake Heaven and Earth as he hath formerly done, or more se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To abstain from the Use of <hi>unnecessary</hi> things of the World, as, Pleasures, Vain Delights, Plays, Pomp, State, Grandeur and Finery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are at such a time part of that Iniquity, against which we see so much Divine Indignation expressed in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</p>
            <p>And here I must not, I ought not to forbear to take notice of that <hi>Undecent Attire of our Women upon their Heads,</hi> at any time unbefitting <hi>Women professing Godliness,</hi> but at such a time as this, when <hi>God</hi> by his Providence calls for Baldness and Sackcloth, and when they should put their Mouths in the Dust, to set up their Crests in that manner, cannot but be displeasing and abominable in the sight of <hi>God</hi> and the good Angels, as it is in the sight of many of his Faithful Servants upon Earth. And therefore I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but think it great <hi>Pity,</hi> that a Lady of sincere Piety and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, as I hope and believe, should be betray'd, through the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfulness in Divine matters of those about her, or their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulness to her, to prostitute <hi>Majesty</hi> to such a Compliance with a vain Generation, who should rather have given the Law to them, and maintaining her ground on the part of Virtue and Gravity, which is essential to Majesty, by the Authority of so great an Example have given a tacit Reproof and Correction to their Vanity, and taught them more consideration and regard to their own Country, than to do such Honour to a Foreign Enemy, as to glory in a voluntary imitating of their Example, even in Levity and Vanity, as if they would lick up their Spittle; an unlucky presage, that we shall at last be delivered, by the just Judgments of <hi>God,</hi> for Correction of our Error, to an involuntary Subjection
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48699:17"/>
to their Will and Power, whose vain Humours we are so apt to follow, if we speedily mend not our Manners.</p>
            <p>Nor may I here pass by in silence another such unhappy Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage or two: As the Celebrating, or rather Profaning, of an Anniversary Solemnity, at a time which at once called for both se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Thansgiving to God, and serious Humiliation under his Mighty Hand, with a light and frothy <hi>Play;</hi> and sullying an il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrious Consultation about matters of great seriousness and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, when the Eyes of all the World were upon them, with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian excessive <hi>Drinking.</hi> These we may understand by what hath been said already, to be displeasing to God, and by the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor, which soon after befell them, who had first so dishonored themselves, <hi>viz</hi> that it was permitted as a just Judgment from him. And these, as they are greater faults in Divinity, than the generality of our Divines can believe; for they contract a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with the common Guilt both of the Nation at present, and of the preceding Kings and their Reigns, to say nothing of other Circumstances; so are they greater faults in Civil Prudence, than our ordinary Statesmen and Polititians are sensible of; for they tend greatly to weaken and abate a Mans Interest in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and esteem of People, making them doubtful both of his Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity in Religion, and of his Prudence and Magnanimity, who will be prevailed on to be a Spectator or Actor in either. It is not Insolence or ill Will, but very Faithfulness and great good Will, which hath induced me to to write this: And such a disposition of Soul toward the Majesty of Heaven, and sense of things, as the present Circumstances require, will make them be well taken from what ever hand they come, with so much Integrity and Affection. And therefore now to return.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To abstain from the use <hi>even of the Necessary things of the World,</hi> as much as Nature and Decency will permit, and particularly from the Delights and Satiety of <hi>Natural Aliments;</hi> not only from the quality of Costly and Delicious Meats and Drinks, but from such a quantity of those which are plain and simple, as perhaps the Appetite might crave. This is the only way to avoid, that Intemperance, which is not easie to be discern'd by others, but is very common, and very much impairs the Health, and shortens the Lives of many people of this Nation, of all degrees, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of such as are not much imploy'd in hard Labour; is of great benefit for Health, and of great Advantage for such Retirements
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48699:18"/>
as I have mentioned; and is very proper and suitable for such oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions. And to this I might with like reason add and recommend an abridgment of <hi>Sleep,</hi> and use of Watching, which a spare Diet would render very easie, and conducing to Health.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In all <hi>Conversation</hi> with others, to be very serious and grave; and by much Affability, Sweetness, and good Admonitions, be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways endeavouring to do good to all; never speak of Religion to recommend themselves, nor forbear through Shame, or for fear of Disparagement by it, a common, base and most dangerous Fault; and be always ready to relieve and defend the Needy and Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and to right the Injured, as far as Means, Ability, or Interest will extend; only with this Caution, that it be done so as may not too much interrupt or disturb the Retirement before mentioned, and the proper Imployments thereof.</p>
            <p>As this Method will redeem much Time for Retirements, so the retrenching so much Expence, may both countervail the time sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted from Business; and help to supply what is imployed in Works of Charity; in all which, regard must be had to peoples different Circumstances. And they who shall seriously enter upon it, and with care, diligence and constancy, keep to it, I doubt not but will find Light in Obscurity, Comfort in Affliction, Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Protection in Danger, great Serenity and Satisfaction in this Life, and Eternal Happiness in a better. Which, next to the Service of our great Lord, and the Preservation of the Nation, is the only Design of this Discourse.</p>
            <p>And for the same purpose, I shall here subjoin the following ABSTRACTS, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="abstract">
               <head>1. <hi>An Abstract of Mr.</hi> Chillingworth<hi>'s Judgment of the State of Religion in this Nation, in his time, which is much more decayed since.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LET us examine our ways, and consider impartially, <hi>What the Religion of most Men is?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are <hi>Baptized</hi> in our Infancy, that is, as I conceive, dedicated and devoted to God's service, by our Parents and the Church, as young <hi>Samuel</hi> was by his Mother <hi>Anna,</hi> and there we take a Solemn Vow, <hi>To forsake the Devil and all his works, the vain Pomp and Glory of the World, with all the covetous desires of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48699:18"/>
it; to forsake also all the carnal desires of the Flesh, and not to follow nor be led by them.</hi> This Vow we take when we be Children, and understand it not: and, how many are there, who know, and consider, and regard what they have Vowed, when they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Men, almost as little as they did being Children. Consider the Lives, and Publick Actions of most Men of all Conditions, in Court, City, and Country, and then deny it, if you can, that those three things which we have renounced in our Baptism; the Profits, Honours, and Pleasures of the World, are not the very Gods which divide the World amongst them; are not served more devoutly, confided in more heartily, loved more affectionately, than the <hi>Father, Son, and Holy Ghost,</hi> in whose Name we are Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized? Deny, if you can, the daily and constant Imployment of all Men, to be either a violent prosecution of the vain Pomp and Glory of the World, or of the Power, Riches, and contemptible Profits of it, or of the momentary or unsatisfying Pleasures of the Flesh, or else of the more Diabolical humours of Pride, Malice, Revenge, and such like. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we are come to <hi>Years capable of Instruction,</hi> many, which is lamentable to consider, are so little regarded by themselves or others, that they continue little better than Pagans, in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Christians, and know little more of God, or of Christ, than if they had been bred in the <hi>Indies.</hi> A <hi>lamentable Case,</hi> and which will one Day <hi>lie heavy</hi> upon their <hi>account,</hi> which might have amended it and did not. But many, I confess, are taught to act over this Play of Religion, and learned to say, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven;</hi> and, <hi>I believe in God the Father Almighty:</hi> But, Where are the Men that live so, as if they did believe in earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, that God is their Almighty Father? Where are they that fear him, and trust him, and depend upon him only, for their whole Happiness, and Love him, and Obey him, as in reason we ought to do to an Almighty Father? Who, if he be our Father, and we be indeed his Children, will do for us all the good he can; and if he be Almighty, can do for us all the good he will; and yet, how few are there, who love him with half that affection as Children usually do their Parents, or believe him with half that simplicity, or serve him with half that diligence? And then for the Lords Prayer, the plain truth is, we lie unto God for the most part clean through it, and for want of desiring indeed, what in word we pray for, tell him to his Face as many false Tales as we make Petitions.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48699:19"/>
For who shews by his endeavours, that he desires heartily that <hi>God's Name should be hallowed;</hi> that is, holily and religiously Worshipped and Adored by all Men? That <hi>his Kingdom should be advanced and inlarged? That his Blessed Will should be universally Obeyed?</hi> Who shews by his forsaking sin that he desires so much as he should do the forgiveness of it? Nay, who doth not revenge, upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, the affronts, contempts, and injuries put upon him, and so upon the matter Curse himself, as often as he says, <hi>Forgive us our Trespasses as we forgive them that trespass against us?</hi> How few de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon God only for their <hi>daily Bread, viz.</hi> the good things of this Life, as upon the only giver of them, so as neither to get nor keep any of them, by any means which they know or fear to be offensive unto God? How few desire in earnest to <hi>avoid Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> Nay, who almost is there, that takes not the Devil's Office out of his Hand, and is not himself a Tempter both to himself and others? Lastly, Who almost is there that desires heartily and above all things so much as the thing deserves, to be delivered from the <hi>greatest Evil;</hi> Sin I mean, and the Anger of God? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this were ill enough, were it in <hi>private,</hi> but we abuse God Almighty also with our <hi>Publick and Solemn Formalities,</hi> we make the Church a Stage whereon to act our parts, and play our Pageants; there we make a profession every Day of <hi>Confessing our Sins with humble, lowly, and obedient Hearts,</hi> and yet when we have talked after this manner, Twenty, Thirty, Forty Years together, our Hearts for the most part continue proud, as impenitent, as disobedient, as they were at the beginning. We make great Protestations, <hi>When we assemble and meet together to render thanks to God Almighty, for the benefits received at his Hands;</hi> and if this were to be performed with words, with <hi>Hosanna's,</hi> and <hi>Hallelujahs,</hi> and <hi>Gloria Patri's,</hi> and Psalms, and Hymns, and such like outward matters, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture we should do it very sufficiently: But in the mean time with our Lives and Actions, we provoke the Almighty, and that to his Face, with all variety of grievous and bitter Provocations; we do Daily and Hourly such things as we know, and he hath as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured us, to be odious unto him; and contrary to his nature; as any thing in the World is to the nature of any Man in the World; and all this upon poor, trifling, trivial, no Temptations: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Our Tongues ingeminate, and Cry aloud <hi>Hosanna, Hosanna,</hi> but the louder Voice of our Lives and Actions is, <hi>Crucifie him, Crucifie him. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:48699:19"/>
If I should reckon up unto you, how many direct Lies every Wicked Man tells to God Almighty, as often as he says Amen, <hi>to this Form of Godliness,</hi> which our Church hath prescribed; if I should present unto you all our acting of Piety, and playing of Humiliation, and personating of Devotion in the Psalms, the Lita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, the Collects, and generally in the whole Service, I should be infinite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We profess, and indeed generally, because it is not safe to do otherwise, that we believe the Scripture to be true, and that it contains the plain and only way to infinite and eternal Happiness: But if we did generally believe what we do profess, if this were the Language of our Hearts as well as our Tongues, How comes it to pass that the Study of it is so generally neglected? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Seeing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore most of us are so strangely Careless, so grosly Negligent of it, is there not great reason to fear, that though we have <hi>Professors and Protestors</hi> in abundance; yet the Faithful, the truly and sincerely Faithful, are, in a manner, failed from the Children of Men? What bút this can be the cause that Men are so commonly Ignorant of so many Articles, and particular Mandates of it, which yet are as manifest in it, as if they were written with the Beams of the Sun? for example;</p>
               <p>How few of our <hi>Ladies</hi> and <hi>Gentlewomen,</hi> do or will understand, that a Voluptuous Life, is Damnable and prohibited to them? Yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> faith so very plainly, <hi>She that liveth in Pleasure is dead while she liveth.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>How few of the <hi>Gallants</hi> of our time, do or will understand, that it is not lawful for them to be as Expensive and Costly in Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, as their Means, or perhaps, their Credit will extend unto? Which is to Sacrifice unto Vanity, that, which by the Law of Christ, is due unto Charity; and yet the same St. <hi>Paul</hi> forbids plainly this Excess even to Women,—<hi>Also let Women,</hi> (he would have said it much rather to the Men) <hi>Array themselves in comely Apparel, with Shamefac'dness and Modesty, not with Embroider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Hair, or Gold, or Pearls, or Costly Apparel;</hi> and to make our Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance the more inexcusable, the very same Rule is delivered by St. <hi>Peter</hi> also 1 <hi>Epist.</hi> 3. 3.</p>
               <p>How few Rich Men are or will be persuaded, That the Law of Christ permits them not to heap up Riches for ever, nor perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to add House to House, and Land to Land, though by lawful means, but requires of them thus much Charity at least, that even
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48699:20"/>
while they are providing for their Wives and Children, they should, out of the Increase wherewith God blesseth their Industry, allot the Poor a just and free proportion? And when they have provided for them in a convenient manner, (such as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves shall judg sufficient-and convenient in others) that then they should give over making Purchase after Purchase, but, with the surplusage of their Revenue beyond their Expence, procure, as much as lies in them, that no Christian remain Miserably Poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where almost are the Men that are or will be persuaded, The Gospel of Christ requires of Men <hi>Humility,</hi> like to that of <hi>little Children,</hi> and that under the highest pain of Damnation? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Would it not be strange News to a great many, that not only <hi>Adultery</hi> and <hi>Fornication,</hi> but even <hi>Uncleanness</hi> and <hi>Lasciviousness;</hi> not only <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Witchcraft,</hi> but <hi>Hatred, Variance, Emulations, Wrath,</hi> and <hi>Contentions;</hi> not only <hi>Murthers,</hi> but <hi>Envying;</hi> not <hi>Drunkenness</hi> only, but <hi>Revelling,</hi> are things prohibited to Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and such as if we forsake them not, we cannot Inherit the Kingdom of Heaven? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I should tell you, That all <hi>Bitterness</hi> and <hi>Evil speaking</hi> (nay, such is the Modesty and Gravity which Christianity requires of us) <hi>Foolish Talk and Jesting,</hi> are things not allowed to Christians, would not many Cry out, These are hard and strange sayings, who can hear them? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To come a little nearer to the business of our Times,—They that maintain <hi>the King's Righteous Cause</hi> with the hazard of their Lives and Fortunes, but by their Oaths and Curses, by their Drunkenness and Debauchery, by their Irreligion and Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, fight more powerfully against their Party, than by all other means they do or can fight for it; are not, I fear, very well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with any part of the Bible: But that strict Caution which properly concerns themselves in the Book of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> I much doubt they have scarce ever heard of it, <hi>When thou goest to War with thine Enemies, then take heed there be no wicked thing in thee;</hi> not only no wickedness in the Cause thou maintainest, nor no wickedness in the means by which thou maintainest it; but no Personal Impieties in the Persons that maintain it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot but <hi>fear, that the Goodness of our Cause may sink un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Burden of our Sins:</hi> And that God in his Justice, because We will not suffer his Judgments to atchieve their prime scope and
<pb facs="tcp:48699:20"/>
intention, which is our Amendment and Reformation, may either deliver us up to the blind Zeal and Fury of our Enemies; or else, which I rather fear, make us Instruments of his Justice each against other, and of our own Just and Deserved Confusion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="abstract">
               <head>
                  <hi>2. An Extract of a Letter from the</hi> Hague. <hi>Concerning two Sermons preached there in the</hi> French<hi>-Church, 2/12</hi> Mar. <hi>90/1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Was yesterday in the French Church, where I heard two very good Sermons, and such as would have given you great satisfaction; one was upon <hi>Jonah 1. 5. But Jonah was gon down into the sides of the ship, and he lay, and was fast asleep.</hi> The scope of what was said was to shew, That the Church was in as great a storm as ever she had been, and that greater security was never seen amongst Professors of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, than was to be found at this day, which threatned greater desola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than our Fathers had ever been witnesses to. The other was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by Monsieur <hi>Arnold,</hi> who is the chief Commander of the <hi>Walden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> as well as their Minister. There was a great Auditory, and, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst others, the Bishop of <hi>London,</hi> Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> Earl of <hi>Monmouth</hi> and Mr. <hi>Wharton:</hi> his Text was, <hi>1 Cor. 1. 27.</hi> from thence he took occasion to tell us, that we were not to expect fine language from him, it being that which God seldom made use of for gaining the ends of the Gospel; that he was to discourse to us of plain Truths, not valuing what should be our Censures of him, if he might approve himself to his God; that we were not to think, that he was afraid before such an Appearance of persons of all ranks, to reprove what was amiss; for if the King himself were present, though he would give him that respect that was due to his Character, yet he would speak the truth, as became a faithfull Servant of Christ: he did with great modesty, without mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of particulars, shew in general how by a few hundreds of the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denses,</hi> God had scattered thousands of proud enemies; and from thence took occasion to exhort us, above all things, to make it our business to have God on our side, because it was through his chusing of them, that the foolish and weak things were able to confound the wise and strong, and withall did shew us, that we were not like persons chosen of God to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the designs and strength of our enemies, while irreligion, vanity and debauchery did so much abound amongst us, and did particularly insist upon the vain Attire of Women; and then, with great seriousness, did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48699:21"/>
us to amend our ways and doings; assuring us (without taking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, as he said, to be a Prophet) of victory over our enemies if we did sincerely set about a Reformation. These things I thought would give you some satisfaction, as they did not a little to me, which hath made me the more particular in my relation. I forgot to tell you that all heard him with great attention, and particularly those of our Countrey, I mean <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;</hi> and I did observe that <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> could not withhold from tears.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="abstract">
               <head>3. <hi>An Abstract of Archbishop</hi> Usher<hi>'s Prediction, concerning a Great Persecution to come upon the Protestant Church, to one who supposed it might have been over in his Life time.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>All you have yet seen hath been but the beginning of Sorrows, to what is yet to come upon the Protestant Churches of Christ; who will e're long fall under a Shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Persecution than ever yet has been upon them. And therefore look ye be not found in the <hi>Outward Court,</hi> but a Worshipper in the <hi>Temple</hi> before the Altar. For Christ will measure all those who profess his Name, and call themselves his People; and the <hi>Outward Worshippers</hi> he will leave out to be trodden down by the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> The <hi>Outward Court</hi> is the <hi>Formal Christian,</hi> whose Religion lies in performing the <hi>Outside Duties</hi> of Christianity, without having an <hi>Inward Life,</hi> and Power of Faith and Love Uniting them to Christ. And these God will leave to be trodden down and swept away by the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> But the <hi>Worshippers within the Temple</hi> and <hi>before the Altar,</hi> are those who do indeed worship God in Spirit and in Truth, whose Souls are made his Temples, and he is honoured and adored in the most inward Thoughts of their Hearts; and they sacrifice their Lusts and vile Affections, yea, and their own Wills to him. And these God will hide in the Hollow of his Hand, and under the Shadow of his Wings. And this shall be one great <hi>Difference</hi> between this last and all the other preceding Persecutions: For in the former, the most eminent and spiritual Ministers and Christians did generally suffer most, and were most violently fallen upon; but in this last Persecution, these shall be preserved by God as a Seed to partake of that <hi>Glory,</hi> which shall immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately follow and come upon the Church, as soon as this Storm shall be over: For as it shall be the <hi>Sharpest,</hi> so it shall be the <hi>Shortest</hi> Persecution of them all; and shall only take away the gross <hi>Hypocrites</hi> and <hi>Formal Professors;</hi> but the <hi>true Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Believers</hi> shall be preserved till the Calamity be overpassed.</p>
               <p>To <hi>this I think very pertinent that other Excellent Passage of his concerning</hi> Sanctification, <hi>in these words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We do not well understand what <hi>Sanctification</hi> and the <hi>New Creature</hi> are. It is no less than for a Man to be brought to an intire Resignation of his Will to the Will of God; and to live in the offering up of his Soul continually in the flames of Love, as a whole Burnt-Offering to Christ. And how little are many of those, who profess Christianity, experimentally acquainted with this Work on their Souls!</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48699:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
