<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King, March 13, 1666/7 by Edward Stillingfleet ...</title>
            <author>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-11">2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14240</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13142391</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13142391</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97979</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A61603)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97979)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 752:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King, March 13, 1666/7 by Edward Stillingfleet ...</title>
                  <author>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert White for Henry Mortlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XIV, 9 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97979:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97979:1"/>
            <p>A
SERMON
Preached before the
KING,
MARCH 13. 1666/7.</p>
            <p>BY
<hi>Edward Stillingfleet,</hi> B. D. Chaplain
in Ordinary to his Majesty.</p>
            <p>Printed by His Majesties especial Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>Robert White,</hi> for <hi>Henry Mortlock,</hi>
and are to be sold at his Shop at the Sign
of the White Hart in <hi>Westminster</hi> Hall.
1667.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97979:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97979:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PROVERBS 14. 9.</bibl>
               <q>Fools make a mock at Sin.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN <hi>God</hi> by his infinite Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
had contrived, and by a
power and goodness, as infinite
as his Wisdom, had perfected
the creation of the visible
world, there seemed to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
wanting to the glory of it, but a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
endued with reason and understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
which might comprehend the design of
his wisdom, enjoy the benefits of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
and employ it self in the celebration of
his power. The Beings purely intellectuall
were too highly raised by their own order
and creation, to be the <hi>Lords</hi> of this inferiour
world: and those whose natures could reach
no higher than the objects of sense, were not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97979:3"/>
capable of discovering the glorious perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of the great Creator: and therefore could
not be the fit <hi>Instruments</hi> of his praise and
service. But a conjunction of both these
together was thought necessary to make up
such a sort of beings, which might at once command
this lower world, and be the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
of him who made it. Not as though
this great fabrick of the world were meerly
raised for man to please his fancy in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation
of it, or to exercise his dominion
over the creatures designed for his use and
service; but that by frequent reflections on
the author of his being, and the effects
of his power and goodness, he might be
brought to the greatest love and admiration
of him. So that the most naturall part of
<hi>Religion</hi> lyes in the gratefull acknowledgments
we owe to that excellent and supreme Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
who hath shewed so particular a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
to man in the creation and Government
of the world. Which was so great and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expressible,
that some have thought, it was
not so much pride and affectation of a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
height, as envy at the felicity and power of
mankind, which was the occasion of the fall
of the <hi>Apostate Spirits.</hi> But whether or no the
state of man were occasion enough for the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97979:3"/>
envy of the <hi>Spirits</hi> above; we are sure the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
of Heaven was so great in it, as could
not but lay an indispensable obligation on all
mankind to perpetuall gratitude and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.
For it is as easie to suppose, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts
and injuries are the most suitable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns
for the most obliging favours; that the
first duty of a <hi>Child</hi> should be to destroy his
Parents; that to be thankful for kindnesses re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,
were to commit the unpardonable sin;
as that man should receive his being and all
the blessings which attend it from <hi>God,</hi> and
not be bound to the most universall obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
to him.</p>
            <p>And as the reflection on the author of his
being, leads him to the acknowledgement of
his duty towards <hi>God,</hi> so the consideration
of the design of it, will more easily acquaint
him with the nature of that duty which is
expected from him. Had man been designed
only to act a short part here in the world,
all that had been required of him, had been
only to express his thankfulness to <hi>God</hi> for
his being, and the comforts of it; the using
all means for the due preservation of himself;
the doing nothing beneath the dignity of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
nature, nothing injurious to those who
were of the same nature with himself; but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97979:4"/>
since he is designed for greater and nobler
ends, and his present state, is but a state of
tryall, in order to future happiness and mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;
the reason of good and evill is not to be
taken meerly from his present, but from the
respect, which things have to that eternall
state he is designed for. From whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,
that the differences of good and evill
are rooted in the nature of our beings, and
are the necessary consequents of our relation
to <hi>God,</hi> and each other, and our expectations
of a future life. And therefore according to
these measures, the estimation of men in the
world hath been while they did preserve
any veneration for <hi>God</hi> or <hi>themselves.</hi> Wisdom
and folly was not measured so much by the
subtilty and curiosity of mens speculations,
by the finess of their thoughts, or the depth
of their designs, as by their endeavours to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
the dignity of mankind; by their piety
and devotion towards <hi>God;</hi> by their sobriety
and due Government of their actions; by the
equality and justice, the charity and kindness
of their dealings to one another. Wisdom
was but another name for goodness, and
folly for sin: then it was a mans glory to be
religious; and to be profane and vitious, was to
be base and mean: then there were no <hi>Gods</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97979:4"/>
worshipped because they were bad, nor any
men disgraced because they were good. Then
there were no <hi>Temples</hi> erected to the meanest
passions of humane nature, nor men became
<hi>Idolaters</hi> to their own infirmities. Then to be
betrayed into sin, was accounted weakness; to
contrive it, dishonour and baseness; to justifie
and defend it, infamy and reproach; to make
a mock at it, a mark of the highest folly and
incorrigibleness. So the Wise Man in the words
of the Text assures us, that they are <hi>Fools,</hi>
and those of the highest rank and degree of
folly, <hi>who make a mock at sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is well for us in the Age we live in, that
we have the judgement of former ages to
appeal to, and of those persons in them whose
reputation for wisdom is yet unquestionable.
For otherwise we might be born down by
that spightfull enemy to all vertue and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
the impudence of such, who it is hard
to say whether they shew it more in commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
sin, or in defending it. Men whose
manners are so bad, that scarce any thing
can be imagined worse, unless it be the
wit they use to excuse them with. Such who
take the measure of mans perfections down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
and the nearer they approach to beasts,
the more they think themselves to act like
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97979:5"/>
men. No wonder then, if among such as
these the differences of good and evil be
laughed at, and no sin be thought so unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,
as the thinking that there is any at all.
Nay the utmost they will allow in the descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption
of Sin, is, that it is a thing that some
live by declaiming against, and others can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
live without the practice of.</p>
            <p>But is the <hi>Chair</hi> of <hi>Scorners</hi> at last proved the
only chair of Infallibility? Must those be the
standard of mankind, who seem to have little
left of humane nature, but laughter and the
shape of men? Do they think that we are
all become such fools to take scoffs for argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and raillery for demonstrations? He
knows nothing at all of goodness, that knows
not that it is much more easie to laugh at it,
than to practise it; and it were worth the
while <hi>to make a mock at sin,</hi> if the doing so
would make nothing of it. But the nature
of things does not vary with the humours of
men; sin becomes not at all the less dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
because men have so little Wit to think
it so; nor <hi>Religion</hi> the less excellent and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous
to the world, because the greatest
enemies of that are so much to themselves
too, that they have learnt to despise it. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
that scorns to be defended by such
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97979:5"/>
weapons whereby her enemies assault her,
(nothing more unbecoming the <hi>Majesty</hi> of
<hi>Religion,</hi> than to make it self cheap, by making
others laugh) yet if they can but obtain so
much of themselves to attend with patience to
what is serious, there may be yet a possibility
of perswading them, that no <hi>fools</hi> are so great
as those who laugh themselves into misery, and
none so certainly do so, as those <hi>who make a
mock at sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if our authority be too mean and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible
to be relyed on, in a matter wherein
they think us so much concern'd (and so I
hope we are to prevent the ruine of mens
souls) we dare with confidence appeal to the
generall sense of mankind in the matter of
our present debate. Let them name but any
one person in all the monuments of former
ages, to whom but the bare suspicion of Vice
was not a diminution to an esteem that might
otherwise have been great in the world. And
if the bare suspicion would do so much among
even the more rude and barbarous Nations,
what would open and professed wickedness
do among the more knowing and civill?
Humane nature retains an abhorrency of sin,
so far that it is impossible for men to have the
same esteem of those who are given over
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97979:6"/>
to all manner of wickedness, though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
of great sharpness of Wit, and of such
whose naturall abilities may not exceed the
other, but yet do govern their actions accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the strict rules of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Vertue.</hi>
And the generall sense of mankind cannot be
by any thing better known, than by an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall
consent of men, as to the wayes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
they express their value and esteem of
others. What they all agree on as the best
character of a person worthy to be loved and
honoured, we may well think is the most
agreeable to humane nature; and what is
universally thought a disparagement to the
highest accomplishments, ought to be looked
on as the disgrace and imperfection of it. Did
ever any yet, though never so wicked and
profane themselvs, seriously commend another
person for his rudeness and debaucheries? Was
any mans lust or intemperance ever recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
among the Titles of his honour? Who
ever yet raised <hi>Trophies</hi> to his vices, or thought
to perpetuate his memory by the glory of
them? Where was it ever known, that sobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety
and temperance, justice and charity were
thought the marks of reproach and infamy?
Who ever suffered in their reputation by being
thought to be really good? Nay, it is so far
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97979:6"/>
from it, that the most wicked persons do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
esteem them whether they will or no.
By which we see, that even in this lapsed and
degenerate condition of mankind, it is only
goodness which gains true honour and esteem,
and nothing doth so effectually blast a grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
reputation, as wickedness and vice.</p>
            <p>But if it be thus with the generality of men,
who were never yet thought to have too
much partiality towards goodness, we may
much more easily find it among those, who
have had a better ground for the reputation
of their wisdom, than the meer vogue of the
people. He who was pronounced by the
<hi>Heathen Oracle,</hi> to be the wisest among the
<hi>Greeks,</hi> was the person who brought down
Philosophy from the obscure and uncertain
speculations of nature, and in all his discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
recommended vertue as the truest wisdom.
And he among the <hi>Iews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 4. 29, 30, 31.</note> whose <hi>soul was as
large as the sand on the Sea shore, whose wisdom
outwent that of all the persons of his own or future
ages,</hi> writes a Book on purpose to perswade
men, that there is no reall wisdom, but to
fear God and keep his commandments: that
sin is the greatest folly, and the meaner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions
men have of it, the more they
are infatuated by the temptations to it. But as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97979:7"/>
there are degrees of sinning, so there are of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in it. Some sin with a blushing countenance,
and a trembling conscience; they sin, but yet
they are afraid to sin: they sin, but in the act
of it they condemn themselves for what they
do; they sin, but with confusion in their
faces, with horrour in their minds, and an
earthquake in their consciences: though the
condition of such persons be dangerous, and
their unquietness shews the greatness of their
folly, yet because these twitches of conscience
argue there are some quick touches left of the
sense of good and evil, their case is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate,
nor their condition incurable: But
there are others who despise these as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
of the <hi>School</hi> of <hi>Wickedness,</hi> because
they are not yet attained to those heights of
impiety which they glory in: such who have
subdued their consciences much easier than
others do their sins; who have almost worn
out all the impressions of the <hi>work of the Law
written in their hearts;</hi> who not only make a
practice, but a boast of sin, and defend it with
as much greediness as they commit it; these
are the men, whose folly is manifest to all men
but themselves; and surely since these are the
men, whom <hi>Solomon</hi> in the words of the <hi>Text</hi>
describes,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97979:7"/>
(1.) By their character, as <hi>Fools,</hi> and,</p>
            <p>(2.) By the instance of their folly, <hi>in making
a mock at sin;</hi> We may have not only the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
to use, but to prove, that name of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
to be due unto them; and (2.) To
shew the reasonablenesse of fastning it upon
them, because they <hi>make a mock at sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I come more closely to pursue
that, it will be necessary to consider another
sense of these words caused by the ambiguity
of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Verb, which sometimes signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies
to deride and scorn, sometimes to plead
for, and excuse a thing with all the arts of
<hi>Rhetorick</hi> (thence the word for <hi>Rhetorick</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived
from the Verb here used) according to
which sense, it notes all the plausible pretences
and subtle extenuations which wicked men
use in defence of their evil actions. For as
if men intended to make some recompence for
the folly they betray in the acts of sin by the
wit they employ in the pleading for them,
there is nothing they shew more industry and
care in, than in endeavouring to baffle their
own consciences, and please themselves in
their folly, till death and eternall flames awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
them. That we may not therefore seem
to beg all wicked men for <hi>Fools,</hi> till we have
heard what they have to say for themselves, we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97979:8"/>
shall first examine the reasonableness of their
fairest Plea's for their evil actions, before we
make good the particular impeachment of <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
against them. There are three wayes espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
whereby they seek to justifie themselves,
by laying the blame of all their evil actions,
either upon the fatall necessity of all events, the
unavoidable frailty of humane nature, or the
impossibility of keeping the Laws of Heaven.
But that none of these will serve to excuse
them from the just imputation of <hi>folly,</hi> is our
present business to discover.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>The fatall necessity of all humane actions.</hi>
Those who upon any other terms are unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
enough to own either <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Providence,</hi>
yet if they can but make these serve their turn
to justifie their sins by, their quarrell against
them then ceaseth, as being much more willing
that <hi>God</hi> should bear the blame of their sins,
than themselvs. But yet the very fears of a <hi>Deity</hi>
suggest so many dreadfull thoughts of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty,
Iustice,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> that they are very well
contented to have him wholly left out; and
then to suppose Man to be a meer Engine, that
is necessarily moved by such a train and series
of causes, that there is no action how bad so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
that is done by him, which it was any more
possible for him not to have done, than for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97979:8"/>
the fire not to burn when it pleases. If this be
true, farewell all the differences of good and
evil in mens actions; farewell all expectations
of future rewards and punishments; <hi>Religion</hi>
becomes but a meer name, and righteousness
but an art to live by. But it is with this, as it
is with the other arguments they use against
<hi>Religion;</hi> there is something within, which
checks and controlls them in what they say:
and that inward remorse of conscience, which
such men sometimes feel in their evil actions
(when conscience is forced to recoil by the
foulness of them) doth effectually confute
their own <hi>hypothesis;</hi> and makes them not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
those actions to be necessary, for which
they suffer so much in themselves because they
knew they did them freely. Or is it as fatall
for man to believe himself free when he is not
so, as it is for him to act when his choice
is determined? but what <hi>series</hi> of causes
is there that doth so necessarily impose upon
the common sense of all mankind? It seems
very strange, that man should have so little
sense of his own interest to be still necessita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to the worst of actions, and yet torment
himself with the thoughts that he did them
freely. Or is it only the <hi>freedome of action,</hi> and
not <hi>of choice,</hi> that men have an experience of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97979:9"/>
within themselves? But surely, however men
may subtilly dispute of the difference between
these two, no man would ever believe himself
to be free in what he does, unless he first
thought himself to be so, in what he
determines? And if we suppose man to have
as great a <hi>freedom of choice</hi> in all his evil acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
(which is the liberty we are now speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of) as any persons assert or contend for,
we cannot suppose that he should have a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
experience of it, than now he hath.
So that either it is impossible for man to know
when his choice is free; or if it may be known,
the constant experience of all evil men in the
world will testifie, that it is so now. Is it
possible for the most intemperate person to
believe, when the most pleasing temptations
to lust or gluttony are presented to him, that no
considerations whatever could restrain his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite,
or keep him from the satisfaction of
his brutish inclinations? Will not the sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,
though groundless, apprehension of
poyson in the Cup, make the Drunkards
heart to ake, and hand to tremble, and
to let fall the supposed fatall mixture in
the midst of all his jollity and excess? How
often have persons who have designed the
greatest mischief to the lives and fortunes of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97979:9"/>
others, when all opportunities have fallen out
beyond their expectation for accomplishing
their ends, through some sudden thoughts
which have surprized them, almost in the very
act, been diverted from their intended purposes?
Did ever any yet imagine that the charms of
beauty and allurements of lust were so irresisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
that if men knew before hand they should
surely dye in the embraces of an adulterous
bed, they could not yet withstand the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
to it? If then some considerations, which
are quite of another nature from all the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
which are presented to him, may quite
hinder the force and efficacy of them upon
the mind of man (as we see in <hi>Ioseph's</hi> resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
the importunate Caresses of his Mistris)
what reason can there be to imagine that
man is a meer <hi>machine</hi> moved only as outward
objects determine him? And if the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
of present fear and danger may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
men from the practice of evil actions,
shall not the far more weighty considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of eternity have, at least an equall, if not a
far greater power and efficacy upon mens
minds, to keep them from everlasting misery?
Is an immortall soul and the eternal happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
of it so mean a thing in our esteem and
value, that we will not deny our selves those
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97979:10"/>
sensuall pleasures for the sake of that, which
we would renounce for some present danger?
Are the flames of another world such painted
fires, that they deserve only to be laughed at,
and not seriously considered by us? Fond
man! art thou only free to ruine and destroy
thy self? a strange fatality indeed, when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but what is mean and triviall shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine
thy choice! when matters of the
highest moment are therefore less regarded,
because they are such. Hast thou no other
plea for thy self, but that thy sins were fatal?
thou hast no reason then to believe but that
thy misery shall be so too. But if thou ownest
a <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Providence,</hi> assure thy self that justice
and righteousness are not meer <hi>Titles</hi> of <hi>his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi>
but the reall properties of his nature. And
he who hath appointed the rewards and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments
of the great day, will then call the
sinner to account, not only for all his other
sins, but for offering to lay the imputation of
them upon himself. For if the greatest abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency
of mens evil wayes, the rigour of his
Laws, the severity of his judgements, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actness
of his justice, the greatest care used to
reclaim men from their sins, and the highest
assurance, that he is not the cause of their ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine,
may be any vindication of the holiness of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97979:10"/>
               <hi>God</hi> now, and his justice in the life to come;
we have the greatest reason to lay the blame of
all our evil actions upon our selves, as to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
the glory of all our good unto himself
alone.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>The frailty of humane nature:</hi> those who
find themselves to be free enough to do their
souls mischief, and yet continue still in the
doing of it, find nothing more ready to plead
for themselves, than the unhappiness of mans
composition, and the degenerate state of the
world. If <hi>God</hi> had designed (they are ready
to say) that man should lead a life free from
sin, why did he confine the soul of man to a
body so apt to taint and pollute it? But who
art thou O man, that thus findest fault with
thy Maker? Was not his kindness the greater,
in not only giving thee a soul capable of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying
himself, but such an habitation for it
here, which by the curiosity of its contrivance,
the number and usefulness of its parts, might
be a perpetual and domestick testimony of the
wisdom of its <hi>Maker?</hi> Was not such a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction
of soul and body necessary for the
exercise of that dominion which <hi>God</hi> designed
man for, over the creatures endued only with
sense and motion? And if we suppose this life
to be a state of tryall in order to a better, (as in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97979:11"/>
all reason we ought to do) what can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined
more proper to such a state, than to
have the soul constantly employed in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
of those sensuall inclinations which
arise from the body? In the doing of which,
the proper exercise of that vertue consists,
which is made the condition of future hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness.
Had it not been for such a composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
the difference could never have been seen
between good and bad men; <hi>i. e.</hi> between
those who maintain the Empire of reason, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted
by the motives of <hi>Religion,</hi> over all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour
faculties, and such who dethrone their
souls and make them slaves to every lust that
will command them. And if men willingly
subject themselves to that which they were
born to rule, they have none to blame but
themselves for it. Neither is it any excuse at
all, that this, through the degeneracy of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
is grown the common custome of the
world; unless that be in it self so great a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
that there is no resisting the power of it.
If <hi>God</hi> had commanded us to comply with all
the customs of the world, and at the same time
to be <hi>sober, righteous, and good,</hi> we must have
lived in another age than we live in, to have
excused these two commands from a palpable
contradiction. But instead of this, he hath
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97979:11"/>
forewarned us of the danger of being led aside
by the soft, and easie compliances of the world;
and if we are sensible of our own infirmities,
(as we have all reason to be) he hath offered us
the assistance of his <hi>Grace</hi> &amp; of that <hi>Spirit</hi> of his,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4. 4.</note>
               <hi>which is greater than the Spirit that is in the world.</hi>
He hath promised us those weapons whereby
we may withstand the <hi>torrent</hi> of wickedness in
the world, with far greater success than the old
<hi>Gauls</hi> were wont to do the inundations of their
countrey, whose custome was to be drowned
with their arms in their hands. But it will be
the greater folly in us to be so, because we have
not only sufficient means of resistance, but we
understand the danger before hand. If we
once forsake the strict rules of religion and
goodness, and are ready to yield our selves to
whatever hath got retainers enough to set up
for a custome, we may know where we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin,
but we cannot where we shall make an
end. For every fresh assault makes the breach
wider, at which more enemies may come in
still; so that when we find our selves under
their power, we are contented for our own ease
to call them <hi>Friends.</hi> Which is the unhappy
consequence of too easie yielding at first, till
at last the greatest slavery to sin be accounted
but good humour, and a gentle compliance
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97979:12"/>
with the fashions of the world. So that when
men are perswaded, either through fear, or too
great easiness to disuse that strict eye which
they had before to their actions, it oft
times falls out with them, as it did with the
Souldier in the <hi>Roman History,</hi> who blinded his
eye so long in the time of the Civil Wars, that
when he would have used it again, he could
not. And when custom hath by degrees ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
away the sense of sin from their conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
they grow as hard as <hi>Herodotus</hi> tells us the
heads of the old <hi>Egyptians</hi> were by the heat of
the Sun, that nothing would ever enter them.
If men will with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> herd with
the beasts of the field, no wonder if their
reason departs from them, and by degrees they
grow as savage as the company they keep. So
powerfull a thing is custome to debauch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
and so easily do the greatest vices by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
obtain admission into the souls of men,
under pretence of being retainers to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<hi>infirmities</hi> of humane nature. Which is
a <hi>phrase,</hi> through the power of self-flattery, and
mens ignorance in the nature of morall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
made to be of so large and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive
a sense that the most wilfull violations of
the <hi>Laws</hi> of Heaven, and such which the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>
tells us do exclude from the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97979:12"/>
it, do find (rather than make) friends enough
to shelter themselves under the <hi>protection</hi> of
them. But such a <hi>protection</hi> it is, which is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
allowed in the <hi>Court</hi> of Heaven, nor will
ever secure the souls of men without a hearty
and sincere repentance, from the <hi>arrest</hi> of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
justice; which when it comes to call the
world to an account of their actions will
make no defalcations at all for the power of
custom, or common practice of the world.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>The impossibility of the command, or rather of
obedience to it.</hi> When neither of the former
plea's will effect their design, but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
the pretended <hi>necessity of humane
actions,</hi> and the more than pretended <hi>common
practice of the world,</hi> their consciences still fly
in their faces and rebuke them sharply for
their sins, then in a mighty rage and fury they
charge <hi>God</hi> himself with <hi>Tyranny</hi> in laying im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible
<hi>Laws</hi> upon the sons of men. But if
we either consider the nature of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
or the promises which accompany it,
or the large experience of the world to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
we shall easily discover that this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
is altogether as unreasonable as either of
the foregoing. For what is it that <hi>God</hi> requires
of men as the condition of their future hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness
which in its own nature is judged im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97979:13"/>
Is it for men to <hi>live soberly, righteously
and godly in this world?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> for that was the end of
Christian Religion to perswade men to do so:
but who thinks it impossible to avoid the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions
of intemperance, not to defraud, or
injure his neighbours, or to pay that reverence
and sincere devotion to <hi>God</hi> which we owe
unto him? <hi>Is it to do as we would be done by?</hi> yet
that hath been judged by strangers to the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
Religion</hi> a most exact measure of humane
conversation; Is it <hi>to maintain an universall kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
and good will to men?</hi> that indeed is the great
excellency of our Religion, that it so strictly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
it; but if this be impossible, farewell
all <hi>good nature</hi> in the world; and I suppose
few will own this charge, lest theirs be su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected.
Is it <hi>to be patient under suffering, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
in our desires, circumspect in our actions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented
in all conditions?</hi> yet these are things which
those have pretended to who never owned
<hi>Christianity,</hi> and therefore surely they never
thought them impossible. Is it <hi>to be charitable
to the poor, compassionate to those in misery?</hi> is it
<hi>to be frequent in prayer, to love God above all things,
to forgive our enemies as we hope God will forgive
us, to believe the Gospel, and be ready to suffer for
the sake of Christ?</hi> There are very few among
us but will say they do all these things alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97979:13"/>
and therefore surely they do not think them
impossible. The like answer I might give to all
the other precepts of the <hi>Gospel</hi> till we come to the
<hi>denying ungodliness and worldly lusts,</hi> and as to these
too, if we charge men with them, they either deny
their committing them, and then say they have
kept the command; or if they confess it, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise
amendment for the furture; but in neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
can they be said to think the command im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible.
Thus we see their own mouths will
condemn them when they charge <hi>God</hi> with laying
impossible <hi>Laws</hi> on mankind. But then if we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
further into the judgements of those who it
may be never concerned themselves so much about
the precepts of <hi>Christian Religion,</hi> as to try whether
they had any power to observe them or not; nay,
if we yield them more (than, it may be, they are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
to enquire after, though they ought to do it)
<hi>viz.</hi> that without the <hi>assistance of divine grace,</hi> they
can never do it: yet such is the unlimited nature of
divine goodness and the exceeding riches of Gods
Grace, that (knowing the weakness and degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy
of humane nature when he gave these com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
to men) he makes a large and free offer
of assistance to all those who are so sensible of
their own infirmity as to beg it of him. And can
men then say the command is impossible when he
hath promised an assistance sutable to the nature of
the duty &amp; the infirmities of men? If it be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97979:14"/>
that some of the duties of <hi>Christianity</hi> are
very difficult to us now; let us consider by what
means he hath sweetned the performance of them.
Will not the proposal of so excellent a reward,
make us swallow some more than ordinary hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships
that we might enjoy it? Hath he not made
use of the most obliging motives to perswade us
to the practice of what he requires, by the infinite
discovery of his own love, the death of his Son,
and the promise of his Spirit? And what then is
wanting, but only setting our selves to the serious
obedience of them, to make his commands not
only not impossible, but easie to us? But our grand
fault is, we make impossibilities our selves, where
we find none, and then we complain of them:
we are first resolved not to practise the commands,
and then nothing more easie than to find fault
with them: we first pass sentence, and then exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
evidences; first condemn, and then enquire
into the merits of the cause. Yet surely none of
these things can be accounted impossible, which
have been done by all those who have been sincere
and hearty Christians; and <hi>God</hi> forbid, we should
think all guilty of hypocrisie, who have professed
the <hi>Christian Religion</hi> from the beginning of it to
this day. Nay more than so, they have not only
done them, but professed to have that joy and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
of mind in the doing of them, which
they would not exchange for all the pleasures
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97979:14"/>
and delights of the world. These were the men,
who not only were patient, but rejoyced in suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings;
who accounted it their honour and glory
to endure any thing for the sake of so excellent a
religion; who were so assured of a future happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
by it, that they valued Martyrdoms above
Crowns and Scepters. But God be thanked, we
may hope to come to Heaven on easier terms than
these, or else many others might nevercome thither,
besides those who think to make this a pretence
for their sin, that now when with encouragement
and honour we may practise our Religion, the
commands of it are thought impossible by them.
Thus we have made good the general charge here
implyed against wicked men, in that they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<hi>Fools,</hi> by examining the most plausible pretences
they bring for themselves.</p>
            <p>I now come to the particular impeachment of
their folly, because <hi>they make a mock at sin.</hi> And
that I shall prove especially by two things: 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
this argues <hi>the highest degree of wickedness.</hi> 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
it betrayes the <hi>greatest weakness of judgement and
want of consideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Because it argues <hi>the highest degree of wickedness.</hi>
If to sin be folly, to make a mock at it is little short
of madness. It is such a height of impiety, that
few but those who are of very profligate conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciences
can attain to, without a long custom in sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
For conscience is at first modest, and starts
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97979:15"/>
and boggles at the appearance of a great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
till it be used to it &amp; grown familiar with it. It
is no such easie matter for a man to get the maste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of his conscience; a great deal of force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
must be used to ones self before he does it.
The natural impressions of good and evil, the fears
of a <hi>Deity,</hi> and the apprehensions of a future state
are such curbs and checks in a sinners way, that
he must first sin himself beyond all feeling
of these, before he can attain to the <hi>seat</hi> of the <hi>scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi>
And we may justly wonder how any should
ever come thither, when they must break through
all that is ingenuous and modest, all that is vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
and good, all that is tender and apprehensive
in humane nature, before they can arrive at it. They
must first deny a <hi>God,</hi> and despise an immortal soul,
they must conquer their own reason, and cancell
the <hi>Law written in their hearts,</hi> they must hate all
that is serious, and yet soberly believe themselves
to be no better <hi>than the beasts that perish,</hi> before men
can come to make a <hi>scoff at religion,</hi> and <hi>a mock at sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And who now could ever imagine that
in a Nation professing <hi>Christianity,</hi> among a
people whose <hi>genius</hi> enclines them to civility and
religion, yea among those who have the greatest
advantages of behaviour and education, and who
are to give the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>civility</hi> to the rest of the
Nation, there should any be found who should
deride religion, make sport with their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneness,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97979:15"/>
and make so light of nothing, as being
damned? I come not here to accuse any, and least
of all those who shew so much regard of <hi>religion</hi> as
to be present in the places devoted to sacred pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses;
but if there be any such here, whose con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences
accuse themselves, for any degrees of
so great impiety; I beseech them by all that is dear
and precious to them, by all that is sacred and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
by the <hi>vows</hi> of their <hi>Baptism,</hi> and their <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation</hi>
of the <hi>holy Eucharist,</hi> by all the kindness of
Heaven which they either enjoy or hope for, by
the death and sufferings of the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that they
would now consider how great folly and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
they betray in it, and what the dreadfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence
of it will be, if they do not timely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
of it. If it were a doubt (as I hope it is not
among any here) whether the matters of <hi>religion</hi>
be true or no, they are surely things which ought
to be seriously thought and spoken of. It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
no jesting matter to affront a <hi>God</hi> of infinite
<hi>Majesty</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> (and he judges every wilfull
sinner to do so) nor can any one in his wits think
it a thing not to be regarded, whether he be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
happy or miserable. Methinks then among
persons of civility and honour, above all others,
<hi>Religion</hi> might at least be treated with the respect
and reverence due to the concernments of it; that it
be not made the sport of entertainments, nor the
common subject of <hi>Playes</hi> and <hi>Comedies:</hi> For is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97979:16"/>
there nothing to trifle with, but <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>service?</hi>
Is wit grown so <hi>schismatical</hi> &amp; <hi>sacrilegious,</hi> that it can
please it self with nothing but <hi>holy ground?</hi> Are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faness
&amp; wit grown such inseparable companions,
that none shall be allowed to pretend to the one,
but such as dare be highly guilty of the other? Far
be it from those who have but the name of <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
either to do these things themselves, or to be
pleased with them that do them: especially in such
times as ours of late have been, when <hi>God</hi>
hath used so many wayes to make us serious if any
thing would ever do it. If men had only slighted
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>religion,</hi> and <hi>made a mock at sin,</hi> when they
had grown wanton through the abundance of
peace and plenty, and saw no severities of <hi>Gods
justice</hi> used upon such who did it; yet the fault
had been so great, as might have done enough to
have interrupted their peace and destroyed that
<hi>plenty,</hi> which made them out of the greatness of their
pride and wantonness to kick against Heaven: but
to do it in despight of all <hi>Gods</hi> judgements, to
<hi>laugh in his face</hi> when <hi>his rod is upon our backs,</hi> when
neither Pestilence nor Fire can make us more
afraid of him, exceedingly aggravates the impiety,
and makes it more unpardonable. When like the
old <hi>Germans we dance among naked swords,</hi> when men
shall defie and reproach Heaven in the midst of a
Cities ruines, and over the Graves of those whom
the arrows of the <hi>Almighty</hi> have heaped together,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97979:16"/>
what can be thought of such, but that nothing will
make them serious, but eternal misery? And are
they so sure there is no such thing to be feared, that
they never think of it, but when by their execrable
oaths they call upon <hi>God</hi> to <hi>damn them,</hi> for fear he
should not do it time enough for them? Thus
while men abuse his patience, and provoke his
justice, while they trample upon his kindness, and
slight his severities, while they despise his Laws
and mock at the breaches of them, what can be
added more to their impiety? or what can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
by such who are guilty of it, but that <hi>God</hi>
should quickly discover their mighty folly by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
them see how much they have deceived
themselves,<note place="margin">Gal. 6. 7.</note> since <hi>God will not be mocked,</hi> but <hi>because
of these things the wrath of God will most certainly come
upon the children of disobedience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 6.</note> Which leads to the
second thing wherein this folly is seen.</p>
            <p>2. Which is in <hi>the weakness of judgement and want of
consideration,</hi> which this betrayes in men. <hi>Folly</hi> is the
great unsteadiness of the mind in the thoughts of
what is good and fitting to be done. It were hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
for many in the world, if none should suffer
in their reputation for want of wisdom, but such
whom nature or some violent distemper have
wholly deprived of the use of their reason and
understandings: But wisdom does not lye in the
rambling imaginations of mens minds (for <hi>fools</hi>
may think of the same things which wise men
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97979:17"/>
practise) but in a due consideration and choice of
things which are most agreeable to the end they
design, supposing the end in the first place to be
worthy a wise mans choice; for I cannot yet see
why the end may not be chosen as-well as the
means, when there are many stand in competition
for our choice, and men first deliberate, and then
determine which is the fittest to be pursued. But
when the actions of men discover, that either they
understand or regard not the most excellent end
of their beings, or do those things which directly
cross and thwart their own designs, or else pursue
those which are mean and ignoble in themselves,
we need not any further evidence of their folly,
than these things discover.</p>
            <p>Now that those who <hi>make a mock at sin</hi> are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of all these, will appear; if we consider whom
they provoke by doing so, whom they most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury,
and upon what reasonable considerations they
are moved to what they do.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Whom they provoke by their making a mock at sin;</hi>
Supposing that there is a <hi>Governour</hi> of the world,
who hath established <hi>Laws</hi> for us to be guided by,
we may easily understand, whose honour and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
is reflected on, when the violations of his
<hi>Laws</hi> are made nothing of. For surely if they had
a just esteem of his <hi>power</hi> and <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
durst make so bold with him, as all those do
who not only commit sin themselves, but laugh
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97979:17"/>
at the scrupulosity of those who dare not When
<hi>Dionysius</hi> changed <hi>Apollos</hi> Cloak, and took off the
<hi>Golden Beard</hi> of <hi>Aesculapius,</hi> with those solemn jeers
of the unsuitableness of the one to the Son of a
beardless Father; and the much greater conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency
of a cheaper garment to the other; it was a
sign he stood not much in awe of the severity of
their looks, nor had any dread at all of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
of their power. But although there be so
infinite a disproportion between the artificial <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities</hi>
of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> and the <hi>Majesty</hi> of him who
made and governs the whole world; yet as little
reverence to his power and authority is shewed by
all such who dare affront him with such a mighty
confidence, and bid the greatest defiance to his
<hi>Laws</hi> by scoffing at them. What is there, the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns</hi>
and <hi>Princes</hi> of the earth do more justly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,
and express the highest indignation against,
than to have their <hi>Laws</hi> despised, their persons af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted,
and their authority contemned? And can
we then imagine, that a <hi>God</hi> of infinite <hi>power</hi> and
<hi>Majesty,</hi> the honour of whose <hi>Laws</hi> is as dear to
him as his own is, should sit still unconcerned,
when so many indignities are continually offered
them, and never take any notice at all of them? It is
true, his patience is not to be measured by our fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
and peevish natures, (and it is happy for us
all that it is not) he knows the sinner can never
escape his power, and therefore bears the longer
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97979:18"/>
with him: but yet his lenity is always joyned
with his wisdom and justice, and the time is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
when patience it self shall be no more. Is it
not then the highest madness and folly to provoke
one whose power is infinitely greater than our
own is, and from the severity of whose wrath we
cannot secure our selves one minute of an hour?
How knowest thou, O vain man, but that in the
midst of all thy mirth and jollity, while thou art
boasting of thy sins, and thinkest thou canst never
fill up fast enough the measure of thy iniquities,
a sudden fit of an <hi>Apoplexy,</hi> or the breaking of an
<hi>Aposteme,</hi> or any of the innumerable instruments
of death, may dispatch thee hence, and consign
thee into the hands of divine justice? And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall
then wilt thou be able to dispute with <hi>God?</hi>
Wilt thou then charge his Providence with folly,
and his Laws with unreasonableness? when his
greatness shall affright thee, his <hi>Majesty</hi> astonish
thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his <hi>power</hi> disarm thee, and his justice pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
against thee: when notwithstanding all thy
<hi>bravado's</hi> here, they own conscience shall be not
only thy accuser and witness, but they judge and
executioner too: when it shall <hi>revenge</hi> it self
upon thee for all the rapes and violences thou hast
committed upon it here: when horror and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion
shall be thy portion, and the unspeakable
anguish of a racked and tormented mind shall too
late convince thee of thy folly in <hi>making a mock</hi> at
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97979:18"/>
that which stings with an everlasting venom. Art
thou then resolved to put all these things to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture,
and live as securely as if the <hi>terrors</hi> of the
<hi>Almighty</hi> were but the dreams of men awake, or the
fancies of weak and distempered brains? But I had
rather believe that in the heat and fury of thy lusts
thou wouldst seem to others to think so, than
thou either doest or canst perswade thy self to such
unreasonable folly. Is it not then far better to
consult the tranquillity of thy mind here, and the
eternal happiness of it hereafter, by a serious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
and speedy amendment of thy life, than
to expose thy self for the sake of thy sensual plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures
to the fury of that <hi>God</hi> whose justice is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite,
and power irresistible? Shall not <hi>the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
of his excellency make thee</hi> now <hi>afraid of him?</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
then <hi>make</hi> any <hi>mock at sin</hi> more, unless thou art
able <hi>to contend with the Almighty,</hi> or <hi>to dwell with ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting
burnings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The folly of it is seen in considering <hi>whom the
injury redounds to</hi> by mens making themselves so
pleasant with their sins. Do they think by their rude
attempts to dethrone the <hi>Majesty</hi> of Heaven, or by
standing at the greatest defiance, to make him
willing to come to terms of composition with
them? Do they hope to slip beyond the bounds
of his power, by falling into nothing when they
dye, or to sue out <hi>prohibitions</hi> in the Court of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
to hinder the effects of <hi>Iustice</hi> there? Do they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97979:19"/>
design to out-wit infinite Wisdom, or to find such
flaws in <hi>Gods</hi> government of the world, that he
shall be contented to let them go unpunished? All
which imaginations are alike vain and foolish, and
only shew how easily wickedness baffles the reason
of mankind, and makes them rather hope or wish
for the most impossible things, than believe they
shall ever be punished for their impieties. If the
<hi>Apostate Spirits</hi> can by reason of their present restraint
and expectation of future punishments be as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant
in beholding the <hi>follies</hi> of men as they are mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
to suggest them, it may be one of the greatest
diversions of their misery, to see how active and
witty men are in contriving their own ruine. To
see with what greediness they catch at every bait
that is offered them, and when they are swallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the most deadly <hi>poyson,</hi> what arts they use to
perswade themselves that it is a healthful potion.
No doubt, nothing can more gratifie them than to
see men sport themselves into their own destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and go down so pleasantly to Hell: when eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
flames become the first awakeners, and then
men begin to be wise, when it is too late to be so:
when nothing but insupportable torments can
convince them that <hi>God</hi> was in earnest with them,
that he would not alwayes bear the affronts of evil
men, and that those who derided the miseries of
another life, shall have leisure enough to repent
their folly, when their repentance shall only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97979:19"/>
their sorrow without hopes of pardon
by it.</p>
            <p>3. But if there were any present felicity, or any
considerable advantage to be gained by this <hi>mocking
at sin,</hi> and undervaluing Religion, there would
seem to be some kind of pretence, though nothing
of true reason for it. Yet that which heightens
this folly to the highest degree in the last place is,
that there can be no imaginable consideration
thought on which might look like a <hi>plausible tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation</hi>
to it. The covetous man, when he hath
defrauded his neighbour, and used all kinds of arts
to compass an estate, hath the fulness of his baggs
to answer for him; and whatever they may do in
another world, he is sure they will do much in this.
The voluptuous man, hath the strong propensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of his nature, the force of temptation which
lyes in the charms of beauty, to excuse his unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
pleasures by. The ambitious man, hath the
greatness of his mind, the advantage of authority,
the examples of those who have been great before
him, and the envy of those who condemn him, to
plead for the heights he aims at. But what is it
which the person who despises Religion, and
laughs at every thing that is serious, proposes to
himself as the reason of what he does? But alas!
this were to suppose him to be much more serious
than he is, if he did propound any thing to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
as the ground of his actions. But it may be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97979:20"/>
a great kindness to others, though none to himself;
I cannot imagine any, unless it may be, to make
them thankfull they are not arrived to that height
of folly; or out of perfect good nature, least they
should take him to be wiser than he is. The <hi>Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists
fool</hi> despises him as much as he does Religion:
for he only <hi>saith it in his heart there is no God;</hi> but this
though he dares not think there is none, yet shews
him not near so much outward respect &amp; reverence
as the other does. Every the <hi>Atheist</hi> himself thinks
him a <hi>Fool,</hi> &amp; the greatest of all other, who believes
a <hi>God,</hi> and yet affronts him and trifles with him.
And although the <hi>Atheist</hi>'s <hi>Folly</hi> be unaccountable,
in resisting the clearest evidence of reason, yet so
far he is to be commended for what he sayes, that
if there be such a thing as <hi>Religion</hi> men ought to
be serious in it. So that of all hands the <hi>scoffer at
Religion</hi> is looked on as one forsaken of that little
reason, which might serve to uphold a slender re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
of being above <hi>the beasts that perish:</hi> nay,
therein his condition is worse than theirs, that
as they understand not <hi>Religion,</hi> they shall never be
punished for despising it: which such a person
can never secure himself from, considering the
<hi>power,</hi> the <hi>justice,</hi> the <hi>severity</hi> of that <hi>God,</hi> whom he
hath so highly provoked. <hi>God</hi> grant, that the
apprehension of this danger may make us so se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
in the profession and practice of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
that we may not by slighting that, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97979:20"/>
               <hi>mocking at sin,</hi> provoke him <hi>to laugh at our calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
and mock when our fear comes;</hi> but that by
beholding the sincerity of our repentance, and
the heartiness of our devotion to him, he may
<hi>turn his anger away from us, and rejoyce over us to do
us good.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97979:21"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97979:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
