<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Campanella revived, or, An enquiry into the history of the Royal Society, whether the virtuosi there do not pursue the projects of Campanella for the reducing  England unto Popery being the extract of a letter to a person of honour from H.S. with another letter to Sir N.N. relating the cause of the quarrel betwixt H.S. and the R.S. and an apology against some of their cavils : with a postscript concerning the quarrel depending betwixt H.S. and Dr. Merrett.</title>
            <author>Stubbe, Henry, 1632-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61868</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7503</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12193729</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12193729</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55946</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A61868)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55946)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 899:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Campanella revived, or, An enquiry into the history of the Royal Society, whether the virtuosi there do not pursue the projects of Campanella for the reducing  England unto Popery being the extract of a letter to a person of honour from H.S. with another letter to Sir N.N. relating the cause of the quarrel betwixt H.S. and the R.S. and an apology against some of their cavils : with a postscript concerning the quarrel depending betwixt H.S. and Dr. Merrett.</title>
                  <author>Stubbe, Henry, 1632-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Osler Library, McGill University.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Stubbs [Stubbe]. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Includes a discussion of Tommaso Campanella's De monarchia hispanica.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Campanella, Tommaso, 1568-1639. --  De monarchia Hispanica discursus.</term>
               <term>Merret, Christopher, 1614-1695.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Royal Society (Great Britain)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-08</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55946:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55946:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CAMPANELLA REVIVED. Or an Enquiry into the HISTORY OF THE Royal Society, Whether the <hi>Virtuosi</hi> there do not pursue the Projects of <hi>Campanella</hi> for the reducing <hi>England</hi> unto <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING The <hi>Extract</hi> of a Letter to a <hi>Person of Honour</hi> from <hi>H. S.</hi> with another Letter to Sir <hi>N. N.</hi> relating the cause of the Quarrel betwixt <hi>H. S.</hi> and the <hi>R. S.</hi> and an Apology against some of <hi>their Cavils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH A Postscript concerning the Quarrel depending betwixt <hi>H. S.</hi> and Dr. <hi>Merrett.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Aut <hi>hoc</hi> inclusi <hi>ligno</hi> occultantur Achivi;</l>
               <l>Aut <hi>haec</hi> in nostros fabricata est <hi>machina</hi> muros,</l>
               <l>Inspectura <hi>domos,</hi> venturaque desuper <hi>Urbi;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aut <hi>aliquis</hi> la<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et <hi>error:</hi> equo ne credite Teucri.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>d for the Author, 167<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:55946:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55946:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THis ensuing Letter was a part of what I sent long ago to a</hi> Person of Honour <hi>in this Nation, to represent the occasion of the quarrel betwixt</hi> Me <hi>and the</hi> Virtuosi, <hi>and shewed the necessity of pursuing it: by such argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I used as gained</hi> his approbation; <hi>and the generality of</hi> seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men <hi>have assented thereunto, though their opinion was, that the design might be of great danger and trouble to the</hi> bold undertaker. <hi>After that, I inserted it into a discourse concerning the</hi> Virtuosi, <hi>in which I debate many other things:</hi> viz. <hi>In op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to</hi> Dr. Merrett, <hi>I deduce the original of</hi> Apothecaries <hi>from the times of</hi> Hippocrates <hi>and</hi> Aristotle <hi>thorough the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>and</hi> Greek <hi>Empires; and shew with what</hi> prudence <hi>both</hi> Physicians <hi>and the</hi> Civil Magistrates <hi>concurred to</hi> their insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution: <hi>and I have largely entreated on that Question, which the</hi> Virtuosi, <hi>in order to the ruine of the</hi> Faculty <hi>of</hi> Physicians, <hi>and of the Trade of</hi> Apothecaries, <hi>to the great alteration of the</hi> Practice of Physick, <hi>and</hi> aggrandising of themselves, <hi>have started, and with</hi> much confidence <hi>and</hi> more ignorance <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. I shew not only sundry</hi> particular impostures <hi>obtruded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us by some of them: as also an account of a certain</hi> Model <hi>of the</hi> R. S. <hi>published in</hi> Germany, <hi>and written from</hi> London; <hi>in which there is so little of</hi> truth, <hi>that I wonder any of the</hi> Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuosi <note place="margin">Vide <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> pag. 65, 66, 67.</note> 
               <hi>should abuse</hi> Foreigners <hi>with such a</hi> Relation; <hi>or imagine that</hi> renown <hi>to be</hi> durable <hi>the foundation whereof is so</hi> vain <hi>and</hi> unstable. <hi>It is there that I demand they would make goood their</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:55946:3"/>
promise <hi>to the learned</hi> Olaus Borrichius, <hi>that</hi> none of their <note place="margin">Vide <hi>Th. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Epist. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ntur. 4. Ep. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Colleagues should publish any thing but by the allowance and consent of the R. Society, that thereby it might be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured against the cavils and exceptions of all Men. <hi>VVhich</hi> assurance <hi>of</hi> theirs, <hi>how ill they have managed, I dare appeal unto the</hi> world <hi>as Judges. I am now indisposed to publish the whole Treatise, and reserve it for some</hi> additions <hi>which</hi> Mr. Evelyns <hi>discourse of</hi> Forrest-Trees <hi>may invite me unto; the</hi> Second Edition <hi>whereof wants not its</hi> defects; <hi>and if I should trouble my self to examine his account of the</hi> Birch-Tree, <hi>it will appear as</hi> ridiculous <hi>as the</hi> History <hi>of</hi> Salt-Peter: <hi>and 'tis to me a</hi> Miracle, <hi>that neither</hi> He, <hi>nor all</hi> his Correspondents <hi>should inform us better of so obvious a thing: Neither is it less strange that I should be necessitated to dispute against another</hi> Virtuoso, <hi>Mr.</hi> Chamberlaine, <hi>whether it be our</hi> King's Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ent State of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> pag. 341. Edition 3. &amp; pag. 61.</note> to define what Books of Scriptur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> are Canonical, and what Apocryphal? <hi>And, whether it be</hi> the Interest of our Monarchy that all the Commonalty be kept poor and in a complaining condition? <hi>But I pass from these considerations, to some exceptions made against what I have already published. It is said, that I have</hi> maliciously represented the places cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured in their History: <hi>which if I have done, it is because they</hi> maliciously writ them: <hi>for I am not conscious of</hi> mis-alledging them, <hi>or of imposing any</hi> other sense thereon, than th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> words do bear: <hi>and if</hi> any man <hi>can</hi> interpret <hi>them otherwise than I do, I confess I have wronged them: but if it be not possible to do so, they must blame</hi> themselves: <hi>However, supposing the passages might bear a more</hi> favourable construction, <hi>yet since the sense I follow is the</hi> most natural, <hi>since that they might be construed to the prejudice of the</hi> Church of England, <hi>it is judged by</hi> me, <hi>and</hi> others, <hi>to be an</hi> important service to the Publick, <hi>to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort a</hi> positive Declaration of their meaning, <hi>lest another</hi> Brerely <hi>make a benefit from</hi> those words <hi>to overthrow the</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion. <hi>I am further pressed with this</hi> intergatory, <hi>why I should imagine that the</hi> R. S. <hi>would subvert the</hi> Faculty of Physicians, <hi>there being so many eminent men of that Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion admitted therein, and so esteemed by them, as that they cannot be judged to</hi> vilisie <hi>that Faculty. I answer,</hi> Quid verba
<pb facs="tcp:55946:3"/>
audio, cum facta videam? <hi>I see</hi> they do do it, <hi>and therefore a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> not to be harangued into another sentiment. At first</hi> they <hi>would have incorporated the</hi> Colledge of Physicians <hi>into</hi> their Society: <hi>but that the</hi> prudent <hi>and</hi> grave <hi>did decline: then they promoted the</hi> Anti-Colledge <hi>of</hi> Pseudo-Chymists, <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging</hi> Odowde <hi>and his</hi> ignorant Adherents <hi>in opposition to the</hi> Physicians: <hi>and this is not more</hi> notorious <hi>to the world, than it is also that those</hi> objections <hi>with which</hi> M. N. <hi>and other</hi> Quacksalvers <hi>amuse the</hi> Age <hi>were suggested unto them by the</hi> Virtuosi, <hi>and derived their repute</hi> from them. <hi>As for Mr.</hi> Glanvills <hi>book, it was perused by</hi> several of their Members, <hi>and corrected</hi> by them, <hi>and how much we are reduceable to a</hi> Society <hi>that could allow of</hi> that, <hi>and would not at my</hi> reiterated importunities <hi>call</hi> it in, <hi>or</hi> disclaim <hi>it, Let all</hi> Physicians <hi>judge. Nor would I have any man to believe that there are so many eminent</hi> Physicians <hi>of the</hi> R. S. <hi>for neither is the number of</hi> those admitted <hi>considerable;</hi> few of note <hi>but have</hi> deserted <hi>it again; the rest</hi> approve not of it: <hi>so that all they talk of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not amount to</hi> three understanding persons; <hi>and were</hi> they more, <hi>I do not find</hi> our Faculty <hi>better secured than that of</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, <hi>or the two</hi> Universities <hi>are by such Members thereof as are imbodyed into this</hi> Trojan-Horse. <hi>It is said also, that my</hi> Animadversions <hi>on Mr.</hi> Glanvill <hi>contain</hi> little of matter; <hi>to which I answer, that</hi> they <hi>contain enough to have made twenty</hi> Virtuosi <hi>famous, and would have acquired them a</hi> Memorial <hi>of</hi> ingenious <hi>and</hi> noble Experimentators: <hi>they contain enough to shew the</hi> ignorance <hi>of that person who had so insulted over all</hi> University-learning, <hi>and particularly over the</hi> Physicians: <hi>They contain enough, since they contain more than</hi> they all knew: <hi>and I think I have done great service to the</hi> learned, <hi>in shewing that these</hi> Virtuosi <hi>are very great</hi> Impostours, <hi>or men of</hi> little reading: <hi>either of which</hi> Imputations, <hi>if</hi> just, <hi>will se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us from</hi> their <hi>arrogance, and abate</hi> their esteem. <hi>I am blamed for diminishing the</hi> glory of our Nation, <hi>by ascribing</hi> all discoveries <hi>to the</hi> Antients, <hi>or else to</hi> Foreigners: <hi>to which I answer, that they take off from the</hi> glory of our Nation <hi>more, who usurp the</hi> inventions of others: <hi>I rather preserve the</hi> cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit <hi>of the</hi> English <hi>(though not of the</hi> Virtuosi) <hi>then diminish
<pb facs="tcp:55946:4"/>
i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> undue praises add not to any mans esteem: <hi>nor do I think I derogate from</hi> Dr. Willis, <hi>if I should say that his notion about the use of the</hi> Cerebrum <hi>and</hi> Cerebollum <hi>was fairly intimated by</hi> Carla Ruini, <hi>that ingenious</hi> Bolognese, <hi>in his</hi> Italian <hi>Anatomy of an</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>orse: <hi>neither do I lessen the performances of the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and</hi> curious <hi>Mr.</hi> R. Boyle, <hi>when I averr that</hi> Aristotle <hi>did held the</hi> Ayre to be ponderous, <hi>and</hi> weighed it <hi>before</hi> him; <hi>or that the</hi> Elasticity <hi>of the</hi> Ayre <hi>was (as to</hi> name <hi>and</hi> thing) <hi>fully proposed by</hi> Pecquetus; <hi>and which is more than I have yet said, yet 'tis true, even the comparison betwixt the</hi> Atmosphear <hi>and</hi> Flocks of Wool <hi>is urged by him.</hi> 
               <q>Fingito tibi Aerem <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Anat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>p. 8. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> hunc velut spong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>osi vel <hi>LANEI</hi> potius cumuli terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queum orbem ambientis molem:—</q> 
               <hi>And,</hi> 
               <q>Insitus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>reae substantiae ad rarescendum Elater spongiae <hi>LANEVE</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam imitatur.</q> 
               <hi>As little is Dr.</hi> Croone <hi>or Dr.</hi> Thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ston <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>jured, if I say that the Experiment about reviving a</hi> strangled Fowl <hi>by blowing</hi> ayre into the Lungs, <hi>was practised by</hi> Vesali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, <hi>and</hi> Bogdan, <hi>and was vulgarly known before, though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps</hi> 
               <note place="margin">V s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>l. de s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>l r. hum. corp. l. 7. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>not to the</hi> Virtuosi: <hi>and that the same</hi> Phaenomenon <hi>suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, if when Children are</hi> Still-born <hi>any one</hi> blow into their <note place="margin">Mr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. apol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>g. pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Breech: <hi>which experiment is well known to many</hi> Midwives; <hi>nor do they doubt the recovery of the</hi> Child, <hi>if the</hi> Guts <hi>do rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thereupon. These, and such like averrments of mine, being</hi> true, <hi>do not lessen the</hi> just esteem of any man, <hi>and argue</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour in me, <hi>not</hi> malice. <hi>Besides, since that the</hi> Virtuosi <hi>did with this</hi> borrowed glory <hi>attempt to over-bear the</hi> Universities <hi>and all others as</hi> Ideots <hi>and</hi> Ignoramus<hi>'s, 'twas necessary to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them that neither the</hi> Antients, <hi>nor modern</hi> Academicks <hi>were so</hi> foolish <hi>as they</hi> painted them out to be, <hi>nor the</hi> R. S. <hi>so</hi> inquisitive <hi>as they would seem: and that if others would practise</hi> those Artifices, <hi>even the</hi> Peripateticks <hi>might</hi> signalize themselves <hi>as easily as the</hi> Royal Society. <hi>But I reserve the further prosecution hereof till another time: that which follows being of more importance to the</hi> Monarchy <hi>and</hi> Religion <hi>of our</hi> Kingdomes, <hi>than that I should detain my Reader any longer</hi> from it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henry Stubbe.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Warwick</hi> May 16. 1670.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55946:4"/>
            <head>CAMPANELLA REVIVED, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ever was there any sort of people that by so many <hi>Artifices</hi> endeavoured to insinuate themselves and their <hi>Religion</hi> into all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and countryes, as that of the <hi>Papists:</hi> there is no <hi>Treaty</hi> or <hi>promise</hi> can secure an <hi>enemy</hi> from their secret <hi>underminings:</hi> there is nothing so <hi>un-moral,</hi> which their <hi>Casu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ists</hi> do not allow of, and <hi>practise;</hi> nothing so <hi>impious,</hi> or <hi>blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> but is an ingredient in their <hi>councils,</hi> when subservient to their <hi>ends:</hi> there is no <hi>shape</hi> or <hi>disguise</hi> which they will not assume, no <hi>humour</hi> which they will not comply with; not an <hi>Action</hi> of theirs but ought to be suspected, since their <hi>Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours</hi> have that influeuce over their <hi>Layety,</hi> that whatsoever may, <hi>but at a distance, prejudice</hi> or tend to the detriment of their <hi>Church,</hi> they instantly put a period and stop thereunto. I speak not this to reflect upon the <hi>Society,</hi> who have found so great <hi>encouragement</hi> from that <hi>party,</hi> by the concurrence of their <hi>persons</hi> and <hi>purs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s:</hi> and so freely keep a <hi>correspondence</hi> with <hi>them</hi> from beyond seas: I only say, that as such an <hi>enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course</hi> is not unknown to the <hi>Congregatio de propaganda fide,</hi> so (whatever Mr. <hi>Sprat</hi> suggests) they do not apprehend the <hi>constitution</hi> to be any way to the <hi>prejudice</hi> and <hi>dis-service</hi> of their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Church.</hi> I believe it is not displeasing to <hi>them,</hi> to see how <hi>friendly</hi> the <hi>Protestants</hi> and <hi>Papists</hi> converse toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>this Assembly:</hi> and it must needs raise their <hi>hopes</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ringing things to a <hi>closer union,</hi> when they perceive the <hi>strangeness,</hi> that ought to be, and <hi>hath been</hi> betwixt them, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, and to read addresses commencing with, <hi>Holy Father.</hi> How much an <hi>Oratour</hi> gains upon his <hi>Auditors</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:55946:5"/>
when he hath made them <hi>attentive,</hi> and what a step that is to gaining upon their <hi>esteem,</hi> and how conducing that is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>persuading them to what he intends,</hi> I well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand: but what benefit and advantage <hi>Popery</hi> may derive from <hi>this,</hi> that our <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> our <hi>Divines</hi> and <hi>Lay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ty,</hi> laying aside all memory of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Irish Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacre,</hi> and <hi>Marian</hi> persecutions, the <hi>Gun-powder Treason,</hi> the <hi>firing of London,</hi> and forgetting all <hi>ani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>osities</hi> and <hi>apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of future dangers,</hi> converse <hi>freely</hi> with, and <hi>write</hi> oblige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to <hi>them,</hi> testifie a great esteem of <hi>them,</hi> and from the <hi>dis-use</hi> of all <hi>harsh</hi> but <hi>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>true censures,</hi> come at length to lay aside all <hi>rancour and bitterness of thoughts;</hi> I say, how great benefit <hi>Popery</hi> may draw hence, I cannot well comprehend: yet I guess in part from what the <hi>Historian</hi> sets down <q>From <note place="margin">Pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> enduring each others <hi>company,</hi> they may rise to a learning of each others <hi>opinions;</hi> from thence to an exchange of <hi>good offices;</hi> from thence to real <hi>friendship:</hi> till at last by such a Gentle, and easie <hi>Method,</hi> our several <hi>intere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> and <hi>sects</hi> may come to suffer one another, with the same peaceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness as men of different <hi>trades</hi> live one by another, in the same <hi>street.</hi>
               </q> Is not this a very fair account of what the <hi>R. S.</hi> will bring things unto? and can we wonder that the <hi>Papists</hi> should be very <hi>civil</hi> in their returns to an <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>embly</hi> that so highly obligeth them? But they add, <q>It is <hi>dishonourable,</hi> to pass an hard censure on the Religions of <hi>all other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 63.</note> It concerns them, to look to the <hi>reasonableness of their faith;</hi> and it is sufficient for us to be established in the <hi>Truth</hi> of our own.</q> Well! Adiew to all the Sermons of Bishop <hi>Andrews</hi> upon the fifth of <hi>November:</hi> all that King <hi>James</hi> writ against the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and to prove the <hi>Pope</hi> to be <hi>Antichrist:</hi> farewell to a great part of our <hi>Homil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> to part of the <hi>thirty nine Articles;</hi> the examples in <hi>Scriptur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> whereby the <hi>prophets</hi> and <hi>holymen</hi> declare against <hi>Edom, Tyre, Sidon,</hi> &amp;c. or against the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharisees,</hi> or <hi>Dian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> at <hi>Ephesus,</hi> or the <hi>Idols</hi> at <hi>Athens,</hi> these arc <hi>dishonourable</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious.</hi> Give me leave to speak to these <hi>Virtuosi</hi> in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the <hi>Romish</hi> Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> viz. <hi>Salvete <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ratres Asini; salvete sratres Lupi.</hi> Oh! how the followers of <hi>Conthen</hi> the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55946:5"/>
               <hi>Jesuit</hi> hugg themselves to hear these insinuations<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Multum profecit error, cum id obtinuit ne delegatur.</hi> See but the <hi>wayes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Conthen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 2. c. 18. Sect. 6.</note> which he proposeth in order to the reducing of <hi>Hereticks</hi> to the <hi>Roman Church</hi> again there, and if <hi>this procedure</hi> be not agreeable to the <hi>examples</hi> which <hi>he</hi> suggests, <hi>may I never find credit.</hi> You see what applauds Mr. <hi>Sprat</hi> would have gained from that <hi>Jesuit</hi> for this <hi>History:</hi> but how would <hi>Campanella</hi> have <hi>clapped his hands</hi> for joy to see this <hi>happy esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment</hi> which <hi>he</hi> so long ago <hi>projected,</hi> in order to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of <hi>England, Holland,</hi> and other <hi>heretical countreys?</hi> It was his <hi>darling</hi> design, and which that <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ryer</hi> (one of the most <hi>politi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>k</hi> that ever was) so often <hi>inculcates</hi> in his book of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Monarchy.</p>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>
                  <hi>Campanella</hi> touching the <hi>Spanish Monarchy.</hi> Ch. 10. pag. 47.</head>
               <p>His Prince <q>Should banish all <hi>Theological Questions</hi> out of <note place="margin">I follow the <hi>English</hi> Ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but the Latin is more <hi>Emphatical.</hi>
                     </note> the <hi>Transalpine</hi> Schools: seeing that all the <hi>Divines</hi> of those parts turn <hi>Hereticks,</hi> by not continuing sirm to the Holy constitutions of the <hi>Pope,</hi> but are still raising up <hi>fresh contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies:</hi> and the wits of these men are to be exercised only in the disputes of <hi>Natural Philosophy.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>He shall do well to shut up all the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew</hi> Schools; because that these two languages have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive to <hi>Monarchy;</hi> and are besides the <hi>main</hi> pillars by which those <hi>Heresies</hi> that chiefly raign at this day are <hi>built</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Our Author did not think of the <hi>Universal Character</hi> of Mr. <hi>Dalgerno.</hi>
                     </note> upon. And therefore, on the contrary, let him endeavour to bring in the knowledge of the <hi>Arabick</hi> tongue; by means whereof the <hi>Mahumetans</hi> may be the better convinced; and the troublesome <hi>Transalpine</hi> wits may employ themselves rather in confuting the <hi>Turks,</hi> than in vexing the <hi>Catholicks</hi> with <hi>their</hi> disputes.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Let him also erect <hi>Mathematical</hi> Schools—because by this <hi>means</hi> the <hi>Peoples</hi> Minds will be diverted from creating <hi>Us [Papists]</hi> any trouble, and will be incited to bend their Studies that way, which may be <hi>useful to the King.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:55946:6"/>
               <head>Ch. 25. pag. 157. Concerning <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <q>Now as concerning the weakning of the <hi>English,</hi> there can <hi>no better way be possibly found out,</hi> then by causing <hi>divisions,</hi> and dissentions amongst <hi>themselves,</hi> and by continually keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the same; which will quickly furnish the <hi>Spaniard</hi> [or <hi>French</hi>] with better and more advantageous <hi>Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> And as for the <hi>Religion</hi> of that people, it is that of <hi>Calvin;</hi> though very much moderated, and not so rigid, and austere as it is at <hi>Geneva:</hi> which yet cannot be so easily extinguished and rooted out <hi>there,</hi> unless there were some certain <hi>Schools</hi> set up in <hi>Flanders</hi> (with which the people of <hi>England</hi> have very great commerce) by means of which <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> much better done by the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> now at <hi>Arundel-</hi>House, under the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of</note> there should be scattered abroad the Seeds of Schisme and Divisions in the <hi>Natural Sciences;</hi> as namely betwixt the <hi>Stoicks, Peripateticks,</hi> and <hi>Telesians,</hi> by which the errours of the <hi>Calvinists</hi> may be made manifest.—Being of a Nature that is still desirous of <hi>Novelties,</hi> and <hi>change,</hi> they are easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought over to <hi>any thing.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Ch. 27, pag. 177. Concerning <hi>Flanders</hi> and lower <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <q>To conquer them there are but two wayes left now to be taken: the first of which is to sow the Seeds of <hi>Division</hi> amongst them: and the second to draw them forth of their own Countrey. <hi>Cadmus</hi> having a design of erecting a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy at <hi>Thebes,</hi> whither he came a <hi>stranger,</hi> is said first to kill a <hi>Serpent;</hi> by which was signified, the Defence and Safe-guard of <hi>Thebes:</hi> and then afterwards to sow the <hi>Teeth</hi> of it; that is to say, to scatter abroad the <hi>Poyson</hi> of <hi>Desire of Innovation,</hi> and an earnestness to be instructed in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Learning,</hi> namely in such <hi>new Sciences</hi> and <hi>Arts,</hi> as he had brought over with him from his own Countrey. And hence <hi>Souldiers</hi> are said to spring up, who through <hi>mutual discord,</hi> slew each other; and the remainders of them that were left, joyned themselves with <hi>Cadmus,</hi> their Head and Captain; so laying the foundation of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55946:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of <hi>Thebes</hi> in <hi>Boeotia.</hi> I affirm therefore that <hi>these very courses</hi> ought to have been taken by the King of <hi>Spain;</hi> and not a war to have been only maintained against them all this while.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And certainly, if the <hi>Southern</hi> people would ever conquer, or lay the foundations of a Monarchy over the <hi>Northern,</hi> see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they are <hi>not strong</hi> enough to bring the same about, they <hi>ought</hi> to have recourse to the <hi>Arts</hi> either of <hi>Cadmus,</hi> or of <hi>Jason:</hi> although of the two, <hi>Jason</hi> went the more wisely to work; seeing he first won the Heart of <hi>Medea,</hi> that is, the <note place="margin">☜</note> good will and affections of the <hi>Northern women</hi> to him.—Afterwards <hi>Jason</hi> by the enchantments of <hi>Medea,</hi> slew the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> that is, the <hi>Guard</hi> of the Kingdome; such as are the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and warlike men of a Nation, with the <hi>Preachers.</hi> And then did he by the means of <hi>Enchanted Oyntments,</hi> tame fierce <hi>Beasts,</hi> the Brazen-footed and Fire-spitting <hi>Bulls;</hi> that is, by his <hi>friendship</hi> and <hi>gifts,</hi> he won over to him the <hi>Nobles</hi> and principal men of the Kingdome. And at length, <hi>by them</hi> he sowed about the <hi>Teeth of the Dragon;</hi> that is, by the assistance of the <hi>Nobles,</hi> he spread abroad the seeds of Discord and <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sention about Religion, Arts,</hi> and <hi>Honours.</hi> Whence, in the last place, sprung up <hi>Souldiers,</hi> that is, <hi>Factions;</hi> (such as are those of the <hi>Guelphs</hi> and <hi>Gibellines,</hi> the <hi>Pontificians</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialists,</hi> the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Catholicks)</hi> wherein they kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led each other: But those that remained, chose <hi>Jason</hi> for their <hi>Head,</hi> and <hi>Commander;</hi> and though few in number, yet afforded Him their assistance in the getting of the <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fleece,</hi> that is to say, such an <hi>Empire</hi> as we hear speak of.</q>
               </p>
               <p>After this he proceeds to direct several things, whereof one <note place="margin">Pag. 180.</note> is, that by all means it be solidly taught, that <hi>the Pope is not <note place="margin">☜</note> Antichrist;</hi> for upon the gaining of this point (sayes <hi>He,</hi> and I desire it may be marked) <hi>do all the rest depend:</hi> And, (in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the casting away of all <hi>practical Divinity,</hi> and the intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of <hi>some such Religion,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Sprat</hi> would have) <q>It must <note place="margin">Pag. 181.</note> be unanimously and stoutly maintained against <hi>them,</hi> that All <hi>Commentaries</hi> whatsoever that have been written upon the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> whether by <hi>Catholicks</hi> or <hi>Hereticks,</hi> ever since S. <hi>Augustins</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:55946:7"/>
time, are to be suspected, and not to be trusted unto.</q> Mr. <hi>Sprat</hi> saith that the foundations on which the Church of <hi>England</hi> stands, are no other, but (in the <hi>first place!)</hi> the Rights of the <hi>Civil power:</hi> the imitation of the <hi>first uncorrupt Churches</hi> (in <note place="margin">Pag. 362.</note> the <hi>second place!</hi> and <hi>thirdly)</hi> the <hi>Scripture expounded by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 355.</note> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Religion</hi> ought not to be the subject of <hi>Disputations:</hi> It should not stand in need of any devices of <hi>Reason:</hi> It should in this be like the <hi>Temporal laws of all Countreys,</hi> towards the obeying of which there is no need of <hi>Syllogysms</hi> or distincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; nothing else is necessary but a bare promulgation (the <hi>Papists</hi> phrase is <hi>sufficient proposition!)</hi> a common apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and sense enough to understand the Grammatical meaning of Ordinary words.</q> Thus he casts off all <hi>Scholastick</hi> and <hi>Polemical</hi> Divinity, and writes as if he did not own the <hi>Three Creeds,</hi> and <hi>four general Councils,</hi> or <hi>thirty nine Articles:</hi> we must use no <hi>Syllogisms,</hi> though to prove the <hi>Trinity,</hi> or <hi>merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riousness of Christs death,</hi> or our interest therein by a <hi>practical Syllogysm,</hi> and <hi>fides specialis misericordiae:</hi> no <hi>Analogy of faith</hi> to regulate us by: no <hi>Church-History:</hi> in fine, we must look <hi>no farther</hi> than the <hi>Grammatical meaning</hi> of <hi>ordinary</hi> words, though the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and <hi>Hoc est corpus meum,</hi> be the <hi>subject of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.—</hi>I find indeed that <hi>Campanella</hi> adds, that <q>the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying <note place="margin">Pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> of Books, and the spinning out of Controversies, do but add Authority to a bad cause, and besides also shews like a kind of Victory.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>These <hi>Hereticks,</hi> after they had put forth <hi>new Bibles</hi> into the world, and wresting all the <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Historians</hi> as they pleased, put such interpretations upon the same as they thought good: they then began, in order thereunto, to apply themselves to the study of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> tongues, and started a thousand Grammatical Niceties, wherewith they have filled up many great Volumes: insomuch that the whole <hi>North</hi> in a manner makes a <hi>Grammatical</hi> war upon us, rather than a <hi>Spiritual:</hi> Whereas We have long since laid aside the study of <hi>Languages,</hi> ever since we overcame the <hi>Hebrews, Greeks,</hi> and <hi>Latines,</hi> and have made them submit themselves to <hi>Christianity,</hi> or else have devested them of the power of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging all Political and Sacerdotal Administrations; as it is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55946:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
with the <hi>Jews</hi> at this day. And therefore we intend not now to trouble our selves any further with <hi>petite Sophistical Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Nor ever shall have occasion to be troubled with <hi>them,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> our <hi>Historian</hi> prevail.</note> and <hi>Grammatical Quirks:</hi> but relying only upon our own strength of Wit, we let alone all prolix <hi>courses of Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plines,</hi> and the tediousness of writing huge Volumes: mean while that <hi>these men</hi> spend their time herein, and <hi>weary</hi> us out almost with their <hi>Cavillings,</hi> although they do not get the better of us. I conceive therefore, that <hi>these men</hi> should be <note place="margin">☜</note> taken off from <hi>these Grammatical Heresies,</hi> namely, by some <hi>New Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences,</hi> and <hi>such wherein we are excellent our selves.</hi> And to this end the <hi>King</hi> should erect certain <hi>Schools</hi> in all the principal Cities, wherein the <hi>Arabick</hi> tongue should be taught: that so by this means there may be such among his Subjects, as shall be able to Dispute with the <hi>Turks, Moors,</hi> and <hi>Persians,</hi> who by the use of that Tongue do spread their <hi>Mahometanisme,</hi> as we do <hi>Christianitie</hi> by the <hi>Latine</hi> Tongue; and so by <hi>these means</hi> our <hi>intestine wars</hi> may be laid aside, and our Arms turned against foreign enemies.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>There should be Schools also erected for the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">☜</note> and <hi>Astronomy,</hi> unto which these <hi>Northern</hi> people should be invited to come, by proposing Salaries for such of them, as shall apply themselves to the Discovering, and giving an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of such <hi>Starrs</hi> and <hi>Constellations,</hi> as are found in the other <hi>Hemisphear,</hi> in the <hi>new world.</hi> For by these means there would redound to the <hi>Spanish</hi> Empire both Honour and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. I would also have the Schools of the <hi>Old Philosophers</hi> to <note place="margin">☜</note> be opened again; as of the <hi>Platonists</hi> and <hi>Stoicks,</hi> and of the <note place="margin">And <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> and <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> too</note> 
                     <hi>Telesians,</hi> that so the people may be diverted from <hi>Theological Questions,</hi> and may apply themselves to study <hi>Questions</hi> of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy:</hi> for those come nearer to the <hi>Christian faith,</hi> than the Doctrine of <hi>Aristotle</hi> doth. Now the <hi>King</hi> in doing these things, shall sollow the example of <hi>Hercules,</hi> who to the end he might the more easily overcome <hi>Antaeus,</hi> drew him <note place="margin">☜</note> forth of his own Territories; and also of <hi>Cadmus,</hi> who brought over <hi>New Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences</hi> with him into <hi>Boeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia;</hi> and by means of the same, got to be Prince of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. And by taking of this course, the <hi>Principal</hi> among the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> when they shall see there is more to be gotten
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55946:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>there</hi> then <hi>here,</hi> forsaking their <hi>Heresies,</hi> will become Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders <note place="margin">☞</note> in the Sects of <hi>Philosophy</hi> and <hi>Astronomy.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>—There should also be erected publick <hi>work-houses</hi> for <note place="margin">☞</note> the exercises of <hi>Mechanical Arts,</hi> to which this people is exceeding apt: and so by this means will the Business of <hi>Navigation</hi> be much promoted, together with the skill of besieging Towns, and of taking them in by the use of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial <hi>Fire-works.</hi> By these means the <hi>People</hi> (probably) will be taken off from their <hi>False Religion,</hi> and <hi>divided one</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">☞</note> 
                     <hi>from another;</hi> to the great advantage of the Kingdome of <hi>Spain,</hi> to whom many will now come and tender their service: and his Empire, which of late hath been contemptible and hateful to the world, shall recover its antient Splendour and Honour.</q>
               </p>
               <p>These are the <hi>passages</hi> which I think I first accommodated to the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> and which served me as a <hi>Key</hi> to expound their <hi>History</hi> by: and although the <hi>indignation</hi> I conceived against Mr. <hi>Glanvill</hi> of the affronts he and his <hi>Assistants</hi> had put upon the <hi>Physicians</hi> was the <hi>first motive</hi> which put <hi>me</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>writing,</hi> yet it was a regard I had to the <hi>Religion</hi> and the <hi>Education of our Youth</hi> (which I found undermined by these <hi>Campanella's)</hi> which <hi>imboldened</hi> me never to <hi>lay aside</hi> my Pen. I was afraid lest our <hi>Virtuosi</hi> with their <hi>trinkets</hi> and <hi>experiments</hi> would serve <hi>this Nation</hi> such a trick as the <hi>Pyed-Piper</hi> at <hi>Hammel</hi> in the Dutchy of <hi>Brunswic</hi> did those Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants: <note place="margin">W<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rus d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Sect. 2.</note> He first played in the Town and all the <hi>Rats</hi> and <hi>Mice</hi> follow'd him, which He so destroyed: then He played again, and their <hi>Children</hi> followed him, and thence He lead them out of the Town unto an <hi>Hill,</hi> into which He went, and they followed him, and perished all. Some of these passages I have censured in my first book printed at <hi>Oxford;</hi> it being manifest, that without a Regard to those <hi>Popish</hi> Machinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, no man would have inserted any thing of <hi>such import</hi> which was no way necessary to the vindication of the <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuosi</hi> or matter intreated on.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:55946:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To his ever honoured Friend, Sir</hi> N. N.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ALthough the <hi>multiplicity</hi> of business arising from my <hi>practice</hi> in the Countrey, and the great inclinations I have to improve each <hi>vacant minute,</hi> in the prosecution of my <hi>studies,</hi> although these occasions render me not so <hi>civil</hi> to my friends by any entercourse of <hi>Letters,</hi> as I <hi>seemingly</hi> ought to be, yet do not they at all diminish my <hi>respects</hi> for them, so that they may as absolutely as ever dispose of my <hi>services,</hi> though the confirmation thereof be not daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd unto them with all that noise of <hi>ceremony</hi> and <hi>Flattery</hi> with which this <hi>impertinent age</hi> doth abound. Your Letter brought with it all those circumstances that could justly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dear it unto me; and I was infinitely satisfied to understand that I had so important a place in that <hi>memory</hi> which retains nothing <hi>vulgar</hi> and <hi>trivial:</hi> These sentiments alone were enough to transport me into some vanity, and place a greater value on my self than I know I merit, because you write, that is think, <hi>I have some;</hi> and I am almost ready to yield that to the <hi>opinion of your judgement</hi> that which I have many demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations against. I am pleas'd to understand that so many <hi>serious</hi> and <hi>real Patriots</hi> of this Kingdome do approve not only of my undertaking the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> but of my <hi>performances</hi> therein: what others, especially <hi>judicious</hi> and <hi>sober persons,</hi> say of us, is a thing no <hi>virtuous person</hi> ought to look upon with indifference: though the greatest comforts in all actions arise from that content which our own <hi>breasts</hi> afford us. My life hath been a continual scene of <hi>dangers,</hi> which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Poverty, Sickness, and other accidents
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55946:9"/>
invo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed me in, but though in a thousand misfortunes I have refl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>cted on my condition as <hi>irreleivable,</hi> yet of all the <hi>intrica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ies</hi> that ever I encountred, tho beginning of <hi>this Quarrel</hi> did represent unto me the <hi>worst</hi> and most <hi>perplexed</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> encountred: All the others appeared like the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, of a <hi>resistless Fate,</hi> this to depend upon my <hi>own election;</hi> All others did at once acquaint me with the whole prospect of the <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rd</hi> I was in, and my thoughts discovered unto me clearly what grounds I might relye upon for <hi>hopes,</hi> and what <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>casions</hi> I had to <hi>despair,</hi> and amidst these resentments I was prepared for any issue <hi>Providence</hi> would ordain me: but <hi>in this</hi> I could not any wayes imagino what might be the conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the attempt, whence to derive any <hi>assurance,</hi> or where to terminate my <hi>fears:</hi> so that I was forced to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all those <hi>melanchollick apprehensions,</hi> and to deduce my encourageme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ts from the <hi>necessity of the Action,</hi> and from that <hi>despair</hi> which made all troubles and even death it self pleasant, since I could make no other estimate of <hi>England,</hi> but that even the poor remains of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> amongst us were so imminently endangered, that I could not expect their <hi>long continuance,</hi> nor with patience think how to survive them. All men represented unto me the perils in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which I threw my self, but none moro than I foresaw my self: none had the confidence to imbolden me, many dissua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me: but in the whole affair I consulted the tranquility of my <hi>own mind,</hi> and determined upon that courso wherein I found the most <hi>content,</hi> not the most <hi>profit:</hi> and agreeable to the directions of that <hi>Hebrew</hi> Proverb, <hi>Though sixty Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours tender you an advice, yet reject not the dictates of your own breast,</hi> I fixed upon those resolutions which were most conformable to my Soul, and in which I found my <hi>internal peace</hi> best established: I left the conduct to God, whose glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was concern'd so highly, and bottomed my self upon this ground alone as to <hi>outward supports,</hi> that my design must be agreeable to all that regarded the interest of the <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> of this land, the welfare of the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> the happiness of <hi>this Generation</hi> and of <hi>Posterity:</hi> and instead of making particular friends (or matter of great <hi>uncertainty</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:55946:9"/>
now) I hoped that the particular concernments of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the two <hi>Universities,</hi> the <hi>Colledge</hi> of <hi>Physicians,</hi> and of all <hi>Artisans,</hi> would supply that defect. The <hi>History</hi> of the <hi>R. S.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Glanvills plus ultra,</hi> did fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish me with undenyable arguments of the <hi>common danger;</hi> and the general and constant <hi>discourses</hi> as well as <hi>deportment</hi> of the <hi>Comical Wits</hi> or <hi>Vertuosi</hi> were such, that no <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ss</hi> or <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> could create another representation of things. Sir, it is not unknown to you what influence <hi>Education</hi> hath upon any <hi>Government;</hi> that without a regard <hi>hereunto</hi> the best <hi>Laws</hi> become <hi>useless</hi> and <hi>ineffectual,</hi> thorough the contempt and malepertness of the Subjects: and the most noble designs of <hi>Princes</hi> frustrated for want of <hi>befitting instruments</hi> to carry them on: By the sole force of <hi>good Education</hi> sundry Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have subsisted, whose constitution hath been <hi>defective,</hi> and whose disturbances and calamities have been such as would have shatter'd into pieces and confusion any <hi>weaker foundation:</hi> of this <hi>Lycurgus</hi> took an especial care, and the paucity of his <hi>Laws</hi> was admirably supplyed by his diligence <hi>herein:</hi> and the neglect hereof is justly censured by <hi>Aristotle</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aristot.</hi> E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ic. l. 10. c. 9.</note> in other Republicks. Upon this account our prudent An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors, (knowing how much more untractable <hi>Northern people</hi> were than others, sacrificing upon any occasion their <hi>lives</hi> unto their <hi>passions)</hi> have been eminent in their cares for the educating of our <hi>Youth,</hi> Gentry and others, to <hi>such knowledge</hi> and <hi>customs</hi> as was necessary to the due honouring of <hi>God,</hi> and the welfare of the <hi>Nation</hi> and <hi>Government.</hi> From this care had our <hi>Universities</hi> their original, and that publick breeding in <hi>Free Schools:</hi> and the advantages are these, that by the <hi>Uniformity</hi> of the instruction mens minds may be better united and cemented together, (no material difference arising, nor each seeming to the other <hi>foolish</hi> and <hi>ridiculous,</hi> where all are inured to the <hi>same sentiments)</hi> and not only that confusion is prevented which <hi>private Tutors</hi> would occasion by insusing <hi>different</hi> and <hi>repugnant</hi> principles into the <hi>Youth,</hi> but even the deportment and inclinations of all becomes evident to the <hi>Magistrates</hi> and others, which best and most naturally discover themselves in their <hi>tender</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55946:10"/>
               <hi>anwary years,</hi> from whence the <hi>prudent</hi> can judge what to hope, or expect from them in their maturity, how to <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, distrust, confide</hi> in or <hi>employ them:</hi> the <hi>Tutors</hi> they have, the <hi>Books</hi> they converse with, the <hi>studies</hi> and <hi>usages</hi> which they like and dislike, are thereby known: and of those evil fruits which some men have afterwards produced, 'tis notorious that the first <hi>buds</hi> and <hi>bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ssoms</hi> were, or might have been observed during their continuance at the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities. Pardon a despised Peripatetick if I tell you that it is an opinion <hi>Aristotle</hi> betrays me into, that the source of all our evils, and the continuance of them, is derived from the neglect of <hi>publick Education:</hi> nor doth there appear to me any possibility of remedying thereof, or reconciling us by the establishment of <hi>new Laws</hi> (how <hi>penal</hi> soever) but by resetling a <hi>fitting Education:</hi> this <hi>dillgently</hi> pursued, would <hi>insensibly</hi> and <hi>infallibly</hi> atchieve that which no <hi>Laws</hi> will ever do where they are to encounter <hi>grown men,</hi> whose <hi>resent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> are <hi>violent,</hi> and their <hi>reasons weak</hi> especially as to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote consequences.</hi> This <hi>general advantage</hi> to the <hi>publick,</hi> was attended with <hi>another</hi> not of less importance: <hi>viz.</hi> that since the condition of our <hi>Nation</hi> and Monarchy requires that all be principled in the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> in opposition to <hi>Popery</hi> (the <hi>restoration</hi> of which would indanger the Title of our <hi>King</hi> to his <note place="margin">Let these Considerations (if others from P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ety seem contemptible) teach us wisdome before an absolute impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y to redr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ss our evils: Loave us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tion but despair, for not h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>g t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ly for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>een and prevented them.</note> 
               <hi>Crown,</hi> or render it <hi>feudatary</hi> and obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to <hi>foreign power,</hi> as any man that is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with <hi>History</hi> must know: it would also <hi>embroyl</hi> us in the restitution of <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> which as <hi>they</hi> make up the greatest part of <hi>most mens estates,</hi> so the rendition of them; if I can judge of the posture of <hi>England</hi> how, will be more <hi>facile</hi> than that of the <hi>Episcopal Revenue</hi> lately was) and in <hi>conformity</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> whilest <hi>custome, example,</hi> and <hi>uniform instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> would represent those <hi>ceremonies</hi> and <hi>habits</hi> as <hi>decent, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly</hi> and <hi>rational,</hi> which would otherwise seem <hi>uncouth,</hi> and <hi>phantastical:</hi> Besides these, it was a further security to our Government, that the <hi>Education</hi> there did qualifie men to a <hi>submission</hi> to and love of our <hi>Government:</hi> It being evident
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55946:10"/>
that the <hi>Paliticks</hi> of <hi>Aristotle</hi> suit admirably with our <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> and men are well prepared to own and support a <hi>reigle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which that intelligent <hi>Phylosopher</hi> so long ago repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented as the <hi>Idea of humane policy,</hi> in opposition to the <hi>Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nioral</hi> and <hi>absolute Monarchy.</hi> The <hi>Ethicks</hi> there are <hi>gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rous,</hi> and subservient to <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>civil prudence,</hi> and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>virtue:</hi> the <hi>Logick</hi> and <hi>Metaphysicks</hi> are so entwisted with the <hi>established Religion,</hi> and so requisite to the support of it against <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> that without a <hi>miracle</hi> the neglect <hi>hereof</hi> must bring a change in the <hi>former:</hi> even <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wisdome</hi> teacheth us that we must vary our <hi>Weapons</hi> and <hi>Militia</hi> according to what our <hi>enemies</hi> practise: thus when the world assumed <hi>Guns,</hi> we have been forced to abandon our <hi>Archery,</hi> and quit those <hi>fortifications</hi> which sufficed against all former approaches, since the <hi>battering Canon</hi> were introduced: the learning of the <hi>Sarracens</hi> prevailing on the minds of men <hi>endued with reason,</hi> the <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Ecclesiasticks</hi> were forced to Study <hi>School-divinity</hi> in opposition to them, and not to rely upon the sole support of <hi>Authority, Legends,</hi> and <hi>feigned Miracles:</hi> and whilst that <hi>Subtlety of reasoning</hi> and <hi>distinguishing</hi> continues amongst our <hi>Adversaries,</hi> 'tis no less than <hi>apparent madness</hi> to cast our <hi>Arms</hi> away, and desert those courses <hi>by which alone</hi> so great a part of the Nation is to be reduced, and <hi>Foreign encroachments</hi> prevented. The Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Learned Languages</hi> is so necessary to <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> and <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil History,</hi> and the understanding thereof (together with the <hi>Original Scripture)</hi> so requisite to our <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> that they must be <hi>enemies to both</hi> that discourage <hi>those Studies,</hi> and looked upon as such as manifestly go about to ruine their <hi>Native Countrey.</hi> With what <hi>facility</hi> are those <hi>Arguments</hi> solved in an <hi>Academical</hi> way, which perplex the <hi>ignorant?</hi> What <hi>sense</hi> do those <hi>terms</hi> bear to an <hi>understanding person</hi> which seem <hi>iusignificant</hi> and <hi>contradictious</hi> or <hi>non-sensical noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to those of <hi>lower intellectuals?</hi> What <hi>intricate cases</hi> are resolved, when it is made evident that their <hi>Authors</hi> are <hi>spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> or intended otherwise? As to that <hi>usual exception</hi> that 'tis an <hi>empty</hi> and <hi>mean employment</hi> for <hi>generous youth</hi> to be wasted in the studying of <hi>Languages,</hi> and <hi>chopping of Logick;</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:55946:11"/>
it arguos <hi>no judgement</hi> in those that use it: for nothing is <hi>mean, despicable,</hi> and <hi>empty,</hi> without which so <hi>high and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant benefits</hi> cannot be attained: By the <hi>same reason,</hi> the exercises of the old <hi>Romans</hi> in the <hi>Campus Martius,</hi> the <hi>Palastra</hi> and <hi>Olympic</hi> games, the modern <hi>Training,</hi> and <hi>Cudgel-playing,</hi> or <hi>shooting at Butts,</hi> must be exploded; yet no <hi>wise man</hi> will assent hereunto: and it is evident, that those <hi>other studies</hi> are as <hi>subservient</hi> to the ends proposed in <hi>them,</hi> as those <hi>others</hi> are to what is designed <hi>therein.</hi> All these so <hi>considerable advantages</hi> which our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> derives from <hi>Academical</hi> education, are designed to be overthrown by the <hi>Historian,</hi> and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon entertainments of the <hi>Virtuosi</hi> consist in debauching our <hi>Nobility, Gentry,</hi> and all the <hi>youth</hi> from <hi>those studies,</hi> as <hi>useless, empty,</hi> and <hi>impertinent:</hi> and how <hi>just,</hi> how <hi>necessary</hi> ought that <hi>undertaking</hi> to seem <hi>universally</hi> which hath no other end than the <hi>silencing</hi> of these <hi>Comediants?</hi> They magnisie, in opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all other knowledge, the <hi>Experimental Philosophy:</hi> were the thing <hi>well modelled,</hi> managed by <hi>discreet persons,</hi> and the <hi>Question</hi> rightly stated, there would be <hi>no controversie</hi> betwixt us: the pursuit thereof would creat us <hi>some profit,</hi> and much of <hi>pleasure:</hi> but whosoever accustomes <hi>Children</hi> or <hi>Youth</hi> to those <hi>divertisements,</hi> shall never breed up any <hi>eminent personage,</hi> nor reduce them afterwards to <hi>serious</hi> and <hi>sedentary studies:</hi> as daily observation shews: And whosoever asserts that such <q>innocent works will certainly have a more sure effect in the composing <note place="margin">History of the <hi>R. S.</hi> pag 342.</note> and purifying mens thoughts, than all the rigid precepts of the Stoical, or the empty distinctions of the Peripatetick Moralists:</q> it is certain he never was acquainted with the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> or <hi>Peripateticks,</hi> but is a <hi>Virtuosi.</hi> I prosess some shame to think that any man should oppose this <hi>Mechanical education</hi> to the <hi>other,</hi> and make use of it to disparage that <hi>Moral disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> which instructs us in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> nature of <hi>virtue</hi> and <hi>vioe,</hi> of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stributive</hi> and <hi>Commutative Justice: humane actings,</hi> and the <hi>due course,</hi> as well as <hi>exorbitances of our passions:</hi> But to prefer the advancement of <hi>such Experiments</hi> before the most <hi>renowned A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>y.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>of the best Princes,</hi> is so strange a passage, that I only say, 'tis well the <hi>Author</hi> thereof is an enemy to, and unacquainted <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in</hi> More Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 37.</note> with <hi>University-Learning.</hi> 
               <q>Non est conveniens proportio inter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55946:11"/>
res differentes specie. Non enim oportet dicore quod hominis perfectio est tanta, vel major equi perfectione.</q> All that is said about the erecting of <hi>Mechanical</hi> or <hi>Sensible Philosophy of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> is but empty talk: <hi>Humane nature,</hi> is not capable of <hi>such atchievements:</hi> 'tis evidontly impossible to attain any <hi>exact knowledge</hi> of the surface of our whole <hi>Terrestrial Globe:</hi> and the <hi>depths of the Earth and water,</hi> are no less <hi>unsearchable:</hi> and as to the <hi>component particles,</hi> their <hi>nature, figure, motions,</hi> and <hi>combinations</hi> are known only to the <hi>Deity:</hi> so that no prudent person is to be amused with these <hi>Rosicrucian</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses: As to the collection of the <hi>History of Nature,</hi> were it not <hi>universal,</hi> it might be of <hi>some use,</hi> and afford not only mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the <hi>railleurs,</hi> but other pretty <hi>illustrations</hi> and <hi>simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes</hi> for the <hi>Rhetoricians;</hi> but I must here complain of them for making us <hi>false relations,</hi> which will create us more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than if they had <hi>done nothing:</hi> and also for this, that since <hi>these men</hi> take upon them to upbraid all the <hi>Aristotelians</hi> and <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ians</hi> for not attending unto <hi>Experiments,</hi> yet do they do little more than steal the <hi>Experiments</hi> of others, and publish them as <hi>their</hi> own, without ever referring to <hi>Authors,</hi> except an <hi>ingenious Virtuos</hi> be concern'd: would these persons be pleased to declare solemnly unto the world that they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand nothing of <hi>antient or modern Writers</hi> (you may see by <hi>Aristotles</hi> gravitation of the <hi>Ayre,</hi> that they never read <hi>him:</hi> nor <hi>Galen,</hi> or <hi>Pliny,</hi> or <hi>Aristotle,</hi> who speak of <hi>Apothecaries</hi> such as <hi>ours)</hi> it were but <hi>candour</hi> in them, and the best way to secure their credit from being thought <hi>Plagiaries</hi> and <hi>Cheats:</hi> so, if they would but get any one to teach them <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> and <hi>Greek,</hi> it would have saved <hi>me</hi> some trouble, as you will see in my <hi>Animadversions</hi> on their <hi>History:</hi> In fine, I doubt not but to make it plain to all the world, that some ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been so <hi>negligent,</hi> most so <hi>ignorant,</hi> we can expect no great things from <hi>them,</hi> nor are to be concern'd for <hi>them</hi> at all in an affair of such importance as the change of <hi>our Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> They might have appeased <hi>me,</hi> would they have called in <hi>those two books;</hi> but since they would not do that, I suspect their intentions, and that they drive on <hi>Campanella's</hi> project: <hi>why should they else have scrupled at it?</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55946:12"/>
Is it below <hi>them</hi> to <hi>acknowledge their errours,</hi> whereas they blame the <hi>Peripateticks</hi> for refusing to confess <hi>theirs?</hi> I am inform'd <hi>by you</hi> that <hi>they say many of my citations are false</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but no man <hi>of reading</hi> will say so: they were <hi>true</hi> when they went from <hi>me;</hi> if the Printer have mistook, I cannot help it: a <hi>Stratagem</hi> of <hi>theirs</hi> hinder'd me from correcting the <hi>Press:</hi> I know some books are <hi>misnamed,</hi> but such <hi>Scholars</hi> as they pretend to be (and who offer to tell the <hi>Parliament</hi> of what in <hi>each invention</hi> is <hi>new</hi> or <hi>old)</hi> can easily correct that: as where I cit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Scheinir: ros. Vagin:</hi> any ordinary man can tell it should be <hi>rosa Ursin:</hi> and so for other defaults: but if the <hi>poor Devils</hi> cannot tell how to apprehend such <hi>Errata,</hi> if they will send to <hi>me,</hi> I will rectifie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ny <hi>citation,</hi> rather then they should give them a <hi>needless trouble</hi> in denying it. There is not <hi>one allegation</hi> that I have not consulted my self, except what relates to <hi>Pecqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> and <hi>Mersennus:</hi> and neither of those <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> were they injured in; but my books being burnt at <hi>London,</hi> those two pieces I wanted: but as to <hi>Pecquet,</hi> if you look into <hi>him:</hi> you will find not only the <hi>gravitation of the Atmosphear,</hi> but the <hi>Elasticity</hi> and comparison with a <hi>Fleece of Wooll,</hi> and Experiment of the <hi>Barometer</hi> (not the <hi>non-sensical appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on)</hi> related as <hi>amply</hi> as in any of the <hi>Virtuosi:</hi> and it is in this manner that <hi>I have injured</hi> them. But they must say something to preserve their credit; yet have I <hi>a thousand faults</hi> more to charge them with: but I reserve them for <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Treatise,</hi> which if <hi>they do not submit</hi> to the two <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities,</hi> and the <hi>Colledge</hi> of <hi>Physicians,</hi> I will publish. In truth, no <hi>Physician</hi> can joyn with <hi>them,</hi> or give <hi>them</hi> any counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance without <hi>betraying his Paculty</hi> to most <hi>unworthy Empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks.</hi> It is intollerable that a company of men that know not what belongs to a <hi>Disease,</hi> or <hi>Remedy,</hi> should arrogate as they do. I have already shew'd the long use of <hi>Ivy-berries</hi> for the <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; Myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> de Catha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>co <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I do not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>A. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he adds not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Plague:</hi> this they bring (out of <hi>Parkinson!)</hi> for an <hi>Arcanum!</hi> The <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nar</hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ls as to the <hi>main ingredient</hi> was publick in <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelius</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> but the making of the <hi>Luna Catharti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> into <hi>Pills</hi> with <hi>white-bread crumb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> is their <hi>invention<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> And if the additional <hi>crumbs of bread</hi> works not the <hi>miracles</hi> (as indeed neither do the <hi>Pills</hi> answer expect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tion at all) neither
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55946:12"/>
is the addition of <hi>Nitre</hi> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>w, nor the <hi>discovery</hi> above what we knew before. I dare undertake to make an <hi>Experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator</hi> of any insipid <hi>Aristotelian</hi> at <hi>this rate,</hi> let him but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to <hi>other mens discoveries:</hi> a <hi>little wit</hi> and a <hi>brazen-face</hi> will serve to that purpose, <hi>without studying.</hi> As to what you farther add, that they decry me for an <hi>Atheist,</hi> and one of <hi>no Religion:</hi> First, I reply that it doth not become <hi>any of them</hi> to upbraid <hi>me</hi> therewith; or if that procedure be excusable, it admits only of <hi>this Apology,</hi> that being to Character a man <hi>altogether unknown</hi> to most, and not <hi>intimate</hi> with any of them, they make <hi>themselves</hi> the <hi>Original,</hi> and so <hi>coppy</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> out <hi>thence:</hi> this is a <hi>fallacy</hi> our <hi>senses</hi> commonly betray us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; for the things which we are unacquainted with farther than by report, or <hi>deceitful Telescopes,</hi> we presently fancy to <hi>resemble</hi> more or less <hi>those objects we daily converse with:</hi> and the <hi>Virtuosi</hi> being <hi>sensible Phylosophers,</hi> act according to <hi>their principles</hi> herein, though not according to <hi>real truth.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, if ever my <hi>tongue</hi> (I am sure my <hi>actions</hi> have not) ever given any occasion to <hi>conjecture so of me,</hi> I beg pardon of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>world</hi> for it: but the occasion of such reports was rather from the <hi>malice</hi> of men, than that they had any ground for it; unless this <hi>were one,</hi> that during the <hi>late times,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I would joyn with <hi>no party</hi> in a <hi>Church,</hi> they imagined that I could be of <hi>no Religion;</hi> whereas I did no more than <hi>Chrysostome</hi> and others before me: A second enducement may have been a custom natural unto me, to defend the <hi>absent</hi> or <hi>depressed,</hi> or <hi>excuse them</hi> against the <hi>censures of illiterate Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries:</hi> other ground I know none, and it is not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by any man from any of my <hi>present writings</hi> I am sure; but the contrary: And it is strange that men pretending to a respect for <hi>our Church,</hi> should thus <hi>conspire</hi> to defame me for so <hi>seasonable</hi> and <hi>powerful a defence thereof:</hi> it being obvious to see that <hi>hereby</hi> I recede from my <hi>Temporal interest,</hi> which <hi>they</hi> know might be better made up by <hi>open debauchery, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency as to Religion, flattering</hi> and <hi>lying:</hi> not to mention the <hi>present</hi> and <hi>future dangers</hi> I run into by this attempt, the final issue whereof is scarce likely to antedate my death: If a profession of the <hi>Protestant Religion, Union with the Church
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55946:13"/>
of</hi> England, <hi>an unblamable life,</hi> and the <hi>hazards</hi> I now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter <hi>voluntarily,</hi> cannot justifie me against <hi>these imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> let them produce <hi>as much</hi> in <hi>their behalfs,</hi> and acquaint me what <hi>more</hi> is requisite, and they shall find I will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline any <hi>fitting testimony</hi> whereby to undeceive <hi>them:</hi> so that they ought not to upbraid a man who appears principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned for the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> with such a <hi>Calumny,</hi> which might with great shew of justice be fixed upon all the Abettours of that <hi>History</hi> of <hi>theirs.</hi> As for the rest you write about, I value it not: those <hi>untruths</hi> are easily refuted; and as yet I cannot believe that they will avow <hi>them</hi> in Print: Let us leave them Sir, <hi>to talk a little</hi> as yet; they have been used to spend their discourses in <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of one another;</hi> be <hi>contented</hi> that you have some <hi>new discourse:</hi> would you have <hi>them</hi> so soon to <hi>hold their peace?</hi> I know a Gentleman who <hi>in the wars</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> at one blow cut off a <hi>man's head;</hi> and the <hi>headless trunk</hi> clapp'd spurs to the horse sides and rid about <hi>ten yards after:</hi> Let these <hi>loosers</hi> talk a little; and then <hi>retire</hi> and <hi>work,</hi> and so cure <hi>their passions</hi> (according as Mr. <hi>Sprat</hi> adviseth) and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to <hi>regain their credit,</hi> which I think is <hi>irrecoverably</hi> lost, if others, <hi>by my example,</hi> will pursue <hi>their failings.</hi> As to his <hi>Majesty,</hi> he cannot suffer when these <hi>Spirits</hi> dis-appear, who like those <hi>Phantasmes</hi> in the <hi>Mines</hi> hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> made a great shew of <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>doing much,</hi> but upon enquiry no such performances are <hi>really found:</hi> All posterity will celebrate the glory of his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to improve the <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>trading</hi> of this Nation: and he is possessed of so many <hi>Royal Virtues</hi> that render him the object of all <hi>our esteem,</hi> that the <hi>removal of these</hi> now will not <hi>derogate</hi> from, but <hi>illustrate</hi> his Renown, and confirm <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the Reverence of his <hi>generosity</hi> and their <hi>detestable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness:</hi> But I doubt I trespass too much upon your patience, and that you are tyred, as I am with <hi>writing,</hi> but not with <hi>any professions</hi> that becomes</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most humble Servant
Hen. Stubbe.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Warwick</hi> June 2<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1670.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:55946:13"/>
            <head>The Postscript.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE <hi>News</hi> you write me about Dr. <hi>Merrett</hi> did at first a little surprise me, and had I not during this last year been accustomed to the <hi>puny Stratagems</hi> of the <hi>Virtuosi,</hi> I should have wondered much to understand that I was entitled to the <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> or that <hi>Apologie for Apothecaries to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice Physick.</hi> But the <hi>Comediants</hi> finding their anger insig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant against me, by reason of the advantages which <hi>their ignorance</hi> had given me over them, have ascribed unto me a <hi>book</hi> which admits of an <hi>easy reply,</hi> and which enterferes with the <hi>Colledge of Physicians,</hi> that so they might seem to <hi>bassle</hi> and <hi>inodiate</hi> me at once in the judgement of that <hi>profession</hi> for which I seem concern'd. I cannot make any particular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, not having seen <hi>his book:</hi> but if Dr. <hi>Merrett</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulted the <hi>principal Apothecaries,</hi> I doubt not but <hi>some of them</hi> could have given him an account of my intentions, and how different my sentiments were from those of <hi>that Authour:</hi> and it was easie for him to learn that I was not the <hi>penner</hi> or <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prover</hi> of the other piece. I writ to some of the Company of <hi>Apothecaries</hi> desiring them to compose the growing <hi>fewd</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them and the <hi>Colledge,</hi> and told them that I neither could nor would encourage them against that <hi>Illustrious As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly;</hi> that it was the interest of <hi>Physicians</hi> to employ Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, as a <hi>distinct profession;</hi> and that it was the <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of <hi>States</hi> that it should be so: that I could deduce the difference of the <hi>employments</hi> thorough Antient and Modern <hi>Greece,</hi> as well as <hi>Rome:</hi> and that the reasons to be alledged against <hi>Physicians</hi> prepairing their <hi>own Medicaments</hi> were such as admitted of <hi>no answer,</hi> nor <hi>evasion</hi> amongst <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:55946:14"/>
men: but that I could never <hi>invent</hi> or meet with any arguments that could induce me to allow of <hi>practicing Apothecaries;</hi> and that I understood so well the <hi>extent</hi> and <hi>difficulty</hi> of my <hi>profession,</hi> that (however they might in <hi>some cases</hi> prosper) I could never defend that <hi>assertion.</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired them to consider that if any <hi>heats</hi> or <hi>indignities</hi> had passed from the <hi>Colledge</hi> towards them, it was their <hi>wisdom</hi> to <hi>pass them by,</hi> and not to abandon their <hi>important concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to indulge any <hi>passion:</hi> that the effect of this <hi>contest</hi> would be, that the impertinent <hi>Virtuosi</hi> and insolent <hi>Quack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salvers</hi> would carry away all the <hi>advantage:</hi> to conclude, there were many defaults needed regulation <hi>in them,</hi> that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the <hi>Physicians</hi> in general would be prejudiced by <hi>this dispute,</hi> yet so many <hi>eminent persons</hi> would continue <hi>famous,</hi> as might divert the Storm upon the heads of the <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and if the <hi>Colledge</hi> would joyn effectually therein, the <hi>project</hi> is not <hi>difficult,</hi> though I would not intimate it. I did therefore earnestly recommend unto their considerations an <hi>union,</hi> and that they would not delude themselves that they could prosecute <hi>their Trades</hi> long, is that <hi>famed body of men</hi> did resolve against <hi>them,</hi> with whose <hi>determinations</hi> I did not doubt but all <hi>intelligent practitioners</hi> in the <hi>Countrey</hi> and <hi>Counties</hi> would comply: but I hoped we should not be put upon <hi>those extreams.</hi> I advised them to reflect upon our <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemies</hi> the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> and see if <hi>they</hi> were not the <hi>principal Incendiaries:</hi> that all the books that had been yet written on <hi>that Subject</hi> proceeded from <hi>them;</hi> and that I look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on it as a design of <hi>theirs</hi> to aggrandise themselves upon the <hi>ruine</hi> of the <hi>Colledge</hi> (a thing they have alwayes endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) and <hi>Apothecaries:</hi> that there wanted not of <hi>them</hi> who purposed to erect a <hi>Laboratory</hi> and <hi>Shop,</hi> whence all should be furnished <hi>cheaper</hi> and <hi>better</hi> than now, as to <hi>general Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decines,</hi> provided <hi>they</hi> would act <hi>themselves</hi> in the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and frequent <hi>Medicaments:</hi> that if they proceeded here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the <hi>Virtuosi</hi> might facilitate their <hi>design,</hi> though their <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> and <hi>unfaithfulness</hi> be such that all men ought to oppose <hi>these Projectors.</hi> Upon this account I did largely handle that Question, <hi>Whether Physicians ought to make their own Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines?</hi> which I resolved in the <hi>Negative,</hi> and urged all those
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55946:14"/>
arguments (with several illustrations) which have hithert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ayed with <hi>prudent Governours</hi> and <hi>Physicians</hi> to establish the <hi>received usage:</hi> but I protested against any encouragement for <hi>Apothecaries to practice.</hi> I answer'd all that Dr. <hi>Merrett</hi> had alledged, and shewed his <hi>intollerable ignorance</hi> in that book; and if we might take an estimate of <hi>his parts</hi> from <hi>that writing,</hi> 'twas manifest he might better imploy his time in studying the <hi>method of Physick,</hi> than composing <hi>Medicaments:</hi> that after 30. years practice 'twas evident he understood not the <hi>Rudiments of that noble Science,</hi> nor could <hi>state a case</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. As for Dr. <hi>Goddard,</hi> who had writ more <hi>warily</hi> and with <hi>greater prudence,</hi> I only dissented from him in the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of Apothecaries,</hi> and treated him as a <hi>Physician</hi> whom I pittyed for being mixed with so <hi>illiterate a company.</hi> This was the purport of my Treatise, which was joyned with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>miscellaneous Discourse</hi> about the <hi>errours</hi> and <hi>cheats</hi> of the <hi>Virtuosi;</hi> and the pernicious influence they would have ere long upon <hi>all Trades</hi> and <hi>Professions,</hi> when they had more <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected</hi> them: that they began with the <hi>rectifying Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> but where they would <hi>end</hi> I did not know: that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooved <hi>all men</hi> to combine against <hi>them,</hi> the tendency of whose <hi>designs</hi> was so <hi>satal</hi> and <hi>malignant:</hi> that I hoped the <hi>Physicians</hi> would consult their <hi>common interest</hi> in opposition to the <hi>Thomsons</hi> and <hi>Odowdes,</hi> &amp;c. and act with that moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which became <hi>wisemen,</hi> &amp; who were tender of continuing the <hi>renown of their Faculty,</hi> which would suddenly else de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve into the hands of <hi>Empiricks;</hi> and demean themselves with that <hi>moderation</hi> which might end in an accord with the <hi>Apothecaries:</hi> that this quarrel was <hi>inconsiderable,</hi> and indeed (as Dr. <hi>Merrett</hi> confesseth) of no <hi>longer continuance</hi> then that of the R. S. and would receive a <hi>period</hi> with <hi>their overthrow;</hi> which not only all <hi>Doctors,</hi> but all <hi>good men</hi> ought to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; that the <hi>disasters</hi> of the late <hi>Dutch</hi> Warr, the <hi>Plague,</hi> and <hi>Fire of London</hi> were less inconveniences than <hi>their perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity:</hi> that <hi>these calamities</hi> admitted of <hi>some remedy</hi> here after; but the <hi>evils</hi> they are likely to occasion <hi>us,</hi> would never be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by any <hi>humane prudence;</hi> and I doubted whether <hi>God</hi> would support us by <hi>his providence,</hi> when they had debauched the Nation from all <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Morality,</hi> as well as <hi>civil Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:55946:15"/>
This was the subject of <hi>that Book,</hi> which I doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> not but will be approved by all <hi>judicious persons:</hi> and the <hi>Colledge</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> see that I can write against Dr. <hi>Merrett</hi> without derogating <hi>from them;</hi> or rather that my intendments were to <hi>support them,</hi> and not dis-serve the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> in the least. I intend to make it publick in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term: the passage of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panella</hi> being taken out thence, hath occasioned that <hi>breach</hi> in it which I have not leisure now to redress: and perhaps I may call those other writings of the <hi>Virtuosi</hi> to an examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which have been the principal cause of all <hi>these contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies,</hi> and which if they be not refuted, 'tis in vai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to attack the <hi>Medela Medecine, Mainwairing,</hi> &amp;c. They must blame <hi>themselves,</hi> not <hi>me,</hi> for any undertaking of this nature; <hi>ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prudence</hi> would have inabled <hi>them</hi> to foresee the <hi>issue</hi> of <hi>those kind of writings;</hi> and a <hi>proportionate candour</hi> now would induce them to <hi>retract them,</hi> without enforcing me to shew how many <hi>unreasonable tryals</hi> they put <hi>us</hi> upon; how many <hi>impertinences</hi> they suggest unto us; how <hi>delusory</hi> their <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ments</hi> are; how 'tis their usual practice to vouch those things for <hi>new discoveries</hi> which we very well <hi>knew before,</hi> and to which if <hi>they were strangers,</hi> it is because they were not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the practice of the most <hi>eminent Physicians.</hi> Let them therefore hence forward permit the <hi>Physicians</hi> to be Judges of their <hi>own Science,</hi> and give them the credit best to understand <hi>their own deficiencies,</hi> and the occasions of any failours in <hi>their practice.</hi> The <hi>blind</hi> may as well judge of <hi>colours,</hi> the <hi>insensible</hi> concerning the objects of <hi>feeling,</hi> as the <hi>Virtuosi</hi> of <hi>Physick.</hi> This is no knowledge that ariseth from <hi>natural wit</hi> alone: <hi>Fancy</hi> without <hi>judgement, reading,</hi> and <hi>observation</hi> will not enable them hereunto: This is a performance <hi>too great</hi> for the <hi>Merretts</hi> and the <hi>Sydenhams:</hi> as I shall shew hereafter; and as little agreeing with Dr. <hi>Sprat;</hi> or Mr. <hi>Glawvill,</hi> whose abilities in matters relating to <hi>their profession</hi> are so contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that 'twere <hi>folly</hi> to expect <hi>much</hi> from them <hi>where they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess not.</hi> I have not time to enlarge farther, being now em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed <hi>otherwise,</hi> and having appointed to spend the next week or two at <hi>Bath</hi> in attendance of a Neighbouring Patient.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>agley</hi> June 14, 1670.</dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:55946:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
