<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons of the present judgement of the Vniversity of Oxford concerning The Solemne League and Covenant, The Negative Oath, The Ordinances concerning discipline and vvorship : approved by generall consent in a full convocation, 1, Jun. 1647, and presented to consideration.</title>
            <title>Judicium Universitatis Oxoniensis. English</title>
            <author>Sanderson, Robert, 1587-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-03">2003-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62025</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183228</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12602983</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12602983</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64210</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A62025)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64210)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 702:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons of the present judgement of the Vniversity of Oxford concerning The Solemne League and Covenant, The Negative Oath, The Ordinances concerning discipline and vvorship : approved by generall consent in a full convocation, 1, Jun. 1647, and presented to consideration.</title>
                  <title>Judicium Universitatis Oxoniensis. English</title>
                  <author>Sanderson, Robert, 1587-1663.</author>
                  <author>Zouch, Richard, 1590-1661.</author>
                  <author>Langbaine, Gerard, 1609-1658.</author>
                  <author>University of Oxford.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Stated by Wood to have been drawn up by Dr. Robert Sanderson in what referred to reason and conscience, and by Dr. Richard Zouche in the legal part, with the help of certain [other] delegates [including Gerard Langbaine.]"--cf. Madan 1926.</note>
                  <note>Translation of: Judicium Universitatis Oxoniensis.</note>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>Reprinted as an appendix to Walton's Life of Sanderson.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 35.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>University of Oxford --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643)</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-12</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64210:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64210:1"/>
            <p>REASONS
Of the present judgement of
the Vniversity of OXFORD,
<hi>CONCERNING</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>The Solemne League and Covenant.</item>
                  <item>The Negative Oath.</item>
                  <item>The Ordinances concerning Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline
and VVorship.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Approved by generall consent in a full
Convocation, 1. Iun. 1647.
<hi>AND
Presented to Consideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:64210:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64210:2"/>
            <head>A Solemn League and Covenant, for
Reformation, and defence of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
the honour and happinesse of
the King, and the Peace and Safety
of the three Kingdomes, England,
Scotland, and Ireland.</head>
            <p>WE Noblemen, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Citizens, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesses,
Ministers of the Gospell, and Commons of all sorts
in the Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of God living under one King, and being of one Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
having before our eyes the glory of God, and the advancement of the
Kingdome of our Lord and Saviour Iesus Christ, the honour and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse
of the Kings Majestie, and His Posterity, and the true pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Lybertie, Safetie, and Peace of the Kingdoms wherein every
ones private condition is included, and calling to mind the treacherous
and bloudy plots, Conspiracies, Attempts, and practices of the Enemies
of God against the true Religion, and Professors thereof in all places,
especially in these three Kingdomes, ever since the Reformation of
Religion, and how much their rage, power, and presumption are of
late, and at this time increased and exercised; whereof the deplorable
estate of the Church and Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the distressed estate of the
Church and Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and the dangerous estate of the
Church and Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> are present and publick Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies;
We have now at last, (after other meanes of supplication, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrance,
Protestations, and Sufferings) for the preservation of our
selves and our Religion from utter ruine and destruction, according
to the commendable practice of these Kingdomes in former times, and
the Example of Gods People in other Nations; after mature delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
resolved and determined to enter into a mutuall and solemne
League and Covenant, wherein we all subscribe, and each one of us
for himselfe with our hands lifted up to the most High God, do
swear:</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:64210:3"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>THat we shall sincerely, really, and constantly, through the
Grace of God, endeavour in our severall places and callings,
the preservation of the Reformed Religion in the Church of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> in Doctrine, Worship, Discipline and Government,
against our common Enemies; The Reformation of Religion
in the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> in Doctrine, Worship,
Discipline and Government, according to the Word of God, and
the example of the best reformed Churches: And shall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
to bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdomes, to
the nearest conjunction and uniformity in Religion, Confession
of Faith, Form of Church Government, Directory for Worship
and Catechizing; That we and our posterity after us may as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren
live in Faith and Love, and the Lord may delight to dwell
in the midst of us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>That we shall in like manner, without respect of persons, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
the extirpation of Popery, Prelacy, (that is, Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
by Archbishops, Bishops, their Chancellours and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missaries,
Deans, Deans and Chapters, Archdeacons, and all
other Ecclesiasticall Officers depending on that Hierarchy) Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition,
Heresie, Schisme, Profanenesse, and whatsoever shall
be found to be contrary to sound Doctrine, and the power of
Godlinesse; lest we partake in other mens sinnes, and thereby be
in danger to receive of their plagues, and that the Lord may be
one, and his Name one in the three Kingdomes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>We shall with the same sincerity, reallity and constancy, in our
severall Vocations, endeavour with our estates and lives, mutual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to preserve the Rights and Privileges of the Parliaments, and
the Liberties of the Kingdomes, and to preserve and defend the
Kings Majesties person and authority, in the preservation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
of the true Religion, and Liberties of the Kingdomes, that
the world may bear witnesse with our consciences of our Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
and that we have no thoughts or intentions to diminish His
Majesties just power and greatness:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:64210:3"/>
               <head>IIII.</head>
               <p>We shall also with all faithfullnesse endeavour the discovery
of all such as have been, or shall be Incendiaries, Malignants, or
evill Instruments, by hindring the Reformation of Religion, divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
the King from his people, or one of the Kingdomes from
another, or making any faction or parties amongst the people, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to this League and Covenant, that they may be brought to
publick triall, and receive condigne punishment, as the degree
of their offences shall require or deserve, or the supream Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories
of both Kingdomes respectively, or others having power
from them for that effect, shall judge convenient.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>And whereas the happinesse of a blessed Peace between these
Kingdomes, denied in former times to our progenitours, is by
the good providence of God granted unto us, and hath been
lately concluded, and setled by both Parliaments, we shall each
one of us, according to our place and interest endeavour that they
may remain conjoyned in a firm Peace and Union to all posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
And that Justice may be done upon the wilfull opposers
thereof, in manner expressed in the precedent Articles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>We shall also according to our places and callings in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
cause of Religion, Liberty and Peace of the Kingdomes, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist
and defend all those that enter into this League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
in the maintaining and pursuing thereof, and shall not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
our selves directly or indirectly by whatsoever combination,
perswasion or terrour to be divided and withdrawn from this
bles<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Union and Conjunction, whether to make defection to the
contrary part, or to give our selves to a detestable indifferencie or
neutrality in this cause, which so much concerneth the glory of
God, the good of the Kingdoms and the honour of the King;
but shall all the dayes of our lives zealously and constantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
therein, against all opposition, &amp; promote the same according
to our power, against all lets and impediments whatsoever; and
what we are not able our selves to suppress or overcome, we shall
<pb facs="tcp:64210:4"/>
reveal &amp; make known, that it may be timely prevented or remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;
All which we shall do as in the sight of God.</p>
               <p>And because these Kingdoms are guilty of many sinnes and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations
against God, and his Son Iesus Christ, as is too manifest by our
present distresses and dangers the fruits thereof; We professe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
before God and the world, our unfained desire to be humbled for
our owne sins, and for the sins of these Kingdoms, especially that
we have not as we ought, valued the inestimable benefit of the Gospel,
that we have not laboured for the puritie and power thereof, and that
we have not endeavoured to receive Christ in our hearts, nor to walke
worthy of him in our lives, which are the causes of other sinnes and
transgressions so much abounding amongst us; And our true and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained
purpose, desire, and endeavour for our selves, and all others un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
our power and charge, both in publick and in private, in all duties
we owe to God and man, to amend our lives, and each one to goe before
another in the example of a reall Reformation, that the Lord may turn
away his wrath and heavy indignation, and establish these Churches
and Kingdoms in truth and peace. And this Covenant we make in
the presence of Almighty God the searcher of all hearts, with a true
intention to perform the same, as we shall answer at that great day,
when the secrets of all hearts shall be disclosed. Most humbly beseech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Lord to strengthen us by his holy Spirit for this end, and to blesse
our desires and proceedings with such successe, as may be deliverance
and safety to his people, and encouragement to other Christian Churches
groaning under, or in danger of the yoke of Antichristian tyrannie; to
joyn in the same, or like Association and Covenant, to the glory of God,
the enlargement of the Kingdome of Iesus Christ, and the peace and
tranquility of Christian Kingdoms and Common-wealths.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:64210:4"/>
            <head>The Negative Oath.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I A. B.</hi> Doe sweare from my heart, that I
will not directly, nor indirectly, adhere un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
or willingly assist the King in this War,
or in this Cause, against the Parliament, nor
any Forces raised without the consent of
the two Houses of Parliament, in this Cause
or Warre: And I doe likewise sweare, that
my comming and submitting my selfe under
the Power and Protection of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
is without any manner of Designe
whatsoever, to the prejudice of the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
of this present Parliament, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the direction, privity, or advice of the
King, or any of his Councell, or Officers,
other then what I have now made knowne.
So helpe me God, and the contents of this
Booke.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:64210:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64210:5"/>
            <head>Reasons why the Vniversity of Oxford
cannot submit to the Covenant, the
Negative Oath, the Ordinance concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
Discipline and Directory mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
in the late Ordinance of Parliament
for the Visitation of that place.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas by an Ordinance of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
assembled in Parliament, for the Visitation
and Reformation of the University of <hi>Oxford</hi>
lately published, power is given to certain persons
therein named as Visitors, to enquire concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
those of the said University that neglect to
take the Solemne League and Covenant, and the Negative Oath
being tendred unto them, and likewise concerning those that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
the execution of the Ordinances of Parliament concerning
the Discipline and Directory, or shall not promote or cause the
same to be put in execution according to their severall places and
callings, We the Masters, Scholars, and other Officers and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
of the said University, not to judge the Consciences of others,
but to cleare our selves before God and the world from all sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion
of Obstinacie, whilst we discharge our own, present to
consideration the true reasons of our present judgment concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the said Covenant, Oath, and Ordinances: Expecting so
much Justice, and hoping for so much Charity, as either not to
be pressed to conforme to what is required in any the premisses,
further then our present judgements will warrant us; or not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
for the refusing so to doe, without cleare and reall sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
given to our just scruples.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64210:6"/>
               <head>§. I.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the Preface to the Covenant.</head>
               <p>THe Exceptions against the Introductory Preface to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
although we insist not much upon, because it may be
said to be no part of the Covenant: yet among the things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
contained, the acknowledgment whereof is implicitely requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
of every Covenanter,
<list>
                     <item>1. We are not able to say, <hi>that the rage, power, and presumption of
the enemies of God</hi> (in the sense there intended) <hi>is at this time
increased.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Nor can truly affirme that we had used, or given consent
to any <hi>Supplication</hi> or <hi>Remonstrance</hi> to the purposes therein
expressed.</item>
                     <item>3. Nor doe conceive the entring into such a mutuall League
and Covenant to be a lawfull, proper and probable meanes
to <hi>preserve our selves and our Religion from ruine and destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. Nor can believe the same to be <hi>according to the commendable
practice of these Kingdomes, or the example of Gods people in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Nations.</hi> When we find not the least foot-step in our
Histories of a sworne Covenant ever entred into by the
people of this Kingdome upon any occasion whatsoever;
nor can readily remember any commendable example of the
like done in any other Nation: but are rather told by the
defenders of this Covenant, that<note n="a" place="margin">Such an Oath, as for Matter, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and other Circumstances, the like hath not been in any Age or Oath we read of in sacred or humane stories. <hi>M.</hi> Nye, <hi>Covenant with Narrative, pag. 12.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>the world never saw the
like before</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. II.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the Covenant in grosse.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> FIrst, we are not satisfied, how we can submit to the taking
thereof, as it is now imposed under a penalty.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Such imposition (to our seeming) being repugnant to the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64210:6"/>
nature of a Covenant: which being a Contract implyeth a
<note n="a" place="margin">Pactum est duorum pluriúmve in idem placitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> consensus. <hi>L. 1. ff. de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>voluntary mutuall consent</hi> of the Contractors; whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
men are to be induced by perswasions, not compelled by
power. In so much that the very words of this Covenant in
the Preface, conclusion, and whole frame thereof runne
in such a forme throughout, as import a consent rather
grounded upon prudentiall motives, then extorted by Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour.</item>
                  <item>2. Without betraying the Liberty, which by our protestation
we are bound, and in the third Article of this Covenant
must sweare, <hi>with our lives and fortunes to preserve.</hi> To
which Liberty the imposition of a new Oath, other then is
established by Act of Parliament, is expressed in <hi>the</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Whereas many of them have had an oath admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred unto them not warrantable by the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They doe humbly pray that no man hereafter be compelled to take such an oath.—All which they most humbly pray—as their rights and liberties according to the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme. <hi>Petit. of Right, 3. Carol.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Right,</hi> and by the Lords and Commons in their<note n="c" place="margin">It is declared 16 <hi>Ian.</hi> 1642. That the King cannot <hi>compell men to be sworne without an act of Parliament.</hi> Exact Collect. pag. 859, 860.</note> 
                     <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations</hi>
acknowledged to be contrary.</item>
                  <item>3. Without acknowledging in the Imposers, a greater Power
then, for ought that appeareth to us, hath been in former
time challenged; Or can consist with our former Protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
(if we rightly understand it) in sundry the most mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall
branches thereof.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Neither, secondly, are we satisfied; (although the Covenant
should not be imposed upon us at all, but only recommended to
us, and then left to our choice;)
<list>
                     <item>1. How we should in wisedome and duty (being Subjects) of
our own accord and free will enter into a Covenant, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
He, whose Subjects we are, is in any wise concerned, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
his consent, either expressed or reasonably presumed.
It being in his power (as we conceive) by the equity of the
Law, <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. to annull and make void the same at his
pleasure.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64210:7"/>
2. How we can (now that His Majesty hath by His publique
<note n="d" place="margin">Proclam. of 9. Octob. 19. Car.</note> 
                        <hi>Interdict</hi> sufficiently made known His pleasure in that
behalfe) enter into a Covenant, the taking whereof he hath
expresly forbidden; without forfeiting that Obedience,
which (as we are perswaded) by our naturall Allegiance
and former Oathes we owe unto all such His Majesties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
as are not in our apprehensions repugnant to the
will of God, or the positive Laws of this Kingdome.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§ III.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the first Article of the Covenant.</head>
               <p>WHerein, first, we are not satisfied, how we can with judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
sweare to endeavour to preserve the Religion of
another Kingdome;
<list>
                     <item>1. Whereof as it doth not concerne us to have very much, so
we professe to have very little understanding.</item>
                     <item>2. Which (so far as the occurrents of these unhappy times
have brought it to our knowledge, and we are able to judge)
is in three of the foure specified particulars, <hi>viz. Worship,
Discipline, and Government,</hi> much worse; and in the fourth
(that of <hi>Doctrine</hi>) not at all better then our own; which we
are in the next passage of the Article required to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme.</item>
                     <item>3. Wherein if hereafter we shall find any thing (as upon far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
understanding thereof it is not impossible we may) that
may seem to us savouring of <hi>Popery, Superstition, Heresie,</hi> or
<hi>Schisme,</hi> or <hi>contrary to sound doctrine,</hi> or <hi>the power of godlinesse;</hi>
we shall be bound by the next Article to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
the extirpation, after we have bound our selves by this
first Article to the preservation thereof.</item>
                     <item>4. Wherein we already find some things (to our thinking)
so far tending towards<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>(viz.)</hi> In ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian, and indifferent Ceremonies unlawfull.</note> 
                        <hi>Superstition</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>viz.</hi> In making their disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and government a mark of the true Church, and the setting up thereof the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting of the throne of Christ.</note> 
                        <hi>Schisme,</hi>
that it seemeth to us more reasonable that we should call
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64210:7"/>
upon them to reforme the same, then that they should call
upon us to preserue it.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, we are not satisfied in the next branch, concerning <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
the Reformation of Religion in our own Kingdome, in <hi>Doctrine,
Worship, Discipline</hi> and <hi>Government;</hi> How we can sweare to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
the same, (which without making a change therein can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be done,)
<list>
                     <item>1. Without <hi>manifest scandall to the Papist and Separatist,</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. By yeelding the cause, which our godly Bishops and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,
and all our learned Divines ever since the Reformation
have both by their writings and sufferings maintained; who
have justified, against them both, the Religion established in
the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be agreeable to the Word of
God.</item>
                           <item>2. By justifying the Papists in the reproaches and scorne by
them cast upon our Religion, whose usuall objection it hath
been and is, that we know not what our Religion is; that
since we left them, we cannot tell where to stay; and that
our Religion is <hi>a</hi>
                              <note n="c" place="margin">Let us not be blamed if we call it Parliament Religion, Parliament Gospel, Parliament Faith. <hi>Harding confut. of Apology, part 6. Chap. 2.</hi>
                              </note> 
                              <hi>Parliamentary Religion.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. By a tacite acknowledgement that there is something both
in the doctrine and worship, whereunto their conformity
hath been required, not agreeable to the Word of God; and
consequently justifying them both, the one in his Recusancy,
the other in his Separation.</item>
                           <item>4. By an implied Confession, that the Lawes formerly made
against Papists in this Kingdome, and all punishments by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
thereof inflicted upon them, were unjust; in punishing
them for refusing to joyne with us in that forme of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,
which our selves (as well as they) doe not approve
of.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Without <hi>manifest wrong unto our selves,</hi> our Consciences,
Reputation and Estates; in bearing false witnesse against our
selves, and sundry other wayes: by swearing to endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
that, as corrupt and vicious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        <list>
                           <pb n="6" facs="tcp:64210:8"/>
                           <item>1. Which we have formerly by our Personall Subscriptions
approved, as agreeable to Gods Word: and have not been
since either condemned by our own hearts for so doing, or
convinced in our judgements by any of our Brethren that
therein we did amisse.</item>
                           <item>2. Which in our Consciences we are perswaded, not to be in
any of the foure specified particulars (as it standeth by Law
established) much lesse in the whole foure, against the Word
of God.</item>
                           <item>3. Which we verily believe (and, as we think upon good
grounds) to be in sundry respects much better, and more
agreeable to the Word of God, &amp; the practice of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique
Church, then that which we should by the former
words of this Article sweare to preserve.</item>
                           <item>4. Whereunto the<note n="d" place="margin">Stat. 13. Eliz. 12.</note> Lawes yet in force require of all such
Clerks as shall be admitted to any Benefice, the signification
of their hearty assent, to be attested openly in the time of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
Service before the whole congregation there present,
within a limited time, and that under pain (upon default
made) of the losse of every such Benefice.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Without <hi>manifest danger of Perjury:</hi> This branch of the
Article (to our best understandings) seeming directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<list>
                           <item>1. To our former solemne Protestation, which we have bound
our selves neither for hope, feare, or other respect ever to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquish.
Wherein the Doctrine which we have vowed to
maintaine, by the name of the <hi>true Protestant Religion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed
in the Doctrine of the Church of England,</hi> we take to
be the same which now we are required to endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
and alter.</item>
                           <item>2. To the Oath of Supremacy, by us also taken, according to
the Lawes of the Realme, and the Statutes of our University
in that behalfe. Wherein having first testified and declared
in our Consciences, that the <hi>Kings Highnesse is the only su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
Governour of this Realme, we doe after swear to our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
to assist and defend all Iurisdictions, Privileges, Preheminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
and Authorities granted or belonging to the Kings High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
His Heires, and Successors, or united and annexed to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64210:8"/>
Imperiall Crowne of this Realme.</hi> One of the which privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges
and Preheminences, by an expresse Statute so annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and that even, <hi>in terminis,</hi> in the selfe-same words in a
manner with those used in the Oath, is the whole power
of Spirituall or Ecclesiasticall Jurisdiction, for the correction
and reformation of all manner of errors and abuses <hi>in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
Ecclesiasticall:</hi> as by the<note n="e" place="margin">Such ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictions, privileges, superiorities and preheminences spirituall and ecclesiasticall, as by any, &amp;c. for the Visitation of the Ecclesiasticall State and Persons, and for reformation order and correction of the same, and of all manner errors, heresies, schismes, abuses, offences, contempts and enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, shall for ever by authority of this present Parliament be united and annexed to the Imperiall Crown of this Realme. <hi>An Act restoring to the Crowne the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Jurisdiction, &amp;c. 1 Elizab. I.</hi>
                              </note> words of the said Statute
more at large appeareth. The Oath affording the <hi>Proposition,</hi>
and the Statute the <hi>Assumption,</hi> we find no way how to
avoyd the <hi>Conclusion.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">of the Second Article of the Covenant.</head>
               <p>FIrst, it cannot but affect us with some griefe and Amazement,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
to see that antient forme of Church-Government, which we
heartily (and, as we hope, worthily) honour; as under which our
Religion was at first so orderly, without violence or tumult, and
so happily, reformed; and hath since so long flourished with Truth
and Peace, to the honour and happinesse of our owne, and the
envy and admiration of other Nations, not only
<list>
                     <item>1. Endeavoured to be extirpated; without any reason offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to our understandings, for which it should be thought
necessary, or but so much as expedient so to doe. But
also</item>
                     <item>2. Ranked with <hi>Popery, Superstition, Heresie, Schisme</hi> and
<hi>Prophanesse;</hi> which we unfainedly professe our selves to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
as much as any others whatsoever.</item>
                     <item>3. And that with some intimation also, as if that Government
were some way or other so <hi>contrary to sound doctrine, or the
power of godlinesse,</hi> that whosoever should not endeavour
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64210:9"/>
the extirpation thereof must of necessity <hi>partake in other
mens sins,</hi> which we cannot yet be perswaded to believe.</item>
                     <item>4. And we desire it may be considered, in case a Covenant of
like forme should be tender'd to the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi>
wherein they should be required to sweare, they would sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely,
really and constantly without respect of persons, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
the extirpation of <hi>Treason, the City Government</hi> (by
a Lord Major, Aldermen, Sheriffes, Common-Councel and
other officers depending thereon) <hi>Murther, Adultery,
Theft, Cosenage, and whatsoever shall be,</hi>—&amp;c. <hi>lest they should
partake in other mens sinnes;</hi> whether such a tendry could be
looked upon by any Citizen that had the least spirit of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
in him as an act of Justice, Meeknesse and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son?</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, for Episcopall Government; we are not satisfied
how we can with a good Conscience sweare to endeavour the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation
thereof, 1. in <hi>respect of the thing it selfe.</hi> Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
which government we thinke we have reason to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
<list>
                     <item>1. That it is (if not <hi>Iure divino</hi> in the strictest sense, that is to
say, expressely commanded by God in his Word, yet) of
<hi>Apostolicall institution,</hi> that is to say, was established in the
Churches by the Apostles, according to the mind and after
the example of their Master <hi>Iesus Christ,</hi> and that by virtue
of their ordinary power and authority derived from him, as
deputed by him Governors of his Church.</item>
                     <item>2. Or at least, that <hi>Episcopall Aristocracy</hi> hath a fairer preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
and may lay a juster title and claime to a Divine insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
then any of the other formes of Church-Government
can doe; all which yet do pretend thereunto, <hi>viz.</hi> that of the
<hi>Papall Monarchy,</hi> that of the <hi>Presbyterian Democracy,</hi> and
that of the <hi>Independents</hi> by Particular Congregations, or Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
Churches.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>2. But we are assured by the undoubted testimony of Antient
Records and later Histories, that this forme of Government
hath beene continued with such an universall, uninterrupted, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questioned
succession in all the Churches of God, and in all King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
that have beene called Christian throughout the whole
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64210:9"/>
world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for fifteen hundred yeers together; that there never was
in all that time any considerable opposition made there against.
That of <hi>Aërius</hi> was the greatest, wherein yet there was little of
consideration, beside these two things: that it grew at the first
but out of discontent; and gained him at the last but the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of an Heretique. From which antiquity and continuance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
we have just cause to fear, that to endeavour the extirpation
thereof,
<list>
                     <item>1. Would give such advantage to the Papists, who usually
object against us, and our Religion, the contempt of antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
and the love of novelty; that we should not be able to
wipe off the aspersion.</item>
                     <item>2. Would so diminish the just authority due to the consenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
judgement and practice of the universall Church (the best
interpreter of Scripture in things not clearly exprest; for
<hi>Lex currit cum praxi:)</hi> that without it we should be at a
losse in sundry points both of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Manners,</hi> at this
day firmely believed and securely practiced by us; when by
the Socinians, Anabaptists, and other Sectaries we should be
called upon for our proofes. As namely sundry Orthodoxall
explications concerning the Trinity and Co-equality of the
Persons in the God-head, against the Arians and other He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques;
the number, use and efficacy of Sacraments; the
Baptising of Infants; Nationall Churches; the observation
of the Lords-Day; and even the Canon of Scripture it
self.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>in respect of our selves;</hi> we are not satisfied, how it <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
can stand with the principles of <hi>Iustice, Ingenuity,</hi> and <hi>Humanity,</hi>
to require the extirpation of Episcopall Government (unlesse it
had been first cleerly demonstrated to be unlawful) to be sincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and really endeavoured, by us,
<list>
                     <item>1. Who have all of us, who have taken any Degree by sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing
the 39. Articles, testified our approbation of that
Government: one of those<note n="a" place="margin">Art. 36.</note> Articles affirming the very
Book containing the form of <hi>their Consecration</hi> to contain
in it nothing contrary to the Word of God.</item>
                     <item>2. Who have most of us (<hi>viz.</hi> as many as have entred into the
Ministery) received Orders from their hands: whom we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64210:10"/>
should very ill requite for laying their hands upon us, if we
should now lay to our hands to root them up, and cannot
tell for what.</item>
                     <item>3. Who have sundry of us, since the beginning of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
subscribed our names to Petitions exhibited or inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
to be exhibited to that High Court, for the continuance
of that Government. Which as we then did sincerely and
really, so we should with like sincerity and reality, still (not
having met with any thing since to shew us our errour) be
ready to doe the same again, if we had the same hopes we
then had of the reception of such Petitions.</item>
                     <item>4. Who hold some of us our livelyhood, either in whole or
in part, by those titles of <hi>Deanes, Deanes and Chapters, &amp;c.</hi>
mentioned in the Articles; being members of some Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giate
or Cathedrall Churches. And our memories will not
readily serve us with any example in this kind since the
world began; wherein any state or profession of men,
though convicted (as we are not) of a crime that might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
deprivation, were required to bind themselves by
oath, <hi>sincerely and really to endeavour</hi> the rooting out of
that (in it selfe not unlawfull) together wherewith they
must also root out themselves, their estates and lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods.</item>
                     <item>5. Especially it being usuall in most of the said Churches, that
such persons as are admitted members thereof, have a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonall
Oath administred unto them, to maintain the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
Immunities, Libertyes, and profits of the same; and
whilst they live to seeke the good, and not to doe any thing
to the hurt, hindrance, or prejudice thereof; or in other
words to the like effect.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, <hi>in respect of the Church of England:</hi> we are not satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
how we can swear to endeavour the extirpation of the esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished
Government, no necessity or just Cause for so doing,
either offering it selfe, or being offered to our understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.
<list>
                     <item>1. Since all change of Government unavoidably bringeth with
it, besides those that are present and evident, sundry other
inconveniences, which no wit of man can possibly fore-see
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64210:10"/>
to provide against, till late experience discover them: We
cannot be sure, that the evils which may ensue upon the
change of this Government, (which hath been of so long
continuance in this Kingdome, is so deeply rooted in the
Lawes thereof, and hath so neere a conjunction with, and so
strong an influence upon the Civill State and Government,
as that the change thereof must infer the necessity of a great
alteration to be made in the other also;) may not be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
then the supposed evils whatsoever they are, which by
this change are sought to be remedied. For there are not
yet any come to our knowledge of that desperate nature,
as not to be capable of other remedy, then the utter extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the whole Government it selfe.</item>
                     <item>2. Whereas the House of Commons have<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>—give advantage to this Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant party to traduce our Proceedings. They infuse into the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that we mean to abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish all Church-Government</hi>— Remonst. 15. Dec. 1641. Exact Collect. pag. 19. <hi>The Lords and Commons doe declare, That they intend a due and necessary Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Government and Liturgie of the Church; and to take away nothing in the one or in the other, but what shall be evill, and justly offensive, or at least unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary and burthensome.</hi> Declar. 9. Apr. 1642. Exact Coll. p. 135.</note> remonstrated,
that it was far from their purpose or desire to <hi>abolish the
Church-Government,</hi> but rather that <hi>all the members of the
Church of England should be regulated by such Rules of Order
and Discipline as are established by Parliament,</hi> and that it was
Malignancie <hi>to infuse into the people</hi> that they had any other
meaning: We are loth by consenting to the second Article
to become guilty of such <hi>Infusion,</hi> as may bring us within
the compasse and danger of the fourth Article of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</item>
                     <item>3. Since it hath been declared by sundry<note n="c" place="margin">Statut. of Carlile 25. E. 1. recited 25. E. 3.</note> Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
That <hi>the holy Church of England was founded in the state of Prelacy within the Realm of England:</hi> We dare not
by endeavouring the extirpation of Prelacy, strike at the
very foundation, and thereby (as much as in us lyeth) co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operate
towards the ruine of this famous Church; which
in all conscience and duty we are bound with our utmost
lawfull power to uphold.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Lastly, <hi>in respect of our Obligations to His Majesty</hi> by our Duty <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:64210:11"/>
and oathes: we are not satisfied how we can swear to endeavour
the extirpation of the Church-Government by Law established,
without forfeiture of those Obligations.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Having in the Oath of Supremacie acknowledged the King
to be <hi>the onely Supreme Governour in all Ecclesiasticall Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
and over all Ecclesiasticall Persons;</hi> and having bound
our selves both in that Oath, and by our Protestation, <hi>To
maintain the Kings Honour, Estate, Iurisdictions,</hi> and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of Rights: it is cleare to our understandings, that we
cannot without disloyalty and injury to Him, and double
Perjury to our selves, take upon us without his consent to
make any alteration in the Ecclesiasticall Lawes or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
much lesse to endeavour the extirpation thereof: Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
the imposers of this Covenant had a power and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
(which they have openly<note n="d" place="margin">They in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse into the people, that we mean—to leave every man to his own fancie—absolving him of that Obedience which he owes under God unto His Majesty, whom we know to be entrusted with the Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall Law, as well as with the Temporall. <hi>Exact Collect. ubi sup. p. 19.</hi>
                     </note> disclaimed) to absolve us
of that Obedience, which under God we owe unto His Majesty,
whom they know to be intrusted with the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall Law.</item>
                  <item>2. We cannot sincerely and really endeavour the extirpation
of this Government, without a sincere desire and reall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour,
that His Majesty would grant His Royall Assent
to such extirpation. Which we are so far from desiring and
endeavouring, that we hold it our bounden duty by our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
prayers to beg at the hands of Almighty God, that he
would not for our sins suffer the King to doe an act so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall
to his honour and conscience, as to consent to the
rooting out of that estate, which by so many branches of
his<note n="e" place="margin">
                        <hi>That he will</hi> grant, keep and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Laws, Customes, and Franchises, granted to the Clergie by the glorious King S. <hi>Edward.</hi> And that he will grant and preserve unto the Bishops, and to the Churches committed to their charge, all Canonicall Privileges and due Law and Iustice; and that he will protect and defend them, as every good King in his Kingdome ought to be Protector and Defender of the Bishops and the Churches under their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Vide Exact Coll. p.</hi> 290, 291.</note> 
                     <hi>Coronation Oath,</hi> he hath in such a solemne manner
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64210:11"/>
sworn by the assistance of God to his power to maintain
and preserve.</item>
                  <item>3. By the Lawes of this Land,<note n="f" place="margin">See Stat. 25. H. 8. 20. &amp; 1. E. 6. 2</note> the <hi>Collation</hi> of <hi>Bishopricks</hi>
and<note n="g" place="margin">See Stat. 39. Eliz. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Deanries;</hi> the<note n="h" place="margin">Stat. 14. E. 3. 4. &amp; 5. &amp; 17. E. 3. 14</note> 
                     <hi>fruits</hi> and <hi>profits</hi> of their Lands
and Revenues during their vacancies; the<note n="i" place="margin">Stat. 26. H. 8. 3. &amp; 1. Eliz. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>first fruits and
yearly tenths</hi> out of all Ecclesiasticall Promotions; and sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
other Privileges, Profits, and Emoluments, arising out
of the State Ecclesiasticall, are established in the Crown, and
are a considerable part of the Revenues thereof; which, by
the extirpation of Prelacy, as it is in the Article expounded,
or by subsequent practice evidenced, will be severed and cut
off from the Crown, to the great prejudice and damage
thereof. Whereunto, as we ought not in common reason,
and in order to our Allegiance as Subjects, yeeld our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent;
so having sworn expresly <hi>to maintain the Kings honour
and estate,</hi> and to our power to assist and defend all Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, &amp;c. belonging to His Highnesse, or united and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed
to the Imperiall Crown of the Realm, we cannot
without manifest Perjury (as we conceive) consent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</item>
                  <item>4. The Government of this Realm being confessedly an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi>
or<note n="k" place="margin">—Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam potesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; meru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imperium a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud nos habet Rex. <hi>Cambd.</hi> Whereas by sundry divers
old authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries &amp; Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles it is manifestly
declared and expressed, that this Realm of England is an Empire, and so hath been
accepted in the world, governed by one Supream Head and King, having the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and royall estate of the Imperiall Crown of the same. <hi>Stat. 24. H. 8. 12. See al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so 1 Elizab. 3.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and that of a most excellent temper
and constitution: we understand not how it can become us
to desire or endeavour the extirpation of that Government
in the Church, which we conceive to be incomparably of all
other the most agreeable, and no way prejudiciall to the
state of so well a constituted Monarchy. In so much as King JAMES would often say, what his long experience had taught him, <hi>No Bishop, no King.</hi> Which Aphorisme,
though we find in sundry Pamphlets of late yeares to have
been exploded with much confidence and scorn; yet we
must professe to have met with very little in the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
of the late times, to weaken our belief of it. And we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64210:12"/>
hope we shall be the lesse blamed for our unwillingnesse to
have any actuall concurrence in the extirpating of Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall
Government: seeing of such extirpation there is no
other use imaginable, but either the alienation of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues
and Inheritances, (which how it can be severed from
<hi>Sacrilege</hi> and <hi>Injustice</hi> we leave others to find out) or to
make way for the introducing of some other form of
Church-Government: which whatsoever it shall be, will
(as we think) prove either destructive of, and inconsistent
with Monarchicall Government, or at least-wise more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall
to the peaceable, orderly, and effectuall exercise
thereof, then a well-regulated Episcopacy can possibly be.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§. V.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the other parts of the Covenant.</head>
               <p>HAving insisted the more upon the two first Articles, that
concern Religion and the Church, and wherein our selves
have a more proper concernment: We shall need to insist the
lesse upon those that follow, contenting our selves with a few (the
most obvious) of those many great, and (as we conceive) just ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, that lye there against.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the third Article, we are not satisfied that our endeavour
to preserve and defend the Kings Majesties Person and Authority
is so limited, as there it is, by that addition, <hi>In the Preservation
and defence of the true Religion, and Libertyes of the Kingdome.</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as
<list>
                     <item>1. No such limitation of our duty in that behalf is to be found,
either in the Oathes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Supremacy and Alleagiance, (which
no Papist would refuse to take with such a limitation) nor
in the Protestation, nor in the Word of God.</item>
                     <item>2. Our endeavour to preserve the Rights and Privileges of
Parliaments, and the Libertyes of the Kingdome, is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
to be sworn of us in the same Article without the like
or any other limitation added thereunto.</item>
                     <item>3. Such limitation leaveth the duty of the Subject, at so much
loosenesse, and the safety of the King at so great uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64210:12"/>
that whensoever the People shall have a mind to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw
their obedience, they cannot want a pretence, from
the same for so doing.</item>
                     <item>4. After we should, by the very last thing we did (<hi>viz.</hi> swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with such a limitation) have made our selves guilty of
an actuall and reall diminution (as we conceive) of His
Majesties just power and greatnesse: the obtestation would
seem very unseasonable (at the least) with the same breath
to call the world to bear witnesse with our Consciences,
that we had no thoughts or intentions to diminish the
same.</item>
                     <item>5. The swearing with such a limitation is a Testimony of the
Subjects Loyaltie (to our seeming) of a very strange nature:
which, the Principles of their severall Religions salved, the
Conscience of a most resolure Papist or Sectary may securely
swallow, and the Conscience of a good Protestant cannot
but strein at.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In the fourth Article,
<list>
                     <item>1. We desire it may be considered, whether the imposing of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
the Covenant in this Article do not lay a necessity upon the
Son, of accusing his own Father, and pursuing him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction;
in case he should be an Incendiary, Malignant, or
other evill Instrument, such as in the Article is described. A
course, which we conceive to be contrary to Religion, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
and Humanity.</item>
                     <item>2. Whether the swearing according to this Article, doth not
rather open a ready way, to Children that are sick of the
Father, Husbands that are weary of their Wives, &amp;c. by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing
such, as stand between them and their desires, of
Malignancy, the better to effectuate their unlawfull intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
and designes.</item>
                     <item>3. Our selves having solemnly protested to maintain the
Liberty of the Subject, and the House of Commons having
publiquely declared against the exercise of an Arbitrary
Power, with Order that their said Declaration should be
printed and published in all the Parish-Churches and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pells
of the Kindome, there to stand and remaine as a testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
of the clearnesse of their intentions; whether the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64210:13"/>
subjecting of our selves and brethren by Oath, unto such
punishments as shall be inflicted upon us (without Law or
Merit) at the sole pleasure of such uncertaine Judges as shall
be upon any particular occasion <hi>deputed for that effect,</hi> of
what mean quality or abilities soever they be, even to the
taking away of our lives, <hi>if they shall think it convenient so to
doe,</hi> though the degree of our offences shall not require
or deserve the same; be not the betraying of our Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
in the lowest, and the setting up of an Arbitrary Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
in the highest degree, that can be imagined.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The substance of the fift Article, being the settling and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a firm peace and union between the three Kingdomes,
since it is our bounden duty to desire, and according to our seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
places and interests by all lawfull meanes to endeavour the
same: we should make no scruple at all to enter into a Covenant
to that purpose, were it not
<list>
                     <item>1. That we doe not see, nor therefore can acknowledge <hi>the happinesse of such a blessed Peace between the</hi> three <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi>
(for we hope Ireland is not forgotten) as in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
is mentioned: So long as Ireland is at War within
it self, and both the other Kingdomes engaged in that
War.</item>
                     <item>2. That since no peace can be firme and well-grounded that is
not bottom'd upon Justice, the most proper and adequate
act whereof is, <hi>Ius suum cui<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>,</hi> to let every one have that
which of right belongeth unto him; we cannot conceive
how a firm and lasting Peace can be established in these
Kingdomes, unlesse the respective Authority, Power, and
Liberty of <hi>King, Parliament,</hi> and <hi>Subject,</hi> as well every one
as other, be preserved full and entire, according to the
known Lawes and continued unquestioned customes of the
severall Kingdomes in former times, and before the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of these sad distractions.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In the sixth Article we are altogether unsatisfied.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 1. The whole Article being grounded upon a supposition,
which hath not yet been evidenced to us, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>this
Cause,</hi> meaning thereby (or else we understand it not) the
joyning in this Covenant of mutuall defence for the prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64210:13"/>
of the late War, was <hi>the cause of Religion, Liberty, and
Peace of the Kingdomes;</hi> and that it so much concerned <hi>the
Glory of God, and the good of the Kingdomes, and the Honour of
the King.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. If all the Premisses were so cleare, that we durst yeeld our
free assent thereunto, yet were they not sufficient to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
to our consciences what in this Article is required to
be sworn of us; unlesse we were as clearly satisfied concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the lawfulnesse of the means to be used for the support<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of such a Cause. For since evill may not be done, that
good may come thereof; we cannot yet be perswaded, that
<hi>the Cause of Religion, Liberty, and Peace,</hi> may be supported;
or <hi>the Glory of God, the Good of the Kingdomes, and the Honour
of the King</hi> sought to be advanced, by such means, as (to our
best understandings) are both improper for those Ends, and
destitute of all warrant from the Lawes, either of God, or
of this Realm.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Lastly, in the conclusion, our hearts tremble to think, that we <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
should be required to pray that <hi>other Christian Churches might be
encouraged by our example to joyn in the like Association and
Covenant, to free themselves from the Antichristian yoke, &amp;c.</hi> Wherein
<list>
                     <item>1. To omit that we doe not know any <hi>Antichristian yoke</hi> under
which we were held in these Kingdomes, and from which
we owe to this either War or Covenant our freedome: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
by the Antichristian yoke be meant Episcopall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
which we hope no man that pretendeth to Truth and
Charity will affirm.</item>
                     <item>2. We doe not yet see in the fruits of this Association or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
among our selves, any thing so lovely as to invite us to
desire (much lesse to pray) that other Christian Churches
should follow our example herein.</item>
                     <item>3. To pray to the purpose in the conclusion of the Covenant
expressed, seemeth to us all one in effect, as to beseech Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
God, the God of Love and Peace,
<list>
                           <item>1. To take all Love and Peace out of the hearts of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,
and to set the whole Christian world in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bustion.</item>
                           <item>
                              <pb n="18" facs="tcp:64210:14"/>
2. To render the Reformed Religion, and all Protestants
odious to all the world.</item>
                           <item>3. To provoke the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> to use more severity
towards those of the Reformed Religion: if not (for
their own security) to root them quite out of their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
Dominions.</item>
                           <item>4. The tyrannie and yoke of Antichrist, if laid upon the
necks of Subjects by their lawfull Soveraigns, is to be
thrown off by <hi>Christian boldnes</hi> in confessing the Truth,
and <hi>Patient suffering</hi> for it; not by taking up Arms, or
violent resistance of the Higher Powers.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">Some Considerations concerning the meaning of
the Covenant.</head>
               <p>OUr aforesaid scruples are much strengthned by these ensuing
Considerations.</p>
               <p>First, that whereas no Oath, which is contradictory to it selfe,
can be taken without Perjury; because the one part of every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction
must needs be false: this Covenant either indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth, or at leastwise (which to the point of conscience is not
much lesse effectuall) seemeth to us to contain sundry Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions:
as namely, amongst others, these:
<list>
                     <item>1. To preserve as it is, without change, and yet to reforme
and alter, and not to preserve, <hi>one and the same Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Absolutely and without exception <hi>to preserve;</hi> and yet upon
supposition to <hi>extirpate</hi> the self-same thing, <hi>viz.</hi> the present
Religion of the Church of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. To reform Church-Government established in <hi>England</hi> and
<hi>Ireland, according to the Word of God:</hi> and yet to extirpate
that Government which we are perswaded to be according
thereunto, for the introducing of another whereof we are
not so perswaded.</item>
                     <item>4. To endeavour <hi>really the extirpation of Heresies, Schismes and
Profanenesse;</hi> and yet withall to extirpate that Government
in the Church, the want of the due exercise whereof we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64210:14"/>
to have been one chief cause of the growth of the
said evils; and doe beleeve the restoring and continuance
thereof would be the most proper and effectuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</item>
                     <item>5. <hi>To preserve with our estates and lives, the liberties of the
Kingdome;</hi> that is, (as in the Protestation is explained) of
the Subject; and yet contrary to these liberties, to submit
to the imposition of this <hi>Covenant,</hi> and of the <hi>Negative
Oath</hi> not yet established by Law: and to put our lives and
estates under the arbitrary power of such as may take away
both from us when they please, not onely without, but
even against Law, <hi>if they shall judge it convenient so to doe.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, we find in the Covenant, sundry expressions of dark <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
or doubtfull construction: Whereunto we cannot sweare in
judgement, till their sense be cleared and agreed upon. As, Who
are the <hi>Common Enemies?</hi> and which be <hi>the best Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches?</hi>
mentioned in the first Article. Who (in the fourth Article)
are to be accounted <hi>Malignants?</hi> How far that phrase of <hi>hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring
Reformation</hi> may be extended? What is meant by <hi>the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
Iudicatory of both Kingdomes?</hi> and sundry other.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by the use that hath been made of this Covenant,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
(sometimes to purposes of dangerous consequence) we are
brought into some fears and jealousies, lest by taking the same
we should cast our selves into more snares then we are yet aware
of. For in the first Article,
<list>
                     <item>1. Whereas we are <hi>to endeavour the Reformation of Religion in
this Kingdome, in Doctrine, Worship, Discipline, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
according to the Word of God, and the example of the best
Reformed Churches:</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. The Reformation in Worship (whereby we could not
suppose any more was intended (according to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<note n="a" place="margin">The Lords &amp; Commons doe declare, That they intend a due and necessary Reformation of the Liturgie of the Church; and to take away nothing therein but what shall be evill, and just<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly offensive, or at least unnecessary and burthensome. <hi>Declarat. 9. Apr. 1642. Exact Coll. pag. 135.</hi>
                              </note> Declaration) then a review of the Service-book,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64210:15"/>
that the translations might be in some places amended,
some alterations made in the Offices and Rubricks; or at
most some of the Ceremonies laid aside for the reasons of
expediency and condescension) hath produced an utter
abolition of the whole form established: without sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituting
any other certain form in the room there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</item>
                           <item>2. The Reformation in point of Discipline and Government
intended (so far as by the overtures hitherto made we
are able to judge) is such, as we conceive not to be <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the Word of God,</hi> nor (for any thing we know) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the example of any Church that ever was in
the world (best or worst) since the Creation.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. In the second Article, our griefe and fears had been lesse,
if we could have observed <hi>the extirpation of Popery, Heresie,
Schisme, and Profanenesse,</hi> to have been as really intended,
and set on with as much speed and animosity, as the extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of <hi>Prelacy,</hi> and that which some call <hi>Superstition.</hi> But
when we see, under the notions of rooting out Prelacy and
Superstition, so much quicknesse used to fetch in the Revenues
of the Church, and the sacred Utensils, (no otherwise guilty
of Superstition, for ought we know, then that they are worth
something) and on the other side, so little yet done toward
the extirpation of Heresie, Schisme, and Profanenesse, (as
things of lesse temporall advantage.) We cannot dissemble
our suspicion, that the designers of this Covenant might have
something else before their eyes besides what in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the Introduction is expressed; and that there is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
meant in this Article, that looketh so like Sacrilege, that
we are afraid to venture thereon.</item>
                     <item>3. In the third Article
<list>
                           <item>1. Although we should not otherwise have apprehended any
matter of danger or moment in the ordering of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,
in the Article mentioned: yet since M. <hi>Challoner in his
Speech,</hi> and others have made advantage thereof to infer
from that very order, that the defence of the Kings Person
and Authority ought to be with subordination to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation
of the Rights and Privileges of Parliaments, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64210:15"/>
the Liberties of the Kingdomes, which <hi>are in the first place,</hi>
                              <note n="c" place="margin">From whence it is most evident, that the Rights and Privileges of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Liberties of the Kingdom are in the first place to be preserved. <hi>Answ. to Scotish Papers, 18.</hi> Nov. <hi>1646. page 21.</hi>
                              </note>
and before it to be endeavoured; We hope we shall be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
if we dare not take the Covenant in this sense; especially,
considering that if the Argument be of any force it will bind
us at least, as strongly to endeavour the maintenance of <hi>the
Kings Person, Honour and Estate</hi> in the first place, and the
rest but subordinately thereunto; because they are so ordered
in the Protestation: And then, that Protestation having the
advantage of preceding, it will bind us more strongly, as
being the first obligation.</item>
                           <item>2. Whereas some have been the rather induced to take the
Covenant in this particular by being told, that that limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<hi>in the preservation and defence of the true Religion and
Liberties of the Kingdomes</hi> was not to be understood exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively:
yet when we finde that the House of Commons in
their answer to the Scottish Papers, doe<note n="d" place="margin">We ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve you mention the defence of the King twice from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, yet in both places leave out <hi>In the preservation and, &amp;c. pag. 39. &amp; 46.</hi> a maine clause, without which the other part ought never to be mentioned. <hi>pag. 56.</hi>
                              </note> often presse
that limitation, as without which the endeavouring to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
the Kings Majesties Person and Authority ought not
to be mentioned; it cannot but deter us from taking the
Covenant in this particular so understood.</item>
                           <item>3. Especially being told in a late pamphlet, that the King not
having preserved the Liberties of the Kingdome, &amp;c. as of
duty he ought, is thereby become a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and so cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth
to be a King, and consequently that his subjects cease to
be Subjects, and owe him no longer subjection. Which as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion,
since we heartily detest, as false and scandalous in
the supposition, and in the inference seditious and divelish;
we dare not by subscribing this Article seeme to give the
least countenance thereunto.</item>
                           <item>4. But it striketh us with horror to think what use hath been
made of this fourth Article; concerning the punishment of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64210:16"/>
Malignants, &amp;c. as by others otherwayes; so especially by
<hi>the Corrector of a speech without dores,</hi> written in the defence
of M. <hi>Challoners</hi> Speech: Who is so bold as to tell the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that they are bound by their Covenant<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> (for the
bringing of evill instruments to condigne punishment) to
destroy the King and his Posterity; and that they cannot
justifie the taking away of <hi>Straffords</hi> and <hi>Canterburies</hi> lives
for Delinquency, whilst they suffer the cheif Delinquent to
goe unpunished.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>§. VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the Salvo's.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Salvo's</hi> that we have usually met withall, for the avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
of the aforesaid scruples, either concerning the whole
Covenant, or some particulars therein of speciall importance:
We find upon examination to be no way satisfactory to our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science.</p>
               <p>The first is that we may take the Covenant <hi>in our own sense:</hi>
but this (in a matter of this nature, <hi>viz.</hi> an imposed promisory
Oath, in the performance whereof others also are presumed to
be concerned) seemeth to be
<list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Contrary <hi>to the Nature and end of an Oath,</hi> which unlesse it
be full of simplicity, cannot be Sworn in Truth and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse,
nor serve to the ending of controversies and
contradictions, which was the use for which it was instituted,
<hi>Heb. 6.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Contrary <hi>to the end of Speech:</hi> God having given us the use
of Speech for this end, that it might be the interpreter of the
minde; it behoveth us as in all other our dealings and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts,
so especially where there is the intervention of an
Oath, so to speak as that they, whom it concerneth, may
clearly understand our meaning by our words.</item>
                     <item>3. Contrary to <hi>the end of the Covenant</hi> it self. Which being the
confirmation of a firm union among the Covenanters, that
by taking thereof they might have mutuall assurance of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
assistance &amp; defence: If one may be allowed to take it
in one sense, &amp; another in a contrary; the Covenanters shall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64210:16"/>
have no more assurance of mutuall assistance each from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
after the taking of the Covenant, then they had before.</item>
                     <item>4. Contrary to the <hi>Solemne profession</hi> made by each Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanter
(in expresse termes in the conclusion thereof) <hi>in the
presence of Almighty God, the searcher of all hearts,</hi> that he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
it <hi>with a true intention to perform the same, as he shall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
it at the great day.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>2 This will bring a scandall upon our Religion,
<list>
                     <item>1. That we practice that our selves, which we condemne in the
Papist, <hi>viz.</hi> Swearing with Jesuiticall equivocations and
mentall reservations.</item>
                     <item>2. That we take the glorious and dreadfull Name of God in
vaine; and play fast and loose with Oathes: in as much as
what we swear to day in one sense, we may swear the direct
contrary to morrow in another. And</item>
                     <item>3. It will give strength to that charge which is layd to the
Presbyterian party, in speciall, both<note n="a" place="margin">Haeretici nec Deo, nec hominibus servant fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.—Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatim hec addo, Calvinistas in hac re deteriores esse quàm Lutheranos. Nam Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistae nullam servant fi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>em: Iura, perjura.—Lutherani moderatiores sunt. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can. 5. Manual. Controv. 14. 2. 4.</hi> &amp;c.</note> by <hi>Iesuites</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">Invent Oathes and Covenants for the Kingdome, dispence with them when he pleaseth, sweare and forsweare as the wind turneth, like a godly Presbyter. <hi>Arraig. of Perfec. in Epist. Ded.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <hi>Sectaries;</hi> that there is no faith to be given to Protestants,
whatever they swear; because they may swear one thing in
their Words, and in their own sense mean another.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The second way is, to take the Covenant with these or the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
like generall <hi>Salvo's</hi> exp<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>essed, <hi>viz. So far as lawfully I may; So far as it is agreeable to the Word of God, and the Lawes of the
Land; Saving all Oathes by me formerly taken,</hi> &amp;c. But.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. We beleeve this mocking of God would be so far from
freeing us from the guilt of Perjury, that thereby we should
rather contract a new guilt of most vile and abominable Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie.</item>
                  <item>2. It seemeth all one unto us (the thing being otherwise suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
unlawfull) as if we should swear to kill, steal, commit
adultery, or forswear our selves, so far as lawfully we may.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64210:17"/>
3. If this would satisfie the Conscience, we might with a good
Conscience not only take the present Covenant, but even
subscribe to the <hi>Councell of Trent</hi> also; yea and to the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kish
Alcoran;</hi> and swear to maintain and defend either of
them, <hi>viz.</hi> so far as lawfully we may, or as they are agreable
to the Word of God.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, for the <hi>second Article</hi> in particular, in the branch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the extirpation of Church-Government, we are told
that it is to be understood of the whole Government, taken col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectively
and in <hi>sensu composito,</hi> so as if we doe endeavour but the
taking away of <hi>Apparitors</hi> only, or of any other one kind of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
officers belonging to the Ecclesiastcall Hierarchy, we
shall have sufficiently discharged our whole promise in that
particular without any prejudice done to Episcopacy. But
<list>
                     <item>1. Neither the composers of the Covenant by their words,
nor the imposers of it by their Actions, have given us the
least signification that they meant no more.</item>
                     <item>2. Yea rather, if we may judge either by the cause or the
effects, we may well think there was a meaning to extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate
the whole government, and every part thereof in the
Article expressed. For
<list>
                           <item>1. The Covenant being (as we have no cause to doubt) fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
at the instance of the Scots and for the easier pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing
of their assistance in the late War, was therefore in
all reason so to be framed and understood as to give them
satisfaction, &amp; (considering what themselves have<note n="c" place="margin">By the Covenant, both Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousands of other His Majesties Subjects of England and Ireland stand bound as well as we to hinder the setting up of the Church-Government by Bishops in the Kingdome of Scotland: And that we as well as they stand bound to endeavour the extirpation thereof in England and Ireland. <hi>Scots Declar. to the States of the United Provinces, 5. Aug. 1645. recited in Answer to the Scots Papers, pag. 23.</hi>
                              </note> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red)
against Episcopacy, we have little reason to beleeve
the taking away Apparitors, or any thing, lesse then the
rooting out of Episcopacy it self, would have satisfied
them.</item>
                           <item>2. The proceedings also since the entring of this Covenant
in endeavouring <hi>by Ordinance of Parliament</hi> to take away
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64210:17"/>
the Name, Power, and Revenues of Bishops doe sadly give
us to understand, what was their meaning therein.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, as to the scruples that arise from the Soveraignty of
the King, and the duty of Allegiance as Subjects; we find two <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
severall wayes of answering, but little satisfaction in either.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The former, by saying (which seemeth to us a piece of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable
and strange Divinity) that <hi>Protection</hi> and <hi>Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> standing in relation either to other, the King being
now disabled to give us protection, we are thereby freed
from our bond of subjection. Whereas
<list>
                        <item>1. The Subjects obligation (<hi>Ius subjectionis</hi>) doth not
spring from, nor relate unto the actuall exercise of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
protection; but from and unto the Princes obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to protect (<hi>Ius Protectionis.</hi>) Which obligation ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
upon him as a duty which he is bound in conscience
to performe, when it is in his power so to doe; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative
obligation thereunto lyeth upon us as a duty
which we are bound in conscience to performe, when
it is in our power so to doe. His inability therefore to
performe his duty doth not discharge us from the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity
of performing ours, so long as we are able to
doe it.</item>
                        <item>2. If the King should not protect us, but neglect his part,
though having power and ability to perform it; his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary
neglect ought not to free us from the faithfull
performance of what is to be done on our part. How
much lesse then ought we to think our selves dis-obliged
from our subjection, when the <hi>Non-protection</hi> on his
part is not from the want of will, but of power?</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The later (wherein yet some have triumphed) by saying
that the Parliament being the supreme Judicatory of the
Kingdome, the King, <hi>wheresoever in person,</hi> is ever present
there <hi>in his power,</hi> as in all other Courts of Justice: and that
therefore whatsoever is done by them, is not done without
the King, but by him. But craving pardon first, if in things
without our proper sphere we hap to speak unproperly or
amisse; We mustnext crave leave to be still of the same mind
we were, till it shall be made evident to our understandings,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64210:18"/>
that the King is there <hi>in his power,</hi> as it is evident to our sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
that he is not there <hi>in his Person:</hi> Which so far as our
naturall reason and small experience will serve us to judge,
all that hath been said to that purpose can never doe.</item>
               </list>
               <p>For, first, to the point of presence:
<list>
                     <item>1. We have been brought up in a beliefe that for the making
of Lawes the actuall<note n="d" place="margin">
                           <p>
                              <hi>The old formes of Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were,</hi> The King willeth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videth, ordaineth, establisheth, granteth, &amp;c. by the assent of Parliament, &amp;c. <hi>See Statutes till 1</hi> H. 4. <hi>After that,</hi> The King, of the assent of the Lords Spirituall and Temporall, and at the speciall instance and request of the Commons of this Realm, hath ordained, &amp;c. <hi>See Statutes 1</hi> H. <hi>4. till 1</hi> H. <hi>7. A forme of such Petition of the Commons, see 1</hi> R. <hi>3. 6.</hi> Prayen the Commons in this present Parliament assembled, that where, &amp;c. Please it therefore your Highnesse, by the advice and assent of the Lords Spirituall and Temporall in this your present Parliament assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by the authori<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>y of the same, to ordaince, &amp;c.</p>
                           <p>No Bill is an Act of Parliament, Ordinance, or Edict of Law, although both the Houses agree unanimously in it, till it hath the Royall Assent. <hi>Ancient Customes, pag. 54.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Assemblee de ceux troys Estats est appellee un Act de Parliament: car sans touts troys nest ascun Act de Parl. <hi>Finch Nomotech. fol. 21.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>We admit that no Acts of Parliament are complete, or formally binding without the Kings assent. H. P. <hi>Answer to</hi> David Ienkins, <hi>pag. 6.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Royall assent</hi> was simply necessary,
and not onely a virtuall assent supposed to be included in
the Votes of the two Houses: otherwise, what use can be
made of his Negative voice? or what need to<note n="e" place="margin">—Which if your Majesty shall be pleased to adorne with your Majesties Royall assent, (without which it can neither be complete and perfect, nor—) <hi>Stat. 1. Jac. 1.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>desire his
Royall assent,</hi> to that which may be done as well without it?</item>
                     <item>2. The<note n="f" place="margin">Stat. 33. H. 1. 21.</note> Statute, providing that <hi>the Kings assent to any Bill signified under his great Seal</hi> shall be to all intents of Law as
 valid &amp; effectual, as if he were personally present, doth clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
import that as to the effect of making a Law, the Kings Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
is not otherwise really present with the two Houses, then
it appeareth either in his Person or under his Seal: Any other
<hi>real presence</hi> is to us a riddle, not much unlike to that of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiation:</hi>
an imaginary thing, rather devised to serve
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64210:18"/>
turnes, then believed by those that are content to make use
of it.</item>
                     <item>3. Such presence of the King there, when it shall be made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
to us either from the writs, whereby the Members of
both Houses are called together, or by the standing Lawes of
the Land, or by the acknowledged judgement, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
practice of former and later ages, or by any expresse
from the King himself, clearly declaring his minde to that
purpose, we shall then as becometh us, acknowledge the
same, and willingly submit thereunto.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And as for the Argument drawn from the <hi>Analogie</hi> of other
Courts, wherein the Kings Power is alwayes supposed to be vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually
present, under submission we conceive it is of no conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Arguments <hi>à minore</hi> and <hi>à majore</hi> are subject to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
fallacies; and unlesse there be a parity of reason in every
requisite respect between the things compared, will not hold
good: A Pety Constable (they say) may doe something
which a Justice of Peace cannot doe: And the Steward
of a pety Mannour hath power to adminster an Oath, which
(as we are told) the House of Commons it self hath no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
to doe.</item>
                  <item>2. That the high Court of Parliament is the supream Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
we have been told it is by vertue of the Kings right of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siding
there, he being<note n="g" place="margin">Dominus Rex habet or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinariam ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictionem, dignitatem &amp; potestatem super omnes qui in regno suo sunt.—Ea quae jurisdictionis sunt &amp; pacis—ad nullum pertinent nisi and coronam &amp; dignitatem Regiam, nec à coronâ se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parari possunt. Bracton <hi>cited by</hi> Stamford, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. cap. 2.</note> the <hi>Supream Iudge,</hi> and the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
of both House his Councell: Which being so, the
reason of difference is plaine between that and other Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories
in sundry respects.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Judges in other Courts are deputed by him, and doe
all in his name, and by his authority; and therefore the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence
of his power in those Courts of ministeriall Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
is sufficient, his personall presence not necessary, neither
hath he any personall vote therein at all. But in the high
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64210:19"/>
Court of Parliament, where the King himself is the Supreme
Judge, judging in his own name and by his own authority,
his Power cannot be presumed to be really present without
either the actuall presence of his person, or some virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
representation thereof signified under his great Seal.</item>
                  <item>2. The Judges in inferiour Courts, because they are to act
all in his name, and by his Authority, doe therefore take
Oathes of fidelity for the right exercising of Judicature in
their severall places; sitting there, not by any proper interest
of their owne, but only in right of the King, whose Judges
they are, and therefore they are called the Kings Judges
and his Ministers. But in the high Court of Parliament, the
Lords and Commons sit there in Councell with the King as
Supreme Judge for the good of the whole Realm; and
therefore they are not called the Kings Judges, but the Kings
Councell: and they have their severall proper rights and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests
peculiar and distinct both between themselves, &amp; from
that of the Kings; by reason whereof they become <hi>distinct</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">For in our Lawes, the Clergie, Nobility, &amp; Communal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are the 3. Estates.—<hi>We your said most lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, (viz.</hi> the Lords Spirituall and Temporall, and the Commons) <hi>represent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Three Estates of your Realme of England,</hi> 1 Eliz. 3.—the State of the Clergie being one of the greatest States of this Realme. 8 Eliz. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Orders,</hi> or, as of late times they have been stiled (in this
sense as we conceive)<note n="i" place="margin">See <hi>Fin<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>h</hi> supra ad lit. [d].</note> 
                     <hi>three distinct Estates.</hi> Each of which
being supposed to be the best Conservators of their own
proper interest; if the power of any one Estate should be
presumed to be virtually present in the other two, that
Estate must needs be in inevitably liable to suffer in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
Interests thereof. Which might quickly prove destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
to the whole Kingdome: The safety and prosperity of
the whole consisting in the conservation of the just rights and
proper interests of the maine parts, <hi>viz.</hi> The King, Lords, and
Commons, inviolate and entire.</item>
                  <item>3. The Judges of other Courts, for as much as their power is
but ministeriall and meerly Judiciall, are bounded by the
present Lawes, and limited also by their owne Acts: so as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64210:19"/>
they may neither swerve from the Laws, in giving Judgement,
nor reverse their owne Judgements after they are given.
But the High Court of Parliament, having (by reason of the
Kings Supreme Power presiding therein) a Power Legislative
as well as Judiciall, are not so limited by any earthly Power,
but that they may change and over-rule the Lawes, and their
own Acts at their pleasure. The Kings Personall assent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
is not needfull in those other Courts, which are boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
by those Lawes whereunto the King hath already given
his personall assent: but unto any Act of Power beside, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond,
above, or against the Lawes already established, we
have been informed, and it seems to us very agreeable to
reason, that the Kings Personall Assent should be absolutely
necessary: Forasmuch as every such Act is the exercise of a
Legislative rather then of a Judiciall power; and no Act of
Legislative power in any Community (by consent of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions)
can be valid, unlesse it be confirmed by such person
or persons as the Soveraignty of that Community resideth
in. Which Soveraignty, with us, so undoubtedly resideth in
the person of the King, that his ordinary style runneth,—<hi>Our</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">The Crown of England hath been so free at all times, that it hath been in no earthly subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to God in all things touching the Regality of the said Crowne.—16 <hi>R.</hi> 2. 5. Omnis sub eo est, &amp; ipse sub nullo, nisi tantùm sub Deo. Parem autem non habet Rex in regno suo, quia—Item nec multò fortiùs superiorem aut potentiorem habere debet, quia sic esset inferior suis subjectis. <hi>Bracton. conten. 1. Rubr. 36.</hi>—Cui <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, legibus ipsis legum vim imponendi potestatem Deus dedit. <hi>Finch Nomotech. in Epist. Dedic. to K.</hi> Iames.</note> Soveraign Lord the King: And he is in the Oath of Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie
expresly acknowledged to be <hi>the onely Supreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
within his Realmes.</hi> And we leave it to the wisdome of
others to consider, what misery and mischief might come to
the Kingdome, if the power of any of these <hi>three Estates</hi>
should be swallowed up by any one or both the other, and if
then under the name of a Judiciall there should be yet really
exercised a Legislative power.</item>
                  <item>4. Since all Judiciall Power is radically and originally in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64210:20"/>
King, (who is for that cause styled by the Lawes<note n="l" place="margin">Fons Iustitiae. <hi>Bracton.</hi> By War to intend the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of the Lawes in any part of them, is to levy War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the King, and consequently Treason by the Statute of 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3.—because they are the Kings Lawes. He is the fountaine from whence in their seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall channels they are deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the Subject. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Saint John's Speech concerning the Earle of Strafford, page 12.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>The
Fountaine of Iustice</hi>) and not in any other Person or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
but by derivation from him: it seemeth to us evident,
that neither the Judges of inferiour Courts of ministeriall
Justice, nor the Lords and Commons assembled in the High
Court of Parliament, may of right exercise any other power
over the Subjects of this Realm, then such as by their respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
Patents and Writs issued from the King, or by the
known established Laws of the Land formerly assented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
by the Kings of this Realm doth appear to have been
from him derived unto them. Which Lawes, Patents and
Writs being the exact boundary of their severall Powers
it hath not yet been made appeare to our understandings,
either from the Lawes of the Realme, or from the tenour of
those Writs by which the Parliament is called, that the two
Houses of Parliament have any power without the King to
<hi>order, command, or transact;</hi> but with him<note n="m" place="margin">—Et ibidem vobiscum colloquium habere, tractare super dictis negotiis tract: vestrum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> consilium impensur: <hi>Writ to the Lords.</hi>
                     </note> to <hi>treat, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult,
and advise</hi> concerning the great affairs of the Kingdome.
In which respect they have sundry times in their Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
to His Majesty called themselves by the name of His
great Councell. And those Lawes and Writs are (as we
conceive) the proper Topick, from which the just power of
the Honourable Houses can be convincingly deduced: and
not such fraile Colletions as the wits of men may raise from
seeming Analogies and Proportions.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:64210:20"/>
               <head>§<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> VIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the Negative Oath.</head>
               <p>WE are not satisfied, how we can submit to the taking of
the <hi>Negative Oath,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Without forfeiture of that <hi>liberty,</hi> which we have sworne
and are bound to preserve. With which liberty we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
it to be inconsistent, that any obligation should be laid
upon the Subject, by an oath not established by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</item>
                     <item>2, Without abjuring our<note n="a" place="margin">Every Subject by the duty of his Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to serve and assist his Prince and Soveraigne Lord at all seasons when need shall require 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 18.</note> 
                        <hi>naturall Allegiance,</hi> and violating
the <hi>Oathes of Supremacy and Allegiance</hi> by us formerly
taken. By all which being bound to our power to <hi>as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit
the King,</hi> we are by this <hi>Negative Oath</hi> required to swear,
from our heart, <hi>not to assist him.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Without <hi>diminution of His Majesties just Power and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,</hi>
contrary to the third Article of the Covenant; by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging
a power in the two Houses of Parliament, in
opposition to the Kings Power. Whereas we professe our
selves unable to understand, how there can be any lawfull
power exercised within this Realme, which is not subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
to the power of the King.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:64210:21"/>
               <head>§. IX.</head>
               <head>Of the Ordinances concerning the
Discipline and Directory.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> FIrst, concerning them all together; we are not satisfied how
we can submit to such Ordinances of the two Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
not having the <hi>Royall Assent,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. As are contrary to the established Lawes of this Realm
contained in such Acts of Parliament as were made by the
joynt consent of King, Lords, and Commons.</item>
                     <item>2. Nor so onely, but also pretend by repeal to abrogat such
Act or Acts. For, since <hi>Ejusdem est potestatis destruere
cujus est constituere,</hi> it will not sink with us, that a lesser po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
can have a just right to cancell and annull the Act of a
greater.</item>
                     <item>3. Especially the whole power of ordering all matters Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall
being by the Lawes in expresse words <hi>for ever
annexed to the Imperiall Crown of this Realm.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Stat. 1. El. 1.</note> And upon
what head that Crown ought to stand, none can be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As to the particular Ordinances: those that concern <hi>the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi>
first.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. If under that title be comprehended the <hi>Government</hi> also:
we cannot submit thereunto, without consenting to the
eradication of a Government of reverend Antiquity in the
Church. Which (notwithstanding the severall changes of
Religion within this Realm) hath yet from time to time
been continued and confirmed by the Publique Laws and
Great Charters of the Kingdome: then which there cannot
be a more ample testimony that it was ever held agreeable
to the Civill Government and the Subjects liberty. Which
also the successive Kings of this Realme at their severall
Coronations have solemnly sworn to preserve. And the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance
whereof for sundry reasons before (upon the second
Article of the Covenant) specified, we heartily with and
desire.</item>
                  <item>2. But if the word <hi>Discipline</hi> be taken (as it is in the first Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64210:21"/>
of the Covenant) as <hi>contradistinguished unto the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi>
there is something even in that also, wherein we are
not fully satisfied, <hi>viz.</hi> the leaving of so much power in so
many persons, and those, many of them of meane quality,
for the keeping back of thousands of well-meaning Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
from the benefit and comfort of the blessed Sacrament.
An Austerity, for which there appeareth not to us any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
warrant from the World of God: But which seemeth
rather repugnant, as to the generall principles of Christian
prudence and charity, so to the directions and practice of S.
<hi>Paul</hi> in particular;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 1. &amp;c.</note> who in a Church abounding with sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
errors and corruptions both in faith and manners, (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
first given order for the excommunicating of one onely
person that by shamelesse continuance in a notorious sinne
had brought a foule scandall upon the Gospell) sufficing
himself then with a generall proposall of the great danger
of <hi>unworthy communicating,</hi> remitteth every other particular
person to a <hi>selfe-examination;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 28. &amp;c.</note> without any order either to
Ministers or Lay-Elders to exclude any from the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
upon their Examination.</item>
               </list>
               <p>As to the Ordinance concerning the <hi>Directory</hi> in particular:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
we cannot without regret of Conscience, (during our present
judgement, and the continuance of the present Lawes) consent to
the taking away of <hi>the Book of Common-Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Which by our Subscriptions most of us have approved:
with a solemne promise therewithall, in the publique Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
to use the forme prescribed therein, and no other.</item>
                  <item>2. Which, according to our said Subscription and Promise,
and our bounden duty according to the Statute in that
case provided, we have hitherto used in our Churches, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
and other Oratories, to the great benefit and comfort
of our soules.</item>
                  <item>3. Which we verily beleeve not to contain any thing which
(with such favourable construction as of right ought to be
allowed to all manner of Writings) is not justly defensible;
which hath not been by learned and godly men sufficiently
maintained against such exceptions as haue been heretofore
taken thereat; and which we are not confident (by the Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64210:22"/>
of Almighty God) we shall be able to justifie (as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
shall be offered) against all Papists, and other op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugners
or depravers thereof whatsoever.</item>
                  <item>4. Which is established by an <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> made (in peaceable
times) by as good and full authority as any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
heaven can have over us. Which doth so weigh with us,
that as it freeth us from the necessity of giving in any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
exceptions against the Directory or any thing therein
contained: so it layeth an inevitable necessity upon us of
contunuing the forme of Prayer therein enjoyned, &amp; of not
admitting any Directory or other forme to the prejudice
thereof, till the said Act shall by the like good and full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
be repealed.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In which Statute there is not onely an <hi>expresse Command</hi> given
to all Ministers for the using of the same; but there are also
<hi>sanctions of severe punishments</hi> to be inflicted upon such of them
as shall refuse so to doe; or shall preach, declare or speak any
thing to the derogation or depraving of the Book of Common
Prayer, or of any thing therein contained, or of any part thereof:
with punishments also to be inflicted upon every other person
whatsoever (<hi>the Lords of the Parliament</hi> not excepted that shall
in like manner declare or speak against the said Book; or shall
by deed or threatning compell or otherwise procure or maintain
any Minister to say open Prayer, or to minister any Sacrament in
any other manner or forme then is mentioned in the said Book;
or shall interrupt or hinder any Minister in the use of the said
formes, as by the words of the said Statute more at large may
appeare.</p>
               <p>Which Statute also hath had such an universall powerfull influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
into the succeeding times, that in all such<note n="*" place="margin">Stat. 23. Eliz. 1. &amp; 29. Eliz. 6. &amp; 35 El. 1. &amp; 2. &amp; 3 Iac. 4. &amp; 5.</note> Statutes as have
been since made against Popish Recusants, the refusing to <hi>be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
at Common-Prayer, or to receive the Sacrament according to the
formes and rites</hi> mentioned in that Book, is expressed as the most
proper legall character, whereby to distinguish a <hi>Popish Recusant</hi>
from a true Protestant. In so much that use hath been made of
that very Character in sundry Acts, since the beginning of this
present Parliament for the taxing of double payments upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusants.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:64210:22"/>
THus have we clearly and freely represented our present
judgement concerning the said Covenant, Negative Oath,
and Ordinances; which upon better information in any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,
we shall be ready to rectifie. Onely we desire it may be
considered, that if any one single scruple or reason in any the
premisses remaine unsatisfied, (though we should receive full sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
in all the rest) the Conscience would also remain still
unsatisfied. And in that case, it can neither be reasonable for
them that cannot satisfie us to presse us, nor lawfull for us that
cannot be satisfied to submit to the said Covenant, Oath and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.
<q>
                     <bibl>QUINTIL.</bibl>
                     <p>Quis damnaverit eum, qui duabus potentissimis rebus defenditur.
Iure &amp; mente?</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>ROM. 14. 22.</bibl>
                     <p>Happy is he that condemneth not himselfe in that which he
alloweth.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 23. marg. read <hi>Haeretici.</hi> pag. 24. l. 12. read <hi>Ecclesiasticall.</hi>
p. 24. l. 27. r. <hi>declared against Episcopacie</hi>) p. 26. l. ult. marg. r. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.
p. 28. 1. 24. r. <hi>be inevitably.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
