<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dew of Hermon which fell upon the hill of Sion, or, An answer to a book entituled, Sions groans for her distressed, &amp;c. offered to the King's Majesty, Parliament, and people wherein is pretended to be proved by Scripture, reason, and authority of fifteen ancients, that equal protection under different perswasions, is the undoubted right of Christian liberty : but hereby confuted, wherein the power and proceedings of the Kings Majesty and the church are vindicated.</title>
            <author>H. S. (Henry Savage), 1604?-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 227 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62249</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S760</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34021</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13661332</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13661332</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101116</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A62249)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101116)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1047:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dew of Hermon which fell upon the hill of Sion, or, An answer to a book entituled, Sions groans for her distressed, &amp;c. offered to the King's Majesty, Parliament, and people wherein is pretended to be proved by Scripture, reason, and authority of fifteen ancients, that equal protection under different perswasions, is the undoubted right of Christian liberty : but hereby confuted, wherein the power and proceedings of the Kings Majesty and the church are vindicated.</title>
                  <author>H. S. (Henry Savage), 1604?-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 81, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epistle dedicatory" signed: H.S.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Savage by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>"Some copies are called 'Toleration, with its principal objections fully confuted, or, An answer'"--DNB.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious tolerance --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Royal supremacy (Church of England)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101116:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101116:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Dew of Hermon Which fell upon the Hill of <hi>SION.</hi> OR AN ANSWER To a Book entituled, <hi>Sions groans for her diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp;c. offered to the Kings Majeſty, Parliament, and people.</hi> Wherein is pretended to be proved by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, Reaſon, and Authority of fifteen Ancients, That equal protection under different perſwaſions, is the undoubted right of Chriſtian Liberty. BUT Hereby confuted, wherein the power and proceedings of the Kings Majeſty and the Church are vindicated.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. Per. 1. 1, 2, 3.</bibl>
               <p>But there were falſe Prophets among the people, as there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you—by reaſon of whom the way of truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jude 8.</bibl>
               <p>Theſe filthy dreamers defile the fleſh, deſpiſe dominion, and ſpeak evil of dignities.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jude 16.</bibl>
               <p>Theſe are murmurers, complainers.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jude 19.</bibl>
               <p>Theſe be they who ſeparate themſelves, ſenſual, having not the Spirit.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Robinſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Sign of the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> in Sr. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:101116:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Geo. Stradling S. T. P. Rev. in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto Pat. D. Gilb. Epiſe. Lond. a Sac. domest.</signed>
               <dateline>Ex Aed. Sab. <date>12. Feb. 1662.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101116:2"/>
            <head>FOR Colonel <hi>R. ATKINS,</hi> One of the Deputy Lieutenants of the County of GLOUCESTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have peruſed the Pamphlet you left at my Lodging, and [ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your deſire grounded upon the conſideration of the advantages, which ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſuck, in things of this nature, from the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Orthodox] given you my ſenſe of it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:101116:3"/>
Which task [if it prove ſatisfactory to any, and particularly to render that Friend of yours, and of your moſt accompliſht Lady's, ſteddy, who is yet balancing in her reſolutions] I ſhall put upon the account of favours done to,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your humble Servant
<hi>H. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:101116:3"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 1.</label>
                  <p>THe events of theſe times the ſame with thoſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the paſſion of Chriſt: only thoſe were meerly eventual, theſe conſequential. Three Churches in three perſons of one houſe. The Golden Rule of our Saviour wreſted by our Adverſaries. Fears and jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, like thoſe that cauſed the war, cauſeleſs.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 2.</label>
                  <p>Their Epiſtle dated the eighth day of the third moneth. The vanity of ſuch date evidenced in anſwer to three queries. <hi>1.</hi> What the moneths in Scripture
<pb facs="tcp:101116:4"/>
were? <hi>2.</hi> By what names they were called. <hi>3.</hi> When they began? And herein <hi>1.</hi> What was the firſt moneth? <hi>2.</hi> When was the firſt day of that moneth? What the Rabbies amongſt theſe men underſtand by the firſt month? Their affectation of ſingularity.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 3.</label>
                  <p>How cheap the ſhedding of mens bloud was to them, which now they would have prevented towards them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They would have none but arbitrary govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Of all, they diſlike Kingly moſt. What is meant by the Harlot in the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> which they would have underſtood of the Pope only. <hi>Simon Magus the Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> Thoſe that work in his vertue and power, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts. The Harlot like a Bird of prey. The men of this generation compared to the Caſt of Sacres, that made the Eagle their quarry. The Pope and they meet in the Antipodes. The Hiſtory of <hi>Stork, Stubner,</hi> and <hi>Muntzer,</hi> Ring-leaders of the Fanaticks. Their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes to deceive. That they are Antichriſtian. Their ſacriledge, and their pretext for it.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 4.</label>
                  <p>The uſe of Muſick in Churches. Commanded in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in every thing that tends to edification. Muſical Inſtruments, whether wind or ſtringed, and Chromatick Muſick allowable, not typical. Thoſe that are againſt the uſe of it under the New Teſtament, would have it to be they know not what themſelves. And if any thing, it is what we hold it to be.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:101116:4"/>
                  <label>Sect. 5.</label>
                  <p>Veſtments, diſtinctions of perſons ſerving and of ſervices under the Goſpel allowed by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of Nature. No Veſtments but Vices reprehended in the Heathen in the New Teſtament. The <hi>Druides</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed not only in white, but under Oaks, which by them were had in veneration, and which the men of this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſeem to allow of, in as much as upon all their Crowns and Scepters, which they wore and bore, they placed the Acorn inſtead of the Croſſe, a figure which the Devil cannot abide. Of happy preſage to us. They confute themſelves by condemning of us. And in juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying themſelves they juſtifie us <hi>a fortiori.</hi> Nothing but order and decency in our Ceremonies.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 6.</label>
                  <p>Biſhops. <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were Biſhops, ſo were the Angels of the ſeven Churches in the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> in the judgement of old Doctor <hi>Reynolds,</hi> Doctor <hi>Uſher,</hi> and <hi>Grotius.</hi> How the Biſhops reſemble the high Prieſts? And the whole frame of Church-Government anſwers to the like order and diſtinction under the Old Teſtament. A Scheme thereof drawn by Biſhop <hi>Andrews.</hi> The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the New Teſtament do ſucceed to Prieſts and Levites, as the Lords day does to the Sahbath. The Lords Prayer contains not only ancient forms in uſe among the <hi>Jews,</hi> but alſo the very deſign of the Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces under the Law. The compariſon made. The Lords Prayer the firſt Liturgy. The Juriſdiction of the Biſhops
<pb facs="tcp:101116:5"/>
proved. <hi>1.</hi> as to their power, <hi>2.</hi> as to the diſtribution of their power: and both out of the New Teſtament. Their right of ſitting in Parliament aſſerted.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 7.</label>
                  <p>Of Churches. The lawfulneſſe of them proved from the example of primitive Chriſtians in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>2.</hi> Their conveniency proved, <hi>1.</hi> In reſpect of their capacity for the Dioceſſe and Pariſhes. <hi>2.</hi> In reſpect of their ſcituation in relation to the Dioceſſe and Pariſhes. <hi>3.</hi> In reſpect of their ſcituation of Eaſt and Weſt. Chriſtians anciently adored towards the Eaſt. Of the Church at <hi>Richlieu</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> whoſe Altar ſtands at the Weſt-end. Of <hi>Covent-garden</hi> Church in <hi>London. 4.</hi> Convenient for the ſcituation of parts within themſelves. They are <hi>Naves inverſae.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in them, what? Some built with a ſingle Croſſe, ſome with a double, and why? The mark in <hi>Ezekiel 9. 4.</hi> was the Croſſe, and that proved not only from the figure of the Letter <hi>Tau,</hi> which was ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Croſſe, but alſo that in all probability it muſt be ſo, though it be, <hi>ſet a mark,</hi> or <hi>mark a mark,</hi> and no more in our Tranſlation. The neceſſity of Churches proved. No ſtumbling-block to the Jews or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 8.</label>
                  <p>How they ſlander the good Laws of the Kindome. The ſame thing they impute to us, is applicable to themſelves. The Harlot in the <hi>Apocalypſe</hi> why ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led?
<pb facs="tcp:101116:5"/>
The integral parts of Antichriſt. Their fury and hypocriſy parallel'd by thoſe in <hi>France. Engliſh Scotti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing,</hi> &amp;c. Rebellion under pretence of Religion unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 9.</label>
                  <p>Of Magiſtrates. Their power is of God, and how? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion the foundation of all Government, proved by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral arguments. <hi>Anſwer,</hi> to their arguments of receiving the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and becoming Papiſts in ſome caſes. A three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold book put into Magiſtrates hands. An errour in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which is accidental makes not void his power. Their ſecond argument anſwered, their third argument anſwered, their fourth anſwered, their fifth anſwered. What power the Church hath to decree Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. Their argument taken from the ceaſing of the Croſs of Chriſt anſwered. Their argument from the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Gallio</hi> anſwered.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 10.</label>
                  <p>The ſecond part of their propoſition anſwered, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Magiſtrate hath no power in Gods worſhip as he is a Chriſtian. The Magiſtrates called Gods <hi>Anointed ones.</hi> Aphoriſm of <hi>K. James</hi> againſt too much ſeverity. Force to be uſed. Of the Apoſtles delivering over unto Satan. Of dividing the inheritance and ridding the Temple.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:101116:6"/>
                  <label>Sect. 11.</label>
                  <p>
                     <hi>2 Cor. 1. 24.</hi> expounded. <hi>Mat. 20. 25.</hi> expounded. <hi>1 Pet. 5. 2, 3.</hi> exponnded. Diſtinction of powers. <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopus puerorum,</hi> what <hi>Pragmatica Sanctio, Imperium ſupra Imperium,</hi> and <hi>Imperium ab Imperio avulſum,</hi> what? The greateſt domineering power is in the men of this Generation. The execrable fact of <hi>Schucker</hi> the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of <hi>Melchior Rinchius,</hi> who cut off his brothers head by inſpiration.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 12.</label>
                  <p>That place of <hi>Mat. 13. Let both grow together till the Harveſt,</hi> expounded and juſtified both as it notes the event of Gods providence, and as it notes the duty of the Civil Magiſtrate.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 13.</label>
                  <p>Their argument taken from the fallibility of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates anſwered. Their argument from the no ſuch need of Magiſtrates now as under the Old Teſtament anſwered. A threefold judgement of the Church. Their argument ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from miſtakes in <hi>Holland,</hi> and from fallibility of Councils anſwered.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 14.</label>
                  <p>Their argument taken from the Royal Law of <hi>whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye would that men ſhould do unto you,</hi> &amp;c. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.
<pb facs="tcp:101116:6"/>
Perſecution in Scripture-ſenſe what? Moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient that all things be determined by Laws. <hi>Lex Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lionis</hi> neceſſary in every good body of Laws. The Temple of the Graces how ſet? ſomething of neceſſity muſt be left to the boſome of the Judge. Private men know not what they would be, ſhould they come to govern.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sect. 15.</label>
                  <p>Chriſtian prudence in a Magiſtrate a ſuppoſition of theirs anſwered. In what caſes the civil ſword may capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally puniſh, proved out of the Law. And that it hinders not the converſion of a ſinner. That Magiſtrates have the ſame power under the New Teſtament, as they under the Old had, proved out of Scripture. The queſtion why Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and blaſphemy are puniſhed with death, and not cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of father or mother, man-ſtealing, adultery, and Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-breaking? anſwered. Their argument taken from the advantages that the Jews had in judging of cauſes, anſwered. The argument taken from the different diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of the Law and the Goſpel anſwered. That of <hi>1 Cor. 4. 5.</hi> expounded. <hi>Judaei &amp; Caelicolae</hi> Law made againſt them. Their argument taken from toleration in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces anſwered. <hi>Pragmatica Sanctio,</hi> what? The Cenſure of the <hi>Sorbon</hi> againſt the temporal power of the Pope. The committing of reformation to Pope or people an errour. Liberty makes not for the ſecurity of princes. The carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> parallel'd in our days, they urge it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, but it makes againſt themſelves.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:101116:7"/>
                  <label>Sect. 16.</label>
                  <p>Liberty granted by the <hi>Kings Declaration from Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> anſwered. Argument taken from Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Conner</hi> anſwered. Our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries abuſe him in making their Authours ſeparatiſts from themſelves, &amp;c. The <hi>10.</hi> perſecutions in the firſt <hi>300.</hi> years. Perſecution otherwiſe taken in the Scripture then in the Law. How, impoſing, and lording, &amp;c. came in with the train and retinue of Antichriſt, and how not? Humane Laws bind the conſcience in themſelves, not for themſelves. Severe Laws made againſt Hereticks, and what they were. <hi>King James</hi> his Embaſſy to the States of <hi>Holland</hi> touching <hi>Vorſtius.</hi> Moderation of the Church of <hi>England</hi> touching things diſputable of Toleration in <hi>Germany, Savoy, Polonia, Roan.</hi> Who the firſt Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of force and violence? Of begging Fryars, &amp;c. Of the <hi>Lollarots.</hi> Spiritnal drunkenneſs worſe then corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. The greateſt drunkards where greateſt liberty of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. Diſputations ſeldome produce good effects, and why?</p>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101116:7"/>
            <head>THE Dew of Hermon Which fell upon the Hill of <hi>SION.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Epiſtle to the Reader, they compare theſe times to that of our Saviours paſſion, wherein <hi>the ſame things,</hi> they ſay, are fallen out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which our Saviour foretold ſhould come to paſſe after his <hi>paſſion,</hi> viz. That <hi>the father hath been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt the ſon, and the ſon againſt the father, three againſt two, and two againſt three, even a mans foes have been they of his own houſhold:</hi> And it is very true that they ſay herein, namely, that the ſame things have fallen out now, as then, but with this difference, <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe diviſions which were predicted by our Saviour to come to paſſe after his death, were meerly eventual as receiving, no cauſality or real influx from the paſſion oſ our Saviour, whoſe Legacy to his Church was peace and unity, given by his Teſtament, and ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his blood: whereas theſe diviſions are not meerly eventual,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101116:8"/>
but conſequential too, neceſſarily following, as an effect does its cauſe, upon the removal of the impediment. For it hath been long ago cleared up to the world, that theſe things had been brewing above threeſcore years before they came to paſſe, but never ripe for execution till the paſſion, or the captivity of the King: whereupon the foundations were caſt down, and the ſinews of Government bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; which once removed out of the way, then did that ſhew it ſelf openly, which <hi>Barclay</hi> in his <hi>Icon animorum</hi> obſerves to have been practiſed privately before, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſons excommunicating the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the father the ſons: laſtly, one ſon excommunicating the other, till three Churches were found in three perſons of one houſe, if it be not a ſolaeciſme ſo to ſpeak. And truly, to uſe their own words, <hi>He is a ſtranger in this our Iſrael, that hath not ſeen theſe things.</hi> And whereas for their pretence, they alledge the golden Rule of our Saviour, <hi>viz. All things whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, the ſame do ye alſo unto them:</hi> Our Saviour ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intended hereby to looſen the reins of Government, and to let them lye upon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the necks of thoſe that are like horſe or mule that have no underſtanding, whoſe mouths muſt be held with the bit and bridle of the Law; but this he would have to be underſtood of a well governed will, ſubjected to right reaſon: otherwiſe a criminal at the bar might ſay to the Judge, my Lord [nay he muſt call him Sirra too] you paſſe ſentence of condemnation upon me, and therefore I ſuppoſe you willing, according to our Saviours Rule, that I paſſe the ſame upon you: let us therefore change places for a while, and ſo we ſhall both, in three dayes, take our turnes at <hi>Tiburn,</hi> or elſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don one the other for what is paſt, and give mutual liberty to do what we pleaſe for the time to come, and ſo not only become the ſons of the free woman, but be freed from that bondage, which thoſe of the bond-woman would bring us into [it is the very Metaphor which they here purſue] which if the Judge refuſes [and he is mad if he does not] then does he [in the ſenſe of the Authors] offer violence to the conſcience of the offenders, as hereafter will appear. <hi>And least this violence and oppreſſion ſhould terminate in the bloud of thoſe, which are dear to God, they have,</hi> as they ſay, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted this to the view of all men,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe are the fears and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, which have occaſioned the ſpilling of ſo much innocent bloud as has been of late ſhed, which cries ſo lowd againſt the men
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101116:8"/>
of their generation [as they call themſelves] that I do not wonder they are afraid of their own [though they fear where no fear is] till <hi>Cain</hi> became the ſhedder of his brothers bloud, he never cried that the next man which met him ſhould ſlay him. This fear and jealouſy was then and is now a meer ſlander of the good Laws and practice of the King, as I ſhall have occaſion hereafter to ſhew.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>THis Epiſtle ended, they date it <hi>the eighth day of the third moneth;</hi> which of it ſelf notes their inclination to thwart all the world though it be for nothing but their mindes ſake. And albeit they come with a ſeeming reſolution of admitting of no proofs but what are taken out of the New Teſtament, yet have no pattern at all for this their manner of dating, but what they are beholden to the Old Teſtament for [for in the New they have no footſtep of it at all] wherein they become guilty of a threefold va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: which I ſhall diſcover upon the reſolution of three Queries. 1. What the moneths in Scripture were? 2. By what names they were called? 3. When they began? For anſwer to the firſt, I ſay. That the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſeemd at firſt to meaſure their moneths according to the courſe of the Sun, calling them MENSES SOLARES, every moneth conſiſting of thirty daies: for the Scripture ſaies, <hi>that the waters prevailed from the ſeventeenth day of the ſecond moneth,</hi> Gen. 7. 11. <hi>unto the ſeventeenth day of the ſeventh moneth,</hi> Gen. 8. 4. that is, full five moneths, and if we will number the daies, they were one hundred and fifty, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. 24. whereby it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that every moneth contained full thirty daies. After the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> departure out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> they meaſured their moneths by the courſe of the Moon: and becauſe the year of the Synodical or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequential moneths of the Moon [which are the longeſt of LUNAR moneths] comes ſhort of the year of the Sun by eleven daies, and a fourth part, hence the <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Greeks</hi> too, every eight years made an Emboliſme, <hi>h. e.</hi> an intercalation or interjection of three moneths, as the Centuriſts have noted out of <hi>Affricanus, Cen.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10. And albeit St. <hi>Aug. de Civ. Dei. l.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 14. and with him others do hold that they reckoned by <hi>Menſes LUNARES,</hi> as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101116:9"/>
well before as after the giving of the Law: yet the ſame father in the ſame place gives to every moneth thirty daies, whereas the full Synodical moneth of the Moon is but twenty nine daies, twelve hours, and fourty four minutes, as <hi>Lud. Vives</hi> hath obſerved upon him: whereunto <hi>Garcaeus</hi> addes three ſeconds and twelve thirds, <hi>Tract. de Temp. Can.</hi> 17. Theſe things being ſo, they muſt tell us what moneths they mean, whether the moneths of the Sun, or the moneths of the Moon? and if of the Moon, then whether the perio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical or Synodical moneth from the beginning whereof they reckon their eighth day? otherwiſe they might have left out their date to this Epiſtle, in as much as dates are to be certain.</p>
               <p>For anſwer to the ſecond. Before the Captivity in <hi>Babylon</hi> the moneths in Scripture are almoſt all reckoned [without name] ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of their Calender, by firſt, ſecond, and third moneth, &amp;c. After their return from Captivity they counted them all by names according to the examble of the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> and <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> amongſt whom they lived, and with whom the ſtudie of the Mathematicks flouriſhed, ſome of thoſe they borrowed from the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> whereof mention is made in <hi>Zachary, Esther, Nehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> &amp;c. neither do I finde that under or after the Captivity, they expreſſed their moneths at all by numeral words. 'Tis true that <hi>Luc.</hi> 1. 26, 36. mention is made of the ſixth moneth: but it's not to be conſtrued of the general account of the whole year, but of that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular thing, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſixth moneth from the conception of <hi>John Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſt</hi> in the womb of his mother <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which compute might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin any day of any ſtated moneth, as well as the firſt of the firſt moneth, <hi>viz.</hi> any day of <hi>Jiar, Sivan, Thamus, Ciſleu,</hi> &amp;c. as well as the firſt of <hi>Niſan</hi> or <hi>Tiſri:</hi> and indeed the Eccleſiaſtical tradition is that this compute began ſix moneths before the twenty fifth of <hi>March,</hi> though thoſe that are againſt the celebration of <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> [which depends hereon] contend againſt it: but their arguments are meerly deſtructive, and brought to puzzle the truth, not to prove any thing at all. Now to apply all this. If the people of God did not ſcruple to call their moneths by the ſame name as the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans</hi> did, among whom they lived, and never after by the firſt, ſecond<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and third, &amp;c. as they had done before; why do theſe men now begin to make it a matter of conſcience to do otherwiſe, and that without example in all the New Teſtament, or in the Old
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101116:9"/>
Teſtament after the return from the Captivity; or laſtly, of any reformed Church in Chriſtendome, which uſe the ſame name; of moneths, and the ſame order of their Calender, as the State wherein they live does.</p>
               <p>The third Querie is, when the moneths mentioned in Scripture began their account of firſt, ſecond, and third, &amp;c? for reſolution whereof it will be requiſite to anſwer to two Queries, 1. What was the firſt moneth? 2. When was the firſt day of that moneth?</p>
               <p>To the firſt I anſwer, That <hi>Buxtorfe</hi> will tell you, in his <hi>Jewiſh Synagogue,</hi> out of the <hi>Talmud,</hi> that the <hi>Jews</hi> had four ſeaſons of the year, which they called the firſt moneths in ſeveral reſpects. But certain it is, out of the Scripture it ſelf, that before their coming out of <hi>Egypt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> the moneth <hi>Tiſri</hi> was their firſt moneth, which began about the Autumnal Equinox [for it is called the feaſt of Ingathering, which is perfected in the end of the year <hi>Levit.</hi> 23. 39. [and to the end of the old year, immediately ſucceeds the beginning of the New] the ſame continued for civil affairs. After their coming out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> their year began in the moneth <hi>NIS AN,</hi> or <hi>ABIB,</hi> which was about the Vernal Equinox, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 2. Then it was that God firſt ſaid, <hi>This moneth ſhall be to thee the beginning of moneths, viz.</hi> in order to ſacred ſolemnities, <hi>h. e.</hi> all the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Law.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond I anſwer, That of theſe moneths of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> no certain time of beginning can be ſhewen, by reaſon of the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of Equinoxes, and the new Moons not recurring in the ſame moments of time. The modern <hi>Jews,</hi> and others that follow them, refer the firſt moneth <hi>NIS AN</hi> to our <hi>March;</hi> and it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that this moneth was called, the moneth of new fruits or ears of corn, becauſe then did the corn put forth full ears, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9. 31. the Barley was in the ear, and the Flax was bolled before they came out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> and this moneth is called, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 3. 15. the time of Harveſt, becauſe then did Harveſt begin: whence it is probable, that this firſt moneth was a little later then the time of our <hi>March:</hi> which is yet more evident from the time of the Vernal Equinox, which in the time of <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> fell the twenty fifth of <hi>March,</hi> not the tenth or eleventh, as now it does: the ſacred vear there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the <hi>Jews</hi> beginning about the Vernal Equinox, it follows, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101116:10"/>
moſt of, or all the firſt moneth thereof, muſt fall in <hi>April.</hi> The like may be ſaid of the firſt moneth of the civil year, which may begin in the middle or end of <hi>September,</hi> or beginning of <hi>October</hi> with us. Now then, theſe Authors dating their Epiſtle the eighth day of the third moneth who can tell whether they mean the third from the Vernal, or the third from the Autumnal Equinox, <hi>h. e.</hi> from the beginning of the ceremonial or civil year? All Ceremonies they ſet themſelves againſt, unleſſe of their own deviſing; and no civil conſtitutions will their conſcience be bound by: wherefore in what moneth of the year, or in what day of the moneth, to find ſuch men, that do not know where to find themſelves, is more then I can do. Some of them [and one of the greateſt Rabbies amongſt them] have dated things <hi>in the firſt moneth, commonly called March;</hi> whom therefore the Ceremonial year ſeems to pleaſebeſt; though the vanity thereof appears from hence, <hi>viz.</hi> That this ſacred year, and the ſeveral periods thereof, was no more to the dating of any thing with the <hi>Jews,</hi> then <hi>Advent,</hi> and the weeks or moneths fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing it, are with us; in as much as it was not by the ſacred, but the civil year that they reckoned the payments of Tythes, the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Debts, the diſcharge of Contracts, their Jubilees, their Sabbatical year, and what not? I ſhould think then, that if they diſlike our account, which is reckoned from the time of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of our Saviour, announced by the Angel to the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, they then ſhould reckon from the firſt moneth following the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of Chriſt, <hi>h. e. January,</hi> the beginning whereof is the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and Julian Epocha. But ſuch direction is the ready way to teach them to do the quite contrary, the deſign of Hereticks having ever been to gain glory by a ſingularity of knowledge; and of theſe in particular to ſpeak ſomething which they underſtand not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, rather then be underſtood by others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>THe Epiſtle to the Reader thus dated and ſubſcribed by ſix men, all as yet in communion together, they begin their Tractate with a ſpecious title, which they call <hi>Sober endeavours to prevent innocent bloud, and to ſtabliſh the Nation in the beſt of ſettlements.</hi> But
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101116:10"/>
when their party ruled, wofull experience tells us, how cheap other mens bloud was to them, and how far they deſired the beſt of ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when they ſtrove againſt all government but an arbitrary one: And among all Governments which they diſlike, that of Kings ſeems chiefly io ſtick upon their ſtomacks, becauſe <hi>The Nations of the World with their KINGS [not with their PROTECTORS and R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPERS]</hi> are ſaid to <hi>drink the wine of the fornication of that abominable</hi> HARLOT; where, by HARLOT they would have only the Pope underſtood, whereas its <hi>Dominatio Romana,</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment or Rule of [not the Pope, but the Emperours] of <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> have obſerved: and indeed the Emperours at that time, whereunto this relates, did <hi>rerum potiri.</hi> If they will not truſt <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> let them believe <hi>Johannes Groſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> of <hi>Geneva,</hi> upon the <hi>Apocalypſe:</hi> the Anagram of whoſe name is (as himſelf makes it) <hi>Sis organon Jeſu:</hi> who ſpeaks, though not the ſame thing, yet enough to prove what I pretend to: for expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the thirteenth, <hi>c.</hi> ſaith, that two things are ſignified by the ſeven heads: 1. The mountains whereon the Woman is ſet. 2. So many heads and ſorts of Governments ſucceſſively. The five firſt of thoſe Governments, <hi>viz.</hi> the Kings, the Conſuls, the Dictators, the Decemvirs, and the Tribunes, were aboliſht in the time of St. <hi>John;</hi> the ſixth, <hi>viz.</hi> the Emperours, was then in vigour, and the ſeventh, <hi>viz.</hi> the Popes, was not as yet, being not made Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign at <hi>Rome:</hi> for St. <hi>John</hi> ſayes, chap. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> v. 10. That the one was, and the other was not yet come. The ten horns, ſayes he, are ten Provinces depending on the Empire of <hi>Rome,</hi> that is to ſay, the more principal, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Italy,</hi> 2. <hi>Spaine,</hi> 3. The <hi>Gaules.</hi> 4. <hi>Almain,</hi> 5. <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> 6. <hi>Greece,</hi> 7. <hi>Aſia minor,</hi> called at this day <hi>Natolia,</hi> 8. <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Aſſyria.</hi> 9. <hi>Egypt,</hi> 10. <hi>Affrica:</hi> and chap. 13. v. 18. <hi>The number of the beaſt is the number of a man:</hi> That is, ſayes he, a number wherewith men ſerve themſelves ordinarily. Now St. <hi>John</hi> writes to the Greek Churches, and in the Greek Language: But the Greeks (as alſo the Hebrews) are wont in numeration to ſerve themſelves of Letters of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101116:11"/>
                  <table>
                     <head>This number then ſtands thus,</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>λ</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>α</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>τ</cell>
                        <cell>300</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ε</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ι</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ν</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ο</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>σ</cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="total">666</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ל</cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ו</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>מ</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>י</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>י</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ת</cell>
                        <cell>400</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="total">666</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Hereunto it is objected, that <hi>(Latinos)</hi> is not written with <hi>(ei)</hi> but with a ſingle <hi>(i)</hi> whereunto he anſwers, that this is a childiſh Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in as much as it is notoriouſly known, that the Greeks do often write the <hi>(i)</hi> Latin, by <hi>(ei)</hi> and that the Latins themſelves pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced <hi>(i)</hi> by <hi>(ei)</hi> the which pronunciation (ſayes he, and that truly) is common and ordinary among the Engliſh at this day. It is true, that ſome among us do affect to pronounce <hi>(i)</hi> everywhere, as Forreigners do, without any regard whether it be long or ſhort, <hi>Ut ſupra communem hominum ſortem ſapere videantur:</hi> but for mine own part, in forreign places, and among Forreigners, I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced it as they do; not that it is better in it ſelf, but that I might be the better underſtood by them; as <hi>Generation,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> I would pronounce <hi>Jeneration,</hi> in <hi>Germany γeneratio; Regem,</hi> in <hi>France, Rejem,</hi> in <hi>Germany Reγem,</hi> and ſo of a number of other words. But to return from my digreſſion, this being enough to prove the Harlot to be a Latin and of <hi>Rome,</hi> but not to be the Pope only.</p>
               <p>To take it in their own ſenſe, they would have our King to be one of thoſe Kings; but they confute themſelves by their own words following, wherein they ſay, that <hi>this Harlot ſitteth upon peoples, and multitudes, and nations, and tongues, and by her ſorceries deceives all nations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> &amp;c. for how does this Harlot ſit upon our King and people, when we abjure all preheminences upon earth above the King, and the King acknowledges no Superiour but God? The Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mentioned 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. they ſeem to make all one with this Harlot: But Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> will have thereby <hi>Simon Magus</hi> to be underſtood. This <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was the Ring-leader of the <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101116:11"/>
he ſate in the Temple of God, called God by the Emperour <hi>Claudius,</hi> who cauſed a Statue to be erected by <hi>liber,</hi> between the two Bridges, with this Inſcription, <hi>Simont Deo ſancto,</hi> to <hi>Simon</hi> the holy God; and he had all rites of divine worſhip performed to him by the <hi>Samaritans.</hi> Yea, thoſe that hold the Popes only to be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, are driven to ſay, That they are ſo, as far only as they work by ſigns and lying wonders in the vertue and power of <hi>Simon Magus:</hi> and if they will have a dominion and rule joyned to it, then it muſt be ſo far forth as they in their actings reſemble that <hi>Dominatio Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana,</hi> or Roman Rule and Domination. And this is called Harlot, a female, for <hi>Dominatio, vertus</hi> and <hi>potentia</hi> are <hi>Feminines:</hi> And it is obſervable, that the <hi>Caliphs</hi> or <hi>Saracenical</hi> Popes [who veſted themſelves in all power ſpiritual and temporal] are of the Femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine Gender. Whoſe power, (as are and were moſt of the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Governments) was Tyrannical, ſet up by <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who compiled his divelliſh doctrine, beginning his Empire about the ſame time that <hi>Boniface</hi> the third aſſumed his Antichriſtian Title beginning his Empire, there being but eleven years between them. Tyrannical Government and Governours are as Birds of prey; amongſt which ſort of Birds the female is ever the largeſt, boldeſt, and moſt moroſe: Inſomuch that a caſt of Sacres once ſet upon an Eagle, and having buffetted and wearied him a good, made him deſcend to the earth by the force of their blows: The Faulconer proud hereof, bragged of it before Him of the <hi>Ottomans,</hi> who took <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who cauſed their necks to be wrung off, for enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing upon their King: Which may very fitly be applyed to the men of this Generation, who may juſtly be called Sacres <hi>[Quaſi quodvis Sacrum aucupantes, imo Sacram Majeſtatem debellantes]</hi> who not contented to prey upon the perſons and eſtates of other of their fellow Subjects, ſeize upon Majeſty it ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> accounting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the only <hi>(Sacri)</hi> Saints which ought to poſſeſs the Earth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of Grace, as the Pope and his party does <hi>in ordine ad ſpiritualia;</hi> both of them fitly reſembling the madneſs of <hi>Thraſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> (or, as ſome ſay, <hi>Thraſimene)</hi> the <hi>Athenian,</hi> who made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that all the ſhips which came into the Haven were his own, and would be very angry with thoſe that went about to reclaim him from ſo ſweet an errour: Theſe are like Mariners that ſail from the ſame Port contrary wayes in the world to make Proſelytes, but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101116:12"/>
meet together in the <hi>Antipodes.</hi> The Popes pretend to <hi>Sanctitas</hi> when in many things it is <hi>mera fatuitas,</hi> as his Holineſſe was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtiled by the Emperour in <hi>Goldaſtus:</hi> ſo the men of this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration pretend to Holineſſe, when as the Devil ſends them ſtrong deluſions to believe a lye: and 'twere happy for ſome of them, did they all but believe it, who are as like their fathers, <hi>Stork, Stubner,</hi> and <hi>Muntzer,</hi> as one egg is like another. This <hi>Nicholas Stork,</hi> and <hi>Mark Stubner</hi> born in <hi>Germany,</hi> did like <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by divers artifices to gain upon the unwary multitude. This, by learning and a certain <hi>acumen</hi> in expounding of Scriptures, the other ignorant of letters, by popular eloquence, <hi>Enthuſiaſms,</hi> and fame of ſecret conference with God. Both theſe, with their great pomp and cunning no man knows what became of. Nevertheleſſe the third of them, <hi>viz. Muntzer,</hi> failed not to make the higheſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the fruit of this new Goſpel, imprinted in the minds of the people by <hi>Stubner</hi> and <hi>Stork.</hi> The <hi>Fanaticks</hi> took occaſion of dividing themſelves into parts, and of renting the Church from <hi>Luther</hi>'s book of Chriſtian Liberty, firſt ſet forth in 1520. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they reading that a Chriſtian man was Lord of all things, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to no man, theſe words were wreſted to a wrong ſenſe by men impatient of their own and others quiet: and thereupon firſt in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and obſcure Cottages, next in open and eminent places, the cruel government of Kings, their pillaging of their Subjects was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected in the preſence of the People. Liberty acquired to all under the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, was boaſted of: complaints were made not onely of the tyranny of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but of ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler matters tolerated by the firſt reformers of the Church: And by this means the two pillars of publick order were weakened, <hi>viz.</hi> the dignity of the Magiſtracy, and the reverence and reſpect of the miniſtry, and the authority of both. Hereupon thoughts were had, and endeavours uſed for the ſetting up of a New and more perfect Church, governed by a new kinde of Policy, and of initiating it's Diſciples by a new Baptiſm. And leaſt that the reſpect had to their former Baptiſm ſhould hinder it, they declaimed againſt Infant-Baptiſm as vain and unlawful, as being given to ſuch as were not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, pretending that this Sacrament was not to be adminiſtred to any but men of full age, and ſuch as were at their own diſpoſal. And that this upſtart Church might take the deeper root, theſe new
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101116:12"/>
Doctors pretended a practice of godlineſſe in themſelves, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to inculcate the ſame into others. I ſence the ordinary themes of their private and publick meetings were, that ſin was to be had in deteſtation, the fleſh to be kept under, and the Spirit ſtirred up duties of charity to be practiſed, the Croſſe of our Lord to be born, faſtings were often to be held, mean garments and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate diet to be uſed, the dreſſe of the whole body to be compoſed rather unto neglect then elegancy, and that few words were to be uſed. It is a wonder to ſee how far by this juggling the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of mankinde transforming himſelf into an angel of light, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted his own kingdom, and how obnoxious theſe new Goſpellers rendred even good men by this feigned ſcheme and form of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe new Doctors, <hi>viz. Muntzer</hi> and his companions, little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the exhortations or invectives of <hi>Luther,</hi> or the threatnings of the civil Magiſtrate, tumult the more for them, complaining that <hi>Luther</hi> and others <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſavoured of nought but carnal things, ſaying, that they had onely broken off ſome boughs of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtianiſm,</hi> leaving the tree and root entire; which, as it ought, they would have to be cut up. And when they found no ſhelter for their errours in the word of God, they fly to new arts of defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves and their errours, they brag of <hi>Enthuſiaſms</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret inſpirations, inculcating into the people, that man was to live by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God, and that therefore we are not to ſearch after wiſdome in books onely, and writings, but that we ſhould give diligence according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of the Apoſtle, that all prophecy. Hence every <hi>Fiſhmonger</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt brag'd of the ſpirit, feigned revelations, invented <hi>Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſms,</hi> after the example of <hi>Stork</hi> and <hi>Muntzer,</hi> opened the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits to Coblers and Cummin ſellers, and whatſoever the ſpirit of errour dictated to any of them, they obtruded upon others for the word of God, though beſides or againſt the written Word. A wide gap being thus opened to <hi>Enthuſiaſms,</hi> any opinions were obtruded upon the ignorant and itching-ear'd people, as namely that no Oaths were obligatory under the Goſpel, they every where preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſedition, and the ſeditious became armed againſt their Princes, inſomuch that the moſt flouriſhing Provinces were hereby deſtroyed, and died in bloud. <hi>Muntzer</hi> he muſt be their <hi>Gideon,</hi> who bore this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101116:13"/>
inſcription in his Banners, namely, <hi>Thomas Muntzer and the ſword of Gideon.</hi> Theſe things and many more may be read in <hi>Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemius de Origine progreſſu, ſectis, nominibus, &amp; dogmatibus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſtarum,</hi> and in the Commentaries of <hi>Sleiden.</hi> It does almoſt <hi>ſuperare Annalium fidem,</hi> for a man would ſcarce believe what outrages have been committed in <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> by <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden, Matthew,</hi> and <hi>Knipperdoling:</hi> whereof this leſt was ſo hardened in his wickedneſſe, that he endured three pinches of a red hot pair of tongs, before he implored the mercy of God; which amongſt other things [whereof ſome are formerly related] are recorded by the ſaid <hi>Sleiden</hi> in the fifth and tenth book of his Commentaries, from whence this <hi>Story</hi> was of purpoſe tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh, anno</hi> 1642. <hi>as a warning piece to</hi> England, <hi>eſpecially for</hi> London, againſt thoſe things, which, by woful experience, we have found to have come to paſſe, and whether they would have proceeded [had not God in mercy turned the ſtream] might eaſily be foreſeen. If this be not the ſpirit of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> [that pretends to be ſo much for Chriſt, and yet ſo much againſt him, as the very word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> implies] I know not what is. If this be the very poiſon, in a cup of gold [whereof theſe men ſpeak] what is? If this be not to make men drunk with the wine of Abomination [which they talk of] what is? If they will have it to be underſtood without a figure of a mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial cup of gold, even his is as truly verified of the men of this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration as of any, inaſmuch as this is called a cup of Abomination, in reference to ſome Abomination committed in, with, or upon ſome cups of gold, and particularly that of <hi>Belſhazzar</hi>'s impious feaſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. when the golden veſſels which were taken out of the Temple of the houſe of God, which was at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> were brought, and the King and his Princes, his wives and his concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines drank in them. And have not the men of this generation done as much in ſpoiling Churches of their ornaments, of their Chalices, of their Treaſures, and they, their wives and concubines have drunk in them to their own Gods, <hi>viz.</hi> their covetouſneſſe, their am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and carnal pleaſures, deriding their conſecration as ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and conſequently accounting that God a Devil to whom they were ſet apart? The onely pretence they have for this their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is, That <hi>Muſick, Vestments, Biſhops, Cer emonies and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es have not any footſttp in the New Teſtament;</hi> whereby they diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101116:13"/>
themſelves to be the moſt rigid ſort of the <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> As do theſe men, ſo did the <hi>Severians</hi> and <hi>Cerdonians,</hi> as St. <hi>Auſtin de Haereſibus ad quod vult Deum,</hi> teſtifies. I muſt therefore encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them within Liſts of their own ſetting, I mean the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or not at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
               <p>FIrſt then for Muſick: Where do they find it forbidden in the new Teſtament? Nay, are we not exhorted to ſing in the new Teſtament? <hi>viz. James</hi> 5. 13. Did not the Diſciples of Chriſt ſing an Hymn or Pſalm after the receiving of the Sacrament? <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 30 and <hi>Mark</hi> 14. 26. Does not St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhort his <hi>Epheſians</hi> to <hi>ſpeak</hi> unto themſelves in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, ſinging and making melody in their hearts unto God? <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 19. And does not the ſame Apoſtle adviſe his <hi>Coloſſions</hi> to <hi>teach</hi> and <hi>admoniſh</hi> one another in <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and <hi>Hymns? &amp;c. Coloſ.</hi> 3. 16. And whether theſe Pſalms, and Hymns and ſpiritual Songs be diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, as <hi>Grotius</hi> notes, or the ſame things, as others contend, they cannot be ſung without <hi>muſick;</hi> and this <hi>ſpeaking, teaching,</hi> and <hi>admonition,</hi> which are the ſubjects of theſe Pſalms, and Hymns and ſpiritual Songs, are an evidence that we may, nay [if the Apoſtles exhortation be of any force with us] we muſt ſing out all things that tend to edification at times convenient. The whole Book of the Pſalms is a confutation of the Adverſaries to this truth, in as much as it being the very pith and marrow of the whole Bible, contains doctrine, admonition, bleſſing, curſing, prophecying hiſtory, prayer, holy enquiries, all wayes of edification and conſolation: yet theſe were not only appointed to be ſung, but were adapted to Organs, Virginals, Viols, and other ſorts of Artificial Inſtruments, both (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) ſtringed and wind, <hi>Pſal</hi> 4. and <hi>Pſal</hi> 5. <hi>in titulis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But to improve their Objection for them,</hi> Where do we find Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans and Chromatick Muſick to be any more then types and ſhadows of things to come?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101116:14"/>
Whereunto I anſwer, That it cannot be proved by any man that Organs and Chromatick Muſick are any more types and ſhadows of things to come under the Goſpel, then other vocal Muſick is; or give, not grant, that they had been ceremonial, they may neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs now be uſed in another acceptation, <hi>viz.</hi> as helps of lifting up of our hearts unto God, the better fitting them for hearing and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine meditation: Neither did God, ſayes <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the 150. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> without cauſe heretofore under the Law, require the multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Muſick, that he might draw the minds of his people from vain and wicked delights [whereunto men are too much addicted] to a holy and advantageous gladneſs; and yet all this was too little, which gave occaſion to the Prophet, <hi>Amos</hi> 6. 5. to ſay, <hi>Woe be unto thoſe that ſing to the ſound of the viol, and invent inſtruments of muſick like David.</hi> Not that <hi>David</hi> was the firſt inventor of thoſe Inſtruments [for it was <hi>Jubal</hi> the ſon of <hi>Lamech, Gen.</hi> 4.] but that they ſtudied all incitements to luxury, defending their fault by the example of <hi>David;</hi> as if <hi>David</hi> had uſed Muſical Inſtruments as provocations to luxury, and not as incitements to piety. Who then can deny, that it is lawful for us to uſe the ſame ſorts of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, ſince the uſe thereof is directed to the ſame ends, and thoſe not typical but moral? Under the Law there was a double uſe of kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Beaſts, the one as a ſacrifice, the other as a ſuſtenance: the taking of it away as a ſacrifice, does not aboliſh the uſe thereof as a ſuſtenance. The like may be ſaid of any Muſick [giving, not granting it to have been ceremonial and typical] that though it might be then typical of things to come, yet the uſe of it at preſent is tropical, <hi>h. e.</hi> for the rectifying of diſorders, and for the raiſing up of our hearts to a holy and heavenly exultation, and drawing our minds from prophane and idle ſongs, in uſe at meretricious meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that deny the uſe of muſical Inſtruments under the New Teſtament, will have them nevertheleſs to be <hi>types of praiſes:</hi> by which nice diſtinction they are driven to confeſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is not ceremonial. Their deceit they would have lye under the ambiguity of the word Type: For 1. it is taken for a material print or impreſſion, made by nails or otherwiſe, as <hi>John</hi> 20. 21. and ſuch types they cannot be. 2. For the ſum of an Epiſtle, or the like, as <hi>Act.</hi> 23. 25. and ſuch they cannot be.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101116:14"/>
3. For a ſhadow or adumbration of a thing or perſon to come; and this by their own confeſſion, or rather affirmation, they are not: for this were to make them ceremonies, which they will have to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiſtinguiſhed from types. 4. For a form of doctrine, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. but Organs, &amp;c. and Voices are not forms of doctrine. 5. For an Image or Statue, <hi>Acts.</hi> 7. 43. and this they cannot be neither, theſe being the work of Painters and Engravers. 6. For examples to be feared, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 6. but theſe they cannot be, there being no judgement in all the Scripture inflicted upon any that uſed ſinging or muſical Inſtruments, no, nor threatned againſt them, unleſs ſuch as abuſed them to luxury. 7. For a ſamplar to be followed, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 17. and as it were a copy given to be taken out by others. And ſuch Types they are, (being propoſed to us to be imitated under the Goſpel) and no other, as has been proved by us, and confeſſed by themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</head>
               <p>AS for Veſtments, the ſame may be ſaid of theſe as of Muſick That though under the Law they were typical of things to come under the Goſpel, yet under the New Teſtiment they are not ſo, but meer diſtinctions of perſons ſerving, and of ſervices to be performed; which we learn not from the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> alone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but from that of Nature too. The Sacrificers among the Heathen had their <hi>Infulaes,</hi> h. e. <hi>Sacerdotates vittas.</hi> The <hi>Druides</hi> performed no ſacred ſervices without the leaves of Oak: and not only the Germans, but the Greeks, adorned their Altars with green leaves of Oak. In the Rites performed to <hi>Ceres,</hi> they were crowned with Oak; in thoſe to <hi>Apollo</hi> with Bayes; in thoſe to <hi>Hercules</hi> with Poplar; in thoſe to <hi>Bacchus</hi> with Myrtle. The Victims and Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels were likewiſe crowned: <hi>Sched. de Di<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Germ. c.</hi> 1 In all which was a decency intended, agreeable to the work they were about. It is very obvious how full the New Teſtiment is of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations againſt the abominable practices of the Heathen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet let theſe men tell me where in all the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles theſe, or the like Ceremonies were reprehended? I know ſome would have me ſay, as <hi>Pliny</hi> does, namely, that the <hi>Druides</hi> ſacrificed in white
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101116:15"/>
garments, that they might thence infer our Surplices to be a Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony derived from Heathens, and abuſed to ſuperſtition: And was not the Oak abuſed by the <hi>Druides</hi> to ſuperſtition, being had in ſo great veneration among them? And yet our late Reformers gave order<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> [which was univerſally obſerved accordingly] for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn, the fruit of the Oak, to be ſet upon the top of their Maces and Crowns, and that inſtead of the Croſs, which had never been abuſed by the Heathen, who had it in deteſtation, as a figure moſt unlike that which is beſt pleaſing to him they worſhipped, <hi>h. e.</hi> the Devil. Which thing ſo done by them was nevertheleſs of happy preſage to us, <hi>viz.</hi> That the tree which bore ſuch fruit ſhould [like that, in the Plains of <hi>Mamre]</hi> ſerve for the ſhelter of our earthly Angel, King <hi>Charles,</hi> from the heat and fury of Rebellion, which was then in the very Noon; until the Croſs reaſſumed its place again upon the top of his Crown. So unlucky are contentious ſpirits many times, that they confute themſelves by going about to condemn others? Oh but theſe men accounting themſelves the only Saints and Servants of the moſt high God, any thing they wear or do muſt be ſanctified to them: For <hi>to the pure all things are pure, but unto them that are defiled and unbelieving is nothing pure.</hi> And if ſo, then they muſt prove, that our Church conſiſteth of unbelievers; that it teaches and practiſes the uncleanneſs and other abominations of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, ſo often noted by the Apoſtles; yea our very worſhip of God to be unclean and abominable, before they can conclude our Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to be unclean and unlawful. But whileſt we maintain the worſhip of the true God, and give up our ſelves to be ordered by his Laws, we are pure, and conſequently to us all things are pure, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 15. a thing which cannot be ſaid of them, whileſt they would have any error in doctrine or worſhip, yea blaſphemy it ſelf to paſſe unpuniſhed, which is the whole drift of this their <hi>Sions groans:</hi> Wherefore <hi>deſinant maledicere, malefacta ne noſcant ſua.</hi> Let them look into themſelves, and their own practiſes, and they will find little reaſon to think themſelves in Heaven, much leſs to pull up the lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der after them, as if none were worthy to follow. St. <hi>Paul</hi> pleads not for this decency only, but for order two, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. which doubtleſs was uſed alſo among theſe Sacrificers. And therefore, as well for the expediency of the thing in it ſelf, as the avoiding of the imputation of rudeneſs and confuſion, wherewith the Grecians here
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101116:15"/>
were apt to load them: the Apoſtle concludes the Chapter with this Canon, <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in order;</hi> ſince there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can prove nothing but decency, order, and uſefulneſs in ſuch ceremonies as we uſe, what they ſay againſt them muſt go for nothing, and prevail as little with us, as a <hi>Rationale</hi> would with them. Which ſhould I produce whereby to give an account of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularities, it would not make me juſtly liable to the <hi>dicterium</hi> of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> [in his Epiſtle to the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> put before his Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the New Teſtament] caſt upon thoſe, who as he ſaies, <hi>collabentibus adium fundamentis de instaurando faſtigio labora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</head>
               <p>AS for Biſhops, there are ſome we read of in the Scripture, who had the appellation to be called Biſhops, but were not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed into a ſuperiour order above others. Others were both cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſo, and diſtinguiſhed into an order ſuperiour unto others; and theſe are the Biſhops here meant by us. Such were <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> as we learn from the ſeveral Epiſtles written unto them by St. <hi>Paul.</hi> Such were the ſeven Angels of the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> in the judgement of Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> in his conference with <hi>Hart,</hi> in the end of the third, and the beginning of the fifth Diviſion: and in the judgement of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> of the Original of Biſhops and Metropolitans, both printed together. Thoſe who by theſe Angels would have the Churches to be meant, do manifeſtly contradict the Scripture. For, ſaies Chriſt there, <hi>the Gandleſticks are the Churches, and the ſtars are the ſeven Angels of the Churches.</hi> I wonder therefore, ſaies <hi>Grotins,</hi> what ſpirit of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction carries men away, that they dare confound things which the Spirit of God ſo manifeſtly diſtinguiſheth. <hi>de Imp. ſum. not. cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca ſacra, c.</hi> 11. And I more wonder that theſe men ſhould ſay that there is <hi>not one word for them in the New Teſtament, or that they ſhould be ſet up by us as Antitypes of the high Prieſts under the Law.</hi> No, Chriſt is onely that. Nevertheleſſe in regard of the diſtinction, which was an Eccleſiaſtical thing among the <hi>Jewes;</hi> I ſay that the Biſhops do reſemble the High Prieſts, and the inferiour Clergy the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101116:16"/>
other Prieſts. For there were in this reſpect many High Prieſts at once, of whom we read many to have been aſſembled together<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 14. 1. every one of which was <hi>ſummus ſacerdos iſtius Claſſis,</hi> the High, or chief Prieſt of that Rank. Theſe ranks had their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral courſes: &amp; <hi>Zachary</hi> was of one of theſe courſes, <hi>viz.</hi> of that of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia, Luc.</hi> 1. 5. not all theſe, but one only was typical, ſhadowing forth Jeſus Chriſt unto them. And even in this High Prieſt there was ſomething beſides the repreſentation, as is plain by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who yielded his obedience to the High Prieſt as governour of the people, <hi>Acts</hi> 23. 5. and that after the Type was expired, which had been unlawfull, had there not been ſomewhat remaining in him beſides the figure. <hi>Eleazar</hi> in <hi>Aaron</hi>'s life-time was <hi>Princeps Principam;</hi> or <hi>Praelatus Praelatorum, Num.</hi> 3. 32. and yet not reputed a Type of Chriſt; and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35. 8. we read of three at once, one onely whereof was the High Prieſt which was the Type of Chriſt, the reſt were not ſo; yet by reaſon of their dignity paramount to others, might reſemble Archbiſhops themſelves. And the other foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned High Prieſts in regard of the place they held above the reſt of their Claſſe, are in a ſort reſembled by our Biſhops. And that this may not ſeem ſtrange to any, 'tis a matter obvious to our obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſcarcely any Ordinance or Order under the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, can be named, which is not derived from others under the Old, by ſome kind of reſemblance intended between them. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands by the Apoſtles was taken up in imitation of that practiſed under the Old Teſtament for the deſignation of ſucceſſors; as <hi>Moſes</hi> uſed it towards <hi>Joſuah, Num.</hi> 27. 18, 20. That the whole frame of Church Government anſwers to the like order and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of perſons and offices in the Old Teſtament is evidenced by the learned Biſhop of <hi>Winton</hi> in a ſcheme to that purpoſe thus drawn, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101116:16"/>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Aaron</cell>
                        <cell rows="7">ſhould be reſembled by</cell>
                        <cell>Chriſt.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Eleazar</cell>
                        <cell>Archbiſhops.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Princes of Prieſts</cell>
                        <cell>Biſhops.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Prieſts</cell>
                        <cell>Presbyters.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Princes of Levites</cell>
                        <cell>Archdea<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ons.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Levites</cell>
                        <cell>Deacons.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Nethinims</cell>
                        <cell>Clerks and Sextons.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>And hereunto he is led by the opinion of the ancient fathers, who ſeem to be of the ſame mind, <hi>viz.</hi> that the ſame form ſhould ſerve both: ſo is St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> ſo St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> St. <hi>Leo</hi> and <hi>Rabanus de vita clericor. The Government of the Church of the Old Teſtament,</hi> ſaies the Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh, was committed to Prieſts and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, unto whom the miniſters of the New Teſtament do now ſucceed in like ſort as our Lords day hath done unto their Sabbath.</hi> So he, in his Original of Epiſcopacy: and if it were reaſonable for Chriſtians to take the <hi>Jewes</hi> for their pattern in drawing their ſcheme of Church government; much more is it for modern Chriſtians to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ancient, a thing which our Church has done in her reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which has retained all things of ancient uſage in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> leſt men ſhould be ſcandalized at us, whileſt we ſeemed to ſet up a new Religion, inſtead of reforming the Old. The very Lords Prayer hath much of conformity, not only to the forms uſed by the <hi>Jewes,</hi> as others have obſerved; but alſo as it ſeems to me, to the very deſign of the <hi>ſacrifices</hi> of the Law, which are all redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible to three kinds. The firſt was the whole burnt-offering to God, as abſolute Lord of Heaven &amp; Earth, and as one to whom belongeth honour from us, ſhould he never beſtow any ſpecial favour upon us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The ſecond was the peace-offering, whereby to obtain at his graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hands all thoſe bleſſings and the degrees thereof, whereof men ſtand in need, whether publick or private, as alſo to expreſſe a thankfulneſſe for all bleſſings, and for all thoſe gracious returns he makes to the prayers of his people from time to time, or at any time. The third was the ſin-offering for the expiation of all or any tranſgreſſions of his holy and divine commandments, and for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101116:17"/>
health of ſoul. In conformity whereunto our Saviour hath in that perfect and abſolute form taught us to offer, by him, a ſpiritual holocauſt to the honour of his name<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who inhabits eternity, in theſe words, <hi>Our Father which art in heaven, hallowed be thy name.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly a ſpiritual peace-offering for the advancement of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in us, and the adimpletion of his will by us, as alſo for a ſupply of all outward neceſſaries in theſe words, <hi>Thy Kingdom come, thy will be done in earth as it is in heaven, Give us this day our dayly bread.</hi> Thirdly, a ſpiritual ſin-offering for the forgiveneſſe of ſins paſt, and for prevention of ſin for the time to come, in theſe words. <hi>And forgive us our treſpaſſes, as we forgive them that treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe againſt us; and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil.</hi> And theſe not without a doxology, as a ſpiritual <hi>Libamen</hi> or meat-offering, [without which no burnt-offering was to be made under the Law] in theſe words; <hi>For thine is the Kingdom, the power, and the glory, for ever and ever. Amen.</hi> And ſo having not only proved the order and diſtinctions of <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> under the New Teſtament, but alſo the firſt Liturgy [ſo the Lords Prayer is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be by <hi>Caſſander in Liturgicis ex Dionyſio,</hi> and ſtands unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably true] to be inſtituted in reſemblance of the like under the Old Teſtament, I come now to prove the <hi>juriſdiction</hi> that they have one over another, and over the reſt of the Church: wherein two things are to be conſidered in relation to our Biſhops, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Their power. 2. The diſtribution of this power. As for the firſt. Their power is ſo connatural, that the chief Judge in <hi>Areopagus</hi> was a Prieſt, hence <hi>Cohen</hi> in <hi>Hebrew</hi> was a common name to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and to Prieſts, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41. 45. <hi>Potipherah was Prieſt, h. e. Prince of On.</hi> The <hi>Druides</hi> among the <hi>Galls</hi> were of the nobleſt ſtock of kindred: they were ſo in <hi>Epirus</hi> and <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> it was uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al as well among the <hi>Grecians</hi> as <hi>Romans</hi> for Kings to be Prieſts, and as <hi>Schedius de Dis Germ</hi> notes out of <hi>Feneſtella,</hi> the Prieſt was never made a diſtinct perſon from the civil Magiſtrate till the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion of Kings out of <hi>Rome:</hi> and that this power ſo challenged by the voice of Nature in the Heathen themſelves, is warranted by the Scriptures of the New Teſtament, I ſhall have occaſion to ſhew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, in anſwer to their objections againſt it. Mean while I ſhall prove the ſecond thing conſiderable, <hi>viz.</hi> The diſtribution of their power. And this is diſtributed according to the diſtribution of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101116:17"/>
civil power, the Biſhop reſiding in the City or chief place, all the Clergy of inferiour places within his Dioceſs are ſubject to him as he is to the Archbiſhop: which is anſwerable to what the Apoſtles at firſt did practiſe in the very beginning of Chriſtianity, and was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by after times, as is obſerved by Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> out of <hi>Acts</hi> 14. and 15. <hi>cc.</hi> and made good againſt the Animadverſions on the Diſſertations touching <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s Epiſtles, <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>ſect.</hi> 6. His words are theſe. <hi>According to the image of the civil government among the Jews, and the like again in their Temple</hi> [forementioned] <hi>the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles appeared to have diſpoſed of Churches every where, and in all their plantations to have conſtituted a ſubordination and dependance of the Churches in the inferiour cities, to thoſe in the chief or metropoles.</hi> An example of this we have in the ſtory of the <hi>Acts,</hi> concerning <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Cilicia,</hi> and the ſeveral Cities thereof, in relation to <hi>Antioch</hi> the Metropolis. For when the Queſtion, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 2. was referred and brought to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> from the Church peculiarly of <hi>Antioch, cc.</hi> 14. 26. and 15. 3. and the Decree of the Council re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to them by whom the Queſtion was propoſed, <hi>h. e.</hi> to the Church at <hi>Antioch, ver.</hi> 22. yet in the Epiſtle wherein the Decree was contained, we find the Brethren through <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Cilicia, i. e.</hi> all the Chriſtians of that Province to be expreſſed and joyned with thoſe of <hi>Antioch, ver.</hi> 23. And after when that Decretal Epiſtle was delivered to the Church of <hi>Antioch, ver.</hi> 30. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> went over <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Cilicia, ver.</hi> 41. and 42. and as they went, they delivered to every City the Decrees of the Council, <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 4. which is an evidence that the churches of thoſe cities related either immediately to <hi>Antioch,</hi> or, as <hi>Antioch</hi> it ſelf did, to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and were in ſubordination to it as to the principal <hi>Metropolis</hi> of ſo wide a Province, according to that of <hi>Philo,</hi> that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was in his time, the <hi>Metropolis,</hi> not of <hi>Judea</hi> alone, but of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regions, in reſpect of the Colonies, which it ſent out of the <hi>Jews</hi> that dwelt in them, naming <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Cilicia</hi> and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, thus for the learned Doctor.</p>
               <p>The ſame is proved out of <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 14. <hi>John to the ſeven Churches in Aſia,</hi> where St. <hi>John</hi> directing his letters unto them thus indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely without any mention of their particular names, he cannot by common intendment be conceived to have underſtood any other thereby, but ſuch as by ſome degree of eminency were diſtinguiſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101116:18"/>
from all the reſt of the churches that were in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and in ſome ſort did comprehend all the reſt under them: for taking <hi>Aſia</hi> here in the moſt ſtrict ſenſe, for the <hi>Lydian,</hi> or [as the Imperial conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions call it] the Proconſular <hi>Aſia:</hi> it is not to be imagined that after ſo long pains taken by the Apoſtles and their diſciples therein there ſhould be found no more then ſeven churches, eſpecially ſince St. <hi>Luke, Acts</hi> 19. 10, 20. teſtifies that <hi>all they which dwelt in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, heard the word of the Lord Jeſus, both Jews and Greeks, ſo mightily grew the word of the Lord and prevailed.</hi> And in particular among the Epiſtles of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> there is one directed to the church in <hi>Trallis,</hi> another to the church in <hi>Magneſia:</hi> and both theſe were ſubject to the Metropolitane of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> See the Archbiſhop of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh,</hi> as above quoted. And for theſe reaſons, as alſo for their eminence in learning and wiſdom, have all Chriſtian Kings of this Realm ever conſulted with them, in the eſtabliſhment of Laws. We read in <hi>Lambert</hi>'s <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and Mr. <hi>Selden</hi>'s Titles of honour, That the Laws of <hi>Ina</hi> King of the <hi>Weſt-Saxons,</hi> were made by the perſwaſion and appointment of his father <hi>Cenredus,</hi> and of <hi>Hedda</hi> and <hi>Erkenwald<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Biſhops, with Senatours, Elders and wiſe men of the people, in a frequent aſſembly of the ſervants of God; which was between the years 712. and 727. The Laws of <hi>Alured</hi> the firſt founder of this Monarchy, were made by his authority, as thoſe of <hi>Ina</hi> had been by his; but <hi>ex conſulto ſapientum</hi> by the advice of the wiſe, which muſt include the Biſhops. 1. Becauſe his Laws were grounded on <hi>Moſes</hi> his Laws. 2. Becauſe nor theſe, nor thoſe of <hi>Ina</hi> did reach to life, except in caſe of Treaſon againſt King or Maſter. 3. Becauſe he hereby allotted much of the Kingdom to <hi>Guthurn,</hi> on condition of <hi>Guthurn</hi>'s becoming Chriſtian. All which are things well beſeeming tho judgement of Biſhops, and are (eſpecially the firſt) arguments ſufficient to convince ſome of Errour that contend our Laws to have had their Original out of the twelve Tables. This was <hi>anno</hi> 871. about 820. years ſince. The Laws of <hi>Ethelſtan, anno</hi> 924. were made by the prudent counſel of <hi>Vlſhelme</hi> Archbiſhop, and the reſt of the Biſhops, &amp;c. wherein an eſtimate was made of all orders of men that then were, or rather a declaration of the Common Law in that point. As firſt, The King was eſteemed at 30000. <hi>Thrymſa's, i. e.</hi> ſo many times three ſhillings; an Archbiſhop at 15000. <hi>Thrymſa's;</hi> a Biſhop or Senatour at 8000. <hi>Thrymfa's;</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:101116:18"/>
General of an army at 4000. one initiated in holy orders, or a <hi>Thame i. e.</hi> a Noble man at 2000. whereby it appears that an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop was double to any ſubject of the Kingdom beſides; and a Biſhop equal to the greateſt Lord in the Land; and every Prieſt as good as the beſt Noble man under the degree of a Senatour; ſo far are any of theſe orders from arrogating, that they have loſt much of that ancient honour, which belonged unto them by the Common Law of this Nation. King <hi>Edmund</hi> called together a frequent aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Eccleſiaſticks and Laicks; where <hi>Oda</hi> and <hi>Woolſtan</hi> Archbiſhop were preſent, with very many other Biſhops, for the ſanction of Laws. So did King <hi>Eldred anno</hi> 948. as <hi>Ingulphus</hi> teſtifies. So <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> and <hi>Canutus</hi> eſtabliſht Laws by the advice of the wiſe. So did <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour with the concurrence of his Princes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Archbiſhops muſt be a part: ſince which time no Acts of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament are made without the Lords Spiritual.</p>
               <p>And that theſe things were allowed to the Prieſts under the Old Teſtament no man will deny, the proofs therein being ſo frequent &amp; pregnant. But our adverſaries here call for proofs out of the New, whereunto I have &amp; ſhall anſwer hereafter in its due time &amp; place, contenting my ſelf at preſent with the Expoſition of that one text of <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 28. <hi>Ye which have followed me, in the regeneration when the Son of man ſhall ſit upon the Throne of his Glory, ye alſo ſhall ſit upon twelve Thrones, judging the twelve Tribes of Iſrael.</hi> This was ſpoken to the twelve Apoſtles which were Clergy men, and the Predeceſſors of all Biſhops; where note that the <hi>comma</hi> ſhould be put immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after <hi>Me;</hi> and <hi>in the regeneration</hi> referred to the <hi>Son of man ſitting on the Throne of his glory,</hi> which was immediately after the deſcent of the holy Ghoſt, a time <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and by way of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence call'd the Regeneration, becauſe then were the gifts of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration and ſanctification more abundantly poured forth then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they had been before; the immediate end whereof was <hi>Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration</hi> or <hi>Renovation:</hi> Then did every Apoſtle beſides his gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral commiſſion, take upon him his particular Epiſcopacy; where he ſate and judged, that is, governed the Church, ſignified here by the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> under which notion the Jewiſh Church had been comprehended. And if it were underſtood of their being aſſeſſors to Chriſt in the laſt judgement, ſurely then I might uſe the argument of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which concludes a <hi>fortiori,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 3. <hi>Know
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101116:19"/>
ye not that we ſhall judge the Angels? how much more things that pertain to this life?</hi> where, under the pronoun <hi>We,</hi> he includes himſelf and all the Apoſtles; In whoſe abſence he would have them rather end all differences (which at any time might happen) by compromiſe, then appeal to Heatheniſh tribunals, from whence they were like to reap nothing but ſcandal to Religion, and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to themſelves, by reaſon of the corruption of the Courts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Epigrammatiſt <hi>ad Sextum.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Et Judex petit, &amp; petit Patronus;</l>
                  <l>Solvas, cenſeo, Sexte, Creditori.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>The Judge does ask a <hi>bribe,</hi> thy Advocate a <hi>fee:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pay then thy Creditour, better pay <hi>one</hi> then <hi>three.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>And ſo having done with Biſhops, come we now to Churches.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</head>
               <p>IT is very true, that where two or three are gathered together in the name of Chriſt, there is he in the midſt of them: which was a ſingular conſolation to the Diſciples of Chriſt, that though they were driven to corners and deſerts, and were fain to wander in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate places, being hated by all men for Chriſts ſake, yet how does this forbid publick meetings, and at publick places, when time and opportunity preſents it ſelf? The people of God may pray in <hi>[Cryptis]</hi> caves, in time of perſecution, therefore they muſt do ſo in time of freedom, when all the world is become Chriſtians, is there any Logick in this? no, no more then would be in this kind of argument. <hi>For the preſent neceſſity it is not good for a man to touch a woman.</hi> Therefore when the neceſſity is over no man may marry. This follows not, but the clear contrary rather. And to make fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proof hereof by Scripture of the New Teſtament, it is obvious to our obſervation that the people of God had not only their <hi>Syne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria's</hi> and National Conventions, but other houſes of prayer erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and called Synagogues, who being converted to the faith by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101116:19"/>
the preaching of the Apoſtles, the Synagogues were made particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Churches: for <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 13. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies of himſelf, that he <hi>perſecuted the Church of God.</hi> Now where was this Church of God? it was in Synagogues, <hi>Act.</hi> 22. 19. <hi>I impriſoned,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>and beat in every Synagogue them that believed on thee:</hi> from whence I obſerve two things, 1. That the example of Chriſtians here, does teach us that its lawfull to ſerve God in Temples made with hands, though he be not, nor ever was confined to them. 2. That it is as lawfull that this be done, though in places abuſed to falſe doctrine and ſuperſtition, as theſe Synagogues, yea their places of Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal convention were, and that by Phariſees, Sadduces, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sects, yea generally by all the <hi>Jews</hi> before their converſion to the faith. And what is teſtified here, of Jewiſh <hi>Synedria's</hi> and Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agogues, is true of Heathen temples, namely, that it is lawfull to dedicate them to Gods worſhip, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. when St. <hi>Paul ſound</hi> at <hi>Athens, an altar dedicated to the unknown God,</hi> he went not about to preach down their altar, but to preach up Jeſus and the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon it, leaſt he ſhould ſeem to be <hi>a ſerter forth of ſtrange Gods,</hi> as indeed he did to ſome nevertheleſs. Nay, a third thing may be hence obſerved, namely, that as theſe Synagogues were ſubordinate to the <hi>Synedria's</hi> or National Aſſemblies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it follows that divers parochials may be ſubordinate to the <hi>Synedrium</hi> of the Cathedral, and the Cathedral to a Provincial or National Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention. And thus much for the lawfulneſs of Churches. Now for the convenience of them. They are convenient, 1. for their capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; the Cathedrals being large enough to contain the Biſhop with the Dean and Chapter, the ſtanding <hi>Synede</hi> of the Dioceſs, beſides the confluence of the whole City and Dioceſs upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. The parochial Churches are leſſer, yet of capacity enough to contain a pariſh. 2. they are convenient for their ſituation, 1. in reſpect of the Dioceſs [if Cathedrals] they being in ſome eminent place thereof, 2. in reſpect of the pariſh [if parochials] they being as near as may be to the middle thereof, 3. in reſpect of the whole world, in as much as they look towards the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> which the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Chriſtians turned to in their adoration, as is teſtified by <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian in Apologet. c.</hi> 16. and by <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Areop. in coeleſt. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erarchia, c.</hi> 11. quite contrary to the Temple of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> whoſe Holy of Holies or upper end was <hi>Weſtward.</hi> Indeed the Church
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101116:20"/>
built by Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> at <hi>Richelieu,</hi> a town of his own building too, hath its Choir <hi>Weſtward,</hi> and its entrance in at the <hi>East</hi> end thereof, which was ſo appointed by him, I ſuppoſe, leaſt otherwiſe it might ſpoil the faſhion of his town, a reſpect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had unto the model according to which it was to be built, and not out of an opinion of the indifferency of ſituation; for albeit he were contented to turn his face ſometimes <hi>Weſtward</hi> in his adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on when living; yet being dead he looks <hi>Eaſtward</hi> in the Chappel of his own building in the Colledge of <hi>Sorbon</hi> where he lyes buried. What was done by the ſaid Church at <hi>Richelieu,</hi> was intended by that in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> but it was not permitted to be conſecrated till the ſaid deſign was altered, which was done <hi>Bonis avibus</hi> too; for <hi>Covent-garden</hi> continnes a flouriſhing part of <hi>London</hi> ſuburbs, whereas <hi>Richelieu</hi> hath nothing in it of the aim of the ſaid Founder, [which was to make it a Univerſity for the ſtudy and teaching of Philoſophy in the <hi>French</hi> tongue] but is like a proud woman, that hangs all upon her back at once; for ſo is this empty of Students and riches, having nothing left to commend it beſides the <hi>ſuperbe</hi> name, ſet out with gay and uniform buildings, as if every houſe there were as a <hi>Rejection</hi> of the Cardinals magnifick Palace that ſtands by and would in time grow emulous of their mother tree, out of whoſe root they ſprang. But to return, 4 Our Churches are convenient for ſituation in reſpect of their parts within themſelves, having an upper end and a lower; this for the font to initiate and give firſt entrance into the Church by Baptiſm; that, for the holy Table which is for a ſpiritual repaſt to <hi>[adulte]</hi> perſons of years the middle for the <hi>Gatechumeni</hi> to ſtand between, 5. in reſpect of the fabrick of the whole, they being like <hi>naves inverſae,</hi> ſhips whoſe Keel is towards heaven. They have alſo <hi>ales</hi> or wings in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which are nothing elſe but continuations of Veſtries, built in reſemblance to Cabins in Ships, and were therefore called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>h. e.</hi> not as a <hi>pyxis</hi> to keep the Hoſt in, as the <hi>Pontificians</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for, but becauſe they were as Cabins for the Maſters of the ſhips to lodge in, derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>thalamus,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to bear, as Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> learnedly obſerves againſt them. Some Cathedrals are built with a ſingle Croſs, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting that whereon our Saviour was crucified [for ſince <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi>'s IN HOC VINCES, Churches have not only
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101116:20"/>
been ſo built in ſome places, but the ſails of ſhips have ever been furled up in manner of a Crucifix] ſome are built with a double Croſſe, the uppermoſt repreſenting that whereon the title was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>viz. INRI</hi> They had no way more ſuitable of enlarging ſuch fabricks, where beauty or neceſſity required it. I might juſtifie the building of Churches in ſuch figures as are moſt proper from that place of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 9. 4. <hi>Go through the midſt of the City, through the midſt of</hi> Hieruſalem, <hi>and ſet a mark upon the foreheads of them that ſigh,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. it is ſaid, <hi>ſlay utterly old and young, both maid and little children and women; but come not neer any man upon whom is the</hi> mark, <hi>and begin at my Sanctuary.</hi> This <hi>mark</hi> in the original is <hi>Tau,</hi> and ſo tranſlated in the Interl. Bibles, and the vulgar Latine by thoſe that were no boys (as <note n="*" place="margin">Viz. Dr. Owen in his <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. l. <hi>4.</hi> digreſ. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>ſome would make them) or ſomething leſs for skill in Hebrew Grammar. Now this letter <hi>Tau,</hi> the laſt in the Hebrew Alphabet was written in the old <hi>Samaritan</hi> character, like a croſſe, as is witneſſed by St. <hi>Hierome</hi> upon the place, and that it was ſo upon the ancient coines they do not deny; and it is ſo both in the Alphabet of coines, and in the Alphabet of <hi>Azarius</hi> exhibited by <hi>Vilalpandus</hi> upon <hi>Ezekiel:</hi> all that they can ſay is, that thoſe coines are <hi>mala mex,</hi> and a kind of counterfeit things; 'tis true, that 1000. counterfeits of Jewiſh coines, and of Romans together, &amp;c. too have been made, which many do buy and furniſh their cloſets withall; all which may be called <hi>mala merx:</hi> But what is this to the genuine pieces, from whence theſe counterfeits were taken: I muſt therefore ſend them to find better arguments to prove their pretenſions, then yet they have brought to light, mean while reſt in this opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> that in caſe we build any conſecrated Temple, or make any holy ſign, as that in Baptiſm is, the fitteſt figure is that of the Croſſe: This letter <hi>Tau</hi> is the firſt letter of <hi>Torab, h. e.</hi> the Law whereby God would ſave the obſervers of his Laws from the common deſtruction, which is a figure of thoſe that ſhall be freed from the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world, being firſt marked by Chriſt our high Prieſt, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied thereby a man clothed in linnen with a Writers Inkhorn by his ſide, <hi>v.</hi> 2. 'tis true, that in our tranſlation it is only [ſet a mark] or as it is in the margin, mark a mark: but why may not this mark be a croſſe rather then any other, having theſe ſignifications in it? neither can any other, I am ſure, no better be given to it; nor yet
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101116:21"/>
more natural: For, 1. It is a figure that is <hi>primo cognitum</hi> of all other, as conſiſting of the concourſe of lines at right angles, which are the common meaſure of themſelves and all other angles what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; and let the Croſſe be made never ſo irregularly, yet if the lines be ſtreight, it will have four angles equal to four right ones<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Secondly, contumous quantity being <hi>diviſibilis in ſemper diviſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liora,</hi> this cannot be done but in <hi>partes equales,</hi> &amp; theſe equal parts cannot be ſet out ſo well as by a Croſſe, whether it be in <hi>plana</hi> or in <hi>cubo, ſc.</hi> in a plain <hi>ſuperficies,</hi> or a <hi>cubical</hi> body, unto the firſt of which all <hi>ſuperficies,</hi> unto the latter, all <hi>ſolids</hi> are to be reduced in meaſuration; as for example, in <hi>oblong ſuperficies</hi> between the unequal ſides.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/> I find a mean proportional, this is the ſide of a ſquare equal to the <hi>ſuperficies</hi> given again in a triangular, between the <hi>perpendicular,</hi> and the half baſe: I find a mean proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, this is the ſide of a ſquare equal to the triangle given: <figure/> The ſame rule ſerves for a <hi>rhomboides</hi> 
                  <figure/>: Thirdly, 'tis no marvel that <hi>Tau</hi> ſhould be originally a Croſſe, when ſo many letters in the Hebrew Alphabet [I ſpeak not of thoſe that follow the caprice of Scribes, or founders of lies] have their geneſis from the parts of a Croſſe, <figure/> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> other letters there be as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which ſeems to be as ſo many chips cut off it by the glance of the tool that hewed them; and of theſe letters all others ſeem to be compounded, as is obvious to our obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; other reaſons might be given for the natural apprehenſion of the Croſſe, but theſe ſhall ſuffice here to infer the probability of that mark to be the ſign of the Croſſe, and the fitneſs of building of Churches after the manner of a Croſſe; Which if they would have demoliſhed becauſe built after the manner of a Croſſe, they muſt pull down many Towns in <hi>England,</hi> which ſeem of deſign to be built after the manner of a Croſſe, eſpecially <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> whoſe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure ſtands thus, 
<figure/>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:101116:21"/>
                  <hi>a</hi> The Ailes gate, <hi>b</hi> the North gate, <hi>c</hi> the South gate, <hi>d</hi> the Weſt gate, <hi>e</hi> the Colledge &amp; St. <hi>Maries</hi> pariſh Church, <hi>f</hi> the Caſtle, <hi>g</hi> the middle row. The Eaſt Weſt and South ſtreets make up a compleat Croſſe; the middle row <hi>g</hi> the Crucifix upon it, the Colledge, &amp;c. <hi>e</hi> our Saviours mother and other Saints lamenting his condition, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their own, the Caſtle <hi>f</hi> the ſouldiers that brought to executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and derided him. And that theſe were the glory of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, has been in effect confeſſed in the Pulpit by one of the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenteſt Independents in the Nation, when he prayed God to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the <hi>Univerſities,</hi> the only remaining glory, as he ſaid, of our Nation, the Cathedrals being then taken away: But what figure ſoever the Churches had been built in, they would have found matter of exception againſt them. Had they been round as thoſe of the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guenots</hi> are, then they had been circles to conjure by, a figure beſt pleaſing to the Devil, as being moſt contrary to a Croſſe: A Croſſe then would have pleaſed them, which now they abhor as a matter of high ſuperſtition, but as the caſe ſtands<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they ſeem to be pleaſed with Churches of the ſame figure as their Religion reſembles. <hi>h. e.</hi> a meere <hi>Parabola.</hi> I come now from the conveniency to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of theſe Churches in ſome regards; for albeit before their conſecration they were in the power of thoſe that gave them, to give or not to give them to thoſe uſes; yet ſince that they are thereby given to God, and ſuch things God accepts for his own, it follows that <hi>Quicunque alienaverit ſacrilegus erit.</hi> He will rob not only a ſociety of men that live by and in them, but God alſo, as <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> did in another thing, but in the like caſe. But I have hinted from whence theſe exceptions ſprang at firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>Stork, Stubner,</hi> and <hi>Muntzer:</hi> And from the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning it is that their exceptions againſt learned men iſſues forth, when Coblers and Furriers are ſet up to preach in hog-houſes, and naſty places. And thoſe things before mentioned would never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>ſtumbling block to the Gentiles,</hi> as they pretend, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by their crying up of their Goddeſs <hi>Diana,</hi> the magnificence of whoſe Temple allured the world to worſhip her; and had they had Temples dedicated to the true God of more magnificence then <hi>Diana</hi>'s was of, they would have cried as loud as they did of <hi>Diana,</hi> that <hi>Great is the God of Heaven;</hi> whereby it is evident that ſuch things may be outward motives of bringing men to the Church, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101116:22"/>
ſo of ſeeing and learning what is there taught and practiſed, which they would not have been allured to, by an aſſembly of men met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a pigs-coat; nay it ſeems by the very argument of theſe men themſelves, that had the Jews beheld as magnifick Temples under Chriſtianity as they had in judaiſme, they would have become Chriſtians. But I ſhall believe neither the one, nor the other touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Jews, till God takes away the vail drawn over their hearts. The wrath of God is not come on them for that, but for crucifying the <hi>Lord of Glory,</hi> and for imprecating his blood upon themſelves and theirs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</head>
               <p>BUt, ſay they, <hi>The bare rejection of truth, and imbracing of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is not all the evil that the Nations generally are engaged in by the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>but for to compleat and fill up the meaſure of their iniquities, like</hi> Nebuchadnezzar, <hi>nothing leſs muſt be inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the ſervants of the moſt high God, that cannot bow down to the golden image of their inventions, then the fiery furnace of perſecution, many times unto death it ſelf.</hi> Whereunto I anſwer, firſt, That this is as clear as the Sun ſhines to be a ſcandal upon the good Laws of the Land, as if they were like thoſe of <hi>Draco</hi> the <hi>Athenian,</hi> of which it was ſaid that they were written in bloud, in as much as they puniſhed every offence alike, without ſuiting the penalty to the quality of the crime. Indeed this would quickly leave no criminals or no men in the Commonwealth, in caſe all offenders were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the ſame puniſhment how various ſoever their offences were, and that puniſhment were death. But I ſhall take the pains to ſhew that this very thing which they here impute to us, is applicable to themſelves. Thus then the Harlot in the <hi>Revelation</hi> is ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it's a counterfeit of the woman, in the twelfth chapter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that is the Church which is there deſcribed to have the Moon under her feet. She is not then the true woman, but a counterfeit, an image only. Now an image may conſiſt of different parts and matters as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> did, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. and yet the ſame image ſtill: ſo does this Harlot conſiſt of ſeveral men of ſeveral Sects, of ſeveral principles, in ſeveral ages, and yet the ſame Harlot, the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101116:22"/>
ſame Antichriſt ſtill, as long as the Devil works generally alike in them all, whereof the <hi>Pope</hi> makes one part, the <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, other Sects [if this be not comprehenſive of all] others, and all this is done by dreams, as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s image was. And becauſe men will not fall down and worſhip their dreams for truths, notwithſtanding they comprehend not <hi>Heterodoxiſms</hi> only, but hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid blaſphemies againſt God and his Son Chriſt, and be deſtructive of the Ordinances of God, and witneſſes of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> they are mad, they ſend forth excommunications, they preach and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice rebellion, they ſay they fight for God, when they fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King Gods Vicegerent, that they are the ſervants of the moſt high God, when it is plain that the Devil carries them ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptive at his will, that they would have Chriſt reign over them, when the Devil reigns in them, that they defend our liberties when they carry us captive, that they maintain our proprieties when they plunder us, that it's done in faith, when it's without charity, that it is to vindicate the liberty of Religion and freedom of the Goſpel, when they make their own paſſion and intereſt the meaſure of it. Hereupon the beautiful feet of thoſe that ſhould be the meſſengers of peace, become ſwift to ſhed bloud, the hands that have been accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to handle the holy Sacraments appear like <hi>Bellona</hi>'s hands embru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in gore, the cloven tongues of the Spirit are turn'd into ſerpents tongues, <hi>Trifidaſque linguas. (Sen. in Medea)</hi> &amp; dividing themſelves into three parts, their mouths that ſhould dictate the oracles of God, are like the mouth of a Leviathan, <hi>Job</hi> 41. 19. whoſe breath kindleth coals, and a flame goes out of it; that hair that ſhould be like that of the ancient of days, white as wool, to note the incorruption of truth, is ſpeckled like ſnakes, ravel'd into philtres, and rowled into treſſes like ſerpents. And could their ſeduced proſelytes but ſee all this, they would want no Rhetorick to undeceive them: but this they have added to the very <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of their impoſture, <hi>ſo.</hi> that the Devil appears in the mantle of <hi>Samuel,</hi> and I know not by what <hi>Gygs</hi> ring they walk inviſible, or elſe God hath ſuffered the eyes of the people to be blinded that they cannot ſee, or by the ſame juſt judgement, hardened their hearts, that they cannot perceive. But if theſe men be in the right, then let the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude,</hi> and the 2 of <hi>Pet. c.</hi> 2. be for ever, as ſome of them would have them, not canonical; for would they lay aſide abſtruſe and obſcure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101116:23"/>
impoyſoned with their preſumptious gloſſes upon them, which are written rather to exerciſe their humility, then cheriſh their preſumption, and ſeriouſly apply thoſe evident truths to their own practices, they would find every verſe, like <hi>Prometheus</hi> his Eagle, feeding upon their inward parts, animated by that lying ſpirit as by fire ſtollen from heaven. And ſince theſe authours men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>France</hi> and other places, what civil commotions have been cauſed there, in order to worſhip. I ſay that they aroſe from men of their generation. For I muſt remember them out of Mr. <hi>Camden</hi>'s <hi>Eliz.</hi> That it is about ſeventy years ſince that Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> laboured of ſuch a monſter as this, which as an image conſiſted of ſeveral parties as of ſeveral materials, one affecting <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> another <hi>Olygarchy,</hi> another <hi>Democracy,</hi> another <hi>Anarchy,</hi> all diſliking the preſent form <hi>Monarchy.</hi> Mean while the preachers eaſily ſnatching the people about by this common motion, became the trumpeters of ſedition, till after the aſſaſinate of their King, they began to diſagree as much about their new Governours, as before they had done about their government. Theſe men in <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> or <hi>Amſterdam</hi> might have paſſed for <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> and had they kept company with <hi>Knipperdoling, John</hi> of <hi>Leyden, Muntzer, Stork,</hi> or any of that Rabble, they had proved ſo indeed, and what they would have been here, we all know, the Devil working alike in them all, though of different Religions. And about this time it was, that the calamities which have befallen this Kingdom were a brewing [as you may read in the <hi>Engliſh Scottizing, and Scots Genevating for Diſcipline,</hi> ſet forth by Archbiſhop <hi>Bancroft]</hi> which theſe Authours here falſly aſcribe to the ſending the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Liturgy into <hi>Scotland.</hi> Suppoſe that, that had been the cauſe, I deny it to have been a juſt one; for let them tell me what warrant they have out of Scripture, or Orthodox Writer, of rebelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Sovereign under pretence of Religion, be it true or falſe. If ſo, where is their ſubject of paſſive obedience, they ſo much boaſt of? And if nothing can be a good ground of rebelling againſt the King, much leſs can it juſtify that which had no end but in the death of the King, and ſlavery of the people, whoſe liberty was pretended to be vindicated. And thus far they have but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, which we having anſwered, as you have heard, let us examine their proofs, or Logical part which all depends upon this one Syllogiſm.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:101116:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</head>
               <p>IF any Magiſtrate under heaven, in the daies of the Goſpel hath power to impoſe any thing in the worſhip and ſervice of God, it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him as he is a Magiſtrate only, or as a Chriſtian ſo conſidered, But that no ſuch power is given by God to any Magiſtrate appears.</p>
               <p>For anſwer to the firſt part hereof, I ſay that he hath power as he is a Magiſtrate only: and this power is given him of God, in as much as Magiſtracy is an Ordinance of God. All powers of the world whatſoever are from him, even thoſe of Tyrants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, though permiſſively only: Lawful powers are from him, as ordained by him. And as theſe are ordained by God, ſo hath he given them power in the worſhip and ſervice of God. For 1. The very Heathens have given the firſt place to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as knowing by Natures inſtinct that without Religion no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of a Commonwealth can be happily inſtituted or adminiſtred. It is an axiom drawn out of the fourth book of <hi>Plate de rep.</hi> that <hi>Religio eſt fundamentum reipublicae, &amp; potiſſima pars publici Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratus, &amp; vere arx atque propugnaculum conſtituendae reipubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae.</hi> without which all the parts of a Commonwealth, like the ſtrings of an inſtrument, will be out of tune, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and therefore another axiom follows thereupon, that <hi>non poteſt immutari ſtatus religionis ſine maximarum legum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutatione, &amp; propterea non eſt temere importanda in rempublicam nova religionis forma:</hi> becauſe it does diſmember and disjoynt the Commonwealth. St. <hi>Paul</hi> diſputing daily at <hi>Athens</hi> touching Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, was brought unto <hi>Areopagus</hi> to be judged by that Court, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 19. as upon whom the buſineſs of Religion was principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incumbent. <hi>Ezra</hi> received the power and juriſdiction from <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes</hi> ſpeedily to execute judgement upon all contumacious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the buſineſs of Religion, <hi>Ez.</hi> 7. 14. whether unto death or baniſhment, or confiſcation of goods, or impriſonment, <hi>Ez.</hi> 7. 25, 26. So did <hi>Cyrus</hi> and <hi>Dari<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> give permiſſion to the <hi>Jews</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edify the Temple; and to to ſacrifice therein, adding money to defray the charges; 2 <hi>Ch.</hi> 29. 15, and 30. 12. <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, Dan.</hi> 3. 29. commanded him to be hewed in pieces that ſhould blaſpheme the God of the Hebrews. Secondly, the Lawyers refer
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101116:24"/>
Religion to thoſe things which belong to the Law of Nation s, in as much as by the guidance of Nature we know that there is a God, which is to be reverenced, &amp; who knows not that to a Magiſtrate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, not only the adminiſtration of poſitive Laws, but of thoſe alſo that belong to the Laws of Nature. Thirdly, if it be the duty of a father of a family to inſtruct his children in the true Religion, and to reduce them from their deviations from it: how much more doth it appertain to the Magiſtrate, who is the father of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, to take care of the religion of his ſubjects. Fourthly, This is requir'd of a Magiſtrate in Scripture, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Kiſſe the Son,</hi> and <hi>ſerve the Lord in fear,</hi> which conſiſteth not only in the adoration of the Son of God [for that is common with him to every true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian] but alſo in the outward adminiſtration of his Kingdom. This therefore was the injunction laid upon the Kings of Iſrael to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved when God ſhould bring them into the Land he promiſed them, <hi>viz.</hi> when they ſit upon the throne that they write them a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of the Law in a book out of that which is before the Prieſts and Levites, <hi>Deu.</hi> 17. 18. And at the inauguration of <hi>Joaſh</hi> the book of the Law of God was given into his hands, 2 <hi>Ch</hi> 23. 18. And fifthly, The examples of holy Princes do teach us that Magiſtrates have the care of Religion committed to them, ſuch were <hi>Moſes, Joſhuah, David, Solomon, Aſa, Jeboſhaphat, Joſiah, Ezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> &amp;c. And albeit theſe men will (what never any, but perſons ſprung from <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> did) reject all examples and teſtimonies out of the Old Teſtament [unleſs it be to ſerve their own turn, [as I have formerly ſhewed them to have done in the date of their Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, the eighth day of the third moneth] yet this, I ſuppoſe, they will hardly deny, namely, that a father under the Goſpel hath and ought to have a care of his children, in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, their own practice witneſſes as much, in that they inſtruct their children in their own principles, and keep them from Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm and Steeple-houſes [as they call the Churches] which they hold to be unlawfull, &amp;c. Now if theſe things are given to a father of a family whoſe power cannot reach as far as a Kings, much more to a King or other Magiſtrate, whoſe juriſdiction is of a larger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and whereof a family is but an integral part. And the ſame compariſon holds between a Maſter and a Magiſtrate, which is not only a father of his Countrey, but a maſter too: for in <hi>Rome,</hi> he
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101116:24"/>
who was Dictatour and bare the power ſupream, was called the Maſter of the people: whence it is that <hi>Cicero</hi> calls <hi>Caeſar</hi> Maſter, and <hi>Livie</hi> witneſſeth that the Dictatour was ſo added to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, that he might be their Moderatour and Maſter. If therefore it be lawfull for a Maſter of a family, ſchool, or ſociety, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive and offenſive in Cauſe of Religion under the Goſpel, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their children, ſcholars, and ſervants, how much more is it given to a Magiſtrate towards his ſubjects, who bears the ſame relation to a Maſter of a family, ſchool, or ſociety, as the whole does to a part.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>ſay they,</hi> if Magiſtrates as ſuch have ſuch an authority, then all Magiſtrates in all Nations, have the ſame power, Then if we lived in <hi>Turkey,</hi> we muſt receive the <hi>Alcoran</hi> and be worſhippers of <hi>Mahomet;</hi> if in <hi>Spatu,</hi> be <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as in <hi>Hen. 8.</hi> his daies, ſometimes <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as in <hi>Edw. 6.</hi> his daies, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is the very argument of the <hi>Papiſts in Calvino Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſmo, l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10. and improved by <hi>Champnaeus.</hi> But its anſwered by <hi>Maſon de Miniſterio Anglicano, l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5. And hereunto I fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay, That as all Magiſtrates in all Nations have power in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, ſo they have the ſame power, but not the ſame skill to govern, nor the ſame Rule to go by in governing; as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ones Rule is his will, another's is the Law: and of thoſe that are limitted by Laws, ſome rule by ſome Laws; others, by other Laws different from them. So 1. in matters of Religion, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates do rule according to the book delivered unto them: ſome have only the book of Nature put into their hands, and theſe have a faculty thereby given them to rule and order Religion according to that, ſuch hath the <hi>Turk,</hi> and all unconverted Magiſtrates. Some have the Book of the Old Teſtament delivered into their hands; and thoſe were ſometimes to rule according to that. So <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 18. it is ſaid, that <hi>when the King ſitteth upon the throne of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, be ſhall write him a copy of the Law in a book, out of that which is before the Prieſts and Levites, and it ſhall be with him, and he ſhall read therein all the daies of his life.</hi> And in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23. 11. it is ſaid that <hi>they brought out the Kings ſon, and put upon him the crown, and gave him the Teſtimony, and made him King,</hi> &amp;c. Some have the book of the New Teſtament put into their hands; and theſe are to order matters of Religion according to this: ſuch
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101116:25"/>
are all Chriſtian Kings, Princes, and Governours. Now whereas they would infer that therefore we muſt receive the ALCORAN, be Papiſts and I know not what, according to the ſole will of our Governours whatever perſwaſion they be of; This is not ſo: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit whatſoever they enjoyn according or not contrariant to theſe Books be firm and inviolable, yet whatſoever they determine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out or againſt theſe Books is void: ſo that the Turk hath not a ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and inviolable power given him to impoſe the ALCORAN and to enjoyn worſhip to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> in as much as no ſuch rule is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the book of Nature delivered unto him: Nature dictates no ſuch thing, and therefore ſuch a thing muſt be given by God himſelf, who is above Nature, or elſe it muſt be acknowledged to be, as it is indeed, a meer Impoſture. The Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had power given them to Rule by the Book of the Law in matters of Religion: But they that did ſet up Idolatry, contrary to the contents of that Book, did abuſe their power, and in that regard their Injunctions were of no force. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> hath the book of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment put into his hands, and conſequently the moral part of the Old Teſtament but he permitting Idolatry, and giving up his power into the Popes hands, whoſe Vaſſal he becomes, [as all Popiſh Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces do] he abuſes this power. If any other Prince does the like, he is not to be followed therein: He is nevertheleſſe paſſively to be obeyed; that is, a Chriſtian-Subject is not to reſiſt him, but he is to ſubmit to ſuch puniſhment as he ſhall inflict upon him, in as much as an errour in the underſtanding, upon which proceeds the abuſe of his power, which is accidental, does not make void his power, which is eſſential to him, and whereunto every ſoul is ſubject, <hi>in foro externo:</hi> The Spirit of God ſayes in the ſame breath, <hi>Fear God, honour the King.</hi> He who doth any thing by command from the King contrary to the command of God, does not fear God; and he that rebelleth or reſiſteth [for it is all one] the King, upon any pretence whatſoever, doth not honour the King, but deſpiſe him, yea and reſiſt the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to themſelves damnation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. The ſame may be ſaid of the Turks forbidding a man to believe in Chriſt, or any thing of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity to ſalvation, wherein he is not to be obeyed, in as much as it is not a thing contrary to the Law of Nature, but of the Inſtitution of the God of Nature, that we <hi>believe in God, and in him whom he hath ſent, Jeſus Chriſt his Son.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:101116:25"/>
                  <hi>2. Secondly, they ſay, that ſince our Saviour tells us, that</hi> all power is given him in heaven and in earth, if the Magiſtrates have any ſuch power, it is committed to them from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and written in the New Teſtament.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, That no power could be given to Chriſt, which he had not before, being God eternal, and therefore we muſt ſay, that all power was in Chriſt naturally and eſſentially. But there's a power given him [which he had not but by gift] diſpenſatorily, as he is the Mediatour, which is nothing elſe but a Rule which he obſerves in the ſalvation of men, as a thing added to his eſſential power. Now infidel Kings receive their power from Chriſts natural and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential power only, being not bound to believe in Chriſt, nor to obſerve the Rules he gives till revealed unto them, but to obſerve the Law of Nature given in Paradiſe according to which they and their ſubjects (infidels) ſhall be judged. Wherefore I hope they will not ſend us to find this in the New Teſtament. Though they ſhould, I have a text for them there too, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 19, 20, 21. <hi>Becauſe that which may be known of God, is manifeſt in them, for God hath ſhewed it unto them.</hi> Kings that believe, receive their power, not from Chriſts natural and eſſential pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er onely, but from his diſpenſatorie power, as he is Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and great Lawgiver to his Church: by which power he does not take away the former, but eſtabliſh it rather. Let them ſhew me where he takes it away? If they do, they muſt ſhew me a contradiction to the words of the Apoſtle, who ſaies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers.</hi> Oh but <hi>theſe were hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Magiſtrates,</hi> ſay they. Whereunto I anſwer, that if every ſoul muſt be ſubject to Heathen Magiſtrates, much more then, to thoſe that believe in Chriſt, who came not to deſtroy, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctify and perfect the Law of Nature.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3. The third thing that they ſay, will fall to the ground upon what has been already ſpoken,</hi> viz. <hi>That</hi> the Apoſtles themſelves refuſed to be obedient to their Rulers, <hi>Act. 4. 19, 20.</hi> When they were commanded to forbear that which they judged to be a part of the worſhip of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That their Rulers enjoyned them not to preach Chriſt, and therein they did well to diſobey, for otherwiſe they had not feared God, in as much as, though their Rulers were above them,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:101116:26"/>
God was above them both. Yet had they not obeyed paſſively as contented to ſuffer reproach for the name of Chriſt, they had erred againſt the fifth commandment of <hi>Honour thy father and mother,</hi> which is equivalent to that in the New Teſtament, <hi>ſo. Honour the King,</hi> which is clean contrary to rebelling or reſiſting him. Theſe things are ſo plain, that I wonder any ſhould ſtumble at them, but that they are ſo blinded with paſſion and ſelf intereſt, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not apprehend them.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4. They ſay in the fourth place, That</hi> all Emperours before <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> were Heathens, and that therefore thoſe texts of Scripture that call for obedience to Magiſtrates, cannot intend obedience in matters of faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Do they think that the New Teſtament, whereof theſe texts of Scripture are a part, belonged only to thoſe that then lived, and not to us alſo? if not, then this text of Scripture, <hi>viz. ye believe in God, believe in me alſo,</hi> belonged not unto us, but to them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that lived then. <hi>As we have oportunity let us do good unto all men, eſpecially to them that are of the houſhold of faith, Gal.</hi> 6. 10. with all the reſt of the New Teſtament belonged not to us, but to them only. They would have the Old Teſtament caſhier'd: and if they reject the New, what Canon ſhall be left to walk by? no faith, no hope, no charity would be then neceſſary; this would be a liberty indeed, here would be room enough for an <hi>Enthuſiaſt</hi> to wander in. But ſtay a little, Thoſe texts of Scripture belonged not to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, who lived in thoſe daies, but to us alſo [as does all the reſt of the New Teſtament, who live under Chriſtian Magiſtrates, and therefore they muſt intend obedience in matters of faith, and that becauſe they are words indefinitely ſpoken, which we are not to reſtrain to our own ſenſe, but rather to enlarge them into an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal propoſition: <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher power,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? In <hi>all</hi> things: for 'tis in <hi>materia neceſſaria,</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly equivalent to an univerſal.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I anſwer, that albeit all Magiſtrates were now Heathens, yet it would comprehenſively intend obedience to them in matters of faith [either active or paſſive] as to competent judges of them. <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix</hi> was a Heathen, <hi>Act.</hi> 24. yet he being the Deputy of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour, St. <hi>Paul</hi> is accuſed before him by <hi>Tertullus:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, ſaies St. <hi>Paul, I am judged concerning the Reſurrection from
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101116:26"/>
the dead, h. e.</hi> concerning a principal Article of faith. The ſame controverſie came ſhortly after before <hi>Feſtus,</hi> wherein St. <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf acknowledged his right of judging: <hi>Here,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>I ought to be judged.</hi> Again, fearing the injuſtice of the Judge, He <hi>appealed unto Caeſar,</hi> who of right was the ſupreme Judge, and a Heathen too. Other examples might be alledged out of primitive Authors, but in vain, againſt men who will deny the Sun ſhines, unleſs proved by expreſſe words of the New Teſtament. But this being the very Argument of <hi>Champnaeus</hi> the <hi>Sorboniſt,</hi> page 580. I leave it further to be anſwered, if need be, by <hi>Francis Maſon de Miniſt. Angl. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5. Fifthly, They ſay,</hi> That if Magiſtrates as ſuch have power from God, in the dayes of the Goſpel, to command in ſpiritual matters, and to puniſh them that obey not, then muſt Chriſtians ſurely be actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally obedient, not only for wrath, but for conſcience ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I deny this Argument, for in commanding any thing contrary to the Word and Will of God, they abuſe their power, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through ignorance or wilfulneſſe, and in that caſe meerly paſſive obedience is to be yielded; for all things of practice are either ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely unlawful, and in ſuch the Magiſtrate is not to be obeyed, and that for conſcience ſake; becauſe God, or Nature, which is the voice of God, is to be obeyed before men; or elſe abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and in ſuch no man can make a queſtion, whether Magiſtrates be to be obeyed or not; or indifferent, which ſtand in <hi>Equilibrio</hi> between good and evil; the grains of the Magiſtrates authority gives weight to that ſide it is put into, which muſt therefore incline us to obedience for conſcience ſake; not that humane Laws can be properly ſaid to bind the conſcience by the ſole authority of the Law-givers, but they do it partly by the equity of the <hi>Laws,</hi> every man being obliged to promote that which conduceth to a publick good; and eſpecially by Divine Authority, which commandeth <hi>every ſoul to be ſubject to the higher powers,</hi> for his conſcience ſake, and not prudentially only. The Queſtion, ſayes the now Lord Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of <hi>Ireland Bramhall</hi> againſt <hi>Militiere,</hi> is ſoon decided. Juſt Laws of lawful Superiours, either Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, have au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to bind the conſcience in themſelves, not for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:101116:27"/>
But it is anſwered, <hi>ſay they,</hi> that all Magiſtrates, ſuppoſe whatever they impoſe. But the Queſtian is, who is to determine, for if the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate, or any other man or men have power from God to judge and determine, what is lawful for men to obey, then no room is left to them to diſpute any of his commands, and ſo the croſſe of Chriſt ceaſes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>The twentieth Article of our Church tells us, who is to determine how, and what?</hi> The CHURCH hath power to decree Rites or Ceremonies, and authority in controverſies of faith, and yet it is not lawful for the Church to ordain any thing that is contrary to Gods word, neither may it ſo expound one place of Scripture that it be repugnant to another: wherefore although the Church be a witneſs and keeper of holy Writ, yet as it ought not to decree any thing againſt the ſame, ſo beſides the ſame ought it not to enforce any thing to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved for neceſſity of ſalvation.</p>
               <p>All things contained in this Article are either indifferent, ſuch are Rites or Ceremonies, or neceſſary, ſuch are matters of faith: In the firſt it hath the power of ordaining, and yet it is not lawful to ordain any thing contrary to Gods Word. In the ſecond, it has the power of explanation, and therefore it is a witneſſe and keeper of holy Writ; yet it ought not ſo to expound one place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that it be repugnant to another, nor enforce any thing beſides the ſame to be believed as neceſſary to ſalvation. Now in caſe they ſhould decree any Ceremonies contrary to the Word of God, or impoſe any thing to be believed beſides the ſame, and ſo ſtir up the Magiſtrate to puniſh the contempt hereof, and the contemners be puniſhed accordingly; How is the Croſs of Chriſt made void in this caſe? Truly not at all, no more then <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> did make void the Croſſe of Chriſt, in refuſing to obey the Rulers of the <hi>Jews,</hi> forbidding them to ſpeak any more in the name of Jeſus, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. On the other ſide, what if no Rites or Ceremonies were decreed againſt the Word of God, and nothing impoſed upon them as neceſſary to ſalvation, but liberty were granted them to embrace nothing but what they could eaſily ſo allow, what ſword of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate would be drawn againſt them? And would not the Croſs of Chriſt ceaſe in their own ſenſe? So then, there were no better way of anſwering their Argument drawn from the ceaſing of the Croſſe of Chriſt, then by granting them their deſire.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:101116:27"/>
                  <hi>In the laſt place, they urge the example of</hi> Gallio <hi>the Roman Deputy of</hi> Achaia, Acts <hi>18. 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.</hi> Which worthy example, <hi>ſay they,</hi> if Magiſtrates would be perſwaded to follow, by judging and puniſhing only civil injuries and wrongs, and leaving ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual differences to be decided, and judged, and puniſhed by jeſus Chriſt according to the Goſpel, they would then find themſelves quickly free from many inconveniencies, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe men either ſpeak merrily, or elſe they wanted ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to prove their Aſſertion, who had none to cite, but that of the moſt corrupt Magiſtrate that ever ſate at the helm of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And behold the worthy example which he gives, <hi>He judged and puniſhed civil injuries,</hi> ſay they: But no ſuch matter; for the Inſurrection againſt <hi>Paul</hi> was a civil injury; they cryed for juſtice, or rather for injuſtice, in a tumultuous way againſt an innocent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and this <hi>Gallio</hi> never relieved, or as much as heard him ſpeak; which had he done, that innocent perſon, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> would haply have proved there as formerly he had done at <hi>Athens,</hi> that that God whom they ignorantly worſhipt did he declare unto them. And it ſeems that he gave the Greeks ſo good ſatisfaction in the matter, that they took <hi>Soſthenes</hi> the Ruler of the Synagogue, and probably the Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader of that Riot, and beat him before his face, as he ſate in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he not as much as rebuked them for it. As for the differences concerning Worſhip, it is ſaid of them, as well as of the civil ones, that <hi>Gallio cared for none of thoſe things;</hi> who probably might have the ſame deſign upon ſome of them in this kind of deportmentof his, that, <hi>Faelix</hi> had, <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 26. who <hi>hoped for a bribe to be given him by Paul:</hi> for this controverſie in all likelihood did not end here, though the event be omitted as impertinent to this ſacred ſtory. Mean while who can juſtifie this to be a worthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, which was ſo unworthily done, <hi>viz.</hi> that he would not heed things that concern the worſhip of God, which all the company judged of right to have appertained unto him? Neither did he himſelf deny that he <hi>had,</hi> but that he <hi>would</hi> have any thing to do with ſuch matters: For why, had not he as much authority as <hi>Areo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagus, Acts</hi> 17. which was the higheſt Court in <hi>Athens,</hi> and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteſt in the world in their proceedings, as we learn from <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> 1 <hi>Rhet.</hi> I. who took upon them to be Judges of ſuch matters, which the Philoſophers themſelves knew right well to appertain unto them, when they brought St. <hi>Paul</hi> to be tryed before them for his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:101116:28"/>
Doctrine: neither did the Apoſtle demurre to their Bill of informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as if it had not been within their Inſtructions for their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 10.</head>
               <p>ANd now having anſwered all their objections againſt a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates power of impoſing any thing in worſhip and ſervice of God, as he is a Magiſtrate only: I come to anſwer their ſecond part of the propoſition; and their reaſons to confirm it; <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>No Magiſtrate hath any ſuch power, as he is a Chriſtian.</hi> For anſwer whereunto, the contrary is evident. For as every member of the Church conſiſteth of an outward, as well as of an inward man, ſo the Government of the Church regardeth the outward, as well as the inward man, which conſiſteth in defending it, and delivering it from its enemies, as alſo in ordering and adorning it. As then, ſayes <hi>Grotius,</hi> the univerſal providence of God, which watcheth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all things though it be of it ſelf ſufficient to diſpoſe and execute every thing: yet for the demonſtration of its manifold wiſdome, it uſeth <hi>(poteſtatibus vicariis)</hi> the ſubſtitution of worldly powers, for the conſervation of the common ſociety of men, whence it is that they are called <hi>Gods.</hi> So alſo the ſpecial providence of God watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over his Church adopteth the ſame powers to himſelf as his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars and Patrons of the true faith <hi>kiſſing Chriſt,</hi> on whom alſo he confers his name, that is to ſay <hi>Annointed.</hi> Theſe are Kings &amp; Princes that govern together with Chriſt, not in equal ſhare of power, but by delegation and Vicarſhip only. Wherefore ſince things ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate do not croſſe one the other, neither does it misbecome the Majeſty of Chriſt to govern the principalls of his Kingdome imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by himſelf, the other partly by himſelf and partly by others, [as it is alſo moſt certain that he uſes the help of Angels] it follows that an earthly Kingdome even as if it reſpects holy things nothing hinders the heavenly and divine Empire of Chriſt. Adverſaries to this Doctrine on the one ſide are Papiſts and Presbyterians, both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging a temporal power in order to ſpirituals, but one of them putting this power into the hands of the Pope, the other into the hands of the Presbytery, thoſe conſtituting <hi>Imperium ſupra impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:101116:28"/>
theſe <hi>Imperium in imperio</hi> at leaſt. And they prove it by this argument; <hi>viz. The Magiſtrate is not of the eſſence of the Church, Therefore he's not neceſſary to the Government thereof.</hi> Anſwer, So neither is the Magiſtrate of the eſſence of a Phyſician, or a Merchant, or of a Maſon; yet he equally governs them all. They both object, that Kings are enjoyned to <hi>adore the Church.</hi> Anſwer, That is to ſay, to adore Chriſt in the Church, ſayes <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> there is a Trope in that part of the prophecy, neither can the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſayes he, be rigidly urged, unleſſe we will transferre that Majeſty to the Church, which is due to Chriſt who is prince of the Earth, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1. 5. It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied, but that as the Church-men have a diſtinct charge from and above others; yea even Kings themſelves, ſo there is a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable honour, and a ſubmiſſion due to them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17. <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your ſouls, as they that muſt give account,</hi> &amp;c. But I anſwer, that that is enjoined to Prince and people, <hi>viz.</hi> that they ſubmit themſelves to their Paſtors, <hi>(quatenus)</hi> as they <hi>ſpeak unto them the word of God,</hi> as the holy Ghoſt himſelf expounds it, v. 7. of the ſame Chapter. The King as he is a ſheep of the fold of Chriſt, is fed by the Biſhop or Paſtor. The Biſhop as a ſheep and a ſubject is fed by the King. The Biſhop as he teaches the King, and adminiſters holy things unto him, is above the King; that is, in the actual execution of his functions. But the King, as he eſtabliſhes theſe things by wholeſome Laws and commands, the Execution of theſe functions, is above the Biſhop: as the Sun is above the Moon, ſo the Moon may be above the Sun in a ſeveral reſpect. In reſpect of the diſtance from the Center of the World, the Sun is ever above the Moon; but in reſpect of Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion above the <hi>Horizon,</hi> the Moon may be &amp; is many times above the Sun: 2. Adverſaries to the foreſaid truth on the other ſide are thoſe with whom we have here to doe, who will not have the Church in any wiſe to be ſubject to any temporal power, in as much as <hi>they receive no ſuch from Chriſt.</hi> And to prove this, they urge here in the firſt place, That <hi>the Lord Jeſus Chriſt would never by any outward force compell men to receive him or his doctrine; for when his Diſciples, ſuppoſing he might uſe violence, [as under the Law] would have had him command fire to come down from heaven [as</hi> Elias <hi>did] to conſume them that would not receive him, Chriſt turned and rebuked them, ſaying, Ye know not what Spirit ye are of, the Son of man is not come to deſtroy
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101116:29"/>
mens lives, &amp;c. Luc.</hi> 9. 54, 55, 56.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The fact of <hi>Elias</hi> was extraordinary, and not juſtifiable by the Law, as they pretend; and ſo had this been in our Saviour, had he done it at their requeſt.</p>
               <p>But what had this been to the reciving of, or rejecting his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? The queſtion was touching the reception of his perſon, and the reaſon why thoſe <hi>Samaritans</hi> did not that act of civility to him as to entertain him, was becauſe either they ſuppoſed he would not have come upon their invitation, or elſe they would not invite him by reaſon of the animoſity that was between the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> as ſuppoſing that a friend of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> or an inhabitant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of neither deſerved, nor would accept of entertainment from them. And all this is clear by that conference of the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> with our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 4. 9. <hi>How is it,</hi> ſaies ſhe, <hi>that thou being a Jew askeſt drink of me that am a woman of Samaria? for the Jews have no dealings with the Samaritans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They further urge,</hi> John <hi>12. 47, 48.</hi> If any man hear my words, and believe not, I judge him not, for I came not to judge the world, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> There are two comings of Chriſt, one ſecretly and in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, that he might be judged and delivered up; the other mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly and majeſtickly that he might judge and remunerate. Now if Chriſt had come at firſt manifeſtly, he had never been crucified, for <hi>had they known it they would not have crucified the Lord of glory,</hi> and had he come majeſtickly with a great retinue of men or angels, which he might have commanded, the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Empire would have trembled at his preſence, ſo far would <hi>Pilate</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Procuratour have been from calling him before his tribunal. Nevertheleſs he did ſometimes uſe outward force in things appertaining to the worſhip of God, giving us thereby not only an adumbration of his ſpiritual Kingdome; but alſo a copy for Magiſtrates his Vicegerents to write after: for finding in the Temple <hi>thoſe that ſold oxen, ſheep, and doves</hi> (John 2. 14.) <hi>and the changers of money ſitting, he made a ſcourge of ſmall cords, and drove them all out of the Temple, and the ſheep and the oxen, and poured out the changers money.</hi> The like did he at another time, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 12, 13.</p>
               <p>For the diſtance of time and other circumſtances do prove that theſe were different acts of our Saviour as all Expolitours agree in this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:101116:29"/>
chapter from the ſecond to the thirteenth verſe, we read how he ſent two of his diſciples to preſs an aſs and a colt to carry him as it were to his Coronation, the which was obeyed, as all good ſubjects will their Sovereign: upon this aſs they put foot-clothes, and mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, the multitudes that met him ſpread their garments in the way, and ſtrewed it with branches of trees, crying on either ſide, <hi>Hoſanna to the Son of David,</hi> which is as much as to ſay, God ſave the King.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing he did after his coming to his Royal City was the reformation of things amiſs in the worſhip of God, <hi>went into the Temple, caſt out them that bought and ſold there:</hi> and there he cured the Kings evil too, <hi>h. e.</hi> ſuch diſeaſes as could not be cured but by this King of the <hi>Jews, v.</hi> 14. to teach all Kings which claim under him to employ their firſt and chiefeſt endeavours, after their enthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nization towards matters appertaining to the worſhip of God, and in works of charity towards ſuch as are in extream neceſſity. But ſhould our Saviour have uſed ſuch authority as often as occaſion preſented it ſelf, he would have been dreaded by all men, and crucified by none, and ſo prophecies would not have been fulfilled. Nevertheleſs he ceaſeth not to govern the Church, and in that ſenſe to <hi>judge the world</hi> by the Magiſtrates and Miniſters of the Word: for as <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaies, ſome actions of Chriſt in the Adminiſtration of his Kingdom are [as he calls them] Terminal, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as concern the beginning and ending of his adminiſtration. Such as concern the beginning of his admiuiſtration are the giving of Laws to his Church, under hope of eternal reward, or under pain of everlaſting damnation. That which concerns the end is a definitive juriſdiction at the laſt day, whereof as he hath done the one, ſo will he do the other himſelf alone, wherein he hath neither companion nor Vicegerent. Other actions of Chriſt are middle actions which come between theſe two terms, which partly concern the inward, partly the outward man. He acteth in the inward man by his Spirit ſeveral waies, <hi>viz.</hi> by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning, by converting, by ſtrengthening againſt temptations, by remitting or retaining ſins: yet he uſeth herein the outward mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of men, <hi>viz.</hi> of Paſtours, private men, Kings, every one in his ſeveral capacity, not as his Vicars or Vicegerents, theſe being not able to produce actions congenial to thoſe of Chriſt; but as his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters only, being apt to the production of ſuch actions as may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101116:30"/>
to the principal cauſe in matters aforeſaid. The actions of Chriſt that concern the outward man, conſiſt in defending and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Church, and in ordering and adorning the fame, as I ſaid before, and herein he uſes the Vicarſhip of his Magiſtrates<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as being apt to produce actions, in this reſpect congenial to his own, whom he therefore calls his Chriſts, <hi>h. e.</hi> his ANOINTED ones. And now whereas they ſay, that <hi>the Apoſtles were far from propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Goſpel by outward force.</hi> It is evident that the ordinary pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Apoſtles and of the Magiſtrates are different things: and who talks of propagating the Goſpel by outward force in either? Our King is the <hi>Deſender of the faith</hi> by the ſword that he holds: He goes not about to propagate it [if by propagation you mean plantation too] by force and violence. His Majeſty is furniſhed with an <hi>Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm</hi> of his learned and judicious Grandfather againſt that, <hi>viz. That it is never good to uſe too much ſeverity or bloudſhed in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: God never loves to plant his Church by violence and bloud.</hi> King <hi>James Aphoriſm</hi> 124. This his Majeſty leaves to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> cruelties in the <hi>Indies,</hi> and to their Inquiſition at home. And as for the Apoſtles, 'tis true they did not propagate the Goſpel by force, [though miſchief enough befell thoſe at whom they ſhook off the duſt of their feet] but yet they did govern eſtabliſhed Churches by force, which was a <hi>delivery over unto Satan,</hi> 1 Cor. 5. 5. <hi>for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the fleſh.</hi> And no other manner of puniſhment could be inflicted on offenders by them, while there was no temporal Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to impower them, or at moſt, none but ſuch as was like their beloved <hi>Gallio,</hi> who cared for none of thoſe things: yet this, TAKE HIM DEVIL, a man would think were more terrible then TAKE HIM JAYLOR, which they have printed in capital letters. Hence ſaies St. <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>I would that thoſe were cut off that trouble you,</hi> which had it been unlawfull to do, had been unlawfull in him to wiſh. As to the <hi>dividing of the inheritance</hi> which our Saviour refuſed [which they have put in the margin as a Buttreſs to hold up the arch and concameration of their argument] I ſay, that our Saviour would not always be vacant to ſatisfy the Avarice of a fellow, (who followed him for ſuch ends) to the neglect of a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs which he had but a ſhort time to diſpatch in the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though ſuch was his zeal of Gods houſe, that he could not forbear the rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Temple of ſacrilegious perſons. And thus their firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:101116:30"/>
falls to the ground with the improvement thereof, to make the ruine of it the greater.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 11:</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOr the further improvement of their foregoing argument, they alledge that place of the Apoſtle, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>1. 24.</hi> Not for that we have dominion over your faith, but are helpers of your joy: for by faith ye ſtand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> For expoſition whereof we ſay, that one thing amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that gave the Apoſtle occaſion of writing this Epiſtle, was the command given by him of delivering the inceſtuous perſon to Satan for the puniſhment of the fleſh. The Apoſtle having founded a Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> falſe Doctours building on this foundation per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded them [as theſe Authours would perſwade others in the like caſes] that St. <hi>Paul</hi> plaied the part of a proud domineering fellow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of one who took more upon him then belonged unto him. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Apoſtle excuſes himſelf and ſaies, that though neceſſity ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to a juſt ſeverity againſt the ſin, yet he aſſumed to himſelf no do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over their faith: no, for that were to pull up that foundation on which they ſtood, for by ſaith ye ſtand, and it were to deſtroy that which he had firſt layed.</p>
               <p>But then ſome may ſay, That though the Apoſtle had power in matters belonging to religious practice, yet it ſeems hereby that he had <hi>none in matters of faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereunto I anſwer, that it's one thing to have power <hi>in</hi> matters of faith, and another to have power <hi>over</hi> matters of faith. To have power <hi>over</hi> matters of faith is the prerogative of Chriſt alone, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the only Law-giver to his Church: to give Laws to the Church is <hi>act to terminalis,</hi> a terminal action of Chriſt, and herein he admits of no Vicarſhip or Vicegerency, as I have already ſaid, which is ſuch as the Popes pretend to in making new articles of faith: and that this is the meaning of this place, is the opinion of ſome that are no ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to our preſent adverſaries. Nevertheleſs to have power <hi>in</hi> matters of faith appertains to the Church, as I have ſaid before, out of the twentieth Article of our Church. And that the Apoſtle had ſuch a power is evident in the caſe of <hi>Hymenaus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> whom
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:101116:31"/>
St. <hi>Paul</hi> delivered unto Satan for making ſhipwrack concerning faith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 20. The ſame Apoſtle alſo ſayes, <hi>Whoſoever loves not the Lord Jeſus, let him be Anathema Maranatha,</hi> 1 Corinth. 16. 22. which ſome call an Excommunication unto death, others interpret it, The Lord cometh: they are both the ſame in effect, at leaſt they imply a greater degree of puniſhment then the former; The delivery unto Satan being only <hi>for the puniſhment of the fleſh, that the ſpirit may be ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> But the Lord coming once in vengeance, <hi>it is a fearful thing to fall into his hands,</hi> as ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 31.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond place they urge is,</hi> Matth. <hi>20. 25. ſc.</hi> The Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe dominon over them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but it ſhall not be ſo among you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That if it be ſo, that in the perpetual office of Paſtors the uſe of the Keyes has a kind of juriſdiction, as I have proved as well by poſitive places of Scripture, as by the real effects that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company it in the Apoſtles, we muſt ſearch out ſome other meaning by this place, then the denyal thereof to them. And then it muſt be either this, <hi>viz.</hi> you look after eaſie ſeats, like thoſe of the Kings of the Gentiles, who rule in eaſe and pleaſure; but it ſhall not be ſo among you: ſo Doctor <hi>Hammond.</hi> Or elſe it muſt be this, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Apoſtles were not to ſtrive for Dominion one over ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but to content themſelves with what they had over the Churches. Or laſtly, it muſt be that which I find in the Treatiſe of the power of the Pope touching the book of <hi>Saternelly</hi> the Jeſuite, written <hi>Anno</hi> 1626. <hi>The Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe dominion over them: but it ſhall not be ſo among you;</hi> that is, you ſhall not exerciſe dominion over the Nations by a temporal ſword, whereunto you your ſelves are ſubject, as is learnt from the example of <hi>Paul,</hi> who declined not the juriſdiction of <hi>Caeſar, Acts</hi> 25. But which expoſition ſoever of theſe three obtains, how does this prove what theſe men have in deſign, <hi>viz.</hi> that no Chriſtian Magiſtrate is to be a Defender of the Faith? If they will grant him to be a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, they muſt allow him a ſuperiority, and veſt him in a power, elſe they will but mock him: and this power extends to matters appertaining to the worſhip of God, as has been likewiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:101116:31"/>
                  <hi>The hird place, 1</hi> Pet. <hi>5. 2, 3.</hi> Feed the flock of God—neither as being Lords over Gods heritage, but being enſamples to the flock.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By what has been ſaid it is evident, that they had a power over the flock of Chriſt, and that not only a power accompanying the Word preached, but a power of overſight; for ſo much is clear out of the very place they here quote, <hi>viz.</hi> v. 2. <hi>Feed the flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof:</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 28. they are called <hi>Overſeers</hi> (the very name <hi>Biſhop is an Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer.)</hi> This power was exerciſed then not in doctrine only, but in diſcipline too: This diſcipline reached to the puniſhing of the body. Therefore we muſt diſtinguiſh of power: As 1. That there is a power inſtituted by Chriſt, or exerciſed by his Apoſtles, as has been evidenced: That ſuch a power may be exerciſed no man can well deny, for whoſoever does, is a Heretick. 2. There is a power of confederation or conſent: the which confederation or conſent was either inſtituted in Primitive times, and derived down from thence to theſe our dayes, ſuch as is juriſdiction meerly eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical; and who diſobeys or ſeparates from this power, is a Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick at the leaſt: or elſe it has been taken up by particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations or Conventicles of men, and this is the power that theſe men would have, which is a meer mock power, under which they will play faſt and looſe at their pleaſure, not unlike that of your <hi>Epiſcopus puerorum,</hi> ſerving only for a Chriſtmaſſe ſeaſon, condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Council of <hi>Baſil</hi> in <hi>Pragmatica Sanctione,</hi> fol. 173: 3. There is a power neither of Gods donation, nor of Apoſtolical preſcription, nor of Eccleſiaſtical Inſtitution, nor of congregational confederation [which I ſaid before to be no proper power at all, in as much as it is not any way obligatory to him who is under it] but of mens own aſſumption, which is either <hi>Imperium ſupra Imperium;</hi> ſuch is the Popes: or <hi>Imperium in Imperio &amp; ab Imperio avulſum;</hi> ſuch is the Presbyterians, as it hath been practiſed in <hi>Scotland.</hi> Or which is Tyrannical in the execution of it, by impoſing new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of faith or Doctrine, contrary to the form of ſound words, as the Pope does do, or cutting off mens heads by inſpiration, as ſome of the other limb of Antichriſt, the Fanaticks have done: and ſo they are not to lord it over Gods heritage.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:101116:32"/>
The fact of <hi>Thomas Schucker,</hi> the Diſciple of <hi>Melohior Rinchius,</hi> is not [unleſſe it be for the horridneſſe of it] to be omitted. This <hi>Schucker</hi> in the middeſt of a numerous Aſſembly of his own gang, pretending he was inſpired from Heaven, cryed, <hi>Woe, woe, woe,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a Sword to be brought him, and withall he called to his Brother <hi>John</hi> to kneel down upon his knees, his Parents with others asking him what he meant by this preparation, he bade them be of good chear, he being about to do nothing but what ſhould be revealed unto him from the heavenly Father. The eyes and minds of all being intent upon this new ſpectacle, this mad Prophet drew the Sword, and therewith divided his ſaid Brothers head from his ſhoulders, which ſtruck his Parents with great grief of heart, and the reſt with terrour. Being apprehended by the Magiſtrate, who would allow him no more liberty of conſcience [for if he had, his own head might have gone after] He ſuffered condign puniſhment for this his cruel fratricide, never all this while repenting of the crime, but conſtantly affirming, that this will of God was revealed unto him from Heaven. This Tragedy happened in <hi>Fano Galli. Anno</hi> 1527. And whether ſome men of this Generation have not dyed much like him, I leave it to thoſe that beheld them.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, as theſe men further alledge, that the <hi>Apoſtles were Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours for the Prince of Peace, and in his ſtead did pray the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers to be reconciled to God.</hi> And what if they would not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Goſpel, but remain without the pale of the Church? <hi>what had they to do to judge thoſe that were without?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 12. What could be expected from ſuch, leſſe then <hi>revilings, perſecutions, defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations?</hi> And what leſſe is expected by God from them, then <hi>bleſſing, ſufferings, intreatings, patience, long-ſuffering, love unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c.?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 12.</head>
               <p>THe next place alledged by them is, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. The Parable of the Tares; whereof it is ſaid, <hi>Let both grow together till the Harveſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:101116:32"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I agree with them, that this place does not only reſpect the ſecond, but the firſt Table, the ſubject whereof is the worſhip of God. But withall I anſwer firſt, with that Expoſitor they mention, that it ſeems not to note the duty of the civil Magiſtrate, but the event of Gods Providence, namely, that God would permit the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitation of the wicked in the world with the juſt; not that the Magiſtrates or Miniſters ſhould permit them, and not by civil pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment or eccleſiaſtical remove them out of the Church or world, if the quality of the offence ſo required it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſay they,</hi> If men did not fight againſt the truth, they would not ſo eminently contradict their own ſayings, for who can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that it ſhould be the mind of God to permit the cohabitation of the wicked in the world with the juſt, as aforeſaid, and yet the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ſhould not permit them, but remove them by civil puniſhment out of the world? Hath the Magiſtrate power to remove thoſe out of the world, that God would have permitted to live? How ſoon may a Magiſtrate, if guided by ſuch a doctrine, bring the bloud of the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent upon himſelf and Nation?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here is no contradiction at all: neither doth a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate bring innocent bloud upon himſelf by going about to put thoſe to death [if they deſerve it] whom the event of Gods providence keeps alive. When a Traytour or Murderer makes an eſcape, the event of Gods Providence keeps him alive, whom the Magiſtrate would have put to death, and this without bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing innocent bloud upon himſelf. <hi>Abraham</hi> did well in going about to ſacrifice his Son <hi>Iſaack,</hi> having a command from God to do it, Yet the event of Gods Providence kept him alive, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 22. The <hi>Gibeonites</hi> were of the <hi>Hivites,</hi> whom God commanded the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to deſtroy, yet the event of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence kept them alive, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 9. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from God to fight againſt the <hi>Benjamites</hi> the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, yet the event of Gods providence gave them the better till the third Encounter, <hi>Judges</hi> 20. How theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars came to paſſe, may be read in their ſeveral ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:101116:33"/>
And how ſuch events may happen frequently under a Magiſtate u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his power, is thus made good. The wiſe Creator of all the World having afforded to every creature, a means moſt ſuitable to its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for the accompliſhment of its end and perefection, and for the removal of impediments which lie in its way thereunto, has done no leſſe to man in as much as for the encouragement of his obedience, and the removal of ſin out of the way to happineſſe; [both which are moral things] he plies him with exhortations, comminations, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, curſes, examples, precepts, which are moral too; and all this may be done by the Miniſters of the word, or of others in their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities. And becauſe, if he ſtayed here, the major part, which have leſſe of Natures firſt inſtitution in them, would be never the better for all theſe; he hath ordained the Magiſtracy, ſo to be <hi>a terrour to evil works to execute wrath on them that do evil,</hi> Rom. 13. without which no man would be able to maintain his proprieties in goods and lands, preſerve his life and liberty, and conſequently all civil ſociety [which not men only, but even beaſts, birds, fiſhes, and in ſects them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſeem to affect] would fall to the ground. Yet let the Magiſtrate do what he can [and let him do but Juſtice] the wicked will have a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitation among the Juſt, and that for theſe reaſons; <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe he is not omniſcient and ſees not all wickedneſſe: 2. although he ſees it, yet he may not by teſtimonies be able to convince all men of their wicked deeds: 3. becauſe that though he may convince, yet all wickedneſſe is not capital whereof perſons may be convinced, without which a man cannot be taken out of the world: and this is the event of Gods providence. If they ſay that he might have uſed natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral means to obſtruct ſo great an evil as ſin is, and to advance the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of man, I ſay then, either the means muſt be made connatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to man, or man to the means: If the firſt, this is done already, in as much as moral and civil means are moſt connatural to man, a free agent and <hi>animal politicum.</hi> If the ſecond, its impoſſible to be done in as much as it were to make him an animate thing, or at the leaſt a Brute, which work, this without choice and that without proper appetition; and conſequently he muſt not have made him at all: for it is well ſaid of <hi>Lactantius de falſa ſapientia,</hi> which is of his works, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 18. Who conſidering the devotion of <hi>Plato,</hi> who gave thanks to Nature for three things. 1. That he was born a man, and not a beaſt. 2. That he was a man rather then a woman, a <hi>Grecian</hi> and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:101116:33"/>
not a <hi>Barbarian.</hi> 3. That he was an <hi>Athenian,</hi> and lived in the time of <hi>Socrates.</hi> Then which, ſaies he, what can be ſaid more like a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard, as though, if he had been a <hi>Barbarian,</hi> a Woman, or an Aſſe, he had been the ſame <hi>Plato</hi> that he was, and not that very thing which had been ſo born? If they ſay that God then may uſe ſupernatural means by working tranſcendently above the wills of men without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying their Nature or abridging their freedome. Whereunto it is anſwered that as, had God done the other, he would have deſtroyed his providence touching the creation of man; ſo, ſhould he do this, he would deſtroy his providence preparatory to the laſt Judgement, wherein every man ſhall receive according to that he hath done in the body whether good or evil. But though this Expoſition be pious and not to be rejected, yet this Parable, methinks more naturally admits of another, which I ſhall lay before the Reader, and which may import the duty of the Magiſtrate and Miniſter of Gods word, as well as the event of Gods providence. It is thus, There are two ſorts of evils which may grow up with the good ſeed of the Law of Nature implanted in man in his firſt creation, or of the Goſpel given for mans renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The one ſort may be <hi>compared to tares</hi> (as here) whereof there is a ſort which the <hi>Greeks,</hi> ſay to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch as grows up of it ſelf among the wheat in an over-moiſt and corrupt earth, without any ſeed ſown at all. Such are thoſe evils ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in manners or opinion which though they ſeem to us, that cannot ſee all things, to grow of themſelves, yet they owe their beginning to the enemy the Devil, who firſt corrupted &amp; endeavours daily more &amp; more to corrupt our Nature. The other ſort of evils are compared to <hi>thorns and briars,</hi> Heb. 6. 8. whoſe end is to be burned, ſuch as are deſperate and incorrigible ſinners, as may be clearly ſeen by the ſcope of the Apoſtle in that place. The firſt ſort are evils of infirmity for the moſt part, which are entwiſted with our Nature, as tares are with corn, and therefore cannot be cut down, unleſſe the good grain goes down with them, all men even the beſt being ſubject unto them. Should the Magiſtrate cut down all theſe, he muſt cut himſelf down for company: and ſhould S. <hi>Paul</hi> have delivered men to Satan for theſe, he muſt have given himſelf into his hands: for though he knew nothing by himſelf, yet was he not hereby juſtified. Nevertheleſs he uſed a ſeverity towards himſelf by <hi>keeping down his body and bringing it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſubjection,</hi> as a Magiſtrate may do towards his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Subjects for reforming
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:101116:34"/>
of leſſer evils and preventing of greater; nay S. <hi>Paul</hi> had the <hi>meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Satan, a thorn in his fleſh, ſent to him, leaſt he ſhould be puffed up with the abundance of Revelations,</hi> 2 Cor. 12. 7. The ſecond ſort are evils of preſumption which like bryars and thorns are not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily entwiſted with our Nature, but yet growing up amongſt the good grain, will choak it, and therefore calls for preſent <hi>curſing, and laſtly for burning,</hi> leaſt in the end of the world, it being all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come bryars and thorns, there would remain no harveſt to the great Husbandman to be brought into his barnes by his reapers: and ſo this world deſtroys Gods providence preparatory to the laſt Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the right hand, as the forementioned ſuppoſition would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it on the left.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 13.</head>
               <p>THeir next Argument is taken from the <hi>fallibility of Magiſtrates, which renders them,</hi> they ſay, <hi>uncapable of judging.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true that no man is infallible: if he were, he were no man; they needed not to have produced the authority of S. <hi>Peter</hi> to prove it. <hi>And now brethren I wot that through ignorance ye did it, as did alſo your Rulers.</hi> The which place proves it but weakly nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in as much as there appeared much of malice in the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our Saviour, in denying and delivering him to be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, whom <hi>Pilate</hi> himſelf <hi>was determined to let go.</hi> They did it ignorantly only in this reſpect, namely, that they <hi>knew him not to be the Lord of Glory.</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> makes no mention of their malice, though great, leaſt thereby they might have thought the door of mercy to have been ſhut againſt them, and ſo they might have come to the ſame end as their ring-leader <hi>Judas</hi> did. Here was a double defect which occaſioned a wrong judegment, one was of knowledge and a well informed underſtanding, the other was of an honeſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of mind; neither of theſe does deſtroy the power of a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, the Rulers remained Rulers ſtill, notwithſtanding their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or malice in this action. Indeed <hi>Plato</hi> ſaies, <hi>Beatas civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates fore ſi aut Philoſophi regnarent, aut reges philoſopharentur:</hi> 'Tis true, that happy is that City where Princes are qualified with gifts ſuitable to their high calling. But if he want, it as if Philoſophy
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:101116:34"/>
did give a right to anothers Kingdom, or were neceſſarily required to the eſtabliſhment of his own. I ſay, that then it was a ſaying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming one that held a community of goods and wives, whereby he would take from ſome, that which was their own, and give to others that which belonged to them, <hi>Lact. l.</hi> 3. 20.</p>
               <p>This conſideration therefore ſerves only, and that very well too, as a motive to care and conſcience in the exerciſe of power, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 19. 7. <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> ſpeaking of this very matter, gave to his Judges, whom he conſtituted, this charge, <hi>Take heed and do it,</hi> or take heed the doing of it. <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 3. 11. ſaid to God, <hi>Who am I, that I ſhould go to Pharaoh, &amp; that I ſhould bring forth the children of Iſrael out of Egypt?</hi> yet God would have him go and do it, <hi>Exo.</hi> 3. 10. 11.</p>
               <p>If then the fallibility of a Magiſtrate as being a man, or the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of his own weakneſſe as ſuch a perſon, was no argument in thoſe daies, againſt the power of the Magiſtrate or the exerciſe of it, how much leſſe is it now under the Goſpel, when the light is ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily greater then in thoſe times theirs was? Hereunto they will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer two things. 1. That Magiſtrates under the Old Teſtament had advantages which ours have not. Whereunto I ſhall reply anon in its due place, 2. That there is no ſuch need of Magiſtrates now: for <hi>in thoſe daies</hi> [the times of the Goſpel] <hi>all ſhall know the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereunto I anſwer, that if <hi>all,</hi> then the Magiſtrates eſpecially, who have a ſpecial promiſe for it, as is evident from what has been alledged. If arguments drawn from the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> prevail not with them, what will they ſay to the Law of Nature? Thus then I argue.</p>
               <p>A Magiſtrates care ought to be about that whereupon principally depends the eſtabliſhment of a Commonwealth, and the ſuppreſſion of opinions and men that would ruine it. But upon Religion prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally depends the eſtabliſhment of a Commonwealth, as is made good from the judgement of the very Heathen themſelves, as hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and what before has been ſhewed, do witneſſe; therefore a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ought to have a principal care of Religion, even by the Law of Nature. This care of Religion conſiſts generally in two things, 1. in ſetting up of Religion it ſelf, without which can be expected no bleſſing from God upon, nor obedience from the people to the Magiſtrate under the notion of Gods Vicegerent. 2. In avoiding of differences in opinions: for from diverſities of opinions men uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:101116:35"/>
fall into diverſity of affection and intereſt, which tends to the ruine of a Commonwealth. 'Tis true that as in a State, provided that all the Citizens hold the ſame fundamental Maxims neceſſary to the undergoing of duties eſſential to its conſervation, the Magiſtrate may tolerate amongſt them a difference in many other matters of leſſe importance. So it is in the Church as long as every man up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds thoſe opinions which make for the honour of God, and peace and unity of the Church, in the communion whereof he lives, leſſer things may be born with. But ſhall every man be his own Judge herein? No, for there's a threefold judgement, a judgement of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, a judgement of direction, and a judgement of juriſdiction: Every Chriſtian has a judgement of diſcretion, <hi>prove all things, hold faſt that which is good,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 21. by applying the rule of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture to his own private conſolation and edification, The Paſtours of the Church [who are the watchmen placed over the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, h. e.</hi> the Church and Houſe of God] have a judgement of direction to expound the holy Scriptures to others. The chief Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours to whoſe care the regiment of the Church is committed in a more ſpecial manner, have not this only, but a higher degree of judgement, which is of juriſdiction, to enjoyn. to reform, to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to condemn, to bind, to looſe judicially and authoritatively in their reſpective charges. If their key ſhall err, whether it be that of knowledge or jurisdiction, they are accountable to their reſpective Superiours from thence to a National, and laſt of of all to a general council. And that ſuch councils be called, ſuch perſons be ſettled, ſuch charges be by the ſaid perſons daily executed, is the Magiſtrates duty to ſee to, and his prerogative to command or allow.</p>
               <p>But <hi>oh</hi> what miſtakes, <hi>ſay they,</hi> by Magistrates, are continued in <hi>Holland</hi> about Religion, &amp;c?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> If ſuch miſtakes are continued in Magiſtrates, how would theſe be multiplied, if every one of the people were left to himſelf? Surely for one that is now, there would be ten thouſand in that caſe. And whereas they urge <hi>Popes, Councils, Oecumenical and National, that they have erred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is anſwered, that when we yield obedience to the Pope, or be concluded by the Councils and Synods which they alledge, they will be found to ſay ſomething to the purpoſe. But ſince they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prove theſe things, they might have ſpared as great a many of lines, as I mean to ſpare in their confutation: yet the 21. Article
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:101116:35"/>
of our Church yields more then they have proved,</hi> viz. <hi>That</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Councils may not be gathered together without the commandment and will of Princes: And when they be gathered together [for as much as they be an aſſembly of men, whereof all be not governed with the Spirit and word of God] they may erre, and ſometimes have erred, even in things pertaining unto God: wherefore things ordained by them, as neceſſary unto ſalvation, have neither ſtrength nor authority, unleſs it may be declared that they be taken out of the holy Scripture. <hi>Now what uſe will our adverſaries here make of this our gratification? Even this,</hi> viz. What ſecurity then can a Magiſtrate have that he does well?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As much ſecurity as a Judge that condemns a Priſoner at the Bar, in as much as the <hi>Notitia Juris</hi> is clear. The probation of the fact depends upon witneſſes, whereupon if a guiltleſſe perſon be condemned, the Judge has done his duty by ordering the formality of the tryal, and ſo has delivered his own ſoul.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 14.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NExt they argue from the Royal Law of Liberty,</hi> viz. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, even ſo do ye unto them, for this is the Law and the Prophets. And thoſe that are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to perſecute, would not be very zealous in their proceedings, if they were ſure that thoſe they perſecute ſhould have the power on their ſides to meet the ſame meaſure unto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That when a man is puniſhed for the committing of any thing unlawful to be done, or omitting that which is unlawful to be left undone, this only is a perſecution in Scripture ſenſe. But when a man is condemned for omitting that which ought, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that which ought not to be done [ſuch are things which are either abſolutely evil or good in themſelves, or being indifferent are made ſo by the intervention of humane authority] this is no perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, but juſtice: And whoſoever ſhall do ſuch juſtice upon any man, and be willing that the priſoner ſhould do ſo to him, the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner would either do it according to the Law as his Rule, and would proceed to ſentence, <hi>ſecundum allegata &amp; probata</hi> as to matter of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:101116:36"/>
fact, and ſo he would do well: for in reaſon [from whence a well ordered will has its denomination] he could not refuſe it: Or elſe the Priſoner coming to judge, would do it in an arbitrary way, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out or againſt Law, and not <hi>ſecundum allegata &amp; probata</hi> for matter of fact, but on his own head, or ſome underhand information of ſome whom the party accuſed ſhall never ſee nor know [as has been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed under the late Tyranny] He were mad if he ſhould. Who would be contented that another mans Bowl ſhould have a byaſs, and his own have none at all? Therefore <hi>Ariſt. Rhet.</hi> 1. 1. ſayes That it is moſt convenient that all things be determined by Laws, and that as few things as may be be left to the power of the Judges: And that 1. Becauſe it is eaſier to find one and a few, then many that are prudent enough to give Laws, or determine Cauſes. 2. Becauſe Laws are made upon mature deliberation going before their Sanction, but Sentences are given on a ſudden, which renders it difficult for the Judges to do right to every man. 3. Becauſe [which is the weightieſt of all reaſons] the judgement of a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver is not of ſingularities and preſent matters, but of things fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and univerſal: but a concional Auditor and Judge are to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine of preſent and definite things, where oftentimes either love, or hatred, or private commodity comes in; in ſo much that they cannot ſufficiently look into the merit of the cauſe, but either private intereſt or trouble will darken their judgement. But there is no good Body of Laws, wherein there is not a <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> h. e. a proviſion made, that any man, whatſoever he be, may have his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt him that has done him wrong, though it were his own Maſter that did it, for otherwiſe a tyranny would be introduced. And on the other ſide, that a man may make or expect a retribution for a favour done, otherwiſe ingratitude would take place. Both which are grounded upon this, namely, <hi>Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, the ſame do ye alſo unto them:</hi> And <hi>the ſame meaſure ye meet ſhall be meaſured to you again,</hi> Matth. 7. 2. So ſacred a thing was gratitude that the Heathen (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> teſtifies, <hi>Eth.</hi> 5. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) put the Temple of the Graces in the way, that a man cannot walk the ſtreet, but he muſt ſtumble upon the duty. And the Civil Law puts it in the ſole power of the Parent to diſinherit his Son for the contrary; whoſe examination is to be reſcinded, and he deprived of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:101116:36"/>
his undeſerved liberty, <hi>Cod.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 50. And though our Laws pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh not unthankfulneſs to the Fathers of our fleſh, the Fathers of our ſpirits, the Fathers of our fortunes [for indeed it being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive of all wickedneſſe, no one puniſhment is enough for it] yet nevertheleſſe the Temple of the Graces is not ſhut againſt theſe. the Law is open to theſe with us: and therefore that Royal Law is ſo far obſerved.</p>
               <p>But yet in as much as the Law is an univerſal precept, as one calls it, in the univerſality whereof all particular Caſes cannot be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, therefore ſomething of neceſſity muſt be left to the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Judge to determine as he thinks meet, provided it be not againſt the Law, which is immutable. In which caſe why ſhould any man prejudge his Judge, who is ſworn to obſerve this Royal Law? Indeed ſhould he do ſo, then what they ſeem to threaten by the Objection here made, they might have juſt cauſe of fear: for they do as good as ſay, Let them look to it, for trump may turn up on our ſide again, which if it does, the ſame rigour which they uſe to us, ſhall we uſe towards them; a Reſolution, not only contrary to this Royal Law, but to Chriſts commandment under the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 39. <hi>Reſiſt not evil, but whoſoever ſhall ſmite thee on the right cheek, turn to him the other alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to anſwer for them as much as poſſibly can be ſaid in favour of them. They may ſay, that they give this as a Rule, which in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prudence a man would obſerve, not but that they would make demonſtration of meekneſs and lenity, ſhould the diſpoſal of affairs fall into their hands.</p>
               <p>But I anſwer, that this is more then they can promiſe; for ſo ſaid <hi>Parmenio</hi> to <hi>Alexander</hi> [when <hi>Darius</hi> offered him ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand talents for the redemption of Priſoners, with all the Land he had on this ſide <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and one of his Daughters for a wife to boot] I would take it if I were <hi>Alexander;</hi> and ſo would I, ſaid <hi>Alexander,</hi> if I were <hi>Parmenio, Plut. in vita Alex.</hi> Private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons know not what themſelves would be, ſhould they come to ſit at the Helm of Government. Then things that make for the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of themſelves, or their Partiſans, may ſeem convenient, which were before abominable in their eyes. One did not know that he ſhould account the Univerſities the only remaining glory of the Nation, till he came to be head of one of the faireſt Colledges in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:101116:37"/>
the Enigmatical pillars were then no longer Myſteries of iniquity. Another would have <hi>Christ-Church</hi> paſſe for a Collegiate Dean and Prebends, till he found Leaſes to be invalid without the prophane Title of Cathedral. A third, and he guilty of the <hi>Magnum latro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinium</hi> of all, was at firſt for a popular Government, till he had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upon the back of the <hi>populaſſe,</hi> which he perſwaded that it could not mannage its liberty without a Rider. And then—what then? As a reward of their ingratitudes to the King, the Father of his Country,
<q>
                     <l>Non equitem dorſo, nec fraenum depulit ore.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 15.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANother Argument is, That</hi> as it is not any wayes lawful from the Word of God, for Chriſtian Magiſtrates in the dayes of the Goſpel, to deſtroy and root out the contrary minded in religious mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters [though Idolaters] ſo ſuch proceedings may ſometimes prove in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the very being of Nations: for ſuppoſe any Nation were wholly heatheniſh Idolaters, and the Word of God coming in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amongſt them, ſhould convert the chief Magiſtrate, and one twentieth part of the Nation more; muſt he then with that twentieth part de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the other nineteen if they will not be converted, but continue in their heatheniſh Idolatry? It cannot poſſibly be ſuppoſed to be warrantable: And this Reaſon holds good againſt the rooting up and deſtroying of Hereticks out of the world, becauſe an excommunicated perſon is as a Heathen or Infidel, <hi>Matth. 18. 17.</hi> Beſides, the Lord calls ſome at the third, ſome at the ſixth, ſome at the ninth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>hour, others at the eleventh: He therefore that deſtroyes any one, though an Idolater, or, &amp;c. hinders his converſion, and ſo brings eternal loſſe to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That a Magiſtrate providing for the eſtabliſhment of a Commonwealth, ought to temper his ſeverity with Chriſtian pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Now it were no prudence at all for him and his twentieth part to wage war with the other nineteen [for a war this were like to beget] in as much as inſtead of eſtabliſhing, this would ruine himſelf and his Commonwealth, with Religion and all.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:101116:37"/>
Suppoſe then that he had nineteen parts on his ſide, and only the twentieth part remained Idolaters, were he to deſtroy that twentieth part? no ſurely, we neither think ſo, nor ever ſaid ſo: The reaſon is, becauſe they were never yet converted [they have not as yet <hi>Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem Juris,</hi> the ignorance whereof excuſeth them] and who knows but that they may be in due time converted? The Queſtion is, Whether in caſe of revolt, (after converſion) to Idolatry, or the like, and in caſe they remain, obſtinate, going on to blaſpheme, the Church-cenſures may not reach them, and the civil Sword over take them, and cut them off, that the infection ſpread no farther?</p>
               <p>We anſwer, that they may; and this is <hi>Law. in God. Juſtin. l.</hi> 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 11. <hi>de Paginis, &amp; ſacrific<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is &amp; Templis. Qui poſt ſanctum ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſma in errore pagan<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. manent, ultimo ſupplicio plectunt.</hi> Let thoſe that ask baptiſme remain in the errour of the <hi>Pagans,</hi> be put to death; <hi>but for thoſe that are not yet baptized, let them without delay take care that their children be baptized: but let the elder firſt be taught the Scriptures, according to the Canons;</hi> and hereunto there is no ſuch penalty annexed; mean while all men are forbidden to aſſay any thing of <hi>Pagan</hi> ſuperſtition, under pain of corporal torment, and condemnation to the ſtanneries or perpetual baniſhment. <hi>Lege Qui. ub. ſupra.</hi> There is a difference then betwixt a <hi>Heathen,</hi> and one that is <hi>As a Heathen.</hi> A <hi>Heathen</hi> ought not to be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated [for it is impoſſible] nor puniſhed with death for his Idolatry, though ſome one that is <hi>As a Heathen,</hi> that is, one that hath been a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and becomes <hi>Heathen</hi> again, may; and hereby his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is not hindred: for the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſayes, That <hi>its impoſſible for ſuch to be renewed by repentance,</hi> Heb. 6. 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the next place they deny</hi> that the Kings Majeſty hath the ſame power in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, that the Godly Kings had amongſt the Jews; for <hi>ſay they,</hi> albeit the Kings of the Jews had power to puniſh-Idolaters and Blaſphemers, and ſome other tranſgreſſors of the then Law of God; yet who tells them that the Magiſtrates under the Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſation have ſuch power; hath the Lord Jeſus ſaid any ſuch thing, or if he has, where is it writen, nay where is it written from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the end of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that Magiſtrates under the Goſpell ſhould have the ſame power in religious cauſes, as thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law? If the Judicial Law be a Rule for Magiſtrates under the Goſpel to walk by, then why muſt it be mangled in pieces by ſome ſort
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:101116:38"/>
of ſinners with death, and not curſers of parents, man-ſtealers, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, Sabbath-breakers which were ſo puniſhable by the Judicial Law?</p>
               <p>I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> That that place of the Prophet <hi>Eſai.</hi> 43. 23. is between the beginninh of <hi>Geneſis</hi> and the end of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> wherein it is ſaid that <hi>Kings ſhall be [h. e.</hi> under the Goſpel] <hi>Thy</hi> [that is the Churches] <hi>nurſing fathers, and Queens thy nurſing mothers.</hi> The O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal is, <hi>giving ſuck or nouriſhers.</hi> Now ſhe that gives milk and nouriſhment to a child will not ſuffer the leaſt mote to be in it, that may do the child hurt, much leſſe ſuch things as may poyſon it. So it is with a Chriſtian Magiſtrate. It is not enough to ſee that the milk of the word be duly diſtributed, to the people, but alſo that blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers and idolaters to the poyſon of Religion, be rooted out. To what purpoſe is it for him to defend her from rapine and violence from abroad [as it is <hi>v.</hi> 26.] if he leaves perdition and ruine at home? And now whereas they ſay <hi>Why does the Magiſtrate puniſh I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry and Blaſphemy with death, and not curſing of father or mother, man-ſtealing, adultery, Sabbath-breaking?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> are ſo puniſhable by the Law of Nature, as well as by the Judicial Law of <hi>Moſes. Job</hi> 2. 9. Sayes <hi>Job</hi>'s Wife to him, <hi>Doeſt thou yet retain thine integrity? curſe God and die.</hi> Whereby it ſeems that preſent death was the ſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of blaſpheming God. And <hi>Job.</hi> 31. 26. <hi>If</hi> ſayes he, <hi>I beheld the Sun when it ſhined, or the Moon walking in brightneſſe; and my heart hath been ſecretly enticed, or my mouth hath kiſſed my hand: this alſo were an iniquity to be puniſhed by the Judge, for I ſhould have denied the God that is above.</hi> From whence it is evident, that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Idolatry is puniſhable by the Magiſtrate; but how? ſurely not with leſſe then what is due to blaſphemy, which ſee here made a conſequent of Idolatry. The other ſins mentioned in their objection are made capital by the Judicial Law alone [which indeed is in moſt things practicable under the Goſpel too, if it ſeems neceſſary or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to the Magiſtrate, and not otherwiſe] only as for Sabbath breaking, there can be none where there is no Sabbath binding, nor has been ſince the abrogation of the Law. Wherefore this their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument taken from things of different Natures thus jumbled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, is as very a fallacy of <hi>many Interrogations,</hi> as this is, <hi>viz. Nonne Socrates, Plato, Ariſtoteles, Petrus, Bucephalus, Leviathan,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:101116:38"/>
ſunt animalia rationalia?</hi> For as ſome of theſe are <hi>animalia ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalia,</hi> ſome not; ſo ſome of thoſe appertain to the Judicial Law, ſome not: ſome may be the ſubject of a poſitive Law under the Goſpel if it ſeems good to the Law-giver; ſome, as namely Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-breaking, cannot, becauſe the Jewiſh day, and the Jewiſh ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of it is abrogated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hereunto they add,</hi> That the Kings of the Jews had advantages [which we want] to direct them in judgement, as the ſtanding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim and Thummim, extraordinary Prophets. Therefore <hi>Ahab</hi> and others leaving theſe ran into various errours, perſecuted or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Prophets, as <hi>Jeremy, Michaia,</hi> and <hi>Elijah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That our Adverſaries even now confeſſed, that the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of Idolaters, Blaſphemers, and ſome other tranſgreſſors, was written in plain precepts of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law, for in anſwer to an Objection, <hi>page</hi> 21. they have theſe words, <hi>viz. But in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer we deny not, but the Kings of the Jews had power to puniſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and Blaſphemers, and ſome other tranſgreſſors of the then Law of God: which power was given them of God, and written in plain precepts in the Moſaical Law.</hi> If they had power to puniſh theſe things, then what theſe things were, was notoriouſly known; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the puniſhment had been unjuſtly inflicted. Why then do they [and that almoſt in the ſame breath] alledge the <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim, Oracle</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> to direct Judges in matter of Law and <hi>Jus univerſale,</hi> which every man is bound to take notice of? And for matter of fact, <hi>Urim, Thummim, Oracle</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> were extraordinary wayes of diſcovery of this or of any thing elſe, never to be made uſe of but when the thing could not otherwiſe be known, and that in a matter of great moment too. The ordinary way of diſcovering matter of fact was by witneſſes, or the confeſſion of the party. In caſe the party would not acknowledge the fault, then <hi>in the mouth of two or three witneſſes every word ſhall be eſtabliſhed,</hi> Deut. 19. 15. And is not the ſame rule given in the Goſpel, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 16? The want therefore of <hi>Urim and Thummim, Oracle</hi> and extraordinary <hi>Prophets,</hi> did not aboliſh the right uſe of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; for then after the Captivity the <hi>Jews</hi> had never had the right uſe of the Magiſtrate. Now then, if excellent Magiſtrates un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law [ſuch as were <hi>Zorobabel</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah]</hi> had no other advantages to Magiſtracy then we have under the Goſpel, their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:101116:39"/>
drawn from advantages which the Jews had above the Chriſtians, falls to the ground, and nothing hinders, but that we may have as good a Magiſtracy under the Goſpel as they had under the Law, and altogether as infallible too, or rather [I might have ſaid] as little fallible, for that they were actually fallible is evident, <hi>Neh.</hi> 7. 64, 65. where we read, that ſome of the Prieſts off-ſpring ſought for the Regiſter of their Genealogy, but it could not be found. What then? The <hi>Tirſhatha</hi> or Governour could not reſolve it how it ſtood, as formerly ſuch things were done: and therefore they were <hi>not to eat of the holy things till there ſtood up a Prieſt with Urim and Thummim,</hi> which never came to paſs: And now, I pray you, where was their greater infallibility from this time to the coming of Chriſt [which was the ſpace of five hundred and thirty years] then Magiſtrates have ever ſince had? As for <hi>Ahab,</hi> whom they urge to have erred, I ſay, that he erred, not for want of advantages which others had, but for want of an honeſt purpoſe of mind, which hindered the right uſe of thoſe advantages, he being a man that had <hi>ſold himſelf to do iniquity,</hi> mean while he ceaſed not to be a Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another Argument they draw from the</hi> different diſpenſations of the Goſpel from thoſe of the Law. <hi>Theſe diſpenſations are now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes more talked of then explained or underſtood, and leaſt of all in this preſent affair.</hi> The diſpenſations are different, <hi>ſay they, and why? Becauſe, forſooth,</hi> under the Goſpel tranſgreſſors are not to be proceeded againſt, as under <hi>Moſes,</hi> by external force and power: God in patience and long-ſuffering waiting on men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi>If tranſgreſſors are not to be proceeded againſt, under the Goſpel, by external power, how is it then ſaid, that <hi>the power beareth not the ſword in vain,</hi> and that it is <hi>the Miniſter of God to execute wrath on them that do evil,</hi> Rom. 13. 4? By <hi>evil</hi> is underſtood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>all evil,</hi> it being in <hi>materia neceſſaria,</hi> according to that of <hi>Pro</hi> 20. 8. <hi>A King that ſitteth on the throne of judgement ſcattereth away all evil.</hi> If <hi>all,</hi> then it is evil committed as well in ſpiritual as ſecular things. And then for patience and long-ſuffering towards ſinners, expecting their repentance: as God is the ſame God, ſo has his patience and long-ſuffering been heretofore as much as now under the Goſpel. Was he not one hundred and twenty years before he brought the Floud upon the world of the ungodly? And was he not grieved
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:101116:39"/>
forty years with his people, before he ſware that they ſhould not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his reſt, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 95. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. Whereas now God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects a preſent embracing of grace offered, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2. <hi>Now is the accepted time,</hi> future repentance is not to be preſumed upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But,</hi> ſay they, <hi>when any continues in diſobedience to the Goſpel, his puniſhment is eternal in the world to come; therefore as the Apoſtle ſaith,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 5. <q>Judge nothing before the time until the Lord come, who will bring to light hidden things of darkneſs, and will make manifeſt the counſels of the hearts, and then ſhall every man have praiſe of God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> And ſo when any one continues in diſobedience to the Law, his puniſhment is eternal too. But what is this place to a mans continuance in diſobedience to the Goſpel? Is it not alledged by St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf a Preacher of the Goſpel? He would not be judged before the time; for what? for his not continuance in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Goſpel? Nothing leſs; for he ever continued in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to it, and ever preached it. The Queſtion was, whether he were faithful in this his ſtewardſhip or no? whereof they were not to be judges, but God alone the ſearcher of the heart. St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf <hi>knew nothing by himſelf, yet was he not thereby juſtified. The heart of man is deceitful above all things:</hi> and if a man may be deceived in his own heart, it were a raſh thing to judge another mans, and that before the time that <hi>the hidden things of darkneſs ſhall be brought to light, and the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed</hi> to the view of all men, as now they are to God. It is therefore raſh and bottomleſs judgement that the Apoſtle here forbids, not that which is paſſed upon good grounds and ſerious deliberation. 2. It is ſaucy cenſure that is here forbidden, to wit, that they being private men ſhould go about to cenſure their Apoſtle and Preacher, when they were rather to be judged by him. 3. It is impertinent judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is here forbidden, in going about to judge the heart, when man looketh on the outward appearance only, and judgeth in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact [not in matter of thought] and this is all the Magiſtrate himſelf pretends to, wherein it is lawful for him to judge, which is confirmed by the ſame Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 6. <hi>Are ye unworthy to judge the ſmalleſt matters?</hi> and v. 4. he takes it for granted, that they have judgement <hi>in things pertaining to this life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:101116:40"/>
But, ſay they, <q>St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13. ſayes, that he was a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer and a perſecuter and if the mind of God had been that he ſhould have ſuffered death in that condition, how ſhould he have had repentance given him, and been ſuch a glorious inſtrument in the Church as afterwards he was?</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That it was neither the mind of God, nor the duty of the Magiſtrate, to cut off St. <hi>Paul</hi> for blaſphemy before his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as this was; and in the time of ignorance, when nor he, nor the Magiſtrates, under whom he lived, knew it to be blaſphemy to ſpeak againſt Chriſt or Chriſtians. Hence it was that he ſaid, that he obtained mercy. The Jews knew not Chriſt to be the Lord of glory for <hi>had they known it they would not have crucified him.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhews them, that a door of mercy was yet opened unto them. The ſame may be ſaid of the Jews, alledged by our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries here. The Jews were never yet converted to Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which may be the reaſon why they are not puniſhed nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for blaſphemy againſt Chriſt. But in that they ſay, that the <hi>Jews are the greateſt blaſphemers of Chriſt that are on the earth,</hi> this is true only implicitely; for ſhould they explicitly blaſpheme they were worthy of puniſhment, yea and were puniſhed by the Imperial Laws, as may be ſeen in <hi>Cod, Juſtiniani l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>de Judaeis &amp; Caelicolis,</hi> where it is decreed, <q>That if any of thoſe <hi>Judaei</hi> or <hi>Caelicolae</hi> did attempt any miſchief againſt them that refuſed to entertain their Sect, they and their confederates ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the fire. <hi>And again,</hi> If any Jew did preſume but to traduce any one to his religion, he was to be condemned to a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of his goods,</q> and puniſhed after a miſerable manner. And a third Law ſayes, <q>That if a Jew preſumed to draw a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to his religion, he was to be proſcribed, and ſuſtein the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of bloud.</q> They have been heretofore permitted to live here, as they are now elſewhere amongſt Chriſtians, but how little it has wrought upon them all the world knows. it is not Gods time yet, it ſeems, to take away the vail that is drawn over their eyes. Mean while you muſt underſtand, that the Jews remaining Jews, do not acknowledge themſelves the natural ſubjects of any Prince in the world. They will admit themſelves to be the local ſubjects of thoſe under whom they are, and will not be received to that neither, but upon conditions of freedome; wherefore it was a Law Imperial,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:101116:40"/>
                  <hi>Cod. Juſtin. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 9. <hi>de Judaeis &amp; Caelicolis, Ritus ſuos citra contemptum Chriſtianae religionis retineant;</hi> that they might retain their Rites without contempt of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p>Neither will it be for the purpoſe of our adverſaries to urge the <hi>Toleration of more then one Religion in other parts of the world, as in</hi> France <hi>and ſeveral parts of</hi> Germany: for firſt, In tolerating of them, they tolerate not blaſphemy or heatheniſh idolatry: for in <hi>France</hi> it ſelf their civil courts take cognizance, <hi>Des crimes de leze-Majeſte divine &amp; humaine, h. e.</hi> of crimes of Treaſon againſt God and the King. 2. in <hi>France</hi> the King permits but two Religions, not all, as theſe men would have done here. So in <hi>Germany</hi> Popery and the <hi>Auguſtane</hi> confeſſion have been permitted together, but not all Religions: and how comes even theſe things to paſs, but becauſe Princes give away that power over the Church, wherein God has veſted them, to the Pope, or people, That the King of <hi>France</hi> hath ſo done is clear from the <hi>Pragmatica Sanctio:</hi> wherein its acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that the Kings of <hi>France</hi> own originally, no Superiour, but God, and that without the ſaid <hi>pragmatical ſanction,</hi> the Acts of the Council of <hi>Baſil</hi> were of no validity, which was done at <hi>Bourges</hi> by an Aſſembly of the Eſtates, and confirmed by the King, ſhortly after the celebration of the ſaid Council of <hi>Baſil,</hi> which was <hi>anno Domini,</hi> 1436. And that this hath ever ſince obtained in <hi>France</hi> appears by the following cenſure of the contrary doctrine.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <head>Cenſure de la ſacree faculte de Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie de Paris, contre la puiſſance temporelle du Pape.</head>
                     <p>LE premier jour d' Auril mil ſix cents vingt ſix, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres la Meſſe du St. Eſprit, l' aſſemblee s eſtant faite a l a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>couſtumee en la ſalle du College de Sorbonne, touchant le lieure impie de Saternelly Jeſuite, ouy le rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port de docteurs que la faculte avoit deputez, leſquels ont expoſe qu es deux chapiſtres qui leur avoiint eſtez Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quez,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:101116:41"/>
eſtoyent contenues les propoſitions ſuivantes: Que le Pape peut punir les Roys &amp; les Princes de peines tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porelles, les depoſer &amp; priver de leur Royaume &amp; eſtats pour crime d' Hereſie &amp; deliurer leurs ſujects de leur o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beiſſance: &amp; que telle a tousjours eſte la couſtume de l' Egliſe. Et non ſculement pour l' hereſie mais encore pour d' autres cauſes, aſcavoir pour leur pechez s' il eſt ainſi expedient: ſi les Prences ſont negligens: s' ils ſont in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capables &amp; inutiles. De plus que le Pape a la puiſſance ſur les choſes ſpirituelles, &amp; ſur toutes les temporelles, &amp; qu'il a cette puiſſance de droit divin. qu'il faut croire que le pouvoir a eſte donne a l' Egliſe &amp; a ſon Souverain Paſteur de punir de peines temporelles les Princes qui pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chent contre les Loix divines &amp; humaines: particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lierement ſi leur crime eſt une hereſie. Ils ont auſſi dit que Saternelly affirme que les Apoſtres eſtoient bien ſujects au Princes ſeculiers, mais non de droit, &amp; meſme qu' auſſi toſt que la majeſtie du Souverain Pontife a eſte eſtablie, tous les Princes luy ont eſte ſujects bref ils ont rapporte que cet Autheur explique ces paroles de Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Mat. 16.</hi> Tout ce que vous liez ſur la terre &amp; non ſeule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment de la puiſſance ſpirituelle, mais auſſi de la tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relle, &amp; qu'il corrompt le text de St. <hi>Paul 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> ad <hi>Cor. 10. Poteſtatem dedit nobis Dominus in aedificationem &amp; non in deſtructionem,</hi> en retranchant une negation, &amp; fait dire a pluſieurs autheurs, qu'il cite de choſes a quoy ils n'ont jamais penſe. concluans que tant, ces choſes que pluſie autres qu'ils ont rapportees meritoient tres-juſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment la correction &amp; la cenſure de la faculte: Monſieur le <hi>Doyen</hi> ayant mis la choſe en deliberation apres que les opinions de tous les Docteurs ont eſte, ouyes &amp; leurs voix recuillies la faculte a improuve &amp; condamne la Doctrine
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:101116:41"/>
contenue en ces propoſitions, &amp; aux concluſions desdites chapitres comme eſtant nouvelles, fauſſes, erronees, &amp; contraire a la parole de Dieu, qui rend la dignite du Souverain Pontife odieux, &amp; ouvre la chemin au ſciſme, qui deroge, a l' authorite Souverain de Roys, qui ne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend que de Dieu ſeul, &amp; empeche la converſion de Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces infidels &amp; heretiques: qui trouble la paix univerſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le &amp; renverſe les Royaumes, les eſtats, &amp; les Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, Bref qui detaurne les ſujets de l' obeiſſance qu'ils doivent a leur Souverains, &amp; les induit a des factions, rebellions &amp; ſeditions, &amp; a attenter de la vie de leur Princes. fait en Sorbonne, les jour &amp; an que deſſus, &amp; receu le <hi>14.</hi> Auril. <hi>1626.</hi> Par le commandement de meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieurs les <hi>Doyens</hi> &amp; Docteurs de la ſacree faculte de The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologie de <hi>Paris.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Signe</hi> Ph. Bouvot.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> deriving themſelves from the confines of <hi>Germany.</hi> The like may be ſaid of the <hi>German</hi> Powers: and <hi>the powers that are are of God, Rom.</hi> 13. and depend immediately upon him. But theſe powers, I ſay, are for the moſt part given away to the Pope by the true owners of them; whereas did they reform Religion by their own authority, as the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have done, all men might quickly be brought to ſubſcribe and ſubmit to that Religion and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which they ſhould authorize according to the word of God, and the conſent of antiquity, which would never have been brought to paſs in <hi>England,</hi> had the Kings referred themſelves herein to <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And whereas they urge that</hi> it makes for the ſecurity of Princes to give libehty to all.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, That then this ſecurity muſt be either from God or man:
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:101116:42"/>
from God it cannot be, in as much as he that gives liberty to all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions evidently ſhews that he has no regard of any, but meerly as to the notion of it: in which caſe, what ſecurity can he expect from God? neither let our preſent adverſaries think they pleaſe God in pleading for a liberty of blaſphemy, though they pretend that their very ſoul abhor it: from <hi>man</hi> it will not be, for thereby he will cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate as many intereſts as Religions, which will unite againſt the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt of all [which they know will aim at an uniformity] though they ſhall no ſooner have beaten down this then they will fall a ſquabbling among themſelves. In which regard it may be ſaid of them as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey,</hi> namely, <q>that it was not their diſſenſion which was the cauſe of the civil war, as was commonly ſuppoſed, but their union rather, in as much as they firſt went about to ruine the authority of the Senate and of the Nobility, and then they quarrelled among themſelves, a thing, ſaies he,</q> which <hi>Cato</hi> many times foretold and propheſied. Thoſe that aim at uſurpation catch moſt fiſh in theſe troubled waters. Thus did <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> whom our adverſaries inſtance in, as if it made for them, when indeed they could not have found an example in all the Bible, or in all the world, that makes more againſt them. <q>They ſay that <hi>Jeroboam</hi> wanting faith to believe that his new kingdom could any ways be ſecured to him, or kept from going back to the linage of <hi>David,</hi> unleſs he deviſed ſome new way of worſhip to keep the people in their own land, and for his ſo doing he thought he had much reaſon of ſtate: whereupon he took counſel and made two calves of gold, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 12. 16, 17, 18. and ſaid unto them, it is too much for you to go up to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> behold thy God, O <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> which brought thee out of the land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which policy of his procured this event which God denounced againſt him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I will bring evil upon the houſe of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and will cut off from <hi>Jeroboam</hi> him that piſſeth againſt the wall, and him that is ſhut up and left in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and will take away the remnant of the houſe of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> as a man taketh away dung till it be all gone. And 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 14. 10, 11 for the ſin wherein he made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin is he branded to all poſterity,</q> &amp;c. whereunto they adde by way of application, <hi>be wiſe new therefore O ye Kings, Pſ.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They ſhould have ſaid, <hi>be wiſe now therefore O ye Rebels,</hi> ſuch <hi>Jeroboam</hi> was. This <hi>Jeroboam</hi> an obſcure fellow, and ſervant
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:101116:42"/>
to <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 11. 26. <hi>rebelled</hi> againſt his King, and by his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices drew away ten tribes after him from <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and the houſe of <hi>David</hi> under which the true worſhip of God remained and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed. Now <hi>Jeroboam</hi> conſidering that he was but a rod ſent to ſcourge Gods people, and to be thrown into the fire at laſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> uſed all means to croſs providence, and to perpetuate the Kingdom to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his poſterity, which he knew to reſt chiefly in the buſineſs of <hi>Religion.</hi> Then well weighing that if he ſuffered the people to uſe their old way of worſhip, it would prove a means to reduce them to obedience to their lawful Sovereign. He therefore perſwades them that they need not go to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſaying that the Calves which he had ſet up, the one in <hi>Bethel,</hi> and the other in <hi>Dan,</hi> were the Gods which brought them out of the Land of <hi>Egypt:</hi> for which the curſe of God lighted on his family, as our adverſaries have noted, and he was branded with a note of perpetual infamy ſo often repeated in the hiſtory of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael, viz. Jeroboam the ſon of Nebat who made Iſrael to ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Juſt ſo was it here: we had a <hi>Jeroboam</hi> who rebelled againſt his <hi>King,</hi> after whoſe death [which he contrived too] he carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the proportion of ten tribes after him: and the better to aſſure them to himſelf, told them they need not look after <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Steeple-houſes,</hi> nor the Religion which was there taught and practiſed by thoſe that frequented them, that they might ſet up the <hi>golden calves</hi> of their <hi>own ſpirits,</hi> and adore them where they pleaſed, <hi>made prieſts of the loweſt of the people,</hi> which were not of the Tribe of <hi>Levi.</hi> That is, ſent thoſe to <hi>preach</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> that had neither <hi>Ordination</hi> nor <hi>learning.</hi> Now he is gone, and how much more of this dunghill is ſwept away, I cannot preciſely tell, but this note of infamy will reſt upon him, namely, that <hi>he made</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>to ſin.</hi> And thus we ſee how their own argument <hi>ab exemplo,</hi> in every particular makes againſt themſelves, and againſt that liberty they contend for, ſo unlucky they have been in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:101116:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 16.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN the next place they preſs the</hi> liberty granted to tender conſciences by the Kings Majeſties Declaration from <hi>BREDAH.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> And ſo they had it, till that fell out which might be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen, <hi>viz.</hi> A making uſe of it to an inſurrection in <hi>London,</hi> which might have put all the Kingdom into a flame, had they not been as fanatick in their undertake as in their opinions, perſwading them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that <hi>one</hi> of them <hi>ſhould chaſe a thouſand.</hi> And why this Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was reſtrained, is ſet forth in the Kings Majeſties Proclamation to that purpoſe, by whom it was never intended to grant a Liberty to others which might put a reſtraint upon his Majeſties own ſelf at laſt.</p>
               <p>As for what they <hi>urge</hi> out of Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Conner</hi> in his <hi>Liberty of propheſying, and his Epiſtle Dedicatory to it,</hi> I ſay that he might think it high time, even for the <hi>Orthodox</hi> to cry up a liberty of opinions amongſt the reſt, when the cry of others had prevailed for the liberty of all Religions but the true: and our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, to render their preſent cry the greater, produce the <hi>teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the ancients in the margin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to make up the <hi>number</hi> 15. <hi>which they promiſed in their Title Page,</hi> they have made ſome of them ſeparatiſts from themſelves, by dividing <hi>Minutius</hi> from <hi>Faelix, Sulpitius</hi> from <hi>Severus, Socrates</hi> from <hi>Scolaſticus;</hi> for otherwiſe they had had but a petty Jury: this they never took from that learned Biſhop: ſince then, <hi>male deſcriben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> yea, and <hi>male vertendo</hi> too, theſe have made them their own; my task will be to anſwer them only: The thing inſiſted on this, that <hi>for the firſt</hi> 300. <hi>years there was no ſign of perſecuting of any man for his opinion, though at that time there were many horrid opinions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That this is either generally to be underſtood: <hi>h. e.</hi> of Chriſtianity in general perſecuted; or elſe of any man or mens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſecuted by other Chriſtian or Chriſtians for matter of opinion. If generally underſtood, I oppoſe thereunto the 10 Perſecutions, which happened in the firſt 300. years. The 1. was under <hi>Nero, anno</hi> 67. whoſe decree was that to confeſſe a mans ſelf to be a Chriſtian,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:101116:43"/>
ſhould be capital. The 2. under <hi>Domitian, ann.</hi> 90. The 3. under <hi>Trajan, ann.</hi> 100. whereof <hi>Plini</hi> to <hi>Trajan, l.</hi> 10. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 111. The 4. under <hi>Adrian,</hi> and <hi>Antoninus Piuy, ann.</hi> 126. The 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> under <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toninus Philoſophus,</hi> and <hi>Antoninus Verus, ann.</hi> 168. The 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> under <hi>Severus, ann.</hi> 203. The 7. under <hi>Maximinus, ann<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 236. The 8. under <hi>Decius, an.</hi> 251. The 9. under <hi>Valerianus, ann.</hi> 258. The tenth under <hi>Diocletian, ann.</hi> 303. If this would be underſtood re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictively of any man or mens being perſecuted by other Chriſtians: I anſwer, 1. That I hope they will recall their word <hi>perſecuting. Horrid opinions</hi> may be proſecuted and puniſhed, not perſecuted; I mean in the Scripture acception of the Word, though in the Law it be ſo accounted. <hi>God. l.</hi> 1. t. 5. <hi>l g. Manichaeos ſeu Manichaeas vel Donatiſta meritiſſima ſeveritate perſequimur.</hi> 2. If <hi>horrid opinions</hi> were only <hi>commenced,</hi> they were but begun; but ſin when it is perfected (and not before) bringeth forth death by the Laws of God, and if horrid ſin, by man too. 3. For proſecuting, or (as they call it) perſecuting for opinions, either commenced or perfected, what power had they to do it withall, when all the Emperours were Heathen, &amp; there was no eminent Magiſtrate to take cognizance of differences among Chriſtians themſelves, otherwiſe then to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment them, that thereby they might become the ruine one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? 2. Of the Authors alledged, the Hiſtorians (whom only I look upon for matter of fact) ſay nothing in the buſineſs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prove nothing at all. As for inſtance, <hi>Sulpitius Severus</hi> ſays no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of one Chriſtians perſecuting another. <hi>Ergo,</hi> one Chriſtian did not perſecute another: this is a <hi>non ſequitur,</hi> it being an argument from humane authority, and therefore holds not negatively, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally from the authority of one that has written but an Epitome, a very manual of hiſtory, which cannot be comprehenſive of all things, neither does he mention any thing but the ten perſecutions, and what relates to them in all that three hundred years, which he does too in leſs then one hundred and fifty lines in <hi>Octavo,</hi> of a St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> print, which could not have been much had it been ſo many lines in a <hi>Minion</hi> or <hi>Nonparil.</hi> And as <hi>Sulpitius Severus</hi> did not, ſo <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates Scholaſticus</hi> could not ſpeak any thing of this matter, in as much as his hiſtory begins with <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> which was after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration of the ſaid three hundred years.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:101116:44"/>
Thirdly, did any of thoſe Authours ſpeak againſt perſecution for matter of opinion? then this is an argument that there was ſuch a perſecution (ſo our adverſaries are pleaſed to call it) or elſe they fought with a ſhadow.</p>
               <p>Their diſlike hereof conſiſted in two things, 1. That any ſhould be put to death meerly for his opinion, and this was St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, who was firſt of opinion that it was not honeſt to uſe any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to miſperſwaded perſons, but afterwards he retracted it, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5. quoted by the Dr. himſelf <hi>lib.</hi> of proph. <hi>ſect.</hi> 14. We agree with St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> as we have ſignified all along, that no man is to be put to death for ſimple hereſy, <hi>h. e. qua</hi> hereſy, unleſs it has joyned with it Blaſphemy, Heatheniſh Idolatry, Sedition, or the like.</p>
               <p>The Doctour himſelf allows puniſhing <hi>Romiſh</hi> prieſts with death, not as for Religion, but as enemies to the ſtate, <hi>Serm. at St. Maries on Gunpow. Treaſon,</hi> neither does the ſaid Dr. diſallow of Laws for puniſhing of Hereticks in general with corporal puniſhment; only he would have the execution of thoſe Laws upon emergencies commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the diſcretion of the Governours of the Church, <hi>ib. ſect.</hi> 17. The ſecond thing thoſe forementioned Authours or any of them diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked was, that any man ſhould be <hi>compelled</hi> to a Religion, not that he ſhould be <hi>corrected</hi> for his wandrings from it: and ſo much is learned from <hi>Tertullian ad Scap. Nec religionis eſt cogere religionem, quae ſponte ſuſcipi debet, non vi;</hi> and this has been our tenet all along.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But, ſay they,</hi> This reſtraining of liberty, impoſing upon mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and lording over their faith, came in with the train and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue of Antichriſt, that is, they came as other abuſes and corruptions of the Church did, by reaſon of the iniquity of the times, and the cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the firſt heats of Chriſtianity, and the increaſe of intereſt, and the abatement of Chriſtian ſimplicity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That if this <hi>reſtraining,</hi> and <hi>impoſing,</hi> and <hi>lording</hi> be meant of the Popes infallibility, and reſolving every thing into that <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera,</hi> then I agree, that it came in with the train and retinue of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</p>
               <p>And its an argument the men of this generation are the train and retinue of Antichriſt, whoſe <hi>opiniatreté</hi> or ſelf-conceitedneſs is
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:101116:44"/>
ſuch, that every one thinks himſelf a Pope in that regard. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the granting of liberty to them is to acknowledge their infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and conſequently, were there a thouſand Religions amongſt them, every one muſt be acknowledged to be the true; and then what would become of ONE LORD, ONE FAITH, ONE BAPTISME? <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 5. but if this reſtraining be meant of any other reſtraint by the Civil Magiſtrate; Liberty was reſtrained be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Phocas</hi> his timeſ [who was called the Midwife of Antichriſt] as may be ſeen in <hi>Cod. Juſtiniani l.</hi> 1. t. 5. and <hi>t.</hi> 9. which <hi>Code</hi> was compoſed, <hi>[Anno</hi> 529. and 530. above ſeventy years before <hi>Phocas]</hi> not of Laws then newly enacted, but of ſuch as had been made by his Predeceſſors long before, amongſt which thoſe that touch the preſent buſineſs were thoſe of <hi>Arcadius, Honorius, Valentinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Theodoſius,</hi> &amp;c. all promoters of the orthodox faith, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore uſhered not in the train and retinue of Antichriſt, which never did ſo lordly and imperiouſly appear as in Pope <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> called <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who ſate at <hi>Rome</hi> between four hundred and five hundred years after <hi>Phocas,</hi> and above five hundred and forty years after the laſt compoſure of the <hi>Code.</hi> He firſt of all the Popes excommunicated the Emperour, and arrogated to himſelf the power of inſtituting an Emperour.</p>
               <p>I agree likewiſe, that <hi>the King of</hi> France <hi>his giving permiſſion to the</hi> Huguenots <hi>has proved proſperous to that Nation,</hi> though moſt proſperous to the <hi>Huguenots</hi> themſelves, who have found more happineſs in peace and obedience, then ever they did in rebellion, and holding out againſt the power and authority of their King. But had he given the ſame liberty to all Religions, it muſt have been the confuſion of it, and as diſpleaſant to the <hi>Huguenots,</hi> as the denyal of liberty to themſelves had been before. In every aſſembly of the <hi>Huguenots</hi> the King has a Commiſſary, to ſee that nothing be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed amongſt them againſt the intereſt of the Crown: But how can ſuch a thing be among men of all Religions, and no Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples?</p>
               <p>I agree likewiſe, <q>That liberty of conſcience ſhould be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in all things where God hath not made a limit:</q> For the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of our Church, before mentioned, ſayes, <q>That ſhe has not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:101116:45"/>
power to impoſe any thing contrary to the Word of God, yea o<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> beſides it,</q> as neceſſary to ſalvation.</p>
               <p>I agree, <q>That the ſoul of man ſhould be free, and acknowledge no Maſter but Jeſus Chriſt:</q> And yet may it be ſubject to humane Laws, which do bind the conſcience in themſelves, not for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but for and on the behalf of God and Jeſus Chriſt, who commandeth <hi>every ſoul to be ſubject to the higher power,</hi> Rom. 13. and in this regard matters ſpiritual may be reſtrained by puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments corporal as we have already ſaid.</p>
               <p>I agree too, that meekneſſe, and charity, and longanimity ſhould be exerciſed towards thoſe in errour: and laſtly, <q>That the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of man, and difficulty of things, ſhould be both put in the balance to make abatement in the deſinitive ſentences againſt mens perſons.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But what is all this to idolatry, ſedition, and blaſphemy, which our Adverſaries have herein endeavoured to maintain as not puniſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by the Magiſtrate? And what is this to thoſe ſteams of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons breathed out of the bottomleſſe pit, againſt which they would not have the Magiſtrate as much as hold his noſe?</p>
               <p>Therefore they go on and ſay, <q>That the beſt of men, and moſt glorious Princes, were alwayes ready to give toleration, but never to make execution for matters diſputable, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond book of the life of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> reports.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> All this we grant: But what is all this to horrid opinions, or practiſes, againſt which ſevere Laws were made by glorious Princes? Theſe were not oſ things diſputable, &amp; <hi>de quibuſdam voculis,</hi> as they are termed in the title of the Chapter of the ſaid ſecond Book of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius,</hi> concerning which there was no Law made, nor like to be made, againſt which any toleration or whereupon any ſentence might be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, upon which any execution might be ſuſpended. But they were of matters of higher concern, as will appear by the Laws themſelves. The firſt was that of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, who after the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council commanded the books of <hi>Arius</hi> to be burnt, and that he who neglected it ſhould be put to death, as is obſerved by <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus a Caſtro. de juſt a Hereticorum punitione l.</hi> 2. <hi>c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 15. So <hi>Theodoſius</hi> commanded the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> to be put to death, as <hi>Minus Celſus Senen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> himſelf witneſſeth. But the <hi>Cod.</hi> of <hi>Juſtinian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> l<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 1, <hi>Tit.</hi> 5. teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:101116:45"/>
more in this matter then I need now to write, wherein we find that there is a Law made by the Emperours <hi>Gratian, Valentinian,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> for the perpetual ſilencing of hereſies and Hereticks, <hi>ut Haereſes perpetuo quieſcant.</hi> Another for interdicting all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles of them to be held either night or day, made by <hi>Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Honorius.</hi> Another againſt the <hi>Manichees</hi> in particular, That they be Out-laws, ſuffer a publication of their goods, barred of all liberality of, or ſucceſſion to others, that all power of giving, or ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or contracting be taken away from them, and much more. Another made by <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Valentinian,</hi> againſt the <hi>Arians, Macedonians, Pneumatomachi, Apollinartans, Novatians,</hi> or <hi>Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Eunomians, Tetradites</hi> or <hi>Teſſareſcaedecadites, Valentinians, Paulians, Papianists, Montaniſts,</hi> or <hi>Pricillianiſts,</hi> the <hi>Phryges</hi> or <hi>Praepuſites, Marcionites, Borborites, Meſſalians, Euchites,</hi> or <hi>Enthuſiasts, Donatiſts, Audians, Hydroparaſtats, Taſcodrogites, Batrachites, Hermogenians, Photinians, Paulianians, Marcellians, Ophites, Encratists, Carpocratites, Saccophorites, (&amp; qui ad imam uſque ſcelerum nequitiam pervenerunt)</hi> the <hi>Manichees,</hi> that they have no place either of abode or convening, <hi>in Romanum locum.</hi> As for the <hi>Manichees,</hi> they were not only to be baniſhed the Cities, but they were to be <hi>(tradendi ultimo ſupplicio)</hi> delivered to death, leaſt the Elements ſhould be infected with them, or injured by them. Another Law was made by them, That they that adhered to the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Neſtorius</hi> ſhould not be called Chriſtians, but <hi>Neſtorians,</hi> from their Author <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> whoſe impious books, written againſt the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> every man was forbidden to have, to read, or to write out, but were diligently to be ſearched for and burned. All places of meeting were thereby forbidden theſe <hi>Nestorians;</hi> and whoſo offended againſt this Law, was to ſuffer pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of his goods. Another Law was made by <hi>Valen.</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi> againſt the followers of <hi>Eutyches,</hi> whoſe opinions were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> conſiſting of three hundred and eighteen Fathers, and in the <hi>Conſtantinopolitan</hi> Council, conſiſting of one hundred and fifty other Biſhops. Theſe were called alſo <hi>Apollinariſts,</hi> and were to ordain no Presbyters under pain of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation; they were to have no Monaſteries, nor meetings by day or by night, under pain of forfeiture of the houſe, if the owner were
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:101116:46"/>
aware of it, or elſe ten pound in gold: they were to have no room in the Militia, &amp;c. Divers other Laws are there to be ſeen, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>Manichees</hi> are puniſhable with death, other Hereticks with confiſcation, or the like. Now albeit the capital puniſhments here mentioned were ſeldome inflicted, yet others doubtleſs were, even thoſe of baniſhment and confiſcation. [Nay, as we have noted before, that ſevere Laws were made againſt the misbehaviour of the Jews. So <hi>Soc. Scholaſt.</hi> tells us, <hi>H ſt.</hi> 7. 16. that condign pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment was undergone by ſome of them, upon the command of the Emperour, for ſcoſſing at Chriſt and Chriſtianity in their Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixion of a Chriſtian Boy] To theſe Laws, it is probable that King <hi>James</hi> had an eye in his Declaration againſt <hi>Vorſtius,</hi> ſent by an Embaſſadour to the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> wherein he manifeſteth his deteſtation of <hi>Vorſtius</hi>'s horrid opinions, as deſerving the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Author, rather then the honour of his being a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Profeſſor in that famous Univerſity of <hi>Leyden.</hi> And this learned King of happy memory I mention, the rather, becauſe our Adverſaries alledge him <hi>writing to the United Provinces, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing them to maintain peace, by bearing one with another in (ſuch) differences of opinions and judgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is true, if by ſuch differences be meant diſputable things, and ſuch perhaps as were meant by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid 55. <hi>c.</hi> of the ſecond book of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> though not the ſame, wherein he would have men perſwaded to a pious <hi>Syncretiſme</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a Schiſme, which might occaſion the Magiſtrate to make uſe of his Sword: which wholeſome counſel it were to be wiſhed men would take amongſt us: where one party decryes the other for <hi>Arminian,</hi> which is it ſelf as faſt decryed for <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> on the other ſide, both, though they differ in their Doctrines, agree in their Uſes and Applications, and take all the Articles of our Church to be for them, as is obſerved by the Kings Majeſty of bleſſed memory, in his Declaration ſet before the book of Articles. But that they might as well agree in Doctrines as Uſes, they ſhould do well to take up that excellent moderation preſcribed by our Church in the cloſe of the ſeventeenth Article, which is, That <hi>Gods promiſes are to be received</hi> [not to curious diſputes, but] <hi>as they are generally ſet forth in the Scripture, and in our doings that will of God is to be
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:101116:46"/>
followed, which we have expreſly declared unto us in the Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for the <hi>Emperours, and Duke of</hi> Savoy's <hi>tolerations, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with that of</hi> Polonia <hi>and</hi> Rome <hi>it ſelf,</hi> alledged here for their defence: I ſay, it is one thing what they did upon State policy, and another thing what they would have done, had they not been under a neceſſity of doing it. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> has made a peace with the <hi>Hollander,</hi> notwithſtanding his claim he makes to the <hi>Low Countries;</hi> why? becauſe he has irons enough in the fire elſewhere. The caſe was ſo with <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Germany, Emanuel</hi> of <hi>Savoy,</hi> the State of <hi>Poland,</hi> the Emperours of <hi>Rome,</hi> a neceſſity lying upon them to do as they did: but by the way I muſt tell you, that there were Laws made againſt the <hi>Novatians</hi> before <hi>Juſtinian</hi>'s time, witneſs that before quoted out of the Code, which was enacted by <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Valentinian</hi> againſt that rabble of Hereticks, whereof the <hi>Novatians</hi> were a part; and even that Law refers to others formerly made particularly againſt their Conventicles, which they falſly called Churches. Neither did the others want Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a liberty of Religion, though they thought it neceſſary to tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate it. Which neceſſity ceaſing, <hi>the Popes</hi> [as their following words would have it] <hi>were the firſt preachers of force and violence in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, and yet it came not ſo ſar as death, but the firſt that preached that Doctrine was</hi> Dominick <hi>the founder of the Order of begging Fryars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That (as I conceive) neither were the Popes the firſt preachers of force and violence, neither was <hi>Dominick</hi> the firſt founder of begging Fryars; for I have already proved, that force in this caſe has been practiſed before, taught by St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by God himſelf, in giving men into the hands of <hi>Satan for the puniſhment of the fleſh.</hi> Nay did not the whole Chriſtian world agree together upon the ſame principle in the holy war againſt Infidels [which is more then we have undertaken to juſtify] though the ſame power which was raiſed againſt them, was turned againſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians upon the inſtigation of <hi>Dominick?</hi> This <hi>Dominick</hi> was not the founder of begging Fryars [for theſe owe their beginning to S. <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>Aſſize]</hi> but of a new order of working Fryars, who being unable to maintain themſelves by working, were forced to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:101116:47"/>
piece out their maintenance by begging. The new Order I call them: for here even in this Iſland about ſix hundred years before <hi>Dominick,</hi> the Monks of <hi>Bangor</hi> were about two thouſand and one hundred that lived upon the work of their hands, as <hi>Bede</hi> witneſſeth. <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſ. Gent. Ang. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>In the next place, to the pretended <hi>injuſtice of the executions that are urged to have been done in the reign of</hi> Henry <hi>the fourth for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of opinion,</hi> I ſay that what was done, was occaſioned not ſo much for opinions, as for the hoſtile manner that the aſſertors of thoſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons aſſembled themſelves in, which was pernicious in it ſelf, and dangerous to the State. Theſe were called by ſeveral names, one whereof was <hi>Lollards,</hi> not as owing their beginning to <hi>Lollardus</hi> a <hi>German</hi> [if I may have the liberty of conjecture] but as being ſo called, <hi>quaſi Lowlords, h. e.</hi> Levellers: for in Acts and Monuments they are alſo written <hi>Lolleards,</hi> the termination whereof comes near to the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> word <hi>Laird</hi> for Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the laſt place it is objected,</hi> Why are we ſo zealous againſt th ſe we call Hereticks, and yet great friends with drunkards, and fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, and ſwearers, and intemperate, and idle perſons, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Argument holds for thoſe that are onely called He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, but are not certainly known to be ſo: whereas that which is Hereſy indeed is a ſpiritual drunkenneſs, and a ſpiritual fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and which uſually carries along with it an intereſt deſtructive to the King and Church, which Hereticks will fight for as eagerly, as a corporal fornicatour will do for his Paramour; and therefore more ſeverely to be puniſhed then corporal drunkenneſs in thoſe that are guilty of it: for it may be ſaid of corporal drunkards, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did of <hi>Dolabella,</hi> whom he was adviſed to beware of, <hi>I am not afraid,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>of ſuch fat perewig'd fellows as he; they are the pale and the lean men that I ſtand in fear of,</hi> meaning <hi>Caſſius</hi> and <hi>Brutus;</hi> ſo <hi>Plut. in vita Caeſaris.</hi> Yet this I adde namely, that he who is a friend to an unbounded liberty of opinions [ſuch as theſe men contend for] is a friend to drunkenneſs too, inaſmuch as he that hath liberty to think what he pleaſes in any thing [for hither theſe men would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend liberty] will judge it lawfull to take a cup too much at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. And where have you greater drinking then amongſt the <hi>Low-Countrey</hi> men, where liberty of opinion is allowed? In ſo
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:101116:47"/>
much, that a very famous man [and he a publick Profeſſour too] failing his Auditours of a Lecture one day, made an Apology for himſelf the next, and ſaid, The reaſon was that he had been drunk over night. This I had from one of the greateſt friends they have in <hi>England,</hi> and therefore not very likely to raiſe a falſe report of them. And to let you know that this Nation obſerves no juſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in any thing appertaining to God or <hi>Caeſar;</hi> another hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed this their moral Scazon, by a metrical one, in theſe words,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Utrinque clauda Gens Batâva jampridem eſt:</l>
                  <l>Sed cur, &amp; unde noſſe vis? id in promptu.</l>
                  <l>Deo rebellis, &amp; rebellis eſt Regi.</l>
                  <l>Hi nonne ſummo jure dicier claudi</l>
                  <l>Per omne crus, &amp; omne per latus poſſunt,</l>
                  <l>Quibus eſt fides luxata, valga, diſtorta,</l>
                  <l>Fide litaſque facta loripes to<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a?</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>The <hi>Batavan</hi> on both feet goes awry:</l>
                  <l>Wouldſt know the cauſe? I'le tell thee by and by.</l>
                  <l>He's Rebel both 'gainſt God, and 'gainſt his Prince.</l>
                  <l>And he whoſe cheverel conſcience can diſpenſe</l>
                  <l>With faith to th' one, and fealty to th' other,</l>
                  <l>His legs, and ſides, and all will halt together.</l>
               </q>
               <p>As for Diſputations ſo much deſired; they are good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but, for the moſt part, ſo partially reported, that I have ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome known any good come of them: for when men cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute what others ſay, they will make them ſay what they can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:101116:48"/>
            <head>Errata Majora.</head>
            <p>In the Contents. Sect 7. read <hi>Situation.</hi> Sect 16. for <hi>Roam</hi> read <hi>Romn.</hi> read <hi>Lolla<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds.</hi> pag. 8. lin. 2. read <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 200. l. 23. read <hi>Ieneratio.</hi> p. 11. l. 5. read <hi>ſtirred up.</hi> p. 12. l. 19. read if this <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>t</hi> the very. p. 15. l. 21. read <hi>Sacerdotales.</hi> p 15. l. 27 read <hi>Dis Germ.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 21. p. 17. l. 27. read <hi>de lmper. ſum. p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> p. 22. l. 31. read <hi>Schedius</hi> and <hi>Dis.</hi> p. 25. l. 27. read <hi>Synode.</hi> p. 26. l. 20. read <hi>Rejet<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</hi> l. 29. read <hi>Ailes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> p. 27. l. 6. dele <hi>are.</hi> l. 19. read <hi>Azarias</hi> and <hi>Villalpandus.</hi> l. 22. read <hi>Roman</hi> and dele <hi>together.</hi> p. 28. l 6. read <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> l. 8. read <hi>plane.</hi> l. 11. read <hi>an oblong.</hi> l. 14. read <hi>given.</hi> l. 15. dele colon: l. 22, read <hi>ſeem.</hi> l. 20. read <hi>letters.</hi> p. 29 l. 3. read <hi>Norti<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> and l. 29. read <hi>exception.</hi> p, 30. l. 32. read <hi>Nebuchadnezzar's.</hi> p. 31. l. 33. read <hi>Gyges.</hi> p. 3<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. l. 24. dele 1. p. 40. l. 3<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. read <hi>Swallow.</hi> p. 41. l. 22. read <hi>rebuking.</hi> p. 42. l. 29. dele <hi>if.</hi> p. 43. l. 24. read <hi>Laws.</hi> p. 44. l. ult. read <hi>agree.</hi> p. 48. l. 5. read <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the ſame effect. l. 18. for <hi>by</hi> read <hi>of.</hi> p. 52. l. 10. dele <hi>of.</hi> l. 13. dele <hi>ſo</hi> l. 32. read <hi>inanimate,</hi> p. 54. l. 7. read <hi>Hereunto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> p. 54. l. 10. read <hi>would deſtroy.</hi> l. ult. for <hi>want it,</hi> read <hi>meant it.</hi> p. 55. l. 9. read <hi>take heed in.</hi> p. 57. l. 24. for <hi>unlawfull</hi> read <hi>lawfull.</hi> p. 58. l. ult. for <hi>examination</hi> read <hi>emancipation.</hi> p. 59. l. 1. for <hi>c.</hi> 50. read <hi>tit.</hi> 50. l. 15. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for <hi>of</hi> read <hi>to.</hi> p. 61. l. 11. for <hi>lib.</hi> 2. read <hi>lib.</hi> 1. l. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. read <hi>Paganis.</hi> l. 13. read <hi>pl<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>untur.</hi> l. 14. for <hi>ask</hi> read <hi>after.</hi> l. ult. read by <hi>puniſhing</hi> ſo me <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ort. l. 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. read <hi>without delay bring themſelve<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and theirs to the holy aſſemblies, and.</hi> l. 20. for <hi>Lege Qui,</hi> read <hi>Lege Name <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. l. 21. for <hi>c.</hi> 9. read <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. p. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7. l. 22. read 1<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>38. l. 29. read <hi>liure.</hi> l. 30. read <hi>fa. culte.</hi> l. 30. read <hi>expoſe.</hi> and read <hi>chapitres.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. l. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>4. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad <hi>ſujets.</hi> l. 5. read <hi>obeiſſanc<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> 16. read <hi>b<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n fai<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſujets.</hi> l. 19. read <hi>ſujets.</hi> l. 21. read &amp;c. l. 27. read <hi>penſe.</hi> l. 28. read <hi>pluſiers.</hi> l. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1. dele, p, 69. l. 9. read <hi>detour<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> l. 14. read <hi>ſa<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> p. 72. l. 25. read <hi>in-ſiſted on is this.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101116:48"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
