<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The three countrey-mens English answers to the clergy-mens Latine charges. Or, the lay-mens plain English, in answer to the unknown language of the pretended spiritual court at Winton Unto which is added a short relation of the dealings of Iohn Hayes priest with two of them after they were excommunicated. Also twenty four queries propounded to be answered by those that call themselves spiritual men.</title>
            <author>Gearle, Edmund, d. 1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222199</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833414</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833414</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37890</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A62481)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37890)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2200:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The three countrey-mens English answers to the clergy-mens Latine charges. Or, the lay-mens plain English, in answer to the unknown language of the pretended spiritual court at Winton Unto which is added a short relation of the dealings of Iohn Hayes priest with two of them after they were excommunicated. Also twenty four queries propounded to be answered by those that call themselves spiritual men.</title>
                  <author>Gearle, Edmund, d. 1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Smith to Edmund Gearle. Signed on p. 9: Edmond Gearle; signed on p. 10: Josiah Wichham, Nicholas Wonson.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends' House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37890:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
Three Countrey-mens Engliſh
ANSWERS
TO THE
Clergy-mens Latine
CHARGES.</p>
            <p>OR,
The Lay-mens plain ENGLISH, in anſwer to
the unknown Language of the pretended Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
Court at <hi>Winton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto which is added a ſhort Relation of the dealings of
<hi>Iohn Hayes</hi> Prieſt with two of them after they were excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated.</p>
            <p>Alſo twenty four Queries propounded to be anſwered by thoſe that call
themſelves <hi>Spiritual men.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>They are waxen fat and ſhining, they do overpaſs the deeds of the wicked,
they execute no judgement, no not the judgement of the fatherleſſe <bibl>Jer. 5. 28.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Wo unto them that are mighty to drink wine, and to them that are ſtrong
to pour in ſtrong drink, which justifie the wicked for a reward, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <bibl>Iſa. 5. 22, 23.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1664.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:37890:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37890:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IN the name of God</hi> Amen. We <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deford Bramſtone</hi> Knight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
do on the complaint of <hi>Henry Burrat</hi> and <hi>Alexander Faithful,</hi> Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians
of the Pariſh Church of lower <hi>Wallop</hi> within the Dioceſs of
<hi>Winton,</hi> as followeth.</p>
            <p>Anſwer,</p>
            <p>IT is written, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in
vain;</hi> &amp; theſe things following are not written in the name of God, nor gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venforth
from his ſpirit, though his name be mentioned but are rather found to
proceed from that which oppreſſeth and reſiſteth the ſpirit of God, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth
his ſervants, there being untruth written therein; and wherefore is it
that you force them to complaint, and then herein as it were complain of them
for complaining, but can you ſay that <hi>Henry Burret</hi> and <hi>Alex. Faithful</hi> are
made Guardians or Overſeers by the Holy Ghoſt to guard your Temple made
with hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That thou <hi>Edmond Gearle</hi> art and haſt been of the Pariſh of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Wallop</hi> in the Dioceſs of <hi>Winton,</hi> and of right ſubject to the Court, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Of right I now belong to God, whoſe name I ſee is prophaned
by ſuch as are called ſpiritual men, and of right my ſoul belongs to
Chriſt the Biſhop thereof, who is the power of God, which is the
higheſt power, to which every ſoul is to be ſubject, he being exalted
at the Fathers right hand far above all principalities and powers, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.
20. 21. and in conſcience to the Lord I am ready to ſubmit unto
the ordinance of men, yea though they be wicked men, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
the name of God.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Alſo, That the foreſaid</hi> Henry Burret <hi>and</hi> Alex. Faithfull <hi>in the
Moneths of</hi> March, April, May, June, July, Auguſt, September, Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
November, December, January, February, <hi>and</hi> March, <hi>in the years
of our Lord 1659. 1660. 1661. and</hi> March, April, May, June, July, Auguſt,
September, <hi>in the years of our Lord, 1662. now going on, and at preſent
are Guardians of the Pariſh Church of lower</hi> Wallop, <hi>and are lawfully ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
admitted and ſworn, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whereas it is ſaid they are lawfully elected and admitted,
by what Law was it they were elected, ſo long ſince as three years
and a half? and if by lawful is meant humane or temporal, then how
comes it to paſſe, that men now by temporal matter are admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
ſpiritual office; or by that which is humane or temporal made
Guardians over, or fitted to guard that which is ſpiritual, or muſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37890:3"/>
the temporal overſee the fpiritual, or elſe is the Church they guard
temporal alſo. If it be, why then do ſpiritual men uphold a temporal
Church. But if by, lawful elected, is meant divine or ſpiritual, then
let themſelves declare what divine power they received from God
or men, when they were elected; and let it be proved by what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
or ſpiritual Law of God or Chriſt they were admitted and ſworn,
and when had any of the Apoſtles or true Miniſters any men ſworn
or ſwearers to guard their Churches.</p>
            <p>3. Alſo that all and ſingulaer lands, meſsuages, tenements, within any parish
within the Dioceſſe of <hi>Winton</hi> aforeſaid, are liable and ſubject to pay to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the repairing of the pariſh Church, when there ſhall be occaſion to
repair the ſame according to the value of the ſame lands and tenements, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe are words, wayes, and things of this world, which
paſſeth away, and of the earth that waxeth old, as if it proceeded from
earthly minded men, who themſelves are liable to covetouſneſſe, &amp;
by ambition and vigour force pariſhioners to be liable to ſuch pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
taxes, and cruelties, that they already begin to be weary
thereof, and theſe lines have not the leaſt ſhew of any Scripture au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
nor Apoſtolical example, neither doth this prove that ſuch as
are not of the world, as Chriſt is not of the world, but are followers
of him, that they ought to pay towards the repairing of a houſe
made with hands, and yet be called a Church, which is another
thing then that for which Chriſt ſhed his bloud, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 28.</p>
            <p>4. Alſo that in the years or moneths aforeſaid, or in ſome of thoſe years or
moneths in the time of the rate or tax made, thou <hi>Edmond Gearle</hi> didſt
have, hold, and occupy a certain meſſage or tenement, with certain lands to
the ſame, belonging and appertaining within the pariſh of lower <hi>Wallop</hi>
foreſaid, and thou wert ſaid, and commonly reported to be the poſſeſſour and
occupier of the ſaid meſſage or tenement and lands aforeſaid,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is written more like the critical ſubtil Lawyers, ſuch
as Chriſt cried wo againſt, who took away the key of Knowledge,
<hi>Luke</hi> 11. 52. As you keep knowledge from our eyes, and not like
men endued with the Spirit of God, though at firſt you take his
name in your mouths, and then go on like them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did ſo, and
hated to be reformed. But by your words, it was ſometime, or never
that I did poſſeſſe ſomething or nothing, and it was ſo, or elſe ſaid or
reported to be ſo, which words opene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h like a wide mouth, but brings
forth little or nothing: but if it be ſo, that once or never I did poſſeſs
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37890:3"/>
a tenement or piece of land, and that your tax was aſſeſſed upon the
ſame, then not upon my perſon; therefore you ſhould have ſought
it from the land according to your own way, whilſt it was in my poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion,
and not upon my perſon, now it is not in my poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>5. Alſo that in the year of our Lord 1659. and in the moneths in the ſame
year, or in ſome or one of them, the pariſh Church of lower <hi>Wallop</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,
was much ruinated, and out of repair in the walls, and tower, ſeats,
and ornaments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and other things to the ſame parish Church belonging and
appertaining, and this was and is true and manifeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Then it ſeems your buildings have been once going down,
and ſo out of repair already, ſo that I perceive it is poſſible your
buildings may decay, and if ſo, then at laſt fall, and come to an end:
but now you appear like them that ſaid, The bricks are fallen down,
but we will build with hewen ſtone. But take you heed leaſt you
weave the Spiders web, and haſten Gods wrath againſt your ſelves,
and then he brings down your high Towers, and makes your walls
like a tottering hedge, and remove your ſeats though you have ſet
your neſts on high, and exalted your ſelves above the ſtars of God,
like thoſe that act ſpiritual wickedneſſe in high places, from the
which when the Lord God brings you down, and rewards you accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to your works, which he will ſurely do, then ſhall you know
that this is true and manifeſt.</p>
            <p>6. Alſo that in the year and moneths, and in the year of our Lord
1659. aforeſaid, and in the moneths of the ſame year in the time of the
rate and tax, making the aforeſaid <hi>Henry Burret</hi> and <hi>Alexander Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi>
guardians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had not within their hands or poſſeſsions, neither were
to receive or have any rents, or lands, or tenements to the ſame Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
or appertaining, or any other means to repair or amend the ſame
pariſh Church, otherwiſe then by m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>king and impoſing a rate and tax on
themſelves, and other Pariſhioners and inhabitants of the ſame Pariſh li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits
and precincts of the ſame Pariſh, and that this is true and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There you have as it was told a large ſtory, how a rate or
tax was made, but here is not one word of the Law of God, nor of the
Goſpel of his Son, nor ſo much as three words of Scripture language,
but non-ſence put in the ſtead thereof, as though there were both
years and moneths in the year 1659. and if you have neither Rents,
Lands, Tenements, nor any other means to uphold your Church
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37890:4"/>
walls from going down, nor to repair the ruinations thereof, but
what you get by force and violence like <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinias,</hi> then that
is the ready way to make all people weary both of you and your
Church too, and this is true, and may come at laſt to be manifefl.</p>
            <p>7. Alſo that in the aforeſaid year 1659. in the moneths in the ſame year
or in one of them, &amp;c. the Guardians, Pariſhoners, and Inhabitants of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
of lower <hi>Wallop</hi> aforeſaid, according to forewarning at certain dayes, or
a certain day and place, &amp;c. or the greateſt part of them came together, and
with unanimous aſſent and conſent did tax and impoſe Rates and Taxes in and
upon all Pariſhoners &amp; Inhabitants, and other Meſſages, Lands or Tenements
within the Pariſh aforeſaid, and within the limits and precincts of the ſame
Pariſh, the holders and occupiers of the ſame, according to the value of the
Meſſages, Lands and Tenements of every perſon for and toward the repaira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
and amendment of the defects of the faid Church, and ornaments, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
things belonging to the ſame Church, and amongſt other Pariſhoners and
Inhabitants of the ſaid Pariſh, thee the aforeſaid <hi>Edmond Gearle</hi> for a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage,
or Tenement and Lands by thee within the Pariſh aforeſaid, limits and
precincts, &amp;c. in the year and moneths, &amp;c. held poſſeſſed, and occupied, and
according to the quantity, quality, and value of the ſame did rightfully and
lawfully tax the ſumme of two ſhillings and two pence to be paid to the
Guardians aforeſaid, for and towards the repairation and amendment of the
defects of the ſaid Church, and ornaments, and other appurtenances to the
ſaid Church belonging; and this is true and manifeſted, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Herein you ſhew again in what year (but very doubtfully)
what moneth the Tax was made, and how it came to be, but not the
leaſt example thereof from any of the Miniſters of Chriſt, though
you do mention it is for and towards the repairations and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of the defects of your Church, and the ornaments belonging
to the ſame, whereby it ſeems your called ſpiritual men are ſeeking
to repair the defects of a temporal Church, for your Church and the
ornaments thereof are things that are ſeen, and the Apoſtle ſaith the
things that are ſeen are temporal, &amp; ſuch things will wax old &amp; decay
and at laſt may vaniſh away, as better things then them did; and it
ſeems your Church ornaments are defective, and the Church it ſelf
defective, and it may be the upholders thereof defective, and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
defective, and the faith vain, and then what ſhall we do there, or
why ſhould we pay mony to have ſuch defective ſtuffe renewed, and
it may be your upholding ſuch defective ſtuffe is not only defective,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37890:4"/>
but alſo to us deſtructive or hurtful both in body, ſoul, and ſtate,
which nothing can be ſo to us, that is truely ſpiritual of God; but
that this Tax of two ſhillings two pence to be paid by me towards
the repairing of the defective Church is rightfully according to any
Goſpel order impoſed upon me, or lawfully according to any Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
Law aſſeſſed upon the Lands I then held, according to any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
direction I do deny, neither do I believe that moſt of the Pariſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners
were together at the ſeaſing of this Tax, neither can you prove
the ſame, and therefore this is falſe, and not manifeſt.</p>
            <p>8. Alſo that after the rate made Tax or Impoſition as aboveſaid, &amp;c.
all the Pariſhioners and Inhabitants of the Pariſh aforeſaid and other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietours,
Poſſeſſours and Occupiers of Meſſages, Lands, and Tenements
within the ſaid Pariſh, limits, and precincts, or the major part of them
have paid or are ready to pay the foreſaid Guardians the Rates and Taxes
upon them Impoſed notwithstanding they have been diſſwaded from paying
the ſame by thee and others, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As for the major part paying the ſaid rates or tax, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor
part go the broad way which leads to deſtruction, who being in
the worlds nature follow their blind leaders, like weary horſes under
their heavy burthens, notwithſtanding they ſee their Teachers
reel to and fro in the matter of their worſhip like the waves of the
Sea, and ſtagger about the manner thereof like drunken men, and caſt
off their profeſſions like ſerpents, and change themſelves in other ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits
like Taylors, and into other colours, ſhews, and faſhions, like
Camelions, and turn with the times, like the wind, and change every
ſeaſon, like the Moon, and conform to any thing, like time-ſervers,
yet not ſo much as transform themſelves into the likeneſſe of the true
Apoſtles of Chriſt, neither do they bear the image or ſhadow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of;
but if moſt of the Pariſhioners aforeſaid have paid your Tax, I
queſtion not but they had rather kept their money, ſome of them
to relieve their Families, and ſome out of ſaving, or covetouſneſſe,
and it may be ſome of them, had as willingly have gone to the Ale-houſe
with it, ſo little zeal may fome of this major part have to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
your defective Church, and ſome that did pay it, might pay
becauſe you rule with ſuch force and cruelty over them, that they
dare not do otherwiſe, and ſo thoſe are not chearful givers, nor wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
payers, and ſo you have not much to boaſt therein; and their
ſouls having ſo little benefit by that decayed and defective Church
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37890:5"/>
that they have ſeveral ſufficient reaſons in themſelves to diſſwade
them not to pay without being perſwaded thereunto by me and
others.</p>
            <p>9. Alſo that thou the aforeſaid <hi>Edmond Gearle,</hi> though thou haſt been
asked and called upon for the aboveſaid ſumme of two ſhillings two pence
oft times or once by the aforeſaid <hi>Henry Burret</hi> and <hi>Alexander Faithful</hi>
guardians, or by one of them, for and towards the reparation of the Church
aforeſaid, yet thou hast denied, or refuſed, or yet doſt delay or defer at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
to pay the ſame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, I had good reaſon ſo to do, and if I had met but
with ſuch reaſonable dealing as uſually is among heathens, they had
not need to have asked more of me, nor have had that unreaſonable
covetouſneſſe to ſeek any more from me towards their defective
Church, for the which there being taken from me by <hi>John Cox,</hi> and
<hi>Nicholas Thomas</hi> in the year 1658. one brewing kettle, one waſhing
kettle, one peuter diſh, worth about twelve ſhillings, though their
own demand was but five ſhillings five pence, which was alſo for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing
the defective Church, ſo that above three years ſince the
guardians of the ſaid Church have had from me about ſix ſhillings
ſeven pence aforehand, which is about three times two ſhillings now
demanded, ſo that of right and by good reaſon, if not according to
your own way there remains due to me near four ſhillings five pence,
and therefore as I ſaid I had good reaſon not to pay any more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
your defective Church.</p>
            <p>10. Alſo that thou knoweſt that the aforeſaid <hi>Henry Burret</hi> and <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander
Faithful</hi> guardians aboveſaid for all and ſingular the matters and
things aboveſaid, and on their parts have rightfully and lawfully complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
unto us and our office in this behalf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is utterly falſe that I do know, that you called guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians
to your foreſaid defective Church, did rightfully and lawfully
complain unto your office for all and ſingular matters and things
aforeſaid, nor yet any part thereof, being utterly falſe, is turned
back unto you as a filthy thing, which is not in the name of God,
though at firſt you did take his name into your mouths, and now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
ſomething worſe then thoſe that began in the Spirit, and end in
the fleſh, if you have only begun with his name in your mouths, and
at the end lies proceed out of the ſame mouth, like bleſſing and
curſing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:37890:5"/>
11. Alſo that thou knowest, believeſt, or haſt heard to be ſaid, that all
and ſingular of the premiſes have been and are true, and concerning which,
and all the ſaid premiſes, the aforeſaid Guardians do require Juſtice to be
adminiſtred, with the effects, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What I know &amp; believe is one thing, and what I have heard
to be ſaid may be another, for I may know and believe the truth,
but if I ſhould harken much to ſuch lying men as the Prieſts of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi>
who have now ſufficiently ſhewed themſelves, I may not only
hear what is ſaid, to be lies, but the lyes themſelves, for they ſaid and
pretended they led us the right way before, and now they would lead
us another way, and ſay this is right, and they ſaid they were Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
of Chriſt before, and now they deny their own profeſſion and
practice, and yet pretend they are Miniſters of Chriſt now, and
though they for filthy lucre turn every way like the wind, and creep
for duſt or earthly things like Serpents, yet ſtill they pretend to be
right; and as for your ſaid Guardians juſtice from you upon me, it
is more like they are forced by you, and your wicked oaths impoſed
upon them to do what they do, when they had rather be quiet with
their neighbours, who by theſe unchriſtian like proceedings are
ſometimes now ſet at variance, and ſo you ſhew your ſelves like fools
that ſtirre up ſtrife, and as for the juſtice of your Court which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
little mercy, I have neither known, nor do I believe, nor certainly
hear that you have full power according to your own Law by ſpecial
Pattent or Broad Seal for what you do, but remember you muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
from God according to your works.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>by me who am a lover of the Truth, called EDMOND GEARLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <p>
               <hi>JAcob</hi> was a plain man and the Lord loved him, and we are plain
men and are perſwaded that Gods love is towards us; however
men may hate us and ſeek occaſion againſt us, and uſe us hardly as
our Fathers were in <hi>Egypt,</hi> but we having the love of God ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad
in our hearts we dare not offend him, in doing or upholding
that which the Lord hath ſhewed us to be evil, and though we have
not much knowledge in the Law, yet we know what is juſt &amp; reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able;
&amp; though we have not much heretofore known the proceedings
in this which you call a Spiritual Court, yet we ſee and plainly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37890:6"/>
that you who are the upholders thereof are not guided by
the ſpirit of God who is Love, nor by the ſpirit of his ſon, who ſaid,
<hi>love your enemies,</hi> but by another ſpirit, the fruits whereof both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
us and before our faces hath appeared to be quite contrary to
the ſpirit of God which is ſhewn by the Apoſtles, <hi>Gal</hi> 5. yea, and
you have ſhewed forth works of darkneſſe towards us, throwing away
our hats, and even abuſing them and us, as once by prophane
curſing of us, and then give us writing wherein (it may be) is
declared what is demanded, but by reaſon it is written in ſuch
a dark way, not only in <hi>Latine,</hi> but in ſuch an unſound and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain
or unknown way, that if we were willing to pay it, we can
ſcarce come to know how much it is, whereby alſo it appears you
are men of ſuch a ſpirit that ſeeks to keep us in darkneſſe and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
and from the knowledge of thoſe things which concerns our
bodies and eſtates as well as our ſouls, that by no means we might
underſtand it, though we much deſire the ſame; and we know no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
that we or any elſe ſhould give any unto you for ſo doing, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
can we be free or clear in the ſight of God to pay towards the
maintenance of ſuch a Prieſthood, which is to be upheld by men of
ſuch a ſpirit, nor to uphold or repair ſuch Temples in which they (not
we) do worſhip, but we confeſſe Chriſt come, and him to be our
Prieſt for ever, and the Biſhop of our ſouls, and our bodies are a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
houſe built up of living ſtones, of which Chriſt is the Head we
own, which is not a Temple made with hands, <hi>for ye are the Temple of
the living God, and I will dwell in them, and walk in them, ſaith the Lord;</hi>
but as for that place built with mens hands called a Church, we own
it not for the Church, and therefore we cannot pay to the upholding
of the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Joſiah Wickham,</item>
                     <item>Nicholas Wonſon.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <p>The Reader may know that the Declarations which theſe three men
received at the Court were one and the ſame, only their names and
the ſummes of Money demanded were ſeveral, as one two ſhillings
two pence, another two ſhillings ſix pence, and the other three
ſhillings.</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37890:6"/>
            <head>Here followeth a ſhort Relation of the actions and dealings of the Prieſt of
the Pariſh (unto which we belong) with us, after we were excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
by them.</head>
            <p>AFter that we had delivered into the Court theſe our Anſwers,
having been abuſed in words, and our hats taken from our
heads, and thrown from us; and alſo one of the Parators curſing of
us (which is of the ſpirit of the wicked one whom they obey) and
having thruſt us forth of their Court, could not be ſatisfied, but
proceeded to excommunication (or curſing) of us from out of fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip
with them (whom we dare not to have union with) we ſay the
Prieſt of the defective Church he proceeded to ſentence of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,
and curſed us from amongſt them, with the which we
reſted well ſatisfied, and had peace with the Lord whom we obey
(though detected and rejected by thoſe whoſe actions ſhew by what
ſpirit they are guided, as may be ſeen in open view<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) Now after they
had thus dealt with us in ſummoning us from time to time to our
great hinderance (who are husbandmen, and got our bread by our
labour) telling us divers times that we ſhould have our articles) or
in writing that which they alledged againſt us, wherein alſo they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
liars, and ſo to be of their father the Devil; for when we came ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to appointment they ſhuffled us off, and would bid us come
another time, and ſo we did ſeveral times before we had it. But to
come to the thing, this Prieſt after he had proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eded to excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication
in publick before his hearers, then he came to us, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
tithe, and coming to <hi>Ioſiah Wickhams</hi> houſe, he asked him
how many ſheep he had ſhorn (he being but Vicar, having the tithe
of wooll, lambs, calves, apples, plumbs, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> unto which he gave him
anſwer, that it mattered not how many ſheep he had ſhorn, for they
were none but his own, at the which he raged; alſo his wife ſaid unto
him, that ſhe thought he would not have offered to come to them
for wages, ſeeing he had before curſed them forth of his Church, unto
which the Prieſt like a (dumb dog) was ſilent, and afterward like a
fox he went far about to bite, and <hi>ſub poena</hi>'d us to appear at the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer
on ſuch a day (it being nominated) and then we went to the
Prieſt to ſpeak with him about it, but he put us by and told us, that
he would ſpeak with us another time, and likewiſe he having before
dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ived us of the benefit of Law, he then ſued us at the Law (which
is double wickedneſſe in the ſight of God, and will appear odious in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37890:7"/>
the ſight of any reaſonable man, and ſeems ridiculous; according to
that Proverb, <hi>Firſt cut off their legs, &amp; then bid them go.</hi> And then for
Non-appearance we were ſerved with a proceſſe by a Bayliffe, and at
that time alſo we went to ſpeak with the Prieſt to know what he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
to do with us, and he ſaid, we muſt go to priſon, if we would
not pay him, whom before he had renounced as Hereticks. Mark peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
this man who profeſſes himſelf a Miniſter of Chriſt, would be
maintained by us whom he hath curſed; ſome of his Church hath alſo
told us, that they muſt not buy or ſell with us, &amp; yet this Prieſt would
have maintenance from us. Surely he and his brethren are not to be
parallel'd, nay the falſe Prophets of old, of whom we read, were not
found in ſuch actions. Would not <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phineas,</hi> wicked men,
(who took the offerings by force) have been aſhamed to have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
as this man hath done, who though they did take the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings
by force, it was of them who were of Iſrael (and not
of the heathen) But theſe Prieſts manifeſt themſelves, yea they
are already manifeſt to us, that can ſee, hear, or underſtand, to
be abſolute wolves, whoſe ſheeps cloathing (though now its but nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row)
by theſe and ſuch like actions will be wholly ſtripped off, and
appear they ſhall even as they are, before the eyes of all. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed,
this Prieſt perceiving that we were reſolved to go to Priſon, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
then to uphold or maintain his belly (which is his God) he then
began to fawn and to wipe his eyes (Crockadile like) pretending he
was ſorry, and bid us we ſhould not go, with other words which he
uſed; yet our minds he could not alter, who had faith in our God,
and did truſt in his name, who hath been a tower of refuge unto us;
and ſo we were brought to this priſon, where we have been kept about
twenty five weeks from our honeſt labours, yea, this ſerpent was ſo
ſubtil, that he choſe (as he thought) the beſt time throughout the
year for his purpoſe, and ſo by that thought to get over us, it being
then the beginning of harveſt, and we had not any man-ſervant to
take care for our corn, and ſo to outward appearance it was in danger
(or ſome of it) of being ſpoiled. But the God whom we ſerve, and for
whoſe cauſe and teſtimony we this day ſuffer provided for us beyond
our expectation, and even raiſed ſome that were our enemies, that
they profred to aſſiſt our wives and chilbren. So our harveſt was
brought in (though it was ſomething more charge to us) in ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
time, praiſes to him that ruleth over all, &amp; ſince we were brought
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ither, ſome of his flock hath ſpoken with him about us, and as we
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37890:7"/>
hear, he gave one of them this anſwer, That if he ſhould let us alone,
others would ſerve him ſo likewiſe, and none would pay him, and ſo
he might ſtarve. Mark how far this man is from that Spirit which ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaid, They laboured day and night, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they would not be chargeable, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 11. 9. But this Prieſt
<hi>Iohn Hayes</hi> he is ſo far from purpoſing to work with his own hands,
that he intends to make others maintain him, whether they are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
or not, and ſo little love hath his hearers towards him, that if
there were not a law he might ſtarve, as appears by his own words. Oh
what a flock hath this man gathered, and what a vineyard hath this
man planted, and what fruitleſſe trees (that cumbers the ground) hath
this man ſet, who would yield him no fruit to ſatisfie his belly, &amp; what
unruly flocks (but more like herds) hath theſe Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
who would give no milk. Surely they are careleſſe ſhepherds,
they gather not, they heal not, they bind not up the wounds of the
ſheep, they ſeek not the loſt, nor regard thoſe that die in pollution.
They eat of the fat, and cloath themſelves with the wooll, ſitting at
eaſe in their houſes, and fill themſelves with wine at their pleaſures:
they waſte the creation on their luſts, and rule over people with ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour:
their wives ſit as Ladies at their feaſts, and they have the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
room in the Synagogues; the people labour in the earth, and
God gives the increaſe, and theſe Caterpillers eat the fruits of their
labours. But the whirlwind of Gods fury ariſeth which ſhall ſcatter
them as the chaffe, and drive them into the lake of woe and miſery,
unleſſe they repent with ſpeed.</p>
            <p>Wherefore all ye people that reads the foregoing with a ſingle eye,
and conſiders the thing with an upright heart; hearken, was there ever
ſuch oppreſſion as this? read the Scriptures, and trace the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
of old, and parallel them wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h this man, and you may eaſily
perceive and underſtand that there was not the like found among
them, for though they were wicked, and their ſins great, and though
their abominations reached unto heaven, wherefore their ſolemn Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies
God could not away with, but their ſacrifices were abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
unto him, and their incenſe which ſhould have been a good
ſavour in his noſtrils became as a ſtink before him, yet we do not read
that any of thoſe Prieſts dealt ſo cruelly with the people, as to thruſt
them from among them, and afterwards to caſt them into priſon, if
they would not maintain them, though by the Law of God there was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37890:8"/>
authority given for them to have tithe; but theſe Prieſts are ſo far
from acting by the Law of God, that many times they do contrary
to the Law of man, in taking away their goods, and keep them in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
alſo. Surely greedy dogs they are, and have manifeſted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
to be. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in his dayes complained of ſuch, <hi>ch.</hi> 56. 10, 11.
The watchmen are all blind, they have no knowledge, they are all
dumb dogs, greedy dogs, that never have enough, looking every one
for his gain from his quarter. So read people, mark your ſhepherds,
behold and ſee, can they underſtand, are they not dumb unleſſe they
have their gain, yea do they not all ſeek it every one from his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
for they never have enough, but ſue at Law, and caſt honeſt men
into priſon, hunt for greater benefices, as witneſſe <hi>Iohn Hayes</hi> of <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop</hi>
who is not ſatisfied with the tithe of one pariſh, nor is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
with ſixty pounds a year, but hungers for more of theſe earthly
things (which is the Serpents meat) yea in ſtead of being ſervant, as
<hi>Paul</hi> was, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 19. He rules as Lord over them, ſuing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
at Law with his Pariſhioners; but the day makes him mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt,
though the beaſts go to their dens, yet the light is broken forth
that diſcovers them all, and they can no longer hide themſelves from
it; wherefore they foam, roar, and rage (and why) but becauſe their
time is ſhort, for the night is over with thouſands, and they are and
ſhall be more manifeſt; a day of trembling is coming upon them,
wherein rocks nor mountains ſhall not hide them from the powerful
ſtroke of the Lamb who is coming to reign; wherefore fear all people,
and dread the Lord God ye inhabitants of the earth, for a day of
howling is coming upon all the workers of iniquity, all ye Prieſts,
Proctors, Deans and Parators, with the reſt of the uncircumciſed,
diſmal is the day which haſtens, and black unto you (who have reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
the light) a day of trouble and anguiſh, a day of torment, and
perplexity, and of great ſorrow ſhall compaſſe you, from the which
there is no way to eſcape but by ſpeedy repentance and amendment
of life; wherefore conſider it before it be too late.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>J. W.</item>
                     <item>N. W.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="questions">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:37890:8"/>
            <head>Now here follows a few Queries for any of thoſe called Spiritual
Men to anſwer.</head>
            <p>1. <hi>Query.</hi> Who ſet up the first Spiritual Court, and where was it ſet
up, or whether there were any one ſet up by the Apostles, or by the Biſhops
in their dayes, as <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>2. If there were any one ſet up by them, then to what end was it ſet up,
and what did they deelare was their intent who did ſet up ſuch a Court?</p>
            <p>3. Whether it was not after the Apoſtles deceaſe before any of theſe
Courts were ſet up (in whoſe dayes) there were many Antichrists entered
into the world?</p>
            <p>4. Whether the night of Apoſtacy did not ſoon come after the Apoſtles
deceaſe, wherein no man could work for God?</p>
            <p>5. Whether it was poſſible for any (who were in this night) to do any
thing for the glory and honour of God.</p>
            <p>6. Whether is the Judge of your Spiritual Court (ſo called) a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
man, and whether he doth act for God.</p>
            <p>7. Whether a ſpiritual man of God who ſits in the Judgement Seat can
ſee ſober men wronged in his Court, and he not reſcue them?</p>
            <p>8. Whether a man who Judges for God can hear ſome or one of his own
Court curſe, and not puniſh him according to the Law provided?</p>
            <p>9. Whether a man that Judges for God can ſee ſuch a man wrong others
more innocent then himſelf, and he take part rather with him that curſes
then with him that is abuſed and innocent?</p>
            <p>10. To what end are your Proctors in your Courts, or for what ſervice
are they, or are they there appointed to cheat the people of their money, if
people have offended why ſhould not all both poor and rich ſuffer alike?</p>
            <p>11. Whether its not a cheat and an abſolute ſin againſt God to take mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
for the offence of one when another that hath not money, or cannot for
conſcience ſake give it you, must ſuffer the utmoſt penalty of the Law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided?</p>
            <p>12. Whether you do not reſpect perſons in ſo doing?</p>
            <p>13. Whether is your Church made up of wood and ſtone, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>14. Or whether men and women gathered together are your Church?
If you ſay its the Church of wood and ſtone which you own,</p>
            <p>15. Then whether Chriſt purchaſed ſuch Churches to himſelf, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
he ſhed his bloud for them, or whether ſuch Churches are to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented
without ſpot to God?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:37890:9"/>
If you ſay men and women gathered are your Church.</p>
            <p>16. Then whether your Church be without ſpot, or whether your Church
members be holy, or whether their ſins be waſhed away by the bloud of
Chriſt?</p>
            <p>If you ſay yes,</p>
            <p>17. Then of what Church are thoſe who are Drunkards, Swearers,
Lyars, Curſers, Perſecutors, Gamesters, Riotors, Whoremongers, Dancers,
Racers, Hunters, they ſaying that they own you, and have fellowſhip with
you?</p>
            <p>18. Whether you own ſuch perſons before mentioned, yea or nay?</p>
            <p>19. Whether your Parators are ſpiritual men?</p>
            <p>If ſo,</p>
            <p>20. Then whether ſpiritual men of God will be drunk, lye, ſwear, call
honeſt mon rogues, and cauſe people to be idle on ſome of the ſix dayes, on
which the Law of God commands them to work?</p>
            <p>21. Whether you allow your Parators in theſe things?</p>
            <p>If you do,</p>
            <p>22. Then whether it be not abſolute deceit and lyes in you to read, and
in pretence own and command people to do that, <hi>viz.</hi> work ſix dayes, when
you intend to puniſh them if they do, and ſend men abroad through the
Countrey for that purpoſe?</p>
            <p>23. Whether you own that Parators may take money of ſome (when they
have feared them) for their pretended offence, and ſo let it be ſufficient for
them, when others that cannot for conſcience ſake give into their mouthes
they bring to you for a farther ſnare.</p>
            <p>24. By what authority do you do theſe things?</p>
            <p>Anſwer theſe Queries if you can, and ſend it abroad in Print to ſatisfie
the people; for many are, and more will be weary of you.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
