<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tom tell-troth, or, A dialogue between the Devil and the Pope about carrying on the plot</title>
            <author>Oldham, John, 1653-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-05">2003-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62856</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25654</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09053788</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09053788</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42337</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A62856)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42337)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1296:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tom tell-troth, or, A dialogue between the Devil and the Pope about carrying on the plot</title>
                  <author>Oldham, John, 1653-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Oldham--Wrenn catalog.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42337:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42337:1"/>
            <head>Tom Tell-Troth: OR, A DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE DEVIL and the POPE, About Carrying on the PLOT.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DEVIL.</speaker>
               <l>MY dear adopted Heir, mine only Son,</l>
               <l>Thou that hast fought, and all my Battels won,</l>
               <l>Inlarg'd my Kingdom, and with Thousand Souls</l>
               <l>Fill'd up the Cat'logue of my sulphury Rowles;</l>
               <l>Whose fi'ry Bulls, and bloody Inquisition,</l>
               <l>Feign'd Purgatory, and thy false Tradition,</l>
               <l>Beads, Images, thy Relicks, Crucifix,</l>
               <l>Indulgence, Pardons, and such taking-tricks,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:42337:2"/>
Have more augmented my Infernal Host,</l>
               <l>Than Pagan-<hi>Rome</hi> her self could ever boast,</l>
               <l>And damn'd more Souls, than Hereticks e're lost.</l>
               <l>This to thy glory I acknowledg—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>POPE.</speaker>
               <l>Grand-sire of Popes, 'tis kindness thus to own</l>
               <l>What duty we thy Nose-led Sons have shown.</l>
               <l>That Letter which I lately did receive</l>
               <l>From thy dark Court, did me such courage give,</l>
               <l>(Which I had answer'd <hi>(Sir)</hi> but for this Reason,</l>
               <l>So many of our men of late for Treason</l>
               <l>Have ply'd old <hi>Charon</hi> so, that he did swear,</l>
               <l>Go and be damn'd your self, d'ye think I care</l>
               <l>To be your Porter? I must tend my Fare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>Is he so flusht? I shall abate his fee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>And well you may, since 'tis encreas'd by me.)</l>
               <l>That welcom Packet (you may it believe)</l>
               <l>To me, I say, did such new vigour give,</l>
               <l>As had not that mysterious English Monster,</l>
               <l>Which Popes or Devils ne're could truly conster,</l>
               <l>Who all our Policies do circumvent,</l>
               <l>That many-headed Beast call'd <hi>Parliament,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cross'd my designs, <hi>Englands</hi> admir'd Prince</l>
               <l>Had fall'n a sacrifice to thee long since.</l>
               <l>But since your Devilship is pleas'd to come</l>
               <l>In person, to your lower Court at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My zeal's blown up to such an heat, nay flame,</l>
               <l>That I resolve it (in the Devils name)</l>
               <l>Neither to stop or stay, I'le take no rest</l>
               <l>Till I have once more fir'd that Rebel nest</l>
               <l>Of Hereticks; and if my Jesu'ts falter,</l>
               <l>I will my self provide them each an Halter.</l>
               <l>Had not base Cowardise appear'd our foe</l>
               <l>At <hi>White-hall, Windsor,</hi> and <hi>New-market</hi> too</l>
               <l>Our work, I'am sure, had not been now to do:</l>
               <l>But since they are so fearful of the Rope,</l>
               <l>They shall expect it from their Father Pope.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42337:2"/>
The next occasion that doth happen fair,</l>
               <l>He that shall slip it, i'faith, I'le send him where</l>
               <l>He shall do penance for his pannick fear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>Heroickly resolv'd, I like it well:</l>
               <l>But how will you go forward, can you tell?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>That I expect from you; but the old Mask</l>
               <l>I think will serve till we have done our task.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>What mask is that, my Son?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>Religion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>Right,</l>
               <l>This mannag'd well, with policy, and might,</l>
               <l>Will do the business: wrest it as you please,</l>
               <l>This way, or that, to give the Actor ease.</l>
               <l>Make it a Shooing-horn, that will eas'ly draw</l>
               <l>Any thing on, and make it seem a Law.</l>
               <l>A Stalking-horse, whereunder you may lurk,</l>
               <l>Till you've accomplish'd your intended work.</l>
               <l>'Tis a brave guil<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Mask that blears the eye,</l>
               <l>And makes a lye seem truth, and truth a lye.</l>
               <l>You've put it on already, use it well,</l>
               <l>And expect aid from all the powers of Hell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>I hope, most Infamous <hi>Apollyon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You will be pleas'd to see how we go on;</l>
               <l>And new inspire us with <hi>Ignatian</hi> zeal,</l>
               <l>To make such Rents as none shall ever heal.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>Doubt not my utmost aid, for 'tis the Pope</l>
               <l>And his Adherents are the only hope</l>
               <l>I have on earth; 'tis by your heads and hands</l>
               <l>My Kingdom in the world so strongly stands.</l>
               <l>Besides, if you consider well how I</l>
               <l>Have taught you to equivocate and lye,</l>
               <l>Then to confirm it by the Sacrament,</l>
               <l>You've little cause to doubt my male-intent.</l>
               <l>A thousand ways I've shewn you how to gull</l>
               <l>The cred'lous multitude, and do you—?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>Nay, pray, Sir, be not thus enrag'd, that I</l>
               <l>Ask the assistance of your pollicy.</l>
               <l>Preceding Popes have by tradition told</l>
               <l>What you by them, and for them did of old.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:42337:3"/>
And I confess (dear Father) you have done</l>
               <l>As much for me as e're you did for Son.</l>
               <l>For which, I vow, I will not fail to sac're</l>
               <l>Those dues to you, I owe unto my Maker;</l>
               <l>And dayly more endeavour Art and Powers</l>
               <l>T' assure you (Sir) I am obliged yours:</l>
               <l>Yet am I but a passive instrument</l>
               <l>In your wise hands, to perfect your intent.</l>
               <l>The Conquests that I win, belong to you,</l>
               <l>And I hold it just, to give the De'il his due,</l>
               <l>And truer Trojans, <hi>Sir,</hi> you have but few.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>I am appeas'd.—Observe now what I say,</l>
               <l>Till all obstructions lying in our way</l>
               <l>Be beaten down, my Scepter cannot sway.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>Name what they are, <hi>Sir,</hi> and the Devil take me</l>
               <l>If I don't do't, unless my Imps forsake me,</l>
               <l>Which I don't fear, for they have plighted troth</l>
               <l>To be thy faithful drudges and mine both:</l>
               <l>And no reserves shall serve, that they can mint;</l>
               <l>If Devil cheat Devil, then the Devils in't:</l>
               <l>Equivicate they may with Hereticks,</l>
               <l>But not with thee or me, who know their tricks.</l>
               <l>Thy counsel therefore Great <hi>Abaddon—</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>First set on work your Engines, to prevent</l>
               <l>That ador'd Idol, called Parliament;</l>
               <l>Hells greatest envy, Popery's mortal foe,</l>
               <l>Popes plague and pest, and <hi>Rome</hi>'s eternal woe.</l>
               <l>These must not sit, for they'l be laying ope</l>
               <l>All our ambushments, and sinister scope:</l>
               <l>See this be done, and then there is no doubt,</l>
               <l>But we shall yet bring matters brave about.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>But grant they do, if we the Members chuse,</l>
               <l>Our party by it then can nothing lose.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>But that's a devilish hazard, if we shall;</l>
               <l>'Tis sufer, therefore, there be none at all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>Agreed, and to this end, in us, I'le see</l>
               <l>That nothing shall be wanting.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>Nor in me.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42337:3"/>
Next, I advise, you speedily depose</l>
               <l>Him, whom th' Almighty his Vicegerent chose:</l>
               <l>Let not that Bugbare, Idol, name of King,</l>
               <l>Into your spirits any terror bring.</l>
               <l>He is Heretical declar'd;—'tis good</l>
               <l>To get his Crown by shedding of his blood,</l>
               <l>'Tis our great loss that He so long hath stood.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>England</hi>'s Gloyr, King and Parliament</l>
               <l>Destroy'd, we cannot fail of our intent,</l>
               <l>To pull down Laws both Civil and Divine,</l>
               <l>And in their room to set up yours and mine.</l>
               <l>A cunning cheat, the Church and State to mend</l>
               <l>By killing Him that should them both defend.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>St. <hi>Coleman</hi> good success unto it send.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>This done, to Trap again, and with that game,</l>
               <l>Cutting won't be amiss, that so the flame</l>
               <l>May ne're extinguish'd be, but by a flood</l>
               <l>Of the accursed Hereticks heart-blood.</l>
               <l>And to this end, see you an Army fix,</l>
               <l>That you ben't bafl'd as in Sixty six,</l>
               <l>And do your work by halves—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>Each man shall strive who shall burn and kill most,</l>
               <l>And I will pray, the Devil take the hindmost.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>It shall be so; and so adieu.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>Nay, stay,</l>
               <l>And think if you've not somewhat more to say.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>What is the Shipping you should set on fire?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis well remembred, my mischievous Sire.]</l>
               <l>A little of that i'th' <hi>Thames,</hi> at <hi>Chatham</hi> too,</l>
               <l>Would greatly weaken our Imperial foe,</l>
               <l>And to our Friends, the <hi>French,</hi> huge service do.</l>
               <l>'Tis well you stay'd, What more?—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>Justice corrupt with Bribes; you see the bait</l>
               <l>Is pleasing, and if large, is taken strait.</l>
               <l>Make rents in Church, fire the Non-Con's zeal,</l>
               <l>And Con's 'gainst him, till they each other peal.</l>
               <l>Preach up the Ceremonies now, and when</l>
               <l>You know 'twill tickle, Preach them down again.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42337:4"/>
Sometimes the Bishop you must stile Divine,</l>
               <l>That under those alone the Church doth shine:</l>
               <l>That all Fanaticks, and their false opinion,</l>
               <l>Are wholly mine, and set up my Dominion.</l>
               <l>Sometimes <hi>Iohn</hi> Presbyter commend, and cry,</l>
               <l>They are the Preaching, Gospel Ministry.</l>
               <l>Then for Plebeans, you'll do very well,</l>
               <l>To banish from their minds all fear of Hell.</l>
               <l>Far from the guilt take punishment of sin,</l>
               <l>And love to God will not restrain 'em in.</l>
               <l>This to do better, take away the Law,</l>
               <l>Give them the Reins, <unclear>force</unclear> not, but slyly draw;</l>
               <l>The Law being ta'ne away, sin is not known;</l>
               <l>And so the game is up, the day your own.</l>
               <l>Stile grossest sins, slips of infirmity,</l>
               <l>And Christian duties, false Idolatry.</l>
               <l>Tell them that Christ hath dy'd, there needs no more</l>
               <l>But bare belief, the rest may pass oth'score.</l>
               <l>That Heaven's their own by Letters-patents granted;</l>
               <l>And there's no sin can damn the Covenanted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>And I believe a small Arithmetick</l>
               <l>May count the number that to God will stick.</l>
               <l>How like you this my Son?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>Like it Sir?</l>
               <l>'Tis like thy self, adored <hi>Lucifer.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>Once more farewell, for I must to my Vault,</l>
               <l>Where I have some already for this fault.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>Nay, Father stay, by mentioning your Cell</l>
               <l>Or Vault, where you and your Companions dwell,</l>
               <l>A secret you have brought into my mind,</l>
               <l>I fain would be resolv'd in: be so kind</l>
               <l>To tell how <hi>Langhorn, Coleman, Gavan, Grove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With th'rest do like our Purgatory Stove?</l>
               <l>Do they not cry that they were all betray'd,</l>
               <l>And curse the Feast too, now the Reck'nings paid?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>Son, I would tell, but if it comes to light,</l>
               <l>It is enough our Vassals all to fright,</l>
               <l>To make them tack about, and leave us quite.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42337:4"/>
And save their Souls by a full confession,</l>
               <l>Which these have lost by damn'd equivication.</l>
               <l>Hark then, my Darling Son, put close thine ear,</l>
               <l>For I must only whisper it, for fear</l>
               <l>Some Heretick should chance to over-hear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>I listen, Father, with my greatest care.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>Such is their carriage Son (the truth to tell)</l>
               <l>They make thy Purgatory a meer Hell.</l>
               <l>They're so inrag'd to see themselves defeated,</l>
               <l>And flaming-mad to think how they are cheated</l>
               <l>Of soul and body both, they vex me more</l>
               <l>Than half the damned that I had before.</l>
               <l>Hark, methinks I hear them! hark—</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Coleman, Langhorn, Gavan,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>O horrid folly! where were our wits, our faith,</l>
               <l>To credit him, who lies what e're he faith!</l>
               <l>Ah! Popish zeal, which we before thought right,</l>
               <l>Proves now the Devil turn'd to an Angel bright.</l>
               <l>O had we but one hours reprieve from Hell,</l>
               <l>To fetch him there, that taught us to Rebel;</l>
               <l>With Father Pope, and all his smooth-tongu'd tools,</l>
               <l>Who made us bloody Traytors, Knaves and Fools;</l>
               <l>Whose curs'd Indulgence, Absolutions, Bull,</l>
               <l>Do silly Souls thus into mischief gull.</l>
               <l>Let's break our Chains and fly into the World,</l>
               <l>And pull down him, that hath us hither hurl'd;</l>
               <l>Lay ope the Plot, the people undeceive,</l>
               <l>That never man may Papist more believe.</l>
               <l>Wee'l tell the King what danger he is in,</l>
               <l>Although they swear, and swear, and swear again,</l>
               <l>Wee'l tell the Duke too, whither he is going</l>
               <l>To his eternal ruine and undoing.</l>
               <l>We will inform each Protestant we meet,</l>
               <l>Of every disguis'd Priest that walks the Street.</l>
               <l>There's not a Romish Factor in the Nation,</l>
               <l>But we'l disclose him fully, and his station:</l>
               <l>Bring them to <hi>Tyburn,</hi> and fill <hi>Charon</hi>'s Boats,</l>
               <l>Fuller than <hi>Bedlow</hi> hath, or Dr. <hi>Oates.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:42337:5"/>
Thus with one mouth your Holiness they Curse,</l>
               <l>Threaten those things, yea, and Ten thousand worse,</l>
               <l>Could they get out.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>And will you let them go,</l>
               <l>To ruine all our fair designs?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D.</speaker>
               <l>No, no,</l>
               <l>Never fear that, my Son, do thou but hast</l>
               <l>All the rest thither, and I'le keep them fast,</l>
               <l>Till thou thy self come to them at the last.</l>
               <l>Where Popes, and Jesuits, and all the crew,</l>
               <l>Which greatly hath enlarged been by you,</l>
               <l>Together shall lye down in infamy,</l>
               <l>Torment and shame, to all Eternity.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42337:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
