<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The royal oake with other various and delightfull scenes presented on the water and the land / by John Tatham.</title>
            <author>Tatham, John, fl. 1632-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-11">2003-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T232</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10302</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13558565</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13558565</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100277</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A63271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100277)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 803:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The royal oake with other various and delightfull scenes presented on the water and the land / by John Tatham.</title>
                  <author>Tatham, John, fl. 1632-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S.G. and R.B.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Celebrated in honour of the deservedly honoured Sir Richard Brown, Bar., Lord Mayor of the city of London, the 29th day of October in the 12th year of His Majesties most happy, happy, reign, An. Dom. 1660, and performed at the costs and charges of the Right Worshipfull Company of Merchant-Taylors, being twice as many pageants and speeches as have been formerly showen."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2003-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100277:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100277:1"/>
            <p>THE ROYAL
OAKE
WITH
Other various and delightfull Scenes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented
on the Water and the Land,
Celebrated in Honour of the deservedly Honoured
Sir RICHARD BROWN Bar. Lord Mayor
OF THE CITY OF
LONDON
The <hi>29th.</hi> day of <hi>October</hi> in the <hi>12th.</hi> Year of his <hi>Majesties</hi> most
happy, happy, Reign, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1660. And performed
at the Costs and Charges of the Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull
Company of
Merchant-Taylors,
Being twice as many Pageants and Speeches as have been
formerly showen,
By JOHN TATHAM.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed by <hi>S. G.</hi> for <hi>R. B.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100277:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100277:2"/>
            <head>TO THE
RIGHT HONOURABLE
Sir RICHARD BROVVN
Knight and Barronet, Lord
MAYOR of the City of
LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is said by the Philosopher, that he merits more
Honour, who can maintain a City in Peace,
then he that defendeth it in Warr, which is
rather fear'd then belov'd, And <hi>Plutarch</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports
that <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> (though a Mighty Vaunter) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest,
that <hi>Cyneas</hi> had won more Citties by his
Wisdome, then he had Conquered with his Sword.
<hi>Corona Civica,</hi> and <hi>Corona Ovalis,</hi> the one of
Oake, the other of Mirtle, were ever held more law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable
by the <hi>Romans</hi> than their <hi>Corona Aurea,</hi>
the Golden Crown, otherwise <hi>Corona Triumphalis</hi>
when the Chariot Wheeles swet Blood; When a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:100277:3"/>
is to be punisht with Warr, Sword, and Flame, any
hair-braind Phaeton will serve the turn, but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
it in Peace and Vnion, requires the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of a solid and wise Magistrate. My Lord, it is
your happiness in this days Triumph to come with
<hi>Corona Civica,</hi> the Cities Love, and (I may
say, and flatter not) the soberer and better part of the
Nations, The Company of <hi>Merchant-Taylors,</hi>
Honoueed by the Brotherhood of so many<note n="*" place="margin">Edw. <hi>the</hi> 3. Rich. <hi>the</hi> 2d <hi>and Queen</hi> Ann <hi>his wife</hi> Hen. <hi>the</hi> 4th. Hen. <hi>the</hi> 5th. Hen. <hi>the</hi> 6.. Edw. <hi>the</hi> 4. Rich. <hi>the</hi> 3d. Hen. <hi>the</hi> 7. 22 Princes and Dukes. 2 Dutchesses 1 Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop. 3 Embassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors. 42. Earls. 5. Countesses 1. Viscount 73. Barons and Lords.</note> Kings and
Princes, receive no small Ioy that you were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
to become a Member thereof; witness the readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
of the <hi>Court</hi> of assistants, to promote the honour
of the Day, and in particular Mr. <hi>Mawrice Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things,</hi>
Mr. <hi>Thomas Nevil,</hi> and <hi>Mr. John Smart,</hi>
who took upon them the care of ordering, and mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
the whole business. <hi>My Lord,</hi> vouchsafe the
acceptance of this Dedication as the early tender of
my serviceable affection who am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord</salute>
               <signed>Your Honours
<hi>Devoted Servant</hi>
IOHN TATHAM</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100277:3"/>
            <head>TO THE
WORTHILY HONOURED
THE COMPANY
OF
MERCHANT-TAYLORS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough I may appear to you a stranger,
your Goodness hath not been so to me; It
is not long since I received a rellish thereof.
<hi>Wines</hi> are tryed at the first peircing, not by quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity,
but taste, and by a little We may conclude
the rest. My Ambition is satisfied, in that this
Year I have had the happiness to serve you; if
my endeavours fall short of your expectation, I
shall blush that my Abilities are not answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to my Will, and begg your Pardon assuring
you, that I have done asmuch as the short allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
of my time would permit: but if in the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey
thereof any thing meet with your liking, it
will be honour enough to him who is thereby
Licensed to subscribe himselfe:</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>The Humblest of your Servants
<hi>IOHN TATHAM,</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:100277:4"/>
            <head>TO THE
READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Know thou dost expect something to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,
this day more then hath been in
ordinary Triumphs heretofore; in regard it is
Celebrated in Honour of a Person of that super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative
loyalty, and Integrity, as the present Lord
Mayor, Not to deceive thy Curiosity herein,
let thine own eyes satisfie thee, and to that end,
repair to the Water, where the first Sceane will
be presented against <hi>White-Hall,</hi> consisting of a
Rock and a Ship floating, Rigg'd, and Man'd.
On the Rock is placed several Figures: <hi>Oceanus,</hi>
the Father of Rivers directs his Speech to the
Lord Mayor, and nere double the number of
Pageants, that formerly were, are seen on the
<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and I shall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> detein thee no longer, but referr
thee to the shew it self, or to the manner there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
set down in the Book</p>
            <trailer>Farewell,</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100277:4"/>
            <head>THE
Royall Oake:
With other various and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull
Scaens presented on the Water and
the Land, and Celebrated in the Honour
of the deservedly Honoured Sir
Richard Brown, Baronet;
Lord Mayor of the City of LONDON, the 29.
October in the 12. year of his Majesties most hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
Reigne, Anno Domi 1660.</head>
            <head type="sub">And performed at the Costs and Charges of the
Right Worshipfull the Company of Merchant
Taylors.</head>
            <head>The Mornings Businesse.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>The whole Body being met at Merchant Taylors
hall, that is to say:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>FIrst, the Master and Wardens in their
Gowns faced, with Foyns and Hoods,
each of them having a Page attending,
habited with blew Cassocks, whire-stockings
and flat Caps; each Page bearing a Target
with their Arms in one hand and a Trunchion
in the other.</p>
            <p>2. The Assistants in their Gowns and Hoods.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100277:5"/>
3. The Livery in their Gowns and Hoods.</p>
            <p>4. The Foyns Batchellors in Gowns and
Hoods.</p>
            <p>5. The Budge Batchellors in Gowns and
Scarlet Hoods.</p>
            <p>6. Forty eight Gentlemen Ushers in Plush
Coats, white Staves and Gold Chains.</p>
            <p>7. Eight other Gentlemen carrying Banners
in Plush Coats, and Skye coloured Scarffs about
their Shoulders.</p>
            <p>8. Three Gentlemen more in Buff Coats,
and Sky coloured Scarffs about their middles.</p>
            <p>9. The Foot Martiall with a like coloured
Scarff about his Shoulder with six Attendants,
and each of them habited in a white Fustian
Dublet, black Breeches, blew stockings, a white
Hat, and blew Hatband, and every one of them
a Trunchian in his hand.</p>
            <p>10. The Serjeant, Trumpeter, with a skye
coloured Scarff about his Shoulders, and eight
other of his Majesties Trumpeters, together
with his Majesties Kettle Drums.</p>
            <p>11. His Majesties Drum Major with a like
coloured Scarff about his Waste, with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties
others Drums.</p>
            <p>12. Twenty other Trumpeters divided and
disposed of into eight Pageants.</p>
            <p>13. Seven other Drums (whereof <hi>Iohn Bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi>
Drum Major to the City is chief) habited
either in Buff coats or Buff coloured Dublets,
and blew Scarffs about their wastes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100277:5"/>
14. <hi>Francis Burgesse</hi> Master of Defence with
his twelve Attendants.</p>
            <p>15. One hundred and twenty poore aged
persons Free-men of the Company in blew
Gowns with red Sleeves, and red Caps, each of
them having a Javelin in one hand, and an Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cochin
in the other; Six other poore people
also Free men of the said Company in blew
Jackets and red Caps appointed to carry the
Silk-works, and twenty foure poore men in
disguises, commonly called Green men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being so met and habited, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid,
about eight a clock, the Foot Marshall
Ranks them out by two and two<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>FIrst, the Pentioners in blew Gowns, in the
head of them is placed three Drums, one
Fife, and the Ensigne whereon the Crest of
the Company is painted.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The severall Banners and Strea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers
carried by the poore men in blew Coats;
in the Front of them four Drums and one Fife.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Budge Batchellors, in the front
of them eight Gentlemen Ushers, the other
two Colours and six Trumpets.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Foyns Batchellors, in the
Front of whom is placed ten Gentlemen U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shers,
and two other Gentlemen, the one car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying
the Companies, the other the Cities Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
and six other Trumpets in the head of
them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100277:6"/>
Fifthly, The Livery, in the front of them,
twelve Gentlemen Ushers, and two other of
the said Gentlement, each of them carrying
two Banners, and foure of his Majesties Drums
with one Fife.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The Assistants, in the front of
whom is placed ten Gentlemen Ushers, two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of the said Gentlemen, one carrying the
Lord Mayor, the other the Cities Banner, and
eight other of the best Trumpets.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, The Master and his four War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,
each of them having a Page attending,
habited as aforesaid, carrying his Coat of Arms
in the Escohin; likewise ten other of the said
Gentlemen Ushers, and two other of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
specified Gentlemen, the one carrying his
Majesties, the other the Duke of <hi>Yorkes</hi> Banner,
his Majesties Serjeant Trumpeter, and eight
other Trumpets, in the front of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being thus Rankt out, the Foot Marshall placeth
himself in the head of the Pentioners, and leads
the way towards his Lordships house, after them
the Banners and Streamers, the Master, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens
and Assistants and Livery following next
them; after them the Wardens of the Yeoman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry,
the Foyns and Budge Batchellors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THe Master and Wardens being come to
his Lordships house, or meeting him by
the way, the Gentlemen Ushers, Colours,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100277:6"/>
Trumpets, Drums and Fifes, remove their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
and now place themselves in the head of
the Juniors; whereas they were placed in the
head of the Seniors before, and so lead on
the accustomed way towards Three Crain
Wharff, beginning with the Pentioners and
Silk-works, and the Budge and Foyns Batchel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors,
the Livery, Assistants, and the Master and
Wardens march next the Lord Mayors Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants.</p>
            <p>The Pentioners and Silkworks being come
to Colledge-hill, do open to the right and left,
making a lane through which the Drums, Fifes
Trumpets, Colours, Gentlemen Ushers, and
Rich Batchellors do passe to the place assigned
to refresh themselves; and the Livery Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,
Master and Wardens and their Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
Ushers do passe to their Barges laid at the
Stairs at the East end of three Crain Wharff.</p>
            <p>The Lord Mayor, Aldermen and their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants
passe into their Barge, laid at the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed
place.</p>
            <p>Their Barges and all other the Companies,
adorned with Streamers and Banners, and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
with Hoe-boyes, Cornets, Drums and
Trumpets; being on the water move towards
<hi>Westminster,</hi> and by the way his Lordship is
saluted with twenty pieces of Ordnance, as
peals of entertainment and joy; Against
<hi>White-hall</hi> appears a large Stage or Fabrick at
the one end whereof is a Ship, floating, rigg'd
and man'd, at the other end a Rock with vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Figures; one representing <hi>Oceanus,</hi> who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100277:7"/>
is said to be God of Seas, and the Father of the
Rivers; He was son to <hi>Coelum</hi> and <hi>Vesta; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelous</hi>
was his son begat of <hi>Thetis;</hi> and the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens</hi>
are said to be the daughters of <hi>Achelous;</hi>
and <hi>Calliope</hi> to shew his Majesty, he walks or
treads upon his Watery Regiment, severall
Fishes are discovered to play at his Feet, and
<hi>Tryton's</hi> sporting themselves; four Virgins
cloathed in white loose garments, and their
Brows circled with Sage, representing the
Nymphs that frequent Rivers.</p>
            <p>Upon his Lordships approach <hi>Oceanus</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresseth
himself in these words.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Oceanus Speech.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I Oceanus</hi> of old <hi>Coelums</hi> race,</l>
               <l>That like a Ring doth Circle and Embrace</l>
               <l>The spacious Vniverse, God of the Main,</l>
               <l>And unto Rivers Lord and Soveraign</l>
               <l>Am come to grace my Daughter, Silver <hi>Thames,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So much admir'd and lov'd by<note n="a" place="margin">Or Cambden<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Causabon</hi> speaks King <hi>James</hi> to be a great lover of this River.</note> Royall <hi>James:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whose peaceful reign did make her murmures sweet</l>
               <l>Not harsh, her Tyde run with harmonious feet:</l>
               <l>'Tis Peace that Barbs the Billows, scumbs the foam,</l>
               <l>Inviteth Trade abroad, and brings it home:</l>
               <l>My Lord, you are a Royall Substitute,</l>
               <l>Your clear Election, is without dispute;</l>
               <l>Imploy your Interest, Trade may now encrease,</l>
               <l>And be envol'd within the Arm of Peace.</l>
               <l>Then shall my Grand-Girles<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Syrens Brittain</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compassed on the East by the <hi>German</hi> Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Sea, on the West the Irish, on the North the <hi>Scotish,</hi> &amp; on the South by a narrow Sea, divided from <hi>Gallia Belgica</hi>
                  </note> not betray, but sing,</l>
               <l>And drink Carouses to great <hi>Britains</hi> King.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The Speech ended, his Lordship and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen
and Companies make for <hi>Westminster,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100277:7"/>
his Lordship being landed, and the accustomed
Ceremonies in the several Courts performed,
they return to <hi>Baynards</hi> Castle, in the way his
Lordship receives another Peal of Ordnance,
as a token of joy; and at <hi>Baynards</hi> Castle his
Lordship and Attendants are entertain'd by the
first Gentlemen Budge and Foyn Batchellors,
their several Attendants; and being in like Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
as they marched from his Lordships house,
the whole body move up <hi>Pauls Wharff</hi> hill to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the East end of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> in the Front of
which, the Gentlemen of the Artillary march
to shew their affection and loyalty, who are led
by Sir <hi>Iohn Robinson,</hi> the President of the said
Fraternity, and Lievtenant of the Tower, in his
Scarlet Gown and Sword: After whom the
Pentioners and his Lordships Company march
in the same manner and equipage as before. His
Lordship being come to the East end of <hi>Pauls,</hi>
as aforesaid, is entertained by a Pageant or
Scean representing a Pavillion or Tent Royal,
flankt with two Camels, the supporters of the
Companies Arms; on the back of each Camel a
figure clothed in white, a Banner in his hand,
and on the 2. stages 9. figures are placed, 5. of
them in livery gowns, representing the Mr. and
Wardens of the Company, and 4. representing
Persons of honour that have been free of the
Company: under the Pavillion sits the figures
of 8. Kings that have been free of the Company.
In the front whereof sits <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. holding in his
hand their first Charter or Patent of Merchant
Taylors; and on a lower seat is placed a grave
Person representing a Souldier &amp; Senator, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100277:8"/>
his Gown a white Armour, holding in the
one hand a Gantlet, the property of a Souldier
in the other a statute Book as a Senator and
maintainer of laws: All parts of this Scaen is
beautified and agreeable with their Arms: His
Lordship drawing neer, the person under the
Pavillion entertains him in these words.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Senators Speech.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <l>I As a Senator, and Souldier doe</l>
               <l>(Relating to your Triumphs) wait on you,</l>
               <l>You being both; A double Lawrell now</l>
               <l>Beset with Stars wreaths your deserving brow;</l>
               <l>Who but a Senator can Souldier be?</l>
               <l>'Tis Valour to be read in Policy:</l>
               <l>For when the Martialist is at a stand,</l>
               <l>The wary Statesman takes him by the hand,</l>
               <l>And leads him through the way did dangerous seem</l>
               <l>" <hi>Nestor</hi> was more then <hi>Ajax</hi> in esteem;</l>
               <l>" Strength without Wisdom, madly runing on,</l>
               <l>" Receives its own Precipitation.</l>
               <l>The Oracle being askt why <hi>Iupiter</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was the chief God, <hi>Mars</hi> being the Souldier,</l>
               <l>Repli'd, he has what to 'ther wants, he's wise;</l>
               <l>Can when he please with Thunder clear the skies,</l>
               <l>Implying that a Governour should be</l>
               <l>Endow'd with Courage and Philosophy,</l>
               <l>Reasons best ward to Argue and dispute;</l>
               <l>A watchfull eye, and a heart resolute:</l>
               <l>Great merrits require great rewards, nor is</l>
               <l>There one more happy then your self in this;</l>
               <l>You have oblig'd your King &amp; Countries love,</l>
               <l>Your receiv'd honours will not barren prove,</l>
               <l>But multiply, since that the Government</l>
               <l>Of our three States rest in one Continent:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100277:8"/>
For where all Rule, no Rule at all can be</l>
               <l>Where dwels Confe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sion but in Anarchy?<note place="margin">K. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. discended l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lly of the <hi>Brittains by Gadwallo,</hi> of the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> by Fargus of the Picks of the daughter of Hung<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> by the sister of Edger of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Danes by the da<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ghter of <hi>K Christian.</hi> and that of the <hi>Normans</hi> by the death of <hi>Henry</hi> th. 20. Edw. 4th. 1480,</note>
               </l>
               <l>Nor can society possibly Twist,</l>
               <l>When every one will be even what he list,</l>
               <l>When Godlike-Monarchy, does keep in Aw,</l>
               <l>Licentious freedome, by a penal Law;</l>
               <l>Derivitive from Heaven; he that did spring,</l>
               <l>From mighty Ancestors, is now your Kign,</l>
               <l>By right succession As the hands of Heaven,</l>
               <l>We bagg'd him, and he was as freely given;</l>
               <l>To rescue us from Wolves, God under whom,</l>
               <l>He is <hi>Vice-Gerent,</hi> safely sent him home,</l>
               <l>To rule his People, that we may express,</l>
               <l>By former Griefs, our new-found Happiness;</l>
               <l>Nor ought we to omit th' Antiquity,</l>
               <l>Of th' Honour'd Company, of which y' are free,<note place="margin">Hen <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th. 1501. and the 17th. year of his Reign. Sir Iohn <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cival.</hi> Sir Steph. Ien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Sir Hen. Hober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne.</note>
               </l>
               <l>By a new choice; <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth first made,</l>
               <l>Them Lynnen Armourers, a select Trade,</l>
               <l>After incorporated by the Name,</l>
               <l>Of Merchant Taylors, by that Prince of Fame.</l>
               <l>and several Kings and Princes have thought good</l>
               <l>To be admitted in their Brother-hood,</l>
               <l>Fiveteen Lord Mayor from the Royal stem,<note place="margin">Sir Tho. White. Sir Tho. Offley Sir Wil. Harper. Sir Tho Roe. Sir Robert Lee. Sir Leo. Holly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Have received Knightwood, you the last otf hem;</l>
               <l>Yet in as great Grace, with your Soveraign,</l>
               <l>Who, cannot of your Loyalty Complain.</l>
               <l>For through the thickest of your troubles you,</l>
               <l>Have shew'd your sellfe to him a Subject true</l>
               <l>And Providence that duty to requite,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sir</hi> Wil. Craven <hi>Sir</hi> Iohn Swy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merton. <hi>Sir</hi> Iohn Gore <hi>Sir</hi> Rob. Ducy <hi>Sir</hi> Abra. Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noldson,</note>
               </l>
               <l>Hath now at last restor'd you to your right:</l>
               <l>For which the Company, and City may,</l>
               <l>Give hearty thankes for this so happy day.<note place="margin">Sir Ric Brown.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100277:9"/>
The speech ended the Sceanes quitts the place
and is conveyed into Cheapside, and make a halt
about the Cross till further Order.</p>
            <p>His Lordship drawing near the Nagg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-head Tavern
is received by another sceane, seated like a wood in
the midst whereof is a formal building like a house, on
the stage or vacant part whereof several persons in the
habit of Wood-men and Wood-Nymphs disport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,
dancing about the <hi>Royal Oake,</hi> never out of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vpon the Companies approach, one of the Woodmen calls to
the rest of his Companions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mass, Gotheard, Mass, Logred, zen, yee, zen, ye, what a
warren a gay voke are yonden, Zibb, Tibb, Trot, Zquot
Wab, Win, Nab, Gin, what done o mean wullo bee zen
the vine zight, ho ho, what pestilent gay vellow's yon
a <hi>Woodman</hi> tis the Lord Mayor.</p>
            <p>Che vears en not vor all that cham resolv'd to zay
zomething tollen</p>
            <lg>
               <head>A speech to the Lord Mayor in a Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick
Dyalect.</head>
               <l>A Meezle take thee, Neame cham glad to zee thee</l>
               <l>Give me thyn hond, how don mine Aunt I prithe</l>
               <l>Had Iche but knowno this zame gaudy Noone,</l>
               <l>Chad don'd on viner Clothes and viner Shoone.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100277:9"/>
Thone we but Rusticks are, and woods done keep,</l>
               <l>Ich know there is vine woole elongs to sheep,</l>
               <l>And zome there are now were the vinest thread</l>
               <l>In zimple Russet ha bin zheltered,</l>
               <l>Wee Woodmen ha been honest Chil zay that</l>
               <l>And a vart vort, cham sure that Iche know what</l>
               <l>The sturdy Oak ha bin a vrend to zome</l>
               <l>It wud no bow, no more o that but Mum</l>
               <l>Iche hope your Lordship takes all in good part</l>
               <l>Cham sure Ich love a Woodman wi mine heart,</l>
               <l>" In down right English Sir y'are welcome to</l>
               <l>" that place of Honour hath been long your due.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The Speech ended Mr. Dyamond and others tumble
and after the Sumerset is perform'd the Rusticks and
the Nymphs make a great shout, at which noise (as
from the Wood) <hi>Silvanus</hi> the Rural God, attyred like a
Huntsman, about his wast a girdle of leaves, his Habit
Russet, on his Brest a starr to distinguish him, and in
his hand a Bugle horn, Accosts the Lord Mayor in these
words.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Sylvanus Speech.</head>
               <l>No more of noise as you respect our Care<note place="margin">At which they all bow. To the Lord Mayor. Between Staff. and Salo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Forsake your Natures, and be still as Ayr.</l>
               <l>Er'e <hi>Time</hi> had laid his Iron Coat aside</l>
               <l>And <hi>Peace</hi> was rather ravisht then a Bride,</l>
               <l>Whil'st that the subtle Eye of Tyranny</l>
               <l>Greedily hunted after Majesty,</l>
               <l>The Close Trunck of the Oak did entertain</l>
               <l>And so secur'd your royal Soveraign,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100277:10"/>
Twice she receiv'd him in her happy womb</l>
               <l>At his conveying hence and coming home</l>
               <l>As though a greater knot had been t'unty</l>
               <l>Then e're was twisted in the Prophesy.</l>
               <l>The pendant leaves his head enshadow'd round</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> only to conceale but to be Crown'd,</l>
               <l>The Barke that brought him, flew<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as though it meant</l>
               <l>To steal upon us without <hi>Times</hi> consent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Thus does the Oak draw a fresh breath from Fame</l>
               <l>By the instinctive vertue of his Name;</l>
               <l>And consecrated ought to be to <hi>Iove</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Producing both th' effects of Peace and Love.</l>
               <l>The Rusticks shall be civiliz'd and now</l>
               <l>Imbrace what heretofore they'd not allow,</l>
               <l>About the Royal Oak the Nymphs shall sing</l>
               <l>And dance a measure to their Lord the King,</l>
               <l>The Woodmen so refus'd, shall on each Tree</l>
               <l>Inscription make of their quit slavery,</l>
               <l>And for a Girdle in a Garter sense</l>
               <l>'Bout th' Oake write <hi>Hony soit qui maly Pence.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Which done his Lordship passeth towards the East
end of Cheapside, where he is entertained by another
sceane, being a Charriot drawn by a Lyon and a Lamb,
in the Chario is placed three figures, PEACE TRUTH
&amp; PLENTY the Chariot is driven by Time who salutes
his Lordship in these words:</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100277:10"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Times Speech.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <l>
                  <hi>TIME</hi> is the Register of all Mens Acts</l>
               <l>Or good, or bad, their vertue and their facts.</l>
               <l>Although by violence he hath bin made</l>
               <l>a Property unto the Traytors Trade;</l>
               <l>Yet Time (that every secret brings to light)</l>
               <l>At last (you see) their Treacheries requites,</l>
               <l>Payes them in their own Coyn, the bloody stamp,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath turn'd Surgeon, cur'd them of the Cramp.</l>
               <l>" Treason may flourish for a little space,</l>
               <l>" but Time at length writes Villane in its face.</l>
               <l>Whil'st <hi>Iulius Caesars</hi> death Revengless past</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> nere was free from sword Fire Plague and Wast</l>
               <l>Till Time reveal'd the Murderers and then</l>
               <l>their better Genius did return agen,</l>
               <l>And clos'd up <hi>Ianus</hi> Temple. Though Time hath</l>
               <l>bin curst by those had neither wit nor faith,</l>
               <l>But rashly did conclude hee'd never mend</l>
               <l>And therefore in despair did wish his End.</l>
               <l>Yet he for every sore and malady</l>
               <l>hath brought you home a <hi>Soveraign</hi> remedy,</l>
               <l>Occasion is his foretop, which had some</l>
               <l>long since ta'ne hold of, bad daies had not come,</l>
               <l>Twas not Times fault, but theirs that let him go,</l>
               <l>Hee's swift of foot, their Courage was but slow,</l>
               <l>You have been wise in this (Sir) to your praise,</l>
               <l>Oretak'n Time, renew'd the Alchion daies,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100277:11"/>
With such Alacrity, that poreing on</l>
               <l>with serious eye, my Enchyridion</l>
               <l>That monstrous Murder that outfac'd the Sun</l>
               <l>Appears to me as yesterday but done,</l>
               <l>So home hath Justice follow'd them, their heels</l>
               <l>are now tript up, each his own horror feels.</l>
               <l>This was Times worke, though wisdome was the scout</l>
               <l>without Time nothing could be brought a bout</l>
               <l>Peace is restor'd; Truth doth in Triumph ride,</l>
               <l>(not long since scorn'd, forsaken, and deny'd.)</l>
               <l>Plenty their hand-maid follows to maintain</l>
               <l>the Majesty of the Heroick Train</l>
               <l>It is a Maxime (Traytors bitter Cupp)</l>
               <l>" warrs maketh Theives, but Peace doth hang them up:</l>
               <l>Since Time has done such Cures by Providence,</l>
               <l>let him not be abus'd under pretence</l>
               <l>Of this, or that, seeds of Phanatick braines;</l>
               <l>But while you Govern (Sir) hold in the Reynes;</l>
               <l>And while the glorious starr-bestudy'd skye</l>
               <l>retains a light your Fame shall never dy.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The speech ended, his Lordship and the whole At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance
pass down the old <hi>Iury,</hi> through Catt-eaten
street and <hi>Ladd</hi> Lane, <hi>Mayden</hi>-Lane, from which place
to his Lordships house a Gallery is a made by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
of the Merchant-Taylors, on the North and on the
South by the Gentlemen of the Artillery and their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants,
where another sceane a Rock is placed on the
top whereof is seated a figure representing Peace
and upon his Lordships entring into his house, Peace
salutes him from the top of the Rock.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100277:11"/>
               <head>PEACES SPEECH</head>
               <l>AFter so many various Sceans of strife</l>
               <l>Horror and Mischief acted to the Life,</l>
               <l>By those that seem'd to owne th shapes of men,</l>
               <l>But Monsters rather were of <hi>Caucus</hi> Denn,</l>
               <l>Whole sulphurous Nostrells breath'd into stine Jarrs,</l>
               <l>Sword, Fire, and Famine, the effect of Warrs,</l>
               <l>Peace (that their hate and fury did exile)</l>
               <l>Is once again return'd unto this Isle,</l>
               <l>And with her brought Truth to Illuminate,</l>
               <l>Your hearts to nourish Love, and banish Hate.</l>
               <l>Truth is the Center wherein all things meet,</l>
               <l>The Chard by which Wisdome directs her feet,</l>
               <l>The ground of science; scale to Charity,</l>
               <l>The unmov'd Rock; Tip of Eternity.</l>
               <l>While Peace and Truth do flourish in the Land.</l>
               <l>Plenty shall wait on it with a full hand,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ceres</hi> shall cram your Barns, and <hi>Bacchus</hi> Crown</l>
               <l>Your Boles, no more of Penury be known,</l>
               <l>Trade long since dead reviv'd, shall be again</l>
               <l>By th' Vertual Influence of your Soveraign,</l>
               <l>Whose gracious Beams, like to the Sun doth shine,</l>
               <l>Upon his Subjects by a power divine,</l>
               <l>Whose Immence, Majesty, and Glory shall</l>
               <l>Outlast Times Age, and the Worlds Funerall.</l>
               <l>Blest be the happy minute of his birth</l>
               <l>That elevates our Joys above the Earth.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Flora</hi> the Queen of May shall honoured be</l>
               <l>By all the sons of <hi>Lyrick</hi> Poesy,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100277:12"/>
And you my Lord, whose Prudent care hath bin</l>
               <l>Imploy'd in the great work to bring him in,</l>
               <l>Keep Faction down, suppress Seditions seed,</l>
               <l>The bag being broke did the Imposthume breed,</l>
               <l>Let it not gather to a head again,</l>
               <l>Infectious matter dwells in a bad brain:</l>
               <l>So shall your years and happiness encrease,</l>
               <l>Live in your Countries, love and dye in Peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The Speech being ended the Companies hasten to
their Hall, the Gentlemen of the Artillery take leave
by their severall Vollies.</p>
            <p>In the undertaking of this days Triumph were imploy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed,
(by a person of approved Judgment, who design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and modelled, the several Fabricks, and Structures
thereof) Capt. <hi>Andrew Dakers</hi> Paynter, Mr. <hi>William
Lightfoot,</hi> Paynter, Mr. <hi>Thomas Whiteing</hi> Joyner, Mr. <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard
Cleere,</hi> Carver, all of them being the Cities Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,
and deserve in their several qualities, ample
Commendations.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100277:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
