<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A True description of a treacherous plot intended against this kingdome by the Lord Digby and his asistants at Sherborne in the county of Dorset with the exact number of armes, muskets, pikes and barrels of gunpowder, to the number of two hundred by him hid and contrived in an old cellar belonging to the Lord George his father : with the manner how and by what accident it came to bee descried : as also how the steward of his house being examined and found faultring in his speech was committed to prison where hee yet remaineth.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63506</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9136</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12532003</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12532003</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62779</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A63506)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62779)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 249:E131, no 34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A True description of a treacherous plot intended against this kingdome by the Lord Digby and his asistants at Sherborne in the county of Dorset with the exact number of armes, muskets, pikes and barrels of gunpowder, to the number of two hundred by him hid and contrived in an old cellar belonging to the Lord George his father : with the manner how and by what accident it came to bee descried : as also how the steward of his house being examined and found faultring in his speech was committed to prison where hee yet remaineth.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Hammond,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bristol, George Digby, --  Earl of, 1612-1677.</term>
               <term>Sherborne (Dorset) --  History.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2000-00</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-07</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62779:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A true description Of a treacherous plot INTENDED against this Kingdome,</p>
            <p>By the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> and his assistants, at <hi>Sherborne</hi> in the County of DORSET:</p>
            <p>With the exact number of Armes, Muskets, Pikes and Barrels of Gunpowder, to the number of two hundred, by him hid and contrived in an old Cellar belonging to the Lord <hi>George</hi> his Father.</p>
            <p>With the manner how and by what accident it came to bee descried.</p>
            <p>As also how the Steward of his House being exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and found faultring in his speech, was committed to prison, where hee yet remaineth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Hammond.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="report">
            <pb facs="tcp:62779:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62779:2"/>
            <head>A true description of a treacherous plot intended against this Kingdome.</head>
            <p>THe wonderfull and quotidiall mercies of God towards this Kingdome, hath often and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally appeared unto us by his so many and never to be enough admired deliverances from both private and forraigne enemies. I need not nominate any particular, in respect there hath been many so late, and others so exemplary, as the memory thereof can by no meanes be extinct or blotted out. But this dire and yet unknowne example which I am about to treat on, which as it is unparalel'd, in respect of privacie; and the more contaminous in respect of the party and author, being formerly a Parliament ment<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an. And as it was dismall, wee the more bound in duty to praise God for his mercy in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing the same unto us. It is thus: The Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> a man whose vote hath formerly beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted iudicious, and for the benefit (or at least<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise so seeming) unto both King and State, whose sedulity, vigilancie, &amp; superior authority in State affaires, hath been much noted, whose continuall labours and indulgent care for the Parliament, hath hidden it selfe under the cloake or shadow of loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and duty towards the State, whose principal endeavours, though now thought pernitious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely
<pb facs="tcp:62779:3"/>
nefarious, have carried with them a colour or elimination of the truth, prove now as clear con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary as the Poets stile, <hi>Qui color albus erat, nunc est contrarius albo.</hi> For no sooner had he opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity offered him, wherein or whereby to vent his sp<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eniall and malicious devices against us, no soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner perceiving a combustion stirring, but like an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vective and opprobrious member, and enemy to the State, but he imploye his industrious, nay most apprehensive and sedulous labours to co-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate our destruction by ioyning his corroberature and strengthening of the enemy with his auxiliary helpes, and not onely so, but hee himselfe in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son advancing, and is not ashamed to appropriate to himselfe the ignominions title of <hi>D<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>x omnium malorum,</hi> the leader, inducer and producer of our malevolent and inauspitious evils, through the profundity and inexorab<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enesse of his deepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented treachery.</p>
            <p>No sooner could a <hi>Lunsford,</hi> or a deviating re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell embrace an op<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtunity of evill, but hee prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, nay chalenges to himselfe the primitive and most specular place of ignominy, to bee a leader and producer of their former ill-intended mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs with this encouragment to his followers, Go you before, and I'le follow; begin you and I will end: or as the Poet <hi>Terence</hi> hath it, <hi>I p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, sequar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ensuing story will testifie his reality and entire affection unto us, to bee but faigned, which you sha<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l note in this sequell: for not onely work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pernitiously here, but studying by all meares possible, to further and provide for machination at
<pb facs="tcp:62779:3"/>
home, to assist his confederates if occasion in that case required, having caused to bee laid up in a deepe Cellar, divers Barrels of Gunpowder, to the number of two hundred, being over-layd and covered with abundance of old Caskes, Faggots, and other lumber; and amongst the rest, some Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins of wine drawne out, others full, to the intent the powder Barrels might be taken for the like. In another place adioyning, being accounted a Store-house for wooll, and such like things, were found three hundred Mu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kets, ready fixt and expedient for service; as also fifteen hundred Arme<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, with Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stols, Carbines, and Harquebusse<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, having nothing in them wanting to supply so many able men upon service. Pikes there were, and Lance likewise, but the number being of no validity, and therefore not expressed. What may bee intended by all this Amunition, and marshall provision, cannot of a certainly bee expressed, although that the Steward or Keeper thereof being taken and very strictly examined by divers iudicious and severe Iustices of Peace, yet could they get nothing out of him but this, That they were his Masters, things of consequence, and committed to his charge: and what wa<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the use or intent concerning them, if they de<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ired to know, they should en<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uire of the owner and purchaser of them who was best able to give them an answer concerning the same. Being fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enquired and examined why they were hid<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en &amp; concealed, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd not admitted to pub<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lick view as well as those Armes which were allowed for his Lordships Honour and defence. Hee answered,
<pb facs="tcp:62779:4"/>
that he never demanded the question of his Master, and therefore was altogether unacquainted and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to give them an answer; but if they were so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily and earnestly desirous to know, they should have stayed untill such time as they had been produced; whenas they would bee able to speake for themselves the intent of their concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Being formerly suspected, and now almost convinced by his owne words of disloyalty, hee was forthwith committed to prison.</p>
            <p>I will now in the next place explain unto you the great and wonderfull mercie of God towards us, and his iust and exemplary punishment shewed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our enemies in the discovery of their wicked and pernitious designes and intentions, who is able to worke by weake meanes, without meanes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to meanes, as in the discourse of the ensuing words palpably appeares. There was divers little Boyes in the Towne of <hi>Sherborne,</hi> conioyned and united together in their disport<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; where (amongst their pastimes) they made Squibs, and divers Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes, with powder: one of them dwelling in the house of my Lord <hi>Digay,</hi> who supplied them with their Amunition; insomuch that many of them carried their workes home with them. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on their Parents demanding them, where they had their implements to compose them, they sayd, <hi>Iohn Pellam,</hi> naming the aforesaid Lad, had enough, and knew where was a Barrell full, and more. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon having iust cause of suspition before, they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a great many wise and sage Protestants of the faid Towne privately together, and motioned the
<pb facs="tcp:62779:4"/>
matter unto them: And upon mature considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on caused the Boy by flattery, to shew them the place where it was: And seeing many Barrels like that wherein the powder was inclosed, opened one other, and found it full. So upon diligent search made, being authorised by divers Iustices, the plot was discovered: For which we are bound to praise and glorifie the holy Name of Almighty God, who hath beene pleased to conserve and keepe us from all dangers. To whom be glory and honour now and for ever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
