<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true, exact, and perfect relation of the famous and renowned victorie gained by the most redoubted armie of the mightie and victorious monarch Philip, of the name the fourth King of Spaine, &amp;c. the seventh of September, being upon the eve of the nativitie of our lady : against the forces of Levvis, of that name the 13 French King : then straightly beleaguering both with navall and land powers the frontier citie of Fuenteravia / written by a Gentleman that was an eyewitnesse of the same.</title>
            <author>Gentleman that was an eyewitnesse of the same.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9851</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13545709</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13545709</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100126</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A63520)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100126)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 255:E173, no 24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true, exact, and perfect relation of the famous and renowned victorie gained by the most redoubted armie of the mightie and victorious monarch Philip, of the name the fourth King of Spaine, &amp;c. the seventh of September, being upon the eve of the nativitie of our lady : against the forces of Levvis, of that name the 13 French King : then straightly beleaguering both with navall and land powers the frontier citie of Fuenteravia / written by a Gentleman that was an eyewitnesse of the same.</title>
                  <author>Gentleman that was an eyewitnesse of the same.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for Samuel Broune,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIII, --  King of France, 1601-1643.</term>
               <term>Philip --  IV, --  King of Spain, 1605-1665.</term>
               <term>Franco-Spanish War, 1635-1659.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100126:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100126:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A true, exact, and
perfect Relation of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
and renowned Victorie, gained
by the moſt redoubted Armie of the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
and victorious Monarch PHILIP, of
that name the fourth King of <hi>Spaine, &amp;c.</hi> the
ſeventh of <hi>September,</hi> being upon the Eve
of the Nativitie of our Lady: Againſt
the forces of LEVVIS, of that name the
13. French King, then ſtraightly beleague<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
both with Navall and Land
Powers the frontier Citie of
FUENTERAVIA.</p>
            <p>Written by by a Gentleman that was an eye-witneſſe
of the ſame.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Royal coat of arms or blazon.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> for <hi>Samuel Broune.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account_of_battle_preparations">
            <pb facs="tcp:100126:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100126:2"/>
            <head>A true, exact, and
perfect Relation of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
and renowned Victorie, gained
by the moſt redoubted Armie of the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
and victorious Monarch PHILIP, of
that name the fourth King of Spaine, &amp;c. the
ſeventh of September, being upon the Eve
of the Nativitie of our Lady: Againſt
the forces of LEVVIS, of that name the
13. French King, then ſtraightly beleague<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
both with Navall and Land
Powers the frontier Citie of
FUENTERAVIA.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hich Citie, by the ſaid overthrow
of the <hi>French</hi> was happily ſuccou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
and relieved: And that this
Relation may beare the greater
colour of truth, and gaine the
greater beliefe in the imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of men: it is not amiſſe (by
the way) to intimate, that it is no partiall Gazet, or
Slanderous tale or Ballad, which upon ſuch occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
are ever prompt to be taken hold of, in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100126:3"/>
wavering conceipts of the giddy multitude. But it
is the reall knowledge, and painfull, and dangerous
experience of one that was Actor in that Tragi-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy,
as he can ſhew good materialls for. But my
deſire (who am bold to terme my ſelfe the Relator of
this exployt) is not to name my ſelfe, but to warrant
the certainty of this true Pamphlet: And to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Citie of <hi>Fuenteravia,</hi> being (according
as the naturall ſcituation thereof could afford conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie
of in incamping and lying in road to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers)
beleagured both by ſea and land, and all paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages,
acceſſe, and conveyances of ſuccour or relief to
the beſieged, ſhut up and ſtrongly barred with ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie
many Trenches, Redouts, Cortadura's, Barriers,
and all ſorts of Millitarie lets, and engines to hinder
and prevent any deſignes of the feared (by them)
Spaniſh powers: So that onely excepted, the care of
the Almighty of his ſervants, there remained no
manner of hope of any earthly helpe to the beſieged.</p>
            <p>But as it is ſeene by dayly experience, that where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
manly courage, or valorous Roman reſolution is
inhabiting, that there it begins to ſhew it ſelfe moſt,
where its help is moſt requiſite and available. So now
the undaunted and couragious Spaniards, though
little in number, by reaſon of their daily loſſes, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
by the over-greedy deſire of glorie, and gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of the Fort of their adverſaries, and by their
high reſolution on the other ſide to withſtand their
enemies intent. The <hi>Alcald,</hi> or Governour of the
Towne, ſeeing to what a ſtreight they were brought,
by this hard pounding of them up by their enemies,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100126:3"/>
like a diſcreet and carefull overſeer of his taske, labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
and ſedulous Paſtor of his intruſted flock: hee
began in time (ſeeing this cloud of Warre hanging
over his head, and thereupon a great tempeſt of
Armes threatned to prevent this ſtorme therefore,
and to ſeek ſhelter afore the ſaid ſtorme for himſelfe,
and the reſt of his warre, and weather-beaten compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
being as aforeſaid daily diminiſhed, and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
on the other ſide everie day more and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing,
ſtill by new freſh and daily reliefes and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors
from their neighbour home, to their great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
and encouragement. The <hi>Alcald,</hi> as is ſaid, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
things as they ſtood, with all ſpeed aſſembled
the prime of his retinue, and told them the ſtate of
the buſineſſe as it ſtood in his conceit, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly
was conceived of by the moſt underſtanding
of them, to be as he conceived: whereupon by general
conſent of all the Commanders then there, a ſpeedy
advertiſement of all the ſeverall particularities tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
the ſtate of the Towne, the beſiegers and the
diſtreſſed, (if not out of hand relieved) beſieged, was
diſpatched to his Catholike Majeſty, which diſpatch
was ſundry and verie oftentimes confirmed, by the
comming ſtill of new advertiſements and ſolicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of preſent ſuccours both to his ſaid ſacred Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie
of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and to the <hi>Almirant</hi> of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> a man
of a moſt ancient and noble familie, eminent in the
Common-wealth by his well-deſerved office, and in
his nature and vertuous qualities, not eaſily paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd,
but ſcarcely imitable: And to conclude,
though not with the twentieth part of his goodnes;
yet in few words to comprehend much, a man that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100126:4"/>
in ſpight of envie (be it ſpoken) may deſervedly be
termed, the Mirrour of compleat Nobilitie, magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity,
and courage, and a true delineated patterne,
and effigies of all thoſe rare parts which ought to bee
comprehended in a true-hearted Noble-man, great
ſtates man, grave Councellour, and warlike director
of a Common-wealth as he was then, being high Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
of the Spaniſh Armie: who having received
theſe ſeverall advertiſements, therein plainly manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
to the world his honeſt heart, cleare conſcience,
loving nature, and ſtout reſolution, by commiſerating
like a good Patriot, the hard caſe of his afflicted coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men;
for preſently and out of hand hee called a
Councell of warre, of the beſt and moſt approved
Leaders in his armie, repreſenting unto them the
grievances and requeſt of the Governour, and his
Garriſon, commanding them, that after ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation
thereof had that night: that the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
they ſhould render him an account of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution
therin, for the beſt prevention of the enemies
deſignes, and moſt convenient meanes of ſuccouring
their dangerouſly engaged friends. But by reaſon of
the ſcarſity of experienced old ſouldiers there was a
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſed diverſitie of opinions touching the matter in
queſtion among them, for lack, as is ſaid, of fit expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced
perſons or inſtruments in that caſe, either for
offence or defence. But at length conſidering that
much profitable time for the purpoſe, may bee ſpent
in little available diſcuſſions, and alſo timely conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
the impoſsibilitie of any reſiſtance left to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants,
againſt ſo great, and ſo reſolutely bent for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
as were the French againſt them. This Chaos of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100126:4"/>
confuſed opinions was broke in ſunder, and all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable
matters therein ſet aſide, leaving nothing
behind, but the pure reall ſubſtance of the neceſſarie
preſent helpe: whereof was framed a a ſetled and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
agreed upon reſolution: which was to ſend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
three Spaniſh Captaines, and foure Iriſh, which
Iriſh Captaines were <hi>Daniel o Cahan, David Barrie,
Oliver fitz Gerald,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Terentio o Gallig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>howe,</hi>
and with the <hi>Auidante Pedro Geraldine,</hi> they
went on with a crew of brave and ſtout ſtomackt
men, reſolved, rather than that they ſhould faile of
ſuccouring their friends in their extremitie to make
their enemies dig up their graves, and them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the heathen cuſtome, to ſprinkle with the
blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of their ſaid enemies, and ſo to offer a humane
ſacrifice for the expiation of their offences on earth:
But as God would have it, there was no ſuch need;
for without let or moleſtation, they entred into the
endangered Citie with deſired, and long expected
ſuccour, to the extream joy and hearty comfort of
the beſieged.</p>
            <p>The Iriſh Captains with their Auidants and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies,
were no ſooner incloſed within the narrow
precinct of the Citie walls, but that like fire, being
removed from a vaſt and large place, where its exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations
had free ſcope of paſſing through the aire
whereby the heat is not ſo forceable, nor extreame,
as it is when the fire is removed into a narrow or
ſtraight room or compaſſe, where thoſe fierie bodies
are reſtrained of their former libertie, and are kept
within the fire, whereby the heat of the fire is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
by reaſon of the reſtraint of the ſaid fierie bodies:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100126:5"/>
Even ſo the couragious and valiant Iriſh, being but a
ſmall handfull of men, in reſpect of their numerous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,
being in the broad fields, though they lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
no courage or will to ſet upon their enemies:
Yet were they not ſo fierie, nor ſo incenſed, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ignorant of the poor caſe their friends and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades
were in within the Towne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but comming in,
and ſeeing in what ſtate things ſtood there, then took
they and kept to themſelves all their unmercifull
and raging bloody humours, and reſtrained them
of their former liberties, which they had in the vaſt
fields of their ignorance of their friends ill-fare, and
ſought licenſe preſently to execute their angry
mood upon their inſulting enemies, pretending that
their haughtie and ſtout ſtomacks could not brooke
nor diſgeſt their enemies ſo neare neighbourhood.
Whereupon licenſe upon great and importunate en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treatie
being granted by the Governor, the Spaniards
and the Iriſh began to give order for the ſally, and
began to encourage their ſouldiers, and to whet and
ſet their luſty and lofty reſolutions on edge in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
them in mind of their former famous acts. Now
all things being in order for the ſally, by the incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating
and Marſhalling of the Companies as the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowneſſe
of the place could afford meanes to doe:
this being done, they iſſued bravely on the ſuddaine,
with ſuch furie and eagerneſſe to fight, as if it had
been a mountaines flood, which beares, and forcibly
carries afore it, men and beaſts, trees and ſtones, by the
force of the riotous Current: Even ſo went on theſe
brave Warriers, till they fell upon the enemies trench,
where they did bloody execution and revenge upon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100126:5"/>
enemies, with ſome loſſe to themſelves; in which
ſkirmiſh, and many more hot and bloody encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
and conflicts I leave to the judicious French,
the cenſure of the courage, and Lion-like magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie
and reſolution of the brave and Heroick Iriſh
men, in their bold and Chivalrous attempts, to the
no ſmall glorie of their moſt renowned King and
Countrie; and not onely in that place, but alſo in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
other places where their memorable and never
dying acts are to their immortall fame, and reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
regiſtred and remaine as examples and patterns to
noble and honour-thirſty minds, and ſtirring knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
motives to poſteritie, as namely, in <hi>Polonia, Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,
Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Almirante de Caſtilla,</hi> the thrice noble, and brave
worthy afore-mentioned, prime Generall of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
Armies, after his arrivall at St. Sebaſtian, hee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatched
like a prudent Chiefetaine many ſpies to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
the paſſages, ſallidas, fortifications, the number
of their enemies watches, with the order of the ſame,
and their vigilancie in ſetting their watches, with
all the poſsible advantages that might be had of their
ſaid watches, fortifications, and ſtrongeſt workes, as
alſo to diſcover the ſtate of the beſieged: of which
being advertiſed by the Governour, and of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
they were in, if not preſently ſuccoured, as alſo
the great forwardneſſe of their enemies proceedings,
if not ſpeedily interrupted. Vpon which notice the
<hi>Almirant</hi> reſolved out of hand to attempt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving
of the Citie both by ſea and land, which his
brave intent, as God would have it, happily tooke
deſired effect, twice by the arrivall of Spaniſh
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100126:6"/>
and Iriſh ſuccours to the beleaguered: Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
all theſe ſuccours arrived in the Towne, and the
flying rumours daily of the Spaniards maine armies
approach, the French obſtinately bent, either to take
the towne, or to loſe themſelves in the purſuit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
daily made their approaches with Trenches, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries,
and other warlike ground-works, and ſo well
plyed themſelves to the Spade and Mattock, that in
ſhort time they came to the Towne ditch and wall,
and there blew up their Mines in three ſeverall places:
by meanes whereof, the walls on that ſide were ſo
ſore ſhaken and broken, that they were even levelled
with the earth: ſo that by this, and the daily skirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes,
and continuall alarums given to them of the
Towne by the enemies keeping them ſtill awake, by
their multitudes, whereas the beleaguered had but
few hands, ſo that they could not change, but that the
ſame men were ſtill upon the Wals, by which, and the
terrible roaring of the French Canon, freely beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
its murthering bullets amongſt the unthankfull,
but not ungratefull beſieged receivers: the one halfe
almoſt of the beſieged were ſlaughtered, and the reſt
ſore wounded, and tired quite with continual watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
and allarums: but in this extremitie the noble
Matrons and yong maidens of the Citie, mightily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived
the drooping (for want of ſtrength, not of
courage) ſouldiers; for ſtill they would be at hand
with powder, Bullets, Guns, ſwords, Pikes; meat and
drinke to the hungrie and thirſty, cure to the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
and their hands were as forward in the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes,
and Counterſcarfes of the Citie, as any ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers
in the Garriſon, and thoſe that were hurt they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100126:6"/>
carryed home to their houſes, and there cheriſhed
them, and cured them as if they had been their owne
Fathers, or Husbands, or Brethren: which <hi>Amazo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi>
behaviour and reſolution ſo animated the aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
ſtrengths, and tyred vigorous ſpirits of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted
Spaniards, and Iriſh, that even then as they
thought (being in the jawes of death) being ſure
they ſhould be ſlain, for yeeld they would not to ſave
a thouſand lives to each one; ſo carefull were they of
their honour, and the reputation of their nation. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
then, I ſay, being in this extremitie, they reaſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
to themſelves new courages, and out of a meer
debilitie, and forced weakneſſe, they ſqueezed to
themſelves new ſtrength and couragious reſolution:
for it is knowne by tryed experience, ever ſince it is
knowne what man and woman are, what power the
force of love of the one Sex hath, to kindle in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous
breaſt of the other, an invincible minde and
boldneſſe, of which, Ages, and Authors, both ancient
and moderne afford multiplicitie of preſidents and
examples, which more fully to expreſſe is not my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
intent: but my purpoſe is to declare, according
to my conſcience, and experience in that warre to ſet
forth fully, and not defraud either ſide of their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily
atchieved glories: for by the womens incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,
and rowſing up of (the almoſt dejected
ſtrengths of) the Garriſon ſouldiers, the reanima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Spaniards and Iriſh were ſo dreadfull to their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieging
enemies, that they durſt no more approach
them than raging &amp; hungrie mawed Lions. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
this, as is ſaid, by the continuall bloody
broyles, and toylſome labours, halfe the ſouldiers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100126:7"/>
beleaguer'd were ſlain, and many more of the French,
and on both ſides great numbers of Crepples, and
maimed limleſſe men eſcaped to preſerve the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
of theſe cruell frayes of <hi>Mars,</hi> by the direfull loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
and borne, and accompanying examples of their
mangled members.</p>
            <p>The Prince <hi>de Conde,</hi> Generall of the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
Kings Armie, imagining wiſely with the reſt of
the Councell of warre, by the great loſſe ſuſtained by
thoſe of the Towne: and alſo by the breaking down
of their walls by his Mines, as is afore related, that
then hee may build a firme ground of giving an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault
to the Towne, upon thoſe great advantages he
ſuppoſed himſelfe to have over thoſe of the Towne,
for their lack aſwell of men, as of defenſible Walls.
As alſo by the great numbers on the other ſide he was
himſelf furniſhed of, of valiant &amp; brave <hi>French</hi> Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers,
and all kinde of warlike Engines for to diſtreſſe
the beſieged. Vpon which ſure foundations ſetling
himſelfe for to give the aſſault, hee preſently gave
command, which was accordingly worthily execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by the reſolute French men, on the right hand of
the breach, where they proceeded with ſuch heat, fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
and valour, as if everie one of them carryed light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
in their armes and weapons, till they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted
upon the ruines of the decayed and battered
walls, by the valorous Spaniſh and Iriſh ſouldiers,
where both parties proceeded one againſt another.
Juſt like as in a ſtormie and tempeſtuous day, the
troubled and raging waves of the ſhipwrack threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
ſea, we ſee doe run with conjoyned and ſtrongly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100126:7"/>
knitted force, intending to carrie all before them,
minding no reſiſtance, but on the ſuddaine we ſee
they are met by the maine and impenetrable front of
ſome high reared ſtonie Cliffe, where contrarie to
their preſumptuous and over-weening expectations,
all their hopes are daſhed, and their powers diſ-joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
and beaten back in diſmembred parcells into the
maine bodie of their inſulting ſeconding mother.
Even ſo were the fierie ſtomacks of the haſty French
cooled and quenched by the pure and precious wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of the unconquerable Spaniſh and Iriſh courages,
and given repulſes: where the French, after their
forced retire, in memorie of their valour, left the
breach full of their dead carkaſſes.</p>
            <p>The French Commanders ſeeing no hope, or any
poſſibilitie of carrying the place by force of aſſault,
propounded to the beſieged certaine overtures of
peace (becauſe they were loath to expect the wearing
them out by hunger, and ſiege: which in Martiall
brunts they could not doe with greateſt advantages)
in which Overtures they propounded the difficultie,
if not impoſsibility of any ſuccour: which indeed to
my owne knowledge was very true. Secondly they
propoſed any quarter they would deſire. Which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions
after conſideration thereof had by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged
(as by men who did not halfe ſo much fear the
imminent danger, nay apparent loſſe of their lives,
as by all preſumption it was like as their loyaltie and
good example to their King and Countrie) were ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
rejected.</p>
            <p>The Illuſtrious <hi>Almirante de Caſtillia</hi> being adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100126:8"/>
of the perill the beleaguered were in, did not
ſo highly in words commend their courage, and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,
but that hee as inwardly dreaded and feared
their danger: wherefore convocating a generall
Councell of warre, of the moſt and beſt experienced
ſouldiers about him, hee imparted the importance,
and conſequence of the buſineſſe to them, with the
difficulties and dangers thereof ariſing, if ſpeedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy
were not applyed; and therefore commanded
their opinions therein, to the beſt availe of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties
ſervice, and diſcharge of their own conſcience
and duty, being intruſted in it.</p>
            <p>In the neck of which conſultation, there arrived a
Poſt from his Catholike Majeſtie, and his great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
and prudent, and worthy Counſellour <hi>Conde</hi>
Duke, confirming as it were afore-hand the enſuing
reſolution of the Councell, which unanimouſly was
to divide the Armie in three parts: the one of which
to bee imployed about the buſying and diverting the
enemies forces from the Towne. And the other
two to attend all opportunities and advantages that
may be taken or offered, either by the negligence of
the enemie, or by the commoditie or ſcituation of
the place, to charge him to his greateſt annoy; and to
endeavour by all meanes to relieve the begirt Citie
of <hi>Fuenteravia.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="account_of_battle">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100126:8"/>
               <p>Vpon this reſolution taken, and all things readily
appoynted, order was given, that the Armie
ſhould march at a ſet and appoynted houre: Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis
<hi>de Mortara</hi> one of the Spaniſh Commanders, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
thoſe under the leading of the <hi>Almirante</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
to approach neare, commanded the vanguard
of his owne Troops to march on towards the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie.</p>
               <p>Then fell on with ſpeed, and unſpeakable courage
the incorporated vanguard of the Corolenia of
Conde Duke, and of the two Iriſh Regiments of
the Earles of Tirone, and Tirconell: the Condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors
and ſouldiers of which ſeemed for haſte and
hunger to fight to prevent deſire it ſelfe: ſo forward
they were to doe their Prince ſervice, and his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
dammage, and detriment: which their deſire
tooke ſpeedy execution, by their eager and furious
falling upon their enemies: ſo that in leſſe than an
houre they took in the two next adjoyning Calina's
with eleven appoynted poſts in them, which the
French did poſſeſſe.</p>
               <p>After this, Serjeant Major <hi>Barrie,</hi> an Iriſh man of
long tryed and approved experience in the warres of
the Low Countries and of Germanie; and one who
gave good tokens of his great skill, and abilitie in
warlike and martiall affaires, and Diſcipline, as well
in this exploit, as in other precedent important ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices,
as it is well knowne to many, having the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100126:9"/>
leading and conduct of the ſaid incorporated van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard
of the Spaniſh armie, hee marched on dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly
without ſtay with incredible warineſſe and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
with his vanguard to the maine great Trench
of his enemy, taking as he marched all the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages
and commodities which the ſcituation of the
place would ſuffer, or any way afford, till hee came
within Piſtoll ſhot of the enemies great and ſtrongeſt
Trench; when on both ſides there began a bloudie
ſkirmiſh, with which there aroſe a great noyſe of
Drums and Trumpets in the French Camp, when
their Artillerie began to roare, and flye bountifully
to the Spaniſh ſide, with which <hi>Barrie</hi> skirmiſhing all
this while upon the brinks of the enemies great and
maineſt trench, and prying narrowly to the enemies
doing, omitting nothing that might becom a skilful
and prudent Leader to his ſouldiers, and a dangerous
and advantagious enemie to his enemies, going from
place to place, ſtill encouraging with comfortable
words, where hee found any coldneſſe of courage,
which hee found in verie few; and putting them in
the moſt forward hope of reward, reforming and
ſetling the ranks in compleat and perfect order, and
putting them in generall in memorie of their former
and famous attchievements, to the renowne and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall
credit of their Nations both of Spaine
and Ireland. So that by theſe, and other his expert
ſedulous and skilfull incouragements, hee made
of the multitude, as if it had been but one compleat
and well compoſed bodie, and made them ſo ready
and willing to obſerve his commands, that hee
could ſcarce command, but it was ſo readily obeyed,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100126:9"/>
that ſcarce any difference could be diſcerned betwixt
the command, and the obedience thereunto: hee
made them ſo ready and dexterous to performe his
will, as if they had beene the body, and he the head:
the body could not obey the will of the head ſooner
than they did his, which was a thing worthy of note
to be done in ſo ſhort a time, and which und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r God
was the chiefe meanes of gaining the victorie.</p>
               <p>Now being thus buſie, as is ſaid, he might perceive
that the enemies horſe made preparation to give
a charge upon him: which perceiving, hee approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
nearer unto them, and powred among them a
whole<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> volley of ſhot, and then prepared himſelf for
the fight, giving preſent inſtructions to that effect, as
one who knew well the valour and reſolution of the
French Horſe: then preſently did hee call into the
vanguard all the Officers reformed and Cavaliers of
the two Iriſh Regiments, who like valiant and brave
Cavaliers made no ſtay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but appeared preſently with
all diligent Obedience at his beck: Of them did
<hi>Barrie</hi> frame the front of the pikes, to reſiſt the
furie of the enemies horſe, the ſhot being ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
divided into all poſſible advantages, to bee taken
according to the naturall ſcituation of the place.</p>
               <p>Thus all things being in perfect order according
to the time, to offend the enemie, and to defend
themſelves, if he ſhould attempt any thing againſt
them: <hi>Barrie</hi> diſpatched five Officers, Vivo's and
Reformed, with preſent advertiſements to <hi>Mortara;</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100126:10"/>
and for other helps, as powder, Matches, and ſuch
like other neceſsities, of which he was not ſo plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
provided as he would, which his requeſt, <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tara,</hi>
like a brave, provident, and wiſe Commander
preſently granted.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Barrie</hi> ſeeing that all things were duely
and decently ordered for the fight, and that the
ſouldiers were provided to their content, began to
incourage them a new with the moſt comfortable
words he could deviſe, calling upon the common ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers
by name thoſe which he knew, the reſt he took
by the hands and promiſed them great rewards, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
ſeverally to each Captain, Commander and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer
under his charge, encouraging them apart;
and then in generall ſhewing them where new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefes
were, in all haſte marching to them: and after
thoſe reliefes, the Reeregard marching in order to
their aſsiſtance: Then <hi>Barrie</hi> the ſecond time ſent
two Reformed Iriſh Officers, advertiſing Marquis
<hi>de Mortara,</hi> that if hee did ſend ſuccour to charge
on the right hand of the great Trench, to buſie that
ſide, hee with the vanguard would with reſolution
fall upon the reſt of the enemies fortifications upon
his perill, and that he hoped to give good accompt
of his proceedings therein. <hi>Mortara</hi> for his owne
diſcharge, and being mightie glad, and joyfull of the
hope he conceived what noble effect the worthy at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
of ſuch a couragious crew as <hi>Barrie,</hi> and his
followers were, would bring forth, if it were well
ſeconded, diſpatched a meſſage out of hand to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100126:10"/>
                  <hi>Almirante,</hi> ſignifying unto him the ſumme of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rries</hi>
honourable requeſts, and Chivalrous intent,
and reſolution, who taking conſideration of the
buſineſſe, and being diſcuſſed among ſome of the
chiefeſt Commanders, Marquis <hi>de Torrecuſa</hi> offered
himſelfe to bee imploy'd according to <hi>Barries</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,
who being licenſed, departed; and having im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>battailed
his men, and incouraged them, as the
ſhortneſſe of time gave leiſure, hee went manfully
and reſolutely, and led his men to give charge upon
the right hand of the enemies great Trench, as <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi>
demanded: but <hi>Torrecuſa</hi> was twice repulſt. Yet
the third time hee gained that ſide of the Trench,
which he aſſaulted, and came at laſt to his appoynted
place of Execution with great courage and diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
where gaining the redout that was on the right
hand, hee and his Spaniards, and Neapolitans,
fought with ſuch vigour and might, that it was
ſtrange to behold, but that it was known they were all
choſen and approved men, led by ſo valiant and wiſe
a Leader as <hi>Torrecuſa</hi> was: And there was another
thing that made theſe doings of <hi>Torracuſa,</hi> and his
traine to ſeeme the leſſe ſtrange, which was to ſee,
with what violence and force <hi>Barrie</hi> and the Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard
of the Iriſh and Spaniſh under his conduct and
command, ſet upon the reſt of the enemies great
Trench, which they took and drove back the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
with ſuch fury, that it was wonderfull to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold:
and where <hi>Torrecuſa</hi> fought with his Neapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litans
and Spaniards, was the cruell effect of Ire and
courage to bee ſeene upon the miſerable mangled
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100126:11"/>
bodies of the killed and ſlaine; the heavy groans of
the wounded, the loud ſhrieks of the diſtreſſed dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ſouldiers; the neighing of hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, the clatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
of Armour, the claſhing of ſwords and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons
together, where a man may ſee revenge quench
her thirſt with humane blood. There was ſlaughter
in her royaltie, crowned with Majeſty, carried, and
treading upon dead and wounded bodies, and to
conclude, there was ſuch a death-breeding confuſion
and terrible deadly dreadfull noyſe of the dying and
wounded, and of Drums, Trumpets, and other
Militarie inſtruments, as if halfe the world were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled
together, and had conſpired with full in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
to deſtroy all man-kinde in the other halfe, and
were aſsiſted by all the ſeverall Elements, ſuch a
Confuſion there was: for where the Spaniards
and Iriſh fought, there was no reſiſtance to be made
againſt them: for they made ſuch a bloody Maſſacre
and havock of their enemies, that by pure force and
dint of ſword they drove them out of their ſtrongeſt
fortification. Which <hi>Barrie</hi> perceiving, and that
<hi>Torrecuſa</hi> and hee had the victorie on both ſides of
the field, by the forcing of their enemies out of that
Trench, he commanded, (his thirſt of honour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
not yet quenched) the vanguard to advance fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
towards the enemie, which they obeying, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately,
the firſt troops of Muſquetiers advancing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
gave way to the reſt to follow them to execute
their Commanders will. The French ſeeing their
laſt refuge to conſiſt in their valorous carriage, with
ſtout courages their Cavallerie gave a brave charge
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100126:11"/>
upon the fore-moſt troops of <hi>Barries</hi> ſouldiers, and
made them retire backe into the Trench they had
formerly taken. Then immediately againe came
freſh ſuccours of <hi>Torracuſa</hi> and <hi>Mortara,</hi> and then
the ſecond time did <hi>Torracuſa</hi> and <hi>Barrie</hi> advance
with the vanguard, and made alſo a diſtance of, till
the Rereguard arrived, and fell with united for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
on the enemie with ſuch furie, that they were
forced to make a vertue of neceſsitie, which was to
retire: which if they had not timely and provident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
done, they had incurred great and moſt imminent
danger. For if a thouſand Muſquetiers of <hi>Don
Pedro Siron,</hi> and <hi>Don Ioſeph deſanta Maria,</hi> had come
upon their backs on the other ſide in a narrow paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage,
hardly could they have retired, or eſcaped, but
with great hazzard and loſſe.</p>
               <p>Now the ſlaughter was the greateſt when they
came to the Sea ſide; where <hi>Barrie</hi> ſhewed himſelfe
a man that could uſe his victorie with moderation,
and mercie to the vanquiſhed, which was a vertue
ſo much commended in ancient and famous Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,
and that deſervedly in my conceit: for after
that the French were paſt hope of eſcape, and that
they ſubmitted themſelves, and held up their hands
for mercie, it was not the part of a man indued with
naturall reaſon, and touched with any tenderneſſe
of Conſcience or generoſitie of minde to kill and
murther them ſo crawling at their feet, and voyd of
all power to defend themſelves, but rather it became
a brutiſh inſulting beaſt; and as wee heare, there are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100126:12"/>
ſome beaſts that never inſult ſo, nor exerciſe any
cruell power upon the conquered: but ſeeing them
voyd of defence, leave them ſo, as namely the King
of Beaſts, the royall Lion.</p>
               <p>Which noble vertue of the Lion <hi>Barrie</hi> notably
imitated here: for hee ſuffered not one man of all
the French, that ſubmitted themſelves and came out
of the Sea, to receive the leaſt hurt or dammage,
but preſerved the lives of great multitudes, who by
all likelyhood had beene all put to the ſword, by
thoſe that neither regarded their honour, nor the
feare of God, but followed and were guided by
their owne unmercifull ſavage humour, and could
away with no reaſon, but their unreaſonable and
brutiſh will: which preſumption and madneſſe <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi>
wiſely reſtrained, by appoynting certaine luſty
ſouldiers of his Retinue, to guard the vanquiſhed
French: giving them in charge, to uſe them as ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
that offered any injurie to the French: which
was the meanes as before is ſaid, that great numbers
of lives were ſaved, as the French can teſtifie; As
alſo with what kindneſſe and courteſie the Iriſh fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
them, being their protectors ever ſince the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
was paſt.</p>
               <p>Now the French thus defeated and routed, and
all their great forces and hopefull preparations bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
deſtroyed, and brought to nothing, the ſpoyles
that were taken were preſented to the <hi>Almirante</hi> of
Caſtilia: Where <hi>Barrie</hi> for his part of the ſpoyles
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100126:12"/>
preſented the Generall with five Enſignes of the
French, as a token of his pains taken in that Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,
and Captaine <hi>Daniel Mac-Curthy,</hi> another Iriſh
Captaine, preſented one Enſigne to the Almirante.
<hi>Torrecuſa</hi> and <hi>Barrie</hi> at the taking in of the great
Trench of the enemies by them, found therein
foure Peeces of Braſſe Ordnance, and afterwards
in the Batterie they found twentie eight, in all thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
two French Braſſe pieces of Artillerie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Almirante de Caſtilia</hi> of whom we ſpake prettie
well afore, gained himſelfe, his King and Countrie,
this day eternall fame and renowne.</p>
               <p>As did Marquis <hi>de Torrecuſa,</hi> revive and increaſe
the glorie of his flouriſhing Countrie of Italy, by
his rare and exquiſite skil ſhewed in his prudent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct,
as well in this as other happy encounters.</p>
               <p>The Noble Marquis <hi>de Mortara</hi> likewiſe ſhewed
himſelfe like a politick and valiant Captaine, as was
expected of him, which to his perpetuall fame, he
with glorie diſcharged.</p>
               <p>The deadly and ghaſtly wounds of the followers
of the <hi>Conde de Agilare,</hi> likewiſe made knowne
their worthy acts, and eager forwardneſſe.</p>
               <p>The brave ſouldiers likewiſe of Mr. <hi>del Campdan,
Ioſeph de ſanta Maria,</hi> and Mr. <hi>del Campden Pedro de
Siron</hi> did no leſſe worthy ſervice: as did alſo Serjeant
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100126:13"/>
Major <hi>Barrie,</hi> with his couragious and magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Iriſh ſouldiers, and not onely the Common
ſouldiers, but alſo the Reformed Officers of the two
Regiments of the Earles of Tirone, and Tirconell,
being all Iriſh, as alſo the Captaines, &amp;c. with
their diviſions conſtantly ſeconding, (as appeareth by
the Certificates of <hi>Barrie,</hi> under whoſe conduct they
ſerved) ſtill with ſuch dexteritie and obedience, that
at no neceſsitie their preſence was wanting, till all
was ended as afore is mentioned, and at large expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
to the everlaſting renowne of their King and
Countrie.</p>
               <p>And no leſſe did appeare the noble mind of Mr.
<hi>Del Camp Carlo Varſa,</hi> by his glorious and brave at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts
in this onſet. And to conclude with them all
in generall, both Spaniards and Iriſh, and Neapoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,
both Commanders and ſouldiers, ſuch were
their brave on-ſets, glorious attempts, and couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
reſolutions in this battaile, and famous (by their
atchievements) victorie obtained againſt their valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
enemies; that all things conſidered according to
the numbers and warlike Equipage, and Martiall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coutrements
on both ſides. The brave and noble
minded triumphing Romans; as namely, <hi>Camillus,
Publicola, Fabius, Emilius, Cato, Scipio,</hi> and the reſt
that attained by their well-imployed Conſulſhips to
their deſerved, and moſt glorious and pompous tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs
over their conquered enemies. Or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
and undaunted Greek Heroes, as were the
great <hi>Macedonian Alexander,</hi> the furious ſpirit
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100126:13"/>
                  <hi>Pirrhus,</hi> and the brave <hi>Spartan Ageſilaus,</hi> the noble
and worthy <hi>Athenians, Pericles, Themiſtocles,</hi> and
<hi>Alcibiades,</hi> or the high minded <hi>Thebans, Pelopidas,</hi>
and <hi>Epaminondas, &amp;c.</hi> Many more as worthy every
way of the Grecian blood and nation, which to
their mortal reputation and honour have left infinite
volumes full of their moſt glorious acts, as memorials
to all worldly eternitie. Theſe two Nations conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
and each ſeverall perſon by himſelfe conſidered,
with his power, and feats done upon their enemies
for ſo ſhort a time, and unexpected execution. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
did he of the one ſide deſerve his inſulting gorge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
triumphs, and ſumptuous ſacrifices and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,
according to the cuſtomes of his Countrie;
nor they on the other part, better deſerve to have
their acts graved, and carved in Gold, Copper, or
Braſſe: Nor to have their Altars, Statues, and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Images to preſerve and record to future and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing
ages, their famous and victorious Conqueſts,
than did theſe renowned Warriers, Spaniards and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,
ſerving under the royall Standards and Banners
of his moſt ſacred Catholick Majeſty, deſerve to have
the moſt exquiſite, and ready, and ſkilfull Quills in
Europe, to indent and beare record of this their moſt
glorious, and never dying victorie.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="Irish_officers">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:100126:14"/>
            <head>Here followes a Liſt of as
many Officers and Cavaliers of the
Iriſh as ſuffered by death and maiming
in this bloody fray, by their ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
purſuit of the victorie, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ſtill the formoſt in
the execution.</head>
            <div type="Irish_wounded">
               <head>Here followeth the names of the hurt Officers.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>FIrſt, Captaine <hi>Teig O Kelly,</hi> Reformed.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tuohill O Haghan,</hi> a Reformed Alferis.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Randall Mac-Donell,</hi> a Reformed Alferis.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn O Naghtin,</hi> a Reformed Alferis.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn O Magher,</hi> a Reformed Sergeant.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Farill Duff O Connor,</hi> a Reformed Sergeant.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Daniel O Begly,</hi> a Corporall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>James O Mloghlin,</hi> a Corporall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Garret O Brin,</hi> a Corporall.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="Irish_dead">
               <head>Theſe inſuing are the names of the ſlaine
Iriſh Officers.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Peter Roch,</hi> a Reformed Alferis.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nicholas Cuſack,</hi> a Reformed Alferis.</item>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100126:14"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William O Hanglin,</hi> a Reformed Sergeant.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Teig O Bradegave,</hi> a Reformed Sergeant.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Patrick Fitz Gerald,</hi> a Sergeant.</item>
                  <item>Cavalier <hi>Dermod Mac-Carthy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Purcell,</hi> a Reformed Corporall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Rulgh,</hi> a Corporall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert O Fwellane,</hi> a Corporall.</item>
                  <item>Cavalier <hi>Iames Barrie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mlaghlin O Dowgane,</hi> a Corporall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edmond O Dij,</hi> a Corporall.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Of which, thoſe that were wounded, and may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
thoſe ſcarres and wounds, they beare as brave
and noble badges of their never-yeelding minds, and
loyalties, and thoſe that were ſlaine, left their bodies
as the more ignoble parts, and Cabinets (to give
their mother earth its naturall due) wherein were
contained and kept thoſe haughtie and heroicall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,
and courages, which were the ſtirrers
and movers of the ſaid bodies, to ſuch noble at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts
as wherewith they attained to the glorious
Laurell of victorie, for their earthly parts, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
which courages were the precious jemmes, lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hornes,
and efficients of their owne quiet repoſe in
the high bed of Fame, where the loud and ſhrill
Trumpet of their worthineſſe ſhall perpetually ſound
out with ecchoing noyſe their deſerved praiſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="afterword">
               <p>Now Gentlemen, and Courteous, and impartiall
peruſers of this, as impartiall and true, but ſhort re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation;
I would not have you thinke, that what
things I ſet downe here, are but heare-ſayes, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100126:15"/>
relations of gagling old Goſsips in their merrie car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowſings:
but that which I deſire of you, and which
I expect as ſole reward for the ſmall paines I tooke
in penning this ſmall Pamphlet, is, to conceive, (and
as the verie and reall truth is) that what I ſet down
here, and offer to your views in everie particular, I
was eye and hand-witneſſe of, and of all the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages
ſpecified in the precedent relation, and was
alſo a partaker of the greateſt hazzards happened in
that enterprize, which I hope in your equall ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,
the truth ſhall be a helpe and mover of beliefe
in your imaginations to my equall diſtributing of a
Relatorie reward to each particular deſerver in this
great exployt: And alſo, though I tell you I was par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker
in the perills; yet to name my ſelfe, I think it
not meet: which alſo I hope may be a motive in you
to my advantage in that way, I deſire it, which is
ſtill deſiring your beliefe to my Relation, and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie
of each ones good deſerts in this ſervice,
which in the faith of a good Chriſtian, and ſouldier,
in no poynt I did faile, according to the retention
of my ſhallow memorie, and ſmall experience it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of that nature. So in this, as in your favourable
Cenſure, and conſtruction of this my courſe, rude,
and ſouldierly penning, and ſtile;</p>
               <closer>I bid you farewell.</closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:100126:15"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
