<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of Colonell Cromwels proceedings against the cavaliers wherein set forth the number of those that were taken, kil'd and maimed at his late victories obtained over them : sent in a letter / from a Gentleman in his army ; dated July 24, 1643, to a friend in London.</title>
            <author>Gentleman in his army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2902</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1587</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12075847</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12075847</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53592</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A63661)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53592)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 239:E62, no 7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of Colonell Cromwels proceedings against the cavaliers wherein set forth the number of those that were taken, kil'd and maimed at his late victories obtained over them : sent in a letter / from a Gentleman in his army ; dated July 24, 1643, to a friend in London.</title>
                  <author>Gentleman in his army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Bejamin [sic] Allen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53592:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A True</hi> RELATION <hi>OF</hi> Colonell Cromwels PROCEEDINGS againſt the <hi>CAVALIERS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is ſet forth the Number of thoſe that were Taken, Kil'd, and Maimed, at his late Victories obtained over them.</p>
            <p>Sent in a Letter from a Gentleman in his Army (Dated <hi>July,</hi> 24. 1643.) to a Friend in <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Bejamin Allen,</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:53592:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53592:2"/>
            <head>A TRVE RELATION <hi>OF</hi> Colonell CROMVVELS PROCEEDINGS Againſt the Cavaliers. VVherein is ſet forth the Number of thoſe that were Taken, Kil'd, and Maimed, in his late Victories obtained againſt them.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Captaine,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Received yours laſt week, &amp;c. for which I thanke you, and which did much mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the anxiety of our ſoules, wherein we were in the apprehenſion of the utter rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, and infinite loſſe of Sir <hi>William Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> as it was before related and repreſented to us, the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53592:3"/>
beſt I confeſſe is bad, but as it pleaſeth the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, ſo things come to paſſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> times to receive evill at his hande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> yet laying aſide our confidence in him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> downe to the Grave, and raiſeth up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to doe his worke intended by ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by great, and hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtrength of fleſh) and he will bring it to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is faithfull, he hath promiſed and he will doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. I ſhould be glad to heare ſome good newes of the <hi>Kentiſh</hi> buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp;c. in the meane time, I ſhall now tell you our own great danger, and therefore great deliverance, (the Lords name be praiſed for it.)</p>
            <p>About Tueſday laſt the Cavaliers came from <hi>Bever</hi> Caſtle, and <hi>Newark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ord, about 1000. of them, as was informed us; they ſet alſo that day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) upon <hi>Peterborough,</hi> but were repelled by Colonell <hi>Palgrave</hi> and his Company, who lay about <hi>Whittleſey</hi> and <hi>Peterborough,</hi> and ſallyed out to them with ſome <hi>Ordnance,</hi> they retired to <hi>Stamford,</hi> whither they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>d in the Countrey, and began to fortifie apace, but it pleaſed God to interrupt them, by ſending Colonell <hi>Cromwell</hi> to them from <hi>Northampton</hi> ſide, or Buckingham, with 6. or 7. Troops, and ſome few Foot.</p>
            <p>On Wedneſday they had ſome Skirmiſhes, firſt at a great houſe called Wothrop Houſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> whence driving them, they retired to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtately houſe, by <hi>Stamford</hi> alſo called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and getting within the Parke Walls, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> round with a ſtone Wall) they made that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>; ſo for that time the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> ſeaſed, for the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53592:3"/>
had few Foot, and no Ordnance. We loſt not a man, or but a man at moſt, he ſlew of theirs a Captain, a Lievtenant, and a Cornet, and ſome 10. or 12. more, and took one Colour, and ſome 20. men, ſo there was a True<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, at leaſt no more fighting till this morning: though the Colonel was within a mile and halfe of the Towne, intending to ſet downe againſt it on Saturday morning laſt betimes, but the ſad raine forbad him. Yeſterday God ſent alſo to his aſsiſtance, Colonell <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard,</hi> (and ſome ſay alſo, Sir <hi>Samuel Luke,</hi>) Colonell <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> alſo came to him with his men and Ordnance, ſo together they made a conſiderable ſtrength, of 3. or 4000. and they ſay 12. or 14. Pieces of Ordnance. They ſtay not, but preſently that night advance all to <hi>Burgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Houſe (whither the Enemy was againe gone for ſanct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uary) ſit downe before it, ſhot with their Ordnance 2 or 3. houres, (beginning at 3. of clock this morning) but could do no good that way, the houſe was ſo ſtrong; they ſound a Parley, offer quarter for the men only to have life and Liberty to depart without their weapons &amp;c. The Enemy refuſes, anſwers, they would neither take nor give quarter: They fall then upon them with their Muſquets, a difficult taske, and full of danger, the fight was very hot and well performed (they ſay) on both ſides, the Enemy being very confident, active, and tryumphing, till about one of clock this after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone; But then their Spirits began to faile them; And they ſounded a Parly, the Colonell moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anly commanded preſently that none of his ſhould dare to ſhoot or kill any man during the parly, upon paine of death, (forgetting their former cruell anſwer) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53592:4"/>
they concluded upon quarter for their lives; for they tooke them all (being two Colonells, ſix or ſeven Captaines, three or 400. Foote<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 150. or 200. Horſe) with all their Armes, &amp;c. And the pillage of the Houſe and how they will deale with <hi>Stanford</hi> now alſo at their mercy) we know not; but if the report be true which we have, that they rung the Bells back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on Wedneſday, when the firſt Skirmiſh was, to call in the Country to aſſiſt the Cavaliers, againſt the Colonell, his mercy will be admirable it they eſcape: for the Providence of God hath beene in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that in all this hot fight for nine or elven houres, we are credibly informed by one that was a Spectator all the while, that not above ſixe or ſeven men were ſlaine, (though many hurt) in the Battell; onely about two miles beyond <hi>Stamford,</hi> towards <hi>Grantham,</hi> ſome 400. Club-men comming in to the aid of the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers, and having killed ſome of the Colonells <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hee ſent three or foure Troopes to meet them they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt killed one of the Captaines; upon which being inraged, they preſently ſlew ſome 50. of them, the reſt fled (they ſay) into the Woods; This is the effect of what we yet hear: Thus it pleaſeth God yet to preſerve us; bleſſed be his name: I ſhould be glad to heare ſome good newes of Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> : you heare (I queſtion not) of the taking of <hi>Gainſ-berry;</hi> and the rich price there 15000. (they ſay) in the Earle of <hi>Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tones<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe</hi> with himſelfe, and abundance of other Knights, and Gentlemen and of brave Horſes, &amp;c. It was ſince beſieged againe by the Earle of <hi>New-Caſtle;</hi> and the Siege raiſed againe (wee heare this day) by my Lord
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53592:4"/>
               <hi>Fairefax;</hi> If it bee true, It's good newes to heare alſo that Noble Lord is in the field again. The Stage of war (you ſee) is now become on our ſide, the Lord be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull unto us; what heare you yet of the Scots? Are the Commiſſioners gone? Here is a muttering about the Lievtenant of the Tower; how goes on your buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for your new Army? What does my Lord Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls Army? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We have had terrible Alarms laſt weeke, but I was at <hi>Cambridge</hi> almoſt all the week with my Wife: The Lord be with us and for us, preſerve, fit, and uſe us for his Glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My love to you both.</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
