<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Trve relation of the proposing, threatning, and perswading the vintners to yeeld to the imposition upon wines declaring the dislike of the generality of retailers, and whatsoever they either did or suffered therein, was meerly by compulsion : and heereby is also truely set forth their great, and almost insupportable losse by this imposition : together with the extreame wrongs and injuries they have suffered in their arreare-money, in their meat-money, and by medium-wine.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11463</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12832462</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12832462</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94332</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A63719)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94332)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 255:E171, no 5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Trve relation of the proposing, threatning, and perswading the vintners to yeeld to the imposition upon wines declaring the dislike of the generality of retailers, and whatsoever they either did or suffered therein, was meerly by compulsion : and heereby is also truely set forth their great, and almost insupportable losse by this imposition : together with the extreame wrongs and injuries they have suffered in their arreare-money, in their meat-money, and by medium-wine.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wine and wine making --  Taxation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-05</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:94332:1"/>
            <p>Faults escaped, by reason of the Authors absence, when the Booke was in printing.</p>
            <p>Page 6. l. 7. For <hi>Hepos, r. Nepos.</hi> p. 8. l. 27. for rules in <hi>r. rule is.</hi> p. 9. l. 12. add <hi>may imagine.</hi> p. 33. marg. <hi>r. Ephes.</hi> 5. 4. p 36. l. 1. <hi>r. many.</hi> l. 7. <hi>r. continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> p. 41. l. 28. <hi>r. indicat.</hi> p. 54. marg. <hi>r. Demosthenes.</hi> p. 62. marg. for hereof, <hi>r. hereof.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94332:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE RELATION OF THE PROPOSING, THREATNING, AND perswading the VINTNERS to yeeld to the <hi>Imposition</hi> upon WINES.</p>
            <p>DECLARING, The dislike of the Generality of <hi>Retailers,</hi> And whatsoever they either did or suffered therein, was meerly by <hi>compulsion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> Heereby is also truely set forth their great, and almost insupportable Losse by this <hi>IMPOSITION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with the extreame <hi>Wrongs</hi> and <hi>Injuries</hi> they have suffered in their <hi>Arreare-Money,</hi> in their <hi>Meat-Money,</hi> and by MEDIUM-WINE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Yeare, MDCXLI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:94332:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94332:2"/>
            <head>A TRVE RELATION OF THE PROPOSING, THREATNING and perswading the VINTNERS to yeeld to the IMPOSITION upon <hi>WINES.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Imposition</hi> upon WINES was propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and required almost three years before <hi>Alderman</hi> ABEL became Master of the <hi>Company;</hi> during which time it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies strongly opposed, and refused by the generality of <hi>Retailers.</hi> And in the last time of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posall before his being Master they utterly refused it, and chose rather to lay themselves downe at his <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties</hi> feet, and stand to his mercy then to consent to that <hi>Imposition,</hi> and humbly gave in their <hi>Answere,</hi> that such payment could not bee made without the undoing and overthrow of <hi>them,</hi> their <hi>Families</hi> and <hi>Trades,</hi> as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by an Order entered in their <hi>Hall-Booke,</hi> bearing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94332:3"/>
date the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>March,</hi> 1637. Hence appeareth the <note n="*" place="margin">A book intituled <hi>A true dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Discovery</hi> to be defective, and the <hi>Author</hi> thereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull in the very entrance of his Booke, who would cunningly make the World believe that this <hi>Project</hi> had its beginning on the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1637. Therein subtilly and of purpose leaving out both the time of contrivement by the <hi>Alderman</hi> and Mr. <hi>Kilvert,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the time of resolute denyals by the Retailing <hi>Vint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> as appears not only by this Order already named, but also by another bearing date the 25. of <hi>October</hi> 1637. which Order doth plentifully shew Mr. <hi>Richard Kilvert</hi> to have a prime hand in the worke.)</p>
            <p>In the Summer following Alderman <hi>Abel</hi> (being <hi>Sheriffe</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> was made Master of the <hi>Company,</hi> who did then call many Courts to presse the yeelding (as he said) to the Kings desire in this <hi>Imposition.</hi> Amongst some of the first Meetings there were reasonable great appearances, to whom the <hi>Alderman</hi> proposed the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, v<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry vehemently urging their consents (most espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially) with two sorts of Arguments.</p>
            <p>The first consisting of many promises, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <note place="margin">Promises:</note> King would pardon all former faults of dressing and selling victualls contrary to the Decree of Star-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; of selling <hi>Wines</hi> above the rates (unknowne who was guilty of) and that (for the future) they should have priviledge to dresse and sell victuals, to sell Tobac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, Beere, Sugar, &amp;c. and be kept free from the danger of informers, as also have the Coopers debarred from buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Wines,</hi> saying hee had gotten the best and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned'st Counsell that could bee had for gold, who told him it was lawfull, and that the King might put what <hi>Imposition</hi> he pleased upon <hi>Wines,</hi> they being a forreigne Commoditie; and further hee said it should bee for the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94332:3"/>
good of the whole <hi>Company,</hi> and that their Posterity af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, and the Child unborne should have cause to blesse God for them. But these perswasions failing, hee sets upon them with</p>
            <p>The second sort of Arguments consisting of divers <note place="margin">Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</note> fearfull threatnings; namely, That they should be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted for dressing of meat contrary to the Decree, that they should be alwayes perplexed with Informers, and disabled to use their trades: That the King was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to settle the <hi>Imposition</hi> whether they yeelded or no, and this his resolution he would not alter: Nay, he said further, That the King would as soone loose the profit of his <hi>Crowne-land</hi> as that benefit; And that (if they consented not) either the Merchants or Coopers would step in and allow it the King.) That the Coopers had already Petition'd for it very earnestly, offering a great summe of money, and pretending themselves bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able then the <hi>Vintners</hi> to doe the Service: And that if the Coopers prevailed, the <hi>Vintners</hi> should become their slaves; and still as any one spake in dislike of it, the <hi>Alderman</hi> retorted most bitter words, frownes and sharp rebukes <note n="*" place="margin">As may by many be suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified.</note> (able to daunt a weak spirit) causing to be put apart, and not permitting him any further liberty of speech, telling them that when he was a young man they durst not speake so saucily, or oppose the Master and Wardens; for if they did, they should be sent away by an Officer to prison.</p>
            <p>All these wayes still failing him, and finding himself not able thereby to prevaile with the major part of the retailing Vintners, he ceased not to warne them dayly to the Hall, intending to wearie them into a consent by his extream and importunate urging, notwithstanding their often resolute denialls, whereupon they did then
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94332:4"/>
forbeare to make their repaires, to the Hall so fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently as formerly they had done to prevent his course and unsavory usage, and this their slacknesse in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, did so vexe the Alderman, that he required those that were present to write downe their names, that so notice might be taken of those that were absent: whereby the Discovery is discovered to be false, which saith, in <hi>pag.</hi> 15. A greater number of drawing Vint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners appeared at those generall Courts then hath beene knowne at any Court of former times. And afterward at some such meeting, when the greatest appearance (for the most part) were the Assistants, and other the ancient and chiefe of the company (whose expectation of sharers in the profit, made them well affected to the worke) they got (if ever) this generall consent preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, expressed (as they say) by the greater part than present holding up their hands. Those who had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to their plot, and had formerly denyed their consents, being the greatest number of the Company were almost totally absent; and if any of them that were then present did yeeld, it might be out of Ignorance, supposing themselves bound to obey, the Alderman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Master of the Company, or out of feare to offend a man so potent, he frequently threatning and mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing those which opposed the worke. These things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, may convince those which pretend the Retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers prosecuted it with such chearefulnesse and earnest desire that Alderman <hi>Abel</hi> did not, nor needed not to perswade them, as <hi>Discovery, pag.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Moreover, upon every meeting of the retailing Vint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, they were not admitted into their Court at their first comming (though it were after the houre appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) but were forced to stay below, sometimes two,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94332:4"/>
three, or foure houres ere they were called up, in all which time the Contractors (doubtlesse) were plotting and contriving how to obtaine the others consent, and in what manner to propose and accomplish their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe: so when the rest of the Company were admitted, the businesse was suddenly moved to them, who wanted such competent time to deliberate thereupon, as the Alderman and Farmers had formerly allowed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</p>
            <p>But the Discoverer saith, It was agreed upon by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Court at the Hall, that the common seale of the Company should passe to seale the Indenture; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, saith he, what can be more plaine then that this was the worke of the whole Company? <hi>pag.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>To which is answered, that there hath beene already a Certificate presented to the Committy, whereunto is about 300. mens hands, all which are ready to testifie upon Oath that they never gave their consents to the passing of the seale. Moreover, the Court so called to obtaine their consents, were not lawfully summon'd; for, besides the Farmers and Assistants, the rest of the dry Vintners were not warned, who had as much right to the Seale, and intrest in the Hall as any other of the Company: so this was a warning of some Vintners in particular, not of the whole Company in generall; the truth of this hath beene manifestly proved already; therefore by this it doth not appeare to the worke of the whole Company.</p>
            <p>Nay Alderman <hi>Abels</hi> owne-words will prove it to be none of the Companies Worke, for at a certaine time after his effecting of it, he tooke so much delight and pleasure in it, that hee clapt his hands upon his breast and said, I thanke God I have now brought that to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which I have beene two yeares a working.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:94332:5"/>
Furthermore, when the Alderman had wrought his ends, and a Proclamation came forth commanding the imposition, both by Tonne and Quart to be paid; some Vintners continued to sell for 6. pence and 12. pence, whereupon Alderman <hi>Abel</hi> sent for them, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned one to shut up his doores if he would not change his price and sell for 7. pence, and 14. pence, and would ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly disable him for drawing of Wine; relating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon that he had (not long before) procured an Order from the Councell Table against one in the country, by vertue whereof, he caused his doores to be shut up, and disabled him utterly for ever keeping Taverne any more, onely because he retailed his Wine at a penny a quart under the Proclamation: and he threatned ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that hee would set up a Taverne right against his doore to undoe him, because he sould for sixe pence a quart.</p>
            <p>And for those which did not, or could not pay the Imposition of forty shillings a tunne within a short time after he required it, he tooke out Extents, and seised their goods, to their great and insupportable losse and detriment, Insomuch that by his cruell threats and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall dealings, they neither durst refuses to pay the imposition, nor yet retaile their Wines at a lower rate, than the Lords by their Proclaimation had limitted. All these things considered doth make it evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare (as the truth is) that Alderman <hi>Abell</hi> as he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived and plotted the project cunningly, so hee prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted it earnestly to the very utmost in the acting thereof.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Losses to the Retailers of Wines.</head>
               <p>Further, it may plainely appeare that the Retailers (those onely excepted that had their shares in the Farme) are and have beene great losers by this impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94332:5"/>
for almost all the wines imported the last three yeares wanted much of gage; particularly, in some of the <hi>French</hi> Wines there wanted 16. gallons i'th tonne, in others 32. 40. 48. 56. and 64. In some few <hi>Spanish</hi> Wines, but eight gallons in most of them 16. 20. and 24. gallons; yet notwithstanding so every two Buts or Pipes of <hi>Spanish</hi> wine, and every 4. under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd-hogs-heads of <hi>French</hi> wines, the 40. shillings was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly exacted and paid without any rebates for their wants, (by which it may appeare that the Retailers have paid about 50. shillings for every tonne of cleare wine which they have bought) besides the great quantities of Lees in them, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther severall losses, as leakage, both in carriage home, and in their cellars, spilling, long deeping, eecaying, on their hands, bad debts, and their great dammages by Mediums.</p>
               <p>Also the Retailers were inforced for many of these wines to pay extraordinary prises, far exceeding the Rates set downe by the Lords; as namely, for some 4. pound. 4. pound 10. s. 5. po. 5. po. 10. s. 6. po. 6. 10. s. and 6. po. 15. s. and such like rates were paid and exacted more and higher than the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from the Lords to sell at; to which may be added the severall charges incident unto them, yet for all this the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailers never did exceed the price allowed by the Lords and set out by Proclamation: all these particulars are manifest trueths sufficiently knowne to all that are dealers in wine: whence the Author of the Booke intitled, <hi>A Discovery:</hi> is discovered to be Ignorant of these things, or very impudent that shall offer to fill three of his <hi>pages</hi> so full of untruthes, <hi>viz. pag.</hi> 25, 26, 27. Read, Compare, Consider, and Iudge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Wrongs and Injuries imposed by Alderman <hi>Abel</hi> and the Farmers.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>1. In the Arreare Money.</head>
                  <p>Whereas the Proclamation gave them no power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive or impose 40. s. a tonne till the 11th. of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1638. at the soonest, yet these Contractors, caused a search and view to be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94332:6"/>
made the last day of May being eleven dayes before, taken an exact account of the wines in all the Vintners cellars in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and in all other places within three miles compasse of the <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itie, though some of them had beene bought long before, which account they kept upon record till Vintage time. And when divers of the Vintners had bought new wines (without which their trades, could not be mannaged) they would not permit them to carry them home without Tickets, which Tickets the Office would not grant, although they paid the 40 s. a tonne, except they also discharged the Arreare accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their account, or sealed bonds to discharge it, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise they could not have home their wines to draw, (though they were already bought of the Merchants and paid for) In this exigent either they must seale those bonds, or themselves, their wives, children and Families, must be utterly ruinated in the losse of their trades for want of wines to supply their dayly Rent and Customers; so they sealed those bonds; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they have beene forc't to pay this Arreare Money as by their bonds taken appeare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>2. Medium Wine.</head>
                  <p>Also they suffered very much by the great quantities of <hi>Medium</hi> wines enforced on them being both very bad and very deare, whereby they were not onely hindered in their trades, but also much damnified in their reputation, in that they were compelled to part with great summes of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for these <hi>Mediums,</hi> and were thereby disabled to keep day with Merchants of whom they had bought good wines for time, and that time expired. The insupportable wrongs and injuries thereby suffered (almost to the utter undoing of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Retailers) hath beene sufficiently manifested (not onely by the imprisoning of many of them, but also) by the severall testimonies thereof made before the Committee.</p>
                  <p>The occasion of this <hi>Medium</hi> was that Invetterate malice and hatred that was in Alderman <hi>Abel</hi> against the Coopers, that, and that onely was both the begetting of the <hi>Medium,</hi>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94332:6"/>
and the very Originall occasion of the Coopers restraint.</p>
                  <p>Also the contriving of the <hi>Medium,</hi> was the Aldermans worke, as for the Retailers, they knew not what it ment when he proposed it; whereupon he tooke great paines, and spent much time in the explanation of it to them.</p>
                  <p>And himselfe, together with Mr. <hi>Griffith</hi> often pressed the consent thereunto very earnestly with many perswasions, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Retailers it would prove as small a matter as Flea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting, &amp;c. whereby it appeares, that the Booke intituled, <hi>A true Discovery,</hi> is a discoverer of untruths, in <hi>pag.</hi> 19. and 21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>3. Meat-Money.</head>
                  <p>Lastly, the Six thousand pounds formerly disbursed by the <hi>Retailers</hi> for dressing of <hi>Meate</hi> they could never yet get re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paid them, though his Majestie allowed it to the <hi>Atlerman</hi> and the rest of the Contractors: And for their defence in so unjust a detention they alledge for themselves two noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious untruths.</p>
                  <p>First, that they were at 2000. l. charge to procure it, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect whereof they would pay but only 12. s. in the pound.</p>
                  <p>Whereto is answered; First, if that assertion were true (which is indeed most false) yet two thirds of the Money re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains good to the lenders which is xiij s. iiij. d. in the pound.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it is further answered, that the 2000. l. (which they pretend it cost them to procure the said Money) they gave it meerely for the obtaining their Farme, as hath beene already proved.</p>
                  <p>In the second place, they alledge that it was agreed at a Meeting in the Hall, there should bee onely 12. s. in the pound repaid.</p>
                  <p>To which is answered, that at that meeting there were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few of the Lenders present, and of them no generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent was obtained; as may evidently appeare by the <hi>Hall Booke</hi> wherein (after the mentioning of some mens names then present) there was entred these very words: <hi>Touching
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94332:7"/>
the Retribution, Division happened, and not settled.</hi> And when the Court was dismissed, Alderman <hi>Abel</hi> and Mr. <hi>Griffeth</hi> asked Mr. <hi>Child</hi> the Clerke of the <hi>Company,</hi> if he had entered downe the Order of yeelding to take xij. s. ith'pound? hee replyed no, for it was not agreed upon, nor ordered; they said it was, and the <hi>Alderman</hi> saidshe must find such an Order, and would have forced him to make the entry: But hee replyed againe that it was unjust for them to require it, and more then they could answer to detaine the Lenders money, for they had no power to give away other mens Estates without their consents: And because Mr. <hi>Child</hi> refused to enter it as an Order agreed upon, they gave him very ill words both that day and divers times afterwards threatning him, and said it was a good deed to have him turned out of his place.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
