<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>John Taylors vvandering, to see the vvonders of the vvest. How he travelled neere 600. miles, from London to the Mount in Cornwall, and beyond the Mount, to the Lands end, and home againe. Dedicated to all his loving friends, and free minded benefactors. In these dangerous dayes for rich men, and miserable times for the poore servants of the late King, (whereof I was one, 45. yeers to his royall father and himself) I thought it needful to take some course to make use of some friends, and devise a painfull way for my subsistence; which was the journey I have past, and this booke heere present; for which purpose I gave out many of these following bills, to which neere 3000. gentlemen and others, have kindly subscribed, to give me a reasonable reward.</title>
            <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203757</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863590</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863590</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115800</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A64216)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115800)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 88:E573[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>John Taylors vvandering, to see the vvonders of the vvest. How he travelled neere 600. miles, from London to the Mount in Cornwall, and beyond the Mount, to the Lands end, and home againe. Dedicated to all his loving friends, and free minded benefactors. In these dangerous dayes for rich men, and miserable times for the poore servants of the late King, (whereof I was one, 45. yeers to his royall father and himself) I thought it needful to take some course to make use of some friends, and devise a painfull way for my subsistence; which was the journey I have past, and this booke heere present; for which purpose I gave out many of these following bills, to which neere 3000. gentlemen and others, have kindly subscribed, to give me a reasonable reward.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeer 1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber [i.e. September] 12 1649".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England --  Description and travel --  1601-1700.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2000-00</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-00</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-08</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-08</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-11</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115800:1"/>
            <p>JOHN TAYLORS
VVandering, to see the VVonders
of the VVEST.</p>
            <p>How he travelled neere 600. Miles, from London to the
Mount in Cornwall, and beyond the Mount, to the
Lands end, and home againe.</p>
            <p>Dedicated to all his loving Friends, and free minded
Benefactors.</p>
            <p>In these dangerous dayes for Rich men, and miserable times
for the Poore Servants of the late King, (whereof I was
one, 45. yeers to his Royall Father and Himself) I thought
it needful to take some course to make use of some friends,
and devise a painfull way for my subsistence; which was
the Journey I have past, and this Booke heere present; for
which purpose I gave out many of these following Bills,
to which neere 3<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>00. Gentlemen and others, have kindly
subscribed, to give me a reasonable reward.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeere 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115800:2"/>
            <head>TAYLORS Westerne Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
to the Mount.</head>
            <l>TIs a mad world (my masters) and in sadnes</l>
            <l>I travail'd madly in these dayes of madnes:</l>
            <l>Eight yeares a <hi>frenzy</hi> did this Land molest,</l>
            <l>The ninth year seem'd to be much like the rest,</l>
            <l>My selfe (with age, griefe, wrongs, and wants opprest,</l>
            <l>With troubles more then patience could digest)</l>
            <l>Amongst those Isles, I chose the least and best,</l>
            <l>Which was to take this journey to the West:</l>
            <l>And sure it is an Argument most fit,</l>
            <l>That he who hath a portion of small wit</l>
            <l>As I have, and good store of friends, 'twere sloth</l>
            <l>And foolery, not to make use of both.</l>
            <l>My wit was worne thread bare, halfe naked, poore.</l>
            <l>And I, with it, went wool-gath'ring for more.</l>
            <l>This long walke (first and last) I undertooke</l>
            <l>On purpose to get money by my Booke:</l>
            <l>My friends (I know) will pay me for my paine.</l>
            <l>And I will never trouble them againe.</l>
            <l>Six hundred miles, I (very neere) have footed,</l>
            <l>And all that time was neither sho'd or booted;</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115800:3"/>
But in light buskins I perform'd this traveli</l>
            <l>O're hill and dale, through dust dirt, flint, and gravell.</l>
            <l>And now no more words I in vaine will scatter,</l>
            <l>But come unto the marrow of the matter.</l>
            <l>My Reader must not her suppose that I</l>
            <l>Will write a treatise of Geography:</l>
            <l>Or that I meane to make ex<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct Relations</l>
            <l>Of Cities, Townes, or Countries scituations;</l>
            <l>Such men as those I turne them o're to reade</l>
            <l>The learned <hi>Cambden,</hi> or the painefull <hi>Speed.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And now (good Reader) I my muse do tune,</l>
            <l>I <hi>London</hi> left, the twenty one of <hi>June</hi>:</l>
            <l>To Brainford, Colebrooke, Maidenhead and Henly,</l>
            <l>I past (the weather faire, the high wayes cleanely)</l>
            <l>To <hi>Abington.</hi> where foure dayes I remain'd,</l>
            <l>By friends and kinsfolkes kindely entertain'd:</l>
            <l>Thankes to my Nephew <hi>John,</hi> with all the rest,</l>
            <l>To whom that time I was a costly Guest.</l>
            <p>AND now me thinkes a little Profe may be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
amongst friends; I left <hi>Abington</hi> on Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesday
the 27. of June, and (for the case of my purse)
I gave 2s. 6d. for the hire of the Skelliton or Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
of a Beast to carry me ten miles to <hi>Farington;</hi> the
thing I was mounted on was neither Horse, Mine, or
Gelding, it was all spirit, with very little (or no flesh.)
It was none of your pursy foggy Jades, and amongst
Horsemen it might have past for a Light Horse, too
much worke, and too little meate, made him as gaunt
as a Greyhound: Thus (mounted like <hi>Don Quixot</hi>)
I entred <hi>Farington,</hi> but worse Guests then I had been
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115800:3"/>
there since these troubles; for the Kings Party burnt
one part of the Towne, and the Parliaments fired the
rest, so that between them there was a good hansome
Market Towne turned into Ashes and Rubbidge: It
begins to bud and spring out againe, for heere and
there a pritty house peepes up: so that it will in short
time be rebuilt, and Phaenix like (out of it's owne
cinders) be revived and reneued to a more pleasing
and beautifull prospect.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Farington</hi> I footed it foure miles to <hi>Hiworth,</hi>
(a Market Towne) and from thence to <hi>Purton</hi> seaven
miles more, where I lodged, there was nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable
in all that dayes travels; but that in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
a Church at a Village called <hi>Kingston,</hi> (five
miles from <hi>Abington</hi> having no steeple; but the
Church at <hi>Purton</hi> (where I lay all night) had two stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples:
but I was certified that the Minister that had
two steeples, had but one Benefice, and he that had
none, had two, by which meanes the reckoning was
even betwixt them, for what the one had, the other
had not.</p>
            <p>The 28. of <hi>Iune,</hi> I betook me to my feete an house
and halfe before the Sunne could shew his face in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mersetshire,
and for one shilling I hired an old drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard
to guide me eight long miles to the Towne of
<hi>Malmsbury,</hi> where all worthy remembrance was, that
I found an Ancient Towne, an old Castle, and new
Ale; from thence I hired a Horse for 25. seaven miles,
and footed it seaven miles more that day to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous,
renowned, ancient, little pritty City of <hi>Bathe,</hi>
I lodged in the Mayors house: But his Worship was
as ignorant as my selfe, for he being a Baker, had let
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115800:4"/>
halfe his house to a Victualler: so he sold bread
without, and I bought drinke within: The next day
I had notice where I was, wherefore I went to his
stall or shop window, and told him what I was, and
that I was he who came nine yeares agoe from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>
to that City with a small Scullers Boate; Mr.
Mayor was pleased to entertaine me most kindely
(with both his hands in his pocket) and like a man of
few words, forbore to say wellcome to Towne; so
wee parting dryly I left him in his shop, Lord Baron
of the Browne Loaves, and Master of the Rolls (in
that place:) but there is no doubt but the man may
live a faire age, and dye in his bed, if be escape the
unfortunate destiny of <hi>Pharoahs</hi> Baker.</p>
            <p>Friday 29. of <hi>Iune,</hi> I had the luck twice to have
not one dry thread about me, (being wet to the very
skin) and yet my cloathes were as dry as a bone: the
reason is, that I was in the Bathe, and my cloathes out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iune</hi> 30. I travelled fifteene miles to the Towne of
<hi>Wells,</hi> where I stayd but little, and found as little mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of observation, but that these holy, prophane days,
and blessed execrable Times of troublesome tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
have spoyled and defaced one of the goodliest
and magnificent Cathedrall Churches in the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
world: But such pious workes as polution and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busing
of Churches, wee neede not goe amongst
Turkes for proofes; for though <hi>Peters</hi> at <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi>
hath scaped reasonable cleanely, yet <hi>Pauls</hi> in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>
hath layen out of order, in ord<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e a battenning.</p>
            <p>The same day I went foure miles further to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
Towne of <hi>Glastonbury,</hi> there I saw the Ruines
of an Abby, which was one of the statelyest and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115800:4"/>
most sumptuous structures in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Europe:</hi> there
<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>aines yet the ruined walls of a Chappell built in
memory of Joseph of <hi>Arimathea</hi> (who as it is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
by Authentique Historians) did first convert this
Land from Paganisme to Christianity: <hi>And wee have
great neede of another good Ioseph to come amongst us,
to doe as much for us now.</hi> But there is no memoriall
of any place where that good old man was buried:
the Abby was walled more then a mile about, with a
wall of free-stone, as faire as <hi>London</hi> wall; it is very
probable that King <hi>Arthur</hi> (our English Worthy)
was there sepulchred: for there I saw some stones
of Marble, of which I placed the broken pieces toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
I read these words in Latin,
<q>Hic jacet Guineverus Regins, Vxores, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Queene <hi>Guinever</hi> was Wife to the great <hi>Arthur,</hi>
and she being buried there, it is to be conjectured that
his bones were not layd far from her.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Camden,</hi> doth quote the Ancient Historian,
<hi>William of Malmsbury,</hi> to write these words follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing
concerning <hi>Glastenbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That it was the first Land of God in <hi>England,</hi> the
first Land of Saints in <hi>England,</hi> the beginning and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
of all Religion in England, the Tombe of Saints,
the Mother of Saints, the Church founded and built by
the Lords Disciples.</p>
            <p>I saw a branch or slip of the Hawthorne Tree that
did beare. Blossomes every yeare (when all other
Trees were frost-bitten, and seemed dead:) this Tree
onely, on Christmas day, the day of our blessed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours
Birth; this Tree did (in its kinde) snew its joy
in comemoration of the Nativity of the Redeemer
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115800:5"/>
of unkinde mankinde: There are all the Inhabitants
in the Towne will verifie it, and thousands in <hi>England</hi>
and other Countries will affirme that it is no Fable:
The Souldiers being over zealous did cut it downe in
pure devotion; but a Vintner dwelling in the Towne
did save a great ship or branch of it, and placed or set
it in his Garden, and he with others did tell me that
the same doth likewise Bloome on the 25. day of
<hi>December,</hi> yearely; I saw the sayd branch, and it
was ten foote high, greene, and flourishing; I did take
a dead Sprigge from it, wherewith I made two or
three Tobacco stoppers, which I brought to <hi>London</hi>;
my humble thankes to Mr. <hi>Brooke,</hi> with (his good
Sister) for they entertained me freely; so that the
Towne of <hi>Glastonbury</hi> was not one penny the richer
for any expences of mine.</p>
            <p>Monday the second of <hi>Iuly,</hi> I went to <hi>Bridgewater</hi>
ten miles, where all that was worthy of note was,
that neare the Towne, at a stile I had a great disaster;
for a shagge or splinter of the stile tooke hold of my
one and onely breeches, and tore them in that extreme
unmercifull, unmannerly manner, that for shame and
modesties sake I was faine to put them off, and goe
breechlesse into the Towne, where I found a botch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
threepenny Taylor, who did patch me up with
such reparations as made me not ashamed to put my
breeches on againe, and trot five miles further to a
ragged Market Towne called <hi>Neather-St<gap reason="illegible: over-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> where ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame
weary, I tooke up my lodging, at a signe and
no signe, which formerly was the Rose and Crowne;
but Roses are withered, and Crownes are obscured,
as the signe was.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115800:5"/>
Surely that day was a mad, sad, glad, auspicious,
unlucky day to me, worse then an Ominous, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermas,
or a dogged byting dog-day; for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stesse
was out of Towne, mine Host was very suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
drunke, the house most delicately deckt with
exquisite artificiall, and naturall sluttery, the roome
be sprinckled and strewed with the excrements of
Pigs and Children; the wall and sielings were ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
and hanged with rare Spiders Tapistry, or cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>web
Lawne; the smoake was so palpable and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicuous,
that I could scarce see any thing else, and
yet I could scarce see that, it so blinded me with
Rheum a signe of weeping; besides all this, the odorif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous
and contagious perfume of that house was able
to outvie all the Millainers in Christendome or So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mersetshire.</p>
            <p>I being thus embellished, or encompassed with these
most unmatchable varieties; but to comfort me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly,
mine Host swing'd off halfe a pot to me, bad
me be merry, and asked me if I would have any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
Beefe and Carrets to supper; I told him yes,
with all my heart; but I being weary of the house, I
went and sate three houres in the street, where mine
Host often did visit me with most delightfull and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dropicall
non-sense; at last, 7 of the clock was struck,
and I went into the house to see if supper were ready;
but I found small comfort there, for the fire was out,
no Beefe to be boyled, mine Host fast asleep, the
Maid attending the hogs, and my hungry selfe halfe
starv'd with expectation; I awaked mine Host, and
asked him where the Beefe was, he told me that he
had none, and desired me to be contented with egges
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115800:6"/>
fryed with parsly; I prayed him to shew me my cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
which he did; the chamber was sutable to the
rest of the house; there I stayd till neere 9 a clock,
expecting fry'd egges, when mine Host came to me
with an empty answer, there were no egges to be had,
so at the last I purchased a piece of bread and butter,
and to bed, and then began my further torments; for
thinking to take a little rest, I was furiously assualted
by an Ethiopian Army of Fleas, and do verily believe
that I layd so manfully about me that I made more
then 500 <hi>mortuus est</hi>: they were so wel grown that as I
took 'em I gave 'em no quarter, but rub'd 'em between
my finger and my thumbe, and they were so plumpe
&amp; mellow, that they would squash to pieces like yong
boyled pease: But all these troubles I patiently past
by, making no more account of them, then of so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Flea-bytings. For my further delight, my cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-pot
seemed to be lined within with crimson plush,
or shag'd scarlet bayes, it had scaped a scowring time
out of minde, it was fur'd with antiquity, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
it had a monumentall savour; and this pisse-pot
was another of my best contentments.</p>
            <p>At last, wearinesse and watching, began to inforce
sleep upon me, so that (in spight of the fleas teeth) I
began to winke, when suddenly, three children began
to cry, and for an hours space I was kept waking,
which made mee fall to the slaughter againe. The
children being hush'd asleep, the game began afresh
amongst the dogs, for the cry was up, and the baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
Currs took the word one from the other, all the
Towne over; and the dogs had no sooner done, but
the day break appeared, and the hogs began to cry
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115800:6"/>
cut for their breakfast: so I arose, and travelled (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most
sleeping) 10. miles that day; which was to a
Towne called <hi>Dunstar,</hi> where upon a lofty hill stands
a strong Castle, it had then a Garrison in it; I'must
confesse I was free there,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>From nasty Roomes, that never fels broomes,</l>
               <l>From excrements, and all bad sents,</l>
               <l>From childrens bawling, and caterwawling,</l>
               <l>From grunting of hogs, and barking of dogs,</l>
               <l>And from byting of Fleas, there I found ease.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The fourth of <hi>Iuly,</hi> I travelled to Exfourd (so na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med)
because it stands near the head, or spring of the
River <hi>Ex,</hi> which runs downe fom North to South
neere 40 miles to the City of <hi>Exeter,</hi> and to <hi>Exmouth,</hi>
where it delivers it selfe into the Ocean, and from
thence to <hi>Brayfourd,</hi> (another Fourd which runs into
the River of <hi>Ex,</hi> as the people told me; but I finde
it not so in the Map,) that dayes journey was sixteene
miles, a teadious weary way for a crazy, old, lame,
bad, foundered footman, I am sure I found it so; for
when I came to my lodging I had more minde to eate
then to fight, and a better stomack to a bed then a
supper.</p>
            <p>The fifth of <hi>Iuly,</hi> I walked but seven mi'es to
<hi>Barnstable,</hi> a very fine sweete Towne, so cleane and
neate, that in the worse of weather, a man may walke
the streets, and never foule shooe or boote; there I
stayd till the next day noone, being well and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely
entertained by one Mr. <hi>Iohn Downes,</hi> who
gave me Fidlers fare, meate, drinke and money, for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115800:7"/>
which I heartily thanked him: From thence I past
by water five miles to <hi>Aplear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuly</hi> the sixt (being Friday) I paced it ten miles to
a place named <hi>Ferry Crosse,</hi> in the Parish of <hi>Allington,</hi>
and the seven day I turned my back upon <hi>Devonshire,</hi>
having gone that day fifteene miles to the first Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket
Towne in <hi>Cornewall</hi> (on the North-side of the
County) named <hi>Stratten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornewall</hi> is the <hi>Cornucopia,</hi> the compleate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate
Horne of Abundance for high churlish Hills,
and affable courteous people; they are loving to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite
a kindenesse, placable to remit a wrong, and
hardy to resort injuries; the Countrey hath its share
of huge stones, mighty Rocks, noble, free, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
bountifull housekeepers, strong, and stout men,
handsome, beautifull women, and (for any that I
know) there is not one <hi>Cornish</hi> Cuckold to be found
in the whole County: In briefe they are in most
plentifull manner happy in the abundance of right and
left hand blessings.</p>
            <p>It is a wonder that such rugged Mountains do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
such fertility of Corn, and Cattle; for if the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
dayes and times of peace were once settled. <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall</hi>
might compare with any County in <hi>England,</hi> for
quantity of all necessaries needfull, and quallity of
persons.</p>
            <p>The ninth of <hi>Iuly</hi> I left <hi>Stratten</hi> and ambled twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
miles to the Towne of <hi>Camelfourd,</hi> and to a Village
called <hi>Blistland,</hi> and there I was taken for the man I
was not; for they suspected me to be a bringer of
Writs and Processe to serve upon some Gentlemen,
and to bring men into trouble: But with much adoe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115800:7"/>
I scaped a beating, by beating into their beliefes that I
was was no such creature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuly</hi> the tenth, I came to <hi>Bodman,</hi> (a Market Town)
and from thence the same day to a Village called St.
<hi>Enedor,</hi> a part of which Parish is called <hi>Penhall,</hi> there
at a Smiths house was good lodging, better cheare,
and best drinke; the Smith was lame, his Wife was
faire and handsome, where if I could haue acted the
part of <hi>Mars,</hi> there might have been played the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy
of <hi>Vulean</hi> and <hi>Venus:</hi> that dayes travell was
eighteen miles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuly</hi> eleaventh, I progressed to <hi>Trure,</hi> another Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket
Towne, which is the Lord <hi>Roberts</hi> his Land; there
I bought a fish called a <hi>Breame</hi> for three pence, it
would have served foure men; after dinner I went
eight miles further to a Towne called <hi>Redruith,</hi> in all
that dayes travells eighteen miles, I saw nothing
strange to me but a few <hi>Cornish</hi> Dawes (or Choughs)
with red bills, and legs: They saluted me upon the
wing, just in the language of our Jack Dawes about
<hi>London, Ka, Ka.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twelfth of <hi>Iuly,</hi> I came within two miles of
Saint <hi>Michaels Mount,</hi> to an ancient house called by
the name of <hi>Trimineague</hi>: it hath been, and is the birth
place of Worthy Families, of the Noble name of the
<hi>Godolphins</hi>: The right owner and possessour of it
now is <hi>Francis Godolphin,</hi> Esquire, a Gentleman en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed
with Piety, Humanity, Affability and Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
he hath a heart charitable, a minde bountifull, and
a hand liberall; he hath (deservedly) the cordiall
love of all the County, and would have the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of earthly contentments, if once these discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115800:8"/>
times were quieted: Seaven dayes I stayed
with him, in which time he was pleased to send a
Kinsman of his (M. <hi>Anthony Godolpheny)</hi> with me to
see the Mount, which I thus describe. It is about a
mile in compasse at the foote, and it rises 700 peces
very steepe to the top, it is in forme like a great hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock
or Reeke, or much like a Mounteere; on the
top or Piram<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of it, is a fine Church called Saint <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaels,</hi>
the sayd Church is now for no other use but a
well stored Magazine with Ammunition, from
whence (for a relique of remembrance) I brought
halfe a yard of Saint <hi>Michaels Mounts</hi> Monumentall
Match: I went to the top of the Church Tower
seventy steps higher, and in my comming downe I
viewed the Bells (which were five in number) being
faire and handsome, they cannot be rung, because the
crack rope Souldiers have broke all the Bell-ropes,
insomuch as for any more ringing there, the Bells be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ropelesse, the people are hopelesse.</p>
            <p>To speake the truth of this so much talked of
Famous Mount; it is lofty, rocky, innaccessible, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable
not to be taken, or kept, nor worth the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
or keeping: It is a barren stony little wen or
wait, that with men, Amunition, and Victualls is able
to defend it selfe; but if it hath not the Sea and Land
to friend, there is an Enemy called hunger (or famine)
that will conquer Mounts and Mountaines: It can do
no service to the seaward, for the water is so shallow,
that no ship can saile within shot of it, and for Land
service the Towne of <hi>Market Iew,</hi> stands better for
defence: The Mount is an Island, and no Island,
twice in every 24 houres: for when the Sea is up,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115800:8"/>
Boates must be used to go to it, but upon the ebbe,
Troopers may ride to it forty in Ranck: <hi>Market Iew</hi>
is about two flight shoote of it, the Mayor whereof
(one <hi>Mr. William Mabb)</hi> caused me to dine with him,
for which I returne him a few printed thanks.</p>
            <p>In the Mount I saw a craggy rugged seat, of Rocky
Upholstery, which the old fabulous rumour calls St.
<hi>Michaels Chayre</hi>: and a Well I saw there, which twice
in 24 howres is fresh water, and salt water: This
Mount had a Garrison within it, which made the
Country people to grumble without it; yet the soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
are pretty civill: and one Captaine <hi>Geary</hi> did cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teously
regard and drink with me at the Maiors house
at <hi>Market Iew.</hi> From thence I returned to Mr. <hi>Godol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins,</hi>
and he did perswade mee to see the Lands end,
fourteen miles further; for which journey on the 16.
day of July, he did lend me 2. horses, with his kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
to ride with me, where (for his sake) I was wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
by the way, with a good dinner, at one Mr. <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vales</hi>
house, from whence I rode, and went as far as I
could ride, goe, or creepe, for rockes and sea: and
there I saw the Island of <hi>Silly,</hi> with other smaller I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slands,
which are sayd to be 16. or 17. in number. The
mayne Island is held for the Prince, by one Captaine
(or as some say, a Knight) called Sir <hi>Iohn Greenvill</hi>; it
is very strong, with a good safe harbour, and as it is
reported there, hath a good fleet of ships in it: some
doe call it a second <hi>Argiere,</hi> for there cannot a ship or
vessell passe by it, but they doe make out upon them,
whereby they have great riches, with all necessaries:
it was 8. leagues at least from me, insomuch that I
could but onely see it dimly, and 2. ships I perceyved
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115800:9"/>
that lay at road (perdue) to give notice (as I conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red)
of the appearance of any shipping that sayled
within their ken: I did cut my name 4. inches deep in
a small patch of earth amongst the Rockes, at the
Lands end, and I am sure no man can go thither and
set his name or foot, halfe a foot before me.</p>
            <p>The same day I returned to one Mr. <hi>Iones</hi> his house
a mile thence, in the farthest Western Parish of the
County of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> called <hi>Sevin</hi>; there I had good
entertainment all night, by the Gentlemans and his
Wives free welcome, which was out of their owne
curteous disposition; but chiefly for Mr. <hi>Godolphins</hi>
sake, to whom at <hi>Trimiweagow</hi> I returned, on the 17.
of July, where I rested one day: and on the 18. day I
tooke my leave, having received 7. dayes hospitality
in plenty, with many other curtesies in money and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
necessaries which I wanted; besides hee sent his
kinsman with mee to direct mee the way to another
<hi>Francis Godolphin</hi> of <hi>Godolphin</hi> house. That Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
is the chiefe of that noble name; his house a state<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ancient Pallace, and my chear and welcome at din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
most freely bountifull. After dinner hee walked
with me, where (in my way) I saw his Mines of Tin,
and a house where his workemen were refining and
melting of Tin, which is a rich commodity. So at my
taking leave of him, hee put ten shillings in my hand,
which came to me in an acceptable time.</p>
            <p>From thence I jog'd 3. miles further, to a house cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<hi>Clowance</hi> in the Parish of <hi>Crowen,</hi> where dwells
one Mr. <hi>Iohn Sentabin,</hi> he is sonne in Law to the first
<hi>Godolphin</hi> I came to, whose daughter he marryed (a
vertuous and beautifull Gentlewoman) where I tooke
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115800:9"/>
a welcome, a supper and a bed, till the next morning,
being <hi>Iuly</hi> 19. he sent a man with me eight Miles to a
sister of his, named Mrs. <hi>Gertrude,</hi> to her I was so
welcome, that after I thought she had been weary of
me, she would faine have had me to stay two dayes
more, which I (with thankes refusing) she lent me a
Mare (and a man to bring her home againe) which
Mare I roade to a Towne called <hi>Penny com quick,</hi>
within a mile of <hi>Pendennis</hi> Castle, which Castle I
looked on a far off, but I durst not attempt to offer to
go into it, for feares and jealousies might have mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
me for a spy; for at all places of Garison, there is
very strict examinations of persons, and at every
Townes end, in all the sea Townes of part of <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall,
Devonshire, Dorsetshire,</hi> and every Shine, no tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller
could passe without catechizing words: <hi>As
what is your name, whence came you, where dwell you,
whither go you, what is your businesse, and wherefore came
you hither?</hi> Now he that cannot answer these parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
demands punctually, is to be had before Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours,
Captaines, Commanders, Mayors, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stables,
where if a man doe chance to be suffered to
passe freely from them, yet it is a hazard of the losse
of a Travellers liberty by either their unbeliefe or
misp ision, and at the best it is a hinderance to a mans
journey and losse of time.</p>
            <p>These considerations made me doubtfull to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume
to looke into <hi>Pendennis</hi> Castle, or any other
Garrison or place of defence: This Castle is seated
very high, and it stands very defensive for the famous
Haven of <hi>Faymouth,</hi> (one of the best Harbours for
shipping in the world:) it was built by King <hi>Henry</hi> the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115800:10"/>
eight, it is impregnable, and as long as it is well man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
amunitioned, and victualled, it is thought to be
invincible, and theres an end of that poynt.</p>
            <p>That day I past a Ferry called King <hi>Harries</hi> Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage,
(but why it is so named few men knowe) there
I lodged at the Ferry mans house, and the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
being 21 of <hi>Iuly,</hi> I travelled twelve miles to a
fisher Towne called <hi>Mevageasie</hi>; that Towne hath
in it two Tavernes, and six Ale-houses, to every one
of which I went for lodging, and not any one would
harbour me, then I fought for a Constable to helpe
me, but no Constable was to be found; the people
all wondring at me, as if I had been some strange
Beast, or Monster brought out of <hi>Affrica</hi>; at which
most incivill and barbarous useage, I began to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry,
and I perceiving that no body cared for my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
I discreetely went into the house where I first de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
lodging; where the Hostes being very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
to give me the courteous entertainement of <hi>Iack
Drum,</hi> commanded me very kindely to get me out of
dores, for there was no roome for me to lodge in. I
told her that I would honestly pay for what I tooke,
and that if I could not have a bed, yet I was sure of
a house over my head, and that I would not out till
the morning: with that a yong saucy knave told me
that if I would not go out, he would throw me out,
at which words my choller grew high, my indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
hot, and my fury fiery, so that I arose from a bench,
went to my youth, and dared to the combate; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at
the Hostesse (with feare and trembling) desired me
to be quiet, and I should have a bed, at which words
my wrath was appeared, and my ire asswaged.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115800:10"/>
But straite wayes another storme seemed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare;
for an ancient Gentleman came suddenly out
of another Roome (who had heard all the former
friendly passages,) and hee told mee that I should not
lodge there, for though I had sought and not found a
Constable, yet I should know that I had found a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice
of Peace before I sought him; and that he would
see me safely lodged: I was somewhat amazed at his
words, and answered him, Let him doe his pleasure,
for I submitted my selfe to his disposall.</p>
            <p>To which he replyde, That I should go but halfe
a mile with him to his house, which I did, and there
his good Wife and he did entertayne me courteously,
with such fare and lodging, as might have accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated
any Gentleman of more worth and better qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
then one that had been ten times in degree before
me: there I stayd the Saturday and all the Sunday,
where I found more Protestant Religion in 2. dayes,
then I had in 5. yeers before. The Gentlemans name
is Mr. <hi>Iohn Carew,</hi> a Gentleman of noble and ancient
descent, and a worthy Iustice of the Peace in those
parts.</p>
            <p>I was certified, that in that little Town of <hi>Mevage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey,</hi>
there are 44. Fisher Boats, which doe fish for Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards,
that every Boat hath 6. men, and that every 2.
Boats have one net between them: they doe call the
2. Boats a Seine; so there are 22. Seines, and 22. Nets:
every Cornish Bushell is in measure 2. Bushels and a
halfe of our measure at London: every 2. Boates (or
Seine) doe spend 250. Bushels of Salt (Cornish mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure)
to salt Pilchards only; every Seine do use 100.
Hogsheads to pickle the sayd Pilchards in yearly. So
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115800:11"/>
that this one little Towne, doth spend by Gods bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing,
and the meanes of those small fishes, every year,</p>
            <p>Of Salt, 22 times 350 Cornish Bushells, which is
in the number of our Bushells, 14000,350.</p>
            <p>Of Hogsheads, or Caske, 2200.</p>
            <p>Of men for 44 Boats, 6 men for each, 264.</p>
            <p>These men with their Families (being many in
Number) are all maintained by Pilchard catching;
but this is not all, for there are other greater <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ownes
in the County, which doe every one of them use the
same trade of fishing, with more and greater numbers
of men, boats, nets, caske, and much more quantity
of salt; some of the other Townes are S. <hi>Keverne,
Foye, Lee,</hi> with others which I cannot recite.</p>
            <p>This infinite number of Pilchards, being salted and
put up in Caske, are bought a mane by the Spanish,
French, Datch, Italian, and other Merchants, and by
them they are either eaten or fold, and transported to
many other people and Nations: And now I hope I
have filled my Renders bellies with Pilchards, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
cloying or offending their stomack<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; if any one
be queasie, or doe feele a wambling in the Gizzard;
let them call for a cup of S<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck, drinke it, and pay for it.</p>
            <p>The 23 of <hi>Iuly,</hi> I came to <hi>Foye,</hi> and to <hi>Loo</hi> or <hi>Low</hi>)
twenty miles; this Towne of <hi>Loo,</hi> is divided in two
parts, or two Townes together, two Mayors, two
Churches, two Governours, and more then two Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions;
all that I can say of either of the <hi>Looes,</hi> is, that
there was Souldiers and swordmen, strong Beere and
dagger Ale, Land flesh and Sea fish in plenty.</p>
            <p>On the 24. of <hi>Iuly,</hi> I turned my back upon <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall,</hi>
and went from <hi>Loo</hi> to <hi>Plimouth</hi> in <hi>Devonshire,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115800:11"/>
twelve miles: At <hi>Plimouth</hi> I stayd not two houres,
the Towne was too full of suspitions to hold me:
There I saw Colonel <hi>William Leg,</hi> a prisoner in the
Towerhouse, or Guild hall, I spake to him (being on
the ore side of the way in a window, and he on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther)
in a low whispering voice that every one might
heare what we sayd; I wished him health and liberty,
and so left him in thraldome; There was two Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
did make me very welcome for two or three
houres; their names were <hi>Thomas Ratcliffe</hi> and <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am
Weekes,</hi> they gave me smoake and drinke in <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi>
for which I require them in Paper and Inck at
<hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That afternoone I left <hi>Plimouth,</hi> and went foure
miles further, to <hi>Plimpton,</hi> and on the morrow (being
Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his day) I hired a horse forty miles to
<hi>Exeter,</hi> where I was two dayes entertained at mine
owne cost, with some charges that <hi>Burgomasters</hi> and
Bookesellers underwent: I can say little of <hi>Exeter,</hi> but
that it is a faire sweete City, a goodly Cathedrall
Church (not yet quite spoyled or stabled) and it had
large Suburbs, with long streets, and many fine dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
till this mad fire of contention turned all to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines,
rubbidge, cinders, Ashes, and fume.</p>
            <p>Two houres before <hi>Phabus</hi> appeared in our hemis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phere,
I was on footback from <hi>Exeter</hi> to <hi>Honiton,</hi> the
27. of <hi>Iuly,</hi> there I had a nights lodging, and dyet of
such a homely fashion, as I have no occasion to boast
of; there I hired a Horse (which proved to be a blinde
Mare) she had two wens as big as clusters of Grapes
hung over both her eyes, and five or six wens on her
shoulders and flanks, all which beautifull ornaments I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115800:12"/>
could not perceive or see till I had road the beast
foure mile, (for I was mounted before the breake of
day;) but when I saw the comelynesse of the beast,
betweene shame and anger I was almost mad at the
Rogue that owned her; and being neere to a Market
Towne called <hi>Axmister,</hi> I dismounted, and footed
eight miles to <hi>Broad Winsor</hi> in <hi>Dersetshire,</hi> where I
was better horst eight miles further to <hi>Evershot,</hi> and
then I paced on foote eight miles further to the
Towne of <hi>Sherbourne,</hi> that dayes travell was 31 mile.</p>
            <p>The 31 of <hi>Iuly,</hi> I went from <hi>Sherbourne</hi> to <hi>Shafis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi>
and so to <hi>Wilton,</hi> and <hi>Salisbury,</hi> 31 mile: At
<hi>Wilton</hi> I saw the Earle of <hi>Pembrokes</hi> Magnificent and
Sumptuous Building and repairing of such a stately
Fabrick, that for strength, beauty, forme, state, gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing,
painting, gilding, carving, pollishing, embelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing
and adorning: It may be a Pallace for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
King in Christendome: the Springs, and Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponds,
the Garden, the Walkes, the rare Artificiall
Rocks and Fountaines, the Ponds with fish on the
house top, the strange figures and fashions of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
workes, the numerous, innumerable varieties of
fruits and flowers; yea all, and every thing that may
make an earthly Paradice, is there to be seene, felt,
heard, or understood, (which because I understand
not) I shut up all with this, there is inestimable cost,
exquisite Art and Artists, most exceeding good work
and workemen, onely one thing (that is quite out of
fashion almost every where) is used there, which is
good and just payment.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Wilton,</hi> to <hi>Salisbury</hi> two miles, there I slee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
out the later end of the whole Moneth of <hi>Iuly.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115800:12"/>
I had a desire to go into the Church there (one of the
fairest in England) but now the playes be downe,
there was no sights to be seen without money, which
though I could have payd, yet for two Reasons I
would not; the one was because I had oftentimes
seene that Church in former times, when Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
was sayd there, and the second cause why I
would not be guilty of Simony, and with corrupting
Mammon enter or intrude into the House of God.</p>
            <p>The first of <hi>August,</hi> I footed to <hi>Andover,</hi> fifteene
old miles, and eighteene new ones, (of the Posts
late measuring:) The next day to <hi>Merrell Greene,</hi> 24
miles, the third day to <hi>Stanes,</hi> eighteene miles, and
the fourth of August fifteene miles to <hi>London</hi>: My
journey being in all 546 miles, which I went and
came in six Weekes, and lay still and rested twelve
dayes in severall places on Weeke dayes, besides six
Sundayes: But all this was nothing to me, being a
youth of threescore and ten, with a lame leg and a
halfe, and there is an end of the story.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Like to the stone of <hi>Sisiphus.</hi> I roule</l>
               <l>From place to place, through weather faire and foule,</l>
               <l>And yet I every day must wander still</l>
               <l>To vent my Bookes, and gather friends good will;</l>
               <l>I must confesse this worke is frivalowse,</l>
               <l>And he that (for it) daigues to give a lowse,</l>
               <l>Doth give as much for't as 'tis worth, I know;</l>
               <l>Yet meerly merily <hi>I</hi> this jaunt did goe</l>
               <l>In imitation of a mighty King.</l>
               <l>Whose warlike acts, good fellowes often sing,</l>
               <l>The King of France and twenty thousand men,</l>
               <l>Went up the Hill, and so came downe agen.</l>
               <l>So I this travell past, with cost and paine,</l>
               <l>And (as I wisely went) came home againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
