<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Character of His Royal Highness, William Henry, Prince of Orange</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-11">2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64421</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2017A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9704</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13766279</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13766279</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A64421)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 852:41 or 2456:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Character of His Royal Highness, William Henry, Prince of Orange</title>
                  <author>Terry, Edward, 1590-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randall Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Terry. Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>"With allowance."</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 852:41 identified as Wing T779 (number cancelled).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-05</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101723:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101723:1"/>
            <p>THE
CHARACTER
OF HIS
ROYAL HIGHNESS
WILLIAM HENRY
PRINCE
OF
ORANGE.</p>
            <p>With Allowance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
Printed for <hi>Randall Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101723:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101723:2"/>
            <head>THE
CHARACTER
Of His ROYAL HIGHNESS
W. H. Prince of Orange.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN the Almighty designs a Great HERO to fight his
Battels, and deliver his People from the Fury and Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of their Enemies, he inspires them with Courage, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
Constancy, and Magnanimity; and so appears to
be <hi>William Henry</hi> Prince of <hi>ORANGE,</hi> if we do but
consider the Wonderful and Glorious Actions he hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
both in Peace and War, and so affable, and of
such a sweet Temper, that it may seem a doubt whether
he hath made greater Conquests over his Enemies by his
Sword, than by the Charming Dispositions of his Mind;
as if he had not only the Meekness of <hi>Moses,</hi> but the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
and Valiancy of <hi>Joshua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by his Birth he seems to be destined by Heaven to be the Saviour of his
Country, and of the Protestant Religion; for his Grandfather, Unkle, and
Father, were so many Bulwarks against the Fury and Tyranny of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi>
and other sworn Enemies of their Country and Religion, which they bravely defended
all their days, against Implacable Foes, to their Confusion, their Countries Peace and
Safety, and to their own Everlasting Honour and Renown.</p>
            <p>For <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Nassau,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> born in the Year 1533. as soon as he
came to Man's Estate (finding his Country, and Religion, and his own Life, through
the Cruelty of <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> in eminent Danger, the Counts of <hi>Egmont</hi> and <hi>Horn,</hi>
and Eighteen other Lords and Gentlemen, and 18000 of meaner Rank executed on
several Scaffolds; and the utter Destruction of his Religion threatned by the <hi>Spanish</hi>
Inquisition) generously took up Arms in Defence of his Country and Religion; and
having drawn several of the States-General into an Association mutually to stand by
one another; after having defeated the Bloody Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> in several Battels, bafled
<hi>Requesenes,</hi> and <hi>Don Iohn</hi> of <hi>Austria,</hi> Governors of the <hi>Spanish Netherlands</hi> for King
<hi>Philip;</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> being no way able to withstand his Victorious Sword in the
Field, caused him Treacherously and Barbarously to be Assassinated by one named <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thazar
Guerard,</hi> a <hi>Burgundian.</hi> And thus fell the Great <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Nassau</hi> a Sacrifice
for his Religion and Country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philip William</hi> his Son, being bred up by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the Catholick Religion,
dyed without any Great Actions performed by him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101723:3"/>
               <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Nassau,</hi> second Son of <hi>William,</hi> valiantly defended his Country for Forty
Years, Won Forty Cities, and <hi>Breda</hi> by a Stratagem never parallel'd by the greatest
Captains; he obtain'd several Signal Victories, but especially the Famous Battel of
<hi>Newport,</hi> and defended <hi>Ostend</hi> Three Years, beleaguer'd by the Marquess <hi>Spinola</hi> with
a Numerous Army; and Dyed in the Year 1625, loaden with Honourable Scars, but
more with Renown and Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Frederick,</hi> Third Son of <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> was not only as couragious,
but more fortunate than the rest; he took <hi>Oldersell, Groll, Bois le Due, Wessell, Mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stricht,
Rhinberg, Skink,</hi> and afterwards the Castle and City of <hi>Breda</hi> in Four Months,
which cost <hi>Spinola</hi> Twelve to master; Won Three Naval Battels, in one of which he
took 20000000 l. from the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> in another, destroyed 40 of their Ships of
War; and thus having utterly broken the Strength of <hi>Spain,</hi> and forced that Proud
Monarch to Renounce his Claim to their Territories, he may be justly said to be the
Founder of the Most Potent Republick in the World; and under the Tablet of this
Heroick Prince, and his Royal Family, deservedly might have been these Verses,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Illustris Origo est</l>
               <l>Principis Augusti, Qualis erit Soboles?</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Resp.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Qualis erit? qualem depinxit Homerus Achillem.</l>
               <l>Marti, &amp; Consilio Nestora, Talis erit.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>And now let us see whether <hi>William Henry</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> by this present Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter
will appear to be such; for I design not the History of his Life, but a short view
of those Glorious Actions he hath performed, by which the whole Word will better
know him, than those that have stared on his wonderful Proportion and Features
e're since his Cradle.</p>
            <p>He is Son to <hi>Henry Frederick</hi> of <hi>Nassau,</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> Eldest Daughter of
<hi>Charles</hi> the First, King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and seems to have ingrossed all the Virtues
and Glories of his Ancestors, the Courage and solid Judgment of his Grandfather <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam;</hi>
the Fortitude and Policy of his Unckle <hi>Maurice;</hi> the Prudence, Fortunate Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess
and Magnanimity of his Father <hi>Henry Frederick,</hi> and with these Virtues he raised
the Republick his Ancestors had saved from Destruction, to a Grandure able to cope with
the greatest Monarchs upon Earth.</p>
            <p>In his Minority the <hi>De Witts,</hi> who had Treacherously sold their Country to the
<hi>French,</hi> with a Devilish Policy undermined the Royal Infant, and his weak Party; they
ingratefully took from him all his Rights, Jurisdictions and Priviledges which his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors
had purchased with the loss of their dearest Blood and Lives, and thereby
Peace, Freedom, and Grandure, for the <hi>Vnited States</hi> of the <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he was 22 Years of Age, the effect of the <hi>De Witts</hi> Treachery began to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,
for the <hi>French</hi> King invading the <hi>Netherlands</hi> with a Powerful Army, like a swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
Ocean when it overtops its Banks overturns all, the <hi>De Witts</hi> had put into the
Garisons Governours who were at their own Devotion, and mann'd them with raw
Soldiers and Burghers; so that through the Cowardise of the one, and Treachery of
the other, the <hi>French</hi> no sooner appear'd at their Gates, but they basely surrendred in
a Day, Fortifications that might have defended themselves from the whole Power of
<hi>France,</hi> many Months.</p>
            <p>This awakened the <hi>Dutch</hi> out of their Lethargy, and the People Sacrificing <hi>Cornelius</hi>
and <hi>John De Witt</hi> to their Fury, he was at <hi>Dort,</hi> and afterwards by the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
Zealand,</hi> and <hi>West Frizeland,</hi> declared <hi>Stadtholder,</hi> and <hi>Captain,</hi> and <hi>Admiral</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101723:3"/>
General of the <hi>Vnited Provinces,</hi> with all the Rights, Jurisdictions, and Priviledges
his Ancestors had enjoyed.</p>
            <p>And now our Young <hi>HERO</hi> taking Command of the Army, he first valiantly
repulses the <hi>French</hi> from the Walls of <hi>Ardenburg,</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Munster</hi> from <hi>Groning,</hi>
takes <hi>Coeverden</hi> in a Day, with the loss of only 60 Men, which cost the Bishop of
<hi>Munster</hi> much Time and Blood to master; as also <hi>Naerden, Bon, Brevill, Lechnich,
Woerden, Creveceur, Hardwick, Vtrecht, Bommell, Campen, Ellburgh, Hatten, Steen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,
Meppel, Northom, Zutphen, Tiel, Arnheim, Dinant, Deventer,</hi> and <hi>Graves,</hi> with
a far greater Celerity than they were taken by the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Munsterians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now he is to engage one of the most Renowned Captains in the World; and
indeed whoever reads the Life of the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> will find it full fraught with
Wonders of Courage, Conduct and Policy: The Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> lay encamped be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind
the River <hi>Pieton,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> with his own Forces, the <hi>Germans</hi> and
<hi>Spaniards</hi> his Allies, endeavour by several Stratagems and Provocations to draw him
to a Battel; but that wary General made their Attempts vain; whereupon the Prince
of <hi>ORANGE</hi> directs his March to <hi>Binch,</hi> but being to pass through very difficult
Ways and Lanes, the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> knowing his Advantage, suffers the Van-Guard,
and some part of the main Body to pass by him, and then silently drawing out his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
and putting them into Battalia, furiously falls upon the Prince of <hi>Vaudemont,</hi>
who was to secure the Rear-guard with 4000 Horse; <hi>Vaudemont</hi> sends to the Prince
of <hi>ORANGE</hi> for Two Battalions of Infantry, (the Place where he engaged being
not so proper for Horse) and has Three sent him, and withall the Troops that lay on
the other side of the River that runs by <hi>Seneff,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> could not force them from
their Post, but passing the River a little higher, and joining all their Forces, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates
wanting Elbow-Room, and the <hi>French</hi> falling upon them from all Parts, the
Confederates were inforced to retire, having lost several Principal Officers: Then the
Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> pushing on his advantage, fell on vigorously on the Horse, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by the Prince of <hi>Vaudemont</hi> and put them to the Rout, and afterwards on the
Duke <hi>de Villa Hermosa</hi> who commanded 16 Battalions of Infantry, who valiantly
withstood their Charge, but at last was forced to a disorderly Retreat, and so put those
that came to his Assistance into much Confusion, whereby the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
Master of the Baggage of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Army.</p>
            <p>Things being in this ill Posture, it was high time for the Young <hi>Belgick</hi> Lyon to rouze
his Courage; he embattel'd the <hi>Imperialists</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the Left Wing, and his own
men in the Right, in such Excellent Order, that being joined by General <hi>Souches,</hi> who
was advanced some hours March before with the Van-Guard, that altho the <hi>French</hi>
were never observed to Fight before with such obstinate Resolution, yet he put a Check
to the Progress of their Victory: The Valourous Prince of <hi>ORANGE</hi> ran with his
Sword in his Hand, and stopt the flight of his Fugitives, then threw himself into the
midst of his Enemies; so that his Army being animated by so Glorious an Example,
Fought with incredible Bravery.</p>
            <p>Neither had the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> any better Success in his Attacking the main Body, or
the Right Wing of the Confederates, altho he charged them with his <hi>Curiasseers,</hi> and
the Troops of Horse of the <hi>French</hi> King's Guards; for the Prince of <hi>ORANGE</hi>
with a Prodigy of Valour maintain'd the Fight, until Nights Black Mantle shrouded
the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> who under that Covert made a disorderly Retreat with his Army,
and left the Field of Battel, the certain Sign of Victory, to the Conquering Prince of
<hi>ORANGE,</hi> who snatch'd the Wreath of Bays that <hi>Conde</hi> had won at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of the Battel from his Brows, and placed it on his own.</p>
            <p>I shall give you but one Instance more of his Martial Prowess, and that is the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
he performed against the Duke of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> a Renowned and Experienced
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101723:4"/>
Captain, at the Famous Battel of <hi>Mons; Luxemburg</hi> was so advantagiously posted, and
slighted the Prince's Design of Attacking him so much, that he was pleased to say, <hi>He would
not rise from his Dinner for the Attempts of the rash Boy;</hi> but the Prince Charged him
with such a Manly Courage and Fury, through all the Storms of Shot and Fire, altho
he was to March up a Hill before he could reach him, and afterwards through deep
and difficult Lanes and Ways, and thick Woods, that he not only made him lose his
Dinner, but forced him to seek a new Lodging, for he drove him out of his Camp, and
possest himself of it, his Tents and Baggage.</p>
            <p>And thus I have given you a short view of the Martial Actions of this Heroick
Prince; and will now only Instance a few of his Politicks relating to the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>There have been many Illustrious Men carried on by the Heat of Youthful Courage,
whom Success hath Crowned with Victory, that have been esteemed great Conquerors;
but all History cannot produce a Parallel of a Person of the Age of this Young Prince,
to have been so great a States-man, and so well skilled in the Politicks of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>When he was declared <hi>Stadtholder</hi> at the Age of about 22 Years, he found the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
quite out of Frame, the Laws prevaricated or overturned, and such a Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
in Cities and Corporations, as we lately had here in <hi>England;</hi> all the Just, Grave,
Worthy Magistrates turned out, and only such put into their Places (tho never so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deserving)
as favoured the Faction of the <hi>De Witts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the City of <hi>Dort</hi> first led the way, and made him their <hi>Stadtholder,</hi> he not
only setled that City, but <hi>West-Friezeland,</hi> and the City of <hi>Middleburg,</hi> which were
all in Uproar and Confusion; he no sooner appear'd amongst them, but their Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences
and Mutinies vanished; the Fame of his Success against their Enemies abroad,
and the Sweetness and Moderation which he exprest at home, gained him so much Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence,
that their Arms fell out of their Hands, the Ancient Magistrates were resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
and all those States and Cities to their former Peace and Tranquility.</p>
            <p>He never had the least Relax from his Martial Employments, but he applied himself
in that spare time in Reformation of the Government; he caused New Elections to
be made of Persons to officiate in the College of Counsellors Elect; and a New Choice
to represent the Body of the Nobility; and placed Men of Integrity and Ability to be
of the Magistracy and Councils of the several Cities; he drew up such Orders for
their well-Government for the future, which he was so far from imposing on them, that
after they had debated them in their several Assemblies, they not only Joyfully appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
of them, but in requital setled the Offices of Governour-General, Captain and
Admiral General on him and his Male Issue.</p>
            <p>Thus this Valorous and Prudent Prince redeemed his Country and Religion from the
slavery of the Potent <hi>French</hi> King, and resetled the Government upon its Ancient <hi>Basis,</hi>
which had been in a horrid Confusion, through the Treachery of the <hi>De Witts,</hi> and the
Disorders which the <hi>French</hi> Invasion had contaminated it withal; and in the Year 1678
that Victorious <hi>French</hi> Monarch was forced, and did conclude a Peace with the Prince
of <hi>ORANGE,</hi> much to his Glory and Renown, and as much to the Advantage of
the States of the <hi>Vnited Provinces;</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King quitting by this Peace, all that he
had taken from them. But as if he were designed by Heaven, not only to be the
Saviour of his own Country and Religion, but the Champion of the Lord of Hosts,
to deliver his true Church from the Fury, Treachery, and Tyranny of its Enemies;
the Church of <hi>England</hi> being surrounded with Dangers, that threatned her on every
side, those Laws that were made and accounted as the Bulwarks against Popery, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
all made invalid. The Judges and Chief Ministers of State then in Office cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101723:4"/>
and such as sought her Ruin. The King himself, tho of Excellent
Qualities, yet poysoned by Jesuits Powder, and other corrupted Officers, by whom
he was misled to his great Misfortune. The Church of <hi>England</hi> being in this
Deplorable Condition, sending up her Prayers to Heaven for a <hi>Moses</hi> to deliver
her, and withal imploring the aid, by her Clergy, Nobility, and Gentry, of our
<hi>William Henry</hi> Prince of <hi>ORANGE,</hi> he pitying her Tears, and to approve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
the only Champion for the Protestant Religion, takes the Almighty's Cause in
hand, and with an inconsiderable Force to what was raised against him, Lands in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
and finds the effects of his Virtues more powerful than his Sword; for the Fame
of his Valour and Conduct, Prudence, Justice and Moderation, being his forerunners,
the Gates of all Cities and Strong-holds opened to him: And not only so, but For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tresses
more obstinate and difficult to Conquer; I mean the hearts of the Clergy, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility
and Gentry of the whole Kingdom: And it is much a Nobler Conquest over
the Hearts, than the Bodies of Men. And he, to shew that his Zeal in this Expedition
was only for the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion, spurs on the Convention of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
Assembled, and leaves it wholly to them to settle the Government, and their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
upon such a firm Basis, that it may hereafter outbrave all the Treachery and
Fury of <hi>Rome;</hi> and that the Laws and Properties of the Subject may be secured from
Tyranny and Oppression for the future.</p>
            <p>I shall now come to a Corallary upon the whole: As to his Phisiognomy, it is Martial;
but tho' there is a fierceness in his Eyes, yet withal a Charming Sweetness, and a little
Melancholly Air in his Countenance, in which you may read Temperance and Mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;
His Courage has been such in his green years, that he opposed the <hi>French</hi> King
in Person, the great <hi>Conde, Turene, Luxemburgh,</hi> and several other great Generals;
and not only measured his Sword with them, but gained much more Honour upon
them, than they did on him. His Patience and Temperance was so great, that he
endured all the indignities the <hi>De Witts</hi> and States-General put upon him in his mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
without a murmur: His Prudence and Policy in Civil Government is without
parallel, in the Setling the Government and Religion of his Country, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
all the confusions the <hi>De Witts,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Invasion had brought it into, on
the old Foundation: And not only so, but improved its Glory to such a pitch, through
his Conduct, that now the States-General of the United Provinces are the most po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
in the World. His Constancy appears, that he was not at all shaken or dejected
at the stupendious devastation the <hi>French</hi> King made, when he first like a Torrent
overwhelmed his Country; much less at the vast advantages that great General the
Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> obtained over him at the beginning of the Battel of <hi>Seneff;</hi> but with
a Constancy and Resolution worthy himself, having born the brunt of their fury,
triumph'd over it, and all their Policies. He talks not much, but very well; and of
great Judgment to discern the best advice given, whether at a Council of War, or a
Debate at the Convention of the States General: Magnificent in his Entertainments,
without prodigality. Women and Wine, the two great Seducers of Mankind, never
could intice him to the least frailty. Thus the Charms of his Valour, Justice, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance,
and the Sweetness of his Disposition makes him Triumph, not only in Battel,
but by a more powerful Conquest, over the hearts of his Opponents, as the Nobility
and Gentry of <hi>England</hi> must acknowledg: So that He may more justly, than <hi>Titus
Vespatiam,</hi> claim the stile of</p>
            <closer>Deliciae humani Generis.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
