<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rights of primogeniture, or, The excellency of royall authority in a sermon preached before His Majesty in the Isle of Wight, upon the anniversary of his birth-day / by James, L. Bishop of Armagh and Primate of Ireland.</title>
            <author>Ussher, James, 1581-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing U221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24650</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08259481</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08259481</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41260</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A64681)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41260)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1242:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rights of primogeniture, or, The excellency of royall authority in a sermon preached before His Majesty in the Isle of Wight, upon the anniversary of his birth-day / by James, L. Bishop of Armagh and Primate of Ireland.</title>
                  <author>Ussher, James, 1581-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Lowdes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Primogeniture --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41260:1"/>
            <p>THE
Rights of Primogeniture:
OR,
THE EXCELLENCY
OF
ROYALL AUTHORITY
IN
A SERMON Preached before His MAJESTY
in the Isle of <hi>Wight,</hi> upon the Anniversary
of His BIRTH-DAY.</p>
            <p>By the R. R. Father in God, JAMES, L. Bishop of <hi>Armagh,</hi>
and Primate of IRELAND.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>—<hi>Nunquam libertas gratior extat</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quam sub Rege pio</hi>—</l>
            </lg>
            <p>LONDON,
Printed for R. LOWNDES, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41260:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41260:2"/>
            <head>THE RIGHTS OF
PRIMOGENITURE, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>GEN. 49. 3.</bibl>
               <q>Reuben, thou art my first borne, my might,
and the beginning of my strength.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is the beginning of <hi>Jacobs</hi> blessing his
Children, which was an act (and a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall
act) of his Faith, as it is <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 20.</p>
            <p>And in this we may see a difference
betwixt the death of <hi>Jacob</hi> and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.
<hi>Abraham, Isaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> were famous in their
Generations: God is not ashamed to be called <hi>their
God.</hi> And if we consider their lives and deaths, we
shall find this difference. <hi>Abraham</hi> in his life was most
glorious, his Faith famous, witnesse his offering his
onely son to God with that strength of Faith, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41260:3"/>
he verily beleeved that <hi>in</hi> Jacob <hi>all the Nations
of the Earth should be blessed,</hi> yet was his Faith so strong
as to be content to offer him up, being perswaded that
God was able to raise him from the dead.</p>
            <p>Now although his life was thus glorious, when ye
come to his death, This is all that is said of him: <hi>Then
Abraham gave up the ghost, and died in a good old age,
and was gathered unto his Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Commonly great things are expected from holy
men at their death, yet ye see <hi>Abraham</hi> was but ordinary
in his death.</p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>Isaac's</hi> life, the Scripture saith but
little, and the selfe same words are used of him at his
death, as was at the death of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jacob</hi> as ordinary in his life as ye shall meet withall;
But his death was a Prophecy of Christ's comming
into the World. He begins with <hi>Reuben,</hi> to whom
(though he had no mind at all to blesse him) he gives his
due; shewes him that the right of Primogeniture belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
unto him, if he had not forfeited it: <hi>Thou art my first
borne, my might, &amp; the beginning of my strength.</hi> For this
reason God commands, that the first borne should have
a double portion. And <hi>so Reuben</hi> should have received,
but that he forfeited it; <hi>Therefore,</hi> saith he, <hi>because thou
art unstable as Water, &amp;c. thy excellency is departed from
thee:</hi> and so he gave it to <hi>Joseph.</hi> In repeating the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogie
of <hi>Jacobs</hi> sonnes, 1 <hi>Chron. 5. 1, 2. Now</hi> (saith the
Text) <hi>the sons of</hi> Reuben <hi>the first borne of Israel,</hi> (for he
was the first borne) but forasmuch, as he defiled his
Fathers bed, his Birth-right was given unto the sons of
<hi>Joseph,</hi> the son of <hi>Israel,</hi> and the Genealogie is not to be
reckoned after the Birth-right, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41260:3"/>
Ye see, though he had forfeited his Birth-right, he
could not forfeit his Primogeniture, but there was an
escheate thereof to <hi>Joseph.</hi> All the rest had a single
Tribe, set out to them, but <hi>Joseph</hi> had two Tribes, and
so the right that should have gone to <hi>Reuben</hi> fell to <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph.</hi>
Besides this, had not <hi>Reuben</hi> forfeited his Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,
he should have had more then this double por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
for there was a promise made, that <hi>Kings should
proceed from him.</hi> Now as in the former <hi>Joseph</hi> suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
him, so in this of Eminency and Power, it fell
to <hi>Judah,</hi> for so it followes in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 5. before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
            <p>Now to Explicate this.</p>
            <p>The Regall power which comes by discent is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed
by a double Eminency. <hi>The excellency of Dignity,</hi>
and <hi>the excellency of Power.</hi> By Dignity you understand,
<hi>all outward glory;</hi> by <hi>Power, all Dominion,</hi> and these are
the two branches of Majesty.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Greekes</hi> do therefore expresse it in the abstract.
In respect of <hi>Dignity,</hi> the Supreame Magistrate is called
<hi>Glory,</hi> In respect of <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> he is called <hi>Lordship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King is not only <hi>Glorious,</hi> but <hi>Glory;</hi> Not only
<hi>Powerfull,</hi> but <hi>Power. Let every soule be subject to the
higher powers.</hi> Both are joyned in the Epistle to <hi>Jude,</hi>
and in the 8. <hi>Verse,</hi> there is a wicked sort described, that
<hi>despise dominion, and speake evill of Dignities.</hi> They
despise Dominion that make no conscience <hi>to blaspheme
the foot-steps of the Lords Anointed.</hi> These men dare
do what <hi>Michael</hi> durst not doe, <hi>Verse</hi> 9. He durst not
bring against the Devill a <hi>railing accusation,</hi> but these
dare <hi>speake evill of Dignities.</hi> And what is their Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure?
<hi>Verse 13. To whom is reserved the blacknesse of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41260:4"/>
darknesse for ever.</hi> We use to say, that those that have
Gods Tokens upon them are past hopes of like. Here ye
may plainly see Gods Tokens upon these men, <hi>they are
reserved to Everlasting Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, let us now come to unfold these two parts of
Majesty, <hi>Dignity,</hi> and <hi>Dominion.</hi> The excellency of
<hi>Dignity,</hi> and the excellency of <hi>Power</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Dignity,</hi> is meant, the outward Pompe and Glory
annexed to the Scepter. For, it is Gods ordinance that
there should be an extraordinary splendour in Majesty
more then in any other. And therefore the Scripture
doth often describe the Courts of Princes, their Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour
at home, and in their Progresse abroad, with dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
and state. <hi>Acts</hi> 25. 23. When King <hi>Agrippa</hi>
and <hi>Bernice</hi> went to heare <hi>Paul,</hi> the Text saith, <hi>They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved
with great Pompe.</hi> It was a thing beseemed the
Regall power so to doe. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 10. 2. The Queen of
<hi>Sheba</hi> came to <hi>Jerusalem</hi> to see <hi>Solomen</hi> with a great
Traine: but she came to a farre greater Court then her
owne. And this State in Courts is not Pride, but it is a
thing allowed by Gods ordinance, as Christ saith, <hi>Those
that weare soft rayment are in Kings Courts.</hi> And spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
of the Lillies of the Field, <hi>I say to you</hi> (saith he) <hi>that
Solomon in all his Glory was not like one of these.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you see a man (though in Russet) attended upon by
others in rich Clothes, you will conclude that man
(though in Russet) to be some great Personage. The
Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> was astonished at what she saw in <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon's</hi>
Court; for, when she beheld the Meat of his
Table (he must not be served as other men) the sitting
of his Servants, the attendance of his Ministers, and his
Cup-bearer, &amp;c. the Text saith, <hi>There was no more
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41260:4"/>
spirit in her.</hi> She was (as a man may say) besides her
self to see this State. And so stately it was, that <hi>Psal.</hi> 45.
it is brought in as an Allegoricall description of the
Glory of Christ and his Church. I need not go to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
Princes to prove this, the Scripture doth suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
evidence it. In <hi>Ester</hi> 1. there is a description of
<hi>Ahasuerus</hi> and his Feast, the like to which you will
not read of in any other Story, it lasted one hundred and
fourscore daies, which was a full half yeare, and with the
greatest Glory that could be, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. When he shewed
the riches of his glorious Kingdome, and the honour of
his excellent Majesty, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So then, this is the first part of Majesty, namely, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
Splendour, which is lawfull and requisite to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
the dignity of a Prince. And as the Prince ought
to have this in his owne Person, and his Attendants, so
all Dignity and Glory rests in him as in the Fountaine,
and all Titles of Dignity are in him also. Even as ye
see in the Firmament, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>There is one Glory of the
Sunne, another of the Moone, and one Starre excelleth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Common-wealth, there are some Knights, some
Lords, some Earles, &amp;c. but all these differences come
from one Sun, one Head, <hi>the Prince.</hi> There is no light
in the Moone but what is derived from the Sunne, even
here is borrowed, the Starres light is borrowed also,
and when the Sonne appeares, they cease to shine. The
Starres at this time shine as much as at Midnight, but
that the Light of the Sunne doth darken them. Even so
in the presence of Majesty, those other Excellent Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities
doe not shine at all.</p>
            <p>2. To come to the Eminency of <hi>Power;</hi> For a King
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41260:5"/>
to have great State and to have no Power, he were then
but a poore King.</p>
            <p>A Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> is served in as Great State as can be,
but he hath no Power at all.</p>
            <p>There is a Subordination of Power in all Government,
which because it cannot go <hi>ad infinitum,</hi> it must needs
rest somewhere, and that is in the King. <hi>Let every Soule
be subject to the Higher powers.</hi> And the Apostle in
1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. distinguisheth, <hi>Whether it be to the King,
as Supreme, or unto Governours, as unto them that are
sent by God, for the punishment of evill doers,</hi> &amp;c. and he
adds, <hi>that by so doing, the Ignorance of foolish men may be
put to silence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any Professour of Religion doe Rebell against the
King, this is a scandall to Religion.</p>
            <p>Now the Apostle did foresee that such there would
be, and therefore Commands that they be put in mind
to be Subject, &amp;c. But if any that professe Religion
doe Rebell (as I said before) it is the fault of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessour,
and not of the Profession; for the Church of
<hi>England</hi> doth teach the Contrary.</p>
            <p>But when men shall not onely practice, but teach Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion,
(for <hi>by their fruits ye shal know them</hi>) this amounts
to a very high Crime indeed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The King</hi> (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> saith) <hi>hath the Excellency of
Power, as sent by God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, what need I say any more? We all sweare that
<hi>the King is the onely Supreame Governour in his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</hi>
A man would think, that that word <hi>onely</hi> might
be spared, since nothing can be above a Supream, but it
is put there by way of <hi>Eminency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There can be no Dominion in the World, unlesse
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41260:5"/>
there be an Eminency of power in some one or other.
If a man be wronged in any Court, he may lawfully
appeale higher, but then, Appeales must not be Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite,
there must be a supremacy of power somewhere to
rest in.</p>
            <p>The Philosopher saith, it must be either in one, or in
all. Where the Eminency of power is in one, it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
a Monarchy. The King must onely have the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
power, for if any be joyned with him, then it is
no Monarchy.</p>
            <p>If the Power be in a certaine number, it is called an
<hi>Aristocracy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Power be in all, a <hi>Democracy;</hi> and all Power
then is derived from the Body of the People, and where
you say so, you destroy the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and erect a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocracy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> hath (as I said before) a marvei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
great State, and yet the State of <hi>Venice</hi> is no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,
because the Supremacy of power is not in him.
He cannot receive a Letter, nor make an Edict without
the States allowance; Nay, he may be called to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt
by them.</p>
            <p>I read in <hi>Josephus</hi> that <hi>Herod</hi> having offended <hi>Cleopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra,</hi>
she be sought <hi>Antony</hi> (who did not use to deny her
any thing) to call him to accompt; but <hi>Antony</hi> refused
so to doe, <hi>Then,</hi> saith he, <hi>He will be no King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Look upon the Common-wealth of <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> They
had Kings lineally descended from the race of <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les;</hi>
but shall we say they had Regall power? nothing
lesse, because there were <hi>Ephori</hi> in that State, A certaine
power in the People to call their Kings to accompt: the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41260:6"/>
Supremacy of power there was not in the Prince.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Switzerland,</hi> there is a <hi>Democracy,</hi> and the onely
Democraticall Government I know of. They have
their Magistrates that governe the people. And yet
though there be many Magistrates that governe in those
Cantons, this is no <hi>Aristocracy,</hi> for at the Magistrates
in <hi>Switzerland</hi> are accomptable to the people, and all
their power is limited by them. The <hi>Supremacy of
power</hi> is in the people there, and thence it comes to be a
<hi>Democracy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eminency of Power. In the word of a King there is
Power,</hi> saith the Preacher, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 8. 4. It was wont to
be so, and by the word of God you see it ought to be so.
But I will not enlarge upon this. It may be some Ears
will not indure sound Doctrine.</p>
            <p>But the King we see must be acknowledged to be
Supreame, and no Superior to the King.</p>
            <p>Farre be it from me (being in Gods place) to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
any man, I thanke God I fear no flesh, but do deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
the truth.</p>
            <p>Having now spoken of the two branches of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty,
<hi>Dignity,</hi> and <hi>Power.</hi> We shall speake of a Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
that descends to Kings. It should have been <hi>Reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lien's</hi>
right here, if God had not taken it from him for a
fault.</p>
            <p>This day is the Birth-day of our Soveraigne Lord.
Birth-dayes of Kings have been usually celebrated with
great solemnity in former times. <hi>Herod's</hi> Birth-day
was celebrated many years after his death: and the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodians</hi>
(for the many mighty workes that <hi>Herod</hi> did)
bleeeved him to be the Messiah.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:41260:6"/>
It pleaseth God that this day begins the 49. year
of His life, and let me call it the year of Jubile to His
Majestie.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jewes</hi> had a custome that in the 49. year of any
mans life, he should be at liberty, what ever his suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings
were before. It must be the desire and prayer of
every loyall heart, that the King may have a Jubile in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.
This is that which Loyalty bids us doe.</p>
            <p>I will not stand too much upon this particular.
But this I will say, O that we knew our happinesse; To
have a King that is the son of Nobles! A King that is
not a Child. A King that is at full age to Governe, by
Wisdome, and Prudence. And truely as God gives
us this blessing, so he expects we should acknowledge it
thankefully. <hi>Eccles. 10, 16. Woe be to thee O Land</hi> (saith
the Preacher) <hi>when thy King is a Child:</hi> And <hi>Blessed art
thou O Land when thy King is the son of Nobles:</hi> that
hath his breeding answerable.</p>
            <p>To have him, when his experience hoth riverted in
him sound judgement, and ability to governe. The
Lord threatned <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> in <hi>Esay 3. 4. I will give Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
to be their Princes, and Babes shall rule over them.</hi>
Those that would have their owne wils, could (I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
you) be content that the youngest should Raigne.</p>
            <p>To have a base man exalted, is one of the things
that the Earth cannot bear. But some body must have
the Government, it doth not belong to all. You see
here is by Birth, one that hath a right unto it.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Jehosaphat</hi> distributed his Estate, 2 <hi>Chron,</hi> 21.
he gave gifts to his other sons, but the Kingdome unto
<hi>Jehoram,</hi> because he was his First-borne. A Kingdome
is not a thing dividable.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41260:7"/>
So the King of <hi>Edom, 2 King.</hi> 3. 27. though he tooke
and offered his Eldest Sonne (that should have reigned
in his stead) as an offering: yet in the propheste of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi>
he is called <hi>the King of Edom,</hi> because he had it in
view.</p>
            <p>Now to come to Christians, We are Kings in our sort,
we are <hi>Primogeniti,</hi> we are the <hi>Israel</hi> of God. When
God sent <hi>Moses</hi> to deliver his People, he bids him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
this Message to <hi>Pharaoh, Exod. 4. 22. Thou shalt
say to Pharaoh, Thus saith the Lord, Israel is my Sonne,
even my First-borne.</hi> Here is our priviledge, though
God hath many Sonnes, yet being found in Christ, we
are all First-borne. And so the Children of God are
called, <hi>Heb. 12. The Congregation of the First-borne.</hi>
Every one that is a Member of Christ hath the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of a First-borne. They are all Heires. In the same
relation that Christ is, by nature, we are by Grace and
Adoption: And being so, we have the Excellency of
Dignity, and the Excellency of Power.</p>
            <p>We do not speak of the Power of this World: Christ
said, <hi>My Kingdome is not of this World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They that preach, <hi>The Saints shall reign upon the Earth,</hi>
did not learne it from God, <hi>For our Kingdome is not of
this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is not that Excellency to be found in any of the
Sonnes of men, as is to be found in one poore Child of
God.</p>
            <p>Will you see <hi>David</hi> a King? when he comes with a
pious Eye, <hi>Psal.</hi> 15. 4. see who are there the most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull
persons. In whose eyes a vile person is contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
but honours them that feare the Lord. When he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41260:7"/>
sees Gods Image in any soule, he honours him; and if
he be a wicked man, a Child of the Devill, he is a vile
person in his eyes. A Sinner (though otherwise never
so Noble) is a very vile person, <hi>Psal,</hi> 16. <hi>My goodnesse,</hi>
saith <hi>David, doth not extend to thee, but unto the Saints
upon the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apostle Saint <hi>John, 1 Joh. 3. Behold</hi> (saith he)
<hi>what manner of love the Father bestowed upon us, that we
should be called the sonnes of God, and therefore the world
doth not know us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But if they be so Excellent, How come they to be so
despised in the World? the Reason is, because the
World doth not know them to be such. The world
doth not know Christs Children, more then they know
Christ himself.</p>
            <p>I have often thought, that when His Majesty was in
<hi>France,</hi> where He was not knowne, a Neglect put upon
Him there, would not have been in any proportion so
bad, as the like must needs be amongst His owne Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.
And so it is with us. We are Spirituall Kings, a
Royall Priesthood: If the world did know us to be
such, they would deale with us otherwise then they doe,
<hi>but our Life is hid with Christ in God,</hi> and one day it <hi>shall
appeare,</hi> and then shall the Righteous shine in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
of their Father.</p>
            <p>Beloved, hereupon it is that the Children of God
have <hi>their Guard of Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King hath a choice Guard to attend him, but
if ye did see what attendance the Children of God
have, you would admire. The Angels of God do pitch
their Tents about them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41260:8"/>
In the <hi>Cantioles,</hi> the State of <hi>Solomons</hi> Bed is descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
with Threescore valiant men about it for a Guard.
What is this but a Type of the Angels of God guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
his owne people, the <hi>Militia</hi> of Heaven?</p>
            <p>But I perceive the time is past, therefore will end
here.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
