<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Olor Iscanus. A collection of some select poems, and translations, / formerly written by Mr. Henry Vaughan silurist. ; Published by a friend.</title>
            <author>Vaughan, Henry, 1622-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-01">2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64746</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 12706608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6212</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12706608</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12706608</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66031</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A64746)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66031)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2900:24, 371:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Olor Iscanus. A collection of some select poems, and translations, / formerly written by Mr. Henry Vaughan silurist. ; Published by a friend.</title>
                  <author>Vaughan, Henry, 1622-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 158, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.W. for Humphrey Moseley, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Added illustrated t.p.</note>
                  <note>Each part has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in British Library (371:5) and Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (2900:24).</note>
                  <note>Item at 371:5 imperfect: lacking all after p. 64.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Literature --  Translations into English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>English poetry --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2000-00</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-09</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-09</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Michigan)</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-11</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:66031:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>SELECT Poems, and translations by Hen: Vaughan Silurist. Flumina amo, Sylvas<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, inglorius</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66031:1"/>
            <p>OLOR ISCANUS. A COLLECTION OF SOME SELECT POEMS, AND TRANSLATIONS, Formerly written by Mr. <hi>Henry Vaughan</hi> Silurist.</p>
            <p>Published by a Friend.</p>
            <p>Virg. Georg.</p>
            <p>Flumina amo, Sylvas<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, Inglorius—</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T.W.</hi> for <hi>Humphrey Moseley,</hi> and are to be sold at his shop, at the Signe of the Prince's Arms in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:66031:2"/>
            <l>—O quis me gelidis in vallibus <hi>ISCAE</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Sistat, &amp; Ingenti ramorum protegat umbrâ!</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:66031:2"/>
            <head>TO The truly Noble, and most Excellently accomplish'd, the LORD KILDARE DIGBY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is a Position <hi>ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> known, and <hi>modern Experience</hi> hath allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it for a <hi>sad truth,</hi> that <hi>Absence</hi> and <hi>time,</hi> (like <hi>Cold weather,</hi> and an <hi>unnaturall dormition</hi>) will <hi>blast</hi> and <hi>wear</hi> out of memorie the most <hi>Endearing obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>; And hence it was that some
<pb facs="tcp:66031:3"/>
               <hi>Politicians</hi> in <hi>Love</hi> have lookt upon the <hi>former</hi> of these <hi>two</hi> as a main re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy against the <hi>fondness</hi> of that <hi>Passion.</hi> But for my own part (my Lord) I shall deny this <hi>Aphorisme</hi> of the <hi>people,</hi> and beg leave to assure your <hi>Lordship,</hi> that, though these <hi>reputed obstacles</hi> have lain long in my way, yet neither of them could <hi>work</hi> upon me: for I am now (without adulation) as <hi>warm</hi> and <hi>sensible</hi> of those <hi>numerous</hi> favours, and <hi>kind Influences</hi> receiv'd some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from your Lordship, as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally was at the <hi>Instant</hi> of <hi>fruition.</hi> I have no <hi>plott</hi> by <hi>preambling</hi> thus, to set any <hi>rate</hi> upon this present <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse,</hi> as if I should presume to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue a <hi>Return</hi> of this nature equall with your Lordships <hi>Deserts,</hi> but
<pb facs="tcp:66031:3"/>
the <hi>designe</hi> is, to let you see that this <hi>habit</hi> I have got of being <hi>troublesome</hi> flowes from two <hi>excusable principles,</hi> Gratitude, and Love. These inward <hi>Counsellours</hi> (I know not how dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly) perswaded me to this <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> and <hi>Intrusion</hi> upon your <hi>name,</hi> which if your Lordship will vouchsafe to own as the <hi>Genius</hi> to these <hi>papers,</hi> you will <hi>perfect</hi> my <hi>hopes,</hi> and place me at my full <hi>height.</hi> This was the <hi>Ayme,</hi> my Lord, and is the <hi>End</hi> of this work, which though but a <hi>Pazzarello</hi> to the <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminoseè Insani,</hi> yet as <hi>Iezamin</hi> and the <hi>Violet</hi> find room in the <hi>bank</hi> as well as <hi>Roses</hi> and <hi>Lillies,</hi> so happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may this, and (if <hi>shin'd</hi> upon by your <hi>Lordship</hi>) please as much. To whose <hi>Protection,</hi> Sacred as your
<pb facs="tcp:66031:4"/>
               <hi>Name,</hi> and those eminent <hi>Honours</hi> which have alwayes attended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on't through so many <hi>generations,</hi> I humbly offer it, and remain in all <hi>numbers</hi> of <hi>gratitude,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Newton</hi> by <hi>Usk</hi> this 17. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb.</hi> 1647.</date>
               <salute>My honour'd Lord, Your most affectionate, humblest Servant</salute>
               <signed>VAUGHAN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:66031:4"/>
            <head>The Publisher to the Reader.</head>
            <p>IT was the glorious <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> that referr'd his <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacies</hi> to the <hi>Fire,</hi> and though <hi>Princes</hi> are sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <hi>Executors,</hi> yet there came a <hi>Caesar</hi> to his <hi>Testament,</hi> as if the <hi>Act</hi> of a <hi>Poet</hi> could not be <hi>repeal'd</hi> but by a <hi>King.</hi> I am not Reader <hi>Augustus vindex:</hi> Here is no <hi>Royall Res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue,</hi> but here is a <hi>Muse</hi> that <hi>deserves</hi> it. The <hi>Author</hi> had long agoe condemn'd these <hi>Poems</hi> to <hi>Obscuritie,</hi> and the <hi>Consumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of that <hi>Further Fate,</hi> which <hi>attends</hi> it. This <hi>Censure</hi> gave them a <hi>Gust</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> and they have <hi>partly</hi> known that <hi>Oblivion,</hi> which our <hi>Best Labours</hi> must <hi>come to</hi> at
<pb facs="tcp:66031:5"/>
               <hi>Last.</hi> I present thee then not onely with a <hi>Book,</hi> but with a <hi>Prey,</hi> and in this <hi>kind</hi> the first <hi>Recoveries</hi> from <hi>Corruption.</hi> Here is a <hi>Flame</hi> hath been sometimes <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguished:</hi> Thoughts that have been <hi>lost</hi> and <hi>forgot,</hi> but now they <hi>break out</hi> again like the <hi>Platonic Reminiscencie.</hi> I have not the Author's <hi>Approbation</hi> to the <hi>Fact,</hi> but I have <hi>Law</hi> on my <hi>Side,</hi> though never a <hi>Sword</hi>: I hold it no man's <hi>Praerogative</hi> to fire his <hi>own House.</hi> Thou seest how <hi>Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> I am <hi>grown,</hi> and if thou doest expect I should <hi>Commend</hi> what is <hi>published,</hi> I must tell thee, <hi>I crie no Sivill Oranges.</hi> I will not say, Here is <hi>Fine</hi> or <hi>Cheap:</hi> that were an <hi>Injurie</hi> to the <hi>Verse</hi> it selfe, and to the <hi>Effects</hi> it can <hi>produce.</hi> Read on, and thou wilt find thy <hi>Spirit ingag'd</hi>: not by the <hi>Deserts</hi> of what wee call <hi>Tolerable,</hi> but by the <hi>Commands</hi> of a <hi>Pen,</hi> that is <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:66031:5"/>
            <head>Vpon the most Ingenious <hi>pair</hi> of Twins, <hi>Eugenius Philalethes,</hi> and the <hi>Authour</hi> of these Poems.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHat <hi>Planet</hi> rul'd your <hi>birth?</hi> what <hi>wittie star?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That you so like in <hi>Souls</hi> as <hi>Bodies</hi> are!</l>
               <l>So like in <hi>both,</hi> that you seem <hi>born</hi> to free</l>
               <l>The <hi>starrie are</hi> from <hi>vulgar</hi> Calumnie.</l>
               <l>My <hi>doubts</hi> are solv'd, from hence my <hi>faith</hi> begins,</l>
               <l>Not only your <hi>faces,</hi> but your <hi>wits</hi> are <hi>Twins.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When this bright <hi>Gemini</hi> shall from earth ascend,</l>
               <l>They will <hi>new light</hi> to dull ey'd mankind lend,</l>
               <l>Teach the <hi>Star-gazers,</hi> and delight their <hi>Eyes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Being fixt a <hi>Constellation</hi> in the <hi>Skyes.</hi>
               </l>
               <byline>T. Powell Oxoniensis.</byline>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:66031:6"/>
            <head>To my friend the Authour upon these his <hi>Poems.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>I Call'd it once my <hi>sloth:</hi> In such an age</l>
            <l>So many <hi>Volumes deep,</hi> I not a <hi>page?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But I recant, and vow 'twas thriftie Care</l>
            <l>That kept my <hi>Pen</hi> from spending on <hi>slight ware,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And breath'd it for a <hi>Prize,</hi> whose pow'rfull <hi>shine</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Doth both <hi>reward</hi> the striver, and <hi>refine</hi>;</l>
            <l>Such are thy <hi>Poems,</hi> friend: for since th'hast writ,</l>
            <l>I cann't reply to any <hi>name,</hi> but <hi>wit</hi>;</l>
            <l>And left amidst the <hi>throng</hi> that make us <hi>grone,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Mine prove a groundless <hi>Heresie</hi> alone,</l>
            <l>Thus I dispute. Hath there not rev'rence bin</l>
            <l>Pay'd to the <hi>Beard</hi> at doore, for <hi>Lord</hi> within?</l>
            <l>Who notes the <hi>spindle-leg,</hi> or <hi>hollow eye</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of the <hi>thinne Usher,</hi> the <hi>faire Lady</hi> by?</l>
            <l>Thus I <hi>sinne</hi> freely, <hi>neighbour</hi> to a <hi>hand</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Which while I aime to <hi>strengthen,</hi> gives <hi>Command</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For my <hi>protection,</hi> and thou art to me</l>
            <l>At once my <hi>Subject</hi> and <hi>Securitie.</hi>
            </l>
            <byline>I. Rowlandson Oxoniensis.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:66031:6"/>
            <head>Vpon the following <hi>Poems.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>I Write not here, as if thy <hi>last</hi> in store</l>
            <l>Of learned <hi>friends,</hi> 'tis known that thou hast <hi>more</hi>;</l>
            <l>Who, were they told of this, would find a way</l>
            <l>To rise a guard of <hi>Poets</hi> without <hi>pay,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And bring as many <hi>hands</hi> to thy <hi>Edition,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>As th'<hi>City</hi> should unto their <hi>May'rs</hi> Petition,</l>
            <l>But thou wouldst none of this, left it should be</l>
            <l>Thy <hi>Muster</hi> rather, than our <hi>Courtesie,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Thou wouldst not beg as <hi>Knights</hi> do, and appeare</l>
            <l>Poet by <hi>Voice,</hi> and <hi>suffrage</hi> of the <hi>Shire,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That were enough to make my <hi>Muse</hi> advance</l>
            <l>Amongst the <hi>Crutches,</hi> nay it might enhance</l>
            <l>Our <hi>Charity,</hi> and we should think it sit</l>
            <l>The <hi>State</hi> should build an <hi>Hospital</hi> for wit.</l>
            <l>But here needs no <hi>reliefe:</hi> Thy richer <hi>Verse</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Creates all <hi>Poets,</hi> that can but <hi>reherse,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And they, like <hi>Tenants</hi> better'd by their <hi>land,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Should pay thee <hi>Rent</hi> for what they understand,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:66031:7"/>Thou art not of that <hi>lamentable Nation,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Who make a blessed <hi>Alms</hi> of <hi>approbation,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Whose <hi>fardel-notes</hi> are <hi>Briefes</hi> in ev'ry thing,</l>
            <l>But, that they are not licens'd <hi>By the King.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Without such <hi>scrape-requests</hi> thou dost come forth</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Arm'd</hi> (though I speak it) with thy <hi>proper worth,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And needest not this <hi>noise</hi> of friends, for wee</l>
            <l>Write out of <hi>love,</hi> not thy <hi>necessitie</hi>;</l>
            <l>And though this <hi>sullen age</hi> possessed be</l>
            <l>With some strange <hi>Desamour</hi> to Poetrie,</l>
            <l>Yet I suspect (thy fancy so delights)</l>
            <l>The <hi>Puritans</hi> will turn thy <hi>Proselytes,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And that thy <hi>flame</hi> when once abroad it <hi>shines,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Will bring thee as many <hi>friends,</hi> as thou hast <hi>lines.</hi>
            </l>
            <byline>EUGENIUS PHILALETHIS <hi>Oxoniensis.</hi>
            </byline>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66031:7"/>
            <head>Olor Iscanus.</head>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the River <hi>Isca.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>WHen <hi>Daphne</hi>'s Lover here first wore the <hi>Dayes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eurotas</hi> secret streams heard all his <hi>Layes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And holy <hi>Orpheus,</hi> Natures <hi>busie</hi> Child</l>
               <l>By headlong <hi>Hebrus</hi> his deep <hi>Eymns</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pil'd.</l>
               <l>Soft <hi>Petrarch</hi> (thaw'd by <hi>Laura</hi>'s flames) did weep</l>
               <l>On <hi>Tybers</hi> banks, when she (<hi>prou'd fair</hi>!) cou'd sleep;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mosella</hi> boasts <hi>Ausonius,</hi> and the <hi>Thames</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth murmure <hi>SIDNEYS Stella</hi> to her <hi>streams,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>While <hi>Severn</hi> sworn with <hi>Ioy</hi> and <hi>sorrow,</hi> wears</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Castara</hi>'s smiles mixt with fair <hi>Sabrin</hi>'s tears.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Poets</hi> (like the <hi>Nymphs,</hi> their <hi>pleasing themes</hi>)</l>
               <l>Haunted the <hi>bubling Springs</hi> and <hi>gliding streams,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>happy banks</hi>! whence such <hi>fair slowres</hi> have sprung,</l>
               <l>But happier those where they have <hi>sate</hi> and <hi>sung!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poets</hi> (like <hi>Angels</hi>) where they once appear</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hallow</hi> the <hi>place,</hi> and each succeeding year</l>
               <l>Adds <hi>rev'rence</hi> to't, such as at length doth give</l>
               <l>This aged faith, <hi>That there their Genii live.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hence th' <hi>Auncients</hi> say, That, from this <hi>sickly aire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They passe to <hi>Regions</hi> more <hi>refin'd</hi> and <hi>faire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>Meadows</hi> strow'd with <hi>Lillies</hi> and the <hi>Rose,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>shades</hi> whose <hi>youthfull green</hi> no <hi>old age</hi> knowes,</l>
               <l>Where all in <hi>white</hi> they walk, discourse, and Sing</l>
               <l>Like Bees <hi>soft murmurs,</hi> or a <hi>Chiding Spring.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But <hi>Isca,</hi> whensoe'r those <hi>shades</hi> I see,</l>
               <l>And thy <hi>lov'd Arbours</hi> must no more <hi>know</hi> me,</l>
               <l>When I am layd to <hi>rest</hi> hard by thy <hi>streams,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And my <hi>Sun sets,</hi> where first it <hi>sprang</hi> in beams,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:66031:8"/>I'le leave; behind me such a <hi>large, kind light,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As shall <hi>redeem</hi> thee from <hi>oblivious night,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in these <hi>vowes</hi> which (living yet) I pay</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shed</hi> such a <hi>Previous</hi> and <hi>Enduring Ray,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As shall from age to age thy <hi>fair name</hi> lead</l>
               <l>'Till <hi>Rivers</hi> leave to <hi>run,</hi> and <hi>men</hi> to <hi>read.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>First, may all <hi>Bards</hi> born after me</l>
               <l>(When I am <hi>ashes</hi>) sing of thee!</l>
               <l>May thy <hi>green banks</hi> and <hi>streams</hi> (or none)</l>
               <l>Be both their <hi>Hill</hi> and <hi>Helicon</hi>;</l>
               <l>May <hi>Vocall Groves</hi> grow there, and all</l>
               <l>The <hi>shades</hi> in them <hi>Propheticall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where (laid) men shall more <hi>faire truths</hi> see</l>
               <l>Than <hi>fictions</hi> were of <hi>Thessalie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May thy gentle <hi>Swains</hi> (like <hi>flowres</hi>)</l>
               <l>Sweetly spend their <hi>Youthfull houres,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And thy <hi>beauteous Nymphs</hi> (like <hi>Doves</hi>)</l>
               <l>Be <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>faithfull</hi> to their <hi>Loves</hi>;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Garlands,</hi> and <hi>Songs,</hi> and <hi>Roundelayes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mild, dewie <hi>nights,</hi> and Sun-shine <hi>dayes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Turtles voyce, Ioy</hi> without <hi>fear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dwell</hi> on thy <hi>bosome</hi> all the year!</l>
               <l>May the <hi>Evet</hi> and the <hi>Tode</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Within thy Banks have no abode,</l>
               <l>Nor the <hi>wilie, winding Snake</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her <hi>voyage</hi> through thy <hi>waters</hi> make.</l>
               <l>In all thy <hi>Iourney</hi> to the <hi>Main</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No <hi>nitrous Clay,</hi> nor <hi>Brimstone-vein</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mixe with thy <hi>streams,</hi> but may they passe</l>
               <l>Fresh as the <hi>aire,</hi> and cleer as <hi>Glasse,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And where the <hi>wandring Chrystal</hi> treads</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rojes</hi> shall <hi>kisse,</hi> and <hi>Couple</hi> heads.</l>
               <l>The <hi>factour-wind</hi> from far shall bring</l>
               <l>The <hi>Odours</hi> of the <hi>Scatter'd</hi> Spring,</l>
               <l>And <hi>loaden</hi> with the rich <hi>Aweare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spend</hi> it in <hi>Spicie whispers</hi> there.</l>
               <l>No <hi>sullen heals,</hi> nor <hi>flames</hi> that are</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Offensive,</hi> and <hi>Canicular,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66031:8"/>Shine on thy <hi>Sands,</hi> nor <hi>pry</hi> to see</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Scalie, shading familie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But <hi>Noones</hi> as mild as <hi>Hasper's</hi> rayes,</l>
               <l>Or the first <hi>blushes</hi> of fair dayes.</l>
               <l>What <hi>gifts</hi> more <hi>Heav'n</hi> or <hi>Earth</hi> can adde</l>
               <l>With all those <hi>blessings</hi> be thou <hi>Clad</hi>!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Honour, Beautie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Dutie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Delight</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Youth</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Crown all about thee And what ever <hi>Fate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Impose else-where, whether the graver state,</l>
               <l>Or some toy else, may those <hi>lomd, anxious Cares</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For <hi>dead</hi> and <hi>dying things</hi> (the Common <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ares</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>showes</hi> of time) he'r break thy <hi>Peace,</hi> nor make</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>repos'd Armes</hi> to a new warre <hi>awake</hi>!</l>
               <l>But <hi>Freedome, safety, Ioy</hi> and <hi>blisse</hi>:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>United</hi> in one loving <hi>kisse</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Surround</hi> thee quite, and <hi>stile</hi> thy borders</l>
               <l>The Land redeem'd from all disorders!</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Charnel-house.</head>
               <l>BLesse me! what damps are here? how stiffe an aire?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kelder</hi> of mists, a second <hi>Fiats</hi> care,</l>
               <l>Front speece o'th' grave and darkness, a Display</l>
               <l>Of ruin'd man, and the disease of day;</l>
               <l>Leane, bloudless shamble, where I can descrie</l>
               <l>Fragments of men, Rags of Anatomie;</l>
               <l>Corruptions ward-robe, the transplantive bed</l>
               <l>Of mankind, and th'Exchequer of the dead.</l>
               <l>How thou arrests my sense? how with the sight</l>
               <l>My <hi>winter'd</hi> bloud growes stiffe to all delight?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Torpedo</hi> to the Eye! whose least glance can</l>
               <l>Freeze our wild lusts, and reseue head-long man;</l>
               <l>Eloquent silence! able to Immure</l>
               <l>An <hi>Atheists</hi> thoughts, and blast an <hi>Epicure.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:66031:9"/>Were I a <hi>Lucian,</hi> Nature in this dresse</l>
               <l>Would make me wish a Saviour, and Confesse.</l>
               <l>Where are you shoreless thoughts, vast tenter'd hope,</l>
               <l>Ambitious dreams, <hi>Aymes</hi> of an Endless scope,</l>
               <l>Whose stretch'd Excesse runs on a string too high</l>
               <l>And on the rack of self-extension dye?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chameleons</hi> of state, Aire-monging band,</l>
               <l>Whose breath (like Gun-powder) blowes up a land,</l>
               <l>Come see your dissolution, and weigh</l>
               <l>What a loath'd nothing you shall be one day,</l>
               <l>As th' Elements by Circulation passe</l>
               <l>From one to th'other, and that which first was</l>
               <l>Is so again, so 'tis with you; The grave</l>
               <l>And Nature but Complote, what the one gave,</l>
               <l>The other takes; I think then, that in this bed</l>
               <l>There sleep the Reliques of as proud a head</l>
               <l>As stern and subtill as your own, that hath</l>
               <l>Perform'd, or forc'd as much, whose tempest-wrath</l>
               <l>Hath levell'd Kings with slaves, and wisely then</l>
               <l>Calme these high furies, and descend to men;</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Cyrus</hi> tam'd the <hi>Macedon,</hi> a tombe</l>
               <l>Checkt him, who thought the world too straight a Room.</l>
               <l>Have I obey'd the <hi>Powers</hi> of face,</l>
               <l>A beauty able to undoe the Race</l>
               <l>Of easie man? I look but here, and strait</l>
               <l>I am Inform'd, the lovely Counterfeit</l>
               <l>Was but a smoother Clay. That famish'd slave</l>
               <l>Begger'd by wealth, who starvea that he may save,</l>
               <l>Brings hither but his sheet; Nay, th' <hi>Ostrich-man,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That feeds on <hi>steele</hi> and <hi>bullet,</hi> he that can</l>
               <l>Outswea: his <hi>Lordship,</hi> and reply as tough</l>
               <l>To a kind word, as if his tongue were <hi>Buffe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is <hi>Chap</hi>-faln here, wormes without wit, or fear</l>
               <l>Defie him now, death hath disarm'd the <hi>Bear.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus could I run o'r all the pitteous score</l>
               <l>Of erring men, and having done meet more,</l>
               <l>Their shuffled <hi>Wills,</hi> abortive, vain <hi>Intents,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Phautasrick <hi>humours,</hi> perillous <hi>Ascents,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66031:9"/>False, empty <hi>honours,</hi> traiterous <hi>delights,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And what soe'r a blind Conceit Invites;</l>
               <l>But these and more which the weak vermins swell,</l>
               <l>Are Couch'd in this Accumulative Cell</l>
               <l>Which I could scatter; But the grudging Sun</l>
               <l>Calls home his beams, and warns me to be gone,</l>
               <l>Day leaves me in a double night, and I</l>
               <l>Must bid farewell to my sad library.</l>
               <l>Yet with these notes. Henceforth with thought of thee</l>
               <l>I'le season all succeeding Iollitie,</l>
               <l>Yet damn not mirth, nor think too much is fit,</l>
               <l>Excesse hath no <hi>Religion,</hi> nor <hi>wit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But should wild bloud swell to a lawless strain</l>
               <l>On Check from thee shall <hi>Channel</hi> it again.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>In Amicum foeneratorem.</head>
               <l>THanks mighty <hi>Silver</hi>! I rejoyce to see</l>
               <l>How I have spoyl'd his thrift, by spending thee.</l>
               <l>Now thou art gone, he courts my wants with more,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Decoy</hi> gold, and bribes me to restore.</l>
               <l>As lesser lode-stones with the <hi>North</hi> consent</l>
               <l>Naturally moving to their Element,</l>
               <l>As bodyes swarm to th' Center, and that fire</l>
               <l>Man stole from heaven, to heav'n doth still aspire,</l>
               <l>So this vast crying summe drawes in a lesse,</l>
               <l>And hence this bag more Northward layd I guesse,</l>
               <l>For 'tis of <hi>Pole-star</hi> force, and in this sphere</l>
               <l>Though th'least of many rules the master-bear.</l>
               <l>Prerogative of debts! how he doth dresse</l>
               <l>His messages in <hi>Chink?</hi> not an Expresse</l>
               <l>Without a fee for reading, and 'tis fit,</l>
               <l>For gold's the best restorative of wit,</l>
               <l>O how he gilds them o'r! with what delight</l>
               <l>I read those lines, where Angels doe Indite?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:66031:10"/>But wilt have money <hi>Og?</hi> must I dispurse?</l>
               <l>Will nothing serve thee but a <hi>Poets</hi> curse?</l>
               <l>Wilt rob an Altar thus? and sweep it once</l>
               <l>What <hi>Orpheus</hi>-like I forc'd from stocks and stones?</l>
               <l>'I will never swell thy <hi>Bag,</hi> nor ring one peale</l>
               <l>In thy dark <hi>Chest.</hi> Talk not of <hi>Shreives,</hi> or gaole,</l>
               <l>I fear them not. I have no land to glutt</l>
               <l>Thy durty appetite, and make thee strutt</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nimrod</hi> of acres; I'le no Speech prepare</l>
               <l>To court the <hi>Hopefull Cormorant,</hi> thine heire.</l>
               <l>Yet there's a Kingdome, at thy beck, if thou</l>
               <l>But kick this drosse, <hi>Parnassus</hi> flowre brow</l>
               <l>I'le give thee with my <hi>Tempe,</hi> and to boot</l>
               <l>That horse which struck a fountain with his foot.</l>
               <l>A Bed of Roses I'le provide for thee,</l>
               <l>And Chrystal Springs shall drop thee melodie;</l>
               <l>The breathing shades wee'l haunt, where ev'ry leafe</l>
               <l>Shall <hi>whisper</hi> us asleep, though thou art deafe;</l>
               <l>Those waggish <hi>Nymph</hi> too which none ever yet</l>
               <l>Durst make love to, wee'l teach the Loving fit,</l>
               <l>Wee'l suck the <hi>Corall</hi> of their lips, and feed</l>
               <l>Upon their spicie breath, a meale at need,</l>
               <l>Rove in their <hi>Amber-tresses,</hi> and unfold</l>
               <l>That glist'ring grove, the Curled wood of gold,</l>
               <l>Then peep for babies, a new Puppet-play,</l>
               <l>And riddle what their <hi>pratling Eyes</hi> would say.</l>
               <l>But here thou must remember to dispurse,</l>
               <l>For without money all this is a Curse,</l>
               <l>Thou must for more bags call, and so restore</l>
               <l>This Iron-age to gold, as once before;</l>
               <l>This thou must doe, and yet this is not all,</l>
               <l>For thus the Poet would be still in thrall,</l>
               <l>Thou must then (if live thus) my neast of honey,</l>
               <l>Cancell old bonds, and beg to lend more money.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:66031:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>To his friend—.</head>
               <l>I Wonder, <hi>Iames,</hi> through the whole Historie</l>
               <l>Of ages, such <hi>Entailes</hi> of povertie</l>
               <l>Are layd on Poets; Lawyers (they say) have found</l>
               <l>A trick to cut them, would they were but bound</l>
               <l>To practise on us, though for this thing wee</l>
               <l>Should pay (if possible) their bribes and fee.</l>
               <l>Search (as thou canst) the old and moderne store</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Rome</hi> and ours, in all the wittie score</l>
               <l>Thou shalt not find a rich one; Take each Clime</l>
               <l>And run o'r all the pilgrimage of time</l>
               <l>Thou'lt meet them poor, and ev'ry where descrie</l>
               <l>A thredbare, goldless genealogie.</l>
               <l>Nature (it seems) when she meant us for Earth</l>
               <l>Spent so much of her treasure in the birth</l>
               <l>As ever after niggards her, and Shee,</l>
               <l>Thus stor'd within, beggers us outwardly.</l>
               <l>Wofull profusion I at how dear a rate</l>
               <l>Are wee made up? all hope of thrise and state</l>
               <l>Lost for a verse: When I by thoughts look back</l>
               <l>Into the wombe of time, and see the Rack</l>
               <l>Stand useless there, untill we are produc'd</l>
               <l>Unto the torture, and our soules infus'd</l>
               <l>To learn afflictions, I begin to doubt</l>
               <l>That as some tyrants use from their chain'd roue</l>
               <l>Of slaves to pick out one whom for their sport</l>
               <l>They keep afflicted by some lingring art,</l>
               <l>So wee are meerly thrown upon the stage</l>
               <l>The mirth of fooles, and Legend of the age,</l>
               <l>When I see in the ruines of a sute</l>
               <l>Some nobler brest, and his tongue sadly mute</l>
               <l>Feed on the <hi>Vocall silence</hi> of his Eye,</l>
               <l>And knowing cannot reach the remedie,</l>
               <l>When soules of baser stamp shine in their store,</l>
               <l>And he of all the throng is only poore,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:66031:11"/>When <hi>French</hi> apes sor forraign fashions pay,</l>
               <l>And <hi>English</hi> legs are drest th'outlandish way,</l>
               <l>So fine too, that they their own shadows wooe,</l>
               <l>While he walks in the <hi>sad</hi> and <hi>Pilgrim-shooe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I'm mad at Fate, and angry ev'n to sinne,</l>
               <l>To see deserts and learning clad so thinne:</l>
               <l>To think how th'earthly Usurer can brood</l>
               <l>Upon his bags, and weigh the pretious food</l>
               <l>With palsied hands, as if his soul did feare</l>
               <l>The Scales could rob him of what he layd there;</l>
               <l>Like Divels that on hid Treasures sit, or those</l>
               <l>Whose jealous Eyes trust not beyond their nose</l>
               <l>They guard the durt, and the bright Idol hold</l>
               <l>Close, and Commit adultery with gold.</l>
               <l>A Curse upon their drosse! how have we sued</l>
               <l>For a few scatter'd <hi>Chips?</hi> how oft pursu'd</l>
               <l>Petitions with a blush, in hope to squeeze</l>
               <l>For their souls health, more than our wants a peece?</l>
               <l>Their steel-rib'd Chests and Purse (rust eat them both!)</l>
               <l>Have cost us with much paper many an oath,</l>
               <l>And Protestations of such solemn sense,</l>
               <l>As if our soules were sureties for the Pence.</l>
               <l>Should we a full nights learned cares present,</l>
               <l>They'l scarce return us one short houres Content,</l>
               <l>'Las! they're but quibbles, things we Poets feign,</l>
               <l>The short-liv'd Squibs and Crackers of the brain.</l>
               <l>But wee'l be wiser, knowing 'tis not they</l>
               <l>That must redeem the hardship of our way,</l>
               <l>Whether a Higher Power, or that starre</l>
               <l>Which neerest heav'n, is from the earth most far</l>
               <l>Oppresse us thus, or angel'd from that Sphere</l>
               <l>By our strict Guardians are kept luckless here,</l>
               <l>It matters not, wee shall one day obtain</l>
               <l>Our native and Celestiall scope again.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:66031:11"/>
               <head>To his retired friend, an Invitation to <hi>Brecknock.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>SInce last wee met, thou and thy horse (my dear,)</l>
               <l>Have not so much as drunk, or litter'd here,</l>
               <l>I wonder, though thy self be thus deceast,</l>
               <l>Thou hast the spite to Coffin up thy beast;</l>
               <l>Or is the <hi>Palfrey</hi> sick, and his rough hide</l>
               <l>With the penance of <hi>One Spur</hi> mortifide?</l>
               <l>Or taught by thee (like <hi>Pythagoras's Oxe</hi>)</l>
               <l>Is then his master grown more <hi>Orthodox?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What ever 'tis, a sober cause't must be</l>
               <l>That thus long bars us of thy Companie.</l>
               <l>The Town believes thee lost, and didst thou see</l>
               <l>But half her suffrings, now distrest for thee,</l>
               <l>Thou'ldst swear (like <hi>Rome</hi>) her soule, polluted walls</l>
               <l>Were sackt by <hi>Brennus,</hi> and the salvage <hi>Gaules.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Abominable face of things! here's noise</l>
               <l>Of bang'd Mortars, blew Aprons, and Boyes,</l>
               <l>Pigs, Dogs, and Drums, with the hoarse hellish notes</l>
               <l>Of politickly-deafe Usurers throats,</l>
               <l>With new fine <hi>worships,</hi> and the old east <hi>teame</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of Justices vext with the <hi>Cough,</hi> and <hi>flegme.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Midst these the <hi>Crosse</hi> looks sad, and in the <hi>Shirt</hi>-</l>
               <l>-<hi>Hall furs</hi> of an old <hi>Saxon Fox</hi> appear,</l>
               <l>With brotherly Ruffs and Beards, and a strange sight</l>
               <l>Of high Monumentall Hats t'ane at the sight</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Eighty eight</hi>; while ev'ry <hi>Bargessi</hi> foots</l>
               <l>The mortall <hi>Pavement</hi> in eternall boots.</l>
               <l>Hadst thou been batc'lour, I had soon divin'd</l>
               <l>Thy Close retirements, and Monastick mind,</l>
               <l>Perhaps some Nymph had been to visit, or</l>
               <l>The beauteous Churle was to be waited for,</l>
               <l>And like the <hi>Greek,</hi> e'r you the sport would misse</l>
               <l>You stai'd, and stroak'd the <hi>Dislosse</hi> for a kisse.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:66031:12"/>But in this age, when thy coole, settled bloud</l>
               <l>Is ty'd t'one flesh, and thou almost grown good,</l>
               <l>I know not how to reach the strange device,</l>
               <l>Except (<hi>Domitian</hi> like) thou murther'st flyes;</l>
               <l>Or is't thy pietie? for who can tell</l>
               <l>But thou may'st prove devout, and love a Cell,</l>
               <l>And (like a Badger) with attentive looks</l>
               <l>In the dark hole sit rooting up of books.</l>
               <l>Quick Hermit! what a peacefull Change hadst thou</l>
               <l>Without the noise of <hi>haire-cloth, whip,</hi> or <hi>Vow?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But is there no redemption? must there be</l>
               <l>No other penance but of liberty?</l>
               <l>Why two months hence, if thou continue thus</l>
               <l>Thy memory will scarce remain with us,</l>
               <l>The Drawers have forgot thee, and exclaim</l>
               <l>They have not seen thee here since <hi>Charles</hi> his raign,</l>
               <l>Or if they mention thee, like some old man.</l>
               <l>That at each word inserts— Sir, <hi>as I can</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Remember</hi>— So the <hi>Cyph'rers</hi> puzzle mee</l>
               <l>With a dark, cloudie character of thee.</l>
               <l>That (certs!) I fear thou wilt be lost, and wee</l>
               <l>Must ask the <hi>Fathers</hi> e'r 't be long for thee.</l>
               <l>Come! leave this sullen state, and let not Wine</l>
               <l>And precious Witt lye dead for want of thine,</l>
               <l>Shall the dull <hi>Market-land-lord</hi> with his <hi>Rout</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of sneaking Tenants durtily swill out</l>
               <l>This harmlesse liquor? shall they knock and beat</l>
               <l>For Sack, only to talk of <hi>Rye,</hi> and <hi>wheat?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O let not such prepost'rous tipling be</l>
               <l>In our <hi>Metropolis,</hi> may I ne'r see</l>
               <l>Such <hi>Tavern-sacrilege,</hi> nor load a line</l>
               <l>To weep the <hi>Rapes</hi> and <hi>Tragedy</hi> of wine!</l>
               <l>Here lives that <hi>Chimick,</hi> quick fire which betrayes</l>
               <l>Fresh Spirits to the bloud, and warms our layes,</l>
               <l>I have reserv'd 'gainst thy approach a Cup</l>
               <l>That were thy Muse stark dead, shall raise her up,</l>
               <l>And teach her yet more Charming words and skill</l>
               <l>Than ever <hi>Coelia, Chloris, Astrophil,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:66031:12"/>Or any of the Thredbare names Inspir'd</l>
               <l>Poore riming lovers with a <hi>Mistris</hi> sir'd.</l>
               <l>Come then I and while the slow Isicle hangs</l>
               <l>At the stiffe thatch, and Winters frosty pangs</l>
               <l>Benumme the year, blith (as of old let us</l>
               <l>'Midst noise and War, of Peace, and mirth discusse.</l>
               <l>This portion thou wort born for: why should wee</l>
               <l>Vex at the times ridiculous miserie?</l>
               <l>An age that thus hath fool'd it selfe, and will</l>
               <l>(Spite of thy teeth and mine) persist so still.</l>
               <l>Let's sit then at this <hi>fire,</hi> and while wee steal</l>
               <l>A Revell in the Town, let others seal,</l>
               <l>Purchase or Cheat, and who can, let them pay,</l>
               <l>Till those black deeds bring on the dark some day;</l>
               <l>Innocent spenders wee! a better use</l>
               <l>Shall wear out our short Lease, and leave th'obtuse</l>
               <l>Rout to their <hi>husks</hi>; They and their bags at best</l>
               <l>Have cares in <hi>earnest,</hi> wee care for a <hi>Iest.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Monsieur Gombauld.</head>
               <l>I'Ave read thy Souls fair night-peece, and have seen</l>
               <l>Th'<hi>Amours</hi> and Courtship of the <hi>silint Queen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her stoln descents to Earth, and what did move her</l>
               <l>To Juggle first with <hi>Heav'n,</hi> then with a <hi>Lover,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>Latmos</hi> loweer rescue, and (alas!)</l>
               <l>To find her out a <hi>Hue and Crie</hi> in Brasse,</l>
               <l>Thy Journall of deep Mysteries, and sad</l>
               <l>Nocturnall Pilgrimage, with thy dreams clad</l>
               <l>In fancies darker than thy <hi>Cave,</hi> Thy <hi>Glosse</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of sleepie draughts, and as thy soul did passe</l>
               <l>In her calm voyage what discourse she heard</l>
               <l>Of Spirits, what dark Groves and ill-shap'd guard</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ismena</hi> lead thee through, with thy proud flight</l>
               <l>O'r <hi>Periardes,</hi> and deep, musing night</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:66031:13"/>Neere fair <hi>Eurotas</hi> banks, what solemn <hi>green</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The neighbour shades weare, and what forms are seen</l>
               <l>In their large Bowers, with that sad path and seat</l>
               <l>Which none but light-heeld <hi>Nymphs</hi> and <hi>Fairies</hi> heat;</l>
               <l>Their solitary life, and how exempt</l>
               <l>From Common frailtie, the severe contempt</l>
               <l>They have of Man, their priviledge to live</l>
               <l>A <hi>Tree,</hi> or <hi>Fountain,</hi> and in that <hi>Reprieve</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What ages they consume, with the sad <hi>Vale</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Diophania,</hi> and the mournfull tale,</l>
               <l>Or th' bleeding vocall <hi>Myrtle</hi>; These and more</l>
               <l>Thy richer thoughts we are upon the score</l>
               <l>To thy rare fancy for, nor doest thou fall</l>
               <l>From thy first Majesty, or ought at all</l>
               <l>Betray Consumption, thy full vigorous <hi>Bayes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wear the same <hi>green,</hi> and scorn the lene decayes</l>
               <l>Of <hi>stile,</hi> or <hi>matter</hi>; Just so have I known</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Chrystal</hi> spring, that from the neighbour down</l>
               <l>Deriv'd her birth, in gentle murmurs steal</l>
               <l>To their next Vale, and proudly there reveal</l>
               <l>Her streams in lowder accents, adding still</l>
               <l>More noise and waters to her Channell, till</l>
               <l>At last swoln with Increase she glides along</l>
               <l>The Lawnes and Meadows in a wanton throng</l>
               <l>Of frothy billows, and in one great name</l>
               <l>Swallows the tributary brooks drown'd fame.</l>
               <l>Nor are they meere Inventions, for we</l>
               <l>In th' same peece find scatter'd <hi>Philosophie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And hidden, disperst truths that folded lye</l>
               <l>In the dark shades of deep <hi>Allegorie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So neatly weav'd, like <hi>Arras,</hi> they descrie</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fables</hi> with <hi>Truth, Fancy</hi> with <hi>Historie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So that thou hast in this thy curious mould</l>
               <l>Cast that commended mixture wish'd of old,</l>
               <l>Which shall these Contemplations render far</l>
               <l>Lesse mutable, and lasting as their star,</l>
               <l>And while there is a <hi>People,</hi> or a <hi>Sunne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Endymions</hi> storie with the <hi>Moon</hi> shall runne.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:66031:13"/>
               <head>An Elegie on the death of Mr. <hi>R.W.</hi> slain in the late unfortunate differences at <hi>Rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Heath, neer <hi>Chester,</hi> 1645.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Am Confirm'd, and so much wing is given</l>
                  <l>To my wild thoughts, that they dare strike at heav'n.</l>
                  <l>A full years griefe I struggled with, and stood</l>
                  <l>Still on my sandy hopes uncertain good,</l>
                  <l>So loth was I to yeeld, to all those fears</l>
                  <l>I still oppos'd thee, and denyed my tears.</l>
                  <l>But thou art gone! and the untimely losse</l>
                  <l>Like that one day, hath made all others Crosse.</l>
                  <l>Have you seen on some Rivers flowrie brow</l>
                  <l>A well-built <hi>Elme</hi> or stately <hi>Cedar</hi> grow,</l>
                  <l>Whose Curled tops gilt with the Morning-ray</l>
                  <l>Becken'd the Sun, and whisperd to the day,</l>
                  <l>When unexpected from the angry <hi>North</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A fatall sullen whirle-wind sallies forth,</l>
                  <l>And with a full-mouth'd blast rends from the ground</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Shady twins,</hi> which rushing scatter round</l>
                  <l>Their sighing leafes, whilst overborn with strength,</l>
                  <l>Their trembling heads bow to a prostrate length;</l>
                  <l>So forc'd fell he; So Immaturely Death</l>
                  <l>Stifled his able heart and active breath.</l>
                  <l>The world scarce knew him yet, his early Soule</l>
                  <l>Had but new-broke her day, and rather stole</l>
                  <l>A sight, than gave one; as if su'bt'ly she</l>
                  <l>Would learn our stock, but hide his treasurie.</l>
                  <l>His years (should time lay both his <hi>wings</hi> and <hi>glasse</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unto his charge) could not be summ'd (alas!)</l>
                  <l>To a full <hi>score</hi>; Though in so short a span</l>
                  <l>His riper thoughts had purchas'd more of man</l>
                  <l>Than all those worthless livers, which yet quick,</l>
                  <l>Have quite outgone their own <hi>Arithmetick.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He seiz'd perfections, and without a dull</l>
                  <l>And mossie <hi>gray</hi> possess'd a solid skull,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:66031:14"/>No Crooked knowledge neither, nor did he</l>
                  <l>Wear the friends name for Ends and policie,</l>
                  <l>And then lay'd by; As those <hi>lost Youths</hi> of th'stage</l>
                  <l>Who only flourish'd for the <hi>Play's</hi> short age</l>
                  <l>And then retir'd, like <hi>Iewels</hi> in each part</l>
                  <l>He wore his friends, But chiefly at his heart.</l>
                  <l>Nor was it only in this he did excell,</l>
                  <l>His equall valour could as much, as well.</l>
                  <l>He knew no <hi>fear</hi> but of his <hi>God</hi>; yet durst</l>
                  <l>No injurie, nor (as some have <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e'r pur'st</l>
                  <l>The sweat and tears of others, yet would be</l>
                  <l>More forward in a royall gallantrie</l>
                  <l>Than all those vast pretenders, which of late</l>
                  <l>Swell'd in the ruines of their King and State.</l>
                  <l>He weav'd not <hi>Self-ends,</hi> and the <hi>Publick</hi> good</l>
                  <l>Into one piece nor with the peoples bloud</l>
                  <l>Fill'd his own veins; In all the doubtfull way</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Conscience</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> rul'd him. O that day</l>
                  <l>When like the <hi>Fathers</hi> in the <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Cloud</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I mist thy face! I might in ev'ry <hi>Crowd</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>See Armes like thine, and men advance, but none</l>
                  <l>So neer to lightning mov'd, nor so fell on.</l>
                  <l>Have you observ'd how soon the nimble <hi>Eye</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Brings th' <hi>Object</hi> to <hi>Conceit,</hi> and doth so vic</l>
                  <l>Performance with the <hi>Soul,</hi> that you would swear</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Act</hi> and <hi>apprehension</hi> both lodg'd there,</l>
                  <l>Just so mov'd he: like <hi>short</hi> his active hand</l>
                  <l>Drew bloud, e'r well the foe could understand.</l>
                  <l>But here I lost him. Whether the last turn</l>
                  <l>Of thy few sands call'd on thy hastie urn,</l>
                  <l>Or some fierce rapid fate (hid from the Eye)</l>
                  <l>Hath hurl'd thee Pris'ner to some distant skye</l>
                  <l>I cannot tell, but that I doe believe</l>
                  <l>Thy Courage such as scorn'd a base Reprieve.</l>
                  <l>What ever 'twas, whether that day thy breath</l>
                  <l>Suffer'd a <hi>Civill</hi> or the <hi>Common</hi> death,</l>
                  <l>Which I doe most suspect, and that I have</l>
                  <l>Fail'd in the <hi>glories</hi> of so known a grave,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:66031:14"/>Though thy lov'd ashes misse me, and mine Eyes</l>
                  <l>Had no acquaintance with thy Exequies,</l>
                  <l>Nor at the last farewell, torn from thy sight</l>
                  <l>On the <hi>Cold sheet</hi> have fix'd a <hi>sad delight,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet what e'r pious hand (in stead of mine)</l>
                  <l>Hath done this office to that dust of thine,</l>
                  <l>And till thou rise again from thy low bed</l>
                  <l>Lent a Cheap pillow to thy quiet head,</l>
                  <l>Though but a private <hi>turffe,</hi> it can do more</l>
                  <l>To keep thy name and memory in store</l>
                  <l>Than all those <hi>Lordly fooles</hi> which lock their bones</l>
                  <l>In the dumb piles of Chested brasse, and stones.</l>
                  <l>Th'art rich in thy own fame, and needest not</l>
                  <l>These <hi>Marble-frailties,</hi> nor the <hi>gilded blot</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of posthume honours; There is not one sand</l>
                  <l>Sleeps o'r thy grave, but can outbid that hand</l>
                  <l>And pencill too, so that of force wee must</l>
                  <l>Confesse their <hi>heaps</hi> shew lesser than thy <hi>dust.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And (blessed soule!) though this my sorrow can</l>
                  <l>Adde nought to thy perfections, yet as man</l>
                  <l>Subject to Envy, and the common fate</l>
                  <l>It may redeem thee to a fairer date;</l>
                  <l>As some blind Dial, when the day is done,</l>
                  <l>Can tell us at mid-night, <hi>There was a Sun,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So these perhaps, though much beneath thy fame,</l>
                  <l>May keep some weak remembrance of thy name,</l>
                  <l>And to the faith of better times Commend</l>
                  <l>Thy loyall upright life, and gallant End.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nomen &amp; arma locum servant, te, amice, nequivi</l>
                  <l>Conspicere,—</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:66031:15"/>
               <head>Upon a Cloke lent him by Mr. <hi>I. Ridsley.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>HEre, take again thy <hi>Sack-cloth</hi>! and thank heav'n</l>
               <l>Thy Courtship hath not kill'd me; Is't not Even</l>
               <l>Whether wee dye by peecemeale, or at once</l>
               <l>Since both but ruine, why then for the nonce</l>
               <l>Didst husband my afflictions, and cast o're</l>
               <l>Me this forc'd <hi>Hurdle</hi> to inflame the score?</l>
               <l>Had I neer <hi>London</hi> in this <hi>Rug</hi> been seen</l>
               <l>Without doubt I had executed been</l>
               <l>For some bold <hi>Irish</hi> spy, and crosse a sledge</l>
               <l>Had layn mess'd up for their <hi>soure gates</hi> and <hi>bridge.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When first I bore it, my oppressed feer.</l>
               <l>Would needs perswade me, 'twas some <hi>leaden sheet</hi>;</l>
               <l>Such deep Impressions, and such dangerous holes</l>
               <l>Were made, that I began to doubt my soals,</l>
               <l>And ev'ry step (so neer necessity)</l>
               <l>Devoutly wish'd some honest Cobler by,</l>
               <l>Besides it was so short, the <hi>Iewish</hi> rag</l>
               <l>Seem'd Circumcis'd, but had a <hi>Gentile</hi> shag.</l>
               <l>Hadst thou been with me on that day, when wee</l>
               <l>Left craggie <hi>Biston,</hi> and the fatall <hi>Dee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When beaten with fresh storms, and late mishap</l>
               <l>It shar'd the office of a <hi>Cloke,</hi> and <hi>Cap,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To see how 'bout my clouded head it stood</l>
               <l>Like a thick <hi>Turband,</hi> or some Lawyers <hi>Hood,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>While the stiffe, hollow pletes on ev'ry side</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Conduit-pipes</hi> rain'd from the <hi>Bearded hide,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I know thou wouldst in spite of that day's fate</l>
               <l>Let loose thy mirth at my new shape and state,</l>
               <l>And with a shallow smile or two professe</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Sarazin</hi> had lost the <hi>Clowted Dresse.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Didst ever see the <hi>good wife</hi> (as they say)</l>
               <l>March in her short cloke on the <hi>Christning</hi> day,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:66031:15"/>With what soft motions she salutes the Church,</l>
               <l>And leaves the Bedrid Mother in the lurch;</l>
               <l>Just so Jogg'd I, while my dull horse did trudge</l>
               <l>Like a Circuit-beast plagu'd with a goutie Judge.</l>
               <l>But this was Civill. I have since known mo<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</l>
               <l>And worser pranks: One night (as heretofore</l>
               <l>Th' hast known) for want of change (a thing which I</l>
               <l>And <hi>Bias</hi> us'd before me) I did lye</l>
               <l>Pure <hi>Adami<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> and simply for that end</l>
               <l>Resolv'd, and made this for my bosome-<hi>friend.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O that thou hadst been there next morn, that I</l>
               <l>Might teach thee new <hi>Micro-cosmo graphie</hi>!</l>
               <l>Thou wouldst have ta'ne me, as I naked stood,</l>
               <l>For one of th' <hi>seven pillars</hi> before the sloud,</l>
               <l>Such <hi>Characters</hi> and <hi>Hierogliphicks</hi> were</l>
               <l>In one night wo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, that thou mightst justly swear</l>
               <l>I'd slept in <hi>Cere-cloth,</hi> or at <hi>Bedlam</hi> where</l>
               <l>The mad men lodge in straw, I'le not forbear</l>
               <l>To tell thee all, his wild <hi>Impress</hi> and <hi>tricks</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like <hi>Speeds</hi> old <hi>Britans</hi> made me look, or <hi>Pitts</hi>;</l>
               <l>His villanous, biting, <hi>Wire-embraces</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had seal'd in me more strange formes and faces</l>
               <l>Than <hi>Children</hi> see in dreams, or thou hast read</l>
               <l>In <hi>Arras, Puppet-playes,</hi> and <hi>Ginger-bread,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>angled Schemes,</hi> and <hi>Crosses</hi> that bred fear</l>
               <l>Of being handled by some <hi>Conjurer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And neerer thou wouldst think (such <hi>strokes</hi> were drawn)</l>
               <l>I'd been some rough statue of <hi>Fetter-lane,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nay, I believe, had I that instant been</l>
               <l>By <hi>Surgeons</hi> or <hi>Apothecaries</hi> seen,</l>
               <l>They had Condemned my raz'd skin to be</l>
               <l>Some walking <hi>Herball,</hi> or <hi>Anatomie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But (thanks to th'day!) 'tis off. I'd now advise</l>
               <l>Thee friend to put this peece to Merchandize;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Pedlars</hi> of our age have business yet,</l>
               <l>And gladly would against the <hi>Fayr-day</hi> fit</l>
               <l>Themselves with such a <hi>Roofe,</hi> that can secure</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Wares</hi> from <hi>Dogs and Cats</hi> rain'd in <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>owre,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:66031:16"/>It shall performe; or if this will not doe</l>
               <l>'Twill take the <hi>Ale-wives</hi> sure; 'Twill make them <hi>two</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fine Roomes of <hi>One,</hi> and spread upon a stick</l>
               <l>Is a partition without Lime or Brick.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Horn'd</hi> obstinacie! how my heart doth fret</l>
               <l>To think what <hi>Mouthes</hi> and <hi>Elbowes</hi> it would set</l>
               <l>In a wet day? have you for two pence e're</l>
               <l>Seen King <hi>Harryes</hi> Chappell at <hi>Westminster,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where in their dustie gowns of <hi>Brasse</hi> and <hi>Stone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Judges lye, and markt you how each one</l>
               <l>In sturdie Marble-plets about the knee</l>
               <l>Bears up to shew his legs and symmetrie?</l>
               <l>Iust so would this; That I think't weav'd upon</l>
               <l>Some stiffneckt <hi>Brownists</hi> exercising loome.</l>
               <l>O that thou hadst it when this Jugling fate</l>
               <l>Of Souldierie first seiz'd me! at what rate</l>
               <l>Would I have bought it then, what was there but</l>
               <l>I would have giv'n for the <hi>Compendious h<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tt?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I doe not doubt but (if the weight could please,)</l>
               <l>'Twould guard me better than a <hi>Lapland-lease,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or a <hi>German</hi> shirt with Inchanted lint</l>
               <l>Stuft'd through, and th'devils <hi>beard</hi> and <hi>face</hi> weav'd in't.</l>
               <l>But I have done. And think not, friend, that I</l>
               <l>This freedome took to Jeere thy Courtesie,</l>
               <l>I thank thee for't, and I believe my Muse</l>
               <l>So known to thee, thou'lt not suspect abuse;</l>
               <l>She did this, 'cause (perhaps) thy <hi>love</hi> paid thus</l>
               <l>Might with my <hi>thanks</hi> out-live thy <hi>Cloke,</hi> and <hi>Vs.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Upon Mr.<hi>Fletchers</hi> Playes, publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, 1647.</head>
               <l>I Knew thee not, not durst <hi>attendance</hi> strive</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Labell</hi> to <hi>wit, Verser remonstrative,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in some <hi>Suburb-page</hi> (scandal to thine)</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Lent</hi> before a <hi>Christmasse</hi> scatter mine,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:66031:16"/>This speaks thee not, since at the utmost rate</l>
               <l>Such <hi>remnants</hi> from thy <hi>piece</hi> Intreat their date;</l>
               <l>Nor can I <hi>dub</hi> the <hi>Coppy,</hi> or afford</l>
               <l>Titles to <hi>swell</hi> the <hi>reare</hi> of <hi>Verse</hi> with Lord,</l>
               <l>Nor politickly big to <hi>Inch</hi> low fame</l>
               <l>Stretch in the <hi>glories</hi> of a strangers name,</l>
               <l>And Clip those <hi>Bayes</hi> I Court, weak <hi>striver</hi> I,</l>
               <l>But a faint <hi>Echo</hi> unto <hi>Poetrie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I have not <hi>Clothes</hi> t'adopt me, not must sit</l>
               <l>For <hi>Plush</hi> and <hi>Velvets</hi> sake <hi>Esquire</hi> of wit,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Modestie</hi> these <hi>Crosses</hi> would improve,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Rags</hi> neer thee, some <hi>Reverence</hi>may move.</l>
               <l>I did believe (great <hi>Beaumont</hi> being dead,)</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Widow'd Muse</hi> slept on his <hi>flowrie bed</hi>;</l>
               <l>But I am <hi>richly</hi> Cosen'd, and can see</l>
               <l>Wit <hi>transmigrates,</hi> his <hi>Spirit</hi> stayd with thee,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>doubly</hi> advantag'd by thy <hi>single</hi> pen</l>
               <l>In <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death</hi> now treads the <hi>Stage</hi> agen;</l>
               <l>And thus are wee freed from that <hi>dearth</hi> of wit</l>
               <l>Which <hi>starv'd</hi> the Land since into <hi>Schismes</hi> split,</l>
               <l>Wherein th'hast done so much, wee must needs guesse</l>
               <l>Wits last <hi>Edition</hi> is now i'th <hi>Presse,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For thou hast <hi>drain'd</hi> Invention, and he</l>
               <l>That writes hereafter, doth but <hi>pillage</hi> thee.</l>
               <l>But thou hast <hi>plotts</hi>; and will not the <hi>Kirk</hi> strain</l>
               <l>At the <hi>Designe</hi> of such a <hi>Tragick brain?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Will they themselves think safe, when they shall see</l>
               <l>Thy most <hi>abominable policie?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Will not the <hi>Eares</hi> assemble, and think't fit</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Synod fast,</hi> and <hi>pray,</hi> against thy wit?</l>
               <l>But they'le not <hi>lyre</hi> in such an <hi>idle Quest,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou doest but <hi>kill,</hi> and <hi>Circumvent</hi> in <hi>Iest,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And when thy anger'd Muse <hi>swells</hi> to a blow</l>
               <l>'Tis but for <hi>Field's,</hi> or <hi>Swansteed</hi>'s overthrow.</l>
               <l>Yet shall these <hi>Conquests</hi> of thy <hi>Bayes</hi> outlive</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Scotish zeale,</hi> and <hi>Compacts</hi> made to grieve</l>
               <l>The <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Spirits,</hi> and when such deeds fayle</l>
               <l>Of their foule Ends, a <hi>faire name</hi> is thy <hi>Bayle.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:66031:17"/>But (happy thou!) ne'r saw'st these <hi>stormes,</hi> our <hi>aire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Teem'd</hi> with even in thy time, though <hi>seeming faire</hi>;</l>
               <l>Thy gentle <hi>Soule</hi> meant for the <hi>shade,</hi> and <hi>ease</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Withdrew betimes into the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi>;</l>
               <l>So <hi>neasted</hi> in some Hospitable shore</l>
               <l>The <hi>Hermit-angler,</hi> when the <hi>mid-Seas</hi> roare</l>
               <l>Packs up his <hi>lines,</hi> and (ere the tempest <hi>raves,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Retyres, and leaves his <hi>station</hi> to the <hi>waves.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus thou diedst almost with our <hi>peace,</hi> and wee</l>
               <l>This <hi>breathing time</hi> thy last fair <hi>Issue</hi> see,</l>
               <l>Which I think such (if <hi>needless Ink</hi> not soyle</l>
               <l>So <hi>Choice a Muse,</hi>) others are but thy <hi>foile</hi>;</l>
               <l>This, or that <hi>age</hi> may write, but never see</l>
               <l>A <hi>Wit</hi> that dares run <hi>Paralell</hi> with thee.</l>
               <l>True, <hi>BEN</hi> must live! but bate <hi>him,</hi> and thou hast</l>
               <l>Undone all <hi>future wits,</hi> and match'd the <hi>past.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Upon the <hi>Poems</hi> and <hi>Playes</hi> of the ever memorable Mr. <hi>William Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>I Did but <hi>see</hi> thee! and how <hi>vain</hi> it is</l>
               <l>To <hi>vex</hi> thee for it with <hi>Remonstrances,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though <hi>things</hi> in fashion, let those <hi>Iudge,</hi> who sit</l>
               <l>Their <hi>twelve pence</hi> out, to <hi>clap</hi> their <hi>hands</hi> at <hi>wit;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I fear to <hi>Sinne</hi> thus <hi>neer</hi> thee; for (<hi>great Saint!</hi>)</l>
               <l>'Tis known, <hi>true beauty</hi> hath no need of <hi>paint.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet, since a <hi>Labell</hi> fixt to thy fair <hi>Hearse</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is all the <hi>Mode,</hi> and <hi>tears</hi> put into <hi>Verse</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can teach <hi>Posterity</hi> our present <hi>griefe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And their own <hi>losse,</hi> but never give <hi>reliefe</hi>;</l>
               <l>I'le tell them (and a <hi>truth</hi> which needs no <hi>passe,</hi>)</l>
               <l>That <hi>wit</hi> in <hi>Cartwright</hi> at her <hi>Zenith</hi> was,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arts, Fancy, Language,</hi> all <hi>Conven'd</hi> in thee,</l>
               <l>With those <hi>grand Miracles</hi> which <hi>deifie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:66031:17"/>The old worlds <hi>Writings,</hi> kept yet from the <hi>fire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Because they <hi>force</hi> these worst times to <hi>admire.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy matchless <hi>Genius,</hi> in all thou didst write,</l>
               <l>Like the <hi>Sun,</hi> wrought with such <hi>stayd beat,</hi> and <hi>light,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That not a <hi>line</hi> (to the most <hi>Critick</hi> he)</l>
               <l>Offends with <hi>flashes,</hi> or <hi>obscuritie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When thou the <hi>wild</hi> of <hi>humours</hi> trackst, thy <hi>pen</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So Imitates that <hi>Motley slock</hi> in men,</l>
               <l>As if thou hadst in all their <hi>bosomes</hi> been,</l>
               <l>And seen those <hi>Leopards</hi> that lurk within.</l>
               <l>The am'rous <hi>Youth</hi> steals from thy <hi>Courtly page</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>vow'd Addresse,</hi> the <hi>Souldier</hi> his <hi>brave rage</hi>;</l>
               <l>And those <hi>soft beauteous Readers</hi> whose <hi>looks</hi> can</l>
               <l>Make some men <hi>Poets,</hi> and make any 'man</l>
               <l>A <hi>Lover,</hi> when thy <hi>Slave</hi> but <hi>seems</hi> to dye,</l>
               <l>Turn all his <hi>Mourners,</hi> and melt at the <hi>Eye.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus, thou thy <hi>thoughts</hi> hast <hi>drest</hi> in such a <hi>strain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As doth not only <hi>speak,</hi> but <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>raign,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor are those <hi>bodyes</hi> they assum'd, <hi>dark Clouds,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or a <hi>thick bark,</hi> but <hi>clear, transparent shrouds,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which who <hi>lookes</hi> on, the <hi>Rayes</hi> so strongly beat</l>
               <l>They'l <hi>brushe</hi> and <hi>warm</hi> him with a <hi>quickning heat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So <hi>Souls</hi> shine at the <hi>Eyes,</hi> and <hi>Pearls</hi> display</l>
               <l>Through the <hi>loose-Chrystal-streams a glaunce of day.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But what's all this unto a <hi>Royall Test?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou art the <hi>Man,</hi> whom great <hi>Charles</hi> so exprest!</l>
               <l>Then let the <hi>Crowd</hi> refrain their <hi>needless humme,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When <hi>Thunder</hi> speaks, then <hi>Squibs</hi> and <hi>Winds</hi> are <hi>dumb.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:66031:18"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:66031:18"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:66031:19"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:66031:19"/>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:66031:20"/>
               <head>To the best, and most accomplish'd Couple—</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BLessings as rich and fragrant crown your heads</l>
                  <l>As the mild heav'n on <hi>Roses</hi> sheds,</l>
                  <l>When at their Cheeks (like Pearls) they weare</l>
                  <l>The Clouds that court them in a teare,</l>
                  <l>And may they be fed from above</l>
                  <l>By him which first ordain'd your love!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fresh as the <hi>houres</hi> may all your pleasures be,</l>
                  <l>And healthfull as <hi>Eternitie</hi>!</l>
                  <l>Sweet as the flowres <hi>first breath,</hi> and Close</l>
                  <l>As th' <hi>unseen spreadings</hi> of the Rose,</l>
                  <l>When he unfolds his Curtain'd head,</l>
                  <l>And makes his bosome the <hi>Suns bed.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Soft as <hi>your selves</hi> run your whole lifes, and cleare</l>
                  <l>As your own <hi>glasse,</hi> or <hi>what shines</hi> there;</l>
                  <l>Smooth as heav'ns <hi>face,</hi> and bright as he</l>
                  <l>When without <hi>Mask,</hi> or <hi>Tiffanie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In all your time not one <hi>Iarre</hi> meet</l>
                  <l>But peace as silent as his <hi>seet.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like the dayes <hi>Warmth</hi> may all your Comforts be,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Untoil'd</hi> for, and <hi>Serene</hi> as he,</l>
                  <l>Yet free and full as is that <hi>sheafe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of Sun-beams gilding ev'ry leafe,</l>
                  <l>When now the <hi>tyrant-heat</hi> expires</l>
                  <l>And his Cool'd locks breath milder fires.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And as those <hi>parcell'd glories</hi> he doth shed</l>
                  <l>Are the <hi>faire Issues</hi> of his head,</l>
                  <l>Which ne'r so distant are soon known</l>
                  <l>By th' <hi>heat</hi> and <hi>lustre</hi> for his own,</l>
                  <l>So may each branch of yours wee see</l>
                  <l>Your <hi>Coppyes,</hi> and our <hi>Wonders</hi> be!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:66031:20"/>
                  <l>And when no more on Earth you must remain</l>
                  <l>Invited hence to heav'n again,</l>
                  <l>Then may your vertuous, virgin-flames</l>
                  <l>Shine in those <hi>Heires</hi> of your fair names,</l>
                  <l>And teach the world that mysterie</l>
                  <l>Your selves in your Posteritie!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So you to both worlds shall <hi>rich presents</hi> bring,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>gather'd</hi> up to heav'n, leave here a <hi>Spring.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>An Elegie on the death of Mr. <hi>R. Hall,</hi> slain at <hi>Pontefract,</hi> 1684.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Knew it would be thus! and my Just fears</l>
                  <l>Of thy great spirit are Improv'd to tears.</l>
                  <l>Yet slow these not from any base distrust</l>
                  <l>Of a fair name, or that thy honour must</l>
                  <l>Confin'd to those cold reliques sadly sit</l>
                  <l>In the same Cell an obscure Anchorite.</l>
                  <l>Such low distempers <hi>Murther,</hi> they that must</l>
                  <l>Abuse thee so, <hi>weep</hi> not, but <hi>wound</hi> thy dust.</l>
                  <l>But I past such dimme Mourners can descrie</l>
                  <l>Thy same above all Clouds of obloquie,</l>
                  <l>And like the Sun with his victorious rayes</l>
                  <l>Charge through that darkness to the last of dayes.</l>
                  <l>'Tis true, fair <hi>Manhood</hi> hath a <hi>female</hi> Eye,</l>
                  <l>And tears are beauteous in a Victorie,</l>
                  <l>Not are wee so high-proofe, but griefe will find</l>
                  <l>Through all our guards a way to wound the mind;</l>
                  <l>But in thy fall what addes the brackish summe</l>
                  <l>More than a blott unto thy <hi>Martyrdome,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which scorns such wretched suffrages, and stands</l>
                  <l>More by thy single worth, than our whole bands,</l>
                  <l>Yet could the puling tribute rescue ought</l>
                  <l>In this sad lofle, or wert thou to be brought</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:66031:21"/>Back here by tears, I would in any wise</l>
                  <l>Pay down the summe, or quite Consume my Eyes.</l>
                  <l>Thou fel<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'st our double ruine, and this rent</l>
                  <l>Forc<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d in thy life shak'd both the <hi>Church and tent,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Learning in others steales them from the <hi>Van,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And basely wise <hi>Emasculates</hi> the man.</l>
                  <l>But lodged in thy brave soul the <hi>book<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sh seat</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Serve'd only as the light unto thy <hi>heat</hi>;</l>
                  <l>Thus when some quitted action, to their shame,</l>
                  <l>And only got a <hi>discreet towards</hi> name,</l>
                  <l>Thou with thy bloud mad'st purchase of renown,</l>
                  <l>And diedst the glory of the <hi>Sword</hi> and <hi>Gown</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy bloud hath hallow'd <hi>Pomfret,</hi> and this blow</l>
                  <l>(Prophan'd before) hath Church'd the Castle now.</l>
                  <l>Nor is't a Common valour we deplore,</l>
                  <l>But such as with <hi>fifteen</hi> a <hi>hundred</hi> bore,</l>
                  <l>And lightning like (not coopt within a wall)</l>
                  <l>In stormes of <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>steele</hi> fell on them all.</l>
                  <l>Thou went no <hi>wool-sack</hi> souldier, nor of those</l>
                  <l>Whose Courage lies in <hi>winking</hi> at their foes,</l>
                  <l>That live at <hi>loop-holes,</hi> and consume their breath</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Match</hi> or <hi>Pipes,</hi> and sometimes <hi>peepe</hi> at death;</l>
                  <l>No it were sinne to number these with thee,</l>
                  <l>But that (thus poiz'd) our losse wee better see.</l>
                  <l>The fair and open valour was thy <hi>shield,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And thy known station, the <hi>defying suld.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet these in thee I would not <hi>Voturs</hi> call.</l>
                  <l>But that this age must know, that thou hadst all.</l>
                  <l>Those richer graces that adorn'd thy mind</l>
                  <l>Like stars of the <hi>first magnitude,</hi> so shin'd,</l>
                  <l>That is oppos'd unto these lesser lights</l>
                  <l>All we can say, is this, <hi>They were fair nights.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Paty</hi> and <hi>Leamme</hi> did unite,</l>
                  <l>And though with <hi>Severall beames</hi> made up <hi>one light,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And such thy Judgement was, that I dare swear</l>
                  <l>Whole <hi>Counsels</hi> might as soon, and <hi>Synods</hi> erre.</l>
                  <l>But all these now are out! and as some <hi>Star</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hurl'd in Diurnall motions from far,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:66031:21"/>And seen to droop at night, is vainly sed</l>
                  <l>To fall, and find an <hi>Occidentall bed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though in that other world what wee Judge <hi>west</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Proves <hi>Elevation,</hi> and a new, fresh <hi>East.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So though our weaker sense den'es us sight</l>
                  <l>And bodies cannot trace the <hi>Spirits</hi> flight,</l>
                  <l>Wee know those graces to be still in thee,</l>
                  <l>But wing'd above us to eternitie.</l>
                  <l>Since then (thus flown) thou art so much refin'd,</l>
                  <l>That we can only reach thee with the mind,</l>
                  <l>I will not in this <hi>dark</hi> and <hi>narrow glasse</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let thy scant <hi>shadow</hi> for <hi>Perfections</hi> passe,</l>
                  <l>But leave thee to be read more high, more queint,</l>
                  <l>In thy own bloud a <hi>Souldier</hi> and a <hi>Saint.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>— Salve aetcrnum mihi maxime Palls!</l>
                  <l>AEteraumg; vale! —</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To my learned friend, Mr. <hi>T. Powell,</hi> upon His Translation of <hi>Malvezzi's</hi> Christian Politician.</head>
               <l>WEe thank you, worthy Sir, that now we see</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Malvezzi</hi> languag'd like our Infancie,</l>
               <l>And can without suspition entertain</l>
               <l>This forraign States-man to our brest or brain,</l>
               <l>You have enlarg'd his praise, and from your store</l>
               <l>By this Edition made his worth the more.</l>
               <l>Thus by your learned hand (amidst the <hi>corse</hi>)</l>
               <l>Outlandish plants thrive in our thankless soile,</l>
               <l>And wise men after death, by a strange fate,</l>
               <l>Lye <hi>Leiguer</hi> here, and beg to serve our <hi>State.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Italy</hi> now, though <hi>Mistris</hi> of the <hi>Bayes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Waits on this <hi>wreath,</hi> proud of a forraign praise,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:66031:22"/>For, wise <hi>Malvezzi,</hi> thou didst lye before</l>
               <l>Confin'd within the language of one shore,</l>
               <l>And like those <hi>Stars</hi> which neer the <hi>Poles</hi> doe steer</l>
               <l>Wer't but in one part of the <hi>Globe</hi> seen cleer,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Provence</hi> and <hi>Nap'es</hi> were the best and most</l>
               <l>Thou couldst thine in, fixt to that single Coast,</l>
               <l>Perhaps some <hi>Cardinal</hi> to be thought wise</l>
               <l>And honest too, would ask, <hi>what was thy price?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then thou must pack to <hi>Rome,</hi> where thou mightst lye</l>
               <l>E'r thou shouldst have new cloathes eternally,</l>
               <l>For though so neer the <hi>seav'n hills,</hi> ne'rthelesse</l>
               <l>Thou cam'st to <hi>Antwerp</hi> for thy <hi>Roman</hi> dresse:</l>
               <l>But now then art come hither, thou mayst run</l>
               <l>Through any Clime as well known as the <hi>Sun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in thy <hi>sev'rall dresses</hi> like the <hi>year</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Challenge acquaintance with each peopled Sphere.</l>
               <l>Come then rare Politicians of the time,</l>
               <l>Brains of some standing, Elders in our Clime,</l>
               <l>See here the method: A wise, solid stare</l>
               <l>Is quick in acting, friendly in debate,</l>
               <l>Ioynt in advice, in resolutions just,</l>
               <l>Mild in successe, true to the Common trust.</l>
               <l>It cements ruptures, and by gentle hand</l>
               <l>Allayes the heat and burnings of a land,</l>
               <l>Religion guides it, and in all the Tract</l>
               <l>Designes so twist, that heav'n confirms the act;</l>
               <l>If from these lists you wander as you steere,</l>
               <l>Look back, and <hi>Caltchile</hi> your actions here,</l>
               <l>These are the <hi>Marks</hi> to which true States-men tend,</l>
               <l>And <hi>greatness</hi> here with <hi>goodness</hi> hath one End.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:66031:22"/>
               <head>To my worthy friend Master <hi>T. Lewes.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>SEes not my friend, what a deep snow</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Candies</hi> our Countries wooddy brow?</l>
               <l>The yeelding branch his load scarse bears</l>
               <l>Opprest with snow, and <hi>frozen tears,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>While the <hi>dumb</hi> rivers slowly float,</l>
               <l>All bound up in an <hi>Icie Coat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let us meet then! and while this world</l>
               <l>In wild <hi>Excentricks</hi> now is hurld,</l>
               <l>Keep wee, like nature, the same <hi>Key,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And walk in our forefathers way;</l>
               <l>Why any more cast wee an Eye</l>
               <l>On what <hi>may come,</hi> not what is <hi>nigh?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Why vex our selves with <hi>feare,</hi> or <hi>hope</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And cares beyond our <hi>Horoscope?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who into future times would peere</l>
               <l>Looks ost beyond his terme set here,</l>
               <l>And cannot goe into those grounds</l>
               <l>But through a <hi>Church-yard</hi> which them bounds;</l>
               <l>Sorrows and sighes and searches spend</l>
               <l>And draw our bottome to an end,</l>
               <l>But discreet Joyes lengthen the lease</l>
               <l>Without which life were a disease,</l>
               <l>And who this age a Mourner goes,</l>
               <l>Doth with his tears but seed his foes.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:66031:23"/>
               <head>To the most Excellently accomplish'd, Mrs <hi>K. Philips.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>SAy wittie fair one, from what Sphere</l>
               <l>Flow these rich numbers you shed here?</l>
               <l>For sure such <hi>Incantations</hi> come</l>
               <l>From thence, which strike your Readers dumbe,</l>
               <l>A strain, whose measures gently meet</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Virgin-lovers,</hi> or times <hi>feet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where language <hi>Smiles,</hi> and accents rise</l>
               <l>As quick, and pleasing as your <hi>Eyes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Poem</hi> smooth, and in each line</l>
               <l>Soft as <hi>your selfe,</hi> yet <hi>Masculine</hi>;</l>
               <l>Where not Coorse trifles blot the page</l>
               <l>With matter borrow'd from the age,</l>
               <l>But thoughts as Innocent, and high</l>
               <l>As <hi>Angels</hi> have, or <hi>Saints</hi> that dye.</l>
               <l>These Raptures when I first did see</l>
               <l>New miracles in Poetrie,</l>
               <l>And by a hand, the<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r good would misse</l>
               <l>His <hi>Bayes</hi> and <hi>Fountaines</hi> but to kisse,</l>
               <l>My weaker <hi>Genius</hi> (cr<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ss<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to fashion)</l>
               <l>Slept in a silent admiration,</l>
               <l>A Rescue, by whole grace disguise</l>
               <l>Pretenders oft have past for wise,</l>
               <l>And yet as <hi>Pilgrims</hi> humbly touch</l>
               <l>Those <hi>Shrines</hi> to which they bow so much,</l>
               <l>And Clouds in Courtship flock, and run</l>
               <l>To be the Mask unto the Sun,</l>
               <l>So I concluded, It was true</l>
               <l>I might at distance worship you</l>
               <l>A <hi>Persian</hi> Votarie, and say</l>
               <l>It was your light shew'd me the way.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Lodestones</hi> guide the duller <hi>Steele,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And high perfections are the <hi>Wheele</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:66031:23"/>Which moves the lesse, for gifts divine</l>
               <l>Are strung upon a <hi>Vi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al line</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which touch<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by you, Excites in all</l>
               <l>Affectio<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>Epidemicall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And this made me (a truth most fit)</l>
               <l>Adde my weak <hi>Eccho</hi> to your wit,</l>
               <l>Which pardon, Lady, for Assayes</l>
               <l>Obscure as these might blast your Bayes,</l>
               <l>As Common hands soyle <hi>Flowres,</hi> and make</l>
               <l>That dew they wear, <hi>weepe</hi> the mistake.</l>
               <l>But I'le wash off the <hi>staine,</hi> and vow</l>
               <l>No <hi>Lawrel</hi> growes, but for your <hi>Brow.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>An Epitaph upon the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Second Daughter to his late Majestie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOuth, Beauty, Vertue, Innocence</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns royall, and select Expence,</l>
                  <l>With Virgin-tears, and sighs divine,</l>
                  <l>Sit here the <hi>Genii</hi> of this shrine,</l>
                  <l>Where now (thy fair soule wing'd away,)</l>
                  <l>They guard the <hi>Casket</hi> where she lay.</l>
                  <l>Thou hadst, e'r thou the light couldst see,</l>
                  <l>Sorrowes layd up, and stor'd for thee,</l>
                  <l>Thou suck'dst in woes, and the <hi>brests</hi> lent</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Milk</hi> to thee, but to lament;</l>
                  <l>Thy portion here was <hi>griefe,</hi> thy years</l>
                  <l>Distilld no other rain, but tears,</l>
                  <l>Tears without noise, but (understood)</l>
                  <l>As lowd, and shrill as any bloud;</l>
                  <l>Thou seem'st a <hi>Rose bud</hi> born in <hi>Snow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A flowre of purpose sprung to bow</l>
                  <l>To headless tempests, and the rage</l>
                  <l>Of an Incensed, stormie Age,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:66031:24"/>Others, e're their afflictions grow,</l>
                  <l>Are tim'd, and season'd for the blow,</l>
                  <l>But thine, as <hi>Rhumes</hi> the tend'rest part,</l>
                  <l>Fell on a <hi>young</hi> and <hi>harmless</hi> heart.</l>
                  <l>And yet as <hi>Balm-trees</hi> gently spend</l>
                  <l>Their tears for those, that doe them rend,</l>
                  <l>So mild and pious thou wert seen,</l>
                  <l>Though full of <hi>Suffrings,</hi> free from <hi>spleen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou didst nor murmure, nor revile,</l>
                  <l>But d<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ank'st thy <hi>wormwood</hi> with a <hi>smile.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As envious Eyes blast, and Infect</l>
                  <l>And cause misfortunes by aspect,</l>
                  <l>So thy sad stars dispens'd to thee</l>
                  <l>No Influxe, but Calamitie,</l>
                  <l>They view'd thee with <hi>Ecclypsed</hi> rayes,</l>
                  <l>And but the <hi>back-side</hi> of bright dayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>These were the Comforts she had here,</l>
                  <l>As by an unseen hand 'tis cleer,</l>
                  <l>Which now she reads, and smiling wears</l>
                  <l>A Crown with him, who wipes off tears.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To Sir <hi>William D' avenant,</hi> upon his <hi>Gondibert.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>WEll, wee are rescued land by thy rare Pen</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poets</hi> shall live, when <hi>Princes</hi> dye like men.</l>
               <l>Th'hast cleer'd the prospect to our harmless <hi>Hill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of late years clouded with imputed Ill,</l>
               <l>And thy <hi>Soft, youthfull couples</hi> there may move</l>
               <l>As chast as <hi>Stars</hi> converse and smile above.</l>
               <l>Th'hast taught their <hi>Language,</hi> and their <hi>love</hi> to flow</l>
               <l>Calme as <hi>Rose-leafes,</hi> and coole as <hi>Virgin-snow,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which doubly feasts us, being so refin'd</l>
               <l>They both <hi>delight,</hi> and <hi>dignifie</hi> the mind,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:66031:24"/>Like to the watrie Musick of some Spring,</l>
               <l>Whose pleasant flowings at once <hi>wash</hi> and <hi>sing.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And where before <hi>Heroick Poems</hi> were</l>
               <l>Made up of <hi>Spirits, Prodigies,</hi> and <hi>fear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And shew'd (through all the <hi>Me<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ancholy flight,</hi>)</l>
               <l>Like some dark Region overcast with night,</l>
               <l>As if the Poet had been quite dismay'd,</l>
               <l>While only <hi>Giants</hi> and <hi>Inchantments</hi> sway'd,</l>
               <l>Thou like the <hi>Sun,</hi> whose Eye brooks no disguise</l>
               <l>Hast Chas'd them hence, and with Discoveries</l>
               <l>So rare and learned fill'd the place, that wee</l>
               <l>Those fam'd <hi>Grandeza's</hi> find out-done by thee,</l>
               <l>And under-foot see all those <hi>Vizards</hi> hurl'd,</l>
               <l>Which bred the wonder of the former world.</l>
               <l>'I was dull to sit, as our fore-fathers did,</l>
               <l>At <hi>Crums</hi> and <hi>Voyders,</hi> and because unbid</l>
               <l>Refrain wise appetite. This made thy <hi>fire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Break through the <hi>ashes</hi> of thy aged <hi>Sire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To lend the world such a Convincing light</l>
               <l>As shewes his <hi>fancy</hi> darker than his sight.</l>
               <l>Nor was't alone the <hi>bars</hi> and <hi>length</hi> of dayes</l>
               <l>(Though those gave <hi>strength</hi> and <hi>starwe</hi> to his <hi>bayes,</hi>)</l>
               <l>Encounter'd thee, but what's an old Complaint</l>
               <l>And kills the fancy, a <hi>forlorn Restraint</hi>;</l>
               <l>How couldst thou mur'd in solitarie stones</l>
               <l>Dresse <hi>BIRTH A'S simi'es,</hi> though well thou might'st her <hi>grones?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, strangely Eloquent, thy self divide</l>
               <l>'Twixt <hi>Sad misfortunes,</hi> and a <hi>Bloomie Bride?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Through all the tenour of thy ample Song</l>
               <l>Spun from thy own rich store, and shar'd among</l>
               <l>Those fair <hi>Adventurers,</hi> we plainly see</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Imputed</hi> gifts, <hi>Inherent</hi> are in thee.</l>
               <l>Then live for ever (and by high desert)</l>
               <l>In thy own <hi>mirrour,</hi> matchless <hi>Gondibert,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in <hi>bright Birtha</hi> leave thy <hi>love</hi> Inshrin'd</l>
               <l>Fresh as her <hi>Emrauld,</hi> and <hi>fair</hi> as her <hi>mind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>While all Confesse thee (as they ought to doe)</l>
               <l>The Prince of <hi>Poets,</hi> and of <hi>Lovers</hi> too.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:66031:25"/>
               <head>Tristium Lib. 5<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Eleg. 3<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. To his fellow-Poets at <hi>Rome,</hi> upon the birth-day of <hi>Bacchus.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>THis is the day (blith god of <hi>Sack</hi>) which wee</l>
               <l>If I mistake not, Consecrate to thee,</l>
               <l>When the soft <hi>Rose</hi> wee marry to the <hi>Bayes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And warm'd with thy own wine reherse thy praise,</l>
               <l>'Mongst whom (while to thy <hi>Poet</hi> fate gave way)</l>
               <l>I have been held no small part of the day,</l>
               <l>But now, dull'd with the Cold <hi>Bears</hi> frozen seat,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sarmatia</hi> holds me, and the warlike <hi>Gere.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My former life, unlike to this my last,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Romes</hi> best wits of thy full Cup did tast,</l>
               <l>Who since have seen the savage <hi>Pontick</hi> band,</l>
               <l>And all the <hi>Choler</hi> of the Sea and Land:</l>
               <l>Whether sad Chance, or heav'n hath this design'd,</l>
               <l>And at my birth some fatall Planet shin'd,</l>
               <l>Of right thou shouldst the <hi>Sisters</hi> knots undoe,</l>
               <l>And tree thy <hi>Votarie</hi> and <hi>Poet</hi> too.</l>
               <l>Or are you God (like us) in such a slate</l>
               <l>As cannot alter the decrees of fate</l>
               <l>I know with much adoe thou didst obtain</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Iovial godhead,</hi> and on earth thy pain</l>
               <l>Was no whit lesse, so wandring thou didst run</l>
               <l>To the <hi>Getes</hi> too, and Snow-weeping <hi>Strymon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>Persia, Ganges,</hi> and what ever streams</l>
               <l>The thirsly <hi>Moon</hi> drinks in the mid-day beames.</l>
               <l>But thou wert twice-born, and the Fates to thee</l>
               <l>(To make all sure) doubled thy miserie,</l>
               <l>My suffrings too are many: if it be</l>
               <l>Held safe for me to boast adversitie,</l>
               <l>Nor was't a Common blow, but from above</l>
               <l>Like his, that died for Imitating <hi>Iove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which when thou heardst, a ruine so divine</l>
               <l>And <hi>Mother</hi>-like, should make thee pitty mine.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:66031:25"/>And on this day, which <hi>Poets</hi> unto thee</l>
               <l>Crown with full bowles, ask, <hi>what's become of me?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Help</hi> bucksome God then! so may thy lov'd <hi>Vine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Swarm</hi> with the num'rous grape, and <hi>big</hi> with Wine</l>
               <l>Load the kind <hi>Elm,</hi> and so thy <hi>Orgyes</hi> be</l>
               <l>With priest lowd showtes, and <hi>Satyrs</hi> kept to thee!</l>
               <l>So may in death <hi>Lycurgus</hi> ne'r be blest,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Pentheus</hi> wandring ghost find any rest!</l>
               <l>And so for ever bright (thy Chiefe desires,)</l>
               <l>May thy <hi>wifes crown</hi> out shine the lesser fires!</l>
               <l>It but now, mindfull of my love to thee,</l>
               <l>Thou wilt, in what thou canst, my helper be.</l>
               <l>You <hi>Gods</hi> have Commerce with your selves, try then</l>
               <l>If <hi>Caesar</hi> will restore me <hi>Rome</hi> agen.</l>
               <l>And you my trusty friends (the Jollie Crew</l>
               <l>Of careless <hi>Poets</hi>!) when, without me, you</l>
               <l>Perform this dayes glad Myst'ries, let it be</l>
               <l>Your first Appeal unto his Deitie,</l>
               <l>And let one of you (touch'd with my sad name)</l>
               <l>Mixing his wine tears, lay down the same,</l>
               <l>And (sighing) to the rest this thought Commend,</l>
               <l>O! There is <hi>Ovid</hi> now our banish'd friend?</l>
               <l>This doe, if in your brests I e'r deserv'd</l>
               <l>So large a share, nor spitefully reserv'd,</l>
               <l>Nor basely sold applause, or with a brow</l>
               <l>Condemning others, did my selfe allow.</l>
               <l>And may your happier wits grow lowd with fame</l>
               <l>As you (my best of friends!) preserve my name.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>De Ponto, Lib.3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. To his friends (after his many sollicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) refusing to petition <hi>Caesar</hi> for his releasement.</head>
               <l>YOu have Consum'd my language, and my pen</l>
               <l>Incens'd with begging scorns to write agen.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:66031:26"/>You grant, you knew my sute: My Muse, and I</l>
               <l>Had taught it you in frequent Elegie,</l>
               <l>That I believe (yet seal'd) you have divin'd</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Repetitions,</hi> and <hi>forestal'd</hi> my mind,</l>
               <l>So that my thronging Elegies, and I</l>
               <l>Have made you (more then <hi>Poets</hi>) prophesie.</l>
               <l>But I am now awak'd; forgive my dream</l>
               <l>VVhich made me Crosse the <hi>Proverb</hi> and the <hi>Stream,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And pardon, friends, that I so long have had</l>
               <l>Such good thoughts of you, I am not so mad</l>
               <l>As to continue them. You shall no more</l>
               <l>Complain of troublesome <hi>Verse,</hi> or write o're</l>
               <l>How I endanger you, and vex my <hi>s<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ife</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVith the sad legends of a banish'd life.</l>
               <l>I'le bear these plagues my selfe: for I have past</l>
               <l>Through greater ones, and can as well at last</l>
               <l>These pettie Crosses. 'Tis for some young beast</l>
               <l>To kick his bands, or with his neck releast</l>
               <l>From the sad Yoke. Know then, That as for me</l>
               <l>VVhom Fate hath us'd to such calamitie,</l>
               <l>I scorn her spite and yours, and freely dare</l>
               <l>The highest ills your malice can prepare.</l>
               <l>'Twas Fortune threw me hither, where I now</l>
               <l>Rude <hi>Getes</hi> and <hi>Thrace</hi> see, with the snowie brow</l>
               <l>Of Cloudie <hi>Amles,</hi> and if she decree</l>
               <l>Her sportive pilgrims <hi>List bed</hi> here must be</l>
               <l>I am content; nay more, she cannot doe</l>
               <l>That Act which I would not consent unto.</l>
               <l>I can delight in vain hopes, and desire</l>
               <l>That state more then her <hi>Change</hi> and <hi>Smiles,</hi> then high't</l>
               <l>I hugge a strong <hi>despaire,</hi> and think it brave</l>
               <l>To <hi>baffle</hi> faith, and give those hopes a <hi>grave.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have you not seen cur'd wounds enlarg'd, and he</l>
               <l>That with the first wave sinks, yielding to th'tree</l>
               <l>VVaters, without th'Expence of armes or breath</l>
               <l>Hath still the easiest, and the quickest death.</l>
               <l>VVhy nurse I sorrows then? why these desires</l>
               <l>Of Changing <hi>Scythia</hi> for the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>fires</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:66031:26"/>Of some calm kinder aire? what did bewitch</l>
               <l>My frantick hopes to flye so vain a pitch,</l>
               <l>And thus out-run my self? Mad-man! could I</l>
               <l>Suspect fate had for me a Courtesie?</l>
               <l>These errours grieve: And now I must forget</l>
               <l>Those pleas'd <hi>idoea's</hi> I did frame and set</l>
               <l>Unto my selfe, with many fancyed <hi>Springs</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Groves,</hi> whose only losse new sorrow brings.</l>
               <l>And yet I would the worst of fate endure,</l>
               <l>E're you should be repuls'd, or lesse secure,</l>
               <l>But (base, low soules!) you left me not for this,</l>
               <l>But 'cause you durst not. <hi>Caesar</hi> could not misse</l>
               <l>Of such a trifle, for I know that he</l>
               <l>Scorns the <hi>Cheap triumphs</hi> of my miserie.</l>
               <l>Then since (degen'rate friends) not he, but you</l>
               <l>Cancell my hopes, and make afflictions new,</l>
               <l>You shall Confesse, and same shall tell you, I</l>
               <l>At <hi>Isler</hi> dare as well as <hi>Tyber</hi> dye.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>De Ponto, lib. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Eleg. 3<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. To his Inconstant friend, translated for the use of all the <hi>Iudases</hi> of this touch-stone-Age.</head>
               <l>SHall I complain, or not? Or shall I mask</l>
               <l>Thy hatefull name, and in this bitter task</l>
               <l>Master my just Impatience, and write down</l>
               <l>Thy crime alone, and leave the rest unknown?</l>
               <l>Or wilt thou the succeeding years should see</l>
               <l>And teach thy person to posteritie?</l>
               <l>No, hope is not; for know, most wretched man,</l>
               <l>'Tis not thy base and weak detraction can</l>
               <l>Buy thee a <hi>Poem,</hi> nor move me to give</l>
               <l>Thy name the honour in my Verse to live.</l>
               <l>Whilst yet my <hi>Ship</hi> did with no stormes dispute</l>
               <l>And tem'prate winds <hi>fed</hi> with a calme salute</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:66031:27"/>My prosp'rous failes, thou were the only man</l>
               <l>That with me then an equall fortune ran,</l>
               <l>But now since angry heav'n with Clouds and night</l>
               <l>Stifled those <hi>Sun</hi>-beams, thou hast ta'ne thy flight,</l>
               <l>Thou knows't I want thee, and art meerly gone</l>
               <l>To shun that rescue, I rely'd upon;</l>
               <l>Nay, thou dissemblest too, and doest disclame</l>
               <l>Not only my <hi>Acquaintance,</hi> but my name;</l>
               <l>Yet know (though deale to this) that I am he</l>
               <l>Whose <hi>years</hi> and <hi>love</hi> had the same <hi>infancie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With thine, Thy <hi>deep familiar,</hi> that did share</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Soules</hi> with thee, and partake thy <hi>Ioyes</hi> or <hi>Care,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whom the same <hi>Roose</hi> lodg'd, and my <hi>Muse</hi> those nights</l>
               <l>So solemnly endear'd to her delights;</l>
               <l>But now, perfidious traitour, I am grown</l>
               <l>The <hi>Abject</hi> of thy brest, not to be known</l>
               <l>In that <hi>false Closes</hi> more; Nay, thou wilt not</l>
               <l>So much as let me know, I am forgot.</l>
               <l>If thou wilt say, thou didst not love me, then</l>
               <l>Thou didst dissemble: or, if love agen,</l>
               <l>Why now Inconstant? came the Crime from me</l>
               <l>That wrought this Change? Sure, if no Justice be</l>
               <l>Of my side, thine must have it. Why dost hide</l>
               <l>Thy reasons then? for me, I did so guide</l>
               <l>My selfe and actions, that I cannot see</l>
               <l>What could offend thee, but my miserie.</l>
               <l>'Las! if thou wouldst not from thy store allow</l>
               <l>Some rescue to my wants, at least I know</l>
               <l>Thou couldst have writ, and with a line or two</l>
               <l>Reliev'd my <hi>famish'd Eye,</hi> and eas'd me so.</l>
               <l>I know not what to think! and yet I hear,</l>
               <l>Not pleas'd with this, th'art <hi>witty,</hi> and dost Jeare;</l>
               <l>Bad man! thou hast in this those tears kept back</l>
               <l>I could have shed for thee, shouldst thou but lack.</l>
               <l>Knows't not that <hi>Fortune</hi> on a <hi>Globe</hi> doth stand,</l>
               <l>Whose <hi>upper</hi> slipprie part without command</l>
               <l>Turns <hi>lowest</hi> still? the sportive leafes and wind</l>
               <l>Are but dull <hi>Emblems</hi> of her fickle mind.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:66031:27"/>In the whole world there's nothing I can see</l>
               <l>Will throughly parallel her wayes, but thee.</l>
               <l>All that we hold, hangs on a slender twine</l>
               <l>And our best states by sudden chance decline;</l>
               <l>Who hath not heard of <hi>Croesus</hi> proverb'd gold</l>
               <l>Yet knowes his foe did him pris'ner hold?</l>
               <l>He that once aw'd <hi>Sicilia</hi>'s proud Extent</l>
               <l>By a poor art could famine scarse prevent;</l>
               <l>And mighty <hi>Pompey</hi> e'r he made an end</l>
               <l>Was glad to beg his slave to be his friend;</l>
               <l>Nay, he that had so oft <hi>Romes</hi> Consull bin,</l>
               <l>And forc'd <hi>Iugurtha,</hi> and the <hi>Cimbrians</hi> in,</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Marius</hi>! with much want, and more disgrace</l>
               <l>In a foul Marsh was glad to hide his face.</l>
               <l>A divine hand swayes all mankind, and wee</l>
               <l>Of one short houre have not the certaintie;</l>
               <l>Hadst thou one day told me, the time should be</l>
               <l>When the <hi>Getes</hi> bowes, and th'<hi>Euxine</hi> I should see,</l>
               <l>I should have check'd thy madness, and have thought</l>
               <l>Th' hadst need of all <hi>Anticira</hi> in a draught;</l>
               <l>And yet 'tis come to passe! nor though I might</l>
               <l>Some things foresee, could I procure a sight</l>
               <l>Of my whole destinie, and free my state</l>
               <l>From those eternall, higher <hi>tyes</hi> of fate.</l>
               <l>Leave then thy pride, and though now <hi>brave</hi> and <hi>high,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Think thou mayst be as <hi>poore</hi> and <hi>low</hi> as <hi>I.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Tristium Lib. 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Eleg. 3<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. To his Wife at <hi>Rome,</hi> when he was sick.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>DEarest</hi>! if you those fair Eyes (wondring) stick</l>
               <l>On this strange Character, know, <hi>I am sick.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sick in the <hi>skirts</hi> of the lost world, where I</l>
               <l>Breath hopeless of all Comforts, but to dye.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:66031:28"/>What heart (think'st thou) have I in this sad seat</l>
               <l>Tormented 'twixt the <hi>Samomate</hi> and <hi>Gete?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor <hi>aire</hi> nor <hi>water</hi> please: their very <hi>skie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Looks strange and unaccustom'd to my Eye,</l>
               <l>I scarse dare breath it, and I know not how</l>
               <l>The Earth that bears me shewes unpleasant now,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Diet</hi> here's, nor <hi>lodging</hi> for my Ease,</l>
               <l>Nor any one that <hi>studies</hi> a disease;</l>
               <l>No friend to comfort me, none to defray</l>
               <l>With smooth discourse the Charges of the day.</l>
               <l>All tir'd alone I lye and (thus) what e're</l>
               <l>Is absent, and at <hi>Rome</hi> I fancy here,</l>
               <l>But when then c<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m'st, I blot the <hi>Anie Scrowle,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And give thee full possession of my soule,</l>
               <l>Thee (absent) I embrace, thee only <hi>voice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And night and day <hi>holy</hi> a Husbands Joyes;</l>
               <l>Nay, of thy name so oft I mention make</l>
               <l>That I am thought distracted for thy sake;</l>
               <l>When my tir'd Spirits faile, and my sick heart</l>
               <l>Drawes in that <hi>fire</hi> which actuates each part,</l>
               <l>If any say, th'art come! I force my pain,</l>
               <l>And hope to see thee, gives me life again.</l>
               <l>Thus I for thee, whilst thou (perhaps) more blest</l>
               <l>Careless of me doest breath all peace and rest.</l>
               <l>Which yet I think not, for (<hi>Deare Soule</hi>!) too well</l>
               <l>Know I thy griefe, since my first woes befell.</l>
               <l>But if strict heav'n my stock of dayes hath spun</l>
               <l>And with my life my errour wilbe gone,</l>
               <l>How easie then (<hi>O Caesar</hi>!) wer't for thee</l>
               <l>To pardon one, that now doth cease to be?</l>
               <l>That I might yeeld my native aire this breath,</l>
               <l>And banish not my ashes after death;</l>
               <l>Would thou hadst either spar'd me untill dead,</l>
               <l>Or with my bloud redeem'd my absent head,</l>
               <l>Thou shouldst have had both freely, but O! thou</l>
               <l>Wouldst have me live to dye an <hi>Exile</hi> now.</l>
               <l>And must I then from <hi>Rome</hi> so far meet death,</l>
               <l>And double by the place my losse of breath?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:66031:28"/>Nor in my last of houres on my own bed</l>
               <l>(In the sad Conflict) rest my dying head?</l>
               <l>Nor my soules <hi>Whispers</hi> (the last pledge of life,)</l>
               <l>Mix with the tears and kisses of a wife?</l>
               <l>My last words none must treasure, none will rise</l>
               <l>And (with a teare) seal up my vanquish'd Eyes,</l>
               <l>Without these <hi>Rites</hi> I dye, distrest in all</l>
               <l>The <hi>splendid sorrowes</hi> of a Funerall,</l>
               <l>Unpittied, and unmourn'd for, my sad head</l>
               <l>In a strange Land goes friendless to the dead.</l>
               <l>When thou hear'st this, O how thy faithfull soule</l>
               <l>Will sink, whilst griefe doth ev'ry part controule!</l>
               <l>How often wilt thou look this way, and Crie,</l>
               <l>O where is't yonder that my love doth lye!</l>
               <l>Yet spare these tears, and mourn not now for me,</l>
               <l>Long since (<hi>dear heart</hi>!) have I been dead to thee,</l>
               <l>Thank then I dyed, when <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> I lost</l>
               <l>That death to me more griefe then this hath Cost;</l>
               <l>Now, if thou canst (but thou canst not) <hi>best wise</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Rejoyce, my Cares are ended with my life,</l>
               <l>At least, yeeld not to sorrowes, frequent use</l>
               <l>Should make these miseries to thee no newes.</l>
               <l>And here I wish my Soul died with my breath</l>
               <l>And that no part of me were free from death,</l>
               <l>For, if it be Immortall, and outlives</l>
               <l>The body, as <hi>Phythagoras</hi> believes,</l>
               <l>Betwixt these <hi>Sarmates ghosts,</hi> a <hi>Roman I</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall wander, vext to all Eternitie.</l>
               <l>But thou (for after death I shall be free,)</l>
               <l>Fetch home these bones, and what is left of me,</l>
               <l>A few <hi>Flowres</hi> give them, with some <hi>Balme,</hi> and lay</l>
               <l>Them in some <hi>Suburb grave</hi> hard by the way,</l>
               <l>And to Informe posterity, who's there,</l>
               <l>This sad Inscription let my marble weare,</l>
               <q>
                  <l>Here lyes the loft-soul'd Lecturer of Love,</l>
                  <l>Whose envy'd wit did his own ruine prove.</l>
               </q>
               <l>But thou, (who e'r thou beest, that passing by</l>
               <l>Lendst to this <hi>sudden stone</hi> a <hi>bastie</hi> Eye,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:66031:29"/>If e'r thou knew'st of <hi>Love</hi> the sweet disease,</l>
               <l>Grudge not to say, <hi>May</hi> Ovid <hi>rest in peace</hi>!</l>
               <l>This for my tombe: but in my books they'l see</l>
               <l>More strong and lasting Monuments of mee,</l>
               <l>Which I believe (though fatall) will afford</l>
               <l>An Endless name unto their ruin'd Lord.</l>
               <l>And now thus gone, It rests for love of me</l>
               <l>Thou shewst some sorrow to my memory;</l>
               <l>Thy Funerall offrings to my ashes beare</l>
               <l>With Wreathes of <hi>Cypresse</hi> bath'd in many a teare,</l>
               <l>Though nothing there but dust of me remain,</l>
               <l>Yet shall that <hi>Dust</hi> perceive thy pious pain.</l>
               <l>But I have done, and my tyr'd sickly head</l>
               <l>Though I would fain write more, desires the bed;</l>
               <l>Take then this word (perhaps my last to tell)</l>
               <l>Which though I want, I wish it thee, <hi>Fare-well.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Ausonii Cupido, Edyl. 6.</head>
               <l>IN those blest fields of <hi>Everlasting aire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Where to a <hi>Myrtle</hi>-grove the soules repaire</l>
               <l>Of deceas'd <hi>Lovers,</hi>) the sad, thoughtfull ghosts</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Injur'd Ladyes</hi> meet where each accosts</l>
               <l>The other with a sigh, whose very breath</l>
               <l>Would break a heart, and (<hi>kind Soules</hi>!) love in death,</l>
               <l>A thick wood clouds their <hi>walks</hi> where day scarce peeps,</l>
               <l>And on each hand Cypresse and Poppey <hi>sleepes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The drowsie Rivers <hi>slumber,</hi> and <hi>Springs</hi> there</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Blab</hi> not, but softly melt into a teare,</l>
               <l>A sickly dull aire <hi>fans</hi> them, which can have</l>
               <l>When most in force scarce breath to <hi>build</hi> a wave.</l>
               <l>On either bank through the still shades appear</l>
               <l>A <hi>Scene</hi> of pensive flowres, whose bosomes wear</l>
               <l>Drops of a <hi>Lever's</hi> bloud, the <hi>Emblem'd</hi> truths</l>
               <l>Of deep despair, and Love-slain <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Youths.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Hyacinth,</hi> and self-enamour'd Boy</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Narcissus</hi> flourish there, with <hi>Venus</hi> Joy</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:66031:29"/>The spruce <hi>Adonis,</hi> and that <hi>Prince</hi> whose flowre</l>
               <l>Hath sorrow languag'd on him to this houre;</l>
               <l>All sad with love they hang their heads, and grieve</l>
               <l>As if their passions in each lease did <hi>live</hi>;</l>
               <l>And here (<hi>alas</hi>!) these soft-soul'd Ladies stray,</l>
               <l>And (oh! too late !) treason in love betray.</l>
               <l>Her blasted birth sad <hi>Semile</hi> repeats,</l>
               <l>And with her <hi>tears</hi> would quench the thund'rers <hi>heats,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then shakes her bosome, as if fir'd again,</l>
               <l>And fears another lightnings <hi>slaming train.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The lovely <hi>Pocris</hi> (here) bleeds, sighes, and swounds,</l>
               <l>Then wakes, and kisses him that gave her wounds.</l>
               <l>Sad <hi>Hero</hi> holds a torch forth, and doth light</l>
               <l>Her lost <hi>Leander</hi> through the waves and night.</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Boateman</hi> desp'rate <hi>Sapho</hi> still admires,</l>
               <l>And nothing but the <hi>Sea</hi> can quench her <hi>fires.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Distracted <hi>Phoedïa</hi> with a restless Eye</l>
               <l>Her disdain'd Letters reads, then casts them by.</l>
               <l>Rare, faithfull <hi>Thysbe</hi> (sequestred from these)</l>
               <l>A silent, unseen sorrow doth best please,</l>
               <l>For her <hi>Loves</hi> sake, and last <hi>good-night,</hi> poor she</l>
               <l>Walks in the shadow of a <hi>Mulberrie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Neer her young <hi>Canace</hi> with <hi>Dido</hi> sits</l>
               <l>A lovely Couple, but of desp'rate wits,</l>
               <l>Both dy'd alike, both pierc'd their tender brests,</l>
               <l>This with her <hi>Fathers</hi> Sword, that with their <hi>Guests.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Within the thickest <hi>textures</hi> of the Grove</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diana</hi> in her <hi>Silver-beams</hi> doth rove,</l>
               <l>Her Crown of stars the <hi>pi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aire</hi> Invades,</l>
               <l>And with a faint light <hi>gilds</hi> the silent shades,</l>
               <l>Whilst her sad thoughts fixt on her <hi>sleepie I ever</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>Latmos</hi>-hill, and his retirements move her.</l>
               <l>A thousand more through the wide, darksome wood</l>
               <l>Feast on their cares, the <hi>Maudlin-Lovers</hi> food,</l>
               <l>For <hi>griefe</hi> and <hi>absence</hi> doe but <hi>Edge</hi> desire,</l>
               <l>And Death is <hi>fuell</hi> to a Lovers <hi>fire.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To see these <hi>Trophies</hi> of his wanton bow</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cupid</hi> comes in, and all in triumph now</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:66031:30"/>(Rash, unadvised Boy!) disperseth round</l>
               <l>The sleepie Mists, his <hi>Wings</hi> and <hi>quiver</hi> wound</l>
               <l>With noise the quiet aire. This sudden stirre</l>
               <l>Betrayes his <hi>godship,</hi> and as we from far</l>
               <l>A clouded, sickly <hi>Moon</hi> observe, so they</l>
               <l>Through the <hi>false Mists</hi> his <hi>Ecclyps'd torch</hi> betray.</l>
               <l>A hot pursute thy make, and though with care,</l>
               <l>And a slow wing he softly <hi>stems</hi> the aire,</l>
               <l>Yet they (as subtill now as he) surround</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His silenc'd course,</hi> and with the thick night bound</l>
               <l>Surprize the <hi>Wag.</hi> As in a dream we strive</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To voyce</hi> our thoughts, &amp; vainly would revive</l>
               <l>Our Entraunc'd tongues, but can not speech enlarge</l>
               <l>'Till the Soule wakes and reassumes her Charge,</l>
               <l>So joyous of their <hi>Prize,</hi> they flock about</l>
               <l>And vainly <hi>Swell</hi> with an <hi>Imagin'd</hi> shout.</l>
               <l>Far in these shades, and melancholy Coasts</l>
               <l>A <hi>Myrtle</hi> growes, well known to all the ghosts.</l>
               <l>Whose stretch'd top (like a <hi>great man</hi> rais'd by Fate)</l>
               <l>Looks big, and scorns his neighbours low estate;</l>
               <l>His <hi>leavy arms</hi> into a <hi>green Cloud</hi> twist.</l>
               <l>And on each Branch doth <hi>sit</hi> a lazie mist.</l>
               <l>A fatall tree, and luckless to the god,</l>
               <l>Where for <hi>disdain</hi> in life (loves <hi>worst</hi> of <hi>Ods</hi>)</l>
               <l>The <hi>Queen</hi> of shades, fair <hi>Proserpine</hi> did rack</l>
               <l>The sad <hi>Adonis,</hi> hithet now they pack</l>
               <l>This little <hi>God,</hi> where, first disarm'd, they <hi>bind</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>skittish wings,</hi> then both his hands behind</l>
               <l>His back they tye, and thus secur'd at last</l>
               <l>The <hi>peevish wanton</hi> to the tree make fast.</l>
               <l>Here at adventure without <hi>Iudge</hi> of Jurie</l>
               <l>He is condemn'd, while with united furie</l>
               <l>They all assaile him; As a thiefe at Bar</l>
               <l>Lest to the Law, and mercy of his Star,</l>
               <l>Hath <hi>Bills</hi> heap'd on him, and is question'd there</l>
               <l>By all the men that have been rob'd that year,</l>
               <l>So now what ever <hi>Fate,</hi> or their own <hi>will</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Scor'd up in life, <hi>Cupid</hi> must pay the bill.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:66031:30"/>Their <hi>Servants</hi> falshood, Jealousie, disdain,</l>
               <l>And all the plagues that <hi>abus'd Maids</hi> can feign,</l>
               <l>Are layd on him, and then to heighten spleen</l>
               <l>Their own deaths crown the summe. Prest thus between</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His faire accusers,</hi> 'tis at last decreed,</l>
               <l>He by those weapons, that they died, should bleed.</l>
               <l>One grasps an <hi>airie Sword,</hi> a second holds</l>
               <l>Illusive <hi>fire</hi> and in <hi>vain,</hi> wanton folds</l>
               <l>Belyes a flame; Others lesse kind appear</l>
               <l>To let him bloud, and from the purple tear</l>
               <l>Create a <hi>Rose.</hi> But <hi>Sapho</hi> all this while</l>
               <l>Harvests the aire, and from a thicken'd pile</l>
               <l>Of Clouds like <hi>Leucas top,</hi> spreads underneath</l>
               <l>A <hi>Sea of Mists,</hi> the peacefull billowes breath</l>
               <l>Without all noise, yet so exactly move</l>
               <l>They seem to <hi>Chide,</hi> but distant from above</l>
               <l>Reach not the eare, and (thus prepar'd) at once</l>
               <l>She doth o'rwhelm him with the <hi>airie Sconce.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Amidst these tumults, and as fierce as they</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> steps in, and without thought, or stay</l>
               <l>Invades her <hi>Son</hi>; her old disgrace is cost</l>
               <l>Into the <hi>Bill,</hi> when <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Shee</hi> made <hi>fast</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In their Embraces were expos'd to all</l>
               <l>The <hi>Scene</hi> of gods stark naked in their <hi>fall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor serves a <hi>verball</hi> penance, but with hast</l>
               <l>From her fair brow (O happy flowres so plac'd!)</l>
               <l>She tears a <hi>Rosie garland,</hi> and with this</l>
               <l>Whips the <hi>untoward Boy,</hi> they gently kisse</l>
               <l>His <hi>snowie skin,</hi> but she with angry hast</l>
               <l>Doubles her strength, untill bedew'd at last</l>
               <l>With a thin bloudie sweat, their <hi>Innate Red,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(As if griev'd with the Act) grew pale and dead.</l>
               <l>This <hi>layd</hi> their spleen: And now (<hi>kind soules!</hi>) no more</l>
               <l>They'l punish him, the torture that he bore,</l>
               <l>Seems greater then his crime; with joynt Consent</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fate</hi> is made guilty, and <hi>he</hi> Innocent.</l>
               <l>As in a dream with dangers we contest.</l>
               <l>And <hi>fictious pains</hi> seem to afflict our rest,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:66031:31"/>So frighted only in these shades of night</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cupid</hi> (got loose) stole to the upper light,</l>
               <l>Where ever since (for malice unto these)</l>
               <l>The <hi>spitefull Ape</hi> doth either <hi>Sex</hi> displease.</l>
               <l>But O that had these <hi>Ladyes</hi> been so wise</l>
               <l>To keep his <hi>Arms,</hi> and give him but his <hi>Eyes</hi>!</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Boet. Lib. 1. Metrum 1.</head>
               <l>I Whose first year flourish'd with youthfull verse,</l>
               <l>In slow, sad numbers now my griefe reherse;</l>
               <l>A broken stile my sickly lines afford,</l>
               <l>And only tears give weight unto my words;</l>
               <l>Yet neither fate nor force my Muse cou'd fright</l>
               <l>The only faithfull Consort of my flight;</l>
               <l>Thus what was once my green years greatest glorie,</l>
               <l>Is now my Comfort, grown decay'd and hoarie,</l>
               <l>For killing Cares th'Effects of age spurr'd on</l>
               <l>That griefe might find a fitting Mansion;</l>
               <l>O'r my young head runs an untimely gray,</l>
               <l>And my loose skin shrinks at my blouds decay.</l>
               <l>Happy the man whose death in prosp'rous years</l>
               <l>Strikes not, nor shuns him in his age and tears.</l>
               <l>But O how deale is she to hear the Crie</l>
               <l>Of th' opprest S<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ule, or shut the weeping Eye!</l>
               <l>While treacherous Fortune with slight honours fed</l>
               <l>My first estate, she almost drown'd my head,</l>
               <l>But now since (clouded thus) she hides those rayes,</l>
               <l>Life adds unwelcom'd length unto my dayes;</l>
               <l>Why then, my friends, Judg'd you my state so good?</l>
               <l>He that may fall once, never firmly stood.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:66031:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Metrum</hi> 2.</head>
               <l>O In what haste with Clouds and Night</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ecclyps'd,</hi> and having lost her light,</l>
               <l>The dull Soule whom distraction rends</l>
               <l>Into outward Darkness tends!</l>
               <l>How often (by these mists made blind,)</l>
               <l>Have earthly cares opprest the mind!</l>
               <l>This Soule sometimes wont to survey</l>
               <l>The spangled <hi>Zodiacks sine way</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Saw th'early Sun in Roses drest</l>
               <l>With the Coole Moons unstable Crest,</l>
               <l>And whatsoever wanton Star</l>
               <l>In various Courses neer or far</l>
               <l>Pierc'd through the orbs, he cou'd full well</l>
               <l>Track all her Journey, and would tell</l>
               <l>Her Mansions, turnings, Rise and fall,</l>
               <l>By Curious Calculation all.</l>
               <l>Of sudden winds the hidden Cause,</l>
               <l>And why the Calm Seas quiet face</l>
               <l>With Impetuous waves is Curld,</l>
               <l>What spirit wheeles th'harmonious world,</l>
               <l>Or why a Star dropt in the <hi>West</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is seen to rise again by <hi>East,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who gives the warm Spring temp'rate houres</l>
               <l>Decking the Earth with spicie flowres,</l>
               <l>Or how it Comes (for mans recruit)</l>
               <l>That Autumne yeelds both Grape and fruit,</l>
               <l>With many other Secrets, he</l>
               <l>Could shew the Cause and Mysterie,</l>
               <l>But now that light is almost out,</l>
               <l>And the brave Soule lyes Chain'd about</l>
               <l>With outward Cares, whose pensive weight</l>
               <l>Sinks down her Eyes from their first height,</l>
               <l>And clean Contrary to her birth</l>
               <l>Poares on this vile and foolish Earth.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:66031:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Metrum</hi> 4.</head>
               <l>WHose calme soule in a settled state</l>
               <l>Kicks under foot the frowns of Fate,</l>
               <l>And in his fortunes bad or good</l>
               <l>Keeps the same temper in his bloud,</l>
               <l>Not him the slaming Clouds above,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Alita's</hi> fierie tempests move,</l>
               <l>No fretting seas from shore to shore</l>
               <l>Boyling with Indignation o're</l>
               <l>Nor burning thunderbolt that can</l>
               <l>A mountain shake, can st<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rre this man.</l>
               <l>Dull Cowards then! why should we start</l>
               <l>To see <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hese tyrants act their part?</l>
               <l>Nor hope, no fear what may befall</l>
               <l>And you d<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sarm their malice all.</l>
               <l>But wh<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th faintly fea<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or wish</l>
               <l>And sets no law to what is <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</l>
               <l>Hath lost the buck<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, and (poor Elfe!)</l>
               <l>Makes up a Chain to bind himselfe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Metrum</hi> 5.</head>
               <l>O Thou great builder of this starrie frame,</l>
               <l>Who fixt in thy eternall throne dost tame</l>
               <l>The rapid Spheres, and lest they jarre</l>
               <l>Hast giv'n a law to ev'ry starre!</l>
               <l>Thou art the Cause that new the Moon</l>
               <l>With full or be dulls the starres, and soon</l>
               <l>Again growes dark, her light being done,</l>
               <l>The neerer still she's to the Sun.</l>
               <l>Thou in the early hours of night</l>
               <l>Mak'st the coole Evening-star shine bright,</l>
               <l>And at Sun-rising ('cause the least)</l>
               <l>Look pale and sleepie in the East.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:66031:32"/>Thou, when the leafes in Winter stray,</l>
               <l>Appointst the Sun a shorter way,</l>
               <l>And in the pleasant Summer-light</l>
               <l>With nimble hourses doest wing the night.</l>
               <l>Thy hand the various year quite through</l>
               <l>Discreetly tempers, that what now</l>
               <l>The North-wind tears from ev'ry tree</l>
               <l>In Spring again restor'd we see.</l>
               <l>Then what the <hi>winter-starrs</hi> between</l>
               <l>The furrowes in meer seed have seen</l>
               <l>The Dog-star since (grown up and born)</l>
               <l>Hath burnt in stately, full-ear'd Corn.</l>
               <l>Thus by Creations law controll'd</l>
               <l>All things their proper stations hold</l>
               <l>Observing (as thou didst intend)</l>
               <l>Why they were made, and for what end.</l>
               <l>Only humane actions thou</l>
               <l>Hast no Care of, but to the flow</l>
               <l>And Ebbe of Fortune leav'st them all,</l>
               <l>Hence th' Innocent endures that thrall</l>
               <l>Due to the wicked, whilst alone</l>
               <l>They sit possessours of his throne,</l>
               <l>The Just are kill'd, and Vertue lyes</l>
               <l>Buried in obscurities,</l>
               <l>And (which of all things is most sad)</l>
               <l>The good man suffers by the bad.</l>
               <l>No perjuries, nor damn'd pretence</l>
               <l>Colour'd with holy, lying sense</l>
               <l>Can them annoy, but when they mind</l>
               <l>To try their force, which most men find.</l>
               <l>They from the highest sway of things</l>
               <l>Can pull down great, and pious Kings.</l>
               <l>O then at length, thus loosely hurl'd</l>
               <l>Look on this miserable world</l>
               <l>Who e'r thou art, that from above</l>
               <l>Doest in such order all things move!</l>
               <l>And let not man (of divine art</l>
               <l>Not the least, nor vilest part)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:66031:33"/>By Casuall evills thus bandied, be</l>
               <l>The sport of fates obliquitie.</l>
               <l>But with that faith thou guid'st the heaven,</l>
               <l>Settle this Earth, and make them even.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Metrum</hi> 6.</head>
               <l>WHen the Crabs sierce Constellation</l>
               <l>Burns with the beams of the bright Sun,</l>
               <l>Then he that will goe out to sowe,</l>
               <l>Shall never reap where he did plough,</l>
               <l>But in stead of Corn may rather</l>
               <l>The old worlds diet, Accorns gather.</l>
               <l>Who the Violet doth love</l>
               <l>Must seek her in the flowrie grove,</l>
               <l>But never when the <hi>Norths</hi> cold wind</l>
               <l>The <hi>Russet</hi> fields with frost doth bind.</l>
               <l>If in the Spring-time (to no end)</l>
               <l>The tender Vine for Grapes we bend,</l>
               <l>Wee shall find none, for only (still)</l>
               <l>Autumne doth the Wine-presse fill.</l>
               <l>Thus for all things (in the worlds prime)</l>
               <l>The wise God seal'd their proper time,</l>
               <l>Nor will permit those seasons he</l>
               <l>Ordain'd by turns, should mingled be;</l>
               <l>Then whose wild actions out of season</l>
               <l>Crosse to nature, and her reason,</l>
               <l>VVould by new wayes old orders rend,</l>
               <l>Shall never find a happy End.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Metrum</hi> 7.</head>
               <l>CUrtain'd with Clouds in a dark night</l>
               <l>The Stars cannot send forth their light.</l>
               <l>And if a sudden Southern blast</l>
               <l>The Sea in rolling waves doth cast,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:66031:33"/>That angrie Element doth boile,</l>
               <l>And from the deep with stormy Coile</l>
               <l>Spues up the Sands, which in short space</l>
               <l>Scatter, and puddle his Curl'd face;</l>
               <l>Then those Calme waters, which but now</l>
               <l>Stood clear as heavens unclouded brow,</l>
               <l>And like transparent glasse did lye</l>
               <l>Open to ev'ry searchers Eye,</l>
               <l>Look soulely stirr'd, and (though desir'd)</l>
               <l>Resist the sight, because bemir'd,</l>
               <l>So often from a high hills brow</l>
               <l>Some Pilgrim-spring is seen to flow,</l>
               <l>And in a straight line keep her Course</l>
               <l>Till from a Rock with headlong force</l>
               <l>Some broken peece blocks up her way</l>
               <l>And fo<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceth all her streams astray.</l>
               <l>Then thou that with inlightned Rayes,</l>
               <l>Wouldst see the truth, and in her wayes</l>
               <l>Keep without <hi>Errour</hi>; neither fear</l>
               <l>The future, nor too much give ear</l>
               <l>To present Joyes; And give no scope</l>
               <l>To griefe, nor much to flatt'ring hope.</l>
               <l>For when these Rebels raign, the mind</l>
               <l>Is both a Pris'ner, and stark blind.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Metrum</hi> 1.</head>
               <l>F<hi>Ortune</hi> (when with rash hands she quite turmoiles</l>
               <l>The state of things, and in tempestuous foiles</l>
               <l>Comes whirling like <hi>Eurious,</hi>) beats quire down</l>
               <l>With head long force the highest Monarchs crown,</l>
               <l>And in his place unto the throne doth fetch</l>
               <l>The despis'd looks of some mechanick wretch.</l>
               <l>So Jests at tears and miseries, is proud,</l>
               <l>And laughs to hear her vassals grone aloud.</l>
               <l>These are her sports, thus she her wheele doth drive</l>
               <l>And plagues man with her blind prerogative;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:66031:34"/>Nor is't a favour of Inferiour strain,</l>
               <l>If once kickt down, she lets him rise again.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Metrum</hi> 2.</head>
               <l>IF with an open, bounteous hand</l>
               <l>(Wholly left at Mans Command)</l>
               <l>Fortune should in one rich flow</l>
               <l>As many heaps on him beslow</l>
               <l>Of massie gold, as there be sands</l>
               <l>Tost by the waves and winds rude bands,</l>
               <l>Or bright stars in a Winter night</l>
               <l>Decking their silent Orbs with light,</l>
               <l>Yet would his lust know no restraints,</l>
               <l>Nor cease to weep in sad Complaints.</l>
               <l>Though heaven should his vowes reguard,</l>
               <l>And in a prodigall reward</l>
               <l>Return him all he could in plore,</l>
               <l>Adding new horours to his store,</l>
               <l>Yet all were nothing. Goods in sight</l>
               <l>Are scorn'd, and lust in greedy flight</l>
               <l>Layes out for more; What measure then</l>
               <l>Can tame these wild desires of men?</l>
               <l>Since all wee give both last and first</l>
               <l>Doth but inflame, and feed their thirst;</l>
               <l>For how can he be rich, who 'midst his store</l>
               <l>Sits sadly pining, and believes he's poore.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Metrum</hi> 3.</head>
               <l>WHen the Sun from his Rosie bed</l>
               <l>The dawning light begins to shed,</l>
               <l>The drowsie sky uncurtains round,</l>
               <l>And the (but now bright stars all drown'd</l>
               <l>In one great light, look dull and tame,</l>
               <l>And homage his victorious flame,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:66031:34"/>Thus, when the warm <hi>Etesian</hi> wind</l>
               <l>The Earth's seald bosome doth unbind,</l>
               <l>Straight she her various store discloses,</l>
               <l>And purples every Grove with Roses;</l>
               <l>But if the Souths tempestuous breath</l>
               <l>Breaks forth, those blushes pine to death.</l>
               <l>Oft in a quiet sky the deep</l>
               <l>With unmov'd waves seems fast asleep,</l>
               <l>And oft again the blustring North</l>
               <l>In angrie heaps provokes them forth.</l>
               <l>If then this world, which holds all Nations,</l>
               <l>Suffers it selfe such alterations,</l>
               <l>That not this mighty, massie frame,</l>
               <l>Nor any part of it can Claime</l>
               <l>One certain course, why should man prate,</l>
               <l>Or Censure the designs of Fate?</l>
               <l>Why from fraile honours, and goods lent</l>
               <l>Should he expect things permanent?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce 'tis enacted by divine decree</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat nothing mortall shall eternall be.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Metrum</hi> 4.</head>
               <l>WHo wisely would sor his retreat</l>
               <l>Build a secure and lasting seat,</l>
               <l>Where stov'd in silence he may sleep</l>
               <l>Beneath the <hi>Wind,</hi> above the <hi>Deep</hi>;</l>
               <l>Let him th' high hils leave on one hand,</l>
               <l>And on the other the false sand;</l>
               <l>The first to winds lyes plain and even</l>
               <l>From all the blustring points of heaven;</l>
               <l>The other hollow and unsure,</l>
               <l>No weight of building will endure.</l>
               <l>A voyding then the envied state</l>
               <l>Of buildings bravely situate,</l>
               <l>Remember thou thy selfe to lock</l>
               <l>Within some low neglected Rock;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:66031:35"/>There when fierce heaven in thunder Chides,</l>
               <l>And winds and waves rage on all sides,</l>
               <l>Thou happy in the quiet sense</l>
               <l>Of thy poor Cell with small Expence</l>
               <l>Shall lead a life serene and faire,</l>
               <l>And scorn the anger of the aire.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Metrum</hi> 5.</head>
               <l>HAppy that first white age! when wee</l>
               <l>Lived by the Earths meere Charitie,</l>
               <l>No soft luxurious Diet then</l>
               <l>Had Effeminated men,</l>
               <l>No other meat, nor wine had any</l>
               <l>Then the Course Mast, or simple honey,</l>
               <l>And by the Parents care layd up</l>
               <l>Cheap <hi>Berries</hi> did the Children sup.</l>
               <l>No pompous weare was in those dayes</l>
               <l>Of gummie Silks, or Ska<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>let bayes,</l>
               <l>Their beds were on some slowrie brink</l>
               <l>And clear Spring water was their drink.</l>
               <l>The shadie Pine in the Suns heat</l>
               <l>Was their Coole and known Retreat,</l>
               <l>For then 'twas not cut down, but stood</l>
               <l>The youth and glory of the wood.</l>
               <l>The daring Sailer with his slaves</l>
               <l>Then had not cut the swelling waves,</l>
               <l>Nor for desire of forraign store</l>
               <l>Seen any but his native shore.</l>
               <l>No stirring Drum had scarr'd that age,</l>
               <l>Nor the shrill Trumpets active rage,</l>
               <l>No wounds by bitter hatred made</l>
               <l>With warm bloud soil'd the shining blade;</l>
               <l>For how could hostile madness arm</l>
               <l>An age of love to publick harm?</l>
               <l>When Common Justice none withstood,</l>
               <l>Nor sought rewards for spilling bloud.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:66031:35"/>O that at length our age would raise</l>
               <l>Into the temper of those dayes!</l>
               <l>But (worst then <hi>AEtna's</hi> fires!) debate</l>
               <l>And Avarice inflame our state.</l>
               <l>Alas! who was it that first found</l>
               <l>Gold hid of purpose under ground,</l>
               <l>That sought out Pearles, and div'd to find</l>
               <l>Such pretious perils for mankind!</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Metrum</hi> 6.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HE that thirsts for glories prize,</l>
                  <l>Thinking that the top of all,</l>
                  <l>Let him view th'Expansed skies,</l>
                  <l>And the Earths Contracted ball,</l>
                  <l>'Twill shame him then, the name he wan</l>
                  <l>Fils not the short <hi>walk</hi> of one man.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>O why vainly strive you then</l>
                  <l>To shake off the bands of Fate,</l>
                  <l>Though same through the world of men</l>
                  <l>Should in all tongues your names relate,</l>
                  <l>And with proud titles swell that storie</l>
                  <l>The Darke grave scorns your brightest glorie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>There with Nobles beggers sway,</l>
                  <l>And Kings with Commons share one dust,</l>
                  <l>What newes of <hi>Brutus</hi> at this day,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Fabricius</hi> the Just,</l>
                  <l>Some rude <hi>Verse</hi> Cut in stone, or led</l>
                  <l>Keeps up the names, but they are dead.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>So shall, you one day (past reprieve)</l>
                  <l>Lye (perhaps) without a name,</l>
                  <l>But if dead you think to live</l>
                  <l>By this aire of humane fame,</l>
                  <l>Know, when time stops that posthume breath,</l>
                  <l>You must endure a second death.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:66031:36"/>
               <head>Metrum 7.</head>
               <l>THat the world in constant <hi>force</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Varies her <hi>Concordant course</hi>;</l>
               <l>That <hi>seeds</hi> jarring <hi>hot</hi> and <hi>cold</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doe the <hi>breed</hi> perpetuall hold;</l>
               <l>That in his golden Coach the <hi>Sun</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Brings the <hi>Rofic day</hi> still on;</l>
               <l>That the <hi>Moon</hi> swayes all those <hi>lights</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which <hi>Helper</hi> ushers to <hi>dark nights</hi>;</l>
               <l>That <hi>alternate tydes</hi> be sound</l>
               <l>The Seas <hi>ambitious</hi> waves to bound,</l>
               <l>Lest o'r the wide Earth without End</l>
               <l>Their <hi>fluid Empire</hi> should extend;</l>
               <l>All this frame of <hi>things</hi> that <hi>be,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Love which rules <hi>Heaven, Land,</hi> and <hi>Sea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Chains, keeps, orders as we see.</l>
               <l>This, if the raines he once cast by,</l>
               <l>All things that now by turns comply,</l>
               <l>Would fall to discord, and this frame</l>
               <l>Which now by sociall faith they tame,</l>
               <l>And comely orders in that fight</l>
               <l>And jarre of th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngs would perish quite.</l>
               <l>This in a holy league of peace</l>
               <l>Keeps King and People with Increase;</l>
               <l>And in the sacred nuptiall bands</l>
               <l>Tyes up chast hearts with willing hands,</l>
               <l>And this keeps firm without all doubt</l>
               <l>Friends by his bright Instinct found out.</l>
               <l>O happy Nation then were you</l>
               <l>If love which doth all things subdue,</l>
               <l>That rules the spacious heav'n, and brings</l>
               <l>Plenty and Peace upon his wings,</l>
               <l>Might rule you too! and without guile</l>
               <l>Settle once more this floting Ile!</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:66031:36"/>
               <head>Casimirus, Lib.4. Ode 28.</head>
               <l>ALlmighty <hi>Spirit</hi>! thou that by</l>
               <l>Set <hi>turns</hi> and <hi>changes</hi> from thy high</l>
               <l>And glorious <hi>throne,</hi> dost here below</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> all, and all things dost <hi>foreknow</hi>;</l>
               <l>Can those <hi>blind plots</hi> wee here discusse</l>
               <l>Please thee, as thy <hi>wise Counsels</hi> us?</l>
               <l>When thou thy <hi>blessings</hi> here dost strow,</l>
               <l>And poure on <hi>Earth,</hi> we flock and flow</l>
               <l>With <hi>Ioyous strife,</hi> and <hi>eager care</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Strugling which shall have the best share</l>
               <l>In thy <hi>rich gifts,</hi> just as we see</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Children</hi> about <hi>Nuts</hi> disagree.</l>
               <l>Some that a <hi>Crown</hi> have got and foyl'd</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Break</hi> it; Another sees it <hi>spoil</hi>'d</l>
               <l>E're it is <hi>gotten</hi>: Thus the <hi>world</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is all to <hi>peece-meals</hi> cut, and hurl'd</l>
               <l>By <hi>sactious hands,</hi> It is a <hi>ball</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which <hi>Fate</hi> and <hi>force</hi> divide 'twixt all</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>men.</hi> But o good God!</l>
               <l>While these for <hi>dust</hi> fight, and a <hi>Clod,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Grant that poore I may <hi>smile,</hi> and be</l>
               <l>At rest, and <hi>perfect peace</hi> with thee.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Casimirus, Lib. 2. Ode 8.</head>
               <l>IT would lesse vex <hi>distressed man</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If <hi>Fortune</hi> in the same <hi>pace</hi> ran</l>
               <l>To <hi>ruine</hi> him, as he did <hi>rise</hi>;</l>
               <l>But highest <hi>states</hi> fall in a trice.</l>
               <l>No <hi>great Successe</hi> held ever <hi>long</hi>:</l>
               <l>A restless <hi>fate</hi> afflicts the throng</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> and lesse dayes</l>
               <l>Serve to <hi>destroy</hi> them, then to <hi>raise.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:66031:37"/>
                  <hi>Good</hi> luck <hi>smiles</hi> once an age, but <hi>bad</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Makes <hi>Kingdomes</hi> in a <hi>minute</hi> sad,</l>
               <l>And ev'ry <hi>houre</hi> of <hi>life</hi> wee drive,</l>
               <l>H<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> o're us a <hi>Prerogative.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then leave (by <hi>wild Impatience</hi> driv'n,</l>
               <l>And <hi>rash resents,</hi>) to rayle at <hi>heav'n,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Leave an <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>nly, weak complaint</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>De<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Fate</hi> have no restraint.</l>
               <l>In the same houre hat gave thee <hi>breath,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou hadst ordain'd thy houre of <hi>death,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But <hi>he</hi> loves <hi>most,</hi> who here will <hi>buy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With a few tears, <hi>Eternitie.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Casimirus, Lib. 3. Ode 22.</head>
               <l>LEt not thy <hi>youth</hi> and <hi>false delights</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cheat thee of <hi>life</hi>; Those <hi>headely flights</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But wast thy <hi>time,</hi> which posts away</l>
               <l>Like <hi>winds</hi> unseen, and swift as they.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beauty</hi> is but meer <hi>paint,</hi> whose <hi>die</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With times <hi>breath</hi> will <hi>dissolve</hi> and <hi>flye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis <hi>wax,</hi> 'tis <hi>water,</hi> 'tis a <hi>glasse</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It <hi>melts, breaks,</hi> and <hi>away</hi> doth <hi>passe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis like a <hi>Rose</hi> which in the <hi>dawne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>aire</hi> with gentle breath doth <hi>sawne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>whisper</hi> too, but in the houres</l>
               <l>Of <hi>night</hi> is sullied with smart showres.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Life</hi> spent, is wish'd for but in vain,</l>
               <l>Nor can past <hi>years</hi> come back again.</l>
               <l>Happy the <hi>Man</hi>! who in this <hi>vale</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Redeems his time, shatting out all</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thoughts</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> whose <hi>longing Eyes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are ever <hi>Pilgrims</hi> in the <hi>skyes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That views his <hi>bright home,</hi> and desires</l>
               <l>To <hi>slaine</hi> amongst those <hi>glorious fores.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:66031:37"/>
               <head>Casimirus Lyric. Lib.3. Ode 23.</head>
               <l>'TIs not <hi>rich furniture</hi> and <hi>gems</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>Cedar-roofes,</hi> and ancient <hi>stems,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor yet a <hi>plenteous, lasting floud</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>gold,</hi> that makes man <hi>truly good.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Leave to Inquire in what <hi>faire fields</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>River</hi> runs which <hi>much gold</hi> yeelds,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vertue</hi> alone is the <hi>rich prize</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can purchase <hi>stars,</hi> and buy the <hi>skies.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let others build with <hi>Adamant,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or pillars of <hi>carv'd Marble</hi> plant,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>rude</hi> and <hi>rough</hi> sometimes did dwell</l>
               <l>Far under <hi>earth,</hi> and neer to <hi>hell.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But <hi>richer</hi> much (from <hi>death</hi> releast)</l>
               <l>Shines in the <hi>fresh groves</hi> of the <hi>East</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Phoenix,</hi> or those <hi>fish</hi> that dwell</l>
               <l>With <hi>silver'd scales</hi> in <hi>Hiddekel.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let others with rare, various <hi>Pearls</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Their <hi>garments</hi> dresse, and in <hi>forc'd Curls</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Bind up their <hi>locks,</hi> look <hi>big</hi> and <hi>high,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And shine in <hi>robes</hi> of <hi>Scarlet-die.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But in my thoughts more <hi>glorious</hi> far</l>
               <l>Those <hi>native stars,</hi> and <hi>speckles</hi> are</l>
               <l>Which <hi>birds</hi> wear, or the <hi>spots</hi> which wee</l>
               <l>In <hi>Leopards</hi> dispersed see.</l>
               <l>The harmless <hi>sheep</hi> with her warm <hi>sheet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cloathes <hi>man,</hi> but who his <hi>dark heart</hi> sees</l>
               <l>Shall find a <hi>wolfe</hi> or <hi>Fox</hi> within</l>
               <l>That kills the <hi>Castor</hi> for his <hi>skin.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vertue</hi> alone, and nought else can</l>
               <l>A diffrence make 'twixt <hi>beast</hi> and <hi>man,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And on her <hi>wines</hi> above the <hi>Spheres</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To the <hi>true light</hi> his <hi>spirit</hi> bears.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:66031:38"/>
               <head>Casimirus, Lib. 4. Ode 15.</head>
               <l>NOthing on <hi>Earth,</hi> nothing at all</l>
               <l>Can be exempted from the <hi>thrall</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of peevish <hi>weariness</hi>! The <hi>Sun</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which our <hi>sore-fathers</hi> Judg'd to run</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clear</hi> and <hi>unspotted,</hi> in our dayes</l>
               <l>Is tax'd with <hi>sullen, Ecclips'd rayes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What ever in the <hi>glorious skie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Man</hi> sees, his rash, <hi>andacious Eye</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Dares Censure it, and in meer <hi>spite</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At <hi>distance</hi> will condemn the <hi>light.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>wholesome mornings,</hi> whose <hi>beams</hi> cleer</l>
               <l>Those <hi>hills</hi> our <hi>fathers</hi> walkt on here</l>
               <l>Wee fancy not nor the <hi>Moons</hi> light</l>
               <l>Which through their <hi>windows</hi> shin'd at <hi>night,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVee change the <hi>Aire</hi> each year, and scorn</l>
               <l>Those <hi>Seates,</hi> in which we first were <hi>borne.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some nice, affected <hi>wond'rers</hi> love</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Belgia</hi>'s mild winters, others remove</l>
               <l>For want of <hi>health</hi> and <hi>honestie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>Summer</hi> it in <hi>Italic</hi>;</l>
               <l>But to no end: The <hi>disease</hi> still</l>
               <l>Sticks to his <hi>Lord,</hi> and kindly will</l>
               <l>To <hi>Venice</hi> in a <hi>Barge</hi> repaire,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Coach</hi> it to <hi>Vienna's</hi> aire,</l>
               <l>And then (to late with <hi>home</hi> Content,)</l>
               <l>They leave this <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rilfull banishment.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But he, whose <hi>Costancie</hi> makes sure</l>
               <l>His <hi>mind</hi> and <hi>mansion,</hi> lives secure</l>
               <l>From such <hi>vain tasks,</hi> can <hi>dine</hi> and <hi>sup</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhere his <hi>old parents</hi> bred him up.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Content</hi> (no doubt!) most times doth dwell</l>
               <l>In <hi>Countrey-shades,</hi> or to some <hi>Cell</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Confines it selfe, and can alone</l>
               <l>Make simple <hi>straw,</hi> a Royall <hi>Throne.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:66031:38"/>
               <head>Casimirus, Lib.4. Ode 13.</head>
               <l>IF <hi>weeping Eyes</hi> could wash away</l>
               <l>Those <hi>Evills</hi> they mourn for <hi>night and day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then gladly I to <hi>cure</hi> my <hi>fears</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With my best <hi>Iewells</hi> would buy <hi>tears.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But as <hi>dew</hi> feeds the growing <hi>Corn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So <hi>Crosses</hi> that are grown <hi>sorlorn</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Increase</hi> with <hi>griefe, teares</hi> make <hi>teares</hi> way,</l>
               <l>And <hi>cares</hi> kept up, keep <hi>cares</hi> in <hi>pay.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>wretch</hi> whom <hi>Fortune</hi> finds to <hi>seare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>melting</hi> still into a <hi>teare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>She <hi>strikes</hi> more <hi>boldly,</hi> but a <hi>face</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Silent</hi> and <hi>drie</hi> doth her <hi>amaze.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then leave thy <hi>teares,</hi> and redious <hi>tale</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of what thou doest <hi>misfortunes</hi> call,</l>
               <l>What thou by <hi>weeping</hi> think'st to <hi>ease,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth by that <hi>Passion</hi> but <hi>Increase,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hard</hi> things to <hi>Soft</hi> will never yield,</l>
               <l>'Tis the <hi>drie Eye</hi> that wins the field;</l>
               <l>A noble <hi>patience</hi> quells the <hi>spite</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Fortune,</hi> and <hi>disarms</hi> her quite.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Praise of a Religious life by <hi>Mathias Casimirus.</hi> In Answer to that Ode of <hi>Horace, Beatus Ille qui procul negotiis,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>FLaccus</hi> not so: That worldly He</l>
               <l>Whom in the Countreys <hi>shade</hi> we see</l>
               <l>Ploughing his own <hi>fields,</hi> seldome can</l>
               <l>Be justly stil'd, <hi>The Blessed man.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That title only fits a <hi>Saint,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whose free thoughts far above restraint.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:66031:39"/>And weighty Cares, can gladly part</l>
               <l>With <hi>house</hi> and <hi>lands,</hi> and leave the smart</l>
               <l>Litigious troubles, and lowd strife</l>
               <l>Of this world for a better life.</l>
               <l>He fears no <hi>Cold,</hi> nor <hi>heat</hi> to blast</l>
               <l>His <hi>Corn,</hi> for his <hi>Accounts</hi> are cast,</l>
               <l>He <hi>sues</hi> no man, nor stands in Awe</l>
               <l>Of the <hi>deuouring Courts</hi> of Law;</l>
               <l>But all his time he spends in <hi>tears</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For the <hi>Sins</hi> of his youthfull years,</l>
               <l>Or having tasted those <hi>rich Ioyes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of a Conscience without <hi>noyse</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sits in some fair <hi>shade,</hi> and doth give</l>
               <l>To his <hi>wild thoughts</hi> rules how to live.</l>
               <l>He in the <hi>Evening,</hi> when on high</l>
               <l>The <hi>Stars</hi> shine in the <hi>silent skye</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Beholds th'<hi>eternall flames</hi> with mirth,</l>
               <l>And <hi>globes</hi> of <hi>light</hi> more large then <hi>Earth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then weeps for <hi>Ioy,</hi> and through his tears</l>
               <l>Looks on the <hi>fire-enamel'd</hi> Spheres,</l>
               <l>Where with his <hi>Saviour</hi> he would be</l>
               <l>Listed above mortalitie.</l>
               <l>Mean while the <hi>golden stars</hi> doe set,</l>
               <l>And the <hi>slow-Pilgrim</hi> leave all wet</l>
               <l>With his own tears, which flow so fast</l>
               <l>They make his <hi>sheps</hi> light, and soon past.</l>
               <l>By this, the <hi>Sun</hi> o're night <hi>deceast</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Breaks in <hi>fresh Blushes</hi> from the <hi>East,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When mindfull of his former <hi>falls</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>strong Cries</hi> to his <hi>God</hi> he calls,</l>
               <l>And with such <hi>deep-drawn sighes</hi> doth move</l>
               <l>That he turns <hi>anger</hi> into <hi>love.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In the Calme <hi>Spring,</hi> when the Earth <hi>bears,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And feeds on <hi>Aprils breath,</hi> and <hi>tears,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Eyes accustom'd to the <hi>skyes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Find here <hi>fresh objects,</hi> and like <hi>spyes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or busie <hi>Bees</hi> search the soft <hi>flowres</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Contemplate the <hi>green fields,</hi> and <hi>Bowres,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:66031:39"/>Where he in <hi>Veyles,</hi> and <hi>shades</hi> doth see</l>
               <l>The <hi>back Parts</hi> of the <hi>Deitye</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then sadly sighing sayes.
<q>
                     <l>O how</l>
                     <l>These slowres with hasty, stretch'd heads grow</l>
                     <l>And strive for heav'n, but rooted here</l>
                     <l>Lament the distance with a teare!</l>
                     <l>The Honey-suckles Clad in white,</l>
                     <l>The Rose in Red point to the light,</l>
                     <l>And the Lillies hollow and bleak</l>
                     <l>Look, as if they would something speak,</l>
                     <l>They sigh at night to each soft gale,</l>
                     <l>And at the day-spring weep it all.</l>
                     <l>Shall I then only (wretched I!)</l>
                     <l>Opprest with Earth, on Earth still lye?</l>
                  </q>
               </l>
               <l>Thus speaks he to the neighbour trees</l>
               <l>And many sad <hi>Soliloquies</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>Springs,</hi> and <hi>Fountaines</hi> doth impart,</l>
               <l>Seeking God with a longing heart.</l>
               <l>But if to ease his busie breast</l>
               <l>He thinks of <hi>home,</hi> and taking rest</l>
               <l>A <hi>Rurall Cott,</hi> and <hi>Common fare</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are all his <hi>Cordials</hi> against <hi>Care.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There at the <hi>doure</hi> of his low <hi>Cell</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Under some <hi>shade,</hi> or neer some <hi>well</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where the <hi>Coole Poplar</hi> growes, his <hi>Plate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of Common <hi>Earth,</hi> without more <hi>state</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Expect their <hi>Lord, Salt</hi> in a <hi>shell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Green <hi>Cheese,</hi> thin <hi>beere, Draughts</hi> that will <hi>tell</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No <hi>Tales,</hi> a <hi>hospitable Cup,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With some <hi>fresh berries</hi> doe make up</l>
               <l>His healthfull feast, nor doth he wish</l>
               <l>For the fatt <hi>Carp,</hi> or a rare dish</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Lucrine Oysters</hi>; The Swift <hi>Quist</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or <hi>Pigeon</hi> sometimes (if he list)</l>
               <l>With the <hi>slow Goose</hi> that loves the <hi>stream,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fresh, various <hi>Sallads,</hi> and the <hi>Bean</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By Curious <hi>Pallats</hi> never sought,</l>
               <l>And to Close with, some Cheap unbought</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:66031:40"/>Dish for <hi>digession,</hi> are the most</l>
               <l>And Choicest <hi>dainties</hi> he can <hi>boast.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus seasted, to the <hi>slowrie Groves,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or pleasant <hi>Rivers</hi> he removes,</l>
               <l>Where neer some <hi>fair Oke</hi> hung with Mast</l>
               <l>He shuns the <hi>Souths</hi> Infectious blast.</l>
               <l>On shadie <hi>hanks</hi> sometimes he lyes,</l>
               <l>Sometimes the open <hi>Current tryes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where with his <hi>line</hi> and <hi>feather'd flye</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He sports, and takes the <hi>Scaly frie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mean-while each <hi>hollow wood</hi> and <hi>hill</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth ring with <hi>lowings</hi> long and shrill,</l>
               <l>And shadie <hi>Lakes</hi> with <hi>Rivers</hi> deep,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eccho</hi> the <hi>bleating</hi> of the <hi>Sheep.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Black-bird</hi> with the pleasant <hi>Thrush</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Nightingale</hi> in ev'ry Bush</l>
               <l>Choice <hi>Musick</hi> give, and <hi>Shepherds</hi> play</l>
               <l>Unto their <hi>sticks</hi> some loving <hi>Lay</hi>;</l>
               <l>The thirsty <hi>Reapers</hi> in thick throngs</l>
               <l>Return home from the <hi>field</hi> with Songs,</l>
               <l>And the <hi>Carts</hi> loden with ripe <hi>Corn</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Come groning to the well-stor'd <hi>Barn.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor passe wee by as the least good,</l>
               <l>A <hi>peacefull, loving neighbourhood,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whose <hi>honest wit,</hi> and <hi>Chast discourse</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Make none (by hearing it) the <hi>worse,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>merry</hi> may</l>
               <l>Help (without <hi>Sin</hi>) to spend the day.</l>
               <l>Could now the <hi>Tyrant usurer</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who <hi>plots</hi> to be a <hi>Purchaser</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of his poor neighbours <hi>seat,</hi> but taste</l>
               <l>These <hi>true delights,</hi> ô with what haste</l>
               <l>And hatred of his wayes would he</l>
               <l>Renounce his <hi>Iewish Crueltie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And those <hi>Curs'd summes</hi> which poor men borrow</l>
               <l>On <hi>use</hi> to day, <hi>remit</hi> to morrow!</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:66031:40"/>
               <head>Ad fluvium Iscam.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>ISea</hi> parens florum, placido qui spumeus ore Lambis lapillos aureos,</l>
               <l>Qui moestos hyacinthos &amp; picti <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> topbi Mulces susurris humidis,</l>
               <l>Dum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <hi>novas</hi> pergunt <hi>menses</hi> Consumere <hi>Lunas</hi> Coelum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <hi>mortale</hi> terit,</l>
               <l>Accumulas cum <hi>Sole</hi> dies, oevum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> per omne <hi>Fidelis</hi> Induras <hi>latex,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O quis Inaccessos &amp; quali murmare lucos <hi>Mutumq</hi>; Solaris <hi>nemus</hi>!</l>
               <l>Per te discepti credo <hi>Thracis</hi> ire querelas Plectrum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <hi>divini senis.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Venerabili viro, praeceptori suo olim &amp; semper Colendissimo M<hi rend="sup">•o</hi>. Mathaeo Herbert.</head>
               <l>Quod vixi, <hi>Mathaee,</hi> dedit <hi>Pater,</hi> haec tamen olim</l>
               <l>Vita sluat, nec erit fas meminisse datam.</l>
               <l>Vltrà Curâsti Solers, peritura<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mecum</l>
               <l>Nomina post <hi>Cineres</hi> das resonare <hi>meos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Divide discipulum: brevis haec &amp; lubrica nostri</l>
               <l>Pars vertat <hi>Patri,</hi> Posthuma vita <hi>tibi.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:66031:41"/>
               <head>Praestrantissimo viro, <hi>Thomae Poëllo</hi> in suum de Elementis oplicae libellum.</head>
               <l>VIvaces <hi>oculorum</hi> Ignes &amp; lumina dia</l>
               <l>Fixit in <hi>angusto</hi> maximus <hi>orbe</hi> Deus,</l>
               <l>Ille <hi>Explorantes radios</hi> dedit, &amp; <hi>vaga lustra</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In quibus <hi>Intuitus</hi> lex<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> modus<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> latent.</l>
               <l>Hos tacitos Jactus, lusus<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> volubilis orbis</l>
               <l>Pingis in <hi>Exiguo,</hi> magne Poëlle, <hi>libro,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Excursus<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> situs<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, <hi>ut</hi> Lynceus opticus, <hi>edis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quot<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> modis</hi> fallunt, quot<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adhibenda sides.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>AEmula naturae</hi> manus! &amp; mens <hi>Conscia coeli!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Illa videre <hi>dedit,</hi> vestra videre <hi>docet.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Ad Echum.</head>
               <l>O Quae srondosae per amoena <hi>Cubilia</hi> silvae</l>
               <l>Nympha <hi>volas,</hi> luco<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <hi>lequax</hi> spatiaris in alto,</l>
               <l>Annosi <hi>numen</hi> nemoris, saltus<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> verendi</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Effatum,</hi> cui sola placent <hi>postrema</hi> velatûs!</l>
               <l>Per te <hi>Narcissi</hi> morientis verba, preces<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Per pueri <hi>Lassatam animam, &amp; Conamina</hi> vitae</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ultima,</hi> palantis<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> precor <hi>suspiria</hi> linguae.</l>
               <l>Da quo secretae haec <hi>Incaedua devia</hi> sylvae,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anfractusq</hi>; loci dubios, &amp; <hi>lusha</hi> repandam.</l>
               <l>Sic tibi <hi>perpetuâ</hi> (merilo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>) haec regna <hi>Juventâ</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Luxurient, dabitur<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tuis, sine sine, <hi>viretis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Intactas</hi> Lunae <hi>lachrymas,</hi> &amp; lambere <hi>rorem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Virgineum,</hi> Caeli<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <hi>animas</hi> haurire tepentis.</l>
               <l>Nec cedant avo <hi>stellis,</hi> sed <hi>lucida</hi> sempèt</l>
               <l>Et <hi>satiata sacro</hi> aeterni <hi>medicamine</hi> veris</l>
               <l>Ostendant longè <hi>vegetos,</hi> ut Sydera, <hi>vultus</hi>!</l>
               <l>Sit spiret Muscata <hi>Comas, &amp; Cynnama</hi> passim!</l>
               <l>Dissundat levis umbra, in funere qualia spargit</l>
               <l>Phoenicis <hi>rogus</hi> out Panchea <hi>nubila</hi> slammae!</l>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
