<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exact relation of all the late revolutions in Messina with their original, causes and progress to this present : as it was communicated by a letter / from an English gentleman at Naples to a person of quality here.</title>
            <author>E. W., English gentleman at Naples.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65676</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14006</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13325842</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13325842</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99071</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A65676)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99071)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 479:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exact relation of all the late revolutions in Messina with their original, causes and progress to this present : as it was communicated by a letter / from an English gentleman at Naples to a person of quality here.</title>
                  <author>E. W., English gentleman at Naples.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: E. W.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Messina (Italy) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99071:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An exact Relation of all the late Revolutions in <hi>Meſſina,</hi> with their Original, Cauſes, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs to this preſent; as it was communicated by a Letter, from an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman at <hi>Naples</hi> to a Perſon of Quality here.</head>
            <head type="sub">Printed by the Original.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Naples <hi>Adj.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>February</hi> the 16th. 1675.</date> S. N.</dateline>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU know very well at my taking my leave of you at <hi>Paris,</hi> and that you were returning for <hi>England,</hi> I deſigned to have in Perſon viſited <hi>Meſſina;</hi> but being come thus near, I am diverted from ſo perilous a Voyage, by the advice of my Friends, and the conſideration of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which attend that Man, who without any concern adventures himſelf into places embroyl'd in War, and involved in Rebellion; Nor indeed could I (though I long ſought after it) find any means of throwing my ſelf from hence into that City, without running the hazard of being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended for a Spy; which (you know well) would prove a knotty affair among ſo jealous a Nation as the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who in thoſe, and Religious caſes, are never ſparing of their Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: theſe thoughts and difficulties made me therefore reſolve to proceed no farther than this City, whence yet I doubt not, but I may in ſome competent meaſure, comply with, and ſatisfie the the injunction you laid upon me, of giving you a particular account of the troubles of <hi>Meſſina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not tell you how it has for ſome Ages paſt, been the hard Fate of the <hi>Sicilians,</hi> as well as <hi>Neapolitans,</hi> to have groan'd under the Yoke of Forreign Servitude, and that <note place="margin">The <hi>Sicilan</hi> Veſpers were ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe at the Ringing the Bell to Even<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Song, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives elſe in Arms, and cut all the <hi>French</hi> Mens Throate.</note>they have for ſome Centuries of Years, been ſometimes expoſed to the <hi>French</hi> Rule, ſome times to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tyranny, and have often by the Aid of the one ſtruggled to rid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the other, though yet they were impatient of either: Of which let the <hi>Sicilian Veſpers,</hi> and the great Revalution of <hi>Naples</hi> in <hi>Maſſaniello</hi>'s time, ſtand as ample Teſtimonies' to omit all other petty Rebellions and Revolts, in which this City, and that of <hi>Meſſina</hi> have always had the ſhare; and though the <hi>Spaniards</hi> may ſeem to have enjoyed for ſeveral Years paſt, a tranquil and quiet Dominion over thoſe people of <hi>Sicily;</hi> yet the embers were only raked over, and the ill humours were not buried, but lull'd aſleep, and from that reſt there was gathered ſtrength and vigour in the hearts of the people in General, and of the Nobility in Special, who were continually bemoaning to one another the bitterneſs of their ſlavery, and now wanted nothing but a happy conjuncture, to endeavour to cruſh that Pride wherewith the <hi>Spaniard</hi> (as they alledged) trampled over Them.</p>
            <p>There had now for ſome Years been held the Office of <hi>Stratico,</hi> or chief Magiſtrate of the City of <hi>Meſſina,</hi> one <hi>Pedro de Lewis de Freg<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> a Man of no very ill or oppreſſive temper, but who ſuffered himſelf wholly to be ruled and governed by the Heads of the Family of <hi>Merli,</hi> to whom he was nearly allyed by Affinity; ſeveral Matches having been made counterchangably between the two Families; and thoſe of the <hi>Merli</hi> by many other great Matches they had made with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> were ſo wholly Spanioliz'd, that they look'd with a kind of ſcorn and contempt upon their own Country-men, and having now got the reins of the Covernment, by reaſon of <hi>Don Pedro</hi>'s eaſineſs, into their own hands, rid furiouſly and ſtretched the proud and haughty temper of the <hi>Spaniards<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> upon the very Tenter-hooks, whilſt that which made their rigour appear ſo much more Notorious, was that the reſt of the people plainly perceived it proceeded from thoſe, who ſhould rather have joyned with them in common Defence againſt it; ſo that to ſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Trampled over by Men of their own Strain, made them conceive a rage and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred implacable, both againſt them, and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> that ſupported them.</p>
            <p>This general murmur at length begot ſeveral private Meetings, and the Famlies of the <hi>Marcheſi, Giri, Grilli, Bentini, Caraffi, Cartoni, Gramani,</hi> and ſeveral other of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal of the City, had ſundry cloſe Aſſemblies in all which they bemoaned, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperated one another; and by degrees begun to encourage each other to contrive ſome way for their Redemption; thus they proceeded to make ſtrong aſſociaſions and firm reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99071:2"/>
and in the end, about <hi>July</hi> 1672, ſent away <hi>Andrea Marcheſi</hi> to the Court of <hi>France,</hi> to try what aſſiſtance they might hope from thence, to back them in any thing they ſhould attempt, and in the mean time continued to hearten up one another, and to blow the Coals of Sedition among the people, who were ſufficiently before animated againſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Government, both by reaſon of the almoſt intollerable burthen of Taxes they perpetually groaned under, and the haughty and the imperious manner wherewith the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Tyraniz'd over them.</p>
            <p>But whether the Crown of <hi>France</hi> had not as yet fully determined to make a Rupture with <hi>Spain,</hi> or for what other unknown occaſion, <hi>Andrea Marcheſi</hi> found not his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions entertained with that Zeal, he and his confederats had expected in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> ſo that upon his return the Factions ſeemed ſomwhat cooler, and grew irreſolute in their Determinations, and in this poſture continued affairs till about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of 1674, when the humors were not only revived, but put into a Flame, by ſeveral occurring accidents but principally by the enſuing occaſion.</p>
            <p>The Exciſe which is laid very high throughout all <hi>Sicily,</hi> eſpecially upon all eatables and wearing apparel is uſually there; as it is likewiſe in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> let out to Farm for Years: Now the Farm of the City and Territory of <hi>Meſſina</hi> which was before in the hands of <hi>Girolomo Mattes, Georgio Caraſſa,</hi> and <hi>Jacomo Spizzone,</hi> with ſome others being expired at <hi>Michaelmas</hi> 1643, was by the aſſiſting Favour of the <hi>Stratico,</hi> and his, and their intereſt with the Vice-Roy, got wholly into the Family of <hi>Merli,</hi> who had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in their hands all the principal Offices appertaining to the Magiſtracy and now height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by this addition, which brought into their power the Treaſure of the place; they thought their Authority boundleſs, and making all their Officers of their own Kindred, Party and Allyes, trampled at their pleaſure over the reſt of the people, oppreſſing them with unuſual Exactions, and without diſtinction, abuſing both Nobility, Gentry, and Commons, who in their Souls breathed forth nothing but Revenge and deſtruction to theſe their violent Oppreſſors.</p>
            <p>And now their Aſſemblies began to be more frequent &amp; real Conſpiracies to be formed; and reſolutions taken to run all hazards rather than any longer endure this Tyranny, and withall the Conjuncture ſeeming more favourable <hi>(France</hi> either having already; or being upon the point to declare War againſt <hi>Spain,) Andrea Marcheſi</hi> is once again diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch't away to the Court of <hi>France,</hi> where he now finds a more favourable reception than formerly, and gaines not only promiſes but aſſurances of a certain ſuccom, as ſoon as ever they appeared in action; with which joyful news he returns home, and heartens the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators, that they begin to make all neceſſary preparations to fall on, and redeem them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their City from ſo intollerable ſlavery, and had at laſt put things in ſuch a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, that they waited only a favourable opportunity to begin the Execution.</p>
            <p>Yet were not things ſo cloſely carried, but that the <hi>Stratico,</hi> and the <hi>Merli</hi> (who knew themſelves juſttly envyed, and were therefore the more watchful.) had got ſome private intelligence, and were grown more than ſuſpicious of the whole contrivance: Wherefore, that they might be in a better poſture to defend themſelves, [for they perceived the whole Body of the People incenſed againſt them] they had ſent an account of their Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies to the Marqueſs of <hi>Bayon</hi> then <hi>Viceroy,</hi> and had procured from him four Companies of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Foot, which they diſpoſed of in the Caſtle of <hi>Matagriſſon,</hi> the Pallace <hi>Royal</hi> and the <hi>Caſtellazzo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This additional force, though it a little Alarum'd, yet not at all disheartned the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators; for they perceived the people rather incenſed than frightned at it, and therefore reſolved not to omit any opportunity to fall on, which the matter it ſelf ſoon gave thems for the <hi>Stratico</hi> and the <hi>Merli</hi> being Fortified with this additional Force, (which they knew was all they could expect, though things grow never ſo deſperate) thought it the beſt way to put a ſtop to this Gangren before it ran any further; and to that end, gave private Orders for the Arreſting of <hi>Paolo Gere, Giorgio Caraſſa,</hi> and <hi>Alberigo Marcheſi,</hi> who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed had been the principal Promoters of the Conſpiracy, and moſt aſſiduous Fomenters of the people's diſcontents. <hi>Paolo Geri</hi> and <hi>Giorgio Caraſſa</hi> fell into the hands of thoſe were ſent to apprehend them but <hi>Alberigo Marcheſi,</hi> having (as it is thought) ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intelligence, had ſecured himſelf in the Pallace of the <hi>Mattei,</hi> (which ſtands in the direct way to the <hi>Caſtellazzo,</hi> whither uſually all Priſoners of Quallity are carried,) and had there in an inſtant gathered together, near two Thouſand Armed Men of the Chief Families of the Conſpirators, and ſome of the Commons their dependants, who as the Guards were paſſing by with their Priſoners, Sallyed out in ſuch Numbers on both ſides the way, that they preſently encompaſſed and ſeiz'd them, doubting no ſuch matter, and being in all not above Fifty, reſcued their Priſoners, and as it were by inſpiration, ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Souldiers of their Coats, clad ſo many of their own number with them, and tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99071:2"/>
likewiſe their Arms, immediatly Marched in good Order towards the <hi>Caſtellazzo,</hi> where, though thoſe within had freſhly received the Rumour that their Companions were aſſaulted; yet ſeeing their Liveries coming, laid aſide all doubt, and became extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily officious to open the Gates and receive them, who having gained the Bridge, gladly let in after them the whole Croud of their Followers; ſo that beyond all hopes or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, the <hi>Caſtellazzo</hi> was in an inſtant Surpriz'd.</p>
            <p>This happy ſucceſs, and that ſo unexpected emboldened them beyond meaſure, and it was preſently ſpread abroad, ſo that in a moment the whole people had the Alarum, &amp; with great alacrity took Arms; and though the <hi>Stratico</hi> and the <hi>Merli</hi> did all they could in this confuſion, and ſent out ſeveral Companies of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Foot to ſuppreſs them, yet they flockd together in ſuch Vaſt Numbers that though the <hi>Spaniards</hi> made many brisk aſſaults, they were at laſt forced to retire with the loſs, in ſeveral Skirmiſhes of near three hundred of their Men, though with the ſlaughter of more than double that Number of <hi>Meſſineſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now the Inhabitants having got this Head (which happened on the 14th of <hi>June,</hi> 1674,) nothing was heard throughout the whole City but clamours, and Exclamations againſt the Tyranny and Oppreſſion of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Government: every one animat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Neighbour to perfect the work they had begun, and crying out, <hi>Let<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Oppreſſors of the People the</hi> Stratico <hi>and the</hi> Merli <hi>Die, and let the Exciſe be baniſhed for Ever:</hi> So that before Night they had got in Arms near 30000 Men, who went under ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Heads of the Conſpiracy into all the Quarters of the City, breaking open the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſeizing the Publick Stores and Mony wherever they found them, and with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable hatred, pulling down &amp; Plundering all the Houſes of the <hi>Merli,</hi> and committing a Thouſand inſolencies; Yet ſo well in this confuſion managed they their buſineſs, that by break of Day they were become Maſters of the Caſtle of <hi>Matagriffon,</hi> the Garriſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in not being able to defend it againſt ſuch Numbers as aſſailed them on every ſide, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſerted it, and made their Retreat to the Royal Palace. In this Caſtle they ſettled a Senate for the Government of Affairs, that they might maintain by Order what they had got by Confuſion.</p>
            <p>The firſt work theſe ſet the people about after having diſpoſed them into ſome better Order, was the gaining of the Royal Palace (whither the <hi>Stratico,</hi> the <hi>Merli,</hi> and all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were retired) which they formally Beſieged, bringing ſeveral pieces of Artillery to batter it: Many, Meſſages were ſent to them by the <hi>Stratico,</hi> and all reaſonable offers that could be thought of made them, but they would liſten to nothing; ſo that the <hi>Sratico</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no fair means would do, reſolved to hold out as long as he could, and in the mean time diſpatched away ſeveral Courtiers to Marqueſs of <hi>Bayon</hi> Vice-Roy of the <hi>Sicily</hi> to acquaint him with the ill Poſture the affairs were in, and to require his ſpeedy Aſſiſtance, but Alas, they found him not in a condition to ſend any ſuddain ſuccour, however, he immediatly ſent away to the Court at <hi>Madrid</hi> to acquaint them with this on expected Revols, and of what ill conſequence it might proveif a timely remedy were not applyed; whereupon Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were given to the Vice-Roy's of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Millan</hi> to <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vy Forces for his Aſſiſtance, and the <hi>Pope</hi> Duke of <hi>Florence, Venecians,</hi> and <hi>Genoveſses,</hi> were ſollcited to lend their Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes to <hi>joyn,</hi> with thoſe of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily</hi> for the Beſieging of the City by Sea; but the <hi>Pope,</hi> Duke, &amp; <hi>Venecian</hi> Excuſed themſelves, though the <hi>Genoveſes</hi> read<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Aſſembled, and immediatly diſpatched away two Gallies. The Marqueſs of <hi>Bayon</hi> ſent likewiſe to the Duke of <hi>Aſtorgas,</hi> Vice Roy of this Kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> for his preſent Aſſiſtance, but received but a cold anſwer; for indeed he was not then in a Poſture, and could only promiſe to uſe his endeavours as afterwards he effectually did.</p>
            <p>Mean while the Siege Palace Royal went on, and ſeveral Aſſaults and Sallyes were made, the <hi>Stratico</hi> and <hi>Merli</hi> defending themſelves very Reſolutely, till on the third of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Beſiegers cauſed a Mine to he ſprung, by which a great part of the Palace was thrown quite to the ground; ſo that the <hi>Stratico</hi> ſeeing himſelf reduced to the laſt Extremity, and finding no longer poſſibility of defending himſelf in that place, and no manner of hopes of Relief, he was forced to come to a Capitulation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſurrender the Palace into the hands of the People upon Terms, that he ſhould March out of the City with ſuch of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Merli,</hi> and all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> that were with him with thin Arms Baggage and one Piece of Cannon, and that all the reſt ſhould be left to the diſpoſition of the People Theſe Conditions were very punctually performed, and the <hi>Stratico</hi> with all his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Marched out to the Caſtle of St. <hi>Salvadore</hi> a little way diſtant from <hi>Meſſina</hi> upon the Marine, but not thinking himſelf ſecure there, he embarked for <hi>Mellazo,</hi> where he found the Marquis of <hi>Bayon,</hi> who was already come thither in order to put things in a Poſture for the reducing <hi>Meſſina</hi> by Force, ſince he could effect nothing by Treaty: For he had made ſeveral overtures to them in Order to an Accomodation, and had ſhewed himſelf
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99071:3"/>
very ready and willing to gratifie them in all reaſonable matters; offering to remove <hi>the Stratico</hi> or chief Magiſtrate, who at firſt was their greateſt pretended grievance; but now they had found out Numbers of others, and to all the Propoſitions made by the Vice-Roy ſeemed utterly Refractory, making in return ſuch high and extravagant demands as he could not in Honour aſſent to, nor the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> by any means grant, without (in a manner) giving away its whole Power and Authority over them; ſo that by their ſtubborneſs, it became apparent that they had hopes and encouragement from Abroad.</p>
            <p>And now the <hi>Meſineſſes</hi> having driven out their <hi>Stratico,</hi> and got the whole City into their hands began to take a care how they might maintain that new Power they had Rebelliouſly Uſurped; wherefore they took heart, and Marched out, forcing all the Neighbouring places to furniſh them with great quantities of Proviſions, which they carefully laid up in ſtores for their future ſupply; they likewiſe took out of the ſeveral Religious Convents all the Plate which was dedicated to Holy uſes, which they Coyn'd into Monies to ſerve their occaſions; nor ſpared they any of the goods of their adverſaries no more than their lives: for in the beginnings of theſe Inſurrections, they put to death above 160 of the Family of the <hi>Merli,</hi> (to whom they bore an unplacable hatred) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which were three Ladies of Quallity, whom they had cauſed to be Beheaded under the Character of Spies, together with a Gentleman of the Family of <hi>Pavordo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto they went on ſuccesfully, the Vice-Roy not being yet got into any condition to check much leſs oppreſs them; ſo that by the middle of <hi>Auguſt</hi> they had brought all the Country within 16 Leagues of the City under their Juriſdiction, and ſent ſeveral Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties into Forreign parts to Solicite Succours, and to buy Powder and other Amunition neceſſary for their Defence; but ſtill their chief Relyance, and what they kept the people united with, was the hopes of a powerful aſſiſtance from <hi>France;</hi> which they had conſtant aſſurances of, which made them the more obſtinate againſt hearkning to an Accomodation, though the Vice-Roy began to draw Forces to gather together at <hi>Mellazo,</hi> and that Five Gallies of <hi>Genova</hi> under the Command of the Marqueſs <hi>Gio: Dilrazzo,</hi> who had taken in 400 <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Soldiers at <hi>Niſita,</hi> was likewiſe arrived there with Command from that Commonwealth, to obſerve what Orders he ſhould receive from the Marquis of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yon,</hi> and moreover the Vice-Roys of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Millan</hi> were making great Preparations, ſo that the cloud began to grow thick over their Heads. Yet whilſt all this Force was gathering together, no endeavours of an amieable compoſure were accepted, but all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions the ViceR-oy could make were ſlighted by the <hi>Meſſineſes,</hi> who now alleadged that they could not with ſafety hearken to any Accomodation till the Marqueſs of <hi>Bayon</hi> had disbanded thoſe Forces he had at preſent with him, and was removed in Perſon to <hi>Paler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo.</hi> And yet all the while they continued thus obſtinate in the very act of Rebellion: It is to be obſerved, they (as is uſual in ſuch caſes) ſtill profeſs'd all duty, Loyalty, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeance to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> declaring that they were forced to take up Arms againſt thoſe who had the Chief Government of the City, who had oppreſſed them with many intollerable Exactions, and done ſeveral things to the prejudice and detriment of their City; upon whoſe removal from the Government, and the redreſſing of their grievances, they pretended to be willing to lay down Arms, and return to their Obedience.</p>
            <p>But to give them the greater encouragement, there happened difference among thoſe ſmall Forces which the Vice-Roy had already drawn together to oppreſs them; a diſpute ariſing between the General, of the <hi>Maltha</hi> and <hi>Genova,</hi> Gallies (which were come to aſſiſt the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> againſt this City) about Precedency; in which the General of the <hi>Maltha</hi> Gallyes, having in ſome manner, at the inſtance of the Vice-Roy of <hi>Sicily,</hi> yielded to the <hi>Genoveſes,</hi> incurred the diſpleaſure of the great Maſter, who in anger ſent for him home, ſo that that aſſiſtance was loſt; and yet to give them more heart, about the latter end of <hi>September</hi> arrived at <hi>Meſſina;</hi> the <hi>Chevalier de Valbelle</hi> with Nine Ships, whereof Six were <hi>French</hi> Men of War, and the other ſtores of Amunition and Proviſion; which gave them ſuch aſſurance of larger Succours from <hi>France,</hi> that with a great deal of Joy they put up the White Standard, declaring that they caſt themſelves under the Protection of that Crown; nor was this only an encouragement in it ſelf, but in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of it: For though upon the firſt breaking out of theſe diſorders, when the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> deſired the State of <hi>Genova,</hi> to ſend ſome of their Gallies to the aſſiſtance of the Vice-Roy of <hi>Sicily,</hi> they readily did it. Yet now the Senate being informed that ſeveral <hi>French</hi> Men of War were arrived at <hi>Meſſina,</hi> and that the Inhabitants had put themſelves under the Protection of that Crown; they for fear of a Rupture with ſo Potent an Enemy, gave immediat Orders for recalling their Gallyes, ſo that that part of the Aſſiſtance was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe loſt.</p>
            <p>Yet both the Vice-Roy of <hi>Sicily,</hi> the Vice-Roys of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Millan,</hi> and the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> proceeded more vigorouſly in giving Orders, and Levying Forces for the reducing of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99071:3"/>
this Citty ere things grew worſe: For now they ſaw what they feared was happen'd, and began to be apprehenſive of greater inconveniencies, (eſpecially ſince they hoped for Aſſiſtance of <hi>Vantrump</hi> with his Fleet had failed them,) and the <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> on the other part encouraged by Succeſſes they had already been flattered with, began to think of attempting greater matters; and on the 10<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>October</hi> took the Caſtle of St. <hi>Salvadore,</hi> which was the only place of Strength the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had remaining near the City, which they immediatly delivered up into the poſſeſſion of the <hi>French.</hi> In this Caſtle the <hi>Spaniards</hi> themſelves well at firſt; the Governour and moſt of the Garriſon having been Slain, was taken, yet then loſt it at laſt as careleſly; for the <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> had made many attempts upon it before the coming of the <hi>Sicurde Valbelle,</hi> but upon his Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, he reſolved formally to Beſiege this Caſtle; and accordingly, on the ſecond of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> at Night, opened the Trenches which were continued till the Fourth at Night; the <hi>Spaniards</hi> being during that time forced from their utmoſt Paliſadoes, and the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers having Seized on a Well about Fifty paces from the Caſtle, from whence they within had all their Water: Whereupon on the Fifth of <hi>October,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Capitulated, and it was agreed, that the Caſtle ſhould be delivered, if not Relieved in Eight Days; during which time, ſeveral Batteries were cauſed by the <hi>French</hi> to the end, the Siege might be continued, if any Aſſiſtance ſhould come to the Beſieged; to hinder which, the <hi>Sieur de Valbelle</hi> Anchor'd his Ships under <hi>San Salvador.</hi> The Tenth of <hi>October,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh Armada,</hi> under the Command of <hi>Don Melchior de la Cueva,</hi> conſiſting of Twenty Sail of Men of War appeared, and came to Anchor in ſome diſorder between <hi>Paradis</hi> and <hi>Noſtredam de la Grote;</hi> whereupon the Beſieged either apprehending them to be <hi>French</hi> Men of War, and conſequently looking upon themſelves as loſt, grew careleſs in keeping the Guards; or elſe for ſome other unknown Reaſons, gave the <hi>Meſſineſſes</hi> opportunity of Entring the Caſtle, which they did without the leaſt difficulty, making themſelves Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of it, and of the Officers and Soldiers in it, whom they carried Priſoners to <hi>Meſſina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 12<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet continuing ſtill at Anchor, and in the ſame diſorder; ſeveral of their Ships having loſt their Rudders, or ſuſtained other damage; the <hi>Sieur de Valbelle</hi> finding the Wind favourable, ſet Sail with his Squadron, conſiſting of Five great Men of War, and Three Fire-Ships, with deſign to Attack the Enemy, and try if he could burn ſome of their Ships; in which the favourableneſs of the Wind, and their diſorder promiſed him ſome Succeſs; but the Enemy perceiving his deſign, ſet Sail, and retired to <hi>Rheggio:</hi> ſo <hi>Valbelle</hi> went a ſhore again, and having given Order for the repairing the Fortifications of St. <hi>Salvador,</hi> and aſſured the Senate of his Maſters Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, took leave, and with his Squadron ſet Sail for <hi>Thoulon.</hi> But the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> was ſo much ſtartl'd at this ſucceſs, that they gave Orders for the Fortifying of <hi>Rheggio</hi> on the oppoſite there, and for the haſtning of the Levyes from all parts of the Dominions of that Crown, leaſt the proceedings of this City ſhould endanger, not only the Peace of all the reſt of <hi>Sicily,</hi> but of the K<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Naples</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>To prevent therefore the Miſchiefs <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at might enſue by any delay in reducing this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious City; the Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Franca</hi> is Commiſſionated Vice-Roy of <hi>Sicily,</hi> in the ſtead of the Marqueſs of <hi>Bayon;</hi> who about the beginning of <hi>November</hi> arrived at <hi>Mellazzo</hi> with 22 Gallyes, and good Supplies of Men, Mony, and Ammunition from <hi>Spain,</hi> to whom the Vice-Roy of <hi>Naples</hi> ſent daily Recruits, as well of Old as New raiſed Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers; beſides the two Regiments ſent by the Vice-Roy of <hi>Millan</hi> from that State: So that now both by Sea, and Land, there appeared a Formidable Power before <hi>Meſſina,</hi> and all Paſſes being block'd up, Proviſions began to grow extreamly ſcarce, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people to be Diffident and Mutinous; and ſome there were that began to cry out for Peace, and though ſtill the oppoſing Party were more Prevalent, yet there wanted not thoſe that did bitterly exclaim againſt thoſe that had brought them into this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture; and indeed the better ſort of them, had ſome apprehenſions: for they not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting to have been Attack'd before Spring, could not fore-ſee, how they could poſſibly for want of Proviſion, hold out all Winter.</p>
            <p>Yet was not the <hi>Sieur de Valbelle</hi> unmindfull of them, nor the aſſurances he had given them of his Maſters aſſiſtance and Protection? Wherefore as ſoon as he Arrived at <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeilles,</hi> he went up Poſt to <hi>Paris,</hi> and repreſenting to His moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, the true State of the Affairs of this City, procured Orders for a ſpeedy Succour, both of Men, and Proviſions, with a conſiderable Squadron of Men of War to convey it to <hi>Meſſina,</hi> for fear of Oppoſition; Mean while, ſeveral Barks with Corn, and other Proviſions ventured in to them, though ſeveral of them fell ſhort, being taken by the <hi>Spainard.</hi> And now, on the 16th. of <hi>December,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Ferrandina</hi> now, newly made Vice-Roy of <hi>Sicily,</hi> in the ſtead of the Marqueſs of <hi>Franca,</hi> arrived at <hi>Meſſina,</hi> with 21 Gallyes, and 8 Men of War; taking in his way ſome Barks, bound hither with Proviſion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99071:4"/>
theſe loſſes, the <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> began now to fail of their wonted ſucceſs; for in an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter they had with the <hi>Spaniards</hi> near the <hi>Sealleta,</hi> they received a great defeat, three or four hundred of them being Slain upon the place, and the reſt beaten to their very Walls.</p>
            <p>Nor was this Defeat at the <hi>Scaletta</hi> left unproſecuted, for, in Purſuance of it, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the arrival of the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Galyes, with a conſiderable quantity of Men; the Duke <hi>Florendina</hi> with great diligence, cauſed them to advance towards the point of <hi>Pedoro,</hi> (whence the <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> had ſome very conſiderable Poſts) and to endeavour to put their Men on ſhore, and drive the Enemy thence; but the <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> perceiving their intention, ſtayed not for them, but immediatly quitted thoſe Poſts, and retired into the City; leaving behind them ſeveral Pieces of Cannon, and good quantity of Ammunition: Whereupon the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Advanced, and took from them the Tower of <hi>Faro,</hi> without any great Oppoſition on the Part of the <hi>Meſſineſes,</hi> and in purſuit of all this, they took likewiſe the Tower of the <hi>Lanterna,</hi> which lyes between the Caſtle of St. <hi>Salvador,</hi> and the City; having had ſecret intelligence with the Signor <hi>Grimaldi,</hi> who had the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it.</p>
            <p>And to add more to their grief was the taking of their truſty Meſſenger Signor <hi>Andrea Marcheſi,</hi> who had been twice in <hi>France</hi> to Solicit Aid for them; and now going a Third time, to haſten thoſe Supplies they ſo earneſtly expected; was taken at Sea, by a ſmall Corſair of this City of <hi>Naples,</hi> and brought in Priſoner hither: ſeveral Letters he had taken with him which diſcovered the Straits they were reduced to, which put the <hi>Spaniards</hi> here in mighty heart: the Town could not long hold out, yet the better to Expedite its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement, the Marqueſs of <hi>Aſtorgas</hi> gave Commiſſions to the Duke of <hi>Martina,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Canſano,</hi> to raiſe two Regiments of Foot, to be ſent into <hi>Sicily;</hi> and <hi>Andrea Marcheſi</hi> was by the Vice-Roy of <hi>Naples</hi> ſent Priſoner to the Court of <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſomewhat to allay all theſe ſorrows, came the ſeaſonable arrival of the <hi>Sieur de Valbelle,</hi> the ſecond time with Eight Men of War, and Eight other Veſſels laden with a conſiderable quantity of Proviſions, and other neceſſaries; beſides a relief of Men: The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet conſiſting of 21 Men of War, and 21 Gallyes had lain a long time in the Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, watching to prevent any Succours comeing in to Town; but now when they ſaw the <hi>Chevalier de Valbelle</hi> appeared with his Squadron, they lay ſtill with all this great Fleet on the <hi>Calabrian</hi> ſide, giving him free paſſage, without offering to make the leaſt oppoſition, or ſhewing any deſign of preventing him; whether it proceeded from ſome difference about Precedency, which happend between the General of the Ships, and General of the Gallyes, ſo that they could not agree who ſhould fall on firſt; Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were ſtupified, as moſt think: For certainly, never came Supply ſo ſeaſonable as this did to the <hi>Meſſineſes,</hi> who were reduced to ſuch Extremities for want of Proviſion, and other Neceſſaries, that they ſeemed not to think of any thing, but how to reconcile themſelves to the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> whereas by this <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>une Supply, they were ſo well Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruited, that they became not at all doubtful of <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ng able to defend themſelves for a good while: The <hi>Chevalies de Valbelle</hi> not only bringing them this Relief, but aſſuring them that the Marqueſs of <hi>Vivonne</hi> would ſoon follow after him, with a far Greater. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon for Joy, as they had at his firſt Arrival, delivered up to him the Caſtle of St. <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vador,</hi> that Commanded the Port; ſo now they delivered up to him the Caſtle of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagriffon</hi> that Commands the Town, whereby the <hi>French</hi> became abſolute Maſters of the City.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding the Duke of <hi>Florendina</hi> endeavoured by all means, and ways poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to endeavour to ſuppreſs them by Land, and was very much afflicted at his miſcarriage by Sea, as were likewiſe the whole Court of <hi>Spain</hi> when they heard it; Yet they gave all the careful Orders they could to bring the matter to a good iſſue, and put things in ſuch a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, that the Vice-Roy might be able to lay a cloſe Siege; and that with a Powerful Army, by firſt of the Spring; to which end, Count <hi>Anthonio Trottie</hi> had ſent his Lt. Colonel from the State of <hi>Millan</hi> into <hi>Germany,</hi> to compleat his Regment to 2000 Men, and the <hi>Sieur Don Emanuel de Portuſtal,</hi> was likewiſe gone thither, to raiſe a new Regiment for the ſervice of <hi>Sicily,</hi> beſides the great Levies that were making in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples;</hi> but in the mean while, ſeveral Veſſels loden with Corn from <hi>Rochel,</hi> under the Conduct of <hi>Monſieur de Gance,</hi> ſeconded the Recruits juſt before brought in by the <hi>Chevalier de Valbelle;</hi> along with whom, there was likewiſe come the Marqueſs of <hi>Valavoir,</hi> with a compleat Regiment of 600 Men, and Title of Commander, in Chief of His moſt Chriſtian Majeſties Forces in <hi>Sicily;</hi> by woſe courage and active aſſiſtance, the Inhebitants of <hi>Meſſina</hi> had ſo mended their Affairs, that they had repaired all thoſe Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, ſo lately ſuſteined by the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> and had regained all thoſe conſiderable Poſts taken from them, (particularly the Towers of <hi>Faro,</hi> and <hi>la Lanterna)</hi> which had put the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99071:4"/>
People into freſh heart, and made them Treat the Marqueſs with ſuch extraordinary Reſpect, and kindneſs; that they lodg'd him in the Pallace Royal, and Stil'd him their Protector and Defender; whilſt on the other ſide, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were Alarum'd and ſo ſencibl of the fault they had committed, of permitting the <hi>Chevalier de Valbelle</hi> and <hi>Grance</hi> to enter with that welcome Relief, that ſtrict Orders were given to the Fleet, to cruiſe with more diligence before the Port; and by all means poſſible, endeavour to prevent the the comeing in of the Marqueſs of <hi>Vivonne,</hi> who was expected with a third Supply, not doubting, but if they could hinder his Entrance, the Proviſions already in the Town, would ſoon be ſpent among ſo Numerous a people; and if they could once more bring them into want, they doubted not but ſoon to bring them to a complyance; and to give more colour to their Affairs, they uſed all diligence to bring as many Forces as they could before the City, and form a cloſe Siege; and it was every where reported that the Forces, lately in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> under the Command of the Duke of St. <hi>Germain,</hi> were already im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barked to come to their Aſſiſtances; and the Marqueſs of <hi>Aſtorgas</hi> Vice-Roy of <hi>Naples</hi> did really labour, with all earneſtneſs to ſupply the Vice-Roy of <hi>Sicily</hi> with a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſiſtance from hence; in Order to which, he demanded of all the Nobillity of this Kingdom, that according to their reſpective Quallities, they ſhould raiſe certain Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to be formed into Troops, and Regiments, for the Service of His Catholick Majeſty againſt the <hi>Meſſineſs:</hi> but all theſe preparations ſeemed, both to themſelves and to their enemies, but as ſo many Bug-Bears; for their whole dependance was really in their Fleet, and they knew very well, that unleſs they could hinder Proviſions from comeing in by Sea, they ſhould be able to do very little, or no good by Land.</p>
            <p>And herein they took their Meaſures right, had they proſecuted them as well, had For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune favoured their diligence, as it did at the beginning of theſe Reſolves; For then it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, that a Ship with 5000 Meaſures of Corn, and 50000 Crowns in Mony fell into their hands, which was a joyful Prize to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and their joys was doubled, when they had at firſt certain intelligence that Corn began to grow ſcarce in the City; and at laſt that the common people were reduced to ſuch great and pinching neceſſities, that they were forced to feed a good while on Horſes, Mules, Cats, and Dogs; and were in the end brought ſo low, that they were conſtrained to take the hides, after they had lain a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable time in the <hi>Tanſat,</hi> and accomodating them in the beſt manner they could diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute them, among the poorer ſort gratis, at two Ounces a Man for a day s Allowance.</p>
            <p>And becauſe afflictions, and diſtreſſes of this kind, have always their concomitant miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs; and among a people oppreſſed with want, ſome are leſs able or willing to endure the Pangs of it than others; and neceſſity puts it their heads to relieve themſelves, though with the general calamity: It happened that a Gunner belonging to <hi>Caſtellazzo,</hi> had kept private intelligence with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> to deliver that Foretreſs into their hands; and to that end, on the 9<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>February</hi> laſt had given Thirty <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſecret Entrance into the place, and a Thouſand more were Advanced hard by to ſocure the deſign; but the Plot coming to be diſcovered by the <hi>French,</hi> the Execution was prevented, and the Gunner taken, and Hang'd; And to prevent ſuch Corruptions for the Future, all the <hi>Meſſineſſes</hi> were removed out of all the Forts, and holds about the City, and <hi>French</hi> put in Garriſon into them; ſo that this miſerable City, was now become abſolutly ſubject to new Maſters.</p>
            <p>Hitherto through all theſe Extremities they bore up, out of the aſſurances they had, that <hi>Monſieur de Vivonne</hi> was at hand, with a conſiderable Supply; though it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible they could have farther ſuſteined themſelves, but muſt have ſtarved, or ſurrendred to the Mercy of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> if His comeing were but a little more delay'd: But it pleaſed God, that on the 11<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>February,</hi> he appeared about a League from the <hi>Fares</hi> mouth, to their unſpeakable Joy, yet had their Joy a ſufficient allay of fear when they beheld the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet, conſiſting of Twenty Men of War, and Sixteen Gallyes ſteering from the <hi>Catabrian</hi> ſide in good Order; yet with great Fury to oppoſe the <hi>French</hi> paſſage, and drive them, if they could, fom entring into the Port, but <hi>Monſieur de Vivonne</hi> perceiving their intentions, ſoon ranged his little Fleet, conſiſting of Nine Men of War, into three Squadrons of three Men of War each, and with great Courage and Reſolution, received the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Charge; Bravely maintaining the Fight by himſelf, againſt all that advantage, from Eight of of the Clock in the Morning, till Noon; about which time, <hi>Monſieur de Valbelle</hi> with ſix Men of War, and three Fire-Ships, came out of <hi>Meſſina</hi> to their aſſiſtance; upon whoſe arrival, the Fight was renewed more briskly on the <hi>French</hi> ſide, than it had bin begun on the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> ſo that about Three of the Clock in the Afternoon, the <hi>French</hi> got the Weather-gage, and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> (no longer able to endure the Brunt) having their Riging very much ſhattered, and Torne, began to Retire; and at length, ſpreading all the Canvas they could, made their way towards the City of <hi>Naples:</hi> Whither they came in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99071:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
about three dayes ſince, in a very Torne and Tattered conditon, and with minds as much dejected as their Fortunes, here being moſt of them: They are but 15 of their Men of War returned hither, and one of thoſe without any Maſts; as for the other Five, one called the <hi>Madona del Populo,</hi> a Ship of Forty Guns, we certainly know to be in <hi>Meſſina,</hi> having been taken by the <hi>Chevalier de Valbelle:</hi> what became of the reſt, they themſelves can give but a very ſlender account; but it is generally believed that being much Torne, they Sunk in the Night after the Fight. The <hi>French</hi> loſs amounted not to above 200 ſlain and wounded. This ſo great and conſiderable Defeat, attended with the conſequence of the ſo lucky Relief of <hi>Meſſina,</hi> has ſo Nettled the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that they Publickly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed againſt the Cowardiſe, and evil managemement of their Generals, and other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Fleet: The Marqueſs of <hi>Aſtorgos</hi> (who all along expreſſed his Zeal, and earneſtneſs to reduce this Rebellious City) ſeemed moſt of all afflicted, and could not forbear to expreſs his particular Reſentments, againſt <hi>Don Melchior del la Ciceva,</hi> and Marqueſs of <hi>Piſo,</hi> the two Admiralls; And it is expected by all Men, that both they, and other Officers, will by the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> be called to a ſtrict account, for a Miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of ſo High a Nature, and which it may reaſonably be expected, will be attended by ſuch Fatal Conſequences: If the <hi>French</hi> (as no doubt but upon ſuch encouragement they will) proceed in this conjuncture, to ſend greater Succours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mounſieur de Vivone</hi> purſued the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> Fighting till it was almoſt Night; but then being informed that the <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> had been already ſeveral dayes without Bread, he left off the Purſuit, and made all haſt he could to relieve them; whoſe Arrival could not but be extream Welcom to thoſe miſerable people, who had endured ſuch Vaſt Extreamities; and that they might (in the beſt manner they could) expreſs their Joy, and Gratitude to His moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, for ſo many and timely Succours; the whole People with U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal conſent, took an Oath of Fidelity to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and received from <hi>Monſieur de Vivonne,</hi> aſſurances that there were yet more conſiderable Succours near at hand. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> were ſo amaz'd at <hi>Monſieur de Vivone</hi>'s Entrance, that they quitted ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral conſiderable Poſts; However they ſeem not utterly disheartned, but give out that they ſhall in a Month or Six weeks, have a great Army in readineſs, and be in a Poſture to lay a cloſe Siege to the City.</p>
            <p>Thus I have given as full an account, according to your deſire, and my promiſe, of the Original Cauſe, and Progreſs of the troubles of this Great, and Populous City hitherto, what the iſſue will be, no body is able to Divine; eſpecially, conſidering the Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy of the Inhabitants, in defending themſelves, and the Powerful Aſſiſtance they have; which until it fails them, they will certainly undergo all hazards, rather than fall again udner the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Yoak (eſpecially now, they have ſo grievouſly offended and Allarum'd them: For, conſidering on the other ſide, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Zeal, and carneſtneſs to reduce them, and fears, and jealouſies they have been put into. It cannot but be imagined, the <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> muſt be [indeed] a miſerable People, if ever by Force they become again their Maſters; and, on the other ſide, it is to be doubted, the <hi>French</hi> will hardly let go, the hold they have now there. I cannot tell therefore, where to place a <hi>Medium</hi> to a recconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe diſorders; unleſs when it ſhall pleaſe God to diſpoſe <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> to a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Peace; ſome happy Expedient (not yet thought of) be found out. I am afraid, I have been too tedious, and therefore take my <hi>leave,</hi> and remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant,
E. W.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:99071:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
