<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief discourse concerning the lawfulness of worshipping God by the common-prayer being an answer to a book entituled A brief discourse concerning the unlawfulness of the common-prayer worship lately printed in New-England, and re-printed in London, in which the chief things objected against the liturgy, are consider'd.</title>
            <author>Williams, John, 1636?-1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66373</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12495181</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12495181</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62493</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A66373)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62493)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 951:67)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief discourse concerning the lawfulness of worshipping God by the common-prayer being an answer to a book entituled A brief discourse concerning the unlawfulness of the common-prayer worship lately printed in New-England, and re-printed in London, in which the chief things objected against the liturgy, are consider'd.</title>
                  <author>Williams, John, 1636?-1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition corrected.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ri. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Williams. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Book of common prayer --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Worship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62493:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62493:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF DISCOURSE Concerning the Lawfulneſs of Worſhipping GOD BY THE COMMON-PRAYER.
Being in ANSWER To a Book, Entituled, A Brief Diſcourſe concerning the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs of the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Worſhip.
Lately Printed in <hi>New-England,</hi> and Re-printed in <hi>London.</hi>
In which, the Chief Things Objected againſt the Liturgy, are conſider'd.</p>
            <p>The Second Edition Corrected.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Let all things be done decently, and in order, <bibl>1 Cor. 14. 40.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ri. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, M DC XCIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:62493:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> 9. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>GEO. ROYSE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:62493:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>HOW <hi>Pious</hi> or <hi>Learned</hi> the Author of the Book I undertake to anſwer may be, I am no more concern'd to know, than I am who the Author is, whom the Publiſher bath thought fit to commend as ſuch; and having ſo done, to conceal. But he is not (as far as I conceive) the more <hi>Learned</hi> or <hi>Pious</hi> for Writing this Book: Not the more <hi>Learned;</hi> for by all the helps he profeſſes to have had from <hi>Dido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clavius,</hi> &amp;c. he is guilty of many groſs and palpable Miſtakes: And not the more <hi>Pious,</hi> becauſe of the uncharitable Reflections and Inferences he every where makes. For would any man of a truly Chriſtian Temper al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge theſe things now againſt the Common-Prayer, which were alter'd or expunged above thirty years before he publiſhed his <hi>Brief Diſcourſe?</hi> Or charge us with <hi>violating</hi> the Word of God, becauſe we change the word <hi>Sabbath</hi> for the <hi>Seventh</hi> Day; or ſay that we <hi>ſacrilegiouſly ſteal</hi> from it, becauſe <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> or <hi>Praiſe the Lord,</hi> is ſometimes left out in the Reading-Pſalms; or that we <hi>equal</hi> the Apocrypha to, and ſet it up <hi>above</hi> the Canonical Scriptures, becauſe it s read on the Higheſt Holy-days (as he ſaith, but not very truly) tho the Articles of our Church expreſly declare them to be only of humane compoſition. Suppoſe now I ſhould treat this Author after the ſame manner; and whereas he profeſſes to have <hi>compared</hi> our <hi>Liturgy</hi> with the <hi>Miſſal,</hi> &amp;c. I ſhould take all advantages given in his Book, to ſhew, that notwithſtanding this, he had never read them. I am certain, I could much more eaſily, and as Charitably do it, as he make good his aboveſaid Charge. For would any one converſant in the <hi>Miſſal, Breviary</hi> and <hi>Ritual</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> have ſaid (as he doth, <hi>p. 5.) That</hi> Beza <hi>notes, that in the</hi> Roman <hi>Liturgy, men are taught to cry,</hi> Jeſu Miſerere mei, <hi>no leſs than ten times one after another?</hi> For what need he quote <hi>Beza</hi> for that which he has (as he ſaith) read him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and which after all, <hi>Beza</hi> miſtook, and he with <hi>Beza;</hi> or rather he miſtakes <hi>Beza</hi> in; ſince the <hi>Jeſu Miſerere</hi> thus repeated, is not in the <hi>Miſſal,</hi> &amp;c. but in private Offices of that Church. Who again, that had been converſant in our Liturgy, would have ſaid, as the Author, <hi>Some have obſerv'd, that of 172 Apocryphal Chapters, but 38 are omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:62493:3"/>
For what need he to be beholden to another's <hi>Obſervation,</hi> for what he that had thus read the Liturgy muſt have under his own eye? So eaſy is it to repay him in his own Coin, if we will reflect and infer after his way.</p>
            <p>It's a ſhrewd ſign this Author was hard put to it to make good his Charge againſt the Liturgy, and to prove his Point, That it's unlawful to <hi>be preſent at the Common-Prayer Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after all, it's of little Service to our Author, and thoſe of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, to make ſuch Exceptions as he has done; for if all things were alter'd and remov'd that he objects againſt, they of his way would be no nearer to us than they are, as the things ſtand at preſent; as long as we are a National Church, and have a Liturgy; and whilſt they continue Independent and Congregational, are againſt the uſe of any Forms, even ſuch as are Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural (as the Lord's Prayer and Decalogue;) nay, againſt reading the Scripture in their Publick Congregations.</p>
            <p>Indeed he had dealt more ſincerely, if he had acquainted his Reader, That they hold it unlawful to communicate with us, becauſe we are a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church; and that they don't joyn in the Common-Prayer Worſhip, becauſe it's a Form, and all Forms are in his Opinion unlawful. This indeed had ſtruck at the Root of all; but this he knew was not ſo eaſily prov'd, nor would look ſo popularly, as to cry out <hi>Heatheniſm, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſm,</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> which he charges our <hi>Service-Book</hi> with. This indeed will rouze the Multitude; and it's no wonder when poſſeſs'd with this Repreſentation of our Worſhip, that the deluded People broke into the Church (Erected at <hi>Boſton</hi> for the Worſhip of God, according to the Church of <hi>England)</hi> to ſearch for the Images they ſuppoſed we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip'd. The time was when the <hi>Antinomians</hi> from among themſelves, <note place="margin">Hiſtory of <hi>Antinomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> in the Preface.</note>treated them in the like way, and call'd them <hi>Legal Preachers, Popiſh Factors, Scribes, and Oppoſers of Chriſt.</hi> And they may remember what had like to have been the Effect of it, if they had not taken up what their Adverſaries call'd a <hi>Bloody Tenet.</hi> And truly we had reaſon to fear it, if there had not been a Superior Authority to over-rule it.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall forbear to recriminate, and ſhall leave the reſt to the Book, where I have let nothing eſcape that requires an Anſwer; and I hope have given a ſufficient Anſwer to it, and in the iſſue have prov'd, that (as far as his Exceptions go) they have no reaſon to forbear being preſent at, or joyning in the Common-Prayer-Book Worſhip; which is the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Firſt Queſtion: Nor that it's unlawful to take an Oath by laying the Hand upon the Bible; which is the Matter of the Second.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62493:3"/>
            <head>A BRIEF DISCOURSE Concerning the Lawfulneſs of Worſhipping GOD BY THE COMMON-PRAYER.</head>
            <p>THE Firſt Queſtion propoſed by the Author, is,<lb/>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What are the Reaſons why you judge it unlawful to be preſent at, or to partake in the Common-Prayer Worſhip?</p>
            <p>The Reaſons he gives are four, taken,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> From the Original of the Common-Prayer-Book, which, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> with the Ceremonies and Worſhip preſcribed therein, I find to be in a great meaſure Popiſh and Heatheniſh.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> From the Matter of the Common-Prayer-Book.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Becauſe Publick Liturgies of humane Compoſure, are an Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Deviation from Primitive Purity.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> In this Age of Light, it would be a great Apoſtacy in the leaſt to countenance or comply with the Common-Prayer-Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Reaſons he advances, and by which he endeavours to juſtify their continuance in a Separation from the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the Worſhip therein Adminiſtred.</p>
            <p>And theſe I ſhall take the liberty to examine.</p>
            <p>For the clearer diſcourſing upon which, I ſhall divide what I have to ſay, into ſo many Chapters, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the Original of the Common Prayer, or <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of the Matter of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of the Original of Liturgies.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Of Worſhip by a Liturgy.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62493:4"/>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the Original of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>OUR Author ſaith, That</hi> the Common-Prayer-Book, with the Ceremonies and Worſhip preſcribed therein, are in a great meaſure Popiſh and Heatheniſh; <hi>and therefore it is unlawful to joyn with it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This will be reſolved into two Queſtions.</p>
               <p n="1">Q. 1. Whether the Common Prayer be taken out of the Maſs-Book; and be Heatheniſh, as well as Popiſh?</p>
               <p n="2">Q. 2. Whether the being taken out of the Maſs-Book, makes it unlawfull to be uſed or joyned with, tho it be good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in it ſelf?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 1. Whether the Common-Prayer is taken out of the Maſs-Book? As our Author takes care to repreſent it, one would think there is little of the <hi>Roman</hi> Service left out in ours. <hi>The Common-Prayer,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is in a great meaſure Popiſh—is taken out of the Popes Maſs-Book—it cannot be denied it's derived from thence,</hi> p. 1. <hi>There is very little in the</hi> Engliſh, <hi>which is not to be found in the other,</hi> p. 2. This is matter of Fact, and ſo is not to be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Authority. He himſelf makes a fair propoſal, which I ſhall accept of, viz. <hi>Let ſuch as have any heſitancy about this matter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Popiſh Miſſal, &amp;c. with the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Liturgy, and they will be convinced,</hi> Of what? That he had never read and compared them; or is guilty of a notorious Abuſe that he puts upon his ignorant Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that after he pretends to have read and compared, ſhall aſſert ſo groſs a falſhood, and ſay, There is very little in the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that is not to be found in the other, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For there is little comparatively in the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which is to be found in the <hi>Roman</hi> Liturgy, and far more is left out, than ever was taken thence. This is indeed directly contrary to what he affirms, and yet let any one compare them, and he will be convinced of the truth of it. Take that which is called <hi>the Cannon of the Maſs,</hi> or Form of Adminiſtring the Euchariſt, and there is no Agreement, not one Collect or Prayer the ſame. Go we to Baptiſm, there is not one Prayer belonging to that Office that is in ours. And as for the Litany, there is not a third part of theirs in ours, and much in ours which is not in theirs.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62493:4"/>
2. There is nothing in the Service of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which makes it <hi>the Popes Miſſal,</hi> and is peculiar to that Church, that is in ours; that is, there is no Popery in our Liturgy. This he is in part forced to acknowledge. <hi>There are,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>things (as Prayers for the Dead, &amp;c.) in the</hi> Roman <hi>Liturgy, which are not tranſlated into</hi> Engliſh. His <hi>Et cetera,</hi> if branched into particulars, would be very large, as he could not but know, if he had <hi>read</hi> and <hi>compared</hi> them. As for Example, Where are their Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, Elevation, and Adoration of the Elements? Where their Solitary Communion, and Communion in one kind? Where their frequent Croſſings of themſelves, and of the Book? Where their material Croſſes, and the Adoration of them? Where their Prayers for the Dead? Where their Interceſſors, the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> and Saints, that are to be found in the Cannon of the Maſs? Where are the many Exorciſms in Baptiſm, the Puffs they blow in the Infant's face, their Conjuration of Salt, <hi>for a wholeſome Sacrament to the driving away of Devils,</hi> that's put into the Mouth of the Infant, <hi>as a propitiation unto Eternal Life?</hi> Where the Spittle with which the Ears and Noſtrils of the Infants are touched with an <hi>Ephphatha, be opened?</hi> Where the <hi>Oyl of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> (as it's call'd) wherewith the Prieſt anoints the Child's Breaſt and Shoulders in form of a Croſs? Where the Chriſm or Oyntment wherewith he anoints the Crown of the Head in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of a Croſs? Where the change of Garments, their Purple and White Robe, that the Child is to <hi>carry unſpotted before the Tribunal of our Lord?</hi> Where the lighted Candle put into the Child's hand, that <hi>when our Lord ſhall come to the Wedding, he may meet him?</hi> Where the many Croſſings of the Head before Baptiſm, and of the Eyes, Ears, Noſtrils, Breaſt, Shoulders, Mouth, &amp;c. to be found in their Ritual and Paſtoral? <hi>Laſtly,</hi> To go no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Where are the <hi>O Holy</hi> Mary, <hi>Mother of God, &amp;c. pray for us?</hi> Where are the Angels and Arch-Angels, the Patriarchs and Prophets, the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts; the Martyrs, Popes, and Confeſſors, the Prieſts and Levites, the Monks and Hermits, the Virgins and Widows, the Forty ſeven Saints in particular, and all Saints in general, that are called upon in their Litany, <hi>Pray for us?</hi> And if nothing that is truly Popiſh be to be found in our Liturgy, we have ſo far reaſon to deny that it's taken out of the Maſs-Book.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I add, That our Service is ſo far from being taken out of he Miſſal, that whatſoever in it is the ſame with the Office in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62493:5"/>
Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is moſtly taken out of the Ancient Offices of the Chriſtian Church. And becauſe every one cannot compare it, I will produce Impartial Authority for it. Thus ſaith Mr. <hi>Ball,</hi> a Nonconformiſt of great Note in the laſt Age, <hi>The</hi> Engliſh <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Trial of the Grounds of Separ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 8. <hi>p.</hi> 152.</note>
                  <hi>is not a Collection out of the Maſs-Book, but a refining of the Liturgy, which heretofore had been ſtained with the Maſs—and is not a Tranſlation of the Maſs, but a Reſtitution of the Ancient Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies.</hi> So the Miniſters of <hi>Old England,</hi> in a Letter to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>New England,</hi> wrote <hi>Anno</hi> 1637. <hi>It's no hard task to ſhew, that our Service-Book was reformed in moſt things according to the pureſt Liturgies, which were in uſe long before the Maſs was heard of in the World,</hi> p 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To theſe I will add one more, for the Character our Author gives of him,</hi> viz. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Jewel <hi>(whom he calls</hi> that great Light in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, <hi>p. 9.) Who ſaith,</hi> We are come as near as poſſibly we could to the Church of the Apoſtles, and of the old Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Biſhops and Fathers—And beſides, we have aimed not only our Doctrine, but Sacraments alſo, and Forms of our Publick Prayers, after the patern of their Rites and Ordinances.</p>
               <p>To ſay the truth, it's a very odd thing to repreſent our Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy as Popiſh, when thoſe that compoſed and uſed the Liturgy, were burnt by the Papiſts for it, and when to this day they will not communicate in it, nor with the Church that uſeth it. Our Author ſaith, <hi>There have been Juſuits and Popiſh Intelligencers that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of our Service, and Pope</hi> Pius 5<hi>th would have ratified it?</hi> And is it therefore Popiſh? The Independent allows the Presbyterian Confeſſion of Faith; And this Author ſaith, p. 4. <hi>It muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that ſuch of the Church-of</hi>-England-<hi>men, as keep to the</hi> 39 <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles in matters of Doctrine, are as Orthodox as any Proteſtants in the world.</hi> And is therefore the Independent a Presbyterian, or this Author a Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-man? I trow not. All is, that they agree in the Common Principles the other receives, and yet one is no more the other, than if they had no agreement in ſuch Principles. And ſo is it here, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy has nothing but what is agreeable to the Doctrine of the Goſpel, and allowable by the Chriſtian Church; and therefore what the Papiſts will, or ought to allow; but for all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that, we are no more Papiſts, nor that any more Popiſh, than the Independent is a Presbyterian, or our Author a Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-man. It was not then, becauſe it was Popiſh, that they approved of our Service, but that it was Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and pure in its Order and Compoſure; neither was it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62493:5"/>
it was Popiſh, that the Pope would have ratified it, but becauſe upon any terms he would have prevailed upon Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to own his Authority, and regain'd her to their Church.</p>
               <p n="4">4. However I deny not, but that the Compilers of the Liturgy did peruſe the Popiſh Offices, and take as much from thence, as was conformable to the Ancient Offices, and was fit to be uſed; and that the rather, that they might the more eaſily ſatisfie doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or diſcontented Minds under the Alterations then made, and induce them to comply with them. And this was the meaning of King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Proclamation. A practice very Chriſtian and commendable, and agreeable to the Apoſtolical prudence, which we read of, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 16. 3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 19, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And which the Nation ſoon felt the happy effects of, when by this excellent Conduct it became, generally ſpeaking, Reformed. But yet after all, ſo little was taken out of the Maſs-Book, &amp;c. that they differ'd more than they agreed in, and more was left than taken out.</p>
               <p>But our Author ſtays not here, <hi>That the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Liturgy,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is originally Heatheniſh as well as Popiſh, is manifeſt,</hi> 1. <hi>In that the Pope's Liturgy from whence ours is deriv'd, is ſo. The Principal Parts of the Maſs-Book were borrowed from Idolatrous Pagans. They came from</hi> Numa Pompilius, <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>Anſ.</hi> It has been ſufficiently made out by Proteſtants, that there is a great Affinity and Agreement between the Heatheniſh and Popiſh Rites; but our Author does an injury to the Argument, when affirming, that the <hi>Principal Parts</hi> of the Maſs-Book, were borrowed from Idolatrous Pagans, he goes no further than <hi>Veſtments, Holy Water,</hi> and <hi>Incenſe,</hi> as if theſe were the <hi>principal Parts</hi> of the Maſs-Book, and the chief things that that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed in with the Idolatry of the Heathens.</p>
               <p>But this indeed is not to our purpoſe. Well! ſuppoſe there be this Conformity between the Papiſt and the Pagan; what is that to us, if we agree with neither? but that he attempts to prove.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For tho he cannot find</hi> Incenſe <hi>and</hi> Holy Water, <hi>and his</hi> Et caetera <hi>among us, yet he ſaith,</hi> What Vain Repetitions does the Common-Prayer Book abound with? In one Service the Worſhippers muſt repeat theſe words. <hi>Good Lord deliver us,</hi> Eight times over. And, <hi>We beſeech thee to hear us,</hi> Twenty times over. The <hi>Gloria Patri</hi> is to be repeated Ten times in the ſame Morning or Evening Service. That the Heathens were wont to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip their Idols juſt after the ſame manner, is clear from <hi>Matth. 7.</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Beza</hi> notes, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Liturgy does abound with them, wherein Men are taught to cry <hi>Jeſu, Jeſu, miſerere mei,</hi> no leſs then Ten times one after another.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62493:6"/>
For the better Reſolution of which, I ſhall proceed in this order.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We grant, that there may be ſuch things as vain Repetitions in Prayers, and other Divine Offices, for that is a fault our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our charges on the Heathens; and what we, as well as our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, charge on the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and is alſo frequently charged by thoſe that uſe and plead for Forms, on thoſe that uſe extempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Prayers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We yet do maintain, That there are ſuch Repetitions in Divine Worſhip, as are not vain, that are neither Heatheniſh or Popiſh. Such do we read of in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> as, <hi>Pſalm,</hi> 57. 1. 75. 1, 4, 5. 94. 1. 103. 1, 2, 22. 107. 8, 15, 21, 31. 136. <hi>throughout.</hi> And thus our Saviour repeated the ſame words thrice in his Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the Garden, <hi>Matt.</hi> 26. 44. and twice on the Croſs, <hi>Matt.</hi> 27. 46. And conſequently all Repetitions are no more condemned by our Saviour in <hi>Matt.</hi> 6. 7. than all long Prayers are, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23. 14. So that the vanity of Repetitions does not conſiſt in uſing the ſame words eight times or twenty times in Prayer. For do we repeat in our Service, <hi>Good Lord deliver us,</hi> eight times: And <hi>Glory be to the Father,</hi> &amp;c. ten times? And, <hi>We beſeech thee to hear us, good Lord,</hi> twenty times? So we find, that they not only had their thrice, and their four times, but their twenty ſeven times in every Verſe of <hi>Pſalm</hi> 136. <hi>His mercy endureth for ever;</hi> which <hi>Pſalm</hi> was moſt uſed on ſolemn Occaſions, as we may find it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 5. 13. 7. 3, 6. 20. 21. <hi>Ezra</hi> 3. 11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 33. 11. So that we may more truly ſay of the Church of God amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> than he doth of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> and their Idols, that <hi>they were wont to Worſhip</hi> God <hi>juſt after the ſame manner,</hi> with Repetitions in their Service, as we.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We are to conſider wherein the vanity of Repetitions conſiſts, ſo as to be after the manner of the Heathens. This admits great variety, and juſt bounds cannot be ſet; ſo that it's not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly ſaid, Here the vain Repetitions begin. But they are ſuch;</p>
               <p n="1">1. When they that uſe them, think that they ſhall be <hi>heard for their much ſpeaking,</hi> as our Saviour ſaith, the Hethens did: Thus the Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> did, crying out, <hi>O Baal hear us,</hi> from Morning till Noon; and accordingly <hi>Elijah</hi> upbraids them, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. 26, 27.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When it is nothing but Tautology, <hi>viz.</hi> a Repetition of the ſame words without new Matter; or of the ſame matter, but in different words. Such were the Verſes of <hi>Battus</hi> the babling Poet. Such were the Hymns uſed often by the Heathens, in the worſhip of their Gods. Such are the <hi>Jeſu, Jeſu,</hi> &amp;c. without Intermiſſion, ſometimes uſed in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62493:6"/>
But when there are diſtinct Petitions, as when we ſay, <hi>We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to hear us good Lord,</hi> it's as lawful to cloſe each after that manner, as it is to ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> which we find to follow every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Petition, and was diſtinctly repeated for twelve times toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after that manner, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. 15.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Vain Repetitions, are when the words are thought ſufficient, tho the Heart be not with them; but this may be common to any. So that tho there are Repetitions in our Service, as there were among the Heathen, and are in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet ours are not vain, nor ſuch Repetitions as theirs, by reaſon of the matter only, if accompanied with the heart.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He ſaith, <hi>Some of the moſt Learned Patrons of Liturgies produce it as an Argument for them, that the Heathens made uſe of Forms in their Idolatrous Worſhip,</hi> p. 5. And ſo he makes this the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Heathens and Chriſtians, that the firſt uſed Forms, but the laſt prayed without them. As for the practice of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, we ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak of it under another Head; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall I trouble my ſelf with the Opinion of thoſe <hi>Learned Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of Liturgies,</hi> he ſpeaks of: But I ſhall take his Argument as it lies before us, which is, That our Liturgy is Heatheniſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we uſe Forms as they did. He might as well have ſaid, our Liturgy is Heatheniſh, becauſe we uſe words as they did; ſince it's no more Heatheniſh to uſe Forms than Words. If they had the uſe of Forms, it rather ſhews the ſenſe that Mankind generally have of this matter; and that there cannot be too great a care taken of our demeanour in Divine Worſhip, according to the Direction of the Wiſe man, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth, &amp;c. for God is in Heaven, &amp;c. therefore let thy words be few,</hi> and well conſidered. But if the Heathens had Forms, ſo had the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſo had Chriſtians, as I ſhall ſhew; and ſo Forms no more make our Worſhip Heatheniſh than Jewiſh. But of this afterwards. But ſuppoſing, that our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy was (as he would have it) taken out of the Maſs-Book; yet,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 2. Will the being taken out of the Maſs-Book, make that Worſhip, which is otherwiſe good and lawful, to become unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be uſed, or joyned with?</p>
               <p>This he affirms, and offers to prove after this manner,</p>
               <p>It's a known maxim <hi>(ſaith he) Omnis honor Idoli eſt Idolatria.</hi> He that ſhall put any reſpect upon an Idol, cannot be clear of the Sin of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; but the Maſs-Book is an Idol. And he that uſeth a Prayer, or joyns with a Prayer taken out of that Book, thereby puts an Honour upon an Idol—How then can we joyn in Prayers taken out of the Idolatrous Maſs-Book, and offer them to the Holy God?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:62493:7"/>
In which there are Three things contained.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Maſs-Book is an Idol.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That to take a Prayer out of the Maſs-Book is a reſpect to an Idol, and is Idolatry.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That it's unlawful to joyn in Prayers taken out of the Maſs-Book.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Maſs-Book is an Idol.</hi> This we may juſtly queſtion, becauſe an Idol is the Repreſentation of ſome Divine or Beatified Object, and that is as ſuch propounded and ſet up for Adoration; ſuch are the Images of God and our Saviour, of Angels and Saints in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But in this ſenſe the Maſs-Book is no Idol; there is no Prototype or Object it repreſents, nor is any ſuch Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration paid to it, as is paid to an Image, or a Crucifix. We grant as well as he, that the Maſs-Book is <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> as it contains ſome things that are ſo, and is uſed in Idolatrous Worſhip: But it no more follows from thence, that it is an Idol, than that the Incenſe, Holy Water, or Veſtments, are Idols, which are uſed when they ſay Maſs. But ſuppoſing the Maſs-Book for once to be an Idol, that we may proceed to the next queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether the taking a Prayer out of the Maſs-Book, be ſuch a reſpect to it, as makes the Prayer to be Idolatrous? To this I anſwer, That the Prayers taken out of the Maſs-Book, and inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our Liturgy, are ſo far from being a reſpect, that it is a diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to it. For at the ſame time that ſome Prayers were taken out, thoſe were rejected that were left behind, for the groſs Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions that were in them; and by ſo doing, the Reformers as much teſtified to all the World their abhorrence of it, as the emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying of the Houſe of the Goods and Utenſils not infected by the Leproſy, and their forſaking it, was a plain declaration of its Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. So that if Prayers taken from thence are good, the uſing them when taken thence, is no Idolatry, and Communion in them no Sin, and no more unlawful than it was to uſe the Veſſels that were carried out of the infected Houſe.</p>
               <p>But this is the main Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <lb/>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whether that which has been uſed in Idolatrous Worſhip, may, if otherwiſe good and lawful, be uſed where the Worſhip is not idolatrous?</p>
               <p>This he denies, and for it offers theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1</hi> We ought not to name an Idol, but with deteſtation; much leſs may we offer it as Worſhip to God. <hi>Pſal. 16. 4. Exod. 23. 13.</hi> Hoſ. <hi>2. 16, 17. P. 4.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62493:7"/>
                  <hi>2.</hi> It was <hi>Paul's</hi> Judgment, that Meat once offer'd to Idols, ſhould not be made uſe of, <hi>1 Cor. 10. 28.</hi> Therefore a Service-Book offer'd to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols ought not to uſed. For there is a parity of Reaſon.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> God hath ſtrictly prohibited his people all ſymbolizing with the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then in civil uſages, becauſe he would not have them imitate the Heathen <hi>Levit. 19. 19, 27.</hi>—eſpecially in matters referring to the Worſhip of God. Hence they were prohibited going up by ſteps to the Altar. <hi>Exod. 20. 24, 26.</hi> to plant a Grove near the Altar, <hi>Deut. 16. 31.</hi> And to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to the Eaſt, <hi>Ezek. 8. 16.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before I proceed to conſider theſe Arguments in particular, I ſhall ſtate the Caſe it ſelf; for reſolving of which, we may obſerve.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there are things Idolatrous in their own nature, or by a ſtanding poſitive Law, and ſo are always the ſame. Such is the Picture of God, and Worſhipping by Images.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There are things that have been cuſtomarily appropriated to Idolatrous Worſhip, and the uſe of which in common eſtimation, has been accounted Idolatrous. Such was the offering Incenſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Heathens;</hi> and therefore the primitive Chriſtians refuſed it, as an acknowledgment of their Worſhip; and the <hi>Thurificati</hi> were reputed Idolaters.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There are other things that are uſed as well in true as Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Worſhip, and are lawful in themſelves; ſuch as Time, Place, Habit, Poſture.</p>
               <p>The firſt is always, unlawful, and makes the worſhip Idolatrous.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is not to be uſed where it has been thus appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and thus accounted, during ſuch an opinion of them.</p>
               <p>So that it's the laſt of theſe that the whole turns upon; for after all the clamour he makes about Idolatry, and the charge he would fain faſten upon us, he can produce nothing that is Idolatrous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, no Images, no Prayers to Saints, nor ſo much as any thing appropriated, or in common eſtimation ſo accounted; no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſings of Books or Images, no ſprinklings of Holy Water; but it all amounts to this, that <hi>Forms</hi> and <hi>Repetitions</hi> have been us'd by Idolaters; that they had <hi>White Garments,</hi> and obſerv'd <hi>Holy-days;</hi> So <hi>p.</hi> 4, 5, 8. Which are things lawful in themſelves (as I ſhall ſhew) and cannot be made unlawful by being us'd in Idolatrous Worſhip. For when Idolatry is not in the nature of the thing, but in the uſe, take away the uſe, and Idolatry ceaſeth; and conſequently it may be lawfully uſed where there is no Idolatry in the Worſhip, and no Idolatry in the uſe of it. And if it be not to be uſed, it's not becauſe it's unlawful in it ſelf to uſe it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62493:8"/>
it's forbidden by God, as was the caſe among the <hi>Jews;</hi> or becauſe of ſome circumſtances that make it inconvenient and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. Thus it was lawful to eat that Meat, which had been offer'd to Idols, when it was afterward expos'd to ſale in the Shambles, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 25, 26.</note>or ſet upon the Table at an Entertainment; becauſe it was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by reſtor'd to a common uſe; when yet it was not lawful to ſit at Meat in an Idols Temple, for that was to have fellowſhip in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. 10, 20. It is then no more Idolatry to uſe a White Garment, or a Temple, or obſerve a Day, or to uſe a Prayer that has been uſed or obſerv'd in Idolatrous Worſhip, or by an Idolatrous Church, than it was to eat Meat that had been offer'd to Idols. Purifie the Gold, and ſeparate the Droſs from it, and the Gold is not the worſe for the Droſs that was before mingled with it. Scrape the Walls, and caſt out the infected ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials of it, ſo that the Houſe be freed from the Leproſie, and it might have been as well inhabited, as if it had never been infected, <hi>Num.</hi> 14. 41. (to make uſe of former Compariſons, <hi>p.</hi> 2<hi>d.</hi> and 3<hi>d.)</hi> and take the things lawful from the things unlawful, and they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come lawful again, and may be lawfully uſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſaith he,</hi> The Rubbiſh of the Leprous houſe was to be caſt into an unclean place: And the Leproſie breaks out ſtill; therefore we may have no communion with it. <hi>p. 3.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſurely it's the ſame thing if we leave the Houſe that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, as it is to carry away the Rubbiſh into an unclean place; elſe why doth he talk of leaving the Communion for the ſake of the Leproſie of Idolatry? We grant the Church we left to be Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous, there the Leproſie is; and therefore we left it; but we left the Idolatry with the Church, and let him prove there is any of the Leproſie of Idolatry in what we have taken out of it, and then he would ſay ſomewhat to the purpoſe; but that he is far from.</p>
               <p>Let us however conſider his Arguments relating to the general part. 1. We ought, ſaith he, not to name an Idol, but with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, much leſs offer it as worſhip to God.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, 1<hi>ſt.</hi> The <hi>naming</hi> there forbidden, is the naming an Idol with reſpect; and indeed the addreſſing any Worſhip to it. So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 4. <hi>Their ſorrows ſhall be multiplied that haſten after another God; their drink-offering of Blood will I not offer, nor take up their name into my Lips:</hi> That is, they might not name them by way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, nor offer Sacrifice to them.</p>
               <p>2<hi>d.</hi> Where is there ſuch a naming of an Idol amongſt us? what reſpect do we give to his Idol the <hi>Maſs-Book?</hi> what Saint do we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62493:8"/>
adore? <hi>But,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>The Prayers are taken out of the Idolatrous</hi> Maſs-Book. But what then, if there be nothing of their Idolatry in the Prayers that are taken thence; when ſuch are taken thence they are no more Idolatrous than before they were taken into the <hi>Maſs-Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2</hi>d. <hi>He ſaith,</hi> It was <hi>Paul</hi>'s<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Judgment, that meat once offer'd to Idols ſhould not be made uſe of, <hi>1 Cor. 10. 28.</hi> Therefore a Service-Book of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to Idols ought not be us'd. For there is a parity of Reaſon.</p>
               <p>I conceive he is much miſtaken in the account he gives of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle's <hi>Judgment,</hi> who is ſo far from maintaining <hi>meat offer'd to Idols to be unlawful,</hi> that he makes it a thing indifferent (as before); and what a perſon may with a ſafe conſcience eat of without ſcruple, unleſs it be with reſpect to another's conſcience that is thereby of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, as the Apoſtle determines it, <hi>v.</hi> 28, 29. Now if Meat of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to Idols might be eaten of, then a Service-Book that has been uſed in Idolatrous Worſhip may be lawfully us'd (when the things contain'd in it are otherwiſe lawful and good.) <hi>For there is a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Reaſon,</hi> as he argues.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3. He ſaith,</hi> God hath prohibited his People all Symbolizing with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>We grant that God did prohibit the <hi>Jews</hi> all ſymbolizing and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with the <hi>Heathens</hi> in their Idolatry. That is not the Queſtion. But,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether an agreement with Idolaters in what was once uſed by them in Idolatry, becomes Idolatry, or be unlawful becauſe it has been ſo uſed?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or whether what was forbidden to the <hi>Jews</hi> is forbidden to all People, And to Chriſtians as well as they?</p>
               <p>Theſe we deny.</p>
               <p>The firſt we deny as to the <hi>Jews,</hi> that every thing us'd in Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Service was unlawful to them; for he ſays, <hi>The Prieſts of</hi> Iſis <hi>uſed to wear Linnen Surplices,</hi> p. 9. and yet ſuch Linnen Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were the Prieſts and <hi>Levites</hi> to officiate in. So Circumciſion was uſed among the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> &amp;c. and yet continued to be uſed among the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, we deny that what was in that kind forbidden to the <hi>Jews,</hi> was forbidden and unlawful to all. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1<hi>ſt.</hi> A great part of what they were forbidden, was with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the people that before inhabited the Land; with whom they were to make no Covenant, but were utterly to deſtroy them, their Altars and Groves, &amp;c. Exod. 23. 32, 33. 34. 12. Deut. 7. 2, 3, 5.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62493:9"/>
2. They were a People very prone to Idolatry, and ſo were tied up by ſtrict Reſtraints and Penalties.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They both came from <hi>Egypt,</hi> where they had long convers'd with Idolatrous Service, and afterward border'd upon Nations violently addicted to Idolatry and Sorcery; and in ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances there were theſe Checks laid upon them; and an aſſimilati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Cuſtoms of ſuch forbidden.</p>
               <p>And all this was not from the nature of the thing, and becauſe all uſages of Idolators were unlawful, but becauſe of the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of people, time, and place: And if ſo, then we muſt leave the caſe of ſymbolizing, and no longer make it a Caſe of Conſcience, but of prudence and expediency; and ſo we are left to judge what is fit to be retained, and what not; what practiſed, and what not.</p>
               <p>And here our Reformers ſhew'd their Prudence and Moderation, by what they choſe; when the Ceremonies were few; and what were the Ceremonies of the Ancient Church, rather than the <hi>Romiſh.</hi> When they choſe ſome, that they might not give offence to the Churches of Chriſt in other parts of the World; and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd no more, that they might not burden their own Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. When the Offices they ſelected were agreeable to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienteſt Offices of the Church.</p>
               <p>So that there was no Reformation in any place, where ſo much temper was preſerv'd, and where the purity of Religion, and the Simplicity and ſolemnity of Divine Service were more regarded: that what was good was retained; what was noxious was purg'd out, and even what was ſuperfluous was exſcinded.</p>
               <p>But this he will not allow.</p>
               <p>For, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> the uſe of ſuch a Liturgy doth harden the Papiſts in their Idolatry, <hi>p. 4. So</hi> the Liturgy came from <hi>Rome,</hi> and will perhaps lead thither again. <hi>p. 18.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, 1. How can ſuch a Liturgy <hi>harden</hi> them in their Idolatry, or <hi>lead</hi> thither, which has none of their Idolatry in it; and in which the Papiſts are expreſly charged with Idolatry? <hi>Vid.</hi> Rubrick at the Communion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How can this harden them, or lead thither, which has been the means of baniſhing and keeping their Idolatry out of the Kingdom?</p>
               <p n="3">3. How can this <hi>harden</hi> them, or <hi>lead</hi> thither, when the Papiſts agree with our Author, <hi>That it's unlawful to be preſent at, or partake in the Common-Prayer Worſhip,</hi> and are excommunicated if they do?</p>
               <p n="4">4. How can this harden them, or lead thither, when there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that the Papiſts more labour to poſſeſs the people with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices againſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62493:9"/>
                  <hi>But he adds,</hi> p. <hi>4.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves are ſcandalized by the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy. It's a celebrated Saying among them, That the Chriſtians have their <hi>Jephilleth</hi> from <hi>Armillus;</hi> that is, their Prayer-Books from <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At what are the <hi>Jews</hi> ſcandalized? is it that we have a Liturgy? So have they themſelves had of latter Ages at leaſt. And ſo the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 13. That he had <hi>ſeen Liturgies written in the</hi> Hebrew <hi>Tongue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it that we receive our <hi>Prayer-Book</hi> from <hi>Antichriſt?</hi> Yes, ſaith he, and for this quotes a <hi>Celebrated ſaying</hi> of theirs. But is this the truer for their ſaying ſo? they ſay, it ſeems, that <hi>Chriſtians have receiv'd their</hi> Prayers <hi>from</hi> Antichriſt: but I hope that there are many Chriſtians in the World, that have Prayer-Books which they never received from the <hi>Antichriſt</hi> he ſpeaks of; So the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Abyſſins,</hi> &amp;c. The whole is at leaſt a ſorry Miſtake, and which, for ought I ſee, he underſtands no more than we do his <hi>Jephilleth.</hi> The caſe is plainly thus; That the Rabbins ſay, that <hi>Armillus</hi> was to be a perſon of prodigious form, begot of a Marble Statue in <hi>Rome,</hi> and was to be the laſt Enemy of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Leader of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Forces againſt them; that he ſhould kill Meſſias <hi>Ben Ephraim,</hi> and at laſt be killed by Meſſias <hi>Ben David.</hi> That he ſhould give <hi>Tephilleth</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and a Law to the Chriſtians, which he and they ſet up in oppoſition to the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> So that we ſee that his <hi>Tephilleth</hi> is the Law as well as the Prayers of Chriſtians; and they make <hi>Armillus</hi> to be toward the end of the World, the laſt Enemy of the <hi>Jews;</hi> and how could our Liturgy, or the Liturgies now uſed by Chriſtians, be the Prayers received from <hi>Armillus,</hi> when <hi>Armillus</hi> is yet to come, according to the Rabinical Notion? if the Reader pleaſes he may have a fuller account of this <hi>Jewiſh Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragantua</hi> in <hi>Buxtorf</hi>'s <hi>Lexicon, Chald. Talmud. Rabbin;</hi> for I am wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this trifling, and unintelligible Jargon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the <hi>Matter</hi> of the <hi>Common Prayer</hi>-Book.</head>
               <p>BEfore I proceed to the particular conſideration of his Objections Relating to this Head; let me obſerve, that if we ſhould grant what he finds fault with to be blame-worthy; yet it's not to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and the point he propoſed; which is to give <hi>Reaſons why he</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62493:10"/>
                  <hi>judges it unlawful to be preſent at, or partake in the</hi> Common-Prayer <hi>Worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that for theſe Reaſons. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. There may be many things that are a reaſon againſt Miniſterial Conformity, which will not be a reaſon againſt communion with the Church; ſince there are thoſe things required to the one, that are not required to the other. Such is the Surplice, the Office for Burying the Dead, Marrying, <hi>p.</hi> 8. &amp;c. which belong to the Miniſter, and not to the People: And therefore tho it ſhould be unlawful to wear a Surplice, or uſe theſe Offices, yet ſince Lay-Communion is not concern'd in them, they are no reaſon for ſeparation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Many of his Objections are only directed againſt the occaſional Offices, and ſo can be no reaſon againſt conſtant communion in the Daily office, or in thoſe Offices in which they do not occur. As ſuppoſing what he alledgeth out of the Office of Burial, Marriage, Baptiſm, &amp;c. to be true and ſufficient, yet tho they may be a reaſon againſt being preſent at the Offices of Burial, Baptiſm, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, they are no reaſon againſt Communion, where thoſe Offices are not concerned.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Things inconvenient, if not unlawful, are no reaſon for a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, becauſe then there could be no Communion with any Church, ſince no Church is without them: And if we ſhould grant the reading a worſe Tranſlation of Scripture, and the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> in the Church, to be things of that nature; yet it will be hard to ſhew them to be unlawful in themſelves, and ſo to make it neceſſary to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from the Church where they are uſed.</p>
               <p>If theſe things be conſider'd, moſt of what he has ſaid will be prevented; but that I may not ſeem to avoid any thing, I ſhall take notice of the Particulars as they lie in order. And his Arguments taken from the Matter of the Service-Book, are</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>(1.)</hi> Some things appointed therein are, in the judgment of ſober and judicious perſons, extremely ridiculous. <hi>As how?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>How many odd and ſenſeleſs Tranſlations of the Holy Scripture have been found therein?</hi> It's well, he ſaid <hi>have been found;</hi> for he is fain to draw all his inferences of that kind, but one, from the <hi>Service-Book,</hi> as it ſtood before the laſt reviſal, and that is <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58. 9. <hi>Or ever their pots be made hot with thorns, ſo let indignation vex them, as a thing that is raw.</hi> At which he Triumphs, <hi>What nonſence is this!</hi> Now I do not think that to be Nonſence which is not ſoon under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; for then what will he make of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> in this Verſe, which has ſeveral difficulties in it? But I think there is a good account to be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62493:10"/>
given of the ſenſe of this Verſion; and that is, E're that the Pots are made hot with the Thorns, they ſhall be ſeverely puniſhed: The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made hot with the Thorns, ſets forth the ſuddenneſs; and the phraſe, <hi>vexing a thing that is raw,</hi> denotes the ſeverity of it.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) His next Inſtance of <hi>things extremely ridiculous,</hi> is, that <hi>in the Liturgy, the Writings of the Prophets, Acts and Revelations, are called Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</hi> If theſe were formerly, they are not now ſo called; but of theſe when read in the place of Epiſtles, it's ſaid, <hi>The portion of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the Epiſtle.</hi> That is, the Sections of Scripture read in that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, are generally Epiſtles; and ſo, as it's uſual in other caſes, gives the name to all: And as it is not now, ſo never was it called the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of the Prophets, Acts, or Revelations; but the Epiſtle taken out of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) He objects againſt the Reſponſes, <hi>Thoſe broken Reſponds,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and ſhreds of Prayer (as</hi> Mr. Cartwright <hi>calls them) which the Prieſts and People toſs between them like Tennis-Balls, ſeem extremely ridiculous to ſtanders-by.</hi> Without doubt this is a venture of Wit; but I ſuppoſe there are <hi>ſtanders-by</hi> that will call it by another Name; and inſtead of Wit, term this ſcurrility in Converſation, and prophaneneſs in Religion; Eſpecially if we conſider how many Pſalms there are in Holy Writ, that are penn'd (or ſuppoſed at leaſt to be ſo, by Learned men) after this way. And whatever his <hi>Standers-by</hi> may think, there are Perſons of Piety ancient and modern, that have thought this way very becoming, and of excellent uſe to quicken Devotion, and excite attention. What may not be ſaid in any caſe by ſuch perſons as theſe, that call this way of Devotion (as he doth) <hi>a taking God's Name in vain?</hi> And what occaſion may others take after the ſame manner, to treat their long Prayers, that are often nauſeous to <hi>ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers-by,</hi> for their affected length, and tedious enlargements, and forc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Repetitions.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. He objects,</hi> The <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book is guilty of violating the ſacred Word of God: <hi>And here he charges it with no leſs than oblite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating, contradicting, adding to it, and detracting from it; and then concludes,</hi> Amongſt men, clipping and corrupting if Coin is Treaſon; and certainly it's a dreadful thing to add to, or take from the Word of God. <hi>Dent. 4. 2. Rev. 22. 19.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it's <hi>certainly a dreadful thing;</hi> and wo to them that are guilty.</p>
               <p>Here I ſhould have expected a rounder Charge by one that had ſo exactly read the Liturgy, and that he would have told the World that we take whole Chapters from the Word of God, and which have no place in our Kalendar, nor are read publickly in the Church,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62493:11"/>
as I do acknowledge. And ſurely if the omiſſion of one Verſe in a Pſalm, and of Hallelujah in others, be a <hi>taking from the Word of God;</hi> then much more is the omiſſion of whole Chapters; nay, of three whole Books. But he durſt not preſs that too far; for if he had, it would have fallen hard upon ſuch as never have the Scriptures read in their Congregations, tho that was a ſolemn part of Divine Worſhip in the Churches of God, as the Scripture informs us, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 21, &amp;c. And if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo deſervedly blamed for reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in an unknown tongue, what do they not deſerve that never read them at all in their Congregations? Surely if they had, according to our Saviour's advice, conſidered the Beam in their own eye, they would not have thus magnified the Mote in their Brother's eye. I remember a Queſtion in a Book of the ſame kind with our Author's, <note place="margin">A Survey of the Book of Common-Prayer; <hi>An. 1610.</hi> p. <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Whether</hi> Proteſtants <hi>do not ſin in defrauding the people of ſome Books and Chapters of Scripture, as well as</hi> Papiſts <hi>in defrauding them of all?</hi> And then what ſort of Proteſtants are they, that with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> defraud the people of all, ſo far as the Publick Service of God is concern'd?</p>
               <p>But to return: Before I ſhall conſider his few Inſtances, that he would make good this Bloody Charge by, I ſhall premiſe a few things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Inſtances he offers are, at the worſt, Miſtranſlations, Slips, and Errors, and not chargeable with Perverſeneſs, according to what we charge upon the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For here is no intereſt to be ſerved: For what is our Church concern'd, whether it be read as the Liturgical Tranſlation has it, <hi>the</hi> 7<hi>th Day;</hi> or as the Common Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <hi>The Sabbath?</hi> whether as that, <hi>they were not obedient to his word;</hi> or as this, <hi>they rebelled not againſt his word?</hi> whether as that, <hi>The rod of the wicked cometh not into the lot of the righteous;</hi> or as this, <hi>reſteth not?</hi> Whether, as in that, the Titles of ſome Pſalms and Hallelujahs are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; or as in this, they are inſerted? Surely here is no intereſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in this, that ſhould incline our Tranſlators of the Pſalter to pick out theſe Texts above all others to make bold with.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Miſtranſlations and Errors of this kind, are no ſufficient reaſon for not uſing ſuch a Tranſlation, and much leſs for ſeparating from a Church where they are uſed; for then no Tranſlation could be us'd, or no Church communicated with, becauſe no Church is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch Tranſlations, and no Tranſlation without ſuch Errors. Thus it was in the Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> when the Septuagint was uſed in publick; Which doth often alter and add to the original <hi>Hebrew;</hi> and yet was not only uſed, but is <hi>quoted</hi> by the <hi>Divine Writers,</hi> even in many places where thoſe Alterations and Additions are. So it alters, <hi>Heb</hi> 10. 5. 11. 21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 18. <hi>Act.</hi> 7. 8. It adds, as <hi>Luk.</hi> 3. 36, 37. <hi>Act.</hi> 7. 14</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62493:11"/>
Then alſo muſt not our common Tranſlation be uſed, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the miſtakes allowed to be in it, does add in many places, and particularly half a Verſe, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 23. So it adds the Dates and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions to the Epiſtles, Chapters, Verſes, and Arguments, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole, <hi>as if Canonical.</hi> And of this kind are all his Inſtances.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As (1.) He ſaith,</hi> The Common-Prayer-Book violates the word of God, as ſometimes the words of Scripture are obliterated, and others put in their room. Thus in the Catechiſm they have changed thoſe words in the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, the Lord bleſſed the ſabbath-day, into the Seventh day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We grant it is ſo; but it's to be remember'd, that it's not ſo in the 20th of <hi>Exodus,</hi> but in the Liturgy; and if the Liturgy differs from <hi>Exodus,</hi> it's a difference without a diſtinction, ſince the Seventh day and Sabbath are all one; and if it differs from <hi>Exodus,</hi> it agrees with the firſt Inſtitution, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 3. where it's ſaid, <hi>God reſted on the ſeventh day, and God bleſſed the ſeventh day, and ſanctified it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>(2.) He ſaith,</hi> Sometimes the Liturgy makes bold directly and in terms to contradict the Scripture; ſo <hi>Pſalm 105. 28.</hi> it's ſaid they were not rebellious, but the Common-Prayer-Book ſaith, they were not obedient; and ſo <hi>Pſal. 125. 3.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We grant, That there is a ſeeming contradiction in words, but not in the meaning of it; for the relative <hi>they</hi> being undetermined, and indifferently to be applied to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> or to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly is this place to be interpreted; if underſtood of the former, it's to be read in the common Tranſlation, <hi>they were not rebellious;</hi> if of the latter, it's to be read in the Tranſlation of the Liturgy, <hi>they were not obedient.</hi> And this laſt reading is according to the preſent reading of the Septuagint, and ſome other Tranſlations that follow that. And yet that Tranſlation was generally uſed by the Primitive Chriſtians, and was worſe than any ever uſed by us. As for Pſal. 125. 3. <hi>The rod of the wicked ſhall not come,</hi> &amp;c. that is, ſo as to reſt there, and ſo as to tempt them beyond what they are able.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>(3.) He ſaith,</hi> Sometimes the Common-Prayer-Book adds to the Scripture; there are three whole Verſes added to the <hi>14</hi>th Pſalm. And the <hi>Gloria Patri</hi> is frequently added to Scripture, as if it were Canonical.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> When he ſaith, That <hi>it is a dreadful thing to add to the word of God,</hi> and charges our Church with it, we might expect ſome very criminal inſtances to make it good; and when he ſaith three whole Verſes are added, one would think that this was ſomewhat invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and herein inſerted by the Church upon ſome wicked ſelfiſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. But, 1. tho we allow that ſuch Verſes are added, yet it's not an addition to Scripture; for tho not found in this place, yet they are in another, <hi>viz. Rom.</hi> 3. 13. and quoted by the Apoſtle from other
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62493:12"/>
Pſalms, &amp;c. 2. It's not the common-Prayer-Book that adds, but the Tranſlations which the common-Prayer followed, <hi>viz.</hi> the Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint and Vulgar; and tho it was a miſtake, yet it's far from being ſuch as incurs the penalty of <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 2, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> I deny that it's added to the Scriptures <hi>as Canonical,</hi> any more than the Contents of the Chapters, the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Verſes of the Bible, or the Dates of the Epiſtles are; nay, I deny that it's added at all; for any one that can read, will ſee that it's not inſerted in the Pſalter, but only rehearſed as the Rubrick directs. And it was for a good end that this was anciently uſed in the Orthodox Churches of old, and is continued in ours, <hi>viz.</hi> in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the <hi>Arians,</hi> and <hi>Anti-Trinitarians. Sozom. l.</hi> 26.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>(4). He ſaith,</hi> Sometimes words are ſacrilegiouſly ſtolen out of the Bible. As the laſt Verſe is omitted, <hi>Pſal. 72.</hi> So are the Scriptural Titles of many Pſalms. And I know not how often thoſe words, <hi>Praiſe ye the Lord,</hi> are left out.</p>
               <p>He durſt not truſt his Reader with the things left out, for they would have appear'd of ſo little Conſequence, as would have betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the weakneſs of his Cauſe, as well as his own partiality: That verſe omitted, Pſal. 72. is this, <hi>the Prayers of David, the Son of Jeſſe, are end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> The Titles of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> are for the moſt part ſuch as are no key to the matter of them, and without which the Pſalms are as intire as the Chapters without the Contents: The Clauſe, <hi>praiſe ye the Lord,</hi> as in the <hi>Hebrew, Hallelujah,</hi> and is only left out when it's independent, and has no immediate Relation to the preceding or following Verſe. And the reaſon of theſe Omiſſions ſeems to be, Becauſe the Pſalms being to be read in Parts, according to the ancient Cuſtom in <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi>'s time and before, or chanted, and ſo read on without na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Pſalm, the Titles, &amp;c. would have made a break in that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And this was done after the manner of Singing the Pſalms in the Temple-Service, in which the Titles, and the paſſage, <hi>the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of David the Son of Jeſſe, are ended,</hi> were to be ſure no part. And ſo it is in the Singing-Pſalms, uſed by the Diſſenters as well as us: And who may as well be charged with ſuch Omiſſions as we, who there, for the reaſon aboveſaid, uſe neither the Verſe nor Titles. Surely theſe Perſons are hard put to it, that after ſuch a bloody charge of violating, adding to, and taking from the Word of God, can produce no better proofs and evidences for it, but only that we leave out the Titles and Hallelujah, and that only in the ordinary Service in the publick, where they themſelves read it not at all; and when upon the like way of arguing, we may charge them with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62493:12"/>
laying aſide the whole Scripture, out of which they read not one Chapter for the information of the People. He goes on,</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>In the Liturgy the Apocrypha Books are made equal with, nay advanced above the Holy Scripture.</hi> Strange! that a Church ſhould be guilty of this, that in their Articles exclude them out of the Canon; and ſaith, That they are not read to confirm any Doctrine, but only for informing the Manners. But let us ſee how he proves this, not by any Aſſertion of the Church, but ſome ſtretches of Arguing. As,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>(1.) They are made equal. For</hi> in the Preface to the Common-Prayer, it's ſaid, nothing ordained is to be read but the pure word of God, or that which is evidently grounded on the ſame. But is the Apocrypha ſo?</p>
               <p>Here for improving his Argument, he alters the words of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face; and for that which is in that, <hi>agreeable to the ſame,</hi> he reads <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently grounded on the ſame,</hi> and then triumphs, <hi>Is the Apocrypha ſo?</hi> But take it how he will, its evident from hence, that the Apocrypha is ſo far from being made equal with Scripture, that there is a plain difference between them; for that to which a thing is agreeable, and on which it's grounded, is above that which is agreeable to it, and grounded upon it. A Plea grounded on the law, is ſurely of leſs Authority than the Law on which it is grounded. The Apocrypha being read, not for eſtabliſhing any Doctrine, but for informing the Mannners; there is nothing in what is appointed of that kind to be read, but what is agreeable to the word of God, and not contrary to it; and ſo may be read, as well as their Sermons be heard, which can pretend to no more.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>(2.) He ſaith,</hi> The Liturgy appoints the Apocrypha to be read as Leſſons, juſt as I find it in the Pope's Service-Book, and in a greater proportion than Scripture; for (as ſome have obſerv'd) of <hi>172</hi> Apocryphal Chapters, but <hi>38</hi> are omitted. So that theſe Books are equalized with the pure word of God.</p>
               <p>But ſurely he doth not find it in our Service-Book, that the Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha Leſſons are read for Canonical Scripture, and declared to be ſo, as they are in the <hi>Pope's Service-Book;</hi> but only as Apocrypha. He that will look for the Apocrypha-Books in the Pope's Bible, as well as Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-Book, will find them mixed with the Canonical, as <hi>Heſter</hi> and <hi>Eſdras,</hi> &amp;c. but he that will find them in our Bibles, will find them by themſelves, and <hi>Apocrypha</hi> in the head of them.</p>
               <p>If, as he affirms, the Apocrypha is read in a <hi>greater proportion</hi> than Scripture, it doth more than equalize, and doth rather advance it above the Scripture, and ſo belongs to his next Aſſertion, which he would have done well to have reſerv'd it to, to make up the proof he is there wanting in.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62493:13"/>
As for what he affirms, that the Apocrypha is read in greater proportion than the Scripture; nothing more falſe. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. All the Second Leſſons throughout the Year, are out of the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. All Epiſtles and Goſpels read on Sundays and Holy-days, are wholly out of Canonical Scripture.</p>
               <p n="3">3. All Firſt Leſſons, on <hi>Sundays</hi> are out of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> and none out of the Apocrypha.</p>
               <p n="4">4. On the 33 Holy-days, on the Week-days, there are but 26 Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha Firſt Leſſons, whereas there are 40 out of the Canonical Scripture.</p>
               <p n="5">5. When the Apocrypha is appointed to be read in Courſe, it's not clear two Months for Firſt Leſſons, but the Holy Scripture is read all the other Ten Months, and more.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Of the 39 Books of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> but 3 are entirely omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>viz. Chronicles,</hi> and <hi>Canticles;</hi> but of the 13 of the Apocrypha, 6 are not read at all.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Of the 929 Chapters of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> 753 are read in courſe, and 176 only omitted (the reaſons for which generally will appear to the Reader), but out of the 172 Chapters of the Apocrypha, there are (not as he ſaith 38) 66 omitted, and among them that of <hi>Tobit,</hi> that he objects againſt. Where methinks he that pretends to have read and compar'd, ſhou'd have had more value for his own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, than to be beholding to others, and to ſay <hi>ſome have obſerved;</hi> for there is nothing like a man's own obſervation in matter of Fact.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3. He ſaith,</hi> The Liturgy advanceth the Apocrypha above the Scripture, by intimating that they are more edifying, and can be leſs ſpared than many portions of the Holy Canon; and by ordering them to be read on the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Holy-days, and many of them twice, ſome thrice in one year.</p>
               <p>Methinks in ſuch a round Charge as this, that <hi>the Liturgy advanceth the Apocrypha above Scripture,</hi> he ſhould have had more than an <hi>inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> for his evidence. He calls it before, High-Treaſon; and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it's very hard to be condemned for it by a bare <hi>Innuendo;</hi> and yet even he fails in his <hi>intimation.</hi> For, 1. if it were true, that the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy order'd the Apocrypha to be read on the <hi>higheſt Holy-days,</hi> and many of them <hi>twice or thrice in the Year;</hi> it would not follow, that they accounted them <hi>more edifying, and leſs to be ſpared</hi> than Scripture; eſpecially when Scripture is read on the higheſt Holy-days, and ſome portions of it twice or thrice in the year too.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It's not true, that it's <hi>ordered to he read on the higheſt Holy-days:</hi> For on the higheſt Holy-days, there is nothing but Scripture to be read; ſuch are all the days dedicated to our Saviour, as the Nativity,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62493:13"/>
Circumciſion, Epiphany, Good-Friday, Reſurrection, Aſcenſion; and all the Lords-days.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He ſaith, <hi>Many of them are read twice, ſome thrice in the year.</hi> For the twice, it's only 25 Chapters, <hi>viz.</hi> 7 in <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and 18 in <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticus:</hi> And as for his thrice, there is none but the 5th. Chapter of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> which after it had been read on <hi>the Converſion of St.</hi> Paul, has 17 Verſes of it read on All-Saints. But now, as to the Scripture, the whole <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> except the <hi>Revelation,</hi> is read over thrice in the year in courſe, beſides Epiſtles, Goſpels, and Leſſons out of it on Holy-days. And the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> is read over once, except as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore excepted, in courſe. And many Portions are read again in the Service of <hi>Sundays</hi> and Holy-days, which amount to above 140 Leſſons; and ſome few have a third Courſe.</p>
               <p>Would any one that obſerves this, think ſuch a Writer, a Perſon of any care, I had almoſt ſaid Conſcience; that utters as black Slanders as Pen can Write, or Mouth can utter, and charges a whole Church with violating the Word of God, and adding to it, and detracting from it, and of advancing human Writings above it, and yet ſhall come off with changing a Seventh day for Sabbath, with leaving out Hallelujah, with Intimations, and Falſities, with others Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, that pretends to have read and compared, and what not; and after all, charges us with this, for Leſſons appointed to be read in the Publick Congregation, when they themſelves read none at all; and have no other Tranſlation of Scripture, than what was tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by us, and which they uſe in Common with us? This is hard uſage indeed; and if we ſhould retort upon them in the like way, we ſhould think, if we may judge of their value for Scripture by their Publick Service, there are none have a leſs eſteem for it than they, that read not one Chapter of it by way of Leſſon throughout the year, as has been before ſaid.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4. He ſaith,</hi> Such things are enjoyned in the Common-Prayer-Book, as (to my Conſcience) cannot be practiſed without Sin.</p>
               <p>But what is this to thoſe that are not obliged to practiſe them? What is it to Laymen, that the Prieſts are required to give the Holy Communion to all new-married Perſons; or to uſe the Prayers over the Dead; or to put the Ring on in Marriage; or uſe the Surplice, &amp;c?</p>
               <p>But what is this which cannot be practiſed without Sin?</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Miniſters are requir'd to give the Holy Communion to all new-married Perſons, whereas Marriage-Feſtivals uſed to be accompanied with ſuch Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements as unfit them. By this Doctrine, all that may Marry, may come to the Lord's Supper, whereas Marriage is An Ordinance which Men as Men
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62493:14"/>
(and not as Chriſtians only) have a right unto. So that by this Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion many will eat and drink Damnation to themſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> (1.) If this was required, yet it's not inconſiſtent with that ſtate, which is rightly call'd, <hi>The Holy Eſtate of Matrimony;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, thoſe Divertiſements do not precede but follow.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Surely thoſe Perſons that are married amongſt us, are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be Chriſtians, and not to be married meerly as Men.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) If any eat and drink their own Damnation, it's their own fault; and the danger of it doth not releaſe any of their Duty, or juſtify their neglect of it.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) But the Common-Prayer-Book doth not compel them; it ſaith only, That <hi>it's convenient at their Marriage, or at the firſt opportunity after it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> When any man is buried, the Prieſt muſt ſay, Almighty God has taken to himſelf the Soul of our dear Brother, perhaps the moſt wicked Wretch on earth. And that his Body is committed to the Ground, in ſure and certain hope of a Reſurrection to Eternal Life; tho he did never truly, nor ſo much as viſibly, to the judgment of Charity, repent of his Sins.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> (1.) The Office of Burial, ſuppoſes that of Viſitation of the Sick to go before, where the Miniſter is appointed to examine, <hi>Whether he repent him truly of his Sins?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) It ſuppoſes the Exerciſe of Diſcipline, and that ſuch as he ſpeaks of, have the Cenſures of the Church exerciſed on them, which if they be not exerciſed, we know whom we are to thank for the relaxation of it.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) However, the Church provides not for extraordinary, but ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Caſes; and if an extraordinary Caſe happens, and be notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, no Rule of this nature then binds.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) If it be not notorious, it's ſafer to err on the charitable ſide.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>(5.) It's not now ſaid, That it's</hi> certain hope of a Reſurrection to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> The putting on the Ring in Marriage, eſpecially the making that Ceremony to be an eſſential Matter, is Superſtition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> (1.) What Superſtition can there be in this, more than in joyning of Hands, both of which are Civil Rites, and fit Declarations of pledging their Troth to each other?</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) How can that be Eſſential, which is one of the <hi>alterable</hi> things meant in the Preface?</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) It's neceſſary there ſhould be ſome Rite uſed, and ſome actions by which the eſpouſal ſhould be ſolemnized, and why not a Ring as well as joyning hands? And why not theſe as well as others? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Bucer</hi> calls it, <hi>a very fit Ceremony.</hi> Script. Angl. cenſ. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Churching Women, and their Offerings, is Jewiſh Superſtition.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62493:14"/>
                  <hi>A.</hi> (1.) Why Jewiſh? Is there any other Sacrifice than that of Thankſgiving offered? as there was, <hi>Levit</hi> 12. 6.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) What Superſtition is there more in kneeling down at offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up Thanks to God, than in putting up a Bill. However <hi>Bucer</hi> ſaith, <hi>This is agreeable to Scripture,</hi> c. 24.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> The Obſervation of Popiſh Holy-days, eſpecially ſuch as are dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to Saints, I look upon as highly Superſtitious.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> (1.) He looks upon them as ſuch, but how far ſoever his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion may paſs with his own Diſciples, yet others expect ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Why doth he add Popiſh? Surely he that has read and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared the Popiſh Liturgy with ours, muſt needs know that we have no Holy-days for Popiſh Saints in our Liturgy. As to which, I ſhall refer our Author to Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> on <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 10.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6. Of the Surplice, he ſaith,</hi> It's highly Superſtitious. When Holy Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were in uſe among the <hi>Jews,</hi> they had an expreſs Command for them. Should they have made a Mitre or Ephod, or other Eccleſiaſtical Garment of their own heads, they would have ſinned greatly? Witneſs <hi>Judg. 8. 27.</hi> If then the Church of God had no power to appoint Sacred Veſtments, no more has the Church in theſe days.—Moreover the Surplice is immediately borrowed from Idolatrous Maſs-mongers.—Dr. <hi>Abbot</hi> (who was no Fanatick) ſaith, That all Prieſtly Garments, whereby Miniſters are diſtinguiſhed from the reſt of the Church, are a ſpecial part of the Character of the Beaſt. The Papiſts take the Surplice from <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Heathens.</hi> There were Veſtments for the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of <hi>Baal, 2 Kings 10. 12.</hi> Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> ſaith, The Prieſts of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> uſed to wear Linnen Surplices. Moreover the greateſt part of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Divines have diſliked this Superſtitious Garment. So Martyr, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. His Argument is, the <hi>Jews</hi> had expreſs Command for their Garments, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> (1.) Had the <hi>Jews</hi> no Power to appoint or obſerve any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to Worſhip without expreſs Command? How then came the Feaſts of <hi>Purim</hi> and <hi>Dedication,</hi> the Places and Houſes of Prayer? Nay, whence came the alteration of the poſture at the Paſſover (which our Saviour complied with) contrary to the firſt inſtitution? And ſurely Veſtments are much of the ſame nature with Times and Places, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Suppoſing the <hi>Jews</hi> might not, what is that to us? Yes, ſaith he, <hi>no more can we.</hi> Why ſo? The Apoſtle ſhews we have a Liberty they had not, and we may as well do what they could not, as forbear what they might not. They had not a liberty as we, becauſe under a School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, and of a Temper that needed it, and whoſe Service was Typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. And yet notwithſtanding this, they had a liberty which they might uſe, and much more then have we.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62493:15"/>
                  <hi>2. The Surplice, he ſaith,</hi> is immediately borrowed from Idolatrous Maſs-mongers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> (1.) What is that, if there be no Idolatry borrowed with it? Do we uſe it to ſanctify Holy-water, Bells, &amp;c?</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) As for his Quotation from Dr. <hi>Abbot,</hi> it's a groſs miſtake, at leaſt; all he ſaith is, That <hi>the Buyers and Sellers,</hi> Rev. 13. 16. <hi>are the Biſhops, Prieſts, and Monks, that expoſe to ſale Maſſes and Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp;c. that bind themſelves by Oath to the Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>and in teſtimony of it, are divided from the reſt of the Church by Rites, Vows, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nctions, Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Garments.</hi> Where he ſpeaks of Garments in general, and no more of Surplices than Gowns; and of Garments they ordinarily wear, ſuch as belong to Monaſtick Orders, &amp;c. But if he had ſpoke of all Garments that diſtinguiſh the Clergy from the Laity, Dr. <hi>Abbot</hi> had been in that a Fanatick, and not Dr. <hi>Abbot,</hi> who himſelf wore ſuch Garments, and ſurely did not think by that, he had a <hi>ſpecial Character of the Beaſt</hi> upon him.</p>
               <p>What he quotes from Biſhop <hi>Jewel,</hi> is not in that place (if any where) he refers to; neither in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Latin</hi> Volume.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> The Papiſts take the Surplice from Jews and Heathens; <hi>and for this latter, quotes the Prieſts of</hi> Baal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> But the Text doth not ſay, they were any more White, than Blue or Black; and he might as well have prov'd our Gowns we or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily wear, or others prove their Cloaks to be ſuch, as well as he prove our Surplices Heatheniſh from that Text.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4. He ſaith,</hi> The greateſt part of our Proteſtant Divines have diſliked it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> (1.) What ſaith he to the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> who all uſe the like? Are not they Proteſtants?</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Do any he names diſlike it ſo, as to think it unlawful?</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) Do they diſlike it ſo, as to make a Schiſm in the Church; or for it Separate from a Church?</p>
               <p>I am certain theſe he produces, do declare juſt contrary. Thus <hi>Pet. Mart. Epiſt. Amico &amp; Hoopero, &amp;c. Beza Epiſt. Grindallo. Zanchy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſ.</hi> c 25. §. 30. <hi>Hemingius in</hi> 4 <hi>Leg. Decal.</hi> §. 29. &amp;c. <hi>Enchir. tit. Adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aph.</hi> c. 16. <hi>Polanus in Ezek.</hi> 44. And <hi>Zanchy</hi> chuſes the Linnen before the Woollen Garment for Divine Offices, as a Sign of Innocence and Holineſs, <hi>de Redempt.</hi> c. 16. I could much enlarge the Catalogue of ſuch Teſtimonies, if it were neceſſary.</p>
               <p>So little did theſe Learned Men think Mr. <hi>Nichol</hi>'s Argument of any force, which our Author propoſes <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>That all Veſtments ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the Worſhip of God, and appointed for the Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spiritual Duties, by the will of Man, are unlawful. But the Surplice is ſo.</q> This our Author ſaith is, <hi>Not eaſy to be anſwer'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:62493:15"/>
But if it be to be anſwer'd, no matter whether it's not eaſy in his Opinion. From hence ariſe two Queſtions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p n="1">Q. 1. Whether it's unlawful to uſe any thing appropriated to the Worſhip of God by the Will of Man?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 2. Whether it's unlawful to uſe any thing in the Worſhip of God that is appointed for the ſignification of Spiritual Duties by the Will of man?</p>
               <p>By the firſt it's unlawful for men to appropriate places, or times, or poſtures to the Worſhip of God. And ſo it's neceſſary, to avoid this Superſtition, to make all the Meeting-places to be houſes of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and to be equally divided between Religious and Common Uſes. By the 2d, any thing that has ſuch a Signification applied to it, is made unlawful, by Vertue of ſuch Signification, and which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch Signification would have been lawful. So a Surplice would have been a lawful Garment, if not appropriated, and without Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification; and might have been in its ſelf worn as well as a Cloak, ſince Cuſtom and Uſe only makes the difference; but appropriate it, and clap a ſignification upon it, it's unlawful: And ſo a Cloak may be turn'd out of Service by the ſame way. So it's in poſture, kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſtanding are indifferent; but once appropriate kneeling to Prayer, and make it ſignificative, and to be a poſture of reverence, and it becomes unlawful. And ſo without end. So much for Mr. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chol</hi>'s Argument, and it's difficulty.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Come we now to the Croſs, <hi>the greateſt Devil amongst all the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols of</hi> Rome; as he tells us Mr. <hi>Parker ſheweth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſaith, 1. The firſt uſers of it were the Hereticks, <hi>Valentinus</hi> and <hi>Montanus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That ſeems hard, when thoſe that wrote againſt them uſed it, as <hi>Origen, Irenaeus, Tertullian,</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> did againſt the former; and ſeveral others againſt the latter. We find it as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient as <hi>Tertullian, Cyprian,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. He ſaith, Mr.</hi> Parker proveth it a ſin againſt all the Commandments, and a breach of the Letter of the ſecond: for men to appoint a Religious Ceremony, is a direct violation of the <hi>2</hi>d Commandment, which forbids all human Inventions in Divine Worſhip, as any part thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is a way of proving too much, and that any one that reads Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> will ſoon perceive he doth: And of this I take this Inſtance of the 2d Commandment to be one, of the letter of which the Author ſaith, the Croſs is a breach. Now the Letter of the Command reſpects two things; 1. Not to make any Graven Image for Religious Worſhip. 2. Not to bow down to any ſuch Object.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62493:16"/>
Now the Croſs uſed in Baptiſm is an <hi>Aerial Croſs,</hi> as he calls it; and where is the Object or the Worſhip? But our Author goes on to prove it after this manner; <hi>for men to appoint,</hi> &amp;c. Here we grant the Propoſition to be true, becauſe God only is to appoint his own Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and ſo it's not in the power of man to appoint any part of it: But now if Religious Ceremonies may be, and yet not be part of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, then they are no ſuch human Inventions as are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; and no direct or indirect violation of the 2d Commandment. Therefore it remains upon him to prove the <hi>Croſs a part of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip:</hi> For we ſay it's only an adjunct, and is no more a part of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, than the ſtriking the Blood upon the Door-poſts was (to make uſe of <hi>Zepperus</hi> his Similitude) or ſitting or kneeling at the Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3. He ſaith.</hi> The Arguments which are brought againſt the uſe of Oyl, Cream, Salt, Spittle in Baptiſm (practiſed by the <hi>Papiſts)</hi> hold as well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Croſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This I deny; for the Scripture ſpeaks honourably of the Croſs of Chriſt, which this refers to, but not at all of the reſt. Again, the Croſs was traduced and reproached by the <hi>Heathens,</hi> which gave occaſion to the uſe of it, and ſo were not the reſt. So that this was uſed with reaſon; thoſe without it.</p>
               <p>His inſtance of the <hi>Gallows</hi> looks ſo prophanely, that I ſhall rather paſs it by, than correct it.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4. He ſaith,</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> adore the Croſs, and it's an Idol, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But do they adore the <hi>Aerial Croſs?</hi> But what is their Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (if it were) to us, that do not adore it?</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> This hath been teſtified againſt by <hi>Zegedinus, Lepperus (it ſhould be</hi> Zepperus) Goulartius, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches uſe it. See <hi>Hemingius, &amp;c. Bucer</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts it <hi>neither indecent, nor unprofitable,</hi> but a Ceremony <hi>of much ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, and of preſent admonition of the Croſs of Chriſt;</hi> Script. Angl. cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. <hi>c.</hi> 12. And generally they account it lawful, and not a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent reaſon for ſeparation; but to be uſed, ſo it be without Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So <hi>Goulartius</hi> in <hi>Cypr. lib. ad Demetr. c.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="8">8. His laſt Inſtance of Superſtition is <hi>kneeling at the Sacrament.</hi> Let us conſider what he has to ſay againſt it.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1. He ſaith,</hi> Men pretend in it reverence to Chriſt; but Chriſt himſelf was perſonally preſent, when his Diſciples partook of the Lord's Supper; yet they did not kneel, but uſed the Table-geſture then cuſtomary among the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> (1.) How is he certain the Diſciples did not kneel, but uſed the cuſtomary Poſture in receiving? For the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Paſſover chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Poſtures, and did not throughout keep to that of diſcumbency. See D. <hi>Lightfoot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:62493:16"/>
(2.) The Queſtion is not what they did, but what may lawfully be done? and then the Queſtion is, whether kneeling be unlawful?</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) They themſelves no more obſerve our Saviour's Poſture, than the <hi>Jews</hi> did that required at the firſt inſtitution. Our Author words it cautiouſly, when he ſaith the Diſciples uſed the Table-geſture <hi>then cuſtomary;</hi> for he well knew it was not ſitting, but leaning, or lying along, and that they uſed this by way of ſignification.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) If the <hi>Table</hi> be the Rule to guide us, then to put on our Hats is ſuitable, as he knows who reaſons.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. He ſaith,</hi> Good and Wiſe men have choſen great ſufferings, rather than comply with this Invention.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> And there were good and wiſe men that compiled the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and uſed and enjoined this poſture; which is an argument he ſeeks to overthrow, <hi>p.</hi> 16. And as Good and wiſe men have allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and approved it; and thought it by no means allowable to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and break Communion for it. Such as <hi>P. Martyr, Zanchy, Beza, Zepperus, &amp;c. Bains, Noyes, Ames, Cartwright,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> In Primitive times Chriſtians did not kneel in the participation of the Euchariſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> (1.) It's certain they did not ſit, for they had no Notion at all of a Table-geſture, as appears by the uſe of the Word Altar, and that they counted that a poſture of irreverence.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) If they ſtood (as he ſaith) on the Lord's-days, their ſtanding was a poſture of adoration, to be ſure, when they received: So St. <hi>Cyril</hi> expreſly, <hi>Catech.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) It's probable that on other days, when not obliged to ſtand, that they kneeled; and ſince they received every day, on ſix Days they kneel'd; So <hi>Juſt. Mart. Reſponſ. ad queſt.</hi> 115. and that more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, becauſe they had a Prayer at receiving, as we have.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4. He ſaith,</hi> It was enjoyned by Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> being fitted to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is a miſtake; for <hi>Honorius</hi> did firſt indeed decree Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to the Hoſt, but not kneeling at it. For that is a poſture no where enjoyn'd in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and ſome of them ſay, it ought to be received ſtanding; but which way, whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>ing ſtanding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or lying, or kneeling, is not material ſay others, as the <hi>Pope</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſpence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> de ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Eucha. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note>himſelf ordinarily receives ſitting, unleſs he celebrates; and then, as all Prieſts then do, he receives ſtanding. And all adore not at the receiving, but at the elevation of the Hoſt.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5. He ſaith,</hi> That Religious Worſhip, which is before a Creature, and with reſpect to it, having no allowance from God, is againſt the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but ſo is kneeling before the Bread and Wine.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:62493:17"/>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> (1.) I queſtion whether God ever allow'd any Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip before a Creature, and with reſpect to a Creature; for that is Idolatry, and no allowance from God can be ſuppoſed to Juſtifie or require Idolatry.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>(2.) I deny that there is any Religious Worſhip with reſpect to the Bread and Wine;</hi> For <hi>that, ſaith our Rubrick,</hi> were Idolatry to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred of all faithful Chriſtians. <hi>But it's only, as it's there ſaid,</hi> for a ſignification of our humble and grateful acknowledgment of the Benefits of Chriſt therein given to all worthy receivers.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6. He draws a Concluſion from the whole,</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy is very Corrupt; now to offer to the Lord a Corrupt thing, is evil, <hi>Mal. 1. 13.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A corrupt thing there, is what is plainly prohibited: Now let him prove the things before diſputed to be ſuch: As for example, that kneeling is forbidden. As for that place in <hi>Malachi,</hi> I leave to his peruſal the <hi>Letter of the Miniſters of</hi> Old-England <hi>to thoſe in</hi> New-England, <hi>p.</hi> 14. where that is explained.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <head type="sub">Publick Liturgies of humane Compoſure are an innovation, and deviation from primitive Antiquity: <hi>And again,</hi> Set Forms of Prayer devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by men are an Innovation.</head>
               <p>FOR this he offers ſeveral Arguments.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1. Saith he,</hi> Had a Liturgy been needful for the edification of the Church, undoubtedly Chriſt, or the Apoſtles by his direction, would have compoſed one, which none of them ever did. And therefore theſe men, who take upon them to compoſe and impoſe a Liturgy on the Churches, aſſume to themſelves more than Apoſtolical Power.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I deny his conſequence: For tho our Saviour and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did, declared and left all things eſſential to a Church, yet there were many things <hi>needful to the edification of the Church</hi> in future Ages that were not expreſly provided for. Our Saviour told the Apoſtles, that <hi>it ſhould be given to them in that hour what they ſhould ſpeak;</hi> and they ſpoke all Languages by preſent infuſion; and ſo were not obliged to think before, or ſtudy or learn a Language; and this was with rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the preſent condition of the Church in thoſe times. And there are no directions for after Ages to learn Languages, &amp;c. So there <hi>was a miraculous gift of Prayer in the Apoſtolical times</hi> (as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <hi>Hom.</hi> 14. in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.) and no expreſs directions given about
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62493:17"/>
it, when that Gift ſhould ceaſe (as he ſaith it did) and when by the ceſſation of it, Forms would be neceſſary. Thus faith <hi>Capellus (Theſ. Salmur.</hi> Part. 3.) <hi>As ſoon as miraculous Gifts ceaſed, and Hereticks began to trouble the Church, there was a neceſſity for Liturgies.</hi> And therefore Mr. <hi>Ball</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Chriſtian Churches</hi> for the ſpace of this 1400 years at leaſt, if not from the Apoſtles times, have had their ſtinted Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies. <hi>Trial.</hi> p. 96, &amp;c. So Letter of Min. of <hi>Old-England, l.</hi> 66<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But this our Author denies, and calls it an Innovation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſaith, 2.</hi> The Liturgies father'd on the Apoſtles, and the ancient Writers <hi>(call'd Fathers)</hi> Learned men have evinced to be ſpurious.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> (1.) It's granted, that thoſe father'd on the Apoſtles were ſo; but tho not the Apoſtles, yet many of the Prayers in them were antient, and the main of that call'd St. <hi>James</hi>'s, was uſed in the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as Dr. <hi>Comber [Original and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Liturgies,</hi> p. 97.] in Anſwer to <hi>Clarkſon,</hi> has ſhew'd from <hi>Cyril.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) It's certain there was a Liturgy compoſed by St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> and <hi>Baſil,</hi> and a great part of what is ſo call'd was certainly theirs; as the aboveſaid Author has ſhew'd, <hi>p.</hi> 167. 172, 209. and of this mind were <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Of the Maſs,</hi> l. 1. c. 6.</note>
                  <hi>Mornay</hi> and <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cenſur.</hi> 9. 10.</note>
                  <hi>Rivet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>(3.) The leaft that can be obſerved from theſe Books, is, that when thoſe Books were writ, then Liturgies were in uſe; ſo</hi> Daille; We deny not but many of theſe Liturgies are ancient, and written about the beginning of the Fourth Century, tho they were corrupted by Additions <note place="margin">De cultu. Lat. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note>and Alterations at ſeveral times after their firſt original.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He would prove from an obſcure Paſſage in <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> that there was <hi>no Book of Prayer uſed by Chriſtians</hi> 200 years after Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Paſſage in <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Which our Author is forced to corrupt, and add to, before he can work it to his purpoſe; for thus he tranſlates it, <hi>according as ſtrength and utterance was afforded to him from Heaven:</hi> whereas word for word it is, <hi>in like manner he</hi> [the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent] <hi>offereth up Prayers to him</hi> [God] <hi>as he has Power,</hi> that is, as fervently as he could: and ſo the ſame Phraſe a little before. Of this ſee Dr. <hi>Comber, p.</hi> 33, &amp;c. And as little does the Paſſage in <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> make for his purpoſe, which is, That the Chriſtians prayed, <hi>Sine Monitore quia de pectore;</hi> which ſurely relates not to the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing extempore; for what teſtimony was that of their Loyalty, more than if they prayed by a Form; but his plain meaning is, they need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no Prompter (as the <hi>Heathens)</hi> but prayed heartily for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, &amp;c. as their Offices ſhew'd.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:62493:18"/>
4. He ſaith, <q>That there was no Liturgy in ſome Churches, or in general uſe in the Church, for above 400 years, is manifeſt from <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates;</hi> who ſaith, <hi>There were ſcarcely two Chriſtians found who uſed the ſame words in Prayer,</hi>
                  </q> l. 5. c. 21.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> (1.) Here he perverts again: For (1.) <hi>Socrates</hi> doth not ſay two Chriſtians, but two Churches. (2.) He doth not ſay, they uſed the ſame <hi>words,</hi> but the ſame <hi>manner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) The Words of <hi>Socrates</hi> do not infer what he would have; for he ſaith, <hi>In Summ among all Sects you ſhall ſcarcely find two Churches agreeing in the manner of Prayer:</hi> Which refers not to the Words, but the Ways, as before deſcribed, <hi>viz.</hi> lighting up Candles, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) Suppoſing it was to be underſtood of the Words, what's that to Extempore Prayer? for they may not have the ſame words, when yet they may have Forms. The Hiſtorian's meaning is, That the Churches had different Forms of Prayer, as well as different Rites: <note place="margin">Maſs. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note>So <hi>Mornay</hi> ſpeaking of the Liturgies of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches; <hi>Tho in ſubſtance the Service of theſe Churches do agree, yet we muſt not think there was one and the ſame Preſcript Form obſerved, and kept in them all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5. He ſaith,</hi> Some plead, that in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church of old there were Forms of Prayer, beſides thoſe of Divine Inſpiration; but what was not, <hi>are all</hi> late compoſures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. If there were Forms of old in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſpiration,</hi> and thoſe Forms to be uſed (as the Scripture ſhews) then it ſhews that Forms may lawfully be uſed.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">So <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay</hi> Maſs. l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> 2. That the <hi>Jews</hi> had ſet-forms of human compoſure, of ancient times, Learned men agree: So <hi>Mornay</hi> ſhews; and that the <hi>Firſt Chriſtians framed themſelves after this manner of Service.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Nay, Learned men obſerve, that Forms were uſed in our Saviour's time; and yet he is ſo far from condemning them, that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vol.</hi> 1. 157, 158, 161.</note>he attended their Service, and compoſed a form like to theirs. So Dr. <hi>Lightfoot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that we ſee he has failed throughout in his attempt of proving Liturgies and ſet-forms an Innovation. But I can tell <hi>what is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation;</hi> and that is, To hold Liturgies unlawful.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:62493:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">It's an Apoſtacy in this Age of Light, to countenance or comply with the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi>-Book Worſhip.</head>
               <p>UPON this his chief Topick is:</p>
               <p>That Good and Learned men have born witneſs againſt the Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy, and choſe to ſuffer rather than comply with it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. There have been as Good and Learned men that have ſhew'd thoſe not to be Corruptions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There have been ſeveral of his Learned and Good men, who he ſaith, <hi>choſe rather to ſuffer, than ſin, by complying with the Liturgy,</hi> that have ſhew'd thoſe Corruptions not to be a ſufficient reaſon for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration: So Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> Mr. <hi>Nicols,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They were ſo far from refuſing Communion for them, that the Old <hi>Nonconformiſts ordinarily and conſtantly uſed the Common-Prayer-Book in their publick Miniſtrations;</hi> as Mr. <hi>Ball,</hi> one of them, declares, <hi>Tryal,</hi> p. 121, 155.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4. All of them teſtified againſt the</hi> Browniſts, <hi>and againſt a ſeparation from the Church.</hi> It was <hi>(ſaith Mr.</hi> Baxter) the Pariſh-Churches that had the Liturgy, which Mr. <hi>Jacob</hi> the Father of the Congregational Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wrote for communion with. The ſame I may ſay of Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> and other Nonconformiſts, whom the Congregational Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren think more favourable to their way.</p>
               <p>In the cloſe, our Author offers ſome farther Objections from <hi>the falſe and corrupt Doctrine</hi> he pretends to find in the Liturgy.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>(1.) As, that</hi> it's certain by God's word, that Children Baptized dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before they commit actual ſin, are undoubtedly ſaved: This, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> ſavours of <hi>Pelagianiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I don't underſtand the falſeneſs, or Pelagianiſm of it. It's certain by God's Word, that <hi>of ſuch is the Kingdom of God,</hi> and ſo they muſt be capable of it. If capable of it, it muſt be upon Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel terms; but what terms they are capable of but Baptiſm, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>(2.) That</hi> there are two Sacraments neceſſary to Salvation; which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies a double Error, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Sacraments are neceſſary to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and that there are more Sacraments of the New-Teſtament than two.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I don't ſee wherein is the firſt Error, if he had truly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it; for it's ſaid in the Catechiſm, two Sacraments <hi>generally</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; that is, that they are a Duty belonging to all perſons that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62493:19"/>
are capable of it; where there are perſons to baptize, and a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to communicate with; and therefore it's not ſaid abſolutely, but <hi>generally</hi> neceſſary.</p>
               <p>As for the latter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Sacrament is not a Scripture-word, but a Term of Art, and ſo hath been variouſly uſed and applied; and therefore to ſet out what it means, the Church has defined what a Sacrament is, and then ſhew'd there are but two: and ſo this Phraſe is uſed to diſtinguiſh it from any other ſo called; and that then none but theſe two are generally neceſſary to all Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>(3.)</hi> The Book ſaith, Some Sins are deadly, as if the Popiſh diſtinction of ſins into Mortal and Venial, were a ſound diſtinction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> How can that be, when Fornication, which is called deadly in the Liturgy, in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is ordinarily accounted a Venial Sin; and when the diſtinction between Mortal and Venial (as uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome)</hi> is ſo contrary to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> It's plain that our Church means thereby no other than <hi>heinous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>(4.) It's ſaid,</hi> Chriſt has redeemed all mankind.</p>
               <p>Anſ. <hi>The Scripture ſaith,</hi> God will have all men to be ſaved; <hi>and that</hi> Chriſt died for all, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. He argues farther, That</hi> A ſtinted Liturgy, is oppoſite to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Prayer, <hi>Eph. 6. 18.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ. <hi>(1.) If ſo, then the Spirit will not communicate it ſelf in a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Diſcourſe of prayer, <hi>p. 31.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Liturgy, or ſtinted Form of Prayer, contrary to the ſenſe of all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Divines. So Dr.</hi> Owen: Suppoſing, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> thoſe who make uſe of, and plead for Forms of Prayer, eſpecially in publick, do in a due man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner prepare themſelves for it by holy meditation, &amp;c. I do not judge that there is any ſuch evil in them, as that God will not communicate his Spirit to any in the uſe of them.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) If ſo, then <hi>almoſt all Churches in the world for theſe</hi> 1300 <note place="margin">Sacrileg. deſert. p. <hi>102,</hi> &amp;c.</note>
                  <hi>years, at leaſt, to this day</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> allows) have been without the Spirit of Prayer.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) If ſo, then we cannot lawfully communicate in, or with a ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Liturgy, which has yet <hi>been approved by all Reformed Churches,</hi> as <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apol.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 13.</note>Mr. <hi>Ball</hi> ſaith; and Mr. <hi>Norton</hi> ſaith it's <hi>lawful to embrace Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Churches, where ſuch Forms in Publick worſhip are in uſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">(4.) As for <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 18. that we are to <hi>pray with all Prayer;</hi> why is that not poſſible by a Liturgy, when there are in it Supplications, Prayers, and giving of thanks?</p>
               <p n="3">3. He lets paſs the Argument, from the miſchief of a preſcript Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, and ſo will I paſs what follows from the trivial, unintelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and dirty Reflections of it. For he knows we can match his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62493:19"/>
                  <hi>Fidler</hi> with Stories of ſome of thoſe that have been Eminent the other way, and could argue upon the ſinfulneſs of unpremeditated and conceived Prayer.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3. He ſaith, Mr.</hi> Cotton <hi>ſpeaketh weightily, in ſaying,</hi> It's unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to bring ordinarily any other Book into the Publick Worſhip of God, beſides the Book of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I know no difference between Reading and Reciting in this caſe; and I have heard Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> uſed a Form of Prayer in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. <note place="margin">See <hi>Clerk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Collect. of Lives, <hi>p. 38.</hi>
                  </note>If he did not, yet all the Nonconformiſts in former times did, as far as ever I could learn.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To cloſe all; he undertakes to Anſwer an Objection, That</hi> Good men were the firſt Collectors and Publiſhers of the Liturgy, and died Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</p>
               <p>This he endeavours to anſwer; and yet when it's to ſerve his own Cauſe, it's a conſiderable Argument. Thus ſaith he before, <hi>The Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the Liturgy have been born witneſs againſt by good Men; and his Father, a Holy Man, ſuffered much for his Nonconformity,</hi> and what not. Now ſurely, if this ſort of arguing is good for them, it's good for us.</p>
               <p>But he Replies further,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> All Perſons employed in it, were not good Men, as <hi>Day</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter.</hi> He was a diſſembling Hypocrite, pretending to be a Proteſtant, but afterwards ſhew'd himſelf to be a Papiſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Here he betrays groſs ignorance, or ſomewhat worſe. For tho <hi>Day</hi> was one of the 18 Biſhops imployed for compiling the Service-Book at firſt, <hi>Anno</hi> 1548. yet at that time he was for Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, and Solitary Maſſes, and againſt having the Service in the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Burnet's</hi> Reformat. Part <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>62.</hi> and Num. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note>Vulgar Tongue.</p>
               <p>And when the next Review was, which was 1550. when <hi>Cranmer</hi> wrote to <hi>Bucer</hi> about it, it does not appear that <hi>Day</hi> was concerned; nay, rather that he was againſt it, for he refuſed to ſet his hand to the Book, before it was enacted by a Law; and was afterward turn'd out of his Biſhoprick, and depriv'd. But to ſay all in a word, What <note place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>163<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> p. <hi>203.</hi>
                  </note>was this <hi>diſſembling</hi> Hypocrite to thoſe who <hi>were truly Pious Men, and acted faithfully according to the Light they had?</hi> as our Author acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He ſaith, Good men chang'd their minds, ſo did <hi>Ridley</hi> and <hi>Cranmer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fox</hi>'s Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Fol. <hi>1465.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> Both groſs miſtakes. For Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> took upon him to defend the Common-Prayer, Miniſtration of the Sacraments, and other Rites and Ceremonies, when in Priſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62493:20"/>
                  <hi>And Biſhop</hi> Ridley, <hi>a little before his Martyrdom, in a Letter to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fox's</hi> Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Vol. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>1940.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>his Friend, ſaith,</hi> This Church had of late the whole Divine Service, all Common and Publick Prayers, framed to the true vein of Holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>And again, after his condemnation, writing an Anſwer to <hi>Grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal,</hi> concerning <hi>Knox</hi>'s peremptory Exceptions againſt the Service-Book; <hi>I grant,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a Man (as he is) of Wit and Learning, may</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Vide Dr. <hi>Taylor.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fox <hi>Martyr. p.</hi> 1521.</p>
                  </note>
                  <hi>find apparent reaſons; yet I ſuppoſe he cannot ſoundly by the Word of God ſo diſprove any thing in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. He ſaith, <hi>Others were much troubled at the Service-Book;</hi> as Biſhop <hi>Hooper,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> at home; and <hi>Calvin, Bucer, Martyr, Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> &amp;c. abroad. So <hi>Alaſco,</hi> and <hi>Knox,</hi> and the firſt Reformers in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As for <hi>Hooper</hi>'s diſſatisfaction, it was not at the Liturgy, but the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, <hi>p.</hi> 125 &amp;c. 166.</note>Epiſcopal Veſtments; in which alſo he at laſt complied.</p>
               <p>And as for <hi>Bucer</hi>'s mind, and <hi>Pet. Martyr</hi>'s, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reader will find it in the Hiſtory of the Reformation, <hi>p.</hi> 154, 155. And <hi>Calvin</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>200</hi> and <hi>206.</hi> and <hi>228.</hi> That of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſco,</hi> printed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no <hi>1550.</hi> And that of <hi>Knox</hi> at Middelb. <hi>1594.</hi>
                  </note>to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Exiles at <hi>Frankford,</hi> declares againſt a rigorous Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and was pleaſed that he retained Moderation in this Caſe.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Alaſco</hi> and <hi>Knox,</hi> whatever they objected againſt the Liturgy, yet both had their Publick Offices, and Forms of Prayer.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4. He ſaith,</hi> In Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time the Biſhops made the Common-Prayer-Book in ſeveral things worſe, and more intollerable, than it was in the days of King <hi>Edward 6.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. And I hope he will confeſs in many things better.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Why thoſe Prayers, &amp;c. were left out, he may ſee in the Hiſtory of the Reformation, <hi>p.</hi> 77, 170, 392.</p>
               <p>The reaſon of which has been before juſtified.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There could be no great alteration to the worſe, if that was all that he mentions; and however is nothing to us, when the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of the Communion is reſtored.</p>
               <p>And now, that he may end as he begun, as he would have our Service-Book come from Popery; ſo he will have it, <hi>That time will diſcover that ſome, who pretend Zeal for the Common-Prayer-Book, are carrying on a deſign for</hi> Rome.</p>
               <p>And time has diſcovered, that ſome of thoſe who pretended Zeal againſt the Common-Prayer, carried on a deſign for <hi>Rome,</hi> and helped them forward in it, or ſtood as it were Neuters; and that the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy has not ſo much a tendency that way, as Separation.</p>
               <p>The World ſaw it in the late Reign, and found that the Church that uſes the Liturgy, was a Bulwark againſt Popery; and when thoſe that were againſt the Liturgy, either baſely complied, fawn'd upon it, or cowardly were ſilent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:62493:20"/>
THe Second Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. 2.</hi> What reaſon have you to ſcruple the lawfulneſs of laying the Hand on the Book, and Kiſſing the Book in Swearing?</p>
               <p>To this he Anſwers,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> We do not find in the Scripture the Lord's Servants were wont to ſwear after this manner; we read of lifting up the hand, &amp;c. which is a natural ſign of Worſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. We find in Scripture, that they were wont to put the hand under the Thigh in ſwearing: And thus the ſame <hi>Abraham</hi> that lift up his hand, required his Servant to ſwear, by putting his hand under his Thigh, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. 2. and ſo <hi>Jacob</hi> made his Son <hi>Joſeph</hi> to uſe the ſame Ceremony when he ſwore, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47. 29. Now what natural Sign of Worſhip was in this Rite?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Since we find different Rites us'd, it's a ſign that practice of the Lord's Servants is to be no Rule to us in this matter; but that we are to govern our ſelves by the Cuſtom of the place where, and the People among whom we live, if there be nothing in it ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He ſaith, and ſeems to allow it, That the <hi>Romans</hi> of old, and <hi>Italians,</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> uſe to lift up the Finger when they ſwear ſolemnly. Now I conceive lifting up the Finger is no natural Sign of Worſhip. And if it had any ſignification, I know no reaſon why the <hi>Germans</hi> may not lift up three Fingers; to intimate, they invoke the Sacred Trinity, which he ſaith, he <hi>cannot juſtify.</hi> Nor why we may not lay the Hand upon, and Kiſs the Book, in token of belief of it, and of our acting according to it, and of our being judged according to it.</p>
               <p>For the Word of God doth not preſcribe in ſuch caſes.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. He anſwers,</hi> Laying the Hand on the Book is a ſymbolizing with Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Idolaters, and Superſtitious <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. It's not a ſymbolizing with Papiſts as ſuch; ſince there are Papiſts that uſe other Ceremonies in ſwearing, as he ſaith, The <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians, Spaniards,</hi> and <hi>Germans</hi> do. And therefore, if this be a reaſon, as we muſt not lift up the Fingers, becauſe they do ſo; ſo we muſt not lift up the Hand, becauſe that is not to be done, but we muſt lift up the Fingers too.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If it was cuſtomary among the <hi>Jews</hi> to produce the Law in giving an Oath, I ſee no reaſon to condemn it; and ſo know no hurt to obſerve it. They uſed alſo to adjure Perſons, and our Saviour readily anſwers to it, when thus call'd upon.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:62493:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>3. He replies,</hi> Kiſſing in a Religious way, is a geſture of Adoration. <hi>And he cloſes it,</hi> This is clearly to Worſhip a Book; and ſo to give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Creature that Honour which is due to God alone. <hi>And before he ſaith,</hi> So help you and the Contents of this Book; is not much better than when the Papiſts ſay, So help me God, and theſe Holy Evangeliſts, which is groſs Idolatry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That Kiſſing may be a Token of Adoration, when the thing kiſs'd is an Object of Adoration, is acknowledged. But it's not a token of Adoration, when the thing kiſſed is not an Object of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration. Thus kiſſing the Calves, and an Image, is an act of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, becauſe the Object is an Object of Adoration; but kiſſing the Book is not, becauſe a Book is no Object of Adoration.</p>
               <p>If it be asked, Why then is the Book kiſſed? I ſay, it's in token of Reverence, as it's the Book of God; and which, if I ſo kiſs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very time I read it, it's ſurely far from being Idolatry. And that it is ſo, appears from what follows, <hi>So help me God, and the Contents of this Book:</hi> which is in different ways, God by his Grace, and the Contents of this Book by their Inſtruction; the one as the efficient, the other the Inſtrumental cauſe. And thus without doubt it's meant in the old Form, <hi>So help me God, and theſe Holy Evangeliſts,</hi> that is, the Goſpel wrote by them; as the name of <hi>Moſes</hi> is given in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to his Writings. So that in this ſence it's neither Idolatry in them, nor any thing like it in us. And we may as lawfully kiſs the Book, as lift up the Hand, ſince neither of them are prohibited by God's Law; and ſo being indifferent in themſelves, we may act as the caſe requires.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:62493:21"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
