<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the King and Queen at White-Hall, May the 4th. M.DC.XC. by William Wake ...</title>
            <author>Wake, William, 1657-1737.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-03">2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66358</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4855</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12376575</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12376575</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60633</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A66358)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60633)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 903:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the King and Queen at White-Hall, May the 4th. M.DC.XC. by William Wake ...</title>
                  <author>Wake, William, 1657-1737.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Chiswell ... and W. Rogers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XVI, 25 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60633:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60633:1"/>
            <p>A
SERMON
Preach'd before the
KING and QUEEN
AT
<hi>WHITE-HALL,
MAY</hi> the 4th. M.DC.XC.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM WAKE,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in
Ordinary to Their Majesties: And Preacher to the
Honourable Society of <hi>GRAYS-INN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Published by Their Majesties Special Comand.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>Chrysost. <hi>Conc. 2. de</hi> Lazar.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiswell</hi> at the <hi>Rose</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in
St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard: And <hi>W. Rogers</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi>
over-against St. <hi>Dunstan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetstreet.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:60633:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60633:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>LUKE xvi. 25.</bibl>
               <q>But <hi>Abraham</hi> said; Son, Remember that <hi>Thou</hi> in
thy life-time receivedst thy God things, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
<hi>Lazarus</hi> Evil things: But now, <hi>He</hi> is
<hi>Comforted,</hi> and <hi>Thou</hi> art <hi>Tormented.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>words</hi> are part of a <hi>Parable,</hi>
in which our <hi>Saviour Christ</hi> sets
forth to us the different Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods
of <hi>God's Providence</hi> in his
dispensations to <hi>Mankind,</hi> with
relation to the <hi>Happiness</hi> of <hi>this
life,</hi> and of <hi>the Other.</hi> That however he may
here seem to scatter his <hi>Blessings</hi> at all adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
upon the <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Bad</hi> indifferently, and
permit the <hi>Wicked</hi> to <hi>triumph</hi> in their Impiety;
Yet there is a time coming when <hi>He</hi> will call
them to a severe account for all their Actions,
and <hi>render to every man according to his Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>There was a certain <hi>rich Man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vers. 19.</note> which was cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in purple and fine linnen, and fared sumptuously
every day. And there was a certain <hi>Beggar,</hi> named
<hi>Lazarus,</hi> which was laid at his Gate full of sores;
And desiring to be fed with the Crumbs which fell
from the rich mans table: moreover the dogs came
and licked His sores. And it came to pass that the beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60633:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
died, and was carried by the Angels into <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s
bosome; The rich man also died, and was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried.
And in Hell he lift up his Eyes, being in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and seeth <hi>Abraham</hi> afar off, and <hi>Lazarus</hi>
in his bosome. And he cried, and said, Father <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi>
Have mercy on me; and send <hi>Lazarus</hi>
that he may dip the tip of his finger in water, and
cool my tongue, for I am tormented in this flame.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>But <hi>Abraham</hi> said; Son, Remember, that <hi>Thou</hi>
in thy life-time receivedst thy <hi>good things,</hi>
and likewise <hi>Lazarus, evil things:</hi> but now,
<hi>He</hi> is <hi>comforted,</hi> and <hi>Thou</hi> art <hi>tormented.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>It has been one of the oldest <hi>Complaints</hi> that
we any-where meet with against the <hi>Providence</hi>
of <hi>God</hi> in his managing the Affairs of this <hi>lower
World,</hi> That He so often permits the <hi>greatest Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi>
to be very <hi>easie</hi> and <hi>prosperous;</hi> whilst <hi>better
men</hi> are forced many times to encounter with all
the difficulties and discouragements, not only
of a poor and despicable Fortune, but that
too rendred yet more uneasie, by the <hi>Injuries</hi>
and <hi>Oppressions</hi> which the wicked are suffered to
bring upon him.</p>
            <p>If we look back into the <hi>state</hi> of the <hi>World</hi>
before our <hi>Saviour;</hi> even then when it pleased
<hi>God</hi> to make <hi>temporal blessings</hi> the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60633:3"/>
to <hi>Obedience;</hi> yet we shall find neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less
the best Men very frequently both won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring
at, and complaining of the <hi>inequality</hi> of
this <hi>procedure. Truly,</hi> says <hi>Holy David,</hi> Psal. lxxiii.
1. <hi>God is good unto</hi> Israel,<note place="margin">Psal. lxxiii. 1,</note> 
               <hi>even to such as are of a
clean heart:</hi>
               <note place="margin">—2,</note> 
               <hi>But as for me, my feet were almost gone,
my steps had well nigh slipp'd:</hi>
               <note place="margin">—3.</note> 
               <hi>For I was envious at
the foolish, when I saw the prosperity of the wicked.</hi>
And <hi>Job</hi> himself, thô so <hi>patient</hi> in his <hi>own suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings,</hi>
yet could not forbear to expostulate with
<hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job xxi. 7.</note> about the <hi>flourishing condition</hi> of <hi>Evil Men;
Job</hi> xxi. 7. <hi>Wherefore do the wicked live, become
old, yea, are mighty in power?</hi> And the best ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
could then be given of this matter was;
That thô <hi>Providence</hi> did permit them to flourish
for a while, yet it commonly brought some se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere
Judgment upon them at the last: And as
the <hi>Heathens</hi> themselves sometimes observed,
therefore raised them up to a height of <hi>fortune</hi>
extraordinary, that their <hi>Fall</hi> might be the
<hi>greater,</hi> and <hi>more remarkable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This was what the</hi> Prophet David, <hi>after all his
search, acquiesced in, as the best Argument both
to satisfy himself, and to vindicate</hi> God Almighty.
Surely,<note place="margin">Psal. lxxiii. 18,</note> 
               <hi>says He,</hi> thou dost set them in slippery places,
and castest them into destruction:<note place="margin">—19.</note> How are they
brought into desolation as in a moment? They are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60633:4"/>
consumed with terrors:<note place="margin">—20.</note> As a dream when one
awaketh, so, <hi>O Lord,</hi> when thou awakest shalt thou
despise their Image. <hi>And again, in another</hi> Psalm;
<hi>He gives this as the reason, why we should not
be troubled at the</hi> prosperity <hi>which</hi> wicked Men
<hi>seem sometimes to enjoy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. xxxvii. 1,</note> Fret not thy self be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
of Evil-doers, neither be thou envious against
the workers of Iniquity;<note place="margin">—2.</note> For they shall soon be cut
down like the grass, and wither as the green herb.
<hi>And</hi> Solomon <hi>not only insists upon the same Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
but almost transcribes the very same words:</hi>
Prov. <hi>xxiv.</hi> 19.<note place="margin">Prov. xxiv. 19,</note> Fret not thy self because of Evil
Men,<note place="margin">—20.</note> neither be thou envious at the Wicked; For there
shall be no reward to the Evil Man, the Candle of the
Wicked shall be put out.</p>
            <p>And the same was the Reflection which the
rest of the <hi>Holy Men</hi> in those times contented
themselves with upon this occasion. They saw
but little of a <hi>future state,</hi> and of that Eternal
Retribution <hi>God</hi> will hereafter make of <hi>Rewards</hi>
and <hi>Punishments,</hi> to every one <hi>according to his
works:</hi> And therefore they sought out that
punishment for <hi>Sinners</hi> in this <hi>World,</hi> which they
could not so certainly assign to them in the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor indeed was this any more than what the
Tenor of the <hi>Law</hi> it self directed them to. For
it having pleased <hi>God</hi> to set before them the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60633:4"/>
of this <hi>present life,</hi> as the <hi>rewards</hi> of their
<hi>Obedience;</hi> and by the <hi>threatnings</hi> of <hi>troubles</hi> and
<hi>disappointments,</hi> of <hi>losses</hi> and <hi>afflictions</hi> now to
be undergone, to affright them from sin: It
was but natural for them to be surprised, when
contrary to all this, they saw <hi>wicked men</hi> in great
<hi>Prosperity;</hi> And to conclude according to what
both the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Methods</hi> of his
<hi>Dispensations,</hi> and their own <hi>Experience</hi> led them
to do, that their <hi>happiness</hi> should not be of any
<hi>long continuance;</hi> but, as the <hi>Psalmist</hi> expresses
it,<note place="margin">Psal. xxxvii. 36.</note> in the <hi>Psalm</hi> I before mentioned, Ps. xxxvii.
35, 36. <hi>I have seen the wicked in great power, and
spreading himself like a green bay-tree:</hi>
               <note place="margin">—37.</note> 
               <hi>Yet he pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
away, and lo, he was not; yea I sought him, but
he could not be found.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such was the <hi>Case</hi> even of the best men here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore
under the <hi>Law:</hi> And I shall not need
to say, how apt we all of us are, to complain
of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Providence</hi> upon the same account even
now. And if not with the <hi>Sceptick,</hi> to take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
from hence to dispute whether he has
any concern at all for the <hi>Affairs</hi> here below;
yet at least with <hi>Jeremy</hi> to reason sometimes
with him of his doings,<note place="margin">Jer xii. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Jer.</hi> xii. 1. <hi>Righteous art
thou,</hi> O LORD, <hi>when I plead with thee, yet let me talk
with thee of thy judgments; Wherefore doth the way
of the wicked prosper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60633:5"/>
But the <hi>Instance</hi> of the <hi>Text</hi> explains the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty,
gives a final <hi>satisfaction</hi> to all our
<hi>doubts,</hi> and for ever <hi>silences</hi> our Complaints;
and <hi>vindicates</hi> both the <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>Goodness</hi> of
<hi>God Almighty.</hi> Whilst drawing aside the <hi>vail</hi>
which hung before their eyes, it gives us a
clear prospect of a state of things, beyond
the narrow bounds of this <hi>present World.</hi> A
<hi>State</hi> where all these seeming Irregularities
shall be set to rights: Where the <hi>Sinner</hi> shall be
divested of all his present <hi>happiness;</hi> And the
<hi>Greatness,</hi> the <hi>Riches,</hi> the <hi>Pleasures</hi> he now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys,
expire into the <hi>sad result</hi> of that <hi>Sarcastick</hi>
Concession, which <hi>Solomon</hi> once made to the
wicked in his days;<note place="margin">Eccles. xi. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Rejoice, O young man, in thy
youth, and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy
youth; Walk in the ways of thy heart, and in the
sight of thine eyes: But know thou, that for all these
things, God will bring thee to judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, but the <hi>Text</hi> carries us yet farther:
It not only sets before us the different state of
the poor despised <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and the rich <hi>Volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary,</hi>
in the <hi>other world;</hi> thô that had been suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
to <hi>justifie</hi> the <hi>Providence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> both for
all the <hi>Good</hi> which the <hi>One</hi> had received, and
for all the <hi>Evil</hi> which the <hi>Other</hi> had suffer'd here
on <hi>Earth:</hi> But seems in great measure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60633:5"/>
to us their several conditions in this <hi>Life,</hi>
as the very <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Reason</hi> of their different
Portions in the other. <hi>Son, remember, that</hi> Thou
<hi>in thy life-time hast received thy</hi> Good things, <hi>and
likewise</hi> Lazarus Evil things; <hi>but now</hi> He <hi>is</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted,
<hi>and</hi> Thou <hi>art</hi> tormented. He does not tell
him of the <hi>Abuse</hi> he had made of his <hi>Riches,</hi> in
employing them only upon his <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suality.</hi>
He reproaches him not with his <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableness,</hi>
that could let this poor man lie
and perish at his <hi>Gate,</hi> and not take so much no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
as his very <hi>Dogs</hi> did of him. No; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presents
to him only the <hi>Happiness</hi> he some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
enjoyed whilst he was in this World;
and the Grandeur and Jollity in which he lived
in it: As if a <hi>continued state of Prosperity</hi> in the
<hi>present life</hi> were almost incompatible with the
Blessings and Glories of the other.</p>
            <p>And however I shall not presume to be so
rash, as to make a general <hi>Rule</hi> of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark;
That those who are <hi>Great,</hi> and <hi>Rich,</hi> and
<hi>Honourable</hi> now, are not to expect any further
<hi>Portion</hi> hereafter: And, <hi>God</hi> be thanked! have
Instances at this time before my eyes, that I
am perswaded, would be sufficient to confute
the uncharitableness of such a <hi>Conclusion:</hi> Yet
thus much I may take leave to observe from it;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60633:6"/>
That such Persons as these, shall of all others
the <hi>most hardly be saved.</hi> And therefore that we
ought to be so far from censuring <hi>God's Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi>
for dispensing so large a share of these <hi>Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings</hi>
to them, or from envying of them upon
any such account; that we should rather pity
their danger, who are beset with so many more
and so much greater Temptations than other
men; And must therefore take a great deal
more care and pains, be much more watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
over themselves, and zealous in their duty;
or else what we falsly call their <hi>Happiness,</hi> may
prove their <hi>ruin</hi> to all <hi>Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was a severe Censure which our <hi>Saviour</hi>
once pass'd upon the <hi>Riches,</hi> and I fear I may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
it to all other the like advantages, to the
<hi>Honours,</hi> the <hi>Power,</hi> the <hi>Pleasures</hi> of this world;
Mat. xix. 23.<note place="margin">Mat. xix. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Verily I say unto you, that a</hi> rich
man <hi>shall hardly enter into the kingdom of heaven.</hi>
And again,<note place="margin">—24.</note> ver. 24. <hi>I say unto you, It is easier for
a Camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a
rich man to enter into the kingdom of heaven.</hi> And
when his <hi>Disciples</hi> thereupon began with some
<hi>amazement</hi> to ask of him,<note place="margin">—25.</note> 
               <hi>Who then can be sav'd?</hi>
We do not find him at all moderating his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection.
He tells them, that it was indeed pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible
for such a one to be saved: But it was like
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60633:6"/>
               <hi>removing a mountain,</hi> or <hi>raising a dead man to life.</hi>
A work to be done only by a <hi>Miracle</hi> of <hi>God's
Grace;</hi> not after the ordinary manner of other
men, but by that <hi>mighty Power</hi> which makes
nothing impossible to a <hi>Divine Agent:</hi>
               <note place="margin">—26.</note> Jesus
<hi>said unto them, With men this is impossible, but with
God all things are possible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is that which I shall now endeavour
both from the <hi>Remark</hi> and the <hi>Example</hi> of the
<hi>Text,</hi> more particularly to represent to you.
I am sensible that I am now speaking to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
of a more than ordinary <hi>Fortune</hi> and <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter</hi>
in the <hi>World.</hi> And I know how much hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
it will be, without great care, for such to be
<hi>saved,</hi> than for those of an <hi>Inferiour degree:</hi> And
therefore how necessary it is, that they should
be fully convinced and persuaded of it. And
I am not in the least apprehensive, that I shall
at all <hi>discourage</hi> their <hi>Piety</hi> by such an Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.
It is the Honour of <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Generons</hi>
minds to be <hi>brave</hi> and <hi>daring.</hi> The <hi>difficulties</hi>
that would affright others, serve only to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
and encourage them the more to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
them. And this <hi>Promise</hi> they have from
<hi>God Almighty,</hi> That as their task is more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult
than other mens, so shall his <hi>Grace</hi> be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spenced
to them in a <hi>greater</hi> and more plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60633:7"/>
               <hi>Degree.</hi> So that if they benot wanting to
themselves, he will not fail to assist their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours:
He will bless them with an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
measure of his <hi>Grace</hi> now, and will
<hi>crown</hi> them with <hi>a more Exceeding and Eternal
weight of glory</hi> hereafter.</p>
            <p>For the better clearing of all which, I shall
observe this <hi>Method:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. I will shew, How much more difficult
it is for those who are <hi>Great,</hi> and <hi>Rich,</hi>
and <hi>Powerful,</hi> to be saved, than for other
men? And upon what <hi>Grounds</hi> it is, that
it becomes so?</p>
            <p>II<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>. I will consider what Influence such a
<hi>Reflection</hi> ought to have upon all <hi>sorts</hi> of
<hi>men,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Upon the <hi>One,</hi> to stir them up to a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<hi>Care</hi> of their <hi>future Happiness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Upon the <hi>Other,</hi> to engage them to a
patient Acquiescence even in the <hi>meanest
Condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, I<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. I am to shew, How much more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult
it is for those who are <hi>Great,</hi> and <hi>Rich,</hi>
and <hi>Powerful,</hi> to be saved, than for other
men? And upon what <hi>Grounds,</hi> and for
what <hi>reason</hi> it is that it becomes so?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60633:7"/>
Now this will appear from these two <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>1st.</hi> Of that <hi>Obligation</hi> which those who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
these <hi>Advantages</hi> lie under, to a more
<hi>strict</hi> and <hi>careful Discharge</hi> of their <hi>duty,</hi>
than other men. And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Of those <hi>Temptations</hi> which these very
things many times bring along with
them, to the ruining of such persons:
Whilst instead of <hi>ministring</hi> to their <hi>Piety,</hi>
and so <hi>encreasing</hi> their <hi>Reward,</hi> they serve
rather to <hi>expose</hi> them the more to <hi>danger;</hi>
and in the consequence thereof, become
oftentimes the greatest Occasion of their
<hi>Eternal Destruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For if such <hi>Persons</hi> as these have a larger and
more comprehensive <hi>Duty</hi> to fulfil, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
of these <hi>Advantages,</hi> than other men; And
if these very things which thus encrease their
<hi>duty,</hi> are also at the same time apt to prove the
greatest Lets and Hindrances to them in the
performance of it; nay perhaps become even
Snares and Temptations to them to draw them
aside from it: 'Tis then a plain case, that their
condition must be more dangerous than that
of <hi>ordinary Christians,</hi> who neither <hi>lie</hi> under such
<hi>Engagements,</hi> nor are <hi>exposed</hi> to such <hi>Temptations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:60633:8"/>
And <hi>1st.</hi> That <hi>those</hi> to whom <hi>God</hi> has given
these <hi>Advantages</hi> above <hi>other men,</hi> do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
become engaged to a <hi>more strict</hi> and
<hi>careful discharge</hi> of their <hi>duty</hi> than <hi>others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For proof whereof I shall need go no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
than that great <hi>Evangelical Rule</hi> of our <hi>Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
Saviour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke xii. 48.</note> Luke xii. 48. <hi>That unto whomsoever
much is given, of him much shall be required; and
unto whom men have committed much, of him they will
ask the more.</hi> He was speaking in the <hi>Verse</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
of the Difference which God would make
in his exactions hereafter, according to the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
degrees of mens <hi>Knowledg</hi> and <hi>Capacities</hi>
now.<note place="margin">Verse 47.</note> 
               <hi>That servant which knew his Lord's will, and
prepared not himself, neither did according to his will,
shall be beaten with many stripes; but he that knew
not, and did commit things worthy of stripes,
shall be beaten with few stripes.</hi> And the same is
the case in all other <hi>Advantages</hi> whatsoever:
Whether they be the <hi>internal</hi> assistances of <hi>Grace</hi>
and <hi>Knowledg;</hi> or else the external Blessings of
<hi>Honour, Riches, Authority,</hi> and the like; What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
the <hi>instance</hi> be, whereby it pleases <hi>God</hi> to
enable us to do more good, and make a more
plentiful return of <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Service</hi> to him than
other men, our Account shall be required in
proportion thereunto, and to <hi>whom God has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
much, of him he will ask the more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:60633:8"/>
So that now then to prove that there is a
greater and more extensive <hi>Duty</hi> incumbent
upon such <hi>Persons</hi> as these I am now speaking
of, than upon the <hi>ordinary sort of Christians,</hi>
I shall need only to shew, that <hi>God</hi> has given
them a <hi>greater Capacity of doing Good;</hi> and that
by consequence it must be their own fault, if
they do not make a return, in some measure at
least, proportionable thereunto.</p>
            <p>1. And the <hi>First Advantage</hi> that I shall mention
is that of <hi>Time:</hi> And which however I fear at
present but little regarded by many of us, is yet
without question not only a very valuable thing
in it self, but such a <hi>Blessing</hi> as whatever we do
now, yet the hour is coming when we shall
All begin to put a just Estimate upon it. And
when I consider the great business a <hi>Christian</hi> has
to do in this World, What <hi>Duties</hi> to fulfil? What
<hi>Lusts</hi> and <hi>Passions</hi> to overcome? How many
<hi>Difficulties</hi> and <hi>Temptations</hi> to encounter with?
And then think, How short our <hi>Life</hi> at the best
is? What Accidents may arrive to throw us the
next moment into the <hi>Grave?</hi> How much of
our <hi>time</hi> the <hi>Necessities</hi> of our <hi>Nature</hi> deprive us
of? How much more is stollen from us by the
unavoidable Obligations which the <hi>Business</hi> and
<hi>Conversation,</hi> and too often the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60633:9"/>
               <hi>Impertinence</hi> of the World lay upon us? To
say nothing now of our very <hi>Vanities</hi> and
<hi>Sins;</hi> Which yet I fear in all of us have their
share, and in many of us a very large one
too, to their Service: I must confess there is
nothing wherein I could sooner chuse to envy
the <hi>Happiness,</hi> of those above me, than in this
one <hi>Advantage;</hi> tho' such as Most of them seem
to put the least value of all upon, and suffer
very little occasion to deprive them of.</p>
            <p>And for the Opportunity which such Persons
hereby have the better to improve their <hi>Piety,</hi>
and pay a more constant and regular Attendance
upon the Offices of <hi>Religion;</hi> it is so very evident,
that I shall not need to say any thing in proof of
it. Whilst being freed from those <hi>Necessities</hi> under
which Others labour; and the supplying where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
not only fills up the greatest part of their <hi>time,</hi>
but too much possesses their very <hi>Hearts</hi> and
<hi>Affections</hi> too: Which being forced to converse
so much with the Affairs of <hi>this World,</hi> become
thereby not a little indisposed to entertain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
with the Joys and Blessings of the other;
They are infinitely more at <hi>liberty,</hi> as well as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly
more <hi>engaged</hi> to lift up their <hi>Minds</hi> and
<hi>Desires</hi> to <hi>Heaven,</hi> and to bless that <hi>God</hi> who has
so highly favour'd them above the rest of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60633:9"/>
               <hi>Mankind;</hi> and to spend that <hi>time</hi> in the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
pursuits of the <hi>Glories</hi> of their <hi>future state,</hi>
which they have no need to do in a solicitous
care for the support of their present condition.</p>
            <p>But I must go yet farther: For such Persons
as these have not only more <hi>Time,</hi> &amp; so a greater
<hi>Opportunity,</hi> as well as higher Engagements
to serve <hi>God,</hi> and work out their <hi>Salvation,</hi> than
the ordinary sort of <hi>Christians;</hi> but they have
moreover <hi>better Capacities,</hi> and <hi>larger Abilities</hi> to
do Good, than <hi>other Men.</hi> For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> If we consider them in themselves, and
their personal Qualifications only, there is often
seen <hi>another kind of Spirit</hi> in them, than what
we find in the <hi>common</hi> and <hi>vulgar</hi> race of
Mankind. Whether it be that from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
they are accustomed to a more generous sort
of Life, and bred up with other <hi>Maxims</hi> and
<hi>Notions</hi> of things, than those of an Inferior
Order: Or that it pleases God, to their greater
Opportunities of serving him in all other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects,
to give a better and more excellent Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity
too, to these than to other Men: But this
is plain, that something there is in the very
<hi>Temper</hi> and <hi>Disposition</hi> of those of a higher Rank,
more generous and excellent than what we or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60633:10"/>
meet with in those Below them. Their
<hi>Thoughts</hi> are more <hi>elevated,</hi> their <hi>Desires</hi> more
<hi>noble,</hi> their <hi>Reason</hi> more <hi>improv'd;</hi> And by stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
upon a higher Ground, they see further than
commonly Others do, whose very <hi>Hearts</hi> and
<hi>Minds</hi> are many times as mean and groveling
as their <hi>Fortunes</hi> and their <hi>Employments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to all which if we add, what such Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
for the most part have, the great happiness
of a better and more ingenuous <hi>Education</hi> too:
It cannot be doubted but as this must needs
put a very great difference in all other respects
between those of a <hi>Higher Quality,</hi> and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Crowd of <hi>Mankind;</hi> so does it at the same
time exceedingly better fit them for the <hi>Service</hi>
of <hi>God,</hi> and for more high and extraordinary
Attainments in the ways of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is indeed very sad to reflect how small a <hi>Sense</hi>
too many of the <hi>Meaner sort</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> seem
to have of <hi>Religion.</hi> And one would almost
wonder how persons bred up in a <hi>Church</hi> where
the <hi>Gospel of Christ</hi> is so duly and plainly preach'd
to them; Where the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> are read to
them in their own <hi>Tongue,</hi> and put into their
<hi>Hands</hi> for their own private Use and Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
should nevertheless so many of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60633:10"/>
as ignorant of the first principles of their
<hi>Religion,</hi> as if they had never enjoyed any of these
opportunities of being instructed in it.</p>
            <p>But then there is this to be said for it; That
neither their <hi>Parts</hi> nor their <hi>Education</hi> enable
them, nor will the necessary affairs of their
Lives permit them to have so distinct and
thorough a knowledge of the <hi>Mysteries</hi> of the
<hi>Gospel;</hi> Of the <hi>Love of God,</hi> and the <hi>Merits</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi>
of our <hi>Redeemer;</hi> Of the <hi>Terrors</hi> of the
<hi>final judgment;</hi> And what the <hi>glories</hi> or <hi>miseries</hi>
of another World import; And what mighty
obligations all these things lay upon us to <hi>live
well,</hi> and <hi>to depart from all iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet even among these, we may find many
who are <hi>zealous</hi> for <hi>God's service</hi> beyond what one
could almost have expected from them. That im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
every Opportunity, suffer no Occasion to
slip them that they can possibly steal from
their present employments, to <hi>encrease</hi> their
<hi>knowledge,</hi> and to <hi>exercise</hi> their <hi>piety.</hi> How much
more ought those to whom <hi>God</hi> has given so
many more and better <hi>opportunities</hi> to do this;
Whose <hi>Souls</hi> are more raised, Whose <hi>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings</hi>
more enlarged, Who know the <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries</hi>
of <hi>Christ's Kingdom,</hi> What <hi>promises God</hi> has
made to assist our <hi>piety,</hi> and What <hi>blessings</hi> he has
<hi>prepared</hi> for ever to <hi>reward</hi> it, to be in an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60633:11"/>
manner careful of themselves: And
not suffer these <hi>poor Souls</hi> to rise up in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
against them and condemn them, for that
being so much better <hi>fitted,</hi> to discharge their
<hi>duty,</hi> and having so much more <hi>liberty</hi> to do it
than they; they have nevertheless so grosly
neglected their <hi>Souls,</hi> and taken no care to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed,</hi>
or it may be even to <hi>equal</hi> them in <hi>well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>3dly,</hi> Such persons as these, have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
more <hi>Time,</hi> and a better <hi>capacity,</hi> than those
of a lower degree; but what is yet more, they
have in many respects, a greater <hi>Ability</hi> too of
<hi>Doing Good,</hi> and of promoting the <hi>Interests</hi> of
<hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> And that especially upon
these Three Accounts,</p>
            <p>(<hi>1st</hi>) Of their <hi>Riches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(<hi>2dly</hi>) Of Their <hi>Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the consequence of both these,</p>
            <p>(<hi>3dly</hi>) Of their very <hi>Example.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(<hi>1st</hi>) If we consider them as <hi>Persons</hi> of <hi>larger
Fortunes,</hi> and more <hi>plentiful Estates,</hi> than other
<hi>Men;</hi> How many <hi>Advantages</hi> will this one thing
minister unto them for the better advancing the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60633:11"/>
               <hi>Service</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Interests</hi> of <hi>Christianity?</hi>
What influence will this give them not only
over their own Houses, but over multitudes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad
who some way or other depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
them, and need only their encouragement
to become religious?</p>
            <p>To pass by all other <hi>Benefits,</hi> and offer
but one Instance instead of many. It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be doubted but that the more it has
pleased <hi>God</hi> to dispense to any one of these
things, the more he not only is able, but ought
in duty to lay out in the Exercise of that most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<hi>Vertue</hi> of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Beneficence;</hi> and than
which I know not whether there be any more
<hi>acceptable</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> or more advantageous to our
<hi>Eternal Salvation.</hi> And though there is scarce
any state so mean as to be utterly exempt
from all discharge of it; yet they are the <hi>Rich</hi>
and <hi>Wealthy;</hi> Those to whom <hi>Providence</hi> has been
<hi>free and liberal</hi> no less to set them an <hi>Example</hi> what
they ought to do to others, than to <hi>enable</hi> them
to Do it; whom we are to look upon as the
chief <hi>Stewards</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and dispensers of its
blessings to the <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>needy.</hi> And therefore
S. <hi>Paul,</hi> though he recommends a <hi>Christian Charity</hi>
to all, and passes by none in his Exhortations to
it; yet we may observe that they are such as these
whom he bids <hi>Timothy</hi> in a particular manner call
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60633:12"/>
upon not to be wanting in it:<note place="margin">1 Tim. vi. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Charge them that are
rich in this world</hi>—that <hi>they be rich in good works;</hi>
               <note place="margin">—18.</note>
               <hi>ready to distribute,</hi>
               <note place="margin">—19.</note> 
               <hi>willing to communicate; laying up
in store for themselves a good foundation against the
time to come, that they may lay hold on eternal life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the next instance, (<hi>2dly,</hi>) that of <hi>Power</hi>
and <hi>Authority:</hi> I shall not need to say what a
mighty <hi>Advantage</hi> this also gives to such <hi>persons</hi>
of doing more than ordinary Good, by obliging
Others to become so. And indeed I cannot tell
whether there be any more truly <hi>beneficial;</hi> but
sure I am, a more <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>worthy</hi> Use there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be made of any <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Authority</hi> we may
have committed to us, than for the promoting
the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Salvation</hi> of <hi>Mens Souls,</hi> and
a <hi>publick sense</hi> of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> in the World.
And how those to whom <hi>God</hi> has given so glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
an <hi>Advantage</hi> as this of serving him, in a
more than Ordinary manner, will be able to
excuse themselves at the <hi>last day,</hi> if they do not
especially employ it to this <hi>best</hi> of <hi>Ends,</hi> I must
confess I do not see: Nor can I perswade my
self, that a <hi>private Piety</hi> is all <hi>God</hi> will exact of
such persons, in whose power it was in some
measure to have <hi>reformed the Age;</hi> and if not to
have made it <hi>Good,</hi> yet at least to have kept it
from being openly and scandalously <hi>wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60633:12"/>
Nay, but (<hi>3dly,</hi>) And to close this Point:
Should those whom we are now speaking of
have no such <hi>Advantages</hi> as these, in point either
of <hi>Riches</hi> or <hi>Authority;</hi> which nevertheless I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
but few of them want: yet still the very
influence of a Great Mans <hi>Example</hi> is benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al.
It not only strikes mens <hi>Eyes,</hi> but for the
most part, I know not how, <hi>charms</hi> their very
<hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> into a <hi>Love</hi> first, and then
into an <hi>Imitation</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>There is nothing more ordinary in the
common practise of the World, than for
those of an <hi>Inferiour Rank</hi> to take their
measures from such as are above <hi>Them.</hi> 'Tis
this makes <hi>Sin</hi> its self become reputable, when
countenanced by the <hi>Examples</hi> of the <hi>Great</hi> and
<hi>Honourable:</hi> And the <hi>Commands of God,</hi> and all
the <hi>Terrors</hi> of <hi>Eternity</hi> are too weak to prevail
against the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Vice,</hi> when got into Credit
and Custome among such persons. How much
more might we hope to see <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive
among us, would the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Nobles</hi> of
our <hi>Israel</hi> seriously resolve to set the <hi>Example:</hi>
And make <hi>Vertue</hi> as necessary to a good <hi>Esteem,</hi>
and <hi>Interest,</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> with Men, as it is to
gain the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Blessings</hi> and <hi>Glories</hi>
of <hi>Eternity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:60633:13"/>
And thus have I consider'd very briefly a few
of those <hi>Advantages</hi> which oblige Persons of
Great <hi>Authority,</hi> and <hi>Fortune</hi> and <hi>Quality</hi> in the
World, to a more strict and careful discharge of
their Duty than other men. Let us see,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> What the <hi>Effect</hi> of all this generally
is. And whether these very <hi>things</hi> at the
same time that they thus lay a greater
<hi>Obligation</hi> upon such Persons, are not
apt, considering the evil Inclinations of
corrupt Nature, to be perverted to a
quite contrary purpose; both to <hi>tempt</hi>
them first, and then to <hi>enable</hi> them to be
more highly <hi>Criminal</hi> than other men?</p>
            <p>In speaking to which <hi>Point</hi> I presume no One
will so far misunderstand me, as to think I have
any design to make an <hi>Apology</hi> for the <hi>Sins</hi> of
<hi>Great Men,</hi> by shewing what extraordinary Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
and Temptations their very condition often
times exposes them to. For though where there
is a sincere desire, and an hearty Endeavour to
live Well, this Consideration perhaps may,
and I doubt not shall prevail with <hi>God</hi> to
make greater Allowances for the <hi>slips</hi> and <hi>infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities</hi>
of such persons, than of those who have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60633:13"/>
not so many Difficulties to encounter with; Yet
cannot this be any Excuse for those who by this
means suffer themselves to be utterly drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
from their <hi>Duty,</hi> and engaged in a <hi>Course</hi>
and <hi>Habit</hi> of <hi>Sin:</hi> But on the contrary, will ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate
<hi>their Guilt the more;</hi> for that knowing
their <hi>Danger,</hi> They <hi>nevertheless</hi> neglected to look
to themselves, and to take that due care they
ought to have done to preserve their <hi>Innocence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>1st,</hi> For the <hi>first Advantage,</hi> that of <hi>Time:</hi>
I have before observed, that this is a <hi>Benefit</hi> which
such <hi>persons</hi> seem to put the least <hi>Value</hi> of all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
though one of the most <hi>considerable;</hi> and I
must now add, that being thus neglected by
them, it proves for the most part a Snare and
a Temptation to them: And this is one of the
chiefest Causes of their <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The man who lives by his <hi>Industry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. iii. 19.</note> and <hi>in the
sweat of his brow eats his bread;</hi> he wants indeed
the Opportunity of paying that constant Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
which others may do, upon the Solemn
Exercises of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Devotion.</hi> His Thoughts
are taken up with the Affairs of this Present Life,
how to carry on his business, and supply his
needs. And this hinders his <hi>Soul</hi> from having <hi>its
Conversation</hi> so much <hi>in Heaven;</hi> whilst his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60633:14"/>
after the things of this <hi>lower World</hi> renders
him very often unable, I had almost said unfit to
contemplate the Joys and Glories of the other.</p>
            <p>But though he cannot therefore be so <hi>active</hi> in
the <hi>more immediate Service</hi> of <hi>God Almighty,</hi> yet he
spends his <hi>time</hi> in serving the <hi>Order</hi> of his <hi>Creation.</hi>
He is <hi>Honest</hi> and <hi>Innocent;</hi> And his <hi>Business,</hi> though
it hinders him from rising so high in Religious
Attainments, as those who have Greater Leisure
may; yet at the same time keeps him from their
Temptations too, and from falling into any
<hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Dangerous Irregularities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilst those who have more <hi>Time</hi> for the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge
of their <hi>Duty,</hi> and whose Thoughts
and Considerations have no need to be thus em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd
upon an anxious sollicitude after the <hi>things</hi>
of <hi>this World,</hi> are yet oftentimes far enough from
raising them up to those of a better. They are
<hi>Idle</hi> and <hi>Lazy:</hi> They look upon it to be one part
of their <hi>Birthright,</hi> indeed the great <hi>Priviledge</hi>
and <hi>Characteristick</hi> of their Condition, to have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
to do; And then the <hi>Tempter</hi> never fails to
stand ready for them: And Experience shews
how easie the Transition is, from the <hi>doing</hi> of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi>
or that which is as good as Nothing, to
the <hi>doing Ill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:60633:14"/>
2. For the <hi>Second Benefit,</hi> that of <hi>Quicker
Parts,</hi> and a more <hi>ingenuous Education;</hi> It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
an <hi>Advantage</hi> not so apt to prove a Snare to
Men as the other; but yet such as may be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
to very wicked purposes. And the <hi>Church</hi> has
in all Ages had but too many <hi>Instances</hi> of this
kind, to shew how much more capable Men of
a <hi>brisk Wit,</hi> and a <hi>Comprehensive Knowledge,</hi> are of
being eminently Wicked, and doing a great deal
of Mischief to Religion than other Men.</p>
            <p>What is it but this that has given Birth to most
of those <hi>Satyrs</hi> and <hi>Pasquils,</hi> wherein we find
not only the <hi>Mysteries</hi> of <hi>Christianity,</hi> but even the
<hi>Practice</hi> of all <hi>Religion</hi> exposed to scorn and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cule?
I shall not need to send you back to <hi>Julian</hi>
and <hi>Porphyry,</hi> and the like profess'd Enemies to
the <hi>Christian Faith</hi> for Witnesses of this. <hi>Our</hi> own
<hi>Age,</hi> and even our <hi>own Country,</hi> has bred up those
who at the same time that they have call'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
by the sacred <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> have never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless
bid defiance to his <hi>Gospel;</hi> and esteem'd
it a piece of <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Gallantry</hi> to <hi>burlesque Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
and laugh the greatest <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi>
out of <hi>Countenance.</hi> Who have employ'd their
<hi>Parts</hi> only to find out some new Colours for <hi>Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticism</hi>
and <hi>Infidelity:</hi> To free themselves from the
<hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> now, and to harden them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60633:15"/>
against the <hi>Fears</hi> of <hi>Damnation</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>But <hi>shall not God visit for these things?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. v. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Shall
not his Soul be avenged on such</hi> Wretches <hi>as These?</hi>
Yes, the time is coming when he shall turn all
their Laughter into Mourning, and bring those
<hi>Evils</hi> upon them they now pretend to <hi>scoff</hi> at
the very Name of. And give them a sad and
Eternal Conviction how much they were mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
in their <hi>Notions,</hi> when they thought <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneness</hi>
to be <hi>Sense;</hi> and to make a mock of <hi>Sin</hi>
and <hi>Damnation</hi> the only sure and approved Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of a Man of <hi>Depth</hi> and <hi>Knowledge:</hi> And
that when all is done, what <hi>Job</hi> so long since ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served
is indeed the very Truth;<note place="margin">Job xxviii. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, the Fear
of the LORD that is Wisdom, and to depart from Evil
that is Understanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when thus even Mens <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
those best <hi>Advantages</hi> to <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> may
be turned into a <hi>Snare</hi> and a <hi>Temptation;</hi> much
more,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> Will those other <hi>Benefits</hi> yet remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
of <hi>Riches,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Greatness,</hi> be found
to fall under this Reflection; which are both infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely
more <hi>Easie</hi> to be <hi>abused,</hi> and not at all less
able to minister to their greater <hi>Guilt,</hi> and in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60633:15"/>
consequence of that, to their more certain <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Truth is, whether we consult our <hi>Reason</hi>
or our <hi>Experience;</hi> What Use such persons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
do make of these things; or What, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
a great deal of Care, they will be apt to
make of them; we shall find but too much
cause to conclude what I am now asserting to be
most true: That if on the one hand, <hi>Riches,</hi> and
<hi>Greatness,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Advantages</hi> that both en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
and engage those who have them, to do
much more good in their Generation than other
Men; yet they may, and without very great
heed, will be apt to expose them to many <hi>Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi>
too; And instead of rendering them more
excellently Good, make them only more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly
Wicked, than otherwise they either
would, or could have been. And I shall not
need to spend the time in a solemn proof of that
which our <hi>Saviour</hi> thought to be so very plain, as
to make it almost a <hi>General Rule,</hi> a kind of <hi>Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rism</hi>
in <hi>Christianity;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. xix. 23.</note> 
               <hi>That a rich man shall hardly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
into the Kingdom of God:</hi> and of which, if
you please, we will take the Instance of our
<hi>Text</hi> for the Application; <hi>Son, remember, That
thou in thy Life time receivedst thy good things, and
likewise</hi> Lazarus <hi>Evil things; But now, He is</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted
<hi>and Thou art</hi> Tormented.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:60633:16"/>
And now to conclude this first <hi>Point:</hi> Is it
thus evident, as we have seen, that persons of a
<hi>greater Quality</hi> and <hi>higher Station</hi> in the world, do
lie under much greater Obligations, and have an
higher and more difficult duty to fulfil than other
Men? And have we so much Reason to believe,
that those very <hi>Advantages</hi> which encrease their <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations,</hi>
are at the same time but too apt to
prove their greatest <hi>Lets</hi> and <hi>Hindrances</hi> in the
fulfilling of them? It must then remain, that
either such persons as these must take a great
Care of themselves, or they shall more hardly
be <hi>saved</hi> than those of an inferiour Rank: Whose
<hi>Duty</hi> is more <hi>Easie,</hi> Whose <hi>Temptations</hi> are much
fewer; Who have neither so great a <hi>Task</hi> to <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil,</hi>
nor so many <hi>Difficulties</hi> to encounter with in
the fulfilling of it.</p>
            <p>Which being so, let us Consider,</p>
            <p>II<hi rend="sup">dly,</hi> What influence therefore this Reflection
ought to have upon All of us:</p>
            <p>1. Upon those who are <hi>Great,</hi> and <hi>Rich,</hi>
and <hi>Honourable</hi> in <hi>the World,</hi> to stir them
up to an <hi>Extraordinary Care</hi> of their <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
Happiness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:60633:16"/>
2. Upon <hi>all others;</hi> to engage them to a
<hi>patient acquiescence</hi> even in the <hi>lowest</hi> and
<hi>meanest Condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ist,</hi> That the Consideration of what we have
now been discoursing, ought to stir up all
such persons as these, to a more than <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
Care</hi> of their <hi>future Happiness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a consequence, that if Men believe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
thing at all of <hi>another Life</hi> after this, must be
allow'd to be the natural result of what we have
now been discoursing. For if both the <hi>Duty</hi> of
such <hi>Persons</hi> be greater, and their <hi>Temptations</hi>
stronger than other Mens; If God expects a
more excellent Service from <hi>Them</hi> than from the
<hi>Ordinary sort of Christians,</hi> and yet they are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
exposed to more Lets and Hindrances than
Others usually are, in the fulfilling of it: What
then can we conclude but that it will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly
concern them, as they tender their
Eternal Welfare, to look very carefully to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,
that they neither come short in their <hi>Duty,</hi>
nor are carried away by the strength and force of
their <hi>Temptations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But here therefore a</hi> Difficulty <hi>will arise; For
if the</hi> Case <hi>be such as we have now shown, and
as indeed our</hi> Saviour Christ <hi>himself hath set it out
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60633:17"/>
to us: If such</hi> Persons <hi>as These</hi> shall hardly be
saved; <hi>and again,</hi> It be easier for a Camel to go
through the Eye of a Needle, than for a rich man to
enter into the Kingdom of Heaven: <hi>Will not this
rather serve to</hi> discourage <hi>than to</hi> heighten <hi>their</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
<hi>after it? And lead them sooner to the</hi>
Epicure's <hi>Conclusion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. xv. 32.</note> Let us Eat and Drink, for to
morrow we shall die; <hi>than to the</hi> Christian <hi>Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of</hi> striving to enter in at the Straight Gate;<note place="margin">Luke xiii. 24.</note>
because many will seek to enter in, and shall not be
Able?</p>
            <p>This indeed seems to be a very reasonable <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,</hi>
and which ought to have a fair and satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory
<hi>Answer</hi> made to it. And therefore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ist,</hi> I reply: It is most certain, that were we
to judge of this matter according to the Power
of <hi>Corrupt Nature,</hi> there might be but too much
Cause for such persons to give way to these kind
of Reflections, and look upon their <hi>Condition</hi> as
little better than <hi>Desperate.</hi> And so much our
<hi>Saviour Christ himself</hi> implies,<note place="margin">Mat. xix. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> xix. 26. <hi>With
men this is impossible;</hi> that is to say, Were we to
look no farther than our own <hi>Natural Strength,</hi>
without considering what the <hi>Grace</hi> of God, and
the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>his Holy Spirit</hi> is able to do, we
might well reckon the Difficulties that arise to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60633:17"/>
hinder the <hi>Salvation</hi> of a <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Great</hi> Man to
be insuperable. But <hi>With God, All things are
possible;</hi> He can make that which is thus difficult
of its self, become <hi>Easie</hi> to us, and remove all
just cause not only of <hi>Despair,</hi> but even of
<hi>Complaint</hi> from us, upon that account. And
therefore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> I say, that such <hi>Persons</hi> as these ought
not to be at all <hi>discouraged</hi> from the prospect of
any of these <hi>Difficulties,</hi> because though their <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
be indeed <hi>Greater,</hi> and their <hi>Temptations</hi> more
dangerous than other Mens; yet if they do but
add their earnest Endeavours, <hi>God</hi> will give them
such a <hi>measure of</hi> his <hi>Grace,</hi> as shall be sufficient
to enable them to overcome all their <hi>Difficulties,</hi>
and to fulfil the <hi>duty</hi> that he requires of them. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus
said, With men this is impossible, but with God all
things are possible.</hi> As if He had said, To enable
a <hi>rich man</hi> to despise his <hi>Wealth</hi> in comparison of
his <hi>Duty;</hi> to support him against the <hi>Temptations</hi>
it exposes him to, and to incline him to make
that due use He ought of it: This is indeed a
Work which <hi>Humane Strength</hi> either could not at
all, or not without some extraordinary <hi>difficulty,</hi>
be able to accomplish. But let not this therefore
discourage any of you; for though <hi>Humane
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60633:18"/>
Strength</hi> cannot do it, a <hi>Divine Power</hi> can. And if
there must be a <hi>double portion</hi> of <hi>Gods Spirit</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow'd
upon such persons, or they cannot be <hi>sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:</hi>
Let them do their parts towards it; let them
<hi>pray fervently,</hi> and <hi>labour sincerely</hi> to discharge their
<hi>duty,</hi> and they shall have a <hi>double portion,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
than they shall perish for want of it. <hi>God</hi> will
give them an <hi>Assistance</hi> suitable to their needs,
and their <hi>Grace</hi> shall be as much greater than that
of <hi>Ordinary Christians,</hi> as their <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>difficulties</hi>
are Greater than Theirs.</p>
            <p>Nay, but this is not yet all: For, <hi>3dly, Our
Saviour</hi> not only assures us, that such persons shall
have a <hi>measure of Grace</hi> proportionable to their
<hi>needs,</hi> though that had been sufficient to remove
all grounds of <hi>despair</hi> from their <hi>minds:</hi> But to
encourage them yet more to a <hi>Carefulness</hi> in their
<hi>duty,</hi> he has promised, that if they do thus hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily
labour to fulfil it, they shall not only have a
sufficient <hi>assistance</hi> from <hi>God</hi> to support them now,
but a more glorious Reward of their <hi>Piety</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.
<hi>Ver.</hi> 27. Where when St. <hi>Peter</hi> remark'd
to Him, how they had despised all their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
concerns to <hi>follow</hi> him, and become his <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples;</hi>
               <note place="margin">—27.</note>
               <hi>Behold, we have forsaken all, and follow'd Thee:
What shall we have therefore?</hi> He not only pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
a <hi>Blessing</hi> upon them for their <hi>Piety,</hi>
               <note place="margin">—28.</note> 
               <hi>ver. 28. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60633:18"/>
I say unto you, that ye which have follow'd me in the
regeneration, when the Son of Man shall sit in the
Throne of his Glory, ye also shall sit upon twelve
Thrones, judging the Twelve Tribes of Israel:</hi> But
makes a <hi>General Promise</hi> to all others, that should
not suffer any of those things they now have to
draw them away from his Service, that they
should receive a more exceeding reward for it,
<hi>ver.</hi> 29.<note place="margin">—29.</note> 
               <hi>And every One that hath forsaken,</hi> not only
that has <hi>actually left</hi> them, but hath in his <hi>mind</hi> so
given them up, as to resolve not to value any of
these things in comparison of his duty; <hi>Every one
that hath</hi> thus <hi>forsaken Houses, or Brethren, or Sisters,
or Father, or Mother, or Wife, or Children, or Lands for
my Names sake, shall receive an hundred fold, and shall
inherit Everlasting Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now when this is the <hi>Case;</hi> When such <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi>
as these have not only a Promise, that <hi>God</hi> will
endue them with a more <hi>plentiful portion</hi> of <hi>his Spirit</hi>
than other men, and so render their <hi>duty,</hi> though
so much <hi>Greater</hi> in its <hi>self</hi> than that of others, yet
<hi>to them</hi> as <hi>easie</hi> as our Lesser Engagements are to
us; Who as we have not their Difficulties, so nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
have we the promises of such an Assistance,
as we see they have, to support us: But are more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over
assur'd, that their Piety shall receive a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable
reward; They shall as much <hi>out shine</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:60633:19"/>
in us in the <hi>Firmament</hi> of <hi>Glory</hi> hereafter, as they
now exceed us in their <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Riches,</hi> and in
what is yet more valuable, their <hi>Ability</hi> of doing
<hi>Good:</hi> It must certainly be very much their fault,
and what will doubtless render them exceedingly
more inexcusable than Other Men, if they be not
in some measure as <hi>careful</hi> of <hi>themselves,</hi> and as
<hi>zealous</hi> in their <hi>duty</hi> as all these excellent <hi>Advantages</hi>
engage them to be; and as for other Mens sakes
as well as their own, we ought to beseech them
that they would become.</p>
            <p>But this is not yet all the Use we are to make
of these <hi>Reflections;</hi> Which ought not only to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease</hi>
the <hi>Piety,</hi> and <hi>inflame</hi> the <hi>Zeal</hi> of those above
us: But at the same time,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> To teach us, whom it has pleased <hi>God</hi> to
place in a <hi>lower,</hi> but if we knew our own Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
a <hi>no less blessed Estate;</hi> to be <hi>perfectly content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
with our Condition, though it should chance
to be never so <hi>low</hi> and <hi>mean</hi> in the World.</p>
            <p>For, since this present Life is but a <hi>time</hi> of <hi>Tryal,</hi>
a <hi>State</hi> in which we are not to continue very long,
and then whatever our <hi>portion</hi> here may be, if we
do but manage our selves as we ought in it, we are
sure we shall be exceedingly Happy in the other
World: Wherefore should we <hi>murmur</hi> or <hi>repine</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60633:19"/>
               <hi>Gods Providence?</hi> As if <hi>Eternal Glory</hi> were
not a sufficient recompence for a little trouble and
misery in the pursuit of it.</p>
            <p>I confess, I am not so great a <hi>Sceptick,</hi> as to go
about to perswade you, that there are not <hi>some Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages</hi>
in a plentiful portion of the Good things
of this present World: Or that it is all one, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
a man be <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>despised,</hi> or else <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable</hi>
in it. But yet this I may affirm; that to
him who is accustomed to think, and has a quick
and lively apprehension of the <hi>Happiness</hi> of the
other Life, the wants of this will be very suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.
And while we can lookup to Heaven, and
there see the poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s bosome,
we shall be able to find an <hi>Argument</hi> not only
of Contentedness, but even of Comfort too in the
Reflection; though we should chance for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
to lie, as he once did, at the <hi>rich mans door,</hi> and
<hi>feed on the Crumbs that fall from his Table.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, Oh! that it would please God, we might
all so seriously meditate on these things, that
whatever our <hi>portion</hi> now be, we may have a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
reversion in <hi>Heaven;</hi> where alone <hi>true Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi>
is to be expected by us.</p>
            <p>Consider, I beseech you, the <hi>Time</hi> is coming, it
cannot be far off, when we must all lie down in
the Grave: When the Rich and Mighty shall as
certainly <hi>die</hi> as the <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Miserable;</hi> and carry
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60633:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
none of their <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Grandeur</hi> along with them.
When all <hi>titles</hi> and <hi>distinctions</hi> shall be forgotten;
and the <hi>greatest Monarch</hi> stand with as little Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
before the <hi>Judgment-Seat of Christ,</hi> as the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest
of his <hi>Vassals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what will it then avail any of us, that we
have been, it may be, <hi>Great</hi> or <hi>Honourable</hi> on <hi>Earth,</hi>
if we must be from henceforth <hi>Miserable</hi> to all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity?</p>
            <p>How shall we then begin to envy the <hi>Blessed For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</hi>
of those men, whom we were wont to despise
heretofore? We thought their <hi>Condition</hi> poor and
miserable. We esteem'd them neglected of God, the
scorn of <hi>Men,</hi> and out-cast of the people. But alas!
now we see the difference; And how much more
fortunate a poor Good Man is in the meanest E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state,
than the Sinner in all the heighth of his most
flourishing Condition.</p>
            <p>And may we then every one of us so effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
ponder all these things, that whatever <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral
Blessings</hi> we now enjoy, yet our portion may
not be in them: Nor that be ever objected to us,
which <hi>Abraham</hi> here called the <hi>Rich Man</hi> in our
<hi>Text</hi> to consider;</p>
            <p>Son, remember, that Thou in thy life-time hast recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
thy Good things, and likewise Lazarus Evil things;
but now He is comforted and Thou art tormented.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60633:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
