<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The high court of justice. Or Cromwells new slaughter-house in England With the authoritie that constituted and ordained it, arraigned, convicted, and condemned; for usurpation, treason, tyrannie, theft, and murder. Being the III. part of the Historie of independencie: written by the same author.</title>
            <title>High court of justice</title>
            <author>Walker, Clement, 1595-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-06">2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66820</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W324D</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203985</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825304</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825304</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29684</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A66820)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29684)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2102:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The high court of justice. Or Cromwells new slaughter-house in England With the authoritie that constituted and ordained it, arraigned, convicted, and condemned; for usurpation, treason, tyrannie, theft, and murder. Being the III. part of the Historie of independencie: written by the same author.</title>
                  <title>High court of justice</title>
                  <author>Walker, Clement, 1595-1651.</author>
                  <author>Andrews, Eusebius, d. 1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed anno Dom. 1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Clement Walker.</note>
                  <note>Includes answers of Eusebius Andrews to the High Court of Justice, 1650 (H4r-I4r).</note>
                  <note>Copy filmed has print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29684:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29684:1"/>
            <p>THE
HIGH COVRT
OF
JUSTICE. OR
CROMWELLS
New Slaughter-houſe in
ENGLAND. With the Authoritie that conſtituted and ordained it,
Arraigned, Convicted, and Condemned; for <hi>Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation,
Treaſon, Tyrannie, Theft,</hi> and <hi>Murder.</hi> Being the III. Part of the Hiſtorie of <hi>Independ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie:</hi>
written by the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>Printed Anno Dom. 1651.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29684:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29684:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:29684:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29684:3"/>
            <head>The Hiſtory
of
INDEPENDENCIE.</head>
            <p>THat every thing is kept and maintained by the
ſame wayes and means it was got and obtained;<note place="margin">Vnumquod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatur eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem modo quo fit.</note> is
a rule true both in Philoſophy and Policy. And
therefore Dominion gotten by fraud and force, muſt by
fraud and force be preſerved. Things impiouſly got,
muſt be impiouſly kept. When uſurped Tiranny layes
its foundation in bloud, the whole Superſtruction muſt
be built with Morter tempered with bloud. One Sin
muſt defend and make good another. And hence ariſeth
a Neceſſity upon Ambitious men to flanck and fortify
one Crime with another. But to pleade this Neceſſity,
which they have ſo willfully drawne upon themſelves, in
juſtification of their wicked Courſes, To expect ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
Obedience and an equall Engagement from men
uninterreſſed therein, and to intitle the Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
and unrevealed will of God thereto (in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
to his will revealed and declared in the Scriptures, as
is now a dayes uſed) is to accuſe the Holy Ghoſt of our
Sinnes, and an hipocriſie ſo impudently ſinfull and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,
that I doubt no age but this, (the Dregs and lees
of time) ever gave an example of the like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>TO illuſtrate my firſt Maxime by ſome forreine Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples
(before I lay the Baſtard at our own doors)
Sylla at Rome, by the power of the Sword,</hi> proclaimed
<hi>(or voted)</hi> himſelf Dictator: to make good which uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation
with a Maske of Authority, he compelled the Senate
<hi>(or Parliament)</hi> to approve of all his fore paſſed villanies,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29684:4"/>
               <hi>Murders and illegal Actes,</hi> and to conferre a power upon
him; <hi>To kill whom he pleaſed and confiſcate their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates;
To build and deſtroy Cities; Diſpoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes;</hi>
And exerciſe an Arbitrary, Supreme Authority,
and then (to establiſh himſelfe in his ſelfe-created power)
he poſted up as Rome, and in moſt Cities of Italy, Bills of
Proſcription, or Outlawry, conteining the names of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
as (without any forme of Lawe, or Juſtice) he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
to be ſlain <hi>by his Souldiers.</hi> Theſe Proſcribed men
were (for the most part) ſuch as having ſome Sparkes of
Roman virtue in them, durſt love the Auntient Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
Lawes and Liberties of Rome, and were therefore
thought fit to be weeded out, as Malignants againſt his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations
and Arbitrary courſes. <hi>Yet many meane ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
fellowes, were proſcribed and murdered, partly for
confiſcation of their Eſtates, and partly to gratify the
Malice and hatred of particular friends who (in that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage)
praid in aid of Syllas ſword to ridd them of their
Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this Auguſtus Caeſar at Rome, having by ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror
of Arms made himſelf Conſul, and finding himſelf
not ſtrong enough fingly to ſubjugate his Country, he
called Antonius &amp; Lepidus to joine with him, with whom
entering into confederacy to ſubvert the Fundamental
Government, and uſurpe the Supreme Authority, They
divide that vaſte Empire betweene them, and <hi>paſſed a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree
amongſt themſelves; That they ſhould be called the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umvirate
for Reforming and Reeſtabliſhing the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi>
(well enough before if they had let it alone) <hi>with
Supreme Authority</hi> to give Eſtates and Offices to whom
they thought fit; without asking the adviſe of Senate or
People. <hi>They appointed what Conſuls, Magiſtrates and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29684:4"/>
they pleaſed:</hi> They deſigned rich donatives, and 18
of the chief Cities of Italy to be given to their Souldiers,
if, by their valor, they ſhould obteine victory over Brutus
and Caſſius, <hi>They fixed publike liſtes or Tables of Proſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
naming ſuch Perſons as they expoſed to ſlaughter.</hi> They
Proſcribed at one time 130 Senators, at another time 150
and 2000 Knights. <hi>Whereby the beſt men for underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
conduct Reſolution and Affection being cut off,</hi> the reſt
(terrified by their example) became but Terra Maledicta
(as Chymickes call it) dull liveles Aſhes or clods of earth,
without power or virtue to quicken them, or make them
productive. After ſome revolutions wherein Auguſtus
and Antonius had diſcarded the dull and ſtupid Lepidus,
and (at laſt) Auguſtus had ſubdued Antonius: Auguſtus
uſurped the Title of <hi>Tribune of the people,</hi> whereby his
Perſon became ſacred and inviolable; and (humouring
the irrational Animals) tooke upon him the eſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection
of that Brutiſh heard, the Raſcall multitude, The
Tribunes of the People having bin originally inſtituted
to protect the People. His next ſtep was to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<hi>Perpetual Dictator,</hi> whereby he arrogated to himſelf a
vaſte, unlimited power above all Laws. The Tribune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
was his Buckler, The Dictatorſhip was his Sword.
And laſt of all (for Ornament only) <hi>He having already
the full power of an abſolute Monarch (although he forbore
the Title of (King) becauſe it was hatefull to the People</hi> and
againſt the Laws ever ſince the Regifugium) he took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
him the Title of <hi>Princeps Senatus, or Preſident of the
Senate;</hi> to keep a correſponding power over that great
Counſell or Parliament: And finally uſurped the Title
and Office of <hi>Imperator or Generaliſsimo</hi> of all forces by
Land and Sea, Garriſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29684:5"/>
Philippe King of Spain Lord of the 17 Belgike Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces
by ſeveral Titles, and under ſeveral Limitations,
Priviledges, Exemptions and Fundamentall Laws ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to which he was to govern and they to obey:<note place="margin">In novum regnum vi armiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum redige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, atque a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis Novis le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus doma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere ac gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginare Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berum. Meteran. in anno 1567. Roidan. in anno 1566. Iohn Fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Petit. Thuanus.</note>
Reſolving to ſubvert the Fundamentall Lawes and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
and reduce thoſe 17 Petty Signiories into one
meere, abſolute Monarchy; ſent the Duke D'Alva thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
(a warrior of a reſolute, ſtern nature) Governour
with a powerfull Army. Who taking advantage of ſome
rude commotions formerly raiſed by the Proteſtants in
throwing downe Images and ſacrilegiouſly plundering
Churches, <hi>erected a New Tribunall Criminall, or (to
ſpeake in our modern, uncowth language) A High Court of
Juſtice,</hi> conſiſting of 12 Commiſſioners or Judges pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely
choſen, moſt of them hangers by of the Law, of
meane fortunes, practiſe, birth and breeding; Covetous,
Ambitious and ſlaviſhly addicted to the Spaniſh facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
To theſe was given by ſpecial Commiſſion full
power and Authority to inquire into, and judge (or to hear
and determine) the forepaſſed commotions, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<hi>they ſtiled this Court, Concilium Turbarum, but the
multitude called it Concilium Sanguinis; or the Bloudy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle.</hi>
This Counſel or Inquiſition did ſuperſede and
extingniſh the Authority of all other Courts of Iudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
and make void all Lawes, Conſtitutions, Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
and Priviledges of the Nation, as to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid
commotions, and all other cauſes they pleaſed to call
high Treaſon. <hi>They had no other boundes, nor limit i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
their proceedings, then what they prefixed to themſelves, in
certain Articles.</hi> Some few whereof I will here preſent
unto my Reader, becauſe <hi>they judged of high Treaſon by
thoſe Articles, not by the known Laws of the Land (a thing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29684:5"/>
very obſervable and applicable to my purpoſe) ſo that they
were not onely Judges, Leges dicere: but alſo Law-makers,
Leges dare: as all Judges are who take upon them a lioertie
to obſerve no ſet forms of proceedings:</hi> but at their own
pleaſure.</p>
            <p>1. ARTICLE.<note place="margin">Petitioning againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for the knowne Laws made Treaſon, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he like the Parliament Practiſeth againſt ſuch as Petitioned for Peace by accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And againſt our High Court of Juſtice, Arbitrary Impriſonments and Taxes.</note> All Petitions heretofore tendered
to the States, or Cities Corporate againſt the erecting
of New Epiſcopall Sees; or againſt the Holy Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
or requiring a Moderation of Decrees or Acts of
State or Parliament, are accounted meer Conſpiracies
againſt God and the King.</p>
            <p>2. ARTICLE. All Nobles, Gentry, Judges, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,
and all others who connived at Hereticall
Sermons, plundering of Churches, and delivering ſuch
Petitions as aforeſaid, pretending the neceſſitie of the
times, and did not reſiſt and oppoſe them.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>ART.</hi>
               <note place="margin">We have forfeited our laws by Conqueſt or elſe our Grandees would not paſſe the two Acts for Treaſon 14 May. 17 Iuly 1649. Nor erect the High Court of Iuſtice, and aboliſh out ancient <hi>Laws</hi> and Government. See Pol. 3. Oct. 1650. and the Caſe of the Kingdom ſtated.</note> Whoſoever affirms, That all his Majeſties
Subjects of Belgia have not forfeited their auncient Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,
Immunities and Lawes for Treaſon: and that it is
not lawfull for the King to uſe and handle them for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid
Treaſons as he pleaſeth, <hi>to prevent the like Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
for the time to come, and that the King is not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
thereby from all Oathes, Promiſes, Graunts, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts
and Obligations whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:29684:6"/>
4.<note place="margin">Compare this with the two Acts for New Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. 14. May. 17. July 1549. and the Act 26. March 1650. and Sr. Jo. Gells caſe ſtated.</note> 
               <hi>ART.</hi> They that affirm, This Counſell or high
Court of Juſtice to exerciſe Tiranny in their Proceedings, or
Judgements; and that they are not Supreme and competent
Judges in all cauſes <hi>Criminal and Civil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5.<note place="margin">Our High Court of Iuſt. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes all this. See Sr. J. Gells caſe ſtated, Printed Aug. 1650.</note> ART. <hi>Thoſe that in caſe of Hereſie deny, that all
manner of Informers and witneſſes of whatſoever Degree
and condition they be, are to be credited:</hi> and that upon the
Teſtimony of any two witneſſes, this High Court ought
to proceed to Judgement execution and conflication of
life and goods, <hi>without publiſhing the cauſe or charge, and
without any legal form of Triall.</hi> All theſe are guilty of
high Treaſon againſt God and the King.</p>
            <p>The Rigor, Cruelty and Injuſtice of this New erected Counſell of Bloud, or High Court of Juſtice, inforced the Lowe Countries to revolt and caſt off the King
of Spain.</p>
            <p>LEt us now examine whether in ſome one little
Province or Iſland belonging to that vaſt Roman
Empire; and in ſome meane, petty fellowes, (Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives
of that Iſland) men even at home of obſcure
birth, breeding and fortunes; we can not finde
examples of Ambition, uſurpation and Tiranny, as
high and tranſcendent, as bloudy and deſtructive; as
covetous and greedy; as any of the fore-cited pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents?
And (which is worſt of all) carried on by
thoſe that call themſelves Chriſtians; nay, Saints
(which is more than they vouchſafe to Saint Peter
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29684:6"/>
and the reſt of the Apoſtles, though glorified Saints
in the Church Triumphant) and ſuch as in all their
bloudy, oppreſſing, cheating Deſignes, (promoted
by perjury, Treachery, breach of Faith, Oaths and
publike Declarations) pretend to the ſingular fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,
Providence and will of heaven as confidently, as
if they could ſhew Gods ſpecial commiſſion, to warrant
Uſurpation, Treaſon, Tyranny and Thievery.</p>
            <p>It is not unknown by what Artifices, frauds, falſified
promiſes, Oaths and covenants, <hi>a party of Antimonar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſts,
Schiſmaticks</hi> and Anabaptiſts lurking in the
Parliament <hi>fooled the People to contribute their blood and
money towards the ſubduing of the King (and in him,
of themſelves)</hi> and how by the ſame wayes and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleties
the ſaid Party in the two Houſes (now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined
openly, under the Generall Title of Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents)
engaging and conſpiring with the Officers of
the Army and Souldiery <hi>expelled by armed force ſeven
parts of eight of the Houſe of Commons,</hi> leaving not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
43 or 44 of their own engaged Party ſitting,
men enriched with publike ſpoiles) and <hi>voting under
the power of the Armies commanders, whoſe commands are
now become a law to the ſaid ſitting Members, as their Votes
are become Laws to the Kingdome.</hi> In Obedience to their
ſaid Maſters of the Army, The ſaid Remainder of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
voted down the Houſe of Lords, (though an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrall
and principall Member of the Parliament of
<hi>England,</hi> farr antienter then the Houſe of Commons,
and having a power of Judicature and to adminiſter
an Oath, (which the Houſe of Commons, never had
nor pretended to have, untill this time that they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow
their Bounds and the whole Kingdomes, under
the protection of their Army,) which prerogative of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29684:7"/>
the Houſe of Lords is clearly demonſtrated by the
Houſe of Commons ſtanding bare before them at all
conſerences, as the Grand Enqueſt doth before the
Judges) becauſe they rejected the Ordinance for
Triall of the King. And <hi>now theſe Dregs and Lees of the
Houſe of Commons, take upon them to be a compleat Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi>
To enact and repeal Statutes, to ſubvert the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall
Government, Laws, and Liberties of the
Land: To pull up by the Roots without Legall
proceedingss) every mans private property and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion,
and deſtroy his life. To burden the people
with unſupportable, unheard of, unparliamentary
Taxes, Impoſitions, Exciſe, Freequarter, buying of
New Arms after the Countrey have been diſarmed of
their old Arms three times in one year;<note place="margin">In their Tax Rolls, they uſually ſet in the Margent to every name private notes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction. An M. an N or P. The letter M. ſtands for Malignant; he that is ſo branded, is highly taxed, and his complaints for redreſſe ſlighted, N. ſtands for a Neuter he is more indifferently rated and, upon cauſe ſhewn, may chan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to be relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. The letter P. ſignifies a perfect Parliamentarian. He is ſo favourably taxed, as he bears an inconſiderable part of the burden, and that they may the better confume with Taxes and want, all ſuch as do not concurre with them in the height of their villanies. The pretended Harliament, are now debating to raiſe the Monethly Tax to 240000. lib or to deprive every man of the third part of his Eſtate, both Reall and Perſonall, for maintenance of their immortall warres, and ſhort lived Common-wealth. Beſides Exciſe, Cuſtomes, Tonnage and Poundage, Freequarter, finding Arms and Horſes; and the ſale of Corporation Lands now in agitation. Whileſt our Grandees enrich all the Banks of Chriſtendome with vaſt ſummer raiſed by publick theft and Rapines.</note> Preſſings
and Levying of Souldiers, Sequeſtrations, Plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of Houſes and Horſe, and many other oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
more than the Turk, Ruſſe or Tarter ever
heard of: of all which our <hi>Grandees are free,</hi> and lay
them upon others as partially as they pleaſe, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely
to conſume them. To make Religion but a
ſtalking horſe to their deſignes, and the Miniſters
thereof but hoſtlers, to rub down, curry and dreſſe it
for their riding: to whom they ſend Commands;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29684:7"/>
what they ſhall, and ſhall not preach to the people;
as if preaching were the Ordinance of man, not of
God. At laſt by way of preparative to their machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,
they paſſe theſe following votes.</p>
            <p>1. That all Supreme power is in the people.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>That the Supreme Authority under them, is in the
peoples Repreſentatives, or delegates in Parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</hi>
Meaning themſelves, (you may be ſure) the Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence
and Elixar of the Houſe of Commons, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted
by thoſe learned Chimicks, Doctour <hi>Fairfax,</hi>
Doctour <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and the reſt, graduated at that
degraded Univerſity of <hi>Oxford.</hi> Here note they voted
the Supreme power to be in the people, that they
might uſe thoſe Gulles, as Conduit Pipes or Trunks
to convey the Supreme Authority into themſelves,
the better to enſlave the people: And <hi>tickle them,
whileſt they faſten about their necks the Iron yoke of a
Military Oligarchy, wearing the Mask of a perpetuall Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. That whatſoever the Commons in Parliament ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act,
ſhall have the power and force of an Act of Parliament,
or Law, without the conſent of the Houſe of Lords, or the
Kings Koyal Aſſent: any ſtatute, law, custome or uſage to the
contrary notwithſtandingr (<hi>they might have ſaid all our
ſtatutes, laws, cuſtomes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>notwithſtanding) This one
vote hath more of</hi> Diſſolution <hi>and more of</hi> Vſurpation
<hi>and</hi> Innovation <hi>in it, than any I yet ever read of;</hi> This
is univerſally Arbitrary, and layes the Ax to the root of all
our Lawes, Liberties, Lives and properties at once.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>What theſe men will, they vote:</item>
               <item>What they vote is Law;</item>
               <item>Therefore what they will is Law.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:29684:8"/>
4. That to wage warre or beare Arms againſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative
body of the People or Parliament is high Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.
<hi>By the law all Treaſons are committed againſt the
King, his Crown and Dignity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. <hi>That the King hath taken up Armes againſt this
Parliament, and is therefore guilty of all the blood ſhed
this warre, and ſhould expiate thoſe crimes with his blood.</hi>
If the King were not guilty, theſe men are; And
therefore they paſſed this Vote, <hi>Se defendendo.</hi> Yet
obſerve that herein they became Judges in their own
cauſe; and forejudged his Majeſty before his Trial;
if that may be called a Triall, that was carried on by
men, who were both Accuſers, Proſecuters, parties
and Judges; and had neither law, Preſident, forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
of proceedings, nor any other foundation of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
or Reaſon to warrant them, nor were delegated
by any lawfull Authority?</p>
            <p>Theſe Votes thus paſſed, and by this kinde of men,
were the foundation upon which they built their
great Engine to deſtroy the King and Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
together with the Religion, Laws, Liberties,
Lives and Properties of the people: all condemned in
that deadly ſentence given againſt the King) For
having (as aforeſaid) created (by their own Votes)
themſelves as abſolute a power as they pleaſed and
caſt the people and all they have into that bottomleſſe
Chaos of their Arbitrary Domination; They erect
an Extrajudiciall, unpreſidented High Court of Juſtice
to Try (or rather to condemn without Triall) the
King: Conſiſting of 150. Commiſſioners; Souldiers,
Parliament men, Trades men; the moſt violent, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged
and factious incendiaries of all the Antimonar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall
faction: Amongſt whom were many low
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29684:8"/>
conditioned mechanicks, and Banquerouts, whoſe
fortunes are ſince repaired out of the Kings Eſtate,
and other publick Lands, Goods and Offices; as a
reward for that Royall Bloud they ſpilt.<note place="margin">See Stat. Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 1. Iac. The Oaths of Allege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, Obededi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and all our Law Books.</note> The
King (the Fountain of Law, Juſtice, Mercy, Honour,
War and Peace; The Head of the Parliament and
Supreme Governour over all perſons, and in all
cauſes) thus violently removed; preſently (as if the
Mounds and Banks of the Sea had been overturned)
an impetuous innundation of bloudy, thieviſh Tyranny
and Oppreſſion brake in udon us: So that no man can
call his life, liberty, houſe, lands, goods or any
other his Rights or Fraunchiſes his own, longer than
the gratious aſpect of ſome of our Graundees, ſhine
favourably upon him.</p>
            <p>In the next place: contrary to their own Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
of the 9. Feb. and 17. March 1648. Wherein
they promiſe that in all things concerning the lives,
liberties, and properties of the people, they will obſerve
the known laws of the Land, with all things incident
therto) <hi>They paſſe misbegotten Acts of Parliament one of
the</hi> 14.<note place="margin">This Stat. 25. Ed. III. e. 2. S. Johns againſt Strafford calls the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the people. And the Stat. 1. Hen 4. chap. 10. Ed. VI. Chap. 12. 1. Mariae J. ratify and highly commend.</note> 
               <hi>of May, another of the 17. of July 1649. whereby</hi>) in
derogation and annihilation of that excellent Stat.
25. Ed. III. Chap. 2. Aſcertaining Treaſons and
reducing them to a ſmall number, And leaving
nothing to the interpretation of the Judges, that the
people might not be enſnared) <hi>they exceeding by mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying
Treaſons, bringing bare words as wel as deeds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
the compaſſe of that offence: and making many duties to
which the laws of God and the land, the Proteſtation and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
the oaths of allegeance, obedience and Supremacy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige
us, to be high Treaſon, &amp; theſe new acts of Treaſon pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
in obſcure, ambiguous terms purpoſely to leave a lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29684:9"/>
of Interpretation in (their own creatures) the Judges;
that the People may be enſnared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King thus taken out of their way. They
paſſe dretended Hcts.<note place="margin">They have converted our ancient Monarchy into a Free-State; and tell us they are the ſtrate. They tell us they have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty upon the People: but they and their petty fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction onely are the People. All the reſt of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilated, and redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that theſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows may become all things: Meere ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving onely to make them of more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. And this groſſe fallacy muſt not be diſputed againſt, leaſt their New Acts of Parliament call it Treaſon.</note> 1. To <hi>Diſinherit his children.</hi>
2. <hi>To aboliſh Kingly Government for ever. 3. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
our ancient well tempered Monarchy into that</hi>
(which they call a <hi>Common-wealth, or Free-State;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
nothing be therein free, but their luſts: nor
hath it any form or face of Civil and juſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;
Wherein a confuſed Multitude rule by
their own Wills, without Law: and for their own
benefit; no conſideration being had of the good
and happineſſe of the People in generall. 4. <hi>They
Conſtitute a Senate or Councel of State of 40. men (amongſt</hi>
which ſome Trades-men, Souldiers, illiterate
Lawyers, Parliament Members, men already engaged
over head and ears in ſinne, therefore to be confided
in) to theſe or any nine of theſe they entruſt the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration
of this Utopian Common-wealth, and
theſe they would have us believe (without telling us
ſo) are the Keepers (or Gaolers) of the Liberties of
England.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being but Introductions to the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation
of theſe Kinglings: and having been already
ſhewed to the world by many pens. I content my
ſelf to give a curſory view of them: and haſt to my
intended task, to ſhew that this Uſurped power, is
kept and adminiſtred, by as wicked and violent poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,
as it was gotten by.</p>
            <p>The firſt endeavour of all Tyrannicall Uſurpers is.
To leſſen the number of their Enemies; either by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29684:9"/>
flattering and deceiving them: or by violently extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating
and rooting them out. And ſuch have been the
attempts of our new <hi>Cromwellian</hi> Statiſts, ever ſince
(without any calling from God or the people) they
toook upon them the Supreme Authority of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
ſubverted our well mixed Monarchy and created
themſelves a Free-State.</p>
            <p>1.<note place="margin">1. A Colluſive Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</note> They endeavoured to ſweeten and allure to act
with them, as many of the Secured and Secluded
Members, Miniſters and other Phesbyterians, as they
could, to the end that <hi>ex poſt facto</hi> being guilty of
their Sinnes, they might be engaged in one common
defence, and go halfs with them in their ignominy
and puniſhment, though not in their power, profit
and preferments: in which the Godly will admit no
Rivalls, but (like their Patron the Devil) cry all's
mine. But this Deſign failed for the moſt part.</p>
            <p>2.<note place="margin">2. An inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Maſſacre</note> Their ſecond Endevour was how to dimmiſh the
number of their Oppoſites, Royaliſts and Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
by a Maſſacre, for which purpoſe many Dark Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorns
and Ponyards were provided laſt Winter,
1649. But ſame prevented this plot: which coming
to be the Common rumour of the Town; put them in
mind of the danger, infamy and hatred, that would
overwhelm them. So this was laid aſide.</p>
            <p>At laſt they invented two other Engins, no leſſe bloudy
then, and as effectuall as a Maſſacre.</p>
            <p>3.<note place="margin">3. The En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement.</note> The Engagement is the firſt of theſe two Gins)
which all perſons are enjoyned to ſubſcribe by
their Act <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Jan. 1649. <hi>To be true to the Common-wealth
of</hi> England, <hi>as it is now eſtabliſhed, without a King
or Houſe of Peeres.</hi> And this is obtruded under
no leſſe penalty, then; To be totally deprived of all
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29684:10"/>
Benefit of Law whatſoever. Now the Laws of the
Land being the onely Conſervators of our lives, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
and Eſtates (without which lawes all men have
a like property to all things, and the ſtrongeſt have
right to all is poſſeſt by the weaker; ſince the Law
onely diſtinguiſheth <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi>) what is this but
to expoſe the Liberties of the Non-Engagers to falſe
Impriſonments; our Eſtates to rapine, ſpoil, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice:
and our Lives aud Perſons to wounds and
Murders, at the will and pleaſure of ſuch as will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage
with our Uſurpers: but eſpecially at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
of their own Souldiers: to whom (I conceive)
this Outlawry was intended as an Alarm or Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to plunder and maſſacre the Non-engagers, and
to pay themſelves their Arrears of which theſe
Parliament men have couſened them) out of their
Eſtates, and though the Souldiers were not ſo wicked
as their Maſters, Yet we daily ſee many good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies
in England deſpoiled of their Eſtates, for
want of protection of the laws, brought to miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
beggery, rather than they will wrong their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
by ſubſcribing this damnable Engagement
contrary to the Proteſtation and Covenant impoſed
by this Parliament contrary to the known law
of this land, which this Parliament hath declared to
obſerve and keep in all things concerning the lives,
liberties and properties of the people, with all things
incident thereto; contrary to this Parliaments rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated
votes, that they would not change the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
Government, by a King, Lords and Commons.
And contrary to the Oathes of Allegeance, Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
and Supremacy: whereby (and by the Stat.
of Recognition 1. Jac.) our <hi>Allegeance</hi> is tied onely
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29684:10"/>
to the <hi>King,</hi> his <hi>Heires</hi> and <hi>Lawfull Succeſſers:</hi> from
which no power on earth can abſolve us; and ſo much
we atteſt in the Oath of Supremacy. <hi>Politicus</hi> (Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter
to our new State-Puppet play) Numb. 19. from
Sept. 19. to Sept. 26. out of the dictates of his Maſters
tells us, that in Anſwer to the Kings Act of oblivion
granted, the Parliament intends to paſſe an Act of
Generall pardon; for which they expect in future a
Generall obedience &amp; ſubmiſſion to the government:
(you ſee though they will not be the Kings ſubjects,
they will be his Apes) and in the beginning of the ſaid
Pamphlet, <hi>Politicus</hi> ſaith; That Protection implies o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,
otherwiſe they may be handled as publike
Enemies and outlawes, and ought to be deſtroyed as
Traitors. Here you have the end to which this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
pardon is intended: it is but a ſhooing-horn to
draw on the utmoſt penalty upon Non-engagers, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
by the ſaid pretended Act 2. Ian. 1649. to
weed them out of this good Land, that the Saints on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
may enjoy the earth and the fullneſs thereof; to
which purpoſe all their new coyned Acts and Lawes
are directed. The Scripture points forth theſe kind of
men, when it ſaith, <hi>The Mercies of the wicked are
cruell.</hi> The ſum of all is; If we will not acknowledge
Allegeance to theſe Muſh-romes, we ſhall be Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
without Alleageance (a Treaſon never yet heard
of in any Law) If we will acknowledge Allegeance,
we put our ſelves in a capacity to be Traitors, when
they ſhall pleaſe to make us ſuch. But let them
know; That we are all Engliſhmen, Free-born
alike, under the Protection of an antient, legall
Monarchy, to which we owe Alleageance: and how
we come to forfeit that legall Protection, our ſetled,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29684:11"/>
laws and Government; and be ſubjected to a New,
unknowne Protection obtruded upon us by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
of upſtarts (Muſhromes of Majeſty, ſo meane
in birth and breeding (for the moſt part) that the
place of a Conſtable equalls the higheſt of their edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation)
impoſing what Lawes and conditions upon
us they pleaſe; I would be glad to heare without
being hindered by Guns, Drums, High Courts of
Iuſtice and other Inſtruments of violence &amp; Murder.
But the greateſt Miſtery in this cheat is, That our
Self-created Supremiſts, having voted the originall
power to be in the people, and but a derivative Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
to be in themſelves as the Repreſentative of
the people, ſhould notwithſtanding ſo yoake their
Soveraigne Lord the people, and make them pay Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeance
to their own Delegates (the 8. part of
a Houſe of Commons) under the penalty (unleſs
they ſubſcribe as the far major part have not) of
outlawing and depriving all the people of this Land
of all benefit of the Lawes they were born to; and
conſequently of annihilating and making them no
longer a Nation or people. As if they were meer
Salvages, newly conquered, collected and formed
into a Politike body or Commonwealth, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed
with Laws newly invented by theſe Novice
Statiſts. But the unlawfullneſs of the ſaid Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
with the Injuſtice of the Self-created power that
obtrudeth it, hath been handled by many good pens:
eſpecially by the <hi>Cheſhire</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> Miniſters in
their Plea for Non-Subcribers. Therfore I paſſe on
to my principall ſcope; <hi>The ſecond Engine appointed
to root out all ſuch as are of a different Party, The High
Court of Iuſtice.</hi> A formidable Monſter, upon which
no pen (that I know of) hath yet adventured.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:29684:11"/>
4.<note place="margin">4. The High Court of Iuſtice.</note> In treating of the High Court of Iuſtice, I muſt
conſider. 1. <hi>By what Perſons and Authority</hi> this new
erected, unpreſidented Court is conſtituted? 2. <hi>Of
what Perſons it is constituted? 3. The way and manner of
their proceedings?</hi> What formalities and Lawes they
obſerve therein? How ſutable to the known Laws of
the Land, and the Parliaments Declarations, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations
and Covenant they are? 4. <hi>To what end
this Court is conſtituted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>The Perſons conſtituting</hi> this extrajudiciall Court
are the preſent, pretended Parliament, conſiſting of
40 or 50 thriving Commons only, who conſpired
with <hi>Cromwell</hi> and the Army to expell 7. parts of 8.
of their follow-Members, without any cauſe ſhowne,
aboliſhed the Houſe of Peers, erected this High
Court of Iuſtice (<hi>in nature of a Court Martiall</hi>) to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the King, aboliſhed Kingly Government: Turned
it into a thing they call a <hi>Free-State;</hi> diſinherited the
Royall Family, and <hi>now uſurp to themſelves (without
any calling from God or the People) more then a Regall,
Legall or Parliamentary Authority,</hi> wherewith they
have ſubverted the Fundamentall Government, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
Laws, Liberties and Property of the Nation,
and envaſſalliſed &amp; enſlaved them to their Arbitrary
Domination; the Authority by which they erect this
extrajudiciall Court is, <hi>The uſurped, Legiſlative power:</hi>
By colour of which they paſſed an Act dated 26.
March 1650. eſtabliſhing the ſaid High Court of
Iuſtice. <hi>Yet their own creature Maſter</hi> St. Johns, <hi>in his
Argument againſt the E. of Strafford,</hi> (in a Book called
Speeches and Paſſages of this great &amp; happy Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
printed by William <hi>Cook</hi> 1641. pag. 24.) ſaith,
<hi>The Parliament is the Repreſentative of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29684:12"/>
wherin the King as head, The Lords as the more No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
&amp; the Commons the other Members, are knit together
as one body Politick; The Lawes are the Arteries &amp; Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments
that hold the body together.</hi> (And a little after)
<hi>Its Treaſon to embeſell a Judiciall Record, Strafford ſwept
them all away. Its Treaſon to counterfeit a</hi> 20<hi rend="sup">s</hi> 
               <hi>peece;</hi> here
is a counterfeiting of Law (ſo in theſe counterfeit
new Acts) we can call neither the counterfeit nor
true one our own. <hi>Its Treaſon to counterfeit the great
Seale for an acre of Land,</hi> no property hereby is left to
any Land at all (no more is there by the votes &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe
of our new Supremiſts (thus far Maſter St. Iohns.
<hi>But that the Parliament doth neceſſarily conſiſt of the King
&amp; the two Houſes aſſembled by his Writ, &amp; can paſſe no
Act, without their joint conſent:</hi> See the Praeambles of all
our Statutes, all our Parliament Records, all our Law
Books: <hi>Modus tenendi Parliamentum.</hi> Hackwells man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of paſſing Bills. Sr. Tho. Smith <hi>de Repub. Anglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.
Cambdeni Britannia.</hi> All our Hiſtorians, Polititi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
and the uninterrupted practiſe of all Ages. That
it is now, lately otherwiſe practiſed; is not by any
Law of the Land, but by the will of lawleſſe power
and Rebellion, that hath cancelled all our Lawes,
Liberties and Properties, and ſubverted our Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall
Government, and disfranchiſed and diſinhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited
the whole Nation. Yet Maſter St. Iohns in his
ſaid Argument againſt Strafford p. 38. was then of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion:
<hi>That to ſubvert the Lawes and Government, and
make a Kingdom no Kingdom, was Treaſon at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Law.</hi> This Act 26. Mar. 1650, is a new modelled
Commiſſion of Oier and Terminer: And all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of the Land, are by the conſequence thereof dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franchiſed
and proſcribed. The illegality and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29684:12"/>
thereof, they have introduced, who in this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
ſo zealouſly complained againſt the Court
of the Preſident &amp; Counſel of York or of the North,
as an intolerable grievance (notwithſtanding it had
been of as long continuance as from 31. H. 8,) as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
by a worthy <hi>Members ſpeech or Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
it</hi> (in the ſaid Book of Speeches &amp; Paſſages p.
409. <hi>made by order of the Houſe of Commons</hi> in April
1649. I find not one Exception there made againſt
the Court of York, to which this upſtart high Court
is not more liable then it. 1. The Commiſſioners of
this high Court are not appointed <hi>to inquire, per Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum
proborum</hi> &amp; <hi>legalium hominum,</hi> that is, by
Iuries; as by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and above 30. Statutes
confirming it, all Commiſſions ought to run. 2. They
are not appointed (nor ſworn) <hi>to heare &amp; determine, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundùm
Leges Angliae,</hi> according to the known Lawes
(as they ought to be) but according to certain Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
&amp; powers given in the ſaid Act 26. March 1650.
3. The ſaid Act 26. March leaves a dangerous lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
to the interpretation and diſcretion of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners
(contrary to what is done in the Act 25.
<hi>Ed.</hi> 3. chap. 2.) namely; It hath <hi>one Clauſe enabling
them to inflict upon Offenders ſuch puniſhment, either by
death or otherwiſe corporally, as the ſaid Commiſſioners,
or the major part of them preſent ſhall judge to apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine
to Justice.</hi> This leaves it in the breſts of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners,
(without any Law or rule to walk by) to
inflict what torments and ignominious puniſhments
they pleaſe, although not uſed in our Nation; and <hi>arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
corporall paines are proper to ſlaves; not to Subjects.</hi>
Here (after the loſſe of all but their bodies) the people
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29684:13"/>
may ſee their bodies ſubject to the lawleſs wills of
our Grandees. And by another clauſe, this Act im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powreth
the Commiſſioners, <hi>To examine witneſſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
oath, or otherwiſe, if need be.</hi> This word (<hi>or otherwiſe,</hi>
&amp;c.) gives them power to examine witneſſes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
oath (if they cannot procure witneſſes ſo far the
ſons of Belial, and cauteriſed in conſcience as to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture
upon an oath) even in caſe of life and death,
and mutilation of members; contrary to the current
of all our Lawes, and practice of all our Courts of
Law, and of all Nations. See Stat. 1. Ed. VI. chap.
12. 5 Ed. VI. chap. 11. Cooks 3. Inſt. pag. 24, 25, 26.
Deut. 17. 6. <hi>Ex ore duorum vel trium peribit qui-occide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi>
Deut. 17. 6. Matth. 18. 16. John 18. 23. 2 Cor. 13. 1.
Heb. 10. 28. This is the moſt arbitrary &amp; deſtroying
liberty that ever was given to Iudges; And ſuch as
none but profeſſed theeves and murderers will accept
or make uſe of. The Scripture ſaith, <hi>An oath is the end
of controverſy between man &amp; man. How then can they end
and determine a controverſy without oath?</hi> But the end
of all controverſies before this Butcher-row of Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
is cutting of throats, and confiſcation of eſtates.
And by the ſame clauſe of the ſaid Act (<hi>To examine
witneſſes) They may, and (I heare) do examine witneſſes
clandeſtinely,</hi> and proceed upon bare Depoſitions read
in Court, whereas they ought to produce the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
face to face in open Court, and there ſweare
them,<note place="margin">See Stat. 5. Ed. VI. chap. 11. &amp; Cookes. 3. Inſt. pag. 26.</note> that the Party accuſed may interrogate them,
and examine the circumſtances, and whether they
contradict themſelves, or one another, for cleering the
Evidence? And whether they be lawfull witneſſes or
no? Nay (I hear) they do privately ſuborn and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage
witneſſes without oath. And then produce them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29684:13"/>
to ſwear what they have formerly related only: and
if they ſcruple at an oath, puniſh them for miſinform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the State. 4. That I may make ſome more uſe of
the aforeſaid Members words, <hi>Whether the King, or a
prevailing Party uſurping his Kingly power, may canton
out a part of his Kingdom) or cull &amp; mark out for ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
ſome principall men, &amp; deny them the benefit of law,
in order thereto, as theſe Judges do) to be tried by ſpeciall
Commiſſion, ſince the whole Kingdom is under the known
lawes &amp; Courts eſtabliſhed at Weſtminſter?</hi> It ſhould
ſeem by this Parliaments eager complaint againſt the
ſpeciall Commiſſion of York, this Parliament hath
determined this queſtion in the negative allready,
(whatſoever their preſent practiſe to carry on their
Deſigne is) See Stat. 17. Car: 1. againſt the Star
Chamber. To what purpoſe ſerve thoſe Statutes, of
<hi>Magna Charta</hi> and the Petition of Right, if men may
be fined and impriſoned (nay murdered) without Law
according to the diſcretion of Commiſſioners? This
diſcretion is the quick-ſand that hath ſwallowed our
Properties and Liberties, (but is now ready to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
our carkaſſes:) Thus far that Gentleman, Whoſe
words then carried the Parliamentary ſtamp upon
them. Let me add ſome more exceptions of my own
againſt this high Court of Injuſtice. 5. <hi>Soldiers of the
Army are appointed by the Act 26. March, to be aſſiſtant
to the Commiſſioners,</hi> contrary to the peaceable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
of the Law, which never makes uſe of any
but civill Magiſtrates and Officers of the Law. See
Stat. 7. <hi>Ed.</hi> l. 2. <hi>Ed.</hi> III. chap. 3. 7. R. II. chap. 13. 6. And
<hi>contrary to the old oath which all Judges ought to take, in
theſe words.</hi> You ſhall ſweare <hi>well</hi> &amp; <hi>lawfully to ſerve
the King</hi> &amp; <hi>people,</hi> in the Office of Juſtice, &amp;c. And <hi>that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29684:14"/>
to what eſtate &amp; condition they be, come before you in the
Seſſions with force and armes, againſt the peace, againſt
the Statute thereof made, to diſturbe the Execution of the
Common Lawes, or to menace the people, that you arreſt
their bodies, &amp;c.</hi> Stat. 18. Ed. III. in An. Dom. 1344. p.
144. Poultons Book of Stat. at large. <hi>But the oath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
for theſe Commiſſioners to take, is not penned in
termes of Indifferency. Nor doth any waies oblige them to
the people.</hi> 26. Mar. 1550. (viz:) <hi>You ſhall ſweare well and
truly according to the beſt of your skill and knowledge, to
execute the ſeverall powers given you by this Act,</hi> (not
well &amp; lawfully to ſerve the people.) Beſides they
ſwear to execute the ſeverall powers given, (<hi>not to do
Juſtice according to the Lawes.</hi>) Now the Lawes are the
only Rules of Iuſtice, by which we diſtinguiſh
crooked from ſtreight, true from falſe, right from
wrong. This is not the work theſe Iudges are packed
for, but to <hi>execute</hi> Acts of <hi>power</hi> and <hi>will.</hi> But powers
are often uſurped, tyrannicall, illegall and unjuſt: So
are theſe. <hi>Injuria eſt quod contra legem fit.</hi> 7. How can the
Houſe of Commons (if it were full and free) conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
a new unpreſidented Court of Iuſtice, nominate
and ordain Iudges, and enable them to adminiſter
Oaths, having never had, nor ſo much as pretended
to have, any power to judge, to nominate Iudges,
or to adminiſter an oath; as having never been more
then the grand Enqueſt of the Kingdom, humbly to
preſent to His Majeſty in a petitionary way, the
grievances of the people? <hi>Nemo dat, quod non habet.</hi>
8. Suppoſe the Houſe of Commons had power of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature,
delegated to them from the people as their
Repreſentative? <hi>Delegatinon poſſunt ſubstituere Delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos,
et Pro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtatam ſibi concreditam, in alios transferre.</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:29684:14"/>
legates can not make ſubdelegates, and transfer their
truſt to others. See Col. <hi>Andrews</hi> 3 Anſwers given in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
this High Court, for his defence. Printed at the
later end hereof.</p>
            <p>2. My Second conſideration will be, <hi>Of what Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
delegated or commiſſioned, this Court Conſiſteth?</hi>
The pretended Act 26. <hi>March</hi> 1650. names 25. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners,
all which (for their better credit) it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteth
Eſquires, amongſt whom are four or five, that
have profeſſed the Law (as far as wearing a lawyers
gown come too) but were better known by their lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
then by their law; untill by adhearing to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing
Schiſmaticks, in ſubverting our laws, they
ſeem to be eminent lawyers. Of <hi>Keeble</hi> ſee the Tryall
of Lieutenant Col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> firſt and ſecond part.
<hi>Steel</hi> cited expired Statutes at <hi>Wincheſter</hi> againſt Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<hi>Burley.</hi> The reſt are (for the moſt part) poore ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
Tradeſmen, ſome ſo young they are but lately
out of their Apprentiſhips, others Broken Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
that have compounded with their Creditors,
ſome of vilde and baſe Profeſſions; One or two
of thoſe Wolviſh Saints (I hear) have with ſome
difficulty eſcaped the gallows for Manſlaying: <hi>William
Wibearde</hi> Eſquire is a Rope-ſeller: this employment
may happily help him to the Hangmans cuſtome.
<hi>William Pemoier</hi> Eſquire was heretofore an Ape-car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier,
Cherry-lickom or Mountredinctido. <hi>Cook</hi> a Vint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
at the Bear at the Bridge foot, he keeps a vaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
ſchoole for our ſanctified Grandees, and their
Ladyes of the Game. If the Houſe of Commons had
power to make Judges (which I have diſproved) yet,
<hi>Ex quovis ligno non fit Mercurius.</hi> They muſt name ſuch
Perſons as may be competent Judges. And therefore
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29684:15"/>
muſt not chooſe. 1. Ignorant men. 2. Nor ſuch
as the Law cals, <hi>Viles Perſonas,</hi> men baſe or contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible
for their Perſons or Sordide callings; Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks
of the loweſt rank. 3. Perſons of Scandalous
life and converſations. 4. Not Banquerouts and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digent
Perſons. <hi>Neceſſitas cogit ad turpia.</hi> 5. Not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
and preingaged Perſons, choſen to ſuppreſſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
party. As theſe Commiſſioners are engaged to
the preſent power to ſuppreſſe all others. 6. Nor <hi>ſuch
as Schiſmatically or Heretically affected, are ſeaſoned with
ſuch Doctrines and Principles, as neither agree with the
Duties of a good Chriſtian, a good Commonwealths man, nor
a good Judge,</hi> Which two laſt Objections not onely
theſe Commiſſioners, but the pretended Parliament
that commiſſioned them are apparently guilty of, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
all of the Independent faction, conſpiring to robb
and root out all other Parties: Royalliſts, Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
and Levellors: For which purpoſe this New Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall
or Inquiſition is ſet up. <hi>Independency being a meer
complication and Syncretiſmus, or rather a Sink and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Sewer of all Errours, Hereſies, Blaſphemies and Schiſms
(though they peeviſhly differ in ſome inconſiderable Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents)
yet having one Generall End or ſcope at which they
all chiefly aym</hi> (viz.) <hi>power, preferment, profit, and the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
of the Truth and Magiſtracy, they have likewiſe
ſome common principles to ſoader them together, which they
uſe as a Means conducing to that generall End.</hi> Some few
whereof I will here ſet down for my Readers ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
1. <hi>To tollerate no King nor Magiſtrate Superiour to
themſelves.</hi> As being a Tyranny or Bondage over the
Chriſtian Liberty of the Saints and Kingdom of Chriſt.
Becauſe they know no Chriſtian Magiſtrate can tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate
them, being (by the <hi>Genius</hi> of their Sect)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29684:15"/>
enemies to all Civill Societies, whether Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,
Ariſtocraticall, Democraticall or Mixed; as
the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> was, before theſe men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed
it. Beſides their common Doctrine, <hi>That they are
appointed to break the powers of the Earth to pieces, To le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell
the hills and fill up the valleies, That they are called,
To bruiſe the Nations with a rod of Iron, and break them
in pieces like a Potters veſſell:</hi> Which they have done in
<hi>England,</hi> and threaten the like in <hi>France, Germany, &amp;c.</hi>
whereof their pulpits and diſcourſes ſound. Obſerve
<hi>their Practiſes in the Low Countries.</hi> Where having by
their ſpies and Emiſſaries, found out ſome Burgers of
the ſame humour with themſelves; They propagated
their Doctrine ſo far; as to endeavour To ſtrike the
Ariſtocraticall Members out of that Commonwealth
by abetting ſome of the States Provinciall to leſſen
(and ſo to aboliſh by degree) The Lords States
Generall (the Optimates of that State) To ruine
the Prince of Orange, to whoſe Family they owe
their Liberty; <hi>To diſſolve the Generall Vnion of the
ſaid Vnited Provinces, and ſo take in pieces the whole
Frame of that Republike.</hi> To ſay nothing of their Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies
in fighting and killing their men, becauſe the
Belgike Lion will not ſtrike ſaile to their Croſſe and
Harp; and in blowing up the Antelope in <hi>Helver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſluice:</hi>
Which ſhews what good Neighbours <hi>Holland,</hi>
and other parts, are like to have of the New State of
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> (when they have made themſelves
intirely by the purchaſe of <hi>Scotland</hi>) that is born (like
our Engliſh <hi>Richard</hi> the 3.) with Teeth in its head;
and ſnappeth at its Neighbours before it be out of
its Swadling clouts. This is the cauſe that <hi>Cromwell,</hi>
before he ſet ſaile for <hi>Ireland,</hi> cauſed his Journey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29684:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29684:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:29684:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29684:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29684:18"/>
the pretended Parliament, To paſſe an Act for tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration
of all Errors, Hereſies and Schiſms, under the
Notion of liberty of Conſcience, and Eaſe for tender
Conſciences. 2. Their ſecond principle is, <hi>That the good
things of this World belong only to the Saints (that is, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves)
all others being uſurpers thereof: and therefore they
may rob, plunder, ſequeſter, extort, cheat and confiſcate (by
illegall Laws of their own making, by extrajudiciall Courts
and partiall Judges of their own conſtituting) other mens
Goods and Eſtates; upon as good Title as the Jews ſpoiled
the Aegyptians;</hi> or expelled the Canaanites. 3. Their
third principle. <hi>That the Spirit (which ſanctifies and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminates
theſe men) in every particular man blows when
and where it will, ſometimes this way, ſometimes that way,
often contrary wayes: And therefore they can make no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
of any certain Rule of Doctrine or Diſcipline, becauſe
they know not which way the Spirit will inſpire.</hi> For this
reaſon they are ſtill pulling down old and ſetting up
new Doctrines, as the Nomades do Cottages, only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
in unconſtancy. They profeſſe their conſciences
are the Rule and Symbol both of their Faith and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
by this Leaden <hi>Lesbian</hi> Rule they interpret, and
to this they conform the Scriptures; not their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
to the Scriptures; ſetting the Sunne Diall by
the clock; not the clock by the Sunne Diall. That e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
man muſt pray according to the Dictates of his
private Spirit; They reject the Lords Prayer, for fear
of quenching the Spirit. <hi>When they break their Faith, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles,
Promiſes, Declarations and Covenants, they alleage,
the Spirit is the Author thereof.</hi> When <hi>Cromwell</hi> (contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
to his Vows and Proteſtations made to the King)
kept him cloſe priſoner in <hi>Carisbrook</hi> Caſtle; He af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<hi>the Spirit would not let him keep his word.</hi> When,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29684:18"/>
contrary to the Publike Faith, they Murdered Him:
they pretended: <hi>They could not reſiſt the Motions of the
Spirit. Sua cuique Deus ſit dira libido.</hi> This Hobgoblin
ſerves all turns. 4. Their fourth principle is. <hi>That they
may commit any Sinne, and retain their Sanctity in the very
act of ſinning: For what is ſinfull in other men, is not ſo
in the Saints; who may commit any crime againſt the Law
of God, and yet it cannot be imputed to them for Sinne;</hi>
Becauſe they know in their Conſciences what they do.
So tender and delicate are their Conſciences; That
<hi>they are capable of any Offence againſt their Neighbor, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
breach of Juſtice or Charity.</hi> A righteous man is a law
to himſelf. 5. Their fifth principle is. <hi>That 7. make a
Church: although men women and children, and that this
Church is Independent upon any other.</hi> The Anabaptiſts
(though they neither profeſs to follow <hi>Paul</hi> nor <hi>Cephas</hi>)
yet declare themſelves to be ſome of <hi>Cromwels</hi> Church,
ſome of <hi>John Goodwins,</hi> ſome of <hi>Kiffins,</hi> ſome of <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences</hi>
and ſome of <hi>Carters</hi> Church. 6. Their ſixth Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent
principle is. <hi>That if a man be queſtioned for any
crime, though his Judges have neither competent witneſſes,
proofs nor Evidence of his guiltineſs, yet if they think in
their Conſciences he is guilty; they may condemn him out
of the Teſtimony of their own private conſciences.</hi> Is it not
fit men ſo principled ſhould be Judges and Jury too; &amp;
condemn men by inſpiration? So Col. <hi>Andrews</hi> and Sr.
<hi>John Gell</hi> were condemned; for <hi>Bernard</hi> and <hi>Pits</hi> (wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
againſt them) were apparently ſuborned by
<hi>Bradſhaw</hi> and Sir <hi>Hen. Mildmay</hi> againſt them: and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworn
in the ſame cauſe; and good proof offered to
the Court, that they were both Flagitious men, of
ſcandalous life and converſation. The letter (ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to be ſent by <hi>Andrews</hi> to <hi>Gell</hi>) was delivered to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29684:19"/>
               <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> whereof <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> ſent a Copy onely to
<hi>Gell</hi> at ten of the clock at night; and had a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
then ready to arreſt <hi>Gell,</hi> which was done early
next morning before he could conveniently diſcover
it: Yet was <hi>Gell</hi> ſentenced for Miſpriſon of High-Treaſon.
See Sr. <hi>John Gells</hi> caſe ſtated, Auguſt 1650.
with Colonel <hi>Andrews</hi> Atteſtation (in his behalf) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
his hand a little before his death. And though Sr.
<hi>John</hi> was Impeached and Mr. <hi>Atturney</hi> proſecuted him
only for Miſpriſion; yet had he much a do to keep
that blood thirſty old curre <hi>Keeble</hi> from taking a leap
at his throat, and giving Judgment againſt him for
High Treaſon. So for want of law Sr. <hi>John</hi> had like
to be hanged by Inſpiration and Inſtinct of the ſpirit.
He that will ſee more of theſe Independent Tenets,
Let him read <hi>Cl. Salmaſius</hi> chap. 10. <hi>Defenſionis Regiae.
Elenchus Motuum nuperorum in Anglia.</hi> And the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of Independency, 1, and 2. part. Theſe 6. I have
ſelected, that by comparing their Doctrine with their
daily Practiſe, the Reader may perceive what pious
Chriſtians, good Patriots, and upright Judges, theſe
engaged, Independent Commiſſioners of the High
Court of Juſtice are like to prove. The builders of
this New Commonwealth or Babel, hold forth to the
People, Juſtice and Liberty, as their Motto: as if
thoſe excellent guifts had never received their birth,
nor bin ſo much as ſhewen to the People untill they
murdered the King, and ſtepped into his Throne.
But how righteous a <hi>Free State</hi> or Commonwealth is
this like to be? And how well are the People therein
like to be inſtructed in the wayes of Righteouſneſſe,
Juſtice and Charity, and improved in good life and
converſation, by men ſo principled as aforeſaid, Let
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29684:19"/>
the world judge. Eſpecially when they obſerve,
That our New Statiſts have enacted in the ſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
Act 2. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1649. enjoyning the Engagement,
That who ſoever will promiſe Truth and fidelity to
them by ſubſcribing the Engagement may deale
falſely and fraudulently with all the world beſides.
And break all Bonds, Aſſurances and Contracts made
with Non-engagers, concerning their Eſtates; and
pay their Debts by pleading in Bar of all Actions,
That the complainant hath not taken the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
This is to robb the Aegyptians of the good
things of this world, This is to break their Faith by
the motions of the Spirit. This is to cheat and rob
their Neighbours without breach of Charity or Juſtice,
and without imputation of Sinne, according to their
aforeſaid Tenets.</p>
            <p>3. I am come now to conſider in the third place,
<hi>The way and Manner of their proceedings;</hi> How con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant
they are to the uſuall proceeding of our known
Laws, and Legall Courts of Judicature? (the beſt
Inheritance of all Freemen) whereof ſee Colonel <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi>
3. Anſwers in his Defence given into the ſaid
High Court, Here with printed.</p>
            <p>1. The firſt Courſe they commonly take is; To
break open mens Houſes, Studies, Cheſts, &amp;c. and
ſeiſe their Papers; and thereby hunt for Matter of
Charge againſt them: And then to examine them
againſt themſelves, upon the ſaid Papers, contrary
to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which ſaith, <hi>Nemo tenetur prodere ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum.</hi>
And contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſtianity,
which forbids a man to deſtroy his own life, or be,
<hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> as many men unwittingly doe, who anſwer
to captious, enſnaring queſtions. What that tempting
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29684:20"/>
queſtion was put to Chriſt; <hi>Art thou the King of the
Jews?</hi> He returned no other Anſwer then: <hi>Thou ſayeſt
it: Why askeſt thou me?</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke them <hi>that heard me,</hi> That
is, Ask witneſſes. It was objected againſt the Oath
<hi>ex Officio,</hi> That it was High Injuſtice to examine a
man againſt himſelf: Becauſe his Anſwers may only
ſerve to condemn, but not to acquit him.</p>
            <p>2. They uſually break open houſes with Souldiers,
at all hours of the night, pulling men out of their beds
with great violence and terrour, and ſo carrying them
away, under pretence whereof Robberies and Murders
have bin committed. Whereas by the <hi>Stat. 1. Edw. VI.
chap. 12. and 5. and 6. Edw. VI. chap.</hi> 11. A man ought
not to be accuſed of High Treaſon, but to one of the
Kings Counſell; or to one of the Kings Juſtices of
Aſſize; or to one of the Kings Juſtices of the peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the <hi>Quorum:</hi> or to 2. Juſtices of the Peace, where
the Offence is committed, <hi>Cooks 3. Inſt. chap. High
Treaſon p.</hi> 26, 27, 28.</p>
            <p>3. They Commit men to priſon without any Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation
or Accuſor made known, and during pleaſure:
and detein them in priſon many years together with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any Legall proceedings or charge againſt them;
ſharing their Eſtates, Offices and Revenues (by Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrations
and Suſpenſions of the Profits) amongſt
themſelves, without any Crime objected: And ſo
leave them to ſterve, rot or dye in naſty Gaoles, for
want of Maintenance, under the cruelty of covetous
and mercileſſe Gaolers, whom they bear out (for
mony) in all their Extortions. And being thus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned
and wounded with the diſpleaſure of the
State no man dares adventure, upon any ſecurity,
to lend him mony for fear of incurring the disfavour
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29684:20"/>
of the State,<note place="margin">Witnes about 3000. Scottiſh Priſoners of Warre ſtarved to death at Durham: where they eat one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for hunger. Theſe were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at the battle of Dunbar An. 1650. 3. Sept. and many hundred Priſoners have been murdered in Goales, with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, cold, naſtineſſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have been robbed of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and no Crime laid to their Charge: This is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a dayly practiſe.</note> and a Note of Malignancy, whereby their
Priſons are become private Slaughter houſes, as well
as their Courts Publike Shambles of Injuſtice. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners
in the Tower of London (To which priſon no
Gaole delivery belongs) were alwayes wont in the
time of (<hi>that ſuppoſed Tyrant</hi>) King Charles I. and his
Predeceſſors, to have allowance from the King, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to their ſeverall degrees; As 5<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. a weeke
for an Eſquire &amp;c. although the King deprived them
of no part of their eſtates untill conviction, and this
Maintenance was provided for them by the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant
of the Tower; and in reſpect of his care and
paines in procuring it he had Fees, and not otherwiſe;
though now they continue and increaſe the ſaid Fees;
the cauſe being taken away the effect ceaſeth not. But
theſe men now in power, after they have Committed
men and robbed them of their Eſtates, without cauſe
ſhewen, are ſo farre from giving them any allowance
to feed them; that they ſhut them up cloſe Priſoners
in unwholſome chambers, denying them the Liberty
of the Tower, and the benefit of freſh Aire (the
Cameleons Diet) for their health, and reſort of
friends, for their accommodation. And that they may
be ſure to <hi>deprive them of all legal means by</hi> habeas cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus
<hi>to recover their liberties;</hi> They commit men by <hi>il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal
warrants</hi> not expreſſing any particuler Offence or
cauſe for their commitment; ſo that it is impoſſible
for the keeper of the priſon to obey the <hi>habeas corpus,</hi>
which is directed to him in theſe words: <hi>Precipimus tibi
quod compus A. B. una cum cauſa detentionis fuae, habeas
coram nobis &amp;c. ad recipiendum ea quae curia noſtra. &amp;c.</hi>
Wherupon the Goaler or Sheriff is to bring his Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
to the Bar and tender his <hi>mittimm</hi> to the Court,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29684:21"/>
ſhewing the particuler cauſe of his Impriſonment,
that the Court may judge whether it be Legall, or no.
<hi>Doloſus verſatur in Generalibus.</hi> In the Acts of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
chap. 25. ver. 26. 27. <hi>Feſtus</hi> thought it unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
to ſend <hi>Paul</hi> a Priſoner to <hi>Caeſar</hi> (to whom he
had appealed) and not withall to ſignifie the Crimes
laid to his Charge. See Cookes 2. Inſtit. fol. 591.</p>
            <p>4. Their uſuall courſe of <hi>practiſing and ſuborning
witneſſes, tempting them with hopes and terrifying them
with fears,</hi> is ſo notorious; that it is known the Counſel
of State have hundreds of <hi>Spies and Intelligencers, Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit-men
and Knights of the Poſt,</hi> ſwarming over all
England as Lice &amp; Frogs did in Egypt: and have both
<hi>Penſions and ſet rates for every polle brought in: So that
now the whole Nation is proſcribed, and every mans head
ſet to ſale,</hi> and made a ſtaple commodity, (far beyond
the definite proſcriptions of <hi>Silla</hi> &amp; the <hi>Triumvirate</hi>
aforeſaid) Theſe ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> are ſent forth to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe
the earth ſeeking whom they may devoure.
Theſe (with the Liberty of Priviledged Spies)
ſpeake bold Language to draw other men into
danger: and plot conſpiracies, which themſelves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
and are rewarded like Decoy Duckes for their
paines. Of this ſort are <hi>Bernard</hi> and <hi>Pits</hi> ſet on work
to betray <hi>Gell</hi> and <hi>Andrews,</hi> as aforeſaid. For which
<hi>Bernard</hi> had 300l. and a Troope of horſe conferred
upon him. <hi>Johnſon</hi> that falſly accuſed Sr <hi>Rob. Sherly</hi>
and <hi>Col. Egerton</hi> for their charity in releiving his
wants, is another; <hi>Varney</hi> is a fourth. So well are
they fitted with theſe Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> that no <hi>Naboth</hi>
can keepe his Vineyard, if a Grandee caſt a covetous
eye upon it; they can prove what they liſt. Nay it is
uſuall for our Grandees to moleſt one man with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29684:21"/>
examining him 20. or 30. ſeverall times, againſt one
Priſoner, &amp; upon one point, to diſtract his memory, &amp;
not to let him be quiet until he perceive, He muſt ſpeak
what their queſtions and diſcourſes lead him to, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem
himſelfe from vexation. To ſay nothing of their
Menaces, To torture men if they will not confes, what
they impudently pretend is already diſcovered by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
means: And their inſinuating into the affections of
witneſſes by asking them: Whether the State doth not
owe them money? And why they doe not uſe fitting
means and opportunities to recover it? And why they
do not make means for ſome beneficial employment?</p>
            <p>5. <hi>In Magna Charta,</hi> chap. 29. it is enacted, <hi>That no
Freeman ſhal be taken or impriſoned; or be diſſeiſed of his
Freehold or Liberties or free Cuſtomes, or be outlawed or
exiled, or any otherwiſe destroyed;</hi> nor <hi>we will not paſſe
upon him or condemne him, but by lawfull Judgement of
his Peares, or by the Law of the Land. We will ſell to no
man, We will not deny or deferre to any man, Juſtice
or Right.</hi> See Statut, 2. Ed. III. chap. 8. 5. Ed.
III. chap. 9. 14. Ed. III. chap. 14. 25. Ed. III.
chap. 4. 11. R. II. chap. 10. Pet. of Right. 3.
Car. 1. 10. Ed. IV. fol. 6. Dier. fol. 104.
Cooke lib. 5, fol. 6. lib. 10. fol. 74. lib. 11. fol.
99. Regiſt. fol. 86. Where note the word
(<hi>Peeres</hi>) ſignifies, that no man is to be condemned
or deſtroyed, but by the lawful verdict of a <hi>Iury of</hi>
12. <hi>ſworne men of the Neighbourhood</hi> where the Fact was
committed; becauſe (in probability) Neighbours
may have beſt cognizance of the Fact, and of the life
and converſation of the Party Accuſed. And theſe
only are <hi>Competent Judges of Matter of Fact;</hi> &amp; in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
caſes of Matter of Law too, if they will take the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29684:22"/>
knowledge of the Law upon them. Neither can this
Petty Jury of 12. men goe upon the priſoner, unleſſe
a <hi>Bill of Inditement</hi> containing the whole Matter of
charge be firſt found in open Court by a Grand Jury
or Enqueſt of ſworne men; who are to enquire of the
Fact upon the Oathes of two lawfull witneſſes (at
leaſt) to every material Point of the Enditement and
then, when the Grande Enqueſt are all agreed, the
Foreman endorſeth upon the backe of the Bill (<hi>Billa
vera</hi>) and then preſents it in open Court, as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation
for the King of the whole Enqueſte:
otherwiſe the Enditement is quaſht, and nul. Cookes
3. Inſtit. chap. High Treaſon and Petty Treaſon.
And whereas the Statut. ſaith, (but by his Peeres, or
by the Law of the Land) <hi>Lex Terrae,</hi> ſignifies, The
Auntient Cuſtomes of the Land; Amongſt which
Fundamentall Cuſtomes; Trials by Juries hold a
principall place. And <hi>when the King Charles I. accuſed
this Parlament, That they dispoſed of the Subjects Lives
&amp; fortunes by their votes, contrary to the known Laws of
the Land, This Parlament in their Remonſtr. Sep,</hi> 1642.
(1. Part. of the Book of Declarations fol. 693.)
<hi>highly reſented it.</hi> And <hi>Magna Charta</hi> being nothing
elſe but an affirmation of the common Law, inſerted
this Clauſe (<hi>or by the Law of the Land</hi>) as a ſpeciall
caution, not to annihilate or fruſtrate (no; not ſo
much as tacitely, or by preterition) any of the ſaid
Fundamentall Lawes or Cuſtomes, nor any other
particular lawfull Cuſtomes, which are not one and
the ſame in all parts of England; Witnes the Cuſtom
of <hi>Savelkind</hi> in Kent. I have told you what our known
auncient. Legall Courts of Juſtice doe. And I muſt
tell you that <hi>Legall formes and ſet Modes of proceedings
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29684:22"/>
are ſo eſſentiall unto Juſtice, that without them we cannot
meaſure the Rectitude or obliquity of juſtice or injuſtice:</hi>
where they do not chalke forth the way, both Judges,
Lawyers, Officers &amp; Atturneys will tread what ſubtle,
obſcure paths they pleaſe, uſurpe an Arbitrary power
and latitude to prevaricate; &amp; ſo far corrupt &amp; work
the Law to their ſence, that they will rather <hi>Leges da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi>
then <hi>Leges dicere,</hi> ſo that what is Law in one mans
caſe, ſhall not be ſo in another mans, They will ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate
and intangle cauſes; that every caſe ſhall be
<hi>Caſus pro amico;</hi> as Civilians call it; when upon full
hearing, The Merits of the cauſe appear ſo equall, and
undiſtinguiſhable on both parts; that the Iudge may
(according to his diſcretion) look upon the Merits of
the Perſons only: and give the cauſe; <hi>Pauperiori, via
Charitatis,</hi> or <hi>digniori, ratione virtutis. Juſtice not fixed
by formalities, wil become ſuch a vagrant, that no man ſhal
know where to find her.</hi> Let us now ſee what our new
ſhambles out upſtart High Court doth. Which in this
worke of Reformation and Deſtruction, ſo much ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors
ſuperſtition and ceremonies, and ſtickes ſo cloſe
to a ſummary way of proceeding, that they have not
onely ſtripped, but flead her: as their Maſters the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
not only fleece, but flea the People. In lieu
of a Bill of Preſentment, by a Grande Enqueſt, the
pretended Parliament or Counſel of State, ſend <hi>a Liſt
of ſuch Perſons names,</hi> as they have proſcribed, And ſet
a <hi>Nigrum Theta</hi> upon, (as men dangerous to their
deſigned intereſt) to the Maſters of their Slaughter-houſe,
The ſaid High Court, together with ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions
as they have taken in corners, againſt the
Priſoners: and this is ſuch a fore judging of them, that
the ſaid Court neither will not dare acquit, whom
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29684:23"/>
their Maſters and pay-Maſters have precondemned.
Next <hi>Articles of Impeachment in nature of a charge</hi> are
drawn up againſt the Priſoner (although ſuch Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
are nothing in Law, which regards only a Bill of
Inditement) Then the Priſoner after a cloſe Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
for he knows not what) upon two dayes warning
is led to the Bar; where the firſt worke is to dazle his
eyes, amaſe and diſtract his judgement and memory
with the terror of their ſouldiers, the Numerouſneſſe,
high affronting words and looks of his Judges; having
thus mortified the Priſoner, he is commanded to hear
his charge read: and bid <hi>plead to it. Guilty; or not Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
If he own their juriſdiction and plead the ſaid Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
Plea, they have him where they would have him:
they never ask him; how he wil be tried? Whether by
God and his Country? for God hath no hand in theſe
proceedings, nor amongſt ſuch Judges; and this rod of
Iron is provided to bruiſe his Country, as well as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.
Lieutenant <hi>Col. Lilbornes</hi> Triall hath taught
them That it is an eaſier Matter for them to packe a
Butcher Row of confiding, partiall Judges, then a
Jury; who are liable to be challenged, if ſuſpected
of partiality. When <hi>Col. Andrewes</hi> claimed to be
tried legally as a Freeman by a Jury and vouched
Great Charter, and many other Statutes, (whereof
ſee his aforeſaid three Anſwers) that ſneaking Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucker,
illitterate <hi>Keeble</hi> anſwered. Thoſe Statutes
were out of date now, (meaning they were taken away
by conqueſt,) <hi>So that this ſhamble Row of Judges, take
upon them to be, both Judges of the Law, (without ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging
the Fundamentall Lawes of the Land, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
any Oath of Indifferency to the People) Triors of the
Fact, or Jurates of life and Death (without being ſworne
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29684:23"/>
to find according to Evidence) as well as Parties and
Proſecutors.</hi> Theeves upon the high way may as
juſtly arraigne a true man before them, becauſe he
brought no money in his purſe, offered to draw his
ſword and hid his money about him in contempt of
their juriſdiction and Authority; and condemne him
upon ſuch a mock Trial &amp; mummery or enterlude of
Juſtice, as theſe Fellowes. <hi>If they allow him counſell,</hi> his
Counſell muſt apprehend the minds of his Iudges, at
his perill; and not be ſo faithfull and diligent as to
helpe his client in earneſt; Leaſt the Counſell of
State, or ſome other power (whoſe will is a Law) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe
and baniſh him 20. miles from London; as
they did Maſter <hi>Sprat,</hi> Sr <hi>Iohn Gells</hi> Sollicitor, before
Sr <hi>Iohns</hi> buſineſſe was ended; whereby Sr <hi>Iohns</hi> was left
deſtitute of means to follow his buſines, himſelf being
cloſe Priſoner. If they permit any <hi>witnes to ſpeak on the
priſoners part,</hi> He coms at his perill: Sr <hi>Iohn Gells</hi> firſt
witnes was ſo baffled in Court, that the reſt ſtole away
&amp; durſt not appeare. <hi>I have not heard whether they give
any Copy of their Articles of Impeachment to the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi>
(for they cover all their doing with ſuch a Plaguy
Egyptian D<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>knes, that we cannot ſee a glimpſe of
light) or whether they goe a Star Chamber way, and
make him Anſwer <hi>Ore tenus,</hi> and <hi>ex tempore</hi> for his life
and Eſtate. <hi>But if they give him any copy, or any time to
anſwer, it is not above four or five dayes, or a weeke, nor do
they allow him Counſell, or any other Cleering of the
way to his defence, untill he have enſnared himſelfe by
owning their juriſdiction, and pleaded the generall Plea,
Not Guilty. If he plead not an iſſuable Plea, and
yeeld to their juriſdiction, quitting all benefit of the
Law &amp; Legal proceedings, the Razor is at his throat, they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29684:24"/>
thirſt after his Blood; &amp; they preſently ſentence him guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of contumacy &amp; take it</hi> pro confeſſo. <hi>And if he do ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
&amp; plead: His plea wil have the operation but of a pſaelm
of Mercy, prolonging his life but for a ſhort time, in the
interim</hi> Keeble <hi>&amp; his Court plays with him as a Cat doth
with a Mouſe, and then devours him. For no man is ſent to
this Court to be tried, but to be condemned. In hac arena
dimicatur ſine miſſione.</hi> Herein they ſhew themſelves
much more tirannous &amp; bloody then the Duke <hi>D' Alva</hi>
when he erected his ſaid counſel of Troubles, called <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium
Sanguinis,</hi> or the bloody conventicle; as this wil
ſhortly be. For ſaith Strada Declar. 1 lib. 7. <hi>Procurator
regius menſes 4. Conficiendae Accuſationi accipiens ſibi;</hi> 5
<hi>Concedebat ad Defenſionemreis (Egmontio, Hornano, &amp;c</hi>)
The Kings Attorney tooke four Months time to draw
up the Charge or Accuſation, and gave five Months
time to the Reſpondents to make their defence. And
had he given leſſe then five Months time, To Inſtruct
Counſell, Pen their Anſwers, produce and ſummon
witneſſes, inquire into the lives &amp; converſation of their
Accuſors, his feet had been ſwift to ſhed blood. <hi>Nulla
unquam de morte hominis cunctatio longa eſt,</hi> But our
Inquiſitors take whole years to themſelves to hunt for
Matter of Accuſation and hire and engage witneſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
men kept in ignorance and want with cloſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment:
and allow not them ſo many dayes to
make their Defence. <hi>All manner of Accuſors and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,
though apparently ſuborned and forſworn in the
ſame cauſe, and proofes without exceptions offered to the
Court that they are of infamous life and converſation, are
in this Court (the Object of whoſe deſires are blood and
Confiſcations, not Iuſtice) lawfull witneſſes,</hi> ſuch witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
were the ſaid <hi>Bernard</hi> and <hi>Pits;</hi> Monſters of man.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29684:24"/>
See Sir <hi>John Gels</hi> caſe ſtated: Printed about Auguſt,
1650. <hi>To Cite any antient, known Laws or Statutes, or
any other then their own new coined Acts, paſſed by this</hi> 8.
<hi>Part of a Houſe of Commons, (ſince they became elect Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
choſen by</hi> Thomas Pride) <hi>is to incur the High Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
of the Court, expreſſed abundantly in their words &amp;
looks. But to put them in minde of the Parliaments many
Declarations, to maintain the ancient known Laws, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
and Properties of the people, is to ſcandall the preſent
Government and incur the Cenſure of that unknown myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
Crime, which knaves call Malignancy.</hi> The witneſſes
and Judges being thus irrefragable, the firſt may ſwear
what they will, the ſecond may judge what they will,
ſince they are left at large and have all things <hi>in ſcrinio
pectoris:</hi> and Book Law muſt give place to Bench Law;
<hi>The Juriſdiction and Authority of this New unparalelled
Court is ſuch a Miſtery of iniquity, ſo unſcrutable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable,</hi>
that if a priſoner ſcruple (in the leaſt) either
it, or any of the uncouth proceedings of it; it is a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
ſin to him, and he is preſently interrupted, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted
both with diſdainfull words and looks. And
told,<note place="margin">See the Triall of K. <hi>Charls</hi> I. in the Hiſtory of Independen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy 2. Part. p. 19 &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>We are ſatisfied with our Authority, that are your Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi>
(ſo are Thieves upon the High way ſatisfied with
their Authority that rob and murther us by Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
and permiſſion.) <hi>It is upon Gods Authority and
the Kingdoms,</hi> (yet what they do is againſt the will of
God revealed in his Scriptures; and againſt the known,
eſtabliſhed Laws, Statutes, and continual Practiſe of
the Kingdome:) <hi>Which Authority commands you in the
name of the People of England to anſwer them.</hi> (Yet at leſt)
9. parts of 10. of the people ſo much abhorre theſe and
other their Practiſes that every mans mouth ſpeakes
againſt them with bitter curſes and reproaches to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:29684:25"/>
reſtrain which they have minted Acts of New Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
to make men Offenders, nay Traitors, even
for bare words; and erected this bloudy, illegall
Theater, The High Court (ſo called, for its High
Injuſtice) as a Spaniſh Inquiſition over them, &amp; every
mans hand would be about their ears, did they not
keep an Army of Janiſaries to ſuppreſſe them.) <hi>Their
Authority they do avow to the whole World, that the whole
Kingdom are to reſt ſatisfied therewith.</hi> (You ſee here a
Whip and a Bell provided to keep the whole Kingdom
in aw: the declared Supreme power of their Soveraign
Lord the people, muſt reſign their known Laws to their
Truſtees, their Repreſentatives in parliament, and take
new Laws from their Arbitrary Votes, or wo be to their
Necks and Shouldiers) <hi>I muſt interrupt you, what you do
is not agreeable to the Proceedings of any Court of Juſtice.
You are about to enter into Argument and diſpute concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Authority of this Court; before whom you appeare
as a priſonner; you may not diſpute the Authority of this
Court: nor will any Court give way to it, you are to ſubmit
to it.</hi> (It is not ſafe to confute a lye told with Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.
Yet if a man be Endicted of Treaſon or Felony
in the Court of Common Pleas, a man may Demurre
to, and diſpute the Juriſdiction of that Court; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
it is not in Criminall Cauſes, <hi>Competens Forum;</hi>
nor the Judges Compentent Judges; every man and
every cauſe muſt be tried <hi>Suo Foro, non Alieno.</hi> 80 if
a Peer be Arraigned in the Kings Bench. And for
this upſtart, unpreſidented High Court; it is no Court
of Judicature at all, as being erected without lawful
Authority; Conſiſting of Incompetent Judges, no
Records belonging to it: and tending to diſinherit,
and disfranchiſe all the People of <hi>England:</hi> and to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29684:25"/>
murder them.) <hi>You may not diſpute the Juriſdiction of
the Supreme and Higheſt Authority of</hi> England, <hi>from
which there is no Appeal, The Votes of the Commons of</hi>
England <hi>aſſembled in Parliament is the Reaſon of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
(Oh Brutiſh, irrational Kingdome!) Where 40.
or 50. Anabaptiſticall Members, the Dregs and Lees of
the Houſe of Commons, after all the beſt and ſincereſt
(7. parts of 8.) had been racked and purged out at the
Bunghole by <hi>Cromwell</hi> the Brewer and <hi>Pride</hi> his Dray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
ſhall be called the Reaſon and Law of the Land.
This confirms the truth of what King <hi>Charls</hi> the I. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
to the Parliament (whereof I have formerly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
(<hi>That they diſpoſed of the Subjects Lives and Fortunes,
by their own Votes, againſt the known Laws of the Land.</hi>
But that there ſhould be no Appeal to their declared
Soveraign Lord the people, from their ſubordinate
Truſtees in Parliament is wonderfull; Conſidering
that in all Governments, The laſt Appeal is ever to the
Higheſt and moſt Abſolute power. But it may be they
will be the Peoples Truſtees in ſpight of their Teeth,
and by the power of the Sword; and ſo free themſelves
from rendring any account of their Stewardſhip.) <hi>You
may not Demurre to the Juriſdiction of the Court. If you
do, they let you know, that they over rule your Demer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,
and affirm their own Juriſdiction. Reaſon is not to be
he heard against the Higheſt Juriſdiction the Commons of</hi>
England, <hi>make a direct &amp; poſitive Anſwer, either by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying
or confeſſing, and put in immediately an iſſuable
Plea,</hi> Guilty, <hi>or</hi> Not Guilty <hi>of the Charge, or we will record
your Default and contumacy, and by an implicite confeſſion
take you guilty pro confeſſo, &amp; immediately give judgment
againſt you.</hi> (This (as I told you before) is it that blanches
the Deer into the Toile, But God deliver us from that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29684:26"/>
Juriſdiction that is too high to hear Reaſon; and that
over rules Demurrers before they be heard.) I have told
you as much of the proceedings of this Court, as the
Novelty, Obſcurity, uncertainty and confuſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
will give me leave. Let me now (by way of overplus)
give you the great dangers and ſlavery that will be fall
all ſorts of People, if they tamely and cowardly ſuffer
themſelves to be deprived of their auticent, legal Tryals
by Endictment and Juries of the Neighbour hood:
(then which the whole world cannot boaſt of a more
equall way) and ſuffer their Lives, Liberties, Eſtates,
and Honours to be ſubject to an Arbitrary, Extrajudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
conventicle of Blood, (<hi>Cromwels new Slaughter houſe</hi>)
which hath neither Law, Juſtice, Conſcience, Reaſon,
Preſident or Authority Divine or Humane, but onely
the pretended Parliaments irrational Votes and the
power of the Sword to maintain it, which will prove a
Cittadell over their Liberties, a ſnare to their Eſtates, a
Deadfall to their lives, and a ſcandal to their honours
and familes, if not timely oppoſed.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>By the Law the Endictment muſt ſpecifie what the
Treaſon is, and againſt what Perſon committed; As againſt
our Soveraign Lord the King, his Crown and Dignity.</hi> But
in the ſaid Articles of Impeachment, it is alleaged that
the Treaſon is committed againſt the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
or, againſt the Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi>
but in this dead-water our turning Tide between
the old Regall, and this new unknown Government;
no man knows how to do, look or ſpeak for fear of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting
the guilt of an Interpretative Treaſon, upon
the ſaid two Statutes for New Treaſons, and before this
boundleſſe, lawleſſe new Court. And <hi>to ſay, that Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
is committed againſt a Government in abſtracto, is Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29684:26"/>
it muſt be ſaid that Treaſon is committed againſt
the Governours in Concreto, naming them.</hi> For there being
<hi>no Treaſon without Allegiance;</hi> And <hi>Allegiance being a
perſonall Obligation, muſt be due from a certain known Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
to a certain known Perſon, or Perſons.</hi> And therefore
<hi>the Keepers of the Liberties of England, not being yet made
known to us, who they are, or where to be found, or what their
power, duty or office is; and being not tied by any ſet Oath
to deal well and truly with the People, (as Kings are by their
Coronation Oath; for if the ſtipulation be not mutuall, the
People are Slaves, not ſubjects</hi>) ſince the Duties of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance
and Protection, Obedience and Command
being reciprocall (as they muſt needs be, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
having declared the Supreme power to be in
the People; they muſt not govern them <hi>Mero Imperio</hi>
(by lawleſſe Votes) like Turkiſh, Tartarian and Ruſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
Slaves. <hi>I cannot ow nor perform Allegiance to thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividua
vaga (the Keepers or Gaolers of our Liberties)</hi> nor
to an Utopian Commonwealth. And without Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
no Treaſon: for in all Endictments of High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
it muſt be alledged; <hi>That the accuſed did (Prodito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riè)
perpetrate ſuch and ſuch Crimes; Contra debitam
Allegantiam ſuam.</hi> And the word (<hi>Proditoriè) ſignifies
the betraying of a Truſt:</hi> According to the Proverbe;
In Truſt, is Treaſon. <hi>Now where there is no profeſſion
of Allegiance, there is no acceptance of a Truſt, no man
can truſt me againſt my will.</hi> I was born under a Regall
Government, have read the Stat. Recognition, 1. Jac.
Have taken (as well as others) the Legall Oathes
of Allegiance, Obedience and Supremacy to the
<hi>King</hi> his <hi>Heires</hi> and <hi>Lawfull Succeſſors:</hi> impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
me by lawfull Authority, and from which no
power on Earth can abſolve me: and ſo much I at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29684:27"/>
in the Oath of Supremacy. And how I ſhould now
come (after the New Moduling of the Parliament and
Kingdome by Souldiers) to ow Allegiance to <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi>
the Brewer, <hi>Scot</hi> the Brewers Clerk, <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> the
murderous petty fogger, Sr. <hi>Hen. Mildmay</hi> the Court
pander and projector, <hi>Holland</hi> the Linckeboy, <hi>John Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi>
that packed a Committee (in which he was a
Member) and Voted to himſelf 2000l. <hi>Love</hi> the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-inducted
Six Clerk, or any other of that Self-created
Authority, let them ſheath their ſwords and
tell me.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>An Endictment muſt certainly alledge the Offence
committed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onel Poſt ſcript at the Latter end of this Book.</note> 
               <hi>in reſpect of the Matter, Time, Place, perſons
and other circumſtances;</hi> But in theſe Articles of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment
they tie themſelves to no ſuch certainties;
Whereby the Accuſed knows not at what ward to lie,
nor how to make his Defence. The Circumſtances of
time, place and perſon, being the aſſured Teſtimony of
all Humane Actions. This lawleſſe Court leaves him in
a vaſt Sea of Troubles, without pole-ſtarre, card or
compaſſe to ſteer by: The Arbitrary Opinions of this
Court, declared upon emergent Occaſions, being a
falſ hearted Pilot to him. <hi>Theſe Judges not being of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
with the priſoner, as our Legal Judges are, who ſwear to
do Juſtice according to the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>By the Law, any learned man that is preſent, may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
the Court; for the benefit of the priſoner, of any thing
that may make the proceedings erronious. Cooks 3. Inſtit.
pag.</hi> 29. But the whole proceedings of this Court, their
meeting and ſitting being erronious, here is no room
left for admonition, To take away their errours, is to
take away the Court.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:29684:27"/>
4. <hi>Cooks 2. Inſt. p.</hi> 51. expounding the 29. chapter of
<hi>Magna Charta,</hi> hath theſe words. <hi>All Commiſſions ought to
be grounded upon the Law of England</hi> (not upon the Votes
of the Houſe of Commons) <hi>and to contain this clauſe in
them. To do what is juſt according to the Laws &amp; cuſtoms of
England;</hi> (not to execute the ſeveral powers given them
by the Act 26. <hi>March</hi> 1650) and a little further he ſaith.
Againſt this Antient and Fundamentall Law I finde an
Act of Parliament made 11. <hi>Hen. VII. chap.</hi> 3. That as
well Juſtices of Aſſize as Juſtices of the Peace, without
any finding or preſentment by the verdict of twelve
men, upon a bare Information for the King before them
made, ſhould have full power and Authority by their
Diſcretions, to hear and determine all Offences &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts
committed, or done by any perſon or perſons,
againſt the Form, Ordinance or effect of any Statute
made and not repealed; ſaving Treaſon, Murder or Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony.
By colour of which Act ſhaking this Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
Law, it is not credible what horrible Oppreſſions
and Exactions, to the undoing of infinite number of
people, were Committed by <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices
of the Peace throughout <hi>England.</hi> And upon this
unjuſt and injurious Act, <hi>a new Office was erected (as
commonly in like caſes it falleth out) and they made Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
of the Kings Forfeitures. (I heare ſuch an other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
will be erected, when the novelty of this wonderfull
High Court is leſſened, and the yoak thereof throughly ſetled
upon the people necks)</hi> Yet obſerve the ſaid <hi>Act 11. H. 7. cap</hi>
3. went not ſo high as to Treaſon, Murder, and Felony.
But by the <hi>Stat. 1. Hen. VIII. chap.</hi> 6. the ſaid <hi>Act</hi> 11.
<hi>Hen. VII.</hi> was repealed, and the reaſon given, For that
by force of the ſaid Act it was manifeſtly known;
That many ſiniſter and crafty, forged and feigned In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29684:28"/>
had bin purſued againſt many of the Kings
Subjects, to their great dammage and wrongful vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
The ill ſucceſſe hereof (ſaith <hi>Cooke</hi>) and the
fearful end of theſe two Oppreſſors, (who were Endict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and ſuffered for High Treaſon for all the ſaid Act 11.
<hi>Hen.</hi> VII. paſſed in a full and free Parliament: <hi>Cook.</hi> 3.
Inſtit. pag. 208.) <hi>Should admoniſh Parliaments, That in
ſtead of this Ordinary and pretious Triall by the Law of the
Land, they bring not in Abſolute and partiall Tryals by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</hi>
And in his 4. Inſtit. p. 41. <hi>Cook</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments
leave all Cauſes to be meaſured by the golden and
ſtreightned wand of the Law, and not the uncertaine
and crooked corde of Diſcretion: for it is not almoſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible
to foreſee, when any Maxime or Fundamental Law of
the Land is altered, what dangerous inconveniences will
follow; as appears by this unjuſt and ſtrange Act</hi> 11. Hen.
VII. chap. 3.</p>
            <p>5. <hi>This Parliament alwayes declared they bore Arms
againſt the King, in Defence of the Laws, Liberties and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties
of the people.</hi> This way ran the whole current of
their Declarations. <hi>And they alwaies-reckoned Magna
Charta, the Petition of Right and Trials by <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uries, the Chief
and moſt Fundamental of all our Laws. See their Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance:
Therefore in their 7. Article againſt</hi> Strafford. <hi>They
charged him with High Treaſon, for giving Judgments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
mens Eſtates, without Trials by Juries. Much aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated
by Mr. St.</hi> Johns <hi>in his aforeſaid Argument againſt
Strafford.</hi> And for the better preſervation of Legall
Trials by Juries, it is provided in the Bill of At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainder
of <hi>Strafford,</hi> that the caſe of the ſame Earle
ſhould not be uſed as a Preſident in ſucceeding
times. <hi>And in two of this Parliaments late Declarations</hi> 9
<hi>Febr. and 17. March, 1648. The Parliament promiſeth.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:29684:28"/>
To preſerve and keep the Fundamentall Laws of the Land, for
preſervation of the lives, Liberties &amp; Properties of the People,
with all things incident thereto. Now to erect an Arbitrarie,
Lawles High Court, to give Judgement againſt mens lives &amp;
Eſtates, and attain their blouds, without Enditement found by a
Grande Jury, and a Triall by a Jury of 12 ſworn men</hi> vicineto;
<hi>is a farr fouler breach of Truſt in them againſt their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign
Lords the People, then all they Charged the King withall;
and a farr Higher Act of Tyranny and Injuſtice then either the
late King; or Empſon and Dudley or Strafford were accuſed
of.</hi> But <hi>if they alleage: They do not put down Juries in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
but onely in ſome particular mens caſes, &amp; upon Neceſsity.</hi>
I Anſwer. <hi>That we are all born Freemen of England alike;
That our Auntient known Laws, Lawes Courts and Trialls by
Juries are our Inheritance equall alike to all. And one Party or
part of the People ought not to be disherited, disfranchiſed or
forejudged no more then another. No man can be ſaid guilty of
any Crime untill he be legally convicted &amp; ſentenced: the Lawe
muſt firſt go upon him &amp; condemn him. Vbi lex non diſtinguit,
non eſt diſtinguendum. If we do not live all under one Lawe,
and forme of Juſtice, we are not all of one Common-wealth,</hi>
See the afore mentioned Gentlemans Argument, <hi>againſt
the Speciall Commiſsion of the Court of York.</hi> For <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity:</hi>
Our preſent power is under none: but the
fears and terrors of their own guiltie conſciences. No
apparence nor probability of any enemy by their own
confeſſion: nor can they pleade in their excuſe, a
Neceſſity which they have brought upon themſelves.
I know <hi>ſome Kings have, de facto, uſed the Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion
of the Sword to cut off ſuch powerfull and dangerous
Perſons as could not ſafely be called to account by the Law;
ſo died</hi> Joab, Adoniah, &amp;c. <hi>For which the rule is. Neminem
adeo eminere debere, ut Legibus interrogari nequeat: qui Jus
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:29684:29"/>
aequum ferre non poteſt, in eum vim haud in juſtam fore.</hi> No
man ought to advance himſelf above the powers of the
Law: He that will not ſubmit to equall Right, if he be
cut off by violence, ſuffers no wrong: <hi>But this is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood
of the Eminency and greatnes of the Perſon, not of the
greatnes of the Crime; whereof no man is to be forejudged; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
a great Crime may prove a great Calumny, untill a Legall
Triall have adjudged it.</hi> But there is no Perſon in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
ſo eminent for power or Authoritie, but that the
leaſt of <hi>Bradſhaws</hi> Ban-dogs can drive him to the Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-houſe,
and make him offer his throat to <hi>Keeble.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>Animadverſio Gladii,</hi> if at any time lawfull, is now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.
<hi>To make great examples, upon men of little power,
is great Injuſtice.</hi> But the way of this Court is not <hi>Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſio
per Gladium.</hi> It is a Mocking, a Counterfeiting, an
Adulterating and Alchimiſting of Juſtice: it is to falſifie
her waights and Ballance, and ſteal her Sword to Commit
Murder withall.</p>
            <p>6. By the knowne Lawes Matter of Fact is entruſted to the
Jury;<note place="margin">See Col. Andrews 3 Anſwers.</note> Matter of Law to the Judges; to prevent all Errors,
Combinations and Partiallities. The Judges are ſworn to do
Juſtice according to the Lawe; The Jury are ſworne to finde
according to their Evidence. <hi>But in this High Court the
Commiſſioners or Judges are all packed, Confiding men,
choſen by and out of one Party, to deſtroy all of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
Party.</hi> They uſurp the Office of Judges not being
ſworn to deal well and lawfully with the People (as by the ſaid
<hi>Stat. 18. Edw. III.</hi>) nor to do Juſtice according to the Lawe.
But onely to execute powers given by the ſaid <hi>Act 26. March</hi>
1650. And they arrogate (as Jury-men) to be Triers of
the Fact, without being ſworn, To find according to Evidence.
So that they are Judges, Juries and Parties, and (for eaſe of
their tender Conſciences (without any Oath of Indifferencie.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29684:29"/>
               <hi>A moſt excellent Compendium of Oppreſſion. They may
go to the Devil for Injuſtice, and not be forſworn. Great
is the Privilege of the Godly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7. <hi>The Priſoner may except againſt his Jurers, either against
the Array, if the Sheriff or Baily impannelling the Jury, be
not wholly diſingaged and Indifferent; both to the cauſe, and
to the Parties, Proſecuting and Proſecuted. Or againſt the
Poll, he may Challenge 35 peremptorily; and as many more as
he can render Legal Cauſe of Challenge for.</hi> As for <hi>defect of
Eſtate,</hi> or other <hi>Abilities,</hi> or for <hi>Partiality, Diſaffection, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement,
Infamy.</hi> But this Array of Jury-men-Judges (<hi>A</hi>
Medley ſo new we knowe not how to expreſſe it) though
picked and empannelled by an Engaged Remainder of the
Commons, and obnoxious to all exceptions, muſt not be
challenged, their backs are too much galled to endure the
leaſt touch. <hi>Take heed you ſcandall not the Court (cries</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
Atturney) See Col. Andrewes 3 Anſweres.</p>
            <p>8. <hi>Many Exceptions in a Legall Triall, are allowed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
Imperfections, Uncertainties and Illegallities in the
Bill of Enditement, for the advantage of the Priſoner.</hi> But
no Exceptions are allowed againſt theſe Illegal Articles of
Impeachement; which are made uncertain, intricate, obſcure
and ambiguous purpoſely to pusſle, confound, and entangle
the Reſpondent.</p>
            <p>9. <hi>By the Lawe a Bill of Enditement muſt have two full
and cleere lawfull witneſſes to every conſiderable Matter of
Fact;</hi>
               <note place="margin">VVhere there is but one witnes, It ſhall be tried by combat before the Earle Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Cook ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>both at finding the Bill and at the Triall.</hi> Cookes 3.
Inſtit. pag. 25. 26. <hi>And Probationes debent eſſe luce cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riores.</hi>
Proofes muſt be as cleere as the Sun; <hi>not ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
upon Inferences, Preſumptions, Probabilities.</hi> And the
Priſoner muſt be <hi>Provablement Attainte,</hi> ſaith the Stat.
25. Ed. III. chap. 2. Cookes 3. Inſtit. pag. 12. <hi>The word
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29684:30"/>
(Atteinted) ſhews he muſt be legally proceeded with: not by ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
power as formerly had bin uſed (and as is now uſed by this
bloudy High Court</hi>) But before theſe Slaughter-men of the
High Court, all manner of witneſſes, Legal or Illegal, one
or two, ſworn or not ſworn, or apparently forſworn and
ſuborned, and all proofes cleere or not cleere are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.
The Priſoner is ſent thither fore-doomed, and hath
his deaths Marck, his fate in his forehead.</p>
            <p>10. <hi>The ſaid</hi> Act 26. March 1650. <hi>Carries two faces
under one hood; and looks backwards as well as forewards.
To facts Precedent as well as Subſequent the ſaid Act,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to the Nature of all Laws, whoſe Office is <hi>to prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite
before it puniſh, to warn before it ſtrike.</hi> Where St. Paul
defineth <hi>Sinne to be The breach of Commandement, or Law.
I had not known Sinne but by the Lawe.</hi> The Law muſt
therefore be precedent to the Offence. But theſe Acts are
not <hi>Laws to admoniſh,</hi> but <hi>Lime-twigges and Trappes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare</hi>
and Catch men. See Col. Andrewes 3. Anſwers at
the latter end of this Book.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, and laſtly I am to conſider. <hi>To what end
and purpoſe this New invented High Court is conſtituted
and appointed?</hi> Concerning which ſee a Letter dated
6. June 1650. <hi>Stilo veteri,</hi> from the Hague, (ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to be <hi>Walter Strick-lands, the Parliaments Agent there</hi>)
as I finde it in <hi>Walter Frostes</hi> Brief Relations of ſome
Affairs and Tranſactions, &amp;c. from Tueſday June 11.
to June 18. 1650. wherein the Epiſtoler hath theſe
words. <q>
                  <hi>One peece of the cure</hi> (viz: of the daungers
that threaten your New State) <hi>muſt be Phlebotomy,</hi> but
then you muſt begin before Decumbency, and then it
will be facile to prevent danger, &amp;c. They are here moſt
of all affraid of your High Court of Juſtice, which they
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:29684:30"/>
doubt may much diſcourage their party, they wiſh you
would not renewe the power thereof, but let it expire:
then they think that after Michilmas they may expect
Aſſiſtance with you. And indeed that Court is of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
as much uſe to you as an Army: and will prevent
the riſing of as many Enemies, as the other will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy,
onely you muſt be ſure to execute Juſtice there
with all Severity. A few of the firſt ſtirrers taken away
by the power thereof, without reſpect to couſen or
Countrey will keep all the reſt quiet. But <hi>whoſoever that
Court condemns, let them be as already dead,</hi> &amp;c. But <hi>let
them be moſt free in cutting the vena Coephalica (that is the
Presbyterian Party) for the Baſilica</hi> (or Royal Party) will
be latent. <hi>The Median</hi> (or levellors) would be ſpared as
much as may be, that the body be not too much emacia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
Beſides the bloud is moſt corrupt in the Coephaliks
(<hi>or Presbyterians</hi>) and is the very <hi>cauſa continens</hi> of your
diſeaſe, You need not fear to take freely of this vein, &amp;c.</q>
Heere you ſee this State-Mountebancke gives you the uſe
and Application of this corraſive. (The High Shambles
of Juſtice) ſo fully that I ſhall not need to comment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
it. And in the latter end of a Letter from <hi>Cromwell,</hi>
dated from Dunbar 4. September 1650. (as I finde it <hi>in
Politicus</hi>) ſpeaking of his new purchaſed victory over the
Scots. <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſaith; <hi>God puts it more and more into your
hands to improve your power,</hi> (viz. your abſolute Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty)
<hi>wee pray own his People more and more,</hi> (that is; The
Army) <hi>they are the Chariots and Horſmen of Iſrael</hi> (of the
Kingdom of the Saints) <hi>diſowne your ſelves but owne your
Authority</hi> (vvhich you enjoy under the Protection of the
Army, your Lords Paramounte) <hi>and improve it; to Curbe
the Proud and the Inſolent,</hi> &amp;c. (That is all men of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29684:31"/>
different Opinions and Parties from them; that will not
engage to be true and owe Allegeance to the Kingdom of
the Saints, and reſigne their Lawes, Liberties and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
to their luſts and wills) That I have not miſconſtrued
the contents of <hi>Cromwells</hi> miſtical Letter will appear by <hi>a
Diſcourſe in the ſame Politicus</hi> Numb. 17. from Thurſday
September 26. to October 3. 1650. Where (according
to his Cuſtom) delivering forth State Oracles to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:
He tells them in plaine Engliſh. <hi>That after the Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
of a Civill warr, there is a Necesſity of ſome ſettlement,
and it can not in reaſon, be imagined, (the Controverſy being
determined by the ſword) that the Conquerers ſhould ſubmit to
the conquered,</hi> though more in number then themſelves.
<hi>Nor are they obliged to ſettle the Government again according
to the former Laws; and Conſtitutions, but may erect ſuch a
form as they themſelves conceive moſt convenient for their
own preſervation. For after a Civil war the written Laws
(viz. eſtabliſhed Laws of the Nation) are of no force, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
thoſe which are not written.</hi> (And a little after) The King
having by Right of war, loſt his ſhare and intereſt in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
and power, being conquered, <hi>by Right of war
the whole must needs reſide in that part of the People which
prevailed over him:</hi> There being no middle power to make
any claim, and ſo <hi>the whole Right of Kingly Authority in
England being by Military Deciſion reſolved into the preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
Party, what Government ſoever it pleaſeth them to erect,
is as valide de Jure, as if it had the conſent of the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
of the People.</hi> That he ſhould affirm That after a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
war the Eſtabliſhed Lawes ceaſe: is ſo groſſe a piece
of Ignorance, that there is hardly any Hiſtory extant
but confutes it; After our Barons warr and the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
warr between <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> Our Eſtabliſhed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:29684:31"/>
Laws flouriſhed; ſo did they after the Norman Conqueſt.
How many Civil Warrs in France have left their Lawes
untouched? That of the Holy League laſted 40 years, <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia</hi>
keeps her Lawes maugre her inteſtine Warrs: What
is now become of the Parliaments declared Supream
power and Soveraigne Lord the People, the Originall and
Fountain of all Iuſt power? are they not all here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed
Ear-bored ſlaves for ever? But I had thought
that an Army of Mercinary Saints raiſed, payed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned
by the Parliament to defend the Religion, Lawes,
Liberties and Properties of the People; and the Kings
Crown and Dignitie, according to the Proteſtation and
Covenant: and the Parliaments Declarations, would
not have made ſuch Carnal and Hypocriticall uſe of
their Victories gotten by Gods Providence and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
Money, as to deſtroy our known Laws, Liberties, and
Properties, and claim by Conqueſt, and impoſe their
own luſts, for Laws upon us, Thereby rendering them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
Rebells againſt their God, their King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.
Nor was it ever the State of the Quarrell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the King and Parliament whoſe Slaves the People
ſhould be? Or whether we ſhould have one King, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning
by the known, eſtabliſhed Lawes? or 40 Tyrants
Governing by their owne luſts and Arbitrary votes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
our written Lawes? Nor can the ſucceſſe make
a Conqueſt juſt, unleſs the cauſe of the warr were Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally
juſt, and the proſecution thereof juſtly managed.
As 1. To <hi>vindicate</hi> a Juſt Claim and Title. 2. <hi>Ad res repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendas.</hi>
To recover Dammages wrongfully ſuſtained.
3. To repell an Injury done to your ſelf, or to your Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in league with you.</p>
            <p>The ultimate end of theſe wicked Endeavours is,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29684:32"/>
To eſtabliſh and cement with the bloud of their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,
the Kingdom of the Brambles or Saints; already
founded in bloud. By cutting off all ſuch by their ſaid
New Acts of Treaſon and High Court of Juſtice, as
will not bow their Necks to their Iron yoake. Which
appears more cleerely in an <hi>Additionall Act giving far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
power to the ſaid High Court,</hi> (dated 27. Aug. 1650.)
<hi>To hear and determine all Miſpriſions or concealments of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi>
mentioned or contained in any of the ſaid Articles or
Acts of Parliaments: And to inflict ſuch puniſhments and
award ſuch execution, as by the Lawes and Statutes have
bin, or may be, inflicted. <hi>This Lawe (if I miſcall it not)
conſidering how they have multiplied Treaſons by their ſaid</hi>
3 <hi>New Statutes,</hi> 14. May. 17. July 1649. <hi>and</hi> 26 March
1650. <hi>Whereby bare words without Act are made High
Treaſon; Contrarie to thoſe well approved Statutes.</hi> 25. Ed. III.
chap. 2. 1. Hen. IV. chap. 10. 1. Edw. VI. chap. 12.
I. Mariae chap. 1. Cooke 3. Inſtit. ſaith, <hi>That words may
make an Heretique, not a Traitor,</hi> Chap. High Treaſon. <hi>And
the Scripture denounceth a wo to him; That maketh a man an
Offender for a word) is one of the cruelst, and most generally
dangerous and entrapping that ever was made. For hereby all
Relations; Husband and Wife; Parents and Children; Brothers
and Siſters, Maſters and Servants are all injoyned to be inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
againſt, and Accuſors of one another (which is to take upon
them the Devils Office (and be, Accuſatores Fratrum) for
light and vain words ſpoken onely in Paſsion or ignorantly: or
elſe they fall into the Jawes of this alldevouring Court</hi> (from
whence, no more then from Hell, there is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption)
<hi>for Miſpriſion of Treaſon: the Penaltie whereof
is loſſe of Libertie and Lands for life; and of Goods for ever,</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:29684:32"/>
Who can imagine leſſe heerby, but that <hi>our Statistes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
to raiſe a yearly revenue by this Court, by Forfeitures
and Confiſcations: and to erect an Office of Maſter of the
States Forfeitures: like Empſons and Dudleis in</hi> Hen. VII.
<hi>time aforeſaid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">10. Dec. 1650. a New Act paſſed, for eſtabliſhing an High Court of Juſtice in Norfolk, Suffolk, Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln and the Iſle of Ely, &amp;c. And ſo by degrees this gangrene ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large it ſelf all the King<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom over.</note> And ſo continue this Court, to weede
out the Auntient Inhabitants <hi>Cananites</hi> and <hi>Amalechites.</hi>
The ſaid Additional Act, 27. Aug. 1650. concludes,
That the ſaid High Court ſhall not examine, Try or
proceed againſt any Perſon other then ſuch as ſhall be firſt
by name appointed by the Parliament or Counſel of
State. It ſhould ſeem the Parliament and Counſel of
State ſupply the want of a Grand Enqueſt; and their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment
is in ſtead of a Bill of Enditement found and
preſented. <hi>As aſſuredly as The High Inquiſition was erected
in Spain by Firdinando and Iſabella to extirpate the Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan
Moors: And the ſaid Councel of Bloud in the Lowe
Countries, by the Duke D'Alva to weed out the Lutherans,
Calviniſtes and Anabaptiſtes. So is this High Court ſet up
in England to root out the Royalliſtes, Presbyterians and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellors;
and generally all that will not wholly concurre with
our Independents in Practiſe and Opinions.</hi> As will mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly
appear when their work is don in Scotland, which
will ſoon be effected: the more zealous Scots being now
as ready to ſell their Kingdom; as they weare formerly
to ſell their King.</p>
            <p>I Conclude therefore upon the Reaſons aforeſaid;
That becauſe the Commiſſioners or Judges are not ſworn
to do Juſtice according to the Lawes: And are Parties
pre-in-gaged (as well as their Maſters, and Pay-Maſters,
that named them) ignorant men, and of vild and baſe
profeſſions uncapable of places of Judicature, Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
Perſons, and ſome of them Scandalous; and the
High Court it ſelf hath neither Law, Preſident, nor any
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29684:33"/>
juſt Authority for Conſtituting thereof or the Judges
therein. And all proceedings before them are directly
Contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the Statut. 25. Edw. III.
chap. 2. The Petition of Right and all other known
and Eſtabliſhed Laws, and the continual Practiſe of our
Nation; and (in many Points (Contrary to the Law of
God and the Dictates of Right Reaſon. <hi>That theſe
Commisſioners are Incompetent Judges; Their Court an
Extrajudicial Conventicle, tending to diſinherite, disfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe
and enſlave all the Free-men of the Nation; and all
Proceedings before them are void and Coram non Judice,</hi>
See Col, Andrews. 3. Anſwers, The ſaid High Court
of Juſtice to be a meer bloudy Theater of Murder and
Oppreſſion. It being againſt Common Reaſon, and all
Laws Divine and Humane, That any man ſhould be
Judge in his own Cauſe. <hi>Neminem poſſe in ſua Cauſa
Judicem eſſe.</hi> Is the Rule in Law. <hi>But this Parliament
and Counſell of State know they can not establiſh and confirm
their uſurped Tyrannie, (The Kingdom of the Saints,) ea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
up the People with Taxes, and ſhare Publike Lands, Offices
and Mony amongſt themſelves: enſlave the Nation to their
Lawles wills and Pleaſures, but by cutting off the most able
and active men of all oppoſite Parties by ſom ſuch expedient
as this Arbitrary Lawleſſe High Court is. The old Legall
way by Juries (being found by John Lilbourns Triall) to
be neither ſure enough nor ſpeedy enough to do their work.
A Butcher-Rowe of Judges being eaſier packed, then a
Jury who may be challenged. So that it fareth with the
People of England, as with a Traviler fallen into the hands
of Theeves. Firſt they take away his Purſe, And then, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
themſelves, they take away his life. So they Robbe
him by Providence, And then Murder him by Necesſity.
And (to bring in their Third Inſiſting Principle) they may
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:29684:33"/>
alleage; They did all this upon Honeſt Intentions; to enrich
the Saints and robb the Egiptians. With theſe 3. Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
they Juſtify all their Villanies.</hi> Which is an Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
ſo meerely their own, That the Devil muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:
They have propagated his Kingdome of Sinne
and Death more by their Impudent Juſtifications, then
by their Turbulent Actions.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>An Additional Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>SInce the Concluſion of the Premiſes hath happened,
the Trial of that worthy Knight Sr. <hi>John Stowell</hi>
of the County of <hi>Sommerſet:</hi> Who having bin often
before this Court, hath ſo well defended himſelf, and
wiped off all Objections, and made ſuch good uſe of the
Articles of the Rendition of Exceſter, that in the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
of all men, and in deſpite of their enſnaring Acts
for New Treaſons, he can not be adjudged guilty of any
Treaſon, Old or New, which was the Summe and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement
of the Charge againſt him. Wherefore the
Court put off his Trial for a longer time, to hunt for
New Crimes and witneſſes againſt him. At laſt came
into the Court as a witnes <hi>John Aſhe,</hi> notwithſtanding
he is a Party many waies engaged againſt him. 1. <hi>Aſhe</hi>
is a Parliament man; in which capacity Sr. <hi>John Stowell</hi>
bore Armes for the King againſt him. 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. <hi>Aſhe</hi> as a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
man is one of the conſtitutors of this Murderous
Court and the Judges thereof, and therefore their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
(who expect rewards from them) beare a more aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
reſpect to his teſtimony, then a witnes ought to have
from Judges. 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. It is publickly known that <hi>Aſhe</hi> hath
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:29684:34"/>
begged of the Houſe a great ſumme of mony out of
the Compoſition for, or Confiſcation of Sr. <hi>Johns</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.
And 4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. It is known to many That during
Sr. <hi>Johns</hi> many years Impriſonment <hi>Aſhe</hi> often labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with Sr. <hi>John</hi> to ſell unto him for 4000<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. a Parcel
of Land which coſt Sr. <hi>John</hi> above 10000<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. promiſing
him to paſſe his Compoſition at an eaſy rate, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
his enlargement from priſon, and ſend him home
in peace and quiet if he granted his deſire. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
with all their malitious diligence, they cannot
finde him guilty of High Treaſon, yet their Articles
of Impeachment Charge him in general Tearms with
Treaſon, Murder, Felony and other High Crimes and
Miſdemeaners; and amaſſe together ſuch a Sozites and
and Accumulation of Offences as if one fail another
ſhall hit right to make him punniſhable in one kinde or
other: ſuch a hailſhot charge cannot wholly miſſe;
either they will have life, eſtate, or both; Contrary to
the Nature of all Enditements and Criminall Charges
whatſoever; which ought to be particular, cleere and
certain (Lamb: pag. 487) that the accuſed may knowe
for what Crime he puts himſelf upon Iſſue, But this
Court (as High as it is) not being Conſtituted a Court
of Recorde; the Priſoner, and thoſe that are concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in him, can have no Recorde to reſorte to either.
1. To demande a writ of Error, in Caſe of Erronious
Judgement. 2. To ground a plea of Auterfois Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite,
in Caſe of New Queſtion for the ſame fact.
3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Or to demande an Enlargement upon Acquitall.
or 4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. To demand a writ of conſpiracy, againſt ſuch as
have combined to betray the life of an Innocent man.
Whereby it followes; That this prodigious Court hath
power onely to Condemne and Execute; not to Acquite
<pb facs="tcp:29684:34"/>
and give Enlargement; Contrary to the Nature of all
Courtes of Iudicature, and of Iuſtice it ſelf: it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
a meer <hi>Slaughter - houſe</hi> to Commit Free - State
Murders in, without, nay againſt Law and Iuſtice: and
not a Court of Iudicature; to condemne the <hi>Nocent,</hi>
and abſolve the <hi>Innocent.</hi> And the Iudges of this Court
runne Paralell with their Father the Devill; who is
ever the Miniſter of Gods wrath and fury; never of his
Mercy.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:29684:35"/>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:29684:35"/>
            <head>The humble Anſwer of Col. Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius
Andrewes Eſquier, to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
againſt him before the
Honourable, The high Court of
Juſtice 1650.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Reſpondent (with favour of this Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Court) reſerving and praying to be allowed,
the benefit &amp; Liberty of making farther Anſwer, if it ſhall
be adjudged neceſſary, offereth to his Honorable Court.</p>
            <p>That by the Stat. or Charter ſtiled <hi>Magna Charta,</hi>
(which is the Fundamentall Law, and ought to be the
Standard of the Laws of England, Confirmed above 30
times, and yet unrepealed, it is in the 29 Chapter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
graunted and enacted.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>That no Free-man ſhall be taken or impriſoned, or be
diſſeiſed of his Freehold or Liberties, or Free Cuſtomes;
or be outlawed or exiled, or any other wayes destroyed,</hi>
Nor, <hi>we ſhall not paſſe upon him, but by a lawfull Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of his Peers, or by the Law of the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>We ſhall ſell to no man, nor deferre to any man Juſtice
or Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Stat. 42. Ed. III. chap. III. The Great Charter is
commanded to be kept in all Points: and it is enacted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That if any Stat. be made to the Contrary, <hi>That</hi> ſhall be
holden for none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Act 26. March 1650. entituled, An Act for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing,
An High Court of Juſtice. <hi>Power is given to
this Court; To Try, Condemne and Cauſe Execution of death
to be done, upon the Freemen of England, according as the
Major Number of any 12 of the Members thereof ſhall Judge
to appertein to Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:29684:36"/>And thereupon the Reſpondent doth humbly inferre,
and affirme, that <hi>the Tenor of the ſaid Act is diametri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally
oppoſite to, and inconſiſtent with the ſaid Great
Charter.</hi> And is therefore by the ſaid recited Stat.
42. Ed. III. to be holden for none.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That it can with no more Reaſon, Equity
or Iuſtice, hold the reputation or value of a Law, (if
the ſaid Stat. had not bin) then if (contrary to the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.
Clauſe of the 29. chap. of <hi>Magna Charta</hi>) it had bin
alſo enacted, <hi>That Juſtice and Right ſhall be deferred
to all Freemen and ſould to all that will buy it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Petition of Right, 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Car: upon premiſing:
That contrary to the Great Charter, Trials and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
had bin had and don againſt the Subjects, by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions
Martial, &amp;c. it was thereby praied, and by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
enacted. That:</p>
            <p>1. No Commiſsions of the like nature might be thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth
iſſued, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. To prevent least any of the Subjects ſhould be put to
death, Contrary to the Laws and Franchiſes of the Land.</p>
            <p>The Reſpondent heereupon Humbly obſerveth; and
affirmeth: <hi>That this Court is (though under a different ſtile)
in nature, and in the Proceedings thereby directed, the ſame
with a Commiſsion Martiall.</hi> The Free-men thereby being
to be tried for life, and <hi>adjudged by the Opinion of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor
Number of the Commiſsioners ſitting, as in Courtes of
Commiſsioners Martiall was practiſed;</hi> &amp; was agreeable to
their Conſtitution: <hi>And conſequently against the Petition of
Right:</hi> in which he, &amp; all the Freemen of England (if it be
granted there be any ſuch) hath and have Right and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,
and he humbly claimes his Right accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Declarations of this Parliament,</hi> Dec. 15. &amp; Jan. 17.
1641. The benefit of the Laws, and the ordinary Courſe
of Juſtice are the Subjects Birthright.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:29684:36"/>
               <hi>By the Declarations</hi> 12. Iuly 16. Octob. 1642. <hi>The proſecution
of the Laws, and due adminiſtration of Juſtice, are owned to be the
juſtifying cauſe of the war, and the end of the Parliaments Affaires
managed by their Swords and Counſells, and Gods curſe is by them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precated,
in caſe they ſhould ever decline thoſe ends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Declaration 17. Aprill 1646. Promiſe was made not
to interrupt the Courſe of Iuſtice, in the ordinary Courts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Ordinance or Votes of Non-addreſſes,</hi> Ian. 1648. It is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured,
<hi>That, though they lay aſide the King; yet they will govern by
the Laws, and not interrupt the courſe of Juſtice, in the ordinary
Courts thereof.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">They forget the 2. Declarations 9. Febr. 17. March 1648.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore this Reſpondent humbly averreth and affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
That <hi>the conſtitution of this Court, is a breach of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
Faith of the Parliament exhibited and pledged in thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations
and Votes to the Freemen of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And upon the whole matter, the Reſpondent (ſaving as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid)
doth affirme for Law and claimeth as is Right. <hi>That:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. This Court in defect of the validity of the ſaid Act, by
which it is conſtituted, hath no power to proceed againſt
him, or to preſſe him to a further Anſwer.</p>
            <p>2. That by virtue of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the Petition of Right &amp;
the before recited Declarations, he ought not to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
againſt in this Court; but by an ordinary Court of
Iuſtice, and to be tried by his Peers.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And humbly prayeth: That this his preſent
Anſwer and <hi>Salvo</hi> may be accepted
and regiſtred.
Euſebius Andrewes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:29684:37"/>
            <head>The Second Anſwer of Col. Euſebius
Andrews Eſquire, To the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
The High Court of Iuſtice.
1650.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Reſpondent (with the Favour of this Honorable
Court) reſerving and praying to be allowed the Benefit,
and Liberty of making further Anſwer, if it ſhal be Neceſſary.
In all humbleneſſe for the preſent Anſwer offereth to this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable
Court.</p>
            <p>That by the Letter and genuine ſenſe of the Act entituled
An Act for eſtabliſhing an High Court of Juſtice. <hi>The ſaid
Court is not qualified to try a Freeman of</hi> England (ſuch as the
Reſpondent averreth himſelf to be <hi>for life in Caſe of Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For that: 1. <hi>The ſaid Court is not Conſtituted a Court of Record;
neither hath Commiſſion returnable into a Court of Record.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that: 1. <hi>The State cannot upon Record</hi> (and but upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord
cannot at all) <hi>have that Account of their Freemen, which
Kings were wont to have of their Subjects, and States exact elſe
where at the hands of their Miniſters of Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>The Freemen, and thoſe who are or may be concerned in him, can
have no Record to reſort to, by which to preſerve the Rights due
to him and them reſpectively.</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>A writ of Errour</hi> in caſe of erronious Judgment.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>A plea of Auterfoies acquit,</hi> in caſe of new queſtion for
the ſame fact.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>An Enlargement</hi> upon Acquitall.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>A Writ of Conſpiracy,</hi> not to be brought untill Acquitall,
againſt thoſe who have practiſed to betray the life of the
Reſpondent.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:29684:37"/>
1. <hi>The Writ of Errour is due by preſidents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paſchae 39. Ed. III. John of Gaunts Caſe Rot. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.
4. Ed. III. Num. 13. Count de Arundells Caſe. Rot.
Parliament 42. Ed. III. Num. 23. Sr. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Lees</hi> Caſe.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Auterfois acquit</hi> appears by:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wetherell</hi> and <hi>Darleis</hi> Caſe. 4. Rep. 43. <hi>Eliz. Vaux</hi> his
Caſe. 4. Rep. 33. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>The Enlargement</hi> appears by:</p>
            <p>Stat. 14. <hi>Hen.</hi> VI. chap. 1. Diers Reports fol. 121.
The year book of Ed. IV. 10. fol. 19.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>The writ of Conſpiracy,</hi> by:</p>
            <p>The Poulters Caſe. 9, Rep. fol. 55.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Court is to determine at a day; without account of their
proceedings, and have power to try, judge, and cauſe Execution:
but not to acquit or give Enlargement. So that the nocent are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
puniſhable; the injured &amp; betrayed not vindicable.</hi> Which are
defects incompatible with a Court of Juſtice, and inconſiſtent
with Juſtice it ſelf; and the honor of a Chriſtian Nation and
Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>The members of this Court, are by the ſaid Act directed to be
ſworn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>Not in Conſpectu populi;</hi> for the Freemans ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Not in words of Indifferency</hi> and obliging in equality.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>But in words of manifeſt partiality,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>You ſhall ſwear; That you ſhall well and truly, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the beſt of your skill and knowledge, <hi>execute the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
powers given you by this Act.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>If the Court be Triers and Judges too, it is humbly offered by the
reſpondent, that it is but reaſonable; that they ſhould be ſworn as
Triers; in the ſight of the Freeman who ſhall be upon his Triall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>And, That as Juſtices of Oyer and Terminer</hi> (They being au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed
to hear and determine by the words of the Act.
<hi>They ſhould take an oath, ſuch as is uſual &amp; equal, ſet down</hi> E. III
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:29684:38"/>
Viz: <hi>You ſhall ſweare, That well and lawfully you ſhall ſerve our
Lord the King, and his People in the Office of Iustice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And
that you deny to no man Common Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Or that this Court (taking Notice of ſuch high matters
as Treaſon, upon the guilt wherof the Freemens life de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends)
ſhould take an Oath (at leaſt) as equall as a Iuſtice
of the Peace. <hi>Daltons Iuſt. of Peace, fol.</hi> 13. the words are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do ſweare that I will do equall Right,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>according
to my beſt wit, cunning and power, after the Laws and Cuſtomes
of the Land, and the Statutes thereof made,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>4. If the Court will be Judges and Triers too: (for they have
power given them to conclude the Freemen, by the opinion
of the major number of twelve, holding ſome reſemblance
(but with a ſignall difference) with the verdict of a Jury)
it were but reaſonable that they ſhould take an Oath cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent
to that uſually adminiſtred to Iury-men. The
words are,</p>
            <p>You ſhall <hi>well and truly try, and true deliverance make, betweene
the Keepers of the Liberties of England, and the Priſoner at the Bar,
according to your Evidence.</hi> So help you God, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>5. When this Court (as it is now conſtituted) hath condemned
a Freeman, by applying their skill and knowledge to the
power given them, whether juſtly or not: the Oath injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
them by the Act 26. March 1650. is not broken, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally;
as to be exactible by man, though God will have
a better account.</p>
            <p>And therefore upon the whole matter premiſed: The
Reſpondent (ſaving as before) averreth for Law and
Reaſon; This Court by the words of the Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting
it; is not qualified, (in reſpect of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
defects) to paſſe upon him for life in caſe of
Treaſon. And praies this his 2<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. Anſwer may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,
with the <hi>Salvo's,</hi> and regiſtred.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Euſebius Andrewes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:29684:38"/>
            <head>The third Anſwer of Col. Euſebius Andrews
Eſquire, to the Honorable, The High
Court of Juſtice 1650.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Reſpondent (with favour of this Honourable
Court) reſerving and praying to be allowed the benefit and
Liberty of making farther Anſwer, if it ſhall be neceſſary, in
all humbleneſs for preſent Anſwer offereth to this Honorable
Court,</p>
            <p>1. That it is his Right (if he admit this Court to be duly and
legally eſtabliſhed, and conſtituted as to their being a Court)
to be tried by his Peeres; men of his own condition and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>That it is within the power of this Court, by the Letter of the Act</hi>
26. March 1650. <hi>Or (at leaſt) not repugnant to the Act; to try him
by ſuch his Peeres,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>That it is his Right to be tried only ſo,</hi> appeares by:
<list>
                  <item>Mazna Charta <hi>chap.</hi> 29.</item>
                  <item>25. Ed. 3. chap. 9.</item>
                  <item>28. Ed. 3. chap. 4.</item>
                  <item>42. Ed. 3. chap. 3.</item>
                  <item>25. Ed. 1. chap. 1. and 2.</item>
                  <item>25. Ed. 3. chap. 2. and 4.</item>
                  <item>37. Ed. 3. chap. 18.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By all which this Right is maintainable; <hi>And the Proceedings
contrary thereunto will be held for none, and to be redreſſed as void
and erronious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that if the Lawes and Courts were not obſtructed in the
caſes of ſome ſort of Freemen of England, the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
contrary to theſe Lawes without a Jury of his
Peeres, were avoidable and reverſable by Writ of Error, as
appeares by the Preſidents vouched in the Reſpondents 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.
Anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:29684:39"/>
3. That it is in the Courts power, To try the Freeman, and
conſequently the Reſpondent by a Jury, of his Equalls; The
Court is humbly deſired to conſider the words of qualification.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>The Court is authoriſed; To hear and Determine: and ſo</hi> (if at
all Commiſſioners) <hi>then Commiſſioners of Oyer and Terminer,
and ſuch Commiſſioners, in their naturall Conſtitution and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall
execution, do proceeed againſt Freemen according to Law
by a Jury of their Peeres,</hi> and not otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Authoriſed to proceed to Triall, Condemnation and Execution:
But not reſtrained to the manner limitative: <hi>As,</hi> to Triall by the
Opinion of the Court, as Triers.</hi> Nor <hi>excluſive,</hi> As, <hi>to Triall
per pares. But is left in the Manner, as in the Judgement it ſelf,
To the Opinion of the major part of 12. and if they ſhall think
fit to try by a Jury, it will be no offence against the Act, there being
no prohibition to the contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though this Reſpondent inſiſteth upon his ſaid Right,
conſiſting with the Courts ſaid power, and the more to induce
the Court to grant him his ſaid Right; <hi>He humbly repreſenteth
the wrong done to himſelf, and in him to the Freemanzy of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
in the following particulars, againſt their juſt Rights depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
upon ſuch Trialls to be allowed or denied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>Challenges to his Triers peremptory, or with cauſe of Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>Seeing, hearing, and Counter-queſtioning the witneſſes</hi> for
clearing of the Evidence; in <hi>matter of Fact</hi> and <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>The being convicted or acquitted by a Full and fully conſented
verdict.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all which benefits as his undoubted Right, and the
Right of all the Freemen of <hi>England,</hi> the Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
maketh claim by theſe Reaſons, Laws and Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents
following.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:29684:39"/>
1. <hi>The benefit of Challenges by the learning of Stanford</hi> in his
Pleas of the Crown, Title Challenge fol. 150. To Challenge
35. without Reaſon ſhewed; and with Reaſon ſhewen, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
Number Adjudged 32. Hen. VI. in <hi>Poinings</hi> caſe, abriged
by Fitzherb. Tit. Challenge, fol. 26. allowed in Hillary 1. Iac.
S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Walter Rawley</hi> and <hi>Brooks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>To the hearing and queſtioning the value and weight of the
witneſſes.</hi> The Laws are plain in <hi>Stanfords</hi> pleas of the Crown
fol. 163. 164. Stat. 1. and 2. of Phil. and Mary, Chap. 10, 11.
1 Ed. VI. chap. 12. Cookes 3. Inſtitut. pag. 12. upon the words
in the St. 25. Ed. III. chap. 2. (Provablement atteint) <hi>Becauſe
the puniſhment was heavy, the proof muſt be punctuall, and not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
preſumptions or Inferences or ſtreins of wit, nor upon Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
ſimili, or Minori ad Majus, &amp;c.</hi> But upon good and
clear proofs, made good alſo by the Stat. 1. Ed. c. 6. 19. Ed. c. 1.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>A verdict by Jury paſſeth from all, or not at all, In this way of
proceeding by the Court immediatly: it paſſeth by way of concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
(or voting) the great fault found with the Star-Chamber;
and all Commiſſionary Courts, proceeding without preſentment or
or Enditement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. <hi>A Verdict paſſeth from a Jury before diſcharged, upon their
Affairs of buſines, or ſupplies of Nature; to prevent corruption by
mony or power. In this way of Triall a man may be heard to day,
and a Sentence given at leaſure, when the power and will of thoſe
by whom the Freeman is proſecuted, be firſt known.</hi> And from
ſuch a proceeding this Reſpondent can hope little equality;
he being (to his knowledge) forejudged already by them.</p>
            <p>And therefore (if at all this Honourable Court think fit
to proceed to a Triall, of this Reſpondent) he claims
the Benefit of <hi>Triall per pares: by Evidence viva voce.</hi>
And reſts on the Opinion of the Court; ſaving (as
formerly) Liberty of farther Anſwer, if over ruled.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And prayes that this his Anſwer and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vos
may be accepted and Regiſtred. Euſebius Andrews.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
