<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The key of saving knovvledge, opening out of the holy Scriptures, the right way, and straight passage to eternall life, or, A dialogue wherein the chiefe principles of the Christian religion are unfolded for the enabling of Christian people, to understand the Word of God ... composed by Geo. Walker ...</title>
            <author>Walker, George, 1581?-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-10">2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W360</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18400047</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18400047</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107490</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A67085)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107490)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1134:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The key of saving knovvledge, opening out of the holy Scriptures, the right way, and straight passage to eternall life, or, A dialogue wherein the chiefe principles of the Christian religion are unfolded for the enabling of Christian people, to understand the Word of God ... composed by Geo. Walker ...</title>
                  <author>Walker, George, 1581?-1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 113 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Badger,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLI [1641]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Puritans --  England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-01</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107490:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107490:1"/>
            <p>THE KEY
OF
SAVING
KNOWLEDGE,
Opening out of the
holy Scriptures, the right
way, and straight passage to
Eternall life.
OR
A Dialogue wherein the chiefe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
of Christian Religion are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded
for the enabling of Christian people,
to understand the Word of God and
to atteine to the true sense and
mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng thereof.</p>
            <p>Composed by <hi>GEO. WALKER</hi> B. of Div.
and Pastor of S <hi>Iohn</hi> the Evangelists Church
in <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON,
Printed by THO. BADGER.
M.DC.XLI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:107490:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107490:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>To his little flock, the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants
of the Parish of S. Iohn the
Evangelist in Watlingstreet in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
Georg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Walker their weake, but wellwish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>astor, commendeth this small token of
his unfeined lvoe, and hearty desire of their
eternall happinesse in the fruition of God; by
their fellowship and communion with him in
the Lord Iesus Christ.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved in the Lord
Christ, seeing now I
have spent one halfe of
my dayes in Preaching
to you and your prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors
the Gospell of Christ, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding
the sacred Scriptures, &amp; in
watching and labouring for the good
of your soules, to wit, for the space of
29 yeares, untill there is not one left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live
of all those inhabitants, who were
masters of families at my first coming
to this place, and did all with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb facs="tcp:107490:3"/>
and voyce make choyce of me to
be their Pastor: I hold it high time
for me, to thinke of my departure from
hence by putting off this earthly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,
and of leaving you as your
predecessors who were my first flocke,
have left me their Pastor behind them
to feed you a succeeding generation.
And least my labour and paines,
which I spent among them for the
good of their soules should seeme to die
with them, and to bee buried in their
graves: I have thought good to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new
the memory of them; and to leave
to the World some Monuments of
that Doctrin I have Preached to them
heretofore, as also to you of latter
times, by Gods gracious assistance,
though in great weaknesse of body, yet
with a willing mind, and with a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
never daunted with any mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings
and threatenings of potent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries,
and malicious persecutors.
The principall heads and true plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
of which doctrine I have brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:107490:3"/>
comprised, and compendiously set
forth in this short Dialogue, which
containes in it the principles and
foundations of Christian Religion
and which I do here commend to you,
as a testimony of that unfeigned love
which I beare to you, and of my fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
desire of the salvation of your
soules. I have already published, and
have ready for the Presse divers lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
Treatises, wherein are conteined
many particular doctrines which may
be reduced to these principall heads;
and are there largely handled, plainly
opened, and fully proved by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
and the true use of them shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in such manner as they have beene
by my mouth publikly preached among
you. But this golden Key, which is
the quintessence of them all, will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
Heaven unto you, if you can learn
to use it aright. It is made of divine
metall, even the Word of God revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
from Heaven, which is more pure
than the most refined gold. It will
<pb facs="tcp:107490:4"/>
teach you by a short and compendious
way to know God, not only in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of Essence in his essentiall attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes;
In the Trinity of persons, and
in his Works of Creation, and actuall
Providence overruling mans fall, and
disposing it and all the evils which
entered in by it, to his own glory, and
the good of his Elect: but also in
Iesus Christ, in whom to know him
the only true God is eternall life, as
our Saviour testifieth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 12. 3.
Here Gods eternall Counsell and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree
of Predestination is discovered:
Here you may learn the saving works
of God, in and by Christ, God and
man humbled in our nature. What
love God hath shewed in giving his
Son for us; and what Christ hath
done and suffered for our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
Here you may see what saving
works God works by his Spirit, shed
on his Elect through Christ, as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation,
Renovation, effectuall
calling, Vnion with Christ, Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption,
<pb facs="tcp:107490:4"/>
Communion of his ransome
for Redemption, of his Righteousnesse
for Iustification, of his satisfaction
for Remission of sins, and Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.
And what Gods Spirit
works in us and by us, as Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
Sanctification, Faith, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
and all holy graces; and how
and by what meanes he enables us to
apply Christ and his benefits unto us,
and to enioy him and them for Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
and also doth beget and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease
grace in his Elect, to wit, by
the Word preached and heard, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments
rightly administred and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,
faithfull and fervent Prayer,
and the like. And how these worke
in the Elect to eternall life and bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednesse,
and are abused by wicked
reprobates, to their owne everlasting
damnation and destruction. These
things have I written to you Fathers
and Masters, that you may read them
your selves, and commend them to
your children and families; I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb facs="tcp:107490:5"/>
them to you Young men, that
you may grow strong, and may over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
the wicked one. And I commend
them to you litle children; that you
may learne to know his name, and that
your sins may be forgiven you for his
names sake. If after so much preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
&amp; teaching you be found ignorant
&amp; unprofitable, it is because the God of
this World hath blinded your minds,
least the light of the glorious Gospell
of Christ, who is the image of God,
should shine unto you. This word
will be to you the savour of death unto
death, and this booke shall witnesse
for me against you, that you are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
ignorant and a lost people. But
if, as I hope, and pray fervently and
wish from my heart; You do cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
receive the love of this Truth:
then shall my Doctrine bee to you the
savour of life unto life, and wee shall
both together, I of my worke and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
in preaching, and you of your
reverence in hearing, and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="tcp:107490:5"/>
in obeying the Word Preached,
receive the reward of righteousnesse,
which Christ hath purchased for
them that beleeve and obey the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell,
even the Crown of glorie, which
never fadeth. This briefe summe of
Christian Religion, with other more
large Treatises I have written in my
bonds, for the common benefit of you
and others, to testifie unto you, that
the many waters of troubles and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutions,
which I suffer for the
Truth sake, which I have preached
unto you, cannot quench my love to
you, nor my desire of your salvation,
nor hinder mee from labouring for
your good. In all which I seeke not
yours, but you. And as I have prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
the Gospell freelie to you, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
seeking any of your temporall
goods, for my ministring of spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
things plentifullie unto you; but
spending besides my spirits, much
substance over and above the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues
of my smal Benefice, which from
<pb facs="tcp:107490:6"/>
you I have received; so I commend
to you freely this and all other works
and labours of my love, which if you
do lovinglie accept and use, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy
to your own advantage, I shall
thinke my work in some good measure
rewarded, and shall ever remaine a
faithfull labourer for the good of your
soules, according to the utmost of my
power, and</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your welwilling, though
weake Pastor,
GEO. WALKER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107490:6"/>
            <head>A briefe Dialogue, wherein
the Father examineth his Son,
concerning the principles of
Religion, in which he hath formerly
instructed him.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y deare Child, why doest
thou complaine because
of thy sicknesse, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
paines and infirmities
which often doe befall
thee, seeing thou by thy
sins pullest them upon thee, and causest
God thus to punish and correct thee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answer.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed in my book of the of the Psalmes
of <hi>David,</hi> I am taught to confesse, that
I was shapen in iniquity, and that in
sin hath my mother conceived me, but
this is the fault of you that are my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
from whom I received in my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107490:7"/>
birth and with my first being this
sinfull corruption.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>It is true, that wee brought thee into
this world a poore sinfull wretch. But
doest thou not know, that this corruption
commeth not from our selves, as the first
causes of it, but from our first parents in
whom thou and we and all mankind have
sinned against God, and lost that image
and likenesse of God, in which wee were
created, and are so infected with the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d malice of the Devill, which hee
breathed into our first parents, that wee
have no power, or will to do the good
which God requireth of us in his Law;
but are forward to run into all sins which
God forbiddeth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>I remember now when you put me
in mind of it, that you have taught me
oftentimes, that God created all
things good at the first, and in <hi>Adam</hi>
he created all man-kind in his owne
image and likenesse; and that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill
by the Serpent did tempt the
woman, and breathed into her his
poyson and drew her into sin, and by
her infected <hi>Adam,</hi> who was the
root and stock of all man-kind; and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107490:7"/>
by drawing him into transgression,
did corrupt him and all man-kind,
defaced Gods image in us al, and stai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
and defiled our nature, so that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versince
we are by nature children of
wrath and disobedience, who of our
selves have no power to will or do
any good, but do run into sin and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall
transgression continually.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>I see and perceive by this, that you
are ready to forget those instructions of
godlinesse which you have often learned,
and have need to have your memory often
rubbed up. And therefore I will stirre
you up to remember the things which I
have often taught you, by asking you
questions concerning the chiefe points of
Christian Religion which you have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
that they may be more deeply prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in your mind, and that you may have
them more ready to put them in practise
when occasion shall be offered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>I acknowledge my selfe bound in a
double bond of thankefulnesse unto
you, both for your godly paines in
t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aching me saving Knowledge, and
for your fatherly care, to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
the things which you have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107490:8"/>
taught me, that I may both beleeve
and practise the things which God
requireth of me, for the obteining of
eternall life, and blessednesse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>My paines of teaching you, are a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
to me, when I see you willing to bee
instructed. And if you answer readily
the questions which I shall aske you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the grounds of Religion, which I
have heretofore taught you, I shall rejoice
in hope and confidence that God hath
chosen you to be a vessell of honour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
you to the state of Grace, and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
you for the state of glory in Heaven.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>I acknowledge with all thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
Gods infinite love, mercy and
bounty to me, in that hee hath ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
me to be borne of Godly and
Christian parents, who as they were
meanes to bring me into the world, a
corrupt sinfull child of <hi>Adam,</hi> so are
Gods speciall instruments to beget me
to God a new creature in Iesus Christ,
by instructing me in his holy Word,
by which his holy Spirit doth take
possession of my soule, worketh in me
Faith, and renueth me after the image
of Christ; wherefore I am ready ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107490:8"/>
to my best understanding and
memory to answer every question
which you shall aske, concerning the
things which I have before heard and
learned from your mouth, humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching
God to print in my heart,
and to enable me by his grace to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise
in my life the things, which by
your often urging and pressing are
printed in my memory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>My first Question therefore shall be
about that which is the first work of God,
by which he gave to man-kind their first
being, I meane the creation of Adam
and all man-kind in him, tell mee what
you have been taught concerning it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>First, I have learned that God cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated
the whole world and all things
therein, <hi>Gen. 1. &amp;</hi> 2.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What God is he who did performe and
perfect so great a work?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </speaker>
               <p>He who is the one only true God,
and besides whom there is no other
God, <hi>Deut. 6. 4. &amp; Isay</hi> 45. 5.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What a one do you conceive this God
to be?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>I conceive him to bee such a one as
his most proper name <hi>Jehovah</hi> doth
signifie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:107490:9"/>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What doth that name signifie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It signifieth that he is and hath his
being of himselfe from all eternity,
without beginning and without end,
and that bee giveth being, motion,
breath, life, and all other things, to
all creatures which live, move, and
breath, and to all other things which
have been, are, or shall bee in the
world, and without him nothing
can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e or come to passe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What do you learn from thence?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>I learne, First, that God is most ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute
of himselfe, and depends upon
none other, neither needeth, either
for his being, glory, or blessednesse
any help, or for the increase of them.
Secondly, that he is before all things,
and is the first cause of them. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
that he is eternall, even one who
was before all times, and is and shall
be the same for ever, without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
and without end. Fourthly,
that he is immutable and unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
in his nature, essence and being,
and in his counsels, will and all other
his attributes and properties. Fiftly,
that he is most perfect, one who wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107490:9"/>
nothing, but hath in him all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies
to the full, so that nothing
can bee added to him to increase his
goodnesse or blessednesse. Sixthly,
that he is infinite and incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible,
no tongue can utter, no eye can
see, nor eare heare, nor heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
nor reason and understanding
comprehend him or his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Wherein doth his infinitnesse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It consists in this, that he hath no
bounds, nor limits, but is above all
degrees of comparison, his whole es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence
is at all times pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sent in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;<note place="margin">1 Kin. 8. 27</note>
and neither Heaven, nor the
Heaven of Heavens, nor all places in
the World can conteine him, or
measure his Substance. He is infinit
in Wisdome, Knowledge, Power,
Goodnesse, Mercy, Iustice, Will,
Counsell, and all other Attributes and
Properties, able to do whatsoever he
will.<note place="margin">Psa. 147<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5</note> He seeth and knoweth all
things, which are, have beene, shall
be,<note place="margin">Isa. 46. 10.</note> or can be, and his Will is the rule
of all things, and is limitted to no
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107490:10"/>
rule or law, but is it selfe the rule and
law of all things.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>If God be infinite in Essence and Will,
and all Attributes, and wholy present
in all places by his whole Essence, and all
his Attributes: How comes it to passe
that he sheweth his glory above the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens
more than in the World which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
and in one place hee do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h shew more
power, and justice, and in another place,
and to other persons hee sheweth more
goodnesse, gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and mercy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>There is great difference betweene
God, as he is in himselfe, and as he is
seene, felt, and apprehended by his
creatures in his Word, and Workes:
Though he is Omnipotent and can do
all things, yet he doth not worke all
things in all to the full, according to
his infinite power, but only so much
as he pleaseth, when, &amp; where and in
whom he will, as in his Wisdome he
thinkes fit for every one Neither can
wee see and conceive Gods Essence,
and properties in themselves, but in
the effects and works of them, which
are limitted by his Will and Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.
And though hee worketh by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107490:10"/>
degrees and by measure: Yet his Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence
and essentiall properties are
without measure and degree, and his
Word is fitted to our capacy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What other properties do you conceive
to be in God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>There is no shadow of excellency,
Vertue, Goodnesse, or Grace in any
creature, but it is in God Essentially,
and Substancially, one and the same
thing with his very Essence and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance.
He is Essentially, Good, Wise,
Iust, Mercifull, Gracious and Loving,
and even Goodnesse, Wisdome, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice
and Mercy it selfe:<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4. 8.</note> And as the
Apostle saith, that God is Love, so
we may truely and most properly say
of him, that he is Goodnesse, Wisdom,
Iustice, and Mercy; and yet hee is in
himselfe a most pure and simple Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence,
free from all mixture, composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
and division.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Wherein doth this purity, and simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of God consist?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It consists, First in this, that
though God filleth Heaven &amp; Earth,
and is in and withall creatures: Yet
his substance is not mingled with any
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107490:11"/>
of them. Secondly, that hee is not
compounded of things different, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of act and power as other Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
substances are, nor of matter
and forme, Substance and Accidents,
such as quantity, quality and the like,
as bodily creatures are. Thirdly, that
he cannot bee divided into severall
parts, as mens bodies are. He is not
of the same kind and nature with any
other thing whatsoever: But is a
most pure simple Spirit, or Spirituall
substance, in comparison of whom the
most pure Spirits and Angels are but
grosse substances and impure: In a
word his Substance and properties
are all one and the same thing; and
wheresoever he is present, there his
whole Essence, and all and every one
of his essentiall properties are actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
present, even in all places at
once.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>If God be only one most pure and
simple: Why do the Scriptures speak of
three persons, the Father, the Sonne,
and the Holy Ghost, and doe call e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
one of them IEHOVAH and
God?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:107490:11"/>
Though there is but one God, and
one Iehovah, even one most pure and
simple Nature and Essence: Yet in
this one pure simple, undivided Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence,
there are three distinct persons,
the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost, all
which three are but one Iehovah, and
one God, and every one of them is
called Iehovah and God; because
they are all of one and the same simple
and Divine Essence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How are they then three persons di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguished
one from another?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>They are distinguished, not by
their Essence, and Nature, which in
all three is one singular and undivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:
but by their personall subsistence
and properties.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Which are they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>First, the Father subsists of himself
and is not begotten of any, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets
the Son: The Son is begotten of
the Father from all eternity, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives
his personall subsistence, from
the person of the Father alone: The
Father and the Son together breath
out the Spirit, and the Spirit hath his
subsistence by proceeding from them
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107490:12"/>
from all eternity. Secondly, in order
the Father is the first, the Son the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,
and the Holy Ghost the third;
though in time and dignity, none of
them is before or after other; but all
are coeternall, consubstantiall and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall
of the same dignity, glory and
Majesty.<note place="margin">Phil. 2. 6.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How can he who is Jehovah and God
eternall, proceed and receive his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonall
subsistence from another? Seeing
Jehovah the true God, is of himselfe and
can receive nothing from any?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is true that the persons conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
according to their nature and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
which is common to all three,
and is one and the same in them all,
cannot beget nor be begotten, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
one from another. For if God
absolutely considered, could beget, as
he is an absolut essence, or be begotten,
or proceed; then there might be more
Gods than one. But a person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonall
subsistence in that one simple es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence
of God may beget another per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
but not another God, and may be
begotten and proceed, not from the
simple essence of God, but from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107490:12"/>
person in that one Essence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
Wherefore the Son is begotten not as
he is one and the same Essence with
the Father, but as hee is another per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
in that Essence: and so the Holy
Ghost proceeds from the Father and
th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Son, as he is another person in the
same Essence: And so Iehovah
the true God doth proceed from
none, nor receiveth any thing from
any: but a person which subsists in
the Essence of God, and is Iehovah
the true God, receiveth subsistence
from another person in the same Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>I see you do rightly conceive of God
the Creator, both in the unity of his Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence,
and in the Trinity of persons. Now
tell me which of the three persons created
the world?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Though the Father is called the
Creator of whom are all things: Yet
he alone did not create the world, nor
any thing in it, but the Son and the
Spirit also did work with the Father,
and had an equall hand in the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of every thing: For in all the
outward works of God, that is the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107490:13"/>
joynt operation of all the three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How doth it appeare that the creation
is the work of all the three persons?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>By plaine testimonies of holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
for in the description of the
Creation, we have expresse mention
of the Word, that is the Sonne, and of
the Spirit, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 1, 2, 3. and <hi>David,
Psal.</hi> 33. 6. saith, by the Word of the
Lord were the Heavens made, and all
the Host of them by the breath of his
mouth, that is, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the son &amp; the Spirit.
For the Sonne is called the eternall
Word, one God with the Father, by
whom all things were made, and
without whom nothing was made
that was made, <hi>John 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 1, 2, 3. And
the Apostle, <hi>Colos.</hi> 1. 16. saith that by
Christ the Son all things were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
that are in Heaven and Earth, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible
and invisible, and by him all
things consist.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>You have well declared the Truth
concerning the Creator, now tell mee
whereof the World was made?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>God made all things of nothing at
the first, to wit, the highest heavens
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107490:13"/>
with the Angels and all the Host of
them; and also the Earth that is the
rude masse without forme and voyd,
which was the common matter of all
the visible world, and this is called
simple and primary creation. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
God created out of that
rude matter the Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ht, that is,
the Fiery and Starry Heavens and
the large Element of the Aire,
which is called the Firmament, and
the Sea, and the dry Land, and
then out of those foure Elements
hee formed and made all other
things, as the Sunne, Moone and
Stars, the Herbs, Plants, and Trees;
the Stones and Mettals, the Fishes,
Birds and all other living creatures;
and this is called, secondary creation,
because all those things were not
made first and immediatly of nothing:
but secondarily were formed out of a
matter, which God had before crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
of nothing; and so al creatures had
their first beginning, and being out of
nothing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> so mighty and omnipotent
is Gods hand farre above the reach of
mans reason.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:107490:14"/>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>After what manner did God create
the World and all things therein?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The Scriptures teach us that hee
created all things: First, most freely
by the liberty of his Will, not by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity
of Nature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Secondly, not rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
but according to his most wise
Counsell and eternall purpose. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
with great ease, and facility, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
paines, toyle or labour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How doth that appeare?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>By the words of <hi>Moses</hi> in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story
of the Creation, where it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded,
that God in the creation did
but say let things be, and so they were
made; so he is said to creat the Light,
the Firmament, the Waters, the dry
Land, the Lights in Heaven, the
Hearbes and Trees, and all things
living and moving on the Earth and
in the Sea. He said let them be, and
they were made and brought into
being, <hi>Gen. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 6, 9, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How doth this speech shew that God
created all things in such manner as you
have said, to wit, freely, wisely, and with
ease and facility?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Very plainely, for these words are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107490:14"/>
not to bee understood properly that
God uttered a sound of words: but
the phrase is Metaphoricall borrowed
from the doings of men. For workes
done by necessity of Nature, men do
without consulting or speaking, or
any pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>scription or direction given
by word of mouth. The things which
men first speake of, and then do, are
done by liberty of will; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
this phrase teacheth us, that
the Creation was a work done, not
by necessity of Nature, but by liberty
of will, that is a work which God, if
he had so been pleased, might have
left undone, and did therefore do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
it was his free will to do it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
wise men do not command,
or prescribe things to be done unlesse
they have consulted, purposed, and
determined, that they shall be so done.
Their words by which they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
and prescribe the doing of great
works, are the open manifestation of
their mind, will purpose, and decree;
and the first thing which belongs to
the actuall performing and effecting
of the worke. And therefore this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107490:15"/>
phrase teacheth us, that as God in his
eternall Counsell had wisely purposed
and decreed; so now God the Father
by his Word the Son, and by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
began to put his wise counsell in
execution, and actually to create and
make all things, and to bring them
outwardly into being according to
his wise counsell, and as hee had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
purposed in himselfe, so the
creation was a work not rashly done,
but wisely according to counsell.</p>
               <p>Thirdly this phrase sheweth, that
as among men, nothing can bee done
with greater ease and facility, and
with lesse toyle or labour, then when
they only say the word let it be done,
and presently it is done, without any
more paines: So it was with God in
the creation, he did as easily and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
paines create all things as a man
doth a thing by saying let it be, which
of al things is most easie as experience
teacheth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What speciall things have you learned
concerning the creation of man-kind?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Foure things especially.</p>
               <p>First, that God consulted about it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107490:15"/>
saying, Let us make man.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that hee made man after
his owne Image and likenesse, male
and female.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that he gave them domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
over all other creatures in the
inferiour world.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that he created a place of
pleasure for them to dwell in, and
there placed them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How doe you understand these
words? And God said, Let us make
man in our image and after our like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>They are thus to bee understood,
not that God the Father, Sonne,
and Holy Ghost did then first enter
into consultation about mans creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
But that as God in the common
counsell of the blessed Trinity, had
from all eternity purposed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed;
so now hee began to put his
decree into execution and actually to
create man, after such a manner and
such a creature as hee had decreed,
even stamped with his Image,
fit to rule over other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:107490:16"/>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Shew me more particularly how God
created man in his own image male and
female?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>First, he made <hi>Adam</hi> of the dust
of the earth, and with breath of life,
created a soule in him, and hee made
him one only, that he might bee the
common stocke and roote of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
from whom the woman also
might have her beginning, and bee
made of his flesh and bone, even of a
fleshy rib taken out of him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he made them both in his
own image, the man first, and when
man appeared so excellent above all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
creatures, that among them all
there could not be found a mate, or
help meet for him; then hee tooke a
rib of the man and made a female, the
woman meete for him in the same
Image, and after the same like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Wherein did the Image <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God consist,
and how was man like unto God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>This Image did consist, first
and principally in his Soule, s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>conda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
in his body, and thirdly in his
whole person.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:107490:16"/>
First, in the substance of his soule,
he was like to God; For as God is a
Spirit, so mans soule was created a
Spirit or spirituall living substance.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in the powers and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties
of his soule, to wit, his reason,
will, desires, and affections, in all
which created perfect and upright in
him, he was like unto God; For as
God knoweth and understandeth all
things: so man by his reason was
able to know and understand all
things, meet for him. As God hath
liberty of will, so man had liberty of
will to do all things, which by his
upright reason, he knew to bee good
&amp; in his power. As God loveth good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
and delighteth in it, so man lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
and desired all good things,
which his upright reason and will
did lead him unto. In all this did
the Image of God primarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How did he beare Gods Image, and
was like to him in his body?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>First, in the upright stature, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
glory, and Majesty of his body;
Secondly, in the abilities, actuity and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107490:17"/>
fitnesse of all members of his body, to
move, work and performe all things,
unto which his upright reason, will,
and affections did move him and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How was man like to God in his whole
person?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>First, as he was perfectly upright,
both in soule, and body, and in his
whole person conformable to Gods
Will, and fit and able to serve and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey
him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as he was in his whole
person, soule and body, endowed
with all ability and fitnesse, to rule
over all other visible living creatures,
and to bee the Lord of them; so hee
bare the Image of God, and was like
to him the supreme Lord of all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Did not Gods Image in Adam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist
in holinesse also, as some do teach
from the Apostles words, <hi>Ephes. 4.
24.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The Image of the first <hi>Adam</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted
only in naturall uprightnesse, as
wise <hi>Salomon</hi> teacheth, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7. 29.
and his perfections, gifts, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments
were only naturall. But
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107490:17"/>
holynesse is a property of the 2 <hi>Adam</hi>
Christ, and is a supernaturall work
and gift of the Spirit, which in our
new birth is shed on us only through
Iesus Christ, and is the image of the
new man made a new creature in
Christ, as the Apostles words plainly
sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w in the fore-named place, <hi>Ephes.
4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</hi> &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 49. &amp; <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 6. If
man had been holy, he could not have
fallen as hee did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Wherein did mans dominion over the
creatures consist?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It consisted in this, that as man was
in nature above them all, and had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
and wisdome to order and rule
them: So God made them all obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
to man, and put in them a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
and love of man, insomuch that
they delighted, and rejoyced to look
on man and to come to him at his call
and to shew their nature and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
qualities, that man might ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire
Gods manifold wisdome shewed
in their creation, and in the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manship
of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Had not man power to sacrifice,
kill, and eat them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as men have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107490:18"/>
had since the fall?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>No verily, For all death, groaning
and vanity of the creatures came in
by mans sin: Mans meat in the state
of innocency was only fruits of trees,
and herbes bearing seed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1 29.
But after mans fall, and the promise
of Christ, God through Christ inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
mans dominion over the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
and appointed the killing and
sacrificing of birds, and beasts to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shew
Christs death for mans redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption
from sin, and withall gave the
flesh of them to man for meat, and
their skins to cloath him; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
wee see that wee gaine more by
Christ, than we lost in <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What place of pleasure was that
which God made for mans dwelling and
habitation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It was the Garden which God plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in <hi>Eden,</hi> the most fruitfull place of
<hi>Mesopotamia,</hi> in which he made to
grow out of the ground, all trees plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant
to the sight, and good for food;
and in that Paradise of pleasure, all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights
did abound which the world
could afford to a naturall man. A ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107490:18"/>
divided into foure streames wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
it, and there was no want of any
thing, which mans upright heart
could conceive or desire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What service did God require of man
for all this bounty and goodnesse, and all
the delights and honour bestowed on
him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Hee required no more service of
man over and above that which his
own reason, will, naturall appetite
and affection did lead him to do of
himselfe; but only to abstaine from
the fruit of one tree, even the Tree of
Knowledge of good and evill, <hi>Gen.</hi>
2. 16. 17.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Was the fruit of that Tree by nature
evill, and hurtfull?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </speaker>
               <p>Surely no, for all things which
God made were very good, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 31
and the fruit was pleasant to the eye,
and good for food, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </speaker>
               <p>Why then did God forbid man to eat
of it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </speaker>
               <p>For good reasons.</p>
               <p>First, to exercise and prove mans
obedience.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to shew that all other
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107490:19"/>
trees were of free gift given to man,
and that God might as well have
kept back all other trees, as this, if hee
had would, which consideration
might justly have moved man to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
Gods large bounty in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
him dominion over the whole
Earth, the Sea, and all the creatures in
them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>When God had made the world and al
things therein very good, did he not by
his wisedome and providence, rule, order
and governe them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Yes verily, he did and doth still by
his Wisdome so order, governe, and
dispose all things, that without his
Will nothing can come to passe in all
the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Wherein doth that Providence of God
consist?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>First, in doing and working all the
good which comes to passe in the
World.<note place="margin">Heb. 1. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Colo. 1. 17</note> For as he gave being to all
things; so he susteineth and keepeth
them in their being by the word of
his power, and by him all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist.
There is no good done in the
world, but he bringeth it to passe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107490:19"/>
immediatly by his own hand, or
else by the power which he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
and continueth to his creatures,
and by his inclining and moving
them to it. For hee worketh in
them both to will and to do, <hi>Philip.</hi>
2. 13.</p>
               <p>Secondly, his Providence consists
in permitting and suffering his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
to abuse his power and strength
which he gives them, and to imploy
it to sin and transgression. And if
God had not wittingly and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
suffered the Devil and the evill An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
to sin and fall, and to tempt and
draw man into sinne, no evill nor
sinne could have entered into the
world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How could God who is infinit in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
willingly suffer sinne to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the World, which is a thing so hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
to him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Hee suffered it in his Wisdome and
Goodnesse, not out of any pleasure,
which he takes in sin, or any evill, or
in the destruction of his creatures, but
because by his Omnipotency hee can
out of evill bring greater good, than
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107490:20"/>
any, which is lost and forfeited by
sin. For by hating sin hee sheweth
his holinesse, by punishing it his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,
by redeeming his elect from it,
his mercy, free grace, and goodnesse,
by the evils which his elect do under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go
for their tryall and correction, and
the misery and torment which they
see inflicted on reprobates, they are
made more sensible of their own hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse,
and more blessed in the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of God and of his glory at last.
And as a man who was never pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
with hunger, and paine of sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
cannot so fully know the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of health, nor so sweetly tast and
relish his meat; so without sight and
sense of evill we cannot so fully know,
nor so sweetly enjoy our own happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
nor so perfectly rejoyce and
glory in the fruition of God and all
his goodnesse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>If sin comes to passe by the will and
providence of God, how is God excused
from being the author of sin?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Very well, For the bare willing
and permitting of a thing, makes not
him who willingly permits it the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107490:20"/>
and cause thereof. To make
God the author of sin, or any way
guilty of it; there are three things
required. First, that God do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
counsell, or perswade men to
commit sin: Or secondly, that he
move, incline, or stir them up to it.
Or thirdly, that when he willingly
permits and suffers it, and is able to
hinde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, he be bound by some Law
and bond of duty (as men are) to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
it to the utmost of his power, and
in no case to will it. But Gods Will
hath no Law besides it selfe; as he is
supreme Lord of all, so he may will or
not will where hee pleaseth. Hee is
bound by no Law to restraine men
from sin: Hee may have mercy on
whom he will, and whom he will, he
may leave to be hardened. Neither
doth God command,<note place="margin">Rom. 9. 18</note> counsell or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade
any man to sin by his Word;
but hath given a Law to the contrary,
by which he forbids sin under paine
of death. And never did hee tempt,
move, incline, or stir up any to sinne:
Therefore he can neither bee the cause
or author of sinne,<note place="margin">Iam. 1. 13.</note> nor any way
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107490:21"/>
partaker in the staine and guilt
of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>But doth not Gods Providence
meddle any more with sinne, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to permit it willingly and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Yes certeinly, God by his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
doth hinder and limit sin, that
it doth not break forth in all wicked
men, nor prevaile to the utmost ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity.
He doth also order and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
the sins of the wicked to his own
glory, and the good of his elect: He
made the fiercenesse of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and
<hi>Senacherib</hi> turne to his honor, fame,
and praise; and the trechery of <hi>Judas</hi>
in betraying, and the cruelty and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> in murthering
Christ, he turned to the redemption
of the world, and the salvation of
his elect in Christ, by his overruling
power and goodnesse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>You have fully justified God from
being the Authour of sin. Now tell me
how man being made in Gods image per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
upright and good could bee
drawne to disobey his Commandement,
which was so just, equall and easie
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107490:21"/>
to bee observed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>By the power, malice and
subtlety of the Devill. For every
creature is in it selfe mutable, and
may decline and bee corrupted, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
it bee brought by Covenant
into Communion with God, who
onely hath immortality, and is of
himselfe unchangeable. Man though
made perfect with all naturall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
was Mutable in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency,
and therefore God made a
Covenant of life with him, upon
condition of his obedience, hee
gave him the Tree of life to bee
a seale of this Covenant, and to
confirme it, and to settle man so
steadfastly in that naturall estate,
that hee could not have beene se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
by any power or subtlety
of the Devill, if hee had received
the seale by eating of the Tree of
life. But the Devill prevented
our first parents, before they had
time to eat of that Tree, and
subtlety by the Serpent insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated
himselfe into the woman,
and by her, into the man
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107490:22"/>
before they were setled and establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by the sealing of the covenant,
breathed into them infidelity and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition,
and by his lyes brought them
into an evill opinion of God, and so
drew them into disobedience and
transgression of Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and made both <hi>Adam</hi> and all
mankind, who were then in his loyns
guilty before God, worthy of death,
and subject to all the evils and curses
which follow sin and disobedience.
For <hi>Adam</hi> the root and stock
being corrupted, and stained with
sin; all the branches which spring
from him, must needs bee partakers
of the same corruption, and of the
malice &amp; enmity against God, which
the Devill breathed into him. Thus
the Devil was the first author of mans
sin and fall, and the Serpent was his
instrument.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>If this be so, why do not the Devill
the author, and the Serpent his instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
beare the punishment, but man
and his posterity suffer for it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </speaker>
               <p>The Devill and the Serpent are
cursed for this sinne with an eternall
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107490:22"/>
curse, from which there is no redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
And <hi>Adam</hi> because by infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
pride, ambition, and an ill and
false opinion of God, which Satan
suggested into his heart, did willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
yeeld to the temptation, and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressed
Gods Commandement, and as
a voluntary agent did work with the
Devill in that act of disobedience,
therefore hee is guilty: yet so as that
his sin is pardonable, and both he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
and all his Elect and Faithfull
posterity are redeemed from it by
Christ.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How comes it to passe, that so small
a thing as that wherein Adam transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
to wit, eating of a forbidden fruit is
counted so great a sin before God, and
brings on all man-kind so many evils and
curses?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The smaller the thing was in
which God required obedience of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi>
the greater was his sin, and the
more blame he deserved; in that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
received so many gifts from
God, and such large dominion over all
earthly creatures by the free gift of
God; he would not upon Gods just
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:107490:23"/>
Command which was so easie to bee
observed, obey his Creator in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steining
but onely from one Tree<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
Besides hee disobeyed God out of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity,
pride, ambition, a false opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
of God, and enmity against his
Majesty. For hee beleeved the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils
words, who said hee should not
dye, and not Gods Word, who had
said that in the day hee did eate hee
should surely dye. Hee in pride and
ambition sought by eating to become
as God; and imagined wickedly,
that God out of envie did forbid
him to eate, of purpose that hee
might not become wise as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe:
So that this disobedience in
so small a matter did include in
it all kindes of sinnes, whereby
the whole Law of God is trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>You have well shewed that this
act of disobedience was an heinous sin.
Now tell me what evils it brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
man-kind?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>First, it stript man naked of all
those perfections of Nature, and all
that uprightnesse and image of God,<note place="margin">Gen 3. 10</note>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:107490:23"/>
in which hee was created; so that
his person, which before for the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
majesty, and comelinesse of it was
reverenced, loved, and served of all
creatures, came to be feared and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred
of them, as an enemy, his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse
made him ashamed, and his
paines and sorrows made his life a
burden to him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, mans nature and frame,
was so stained and corrupted by this
sin, that neither he nor any of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity
can understand things aright,
nor will,<note place="margin">Psa. 49. 12</note> nor do any good; but are
altogether perverse &amp; froward, prone
to all wickednesse, very slaves of sinne
and Satan, and by Nature children of
wrath.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Gen. 3. 17.</note> it brought a curse upon
the ground for mans sake, so that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
his hard labour and sweet it yeelds
no good fruit, but only thornes, thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles
&amp; other noysom weeds &amp; plants.<note place="margin">vers. 19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Lastly, it brought all mankind in
bondage to death, both temporal (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
is such a corruption of the body, as
doth separat the soule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it &amp; make it
utterly unfit for the soule to lodge in)
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107490:24"/>
and also eternall, which is the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of him with eternall destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
from the presence of God, and
from the glory of his power.<note place="margin">2 Thes. 1. 9.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Is there any hope of deliverance,
from this foule staine, &amp; guilt of sins, and
from death, and all evill of wrath,
which are the fruits and effects of it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>There is no hope of deliverance in
any thing which mans wit and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
can devise, or man by his art, skil,
and power can performe. All crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
in the world can yield him no
help. God only of his infinit mercy,
free grace, love and kindnesse to man-kind
hath from all eternity, ordeined
an all-sufficient Saviour, and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
even his only begotten son, who
immediatly after mans sin and fall,
did undertake for man, staid the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
of the sentence and punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of death, and was promised to
become the seed of the woman, and by
suffering death and all the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
due to sin in our nature,<note place="margin">Heb. 2. 14.</note> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme
man-kind from sin,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4. 8.</note> and death,
and to destroy the Devill, who had
the power of death, and to dissolve all
his workes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:107490:24"/>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Who is this Son of God, which did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake
to redeeme man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is the Lord Iesus Christ, who
was first promised under the name of
the seed of the woman, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15.
which should break the serpents head,
and afterward was promised to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,
Isaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> under the
name of the blessed seed,<note place="margin">Gen. 12 8. 22.</note> in whom all
the nations of the earth should be bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.
And to <hi>David,</hi> and by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
by the name of <hi>Messiah,</hi> that is
the annoynted Saviour of the seed of
<hi>David.</hi> And at last in the fulnesse of
the time, when hee was made flesh,
tooke our nature upon him, and was
borne of a Virgin, did beare the name
of Iesus; and is now preached and
made knowne to the world, under the
name of the Lord Iesus Christ.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Why did not Christ come in the flesh in
the beginning or first age of the world,
and worke mans redemption, that the
Fathers who lived under the old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
might bee redeemed and saved by
him, as we now are under the Gospell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The Incarnation of Christ, and all
things which he did and suffered for
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:107490:25"/>
our redemption in the dayes of his
flesh, were present with God from all
eternity, (as all times, and all things
which come to passe in all times past,
present and to come, are continually
present with him) and were as effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall
to satisfie his justice, appease his
wrath, and to purchase and procure
perfect salvation to men at his hands;
as they are now ever since they were
actually performed. And through
Christ promised, God did shed his
Spirit on the Fathers of old, as hee
now doth on us through Christ gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
and exhibited, and by the Spirit
united them to him in one spirituall
body, and wrought in them Faith, by
which they did (as it said of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham)</hi>
see the day of Christ beleeve in
him,<note place="margin">Iohn 8. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> were partakers of all his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits,
and were made conformable to
him both in his death and life by mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification
and sanctification.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Why did Christ come and satisfie for
sinfull men, in the mids of yeares between
the times of the Old and New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Because that was the most fit and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:107490:25"/>
seasonable of all times for man-kind
for divers reasons.</p>
               <p>First, if he had appeared in the first
ages of the world, the memory of him
would have been worne out. For as
the people of the Gentiles within a
few ages forgot the promises of
Christ made to <hi>Adam, Noah</hi> and <hi>Sem,</hi>
and lost the knowledge of them: so
men would have forgotten Christ,
and all his doings, and sufferings long
ago; for the world loveth changes,
and loathing old things, seeketh after
novelties.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the deferring of Christs
comming held the world in suspence
and expectation with promises from
age to age, still more plainely renued;
that after much longing his comming
might be so much more welcome, and
men might with greater joy receive
him.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the world increasing in sin
and corruption, and being growne so
hard, that weaker meanes and obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer
revelation could worke litle upon
men; it was Gods Wisdome to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
the appearance of Christ, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:107490:26"/>
the publishing of the powerfull Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell
for these latter evill days, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the fittest meanes for these har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
times.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, if Christ in our nature
had made satisfaction in the first ages
of the world, and had paid our ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some
so many ages before wee were
borne or had our being; it had not
been so equall and proportionable to
justice, as now it is, by reason of his
comming in the midst of yeares, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the Old and the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
For by this meanes Gods for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance
of the ransome and satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
for the sinnes of the Fathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
Christs death, is recompensed
with payment of our debt, and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
a full satisfaction for our sinnes as
much before hand, even many ages
before our committing of sinne, or
running in debt to his Majesty in our
own persons.</p>
               <p>Lastly, it was necessary that many
of the members of his elect and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
Church should by the Spirit bee united
to him, and by Faith have
Communion with him before and at
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:107490:26"/>
his comming &amp; appearing in the flesh,
that being the head of the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually
through them, He might by
Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion and imputation of the sins
of so great a body &amp; multitude, justly
suffer the punishments due to the sins
of his people even of them who were
in after ages to grow up into the same
mystical body by the same Spirit. If
he had beene borne in the beginning
of the world, before the Church of the
Old Testament had any actuall being,
he could not have been the actuall
head of the body, nor united to the
Church, which as yet was not in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
and so could not have borne the
sins of his Church, nor justly suffered
the punishment of them. Therefore
the Apostle very fitly cals the time of
Christs comming in the flesh the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of time, that is, the time most
seasonable, <hi>Gal. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 4.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What have you learned concerning
Christs person needfull to be knowne and
beleeved?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>I have learned, That as he was the
eternall Son of God, one and the same
God, and of the same nature and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:107490:27"/>
with the Father, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
hee did undertake, according to
Gods eternall Counsell to bee the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator
between God and man, and to
mediate for man from the day of his
fall; and as hee was promised to bee
the Seed of the woman, so hee did in
fulnesse of time assume and take into
personall union with himselfe, the
whole nature, and substance of a man,
and was made of the seed of <hi>Abraham</hi>
and <hi>David</hi> in the womb of a Virgin,
of their seed, a man like unto us in all
things, but without sin, even the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
one of God, and so was God and
man in one person.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How could hee bee borne a pure holy
man without sinne, of a woman, a
daughter of Evah, and of the same na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
with the rest of man-kind, who are
all corrupted in Adam?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>God Almighty, who alone is able
to bring a cleane thing out of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane,
did by his power over-shadow
the Virgin his mother, and the holy
Ghost came upon her,<note place="margin">Luk 1. 35.</note> and framed out
of her seed and substance an holy seed,
and so hee was conceived and borne
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:107490:27"/>
without sinne, perfectly holy both in
soule and body, and filled with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Ghost.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How could he being so perfectly holy,
be subject to infirmities, and to death, and
other punishments due to sin?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </speaker>
               <p>Though he knew no sin, yet he was
made sin for us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 21. and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
most holy and righteous in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,
he tooke all our sins upon him,
and bare all our sorrows and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
that he might thereby satisfie
Gods infinit justice, pay our ransome,
and redeeme and reconcile us unto
God, <hi>Isa.</hi> 53. 4, 6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How and by what meanes hath Christ
redeemed us from wrath, and wrought
our salvation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>By executing and performing the
office of a Mediator between God and
men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How is he a Mediator?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>As he is God the Son, equall with
the Father, so he is a person of infinite
value, and worthy to be accepted, and
able to make a full satisfaction for all
sin to Gods Iustice, and to pay a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some
of infinit value. And as hee is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:107490:28"/>
man of the same nature and substance
with all man-kind, and the first fruits
of the whole lumpe; so hee is fit to
make satisfaction in the same na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
which sinned, and is our brother
and friend, and one who is touched
with the feeling of our infirmities,<note place="margin">Iob 16. 21.</note>
and is compassionate towards us,<note place="margin">Heb. 2. 17. &amp; 4. 11.</note> and
deales faithfully for us. As he is God,
so he is too high to be a Mediator for
man, and as he is man, so hee is too
low to mediate and plead to God for
us sinners: But as he is God and man
in one person, so he is most fit to come
as a Mediatour betweene God and
men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Wherein doth Christs Mediation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>In the faithful execution of a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold
office:
<list>
                     <item>The first, of a Prophet.</item>
                     <item>The second, of a Priest.</item>
                     <item>The third, of a King.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How did he execute the office of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>By Prophecying, Preaching, and
Revealing the Will of God from the
beginning, both in his own person,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:107490:28"/>
and also by his Prophets, Apostles and
Ministers of the Word and Gospell.
In the old world he went forth in the
Spirit, and soake to the godly Fathers,
<hi>Enoch, Methushelah, Noah</hi> and others,
and by them preached to the wicked,
especially while the Arke was a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring,
as the Apostle testifieth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi>
3. 19. He in the forme of man, and
sometimes of an Angell spake to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,
Isaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 18. 26.
&amp; 32<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24. Hee was the Angell of the
Covenant, which appeared to <hi>Moses</hi>
in the bush, and said, <hi>I am the God of
Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the
God of Jacob,</hi> Exod. 3. Hee spake also
at sundry times, and in divers man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
as apparitions, dreames and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions
to the Fathers in times past, and
by his Spirit inspiring and moving
the Prophets, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 1. And in the
dayes of his flesh he preached the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell
with his own mouth. And as
after his Ascension, he sent down the
Holy Ghost upon his Apostles, and
gave them the gifts of Tongues, and
of Knowledge to Prophecy and
Preach the Gospell to all Nations,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:107490:29"/>
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2. So he is with them in their
true successors the Ministers of the
Gospell to the end of the world, <hi>Mat.</hi>
28. 20. And by his Spirit gives them
knowledge and utterance, to teach
and expound the Scriptures, and to
bring men to the saving knowledge
of the truth. And in a word he is the
great Prophet whom God promised
to raise up to his people, like unto
<hi>Moses,</hi> whom all ought to heare and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey
in all things, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 15. And no
other Prophets or Preachers, are to be
heard, but those which Preach in his
Name, truly according to his Word
conteined in the holy Scriptures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Wherein doth the office of his Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
consist?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>In making attonement betweene
God and men, both by offering up
himselfe, and all sufficient Sacrifice
for all our sins, in his obedience unto
death, and in suffering all punishments
due to sin, and by bringing in eternall
righteousnes, which is his perfect ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling
of the Law in the obedience of
his whole life, <hi>Dan. 9. 24. Rom.</hi> 8. 3, 4.
&amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 21. For in these two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:107490:29"/>
the whole work of mans redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption,
and the full ransome and sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
of attonement which is needfull
to reconcile men unto God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How can the sufferings of one man sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
for all men, and the righteousnesse
of one be able to justifie all that are to bee
justified?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The man Christ as hee fulfilled the
Law, and suffered in our nature, so his
righteousnesse and satisfaction is hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,
and is proper only to mankind,
for as man sinned, so man satisfied<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
But as this man Christ, is also God in
the same person: So his righteousnes
and satisfaction is Divine of infinite
value and worth, even the righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
and suffering of God; and that
is more than if all men had suffered e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
death, and fulfilled in their
own persons every jot and title of the
Law, and all the righteousnesse
thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>If Christs infinite Godhead doth adde
so much to his obedience performed in our
Nature, and makes his sufferings of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
worth and value: What need was
there of shedding his bloud unto death,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:107490:30"/>
and of suffering all the stormes of Gods
wrath, was not (as some say) one drop
of his bloud sufficient to redeeme the
world?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Though Christ is a person of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
value, because he is God; yet as
he could not be a compleat and perfect
Mediator, if hee had taken into his
person the body only of a man, and
not a complete Manhood consisting
both of soule and body: So suffering
in part, and obeying the Law in part,
could not bee made a complete sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction,
for justice requires a full
suffering of all kinds of punishment
due to man for sin, even of death it
selfe, and a perfect fulfilling of the
whole Law; otherwise there is no
righteousnesse: If one drop of Christs
bloud shed for sin had beene a suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
price of redemption: than it had
been injustice in God to exact more,
and undiscreet, and vaine prodigality
in Christ to poure out all his bloud,
and his soule to death, when one drop
was enough.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Is this all that Christ doth as a Priest?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>This is all that Christ did in paying
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:107490:30"/>
mans ransome and price of attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
but to make men partakers of
it, and of the benefit thereof, he doth
make intercession to God for them,
as appeares, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 34. and <hi>Heb.</hi>
7. 25.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How doth Christ make intercession?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>First, by praying for his Elect and
Faithfull,<note place="margin">Iohn 17.</note> whom the Father had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
him out of the world, this he did
in the dayes of his humiliation.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by sitting at Gods right
hand, hee presents continually before
God his perfect satisfaction and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse
in the behalf of all his Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
members,<note place="margin">Rev. 8. 3.</note> and with his Sacrifice
and Intercession, doth as it were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume
all their Prayers, and make
them acceptable in the sight of
God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Doth not Christ as well make Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession
for all, as hee dyed for all man-kind?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Though Christ dyed and fulfilled
the Law for a common benefit to all
man-kind and his ransome is suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
to save all; yet he never purposed
to redeeme all men by his death. For
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:107490:31"/>
hee knew that many were already
damned, and past all hope of redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption
before he dyed, and that <hi>Iudas</hi>
was a son of perdition, and therefore
hee did not purpose to give himselfe a
ransome for them. Besides he himself
testifieth that hee did not pray for the
world, but only for his Elect given
to him by his father out of the world,
<hi>Ioh. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 9. Therefore he did much lesse
dye with an intent purpose and desire
to redeeme and save them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How doth Christ execute his Kingly
office?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>By ruling spiritually in his Church,
and giving his Spirit and all spirituall
gifts to men, by which they are fitted
and furnished with severall gifts, for
severall offices, and functions, in that
his mysticall body. The distribution
of all honors, offices, and dignities, as
of some to be Apostles, some Prophets,
some Evangelists, others Pastors and
Teachers, is in his hand. No man is
capable of such honours, and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
nor fit for such offices, but by his
gifts and qualifications. Whosoever
thrusts himselfe into the office of a
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:107490:31"/>
Bishop, Elder, Pastor, or publike
Preacher without such gifts, and
calling, as hee hath in his Word
prescribed, hee is a thiefe, and an
usurper, as our Saviour himselfe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifieth,
who is the onely doore by
which men must enter into his sheep-fold,
<hi>Iohn</hi> 10. Hee ruleth also in the
hearts of all Faithfull people by his
Word and Spirit, as by a Law, and
that Law is the rule of their life, and
of all their actions. Hee also by his
power defends his Church from all
enemies, and takes just revenge on
their persecutors and oppressors for
all power is given him in Heaven
and Earth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 18. and hee
hath all judgment committed to him,
<hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 27. All the Saints fight under
his Royall Standard against the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,
the World, the Flesh, Sinne
and Antichrist, being armed by him
with the whole armour of God, <hi>Eph. 6
11.</hi> He will treade down Satan under
their feet, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 20. and by the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
of his lips will destroy the wicked
one, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2. And by his iron rod
break in pieces all his enemies, like a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:107490:32"/>
Potters vessell, <hi>Psal.</hi> 2. So that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
can be required in a King, for
the well ordering and ruling of his
Kingdome, by judgement and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse;
for the mercifull relieving
and he ping of them in their need.
For the powerfull defending of them
from all dangers, and for the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of just revenge on their enemies;
all this is abundantly found in Christ
as he is the Lord and King of his
Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>You have well shewed that Christ both
in respect of his Person and Offices, is an
all-sufficient Redeemer and Saviour, and
is able by the infinite worth of his Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation
to save all men: Now then tell me
why all men are not saved?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Though Christ his ransome and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
is able to save and redeeme
all that are partakers thereof, even all
mankind, if they had grace to receive
and apply him and all his merits
by Faith, Yet because none have spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
communion with him, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
they whom God hath chosen to
eternall life in him, and predestinated
to be effectually called, according to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:107490:32"/>
his purpose, to the state of grace, and
to be made conformable to his image:
Therfore many who are not elect, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
their own evil ways, and have no
will nor care to repent of their sins,
and beleeve in Christ, but run wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
into destruction and perish.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Hath God then chosen from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
a certeine number only of man-kind
to salvation in Christ?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Yea verily. For the Scriptures
plainly testifie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>First, that God hath a certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of particular persons, whom hee
hath from all eternity predestinated
both to eternall life in Christ, and also
to the meanes which lead unto life, to
wit, redemption, effectuall calling, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption,
faith and the like, <hi>Ephes. 1. 4.
5, 11. &amp; Rom. 11. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7. &amp; Act.</hi> 13. 48.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the persons elected
are they only who are called in time,
according to his purpose, iustified<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
made conformable to the image of his
Son, and at length glorified, <hi>Rom. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
28, 29, 30.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that they are chosen not
for any work which God foresaw in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:107490:33"/>
them, but meerely according to the
good pleasure of his own Will, <hi>Rom.
9. 11. 15. Eph.</hi> 1. 5.</p>
               <p>And fourthly, that all they who
continue in obstinacy and impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
unto the end, and are damned, were
of old ordeined to that damnation, &amp;
destructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1 <hi>Thes. 5. 9. 1 Pet. 2. 8. Jud.</hi> 4.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>If God hath not ordeined men to Faith
in Christ repentance, and good works, but
hath willingly rejected them, as he did E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sau
before he had done any evill; and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
them up to hardnesse, and impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
as he did Pharaoh: Why is he angry
with them, for none can resist his Will?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is too much presumption in men
to dispute against God, and to judge
of his actions by their owne shallow
reason. For he is not to give account
of any of his matters, nor to answer
for his doings, <hi>Iob 33. 13. Rom.</hi> 9. 19.
And yet it is reason that every absolute
Lord should do what he list with his
own, &amp; that as the potter hath power
over the clay to make of the same lump
one vessell unto honour, and another
unto dishonor; so God much more
should have power over his creatures,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:107490:33"/>
to ordaine and make some vessels of
honor, and leave others to follow
their own evil ways which they have
found out to themselves, and are not
lead into by him, and so to perish;
seeing their evill and destruction by
his over-ruling wisdome and power
doth turne to the greater good of his
Elect, and makes the glory of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse,
Iustice, Power and Mercy shine
forth more clearely to them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Doth the benefit of Christ the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,
 and Redeemer reach only to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Though the saving vertue of Christ
belongeth only to the elect; yet there
is a common benefit of Christ, wherof
reprobates are partakers, which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth
also to all the world. For hee is
said to preserve man and beasts, that is,
to keep them in life and being, <hi>Psal.</hi>
36 6. and to be the Saviour of all, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially
of them that beleeve, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi>
4. 10. and to give himselfe a ransome
for all, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 26. and by him all
things are said to consist, <hi>Coloss. 1.
17.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How can Christs vertue reach to them
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:107490:34"/>
who are a far off Aliens and Strangers
from him, and enemies to his Crosse and
sufferings?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It reacheth to them not immediatly
by vertue of union with him, as it
doth to the Faithfull, but after a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condary
manner for his Elects sake.
For Christ by his mediation hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined
of God, that all the World
which was made for mans use, should
be upheld by his generall providence,
that the Heavens, and the Sun, Moon
and Stars, should keep their course,
and continue in their naturall being,
and give light and influence to the
good and the bad, the just and unjust,
and that the Aire, the Earth, and the
Sea, should breed and nourish living
creatures, and herbes, plantes, fruit-trees
and all other things usefull for
men, yea the wicked prosper and
flourish in wealth and strength, either
that they may be a wall of defence to
the Elect which live among them, or
that they may build houses, plant
vineyards, and subdue the Earth for
them, as the cursed <hi>Canaanites</hi> did for
<hi>Israel;</hi> or that they may be progenitors,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:107490:34"/>
and instruments, to bring forth an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
seed, as our fore-fathers the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
Gentiles were to us their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
progeny; or for the punishing
and correcting of the sins of the elect,
as the Canaanites were kept alive to
punish the Israelites when they sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;
and for the tryall and exercise
of their Faith and patience by unjust
persecution. Christ by his Mediation
hath procured all these things for his
elects sake, to all creatures, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise
should have perished with
man being all stained and corrupted
by his sin. And hence it is that he is
said to beare up the pillars of the
world, when the earth and the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants
thereof are dissolved, <hi>Psal. 75
3.</hi> And thus farre we may grant and
acknowledge an universall grace,
which Christ by his Mediation hath
procured to all the world, even to
the wicked reprobates which pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </speaker>
               <p>Hath not Christ procured to all man-kind
grace and ability, to beleeve, repent
and be saved, if they will do as much as
they are able for the obteining of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:107490:35"/>
and other saving graces of the
Spirit?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>No certeinely, For Regeneration,
Effectuall calling, Faith, and all sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
Graces are purchased and given
by Christ, only to the Elect, for whom
alone he prayed, and doth still make
intercession: And they also while
they remaine in the common state of
Nature, have no power in themselves,
either to will or to do any work tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
good, but are dead in trespasses and
sins,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2. 1. They are aliens and
enemies in their minds, and all their
thoughts incline to evill, <hi>Colos.</hi> 1. 21.
If all men, even they who perish, had
power and liberty of will, to beleeve
and be saved, certeinely some of them
who are not elect, would beleeve and
be regenerate, and use their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
to the saving of their soules. For it
is given for that end, that it might be
brought into act, and take effect; if it
never doth, it is given by God in
vaine. But Nature, as the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers
observed, never gives power in
vaine, and much more doth the God
of Nature, abhorre to give men a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:107490:35"/>
vaine power which never comes into
act.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>If it be not in their power to do any
worke tending to life, nor to beleeve and
repent: why are they condemned for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity,
impenitency, and omission of good
works?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Though they cannot beleeve nor
repent to salvation, yet they have a
power left by common grace, to use
the meanes which lead to Faith, and
Repentance, as hearing of the Word,
reading the Scriptures, hearkning to
Reproofes and to good admonitions
and exhortations, and this naturall
power they refuse to exercise, and
wickedly and wilfully neglect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
those outward meanes. Also by
their sin in <hi>Adam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> they have disabled
themselves, are become froward and
averse from all actions truly good, and
are a cursed generation justly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How come the Elect to bee redeemed,
and saved by the Mediation of Christ;
seeing they by nature have no more inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest
in Christ than others?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>They are redeemed and saved by
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:107490:36"/>
the most gracious supernaturall work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of God in them, according to his
eternall Counsel, Purpose and Decree.
For as he hath ordeined them to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
life in Christ, before the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the world, so it doth in the
time appointed, gather them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,
in and by the Lord Iesus
Christ.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>By what meanes doth God worke sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
grace in them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>By the Ministery and Preaching of
his holy Word, which is a worke of
the Propheticall office of Christ. For
by that Word spoken to the Elect Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
of old, in Dremes, Visions, and
Apparitions; and after spoken and
written by <hi>Moses,</hi> the Prophets and
Holy men of God, who spake as they
were moved by the Holy Ghost; and
since by the mouth of Christ and his
Apostles, Evangelists and their suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors;
hee hath revealed and doth
continually reveale himselfe to them
in Christ, teacheth them the onely
right way to salvation, cals upon
them, and invites them by gracious
promises to come unto him; and by
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:107490:36"/>
the threatenings of the Law, he drives
them out of themselvs, discovers their
sins, and the dangerous estate in which
they are by reason of sinne, and suffers
them to find no place wherein to rest,
untill like <hi>Noahs</hi> dove, they flee unto
his Arke the true Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Can the Word Preached bring men to
Christ, and to salvation in him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is the only outward ordinary
meanes which God useth for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
and we never read of any, who
without the word beleeved, were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
effectually to Christ and saved. All
Heathen, Infidels, Turks and Pagans,
who either never heard the Word
Preached, or hearing do refuse and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
it, do undoubtedly perish in their
unbeliefe. For he that beleeveth not
is condemned already. <hi>John</hi> 3. 18. and
without the Word heard none can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What then shall wee thinke of infants
borne of beleeving parents, which dye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
they heare, or are able to beleeve the
Word?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ:</speaker>
               <p>God teacheth and inclineth them
inwardly by his Spirit to long after
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:107490:37"/>
Christ and to grope after him, as they
do after their mothers breasts for milk
and bodily nourishment: but yet not
without the Word. For by the Word
preached to their Fathers, hee workes
Faith in them, and makes his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
of life in Christ with them and
their seed; and so by the Ministery of
the Word, their infants come to be in
the Covenant. And God doth often
times sanctifie them by his Spirit
from the wombe (as we read of <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi>
and <hi>John</hi> the Baptist) or in their
baptisme at the Prayers of his Church.
And therefore we ought charitably to
beleeve and judge, that children of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving
parents, as they are from the
wombe holy by dedication, 1 <hi>Cor. 7.
14.</hi> and capable of baptisme, so are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
baptized by the Spirit into
Christ; and if they dye in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy,
are saved by the free Grace of
God, who worketh all things after
the counsell of his own will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How doth the Word preached worke
saving grace in men?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Not barely by it selfe, nor by any
divine vertue inherent in it; but by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:107490:37"/>
the free grace of God, and the inward
operation of the Spirit working with
it, when and where, and in whom
he will. For the Word preached
doth not profit, when its notmingled
with Faith in them that heare it, <hi>Heb.</hi>
4. 2. as we see in the Iewes, to whom
Christ himselfe preached, and yet they
were not turned to God; but the
Word by him spoken, through their
infidelity turned to their hurt,
wrought to the hardening of them in
their sins, and left them without all
excuse or any cloak for their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
<hi>Iohn</hi> 15. 22.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What are those necessary works and
saving graces, which God by his Word
and Spirit worketh in men to bring them
to salvation in Christ?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>They are works and graces, which
flow from Gods eternall election and
are only wrought in the elect. They
are necessary, because without them
none can be saved, and they are called
saving works and graces, because the
persons in whom they are once
wrought, can never fall away and
perish, but shall certeinely persevere
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:107490:38"/>
in them and be saved: And they all
may be brought under two heads.</p>
               <p>The first are the works, which God
alone by his Word and Spirit work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
in his Elect.</p>
               <p>The second sort, are the works
which God so worketh, that they also
do cooperat with him, and work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with his Spirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Which are the works which God alone
by his Spirit worketh in the Elect?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The first is regeneration, from
which all the rest do flow, to wit, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation,
which is called renuing of
the holy Ghost, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 5. Effectuall
calling, union with Christ, adoption
and Communion of all Christs bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits,
as of his ransome, satisfaction,
righteousnesse and intercession for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,
remission of sins, justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and perfect reconciliation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Which is the first saving grace?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The first, which is the ground of al
the rest, is Regeneration.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What is Regeneration?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is that worke of God by which
he sheds the Holy Ghost on his Elect,
through Iesus Christ,<note place="margin">Tit. 3. 5, 6.</note> of which Spirit
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:107490:38"/>
given to dwell in them as his immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
seed, they are borne again and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
new creatures, and spirituall
members of Christ, and children of
God by a new birth and Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What is Renovation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is the work of God, which he by
his Spirit shed on them, and dwelling
in them, doth work in them, renuing
them after the image of Christ, and
making them conformable to him,
both in his death, by mortification,
and in his life, by vivification.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What is Mortification?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is that work of Gods Spirit
wherein hee deriveth the vertue of
Christs death unto them, and worketh
in them such a sense of their misery,
sin, and corruption, and such a godly
griefe, sorrow, contrition of heart,
loathing and abhorring of themselvs,
as doth tame their rebellious lusts, and
gives a deadly blow to the old man
of sinfull corruption in them; so that
sinne can no more reigne in their
mortall bodies, but by grace they
prevaile more and more over their
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:107490:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
corruption and do mortifie it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What is Vivification?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is that worke of the Spirit by
which he derives the vertue of Christs
holy life unto them to quicken them,
and sanctifie them by inherit holines,
and to make them in the whole course
of their life conformable to the holy
and upright life of Christ.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What gifts and graces are wrought in
the Elect by Renovation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The first which is, as it were, the
root of the rest is Faith. For as the
Devill did first breath into <hi>Adam</hi> an
unbeleefe, and distrust of God and his
truth, so that hee beleeved not the
Word and threatning of God, but
gave credit to Satans lyes, and relyed
on them, and by his false beliefe, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
drew him on to a false opinion of
God, and a conceipt that God envyed
his greater good, whereupon hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
proudly to imagine that he might
by eating of the forbidden tree become
wise as God, and did conceive enmity
in his mind against God, ambitious
lusts, and evill affections: So God in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:107490:39"/>
renuing man doth first worke Faith
in him, which is the gift of beleeving
in God, and relying on his Word and
Promises. And by his Word belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
he gives light of unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>standing,
and knowledge, which drives out
errors, and false opinions, and enables
man to see his owne vilenesse, and
Gods goodnesse towards him, whence
ariseth the grace of humility and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance;
also a sincere holy love of
God, feare and reverence of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty,
joy, rejoycing, hope, and delight
in God, and a will and desire to obey
him in all things, and in a word, all
Christian vertues, by which a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
conformable to Christ.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What is Effectuall Calling!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is the work of the Spirit of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation,
who by giving to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
a new heart and spirit, doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline
and enable them to follow the
outward calling of the Word, and to
turne from darknesse to light, and
from the power of Satan unto God,
<hi>Act.</hi> 26. 18.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What is the Vnion of the Elect with
Christ?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:107490:40"/>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is not a making of their severall
persons one undivided Essence and
Substance with the person of Christ.
For that unity is only in God, and in
the three persons of the blessed Trinity:
Neither is it a making of them one
person with Christ, by such a personal
union as is between his Godhead, and
Manhood, and betweene the soule and
body of every man: Neither is it a
bodily uniting of them with Christ,
by a bodily mixture and composition
of the substance of their soules, and
bodyes, with the substance of the soule
and body of Christ, as wine and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
are mingled together: For such
an union makes the things united in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>separable
in place one from another;
so that wheresoever Christs body is,
there they must needs be, and can be in
no other proper place who are thus u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited:
Neither is this union only in
heart and affection. But this is a spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall,
mysticall and substantiall uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
in which Christ sitting at Gods
right hand above the Heavens, and
they dispersed over all the Earth, are
made one spirituall, and mysticall
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:107490:40"/>
body, whereof Christ is the head and
they members, by meanes of the same
Spirit dwelling and working in
them, after the same maner as he dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
and worketh in the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of Christ from his first concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and framing in the wombe. For
by one Spirit they are all Baptized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
one body, whereof Christ is the
head, and being many members, they
make up one body, even as all mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
in naturall body, though they
be many, make up but one body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
they all have but one soule and
life, the holy Spirit of which they
are regenerate, borne againe, and
made new creatures is the sure spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
band of union betweene Christ
the head, and them the members of
the same mysticall body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What is Adoption?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is a necessary consequent of the
union of the Elect with Christ. For
Christ being the only begotten Son of
God by eternall generation, as hee is
God, and as hee is Man by personall
union with God the Sonne, and by a
supernaturall and miraculous genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:107490:41"/>
and so heire of all things, <hi>Heb. 1.
2.</hi> It must necessarily follow, that
whosoever are in him, one body with
him, and lead by his Spirit, do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
come under the account of children
and heires of God, and of coheires
with Christ, and so God the Father
doth esteeme, respect and accoumpt
them, &amp; the Spirit dwelling in them
doth witnesse with their spirit that
they are the children of God. <hi>Rom. 8.
16.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What is the Communion with Christ
of all his benefits?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is a consequent that is a grace
necessarily following from union
with hrist. For whosoever are by
one Spirit baptized into Christ, and
made one spirituall body with him,
as really and substantially as all
members in a mans body, are one na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
body with the head, they
must needs have such a spirituall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
of all Christs treasures, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,
and endowents as is the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
communion which all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
in a mans body have with the
head. Christs sufferings, satisfaction
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:107490:41"/>
for sin, righteousnesse, ransome and
intercession are theirs,<note place="margin">Rom. 5. 19. &amp; 10. 4.</note> and they have
a right and interest in them,<note place="margin">Rom. 3. 7:</note> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
of them all.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 21.</note> And thus God
justifies and makes them fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally
righteous by Christs perfect
righteousnesse, frees them from the
guilt of all their sins, by his satisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
sufferings, and accepts them for his
redeemed, and reconciled ones
through Christs intercession, and
makes them actually accepted in his
beloved Christ, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What are the works of saving grace,
which God so worketh in the Elect, that
they also being moved by his Spirit, do
cooperat and worke together with
him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>They are the actions of the Elect
regenerat, exercising by the motion
of the Spirit those spirituall gifts, and
Christian vertues, which were given
them by renovation or renuing of the
holy Ghost.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Which is the first of them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </speaker>
               <p>The first is actuall Faith, or Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
in God and in Christ, for as the
gift of Faith is the first of all spirituall
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:107490:42"/>
gifts, which by the renuing of the
holy Ghost, is wrought in the elect
regenerate: So the worke of their
Faith, that is, actuall beleeving is the
first of all, which by the motion of
the Spirit, they performe after they are
quickned and raised up to live a spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Why is the work of their Faith the first
before the acts of knowledge, repentance,
love, hope, and the rest?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Because Faith possesseth the whole
heart and soule of man, and informeth
after a sort all the powers and
faculties thereof: even the understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
will, and affections. It is the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening
of the understanding to take
notice of Gods goodnesse, and of the
truth of his Word. It is the inclining
of the will, to give assent to the whole
Word of God and all truth therein re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed,
and to acknowledge all Gods
Truth, Goodnesse, and Mercy in
Christ. It is the rectifying of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
and the plyablenesse of them
to trust in God, to rely on him, to
hope in his mercy; to love, feare, and
reverence him, and to hate all offence
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:107490:42"/>
of his holy Majesty, to sorrow for sin
with godly sorrow to repentance, to
rejoyce and delight in the things of
God, and to bee zealous of good
works, and resolve to serve, honour,
and obey God in a constant course of
life. This saving Faith sets a work all
other graces, and therefore all works
of true godlinesse, holinesse, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse
performed by the Elect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate,
and sanctified, are called
fruits of Faith, by which their Faith
is openly shewed, and made knowne
as a tree by the fruits of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Which is the proper work of true saving
Faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ:</speaker>
               <p>The proper work of it by which all
other graces are set a work is a firme,
and stedfast beleeving with the whole
heart, of the Word of God, and all
things therein revealed, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
their salvation by Christ, that
is, both eternall life in the fruition of
God, and the way to it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What difference is there betweene this
beleeving and that which is in Devils,
and in carnall hypocrites who beleeve
these things, or at least many of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:107490:43"/>
them at some times?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>There is as great difference between
them, as between light and darknesse.
The beleeving of the Elect regenerat
proceeds from a supernaturall cause,
and from a Divine and holyroot, even
the Spirit of God dwelling in them,
as Gods immortall seed, and sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
them, and therefore it is holy,
firme, and stedfast, and reacheth
beyond all hope, sense and reason. But
that of the Devils and carnall hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites,
proceeds from their own natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
reason, convinced by sense, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
and plaine arguments, or by a
common illumination of the Spirit,
shining from without into the hearts
of hypocrites, and temporary belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
as we read of <hi>Simon Magus,
Act.</hi> 8. 13. and the hypocriticall Iews
who beleeved in Christs name, when
they saw his miracles, <hi>John</hi> 2. 23. And
therefore their beleeving is carnall
temporary and vanishing, and goeth
no further than sense and naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
do lead. The beleeving of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
is the subsisting of things hoped
for, and the evidence of things not
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:107490:43"/>
seen, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 1. That is, they have the
things which they beleeve, as certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
as they beleeve that they have them
and hope for them, and their beleeving
is a cleare evidence to them of their
being in Christ, and of their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
with him in grace, and of their
portion in Heaven, which things are
not seene with carnall eyes of sense or
reason. For the Spirit which works
this beleefe, hath united them to
Christ, and made Christ and all his
benefits theirs already, so that their
beleeving is infallible and cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
them. But Devils, carnall
men, and hypocrites cannot reach so
far as to beleeve their own particular
salvation in Christ, or their having
of things thereto belonging: And if
any of them do at any time, <hi>Mich. 3.
11.</hi> it is but a false and vanishing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe.
In a word whosoever doth by
a true saving Faith, beleeve histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally
the Word of God, and the truth
therein conteined, he hath withall an
affiance in God, and grace to beleeve
by all other acts of Faith, even to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
to himselfe all Gods promise by
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:107490:44"/>
beleeving steadfastly that they belong
to himself in particular. For as the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> works this faith is the fountain
of all grace, and unites the beleevers to
Christ, &amp; makes him &amp; all his benefits
theirs. So this Faith necessarily produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
all acts of beleeving in them, and
makes them able by beleeving, to apply
to themselvs &amp; to enjoy all blessings,
which are to be found in Christ.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What benefits do the Elect receive by
their actuall beliefe, and exercise of their
saving Faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>They receive hereby, First a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable
sense, feeling and fruition of
their regeneration, renovation, effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall
calling, union, adoption, remis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
of sins, justification, reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and in a word communion of all
Christs benefits, and hence it is, that
they are said by Faith to turne to God
to be united to Christ adopted, justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
and to obtaine remission of all
their sins, that is, in their own sense,
and feeling.</p>
               <p>And secondly, by this actuall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving,
and by the sense and feeling,
which it brings to the beleevers, all
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:107490:44"/>
other graces are set a worke, and more
and more increased in them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How doth beleeving give to the Elect
a feeling of their regeneration, renovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
effectuall calling union, adoption, and
other saving works of God in them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>First, as it is a fruit and work of the
Spirit of regeneration and adoption,
which hee never workes in any but
them who are regenerate, made new
creatures effectually called, united to
Christ, adopted and have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of all his benefits: so it is a cleare
evidence to them of those graces in
themselves, and by it the Spirit wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesseth
with their spirits, that they
are the children of God by regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and adoption, and are effectually
cald and engraffed into Christ, become
new creatures, heires of God and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heires
with Christ. Secondly, the act
of beleeving by a true saving Faith is
an applying of the things beleeved to
themselvs, and by beleeving that they
are regenerat, renued, effectually cald,
united, adopted and have co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of
Christs perfect satisfaction, interces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
and righteousnesse, they possesse
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:107490:45"/>
and injoy all those graces, and are in
their own sense fully reconciled to
God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How are they justified and have their
sins pardoned by Faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>They are justified and have their
sins remitted by Faith, not as by an
instrumentall cause and meanes to
make them righteous before God; but
as by the hand of the soule, receiving
and applying to themselves the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse
of Christ to make them
righteous in their own sense and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.
And their actuall beleeving that
they are justified and pardoned, is
neither their righteousnesse, nor the
satisfaction for their sins, nor any
thing which in it selfe properly is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
of God or reputed for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse
and satisfaction, but is only
the applying of Christs righteousnes
and satisfaction to themselves, and an
assuring of themselves, that by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
thereof they are justified.
And by this beleeving they possesse
and sweetly enjoy them, and are in
their owne sense and feeling, justified
and absolved from the guilt of al their
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:107490:45"/>
sins, and obteine this testimony from
God that they are righteous, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 3.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Can any man bee justified before hee
doth actually beleeve?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>If we take justification in the first
most proper and principall sense, as
it is the act of God alone, communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating
Christs righteousnesse and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
to his elect, when hee doth
first unite them to Christ by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
and make Christ theirs with all
his treasures: Then it must bee gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
that men may be and are justified,
before and without any expresse act
of beleeving: As for example, elect
infants which dye in their infancy,
when they are regenerated and united
to Christ by his Spirit, they have
communion of his righteousnesse, and
are justified and made righteous, and
all their sins are abolished and blotted
out, and yet they do not actually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,
nor performe any explicit and
expresse act of Faith. Also they who
are not effectually called to the state
of grace, and to communion with
Christ till they come to yeares of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion,
though they have the gift of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:107490:46"/>
Faith immediatly at the same time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused
into them: yet Christs righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse
is in order of nature commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated
to them and they are made
righteous by it before God, before
they do actually beleeve, or can truly
beleeve that Christ is made to them
righteousnesse, or can by beleeving
possesse and enjoy his righteousnesse
for justification. As a child may bee
borne, or made an heire to Lands, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
and riches, and may have a true
right and interest in them, and bee
Lord of all, before hee hath wit to
know his own estate, or discretion to
possesse actually and use them: So
men may be justified by Christs righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse
madetheirs, in the first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
of their regeneration and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
union with Christ, before they
do actually beleeve, and sensibly pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse,
and enjoy Christ and his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
for justification. But if we take
justification in a secondary sense, as it
is an act wherein the elect themselves
do cooperat and work together with
God, by receiving and applying to
themselves particularly the gift of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:107490:46"/>
righteousnesse freely given unto them,
and by possessing and enjoying it;
then must actuall beleeving go before
it as the instrumentall cause, by which
God justifieth them in their own sense
and feeling, and upon which he doth
esteeme and account them righteous
in the intercourse betweene him
and them, and gives them his war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
to esteeme themselves justified
with him. But if we take justificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
in a Iudiciary sense, as it is used in
Courts of Iustice and Iudgement, for
proving, declaring and pronouncing
men righteous: Then not only Faith
and actuall beleeving, but also repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
amendment of life, and all holy
Christian duties, and good works of
piety, mercy and charity must neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarily
go before as evidences, testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,
and proofes by which men must
be justified, that is judged declared and
pronounced righteous.</p>
               <p>First, in the Court of their owne
conscience, so often as sin and Satan
stand up against them to accuse them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in the common judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:107490:47"/>
Thirdly, in the generall judgement
at the last day.</p>
               <p>Of the first, Iustification, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle
speakes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 19. where he saith
that by the obedience of Christ many
are made righteous, and <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 4. and
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 21. Of the second he speakes,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 28. and 4. 3. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 8. where
he saith, we are justified by saith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
workes or deedes of the Law.</p>
               <p>Of the third Saint <hi>James</hi> speakes,
where he saith, that <hi>Abraham</hi> was
justified by works, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 21. and
<hi>Job</hi> 13. 18. where he saith, <hi>Behold now
I have ordered my cause, I know that I
shall be justified,</hi> and this S. <hi>Paul</hi> cals
justification of life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 18. because
it is an adjudging of men to eternall
life, according to the evidence of
their works, as our Saviour sheweth,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 35.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How doth justifying Faith differ from
that which they call historicall Faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>They both in the elect are one and
the same Faith, and differ onely as se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
acts of the same Faith exercised
about severall objects. For when
they beleeve the History of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:107490:47"/>
and that those things are true
which they heare, or read out of Gods
Word, this is called historicall Faith.
But when they beleeve firmely and
confidently, that the promises of God
in Christ belong to them, and that
Christ, with his righteousnes is given
to them of God, &amp; made theirs, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving
&amp; applying of Christs righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes
to themselves is the justifying
act of Faith. And whereas the histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
saith of Devils and carnall men, is
only an assent unto the Word of God,
that it is true, arising from carnal rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
and arguments convincing the
judgement without any affection to
the truth, or any relying on it. On
the contrary every act of beleeving
any word or promise of God; if it
proceeds from a true Faith in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect,
is not a naked assent ruled by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
and naturall reason, but guided
by Gods Spirit, and joyned with a
relying on God, and his Word, upon
the Divine authority of the speaker,
and may be brought as an evidence of
their salvation, &amp; may in that respect
be called a saving beliefe, as we see at
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:107490:48"/>
large, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. where beleeving that
the worlds were framed by the Word
of God. And that God would bring
a flood upon the world and destroy
all except them that were in the Arke
made by his appointment; and that
he would give the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> to
the seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> the Israelites,
and after 400 yeares deliver them out
of Aegypt, and such like acts of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,
proceeding from an holy spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
Faith, are declared to bee saving
Faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How doth actuall beleeving set a work
all other graces, and increase them more
and more in the Elect regenerate, and
justified?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>By the sense, feeling, and sweet frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of Christ and his righteousnesse,
satisfaction, and intercession, it brings
us to the sight and experimentall
knowledge of the goodnesse, bounty,
love and mercy of God to us in Christ.
And being justified by Faith,<note place="margin">Rom. 5. 1.</note> we have
peace with God through our Lord
Iesus Christ, and rejoyce in hope of
the glory of God, and hereby the holy
Ghost sheddeth the love of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:107490:48"/>
in our hearts, so that being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed
with the love of God, wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
more and more to hate and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre
our owne vile corruptions and
sins, which are offensive to his holy
Majesty: We are ashamed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded,
because we have by our sins
so often provoked so gracious a God,
and mercifull Father, wee grieve and
mourne and sorrow with godly sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
to repentance, wee strive and
wrastle against our lusts, and by the
assistance of the Spirit, tame and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due
them; so that sinne can no more
reigne in our mortall bodies, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
to sollow hard after God, to
cleave to him in love, and to bee still
more &amp; more united to Christ in love
and zealous affection of heart: And in
holinesse and newnesse of life we stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
and strive to be conformable to his
image; and in a word we are stirred
up to use all care and endeavour, that
wee may abound in all good works,
and still forgetting those things
which are behind, may reach forth
unto those things which are before
and presse hard towards the marke
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:107490:49"/>
for the price of the high calling of God
in Christ Iesus: In all which workes
of saving grace, as God moves us by
his Spirit, so we being moved, ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,
and made a free people, do coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate
and work together with him,
till we come to the measure of the age
of the fulnesse of Christ, and be fitted
to see God in glory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What outward meanes are to bee used
whereby the Spirit of God may worke in
the Elect, and beget and increase Faith
and beliefe with all other saving graces
in them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The chiefe outward meanes is the
Word of God, without which God
doth not ordinarily shed his Spirit
on them, beget them again and by his
Spirit work saving grace, and the
works of grace in them. For they are
borne again of incorruptible seed, that
is, of the Spirit by the Word of God,
1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 23. and regeneration which is
Gods shedding of the holy Ghost on
them, through Christ and the first sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
worke, even the ground worke
of all other saving graces is not to be
found where the Word is not Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:107490:49"/>
By the Word of Christ the
holy Gospell only, the Spirit speaks
inwardly to mens hearts, and leads
them into all truth, <hi>John</hi> 16. 13. By
the Word preached hee begets Faith,
for Faith commeth by hearing, and
none can beleeve except heheare, <hi>Rom.</hi>
10. 14, 17. The Word is the whole
and perfect rule of Faith, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
the elect beleeve to salvation,
is conteined in the Word, and there
only to be learned, <hi>John</hi> 3. 39. The
threatenings of the Law are the
meanes by which the Spirit discovers
to beleevers the danger of sin, and
their own misery, humbles them in
their own eies, and drives them out
of themselves to Christ by repentance.
The precepts of the Law prescribe to
them the right way in which they
ought to walk, and is a lamp to their
feet, and light to their steps, <hi>Psa. 119
105.</hi> The Word of the Gospell is the
Covenant of life, and sets before them
the goodnesse, bounty, love and mercy
of God in Christ, and by it the Spirit
inflames them with the love of God,
with joy and delight in God, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:107490:50"/>
with zeale for his glory, and stirres
them up to imitate God in works of
mercy, love, and charity, and in all
holinesse and sanctification, till they
be conformed to Christ, and to serve,
honour, and worship God. And in
a word, the whole Scripture, which
is the sure, infallible Word of God,
<hi>given by Divine inspiration, is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
for doctrine, for reproofe, for corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
and for instruction in righteousnes,
that the man of God may bee perfect
thorowly furnished unto all good works,</hi>
2 Tim. 3. 16. 17.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How must the Word of God bee used,
that it may be such an effectuall meanes
of the Spirit to worke all these gracious
effects in Gods elect people?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It must not only be read out of the
Sacred Scriptures, in which it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded
by the Prophets and Apostles;
but also preached, and expounded by
godly, able and learned Ministers,
who are called and sent of God, <hi>Rom.</hi>
10. 15. For they are Gods watchmen,
who have a charge given to watch
for mens soules, <hi>Ezek. 3. 17. &amp; Heb.</hi>
13. 17. They are his Shepheards and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:107490:50"/>
Overseers to feed his flock with his
Word, the Bread of Life, <hi>Act. 20. 28.
&amp; Ezek. 34. &amp; 1 Pet. 5. 2. Ephes.</hi> 4. 11.
And by delivering Gods message faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuly,
they obteine this honour to
themselves to bee called the Angels of
the Lord, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 7. and Gods Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadours,
2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20. and to be spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
Fathers under God, who beget
children to God in Christ by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell,
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 15.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What other meanes are to be used?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ:</speaker>
               <p>None but such as God hath prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
in his holy Word, to wit, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments
which are seales annexed to
the Word, publike Prayers, Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and Worship of God, And also
good education, and private Prayers,
and instruction, and often reading of
Gods Word alone, and in private Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What is a Sacrament?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is a religious action prescribed
by God, in which by using outward
visible rites consecrated to be signes,
seales, pledges, and remembrances of
the invisible graces promised and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
in Christ, the Covenant of grace
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:107490:51"/>
is sealed to his people, their Faith
confirmed, and all holy graces stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
up, quickened, and increased in
them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How many Sacraments are now in use
under the Gospell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>There are but two properly so cald,
and ordeined to be seales of the whole
Covenant of Grace: Baptisme, and
the Lords Supper. For these two are
expresly commanded and commended
by our Saviour, to the Church in the
Gospell, and to every true member
thereof. There are divers other signes,
pledges, and remembrances of bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits
and blessings past or to come; but
they either do not belong to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,
as imposition of hands in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deining
Pastors and Elders, is proper
to them who are so ordeined: Or els
beside their signification, they have
other more principall uses, as the
weekely Sabbath, besides that it is a
pledge of the eternall rest in Heaven,
and a signe that God is our God, who
doth sanctifie us. It serves chiefly to
be the first fruits of our time, and is to
be spent wholly in the worship of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:107490:51"/>
God publike and private, preaching
and hearing of the Word, Prayer and
other Religious exercises, by which
God is immediatly served, and our
soules edified. So also holy Feasts,
and Dayes which are remembrances
of some great blessings, as Easter,
Pentecost, the dayes of Christs Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,
Passion and Ascension, besides
their signification have other far more
principall use, to wit, the solemne
worship, and service of God, such as
is used on the Sabbath, and therefore
they are called holy Signes and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
improperly, and in a secondary
sense. But Baptisme and the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist
serve only for Signes, Seales and
Pledges, and have no other notable
use.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What is the Sacrament of Baptisme?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is an outward washing of the
body with pure water, applyed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
by dipping or sprinkling, ordeined
by God to be a Sacrament, that is, a
Signe, Seale and Pledge of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to the party baptized, by which
outward rite, hee is received into the
true visible Church, and dedicated to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:107490:52"/>
Christ, to bee a member of his body,
and a faithfull servant of God all the
dayes of his life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>To whom doth this Sacrament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It belongs to all that are either
borne in the Church of God, or by the
Word preached are called to beleeve
in Christ, and to professe true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
Religion, after they are come to
yeares of discretion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What warrant have Gods Ministers
to baptize Infants, and to give them the
Signe, Seals, and Pledge of Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
which a great number of them, that
are borne in the Church never have, but
are reprobates and shew themselves so to
be, by living in sin all their dayes, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in impenitency?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>They have sufficient warrant in the
Word of God. For the Apostle saith,
that children of beleeving parents
are not uncleane but holy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14.
that is, they are so far within the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
(being in their infancy, as it
were members of their beleeving pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
and wholy at their disposing)
that they may justly bee dedicated to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:107490:52"/>
God by Baptisme, (as <hi>Samuel</hi> was by
his mothers vow) and received into
the true Church. The vow which
their parents and guardians made for
them in baptisme, is a band to tye
them to serve God so soon as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
to have knowledge and discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
Certeinly Gods grace and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
towards Infants of Christian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
under the Gospell, is not strai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened
more than to Infants in the
Old Testament, whose males were
Circumcised the eight day after their
birth. Baptisme, and the promise and
Vow therein ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e for them is as
powerfull a meanes and motive to
provoke them from their youth to
serve God, as Circumcision was to
the children of Israel. Also Christ
hath taught us that his blessing &amp; the
Kingdom of eaven belongs to them,
<hi>Marc.</hi> 10. 13. And the Apostles bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
whole housholds of beleeving
men and women, not refusing any
children, as we read of <hi>Lydias</hi> and the
Iaylors houshold, <hi>Acts 16. 15.
33.</hi> In a word, many who were at
full age called by the Gospel preached
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:107490:53"/>
to beleeve by a temporary carnall
saith, and to professe Christ, were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
truly regenerate, as <hi>Judas, Simon
Magus, Demas,</hi> and others, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
hypocrites and backsliding re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates;
and yet this was never
counted a just cause to hinder or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straine
the Apostles from baptizing al
who professed Christ outwardly, for
feare of prophaning the Sacrament of
Baptisme, and abusing the holy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
of Christ.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How doth the Spirit of God by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme
increase grace in men, and set it a
worke?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>So often as they are put in minde
of their Baptisme, either by the
name of Christians or their owne
proper names given in Baptisme,
when they are called by them, or by
seeing others baptized; the Spirit of
God doth thereby as by a sure pledge
assure the Faithfull that God is their
Father, and they are his children in
his Son Christ, borne againe of the
Spirit, and so confirmes their Faith in
that communion which they have
with God the Father and his Son Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:107490:53"/>
Christ; hereby he stirs them up to
remember, that their endeavour ought
to be to walke in newnesse of life, as
new creatures, adopted to God, called
unto Christ out of the world mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and dead to the world, and sinfull
lusts, and sanctified to lead a godly
life in all righteousnesse and true holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What is the Sacrament of the Lords
Supper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It is that holy ordinance instituted
by Christ after his last Supper, in
which by Bread and Wine consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
with blessing and giving of
thankes, and by the publike Minister
given and distributed; and received,
eaten and drunk, by the people as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled,
Christ God and Man their
Redeemer, together with all his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
and full satisfaction, made and
performed in the dayes of his humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,
in the forme of fraile flesh and
bloud, is signified and sealed to them
and in greater measure given, and of
them received by Faith, as a spirituall
nourishment to feed their soules to
life eternall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:107490:54"/>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Is Christ given to all, and received
of all who partake of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>He is Sacramentally given, that is,
the true signes and pledges, of him,
are given to all, and of them received;
but he is not spiritually given to any
but true beleevers, and worthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers;
Neither do any effectually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
him or his benefits to the feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of their soules, but only they who
lay hold on him by a lively working
Faith. For the giving, receiving,
eating, drinking, is not carnall, but
spirituall, as our Saviour himselfe
sheweth, <hi>John</hi> 6. 63. saying, <hi>It is the
Spirit that quickeneth, the flesh profiteth
nothing, the words that I speake they are
spirit, and they are life.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Why doth Christ call the Bread given
and eaten, his Body, and the Wine his
Bloud, if hee be not in them bodily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,
and his Flesh and Bloud given and
received bodily?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The true reason of his speaking so is
to call our thoughts to the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
of him in the state of humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and of his infirmities, obedience
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:107490:54"/>
and sufferings, which in that estate he
did undergo in the forme of fraile
flesh and bloud for us, and to stirre us
up so to apprehend him, and feed on
him by Faith. For Christ did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme
us, and pay our ransome by any
thing which he did as God before his
Incarnation, nor by any thing which
he doth as man exalted and glorified;
but as hee God and Man in the dayes
of his flesh, fulfilled the whole Law,
and suffered all punishments due to
mans sin, so hee paid our ransome,
brought in eternall righteousnesse, and
made full satisfaction to Gods Iustice,
and these are the things which toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
with himselfe are signified and
sealed by Bread and Wine, and are
Spiritually given to, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
by the Faithfull in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How can true Beleevers bee said to
receive Christ and his benefits, seeing
they are already united to him, and have
Communion of them all, and his satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
and righteousnesse is made theirs
before in their regeneration, when they
were first effectually called, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:107490:55"/>
made fit to partake of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The Spirit of God by this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
rightly administred, doth as by
a sure pledge confirme and increase
their Faith, and set it a worke to lay
hold on Christ, and to apply him and
his righteousnesse, and satisfaction to
themselvs more strongly and sensibly,
and by this meanes they are more fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
united to him in love and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
and have a more sweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
with him of all his benefits,
which doth like a plentifull feast, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fresh
and feed their soules, strengthen
them in all grace, and this is as it
were a new and fresh receiving of
Christ and the benefits of his Life and
Death, more abundantly &amp; in greater
measure than they had him before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>You have well declared the efficacy of
the Sacraments, and how the Spirit
worketh by them. Now tell me what the
other meanes are, and first what is pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
and invocation both publike and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Prayer and Invocation, if it bee
publike, is the speech of the whole
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:107490:55"/>
Congregation, and if it be private of
one person or more directed to God,
in the Name of Iesus Christ, wherein
all needfull blessings and increase of
grace, are asked and desired in Faith,
and Hope, that God will give them
for Christ his sake, in such a measure as
he in his wisdome doth know to be
fit for every one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How is grace thereby increased?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The Spirit of God by stirring our
hearts to pray, and by putting fit
words in our mouths, or in the
mouths of them who are the mouth of
the Congregation, inflameth our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
exerciseth our Faith, kindleth
our desires, and reviveth the sense and
feeling of our wants. And by dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
us to pray to God in the Name
of Iesus Christ, he maketh us implici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely
to acknowledge and confesse that
God is the author of all blessings, and
giver of all grace, and so maketh us
to give to him in our prayers all the
glory with all humble thankfulnesse.
And God who is gracious, rich in
mercy, faithfull, and true in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises,
will accept our holy and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:107490:56"/>
humble desires, and for Christs sake
and his own truths sake, grant our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests
and give a supply of grace, and
an increase of blessings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest:</speaker>
               <p>How doth the publike worship of God
increase grace?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The publike worship of God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
outwardly and frequently in
the congregation of his people, by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
preaching and reverent hearing of
his Word, prayses, thankes, singing of
Psalmes, and reverent gestures and
behaviour, according to Gods Word,
is a speciall meanes by the inward o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration
of the Spirit, to kindle and
increase devotion in the hearts of all
his people. It is their using of his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents,
and improving of his graces in
them to his glory. And God hath
promised that as they get more gaine
of grace, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 29. so hee will still
adde more unto them, and will surely
establish them, give them the gift of
perseverance and uphold them by his
grace unto the end, till they be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
to glory and come to eternall life
and blessednesse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Wherein doth the eternall life and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:107490:56"/>
blessednesse of the Elect consist?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>In the eternall sight, knowledge,
and fruition of God in his Heavenly
glory, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5. 27. For when Christ
hath fully purged, and sanctified his
Church and people, and made them fit
to see God, then will he present them
before his glorious Maiesty to dwell
in his presence, where is fulnesse of
joy and pleasures for evermore, <hi>Psal.
16.</hi> 11.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Where shall they enjoy this blessednes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>In the Heavens where a Kingdom
is prepared for them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 32. and
<hi>John</hi> 14. 2. an inheritance incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible,
and undefiled which shall never
fade away, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. which is farre
above all that the eye hath seen, or the
eare heard, or that ever entered into
the heart of man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>When shall they come to possesse this
blessed inheritance?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>They have the earnest of it in this
life in the state of grace, even the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
of adoption by which they are sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
up to the day of full redemption,
and even here in this life they finde
that sweetnesse and communion with
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:107490:57"/>
God,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 8.</note> that though they see him not,
yet beleeving they rejoyce with joy
unspeakeable and full of glory. But
when their soules are loosed out of the
prison of the body,<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 23.</note> then shall their
spirit bee made perfect,<note place="margin">Phil. 1. 23.</note> and they shall
in that better part depart hence and be
with Christ, and reigne in glory, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
the last great day of account, the
generall judgement. At which time
the Lord Iesus Christ shall descend
from heaven, &amp; bring them with him.
And he the Prince of Angels with the
commanding voyce of the Archangell
shall call all the Angels of God to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
him,<note place="margin">Mat. 24. 31</note> and to gather before him al
his Elect from the foure winds,<note place="margin">1 Thes. 4. 15, 16.</note> from
one end of Heaven to the other, and
by the power of his voyce and the
sound of the trumpet of God, shall
raise up their dead bodies purged in
the grave, from all the degrees of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,
and brought up in a most
glorious forme like unto his own glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
body:<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 21:</note> Which bodies shall not
be prevented by the Elect and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
then alive on earth, but shall bee
first raised up and joyned with their
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:107490:57"/>
glorified soules, before those then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
shall be changed,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 52.</note> and in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
in the twinckling of an eye shall
they all together be ready to meet the
Lord in the ayre,<note place="margin">Mat. 25. 33</note> whither they shall
be caught up, and being set at his
right hand shall receive this comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
sentence, <hi>Come yee blessed of my
Father, inherit the Kingdome prepared
for you from the foundation of the world,</hi>
and so they shall bee ever with the
Lord and raigne with him in glory
world without end, 1 <hi>Thes. 4. 17. &amp;
2 Tim, 2. 12. &amp; Rev.</hi> 22. 5.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>But what shall become of all wicked
reprobates, who were never chosen, nor
called to be of this number?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Their bodies also shall be raised up
to everlasting shame, and joyned with
their cursed soules, that as they have
sinned in both, so they may in both be
punished, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 2. They shall also
be gathered together like a flock of ill
savouring goates by themselves and
brought before the judgement seat of
Christ full sore against their will,
with horror, howling and trembling:
And tumbling and groveling on the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:107490:58"/>
earth as if they would creep into the
ground intermingled among the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils
and wishing that the rocks and
mountaines might fall on them, and
the hils cover them, but all in vaine;
<hi>Luke</hi> 23. 30. they shall receive an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy
doome. For the Iudge sitting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
in the aire, attended with all his
glorious Angels, &amp; with all his elect
Saints, caught up to meet him in their
glorious bodies, and to sit with him
in judgement, shall with a dreadfull
voice passe this woful sentence against
them, <hi>Math. 25. 41. Depart from me ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
cursed into everlasting fire, prepared for
the Devill and his angels.</hi> And then shal
they go into everlasting destruction,
and be punished in unquenchahle fire,
from the presence of God, and from
the glory of his power; where a
gnawing worme which never dyeth,
shall torment them world without
end, 2 <hi>Thes. 1. 9. Isa. 66. 24. Mark.</hi> 9. 44.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>What may wee conceive of the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
 and torment of the wicked after
this judgement?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>It far surpasseth all conceipt of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
man, being such as all the tongues
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:107490:58"/>
of men and Angels are not able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse.
But this is plaine by Scripture,
that whatsoever can be conceived, or
is named among men as a cause of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme
torment, or a meanes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease
it beyond all measure, that shall
be in their damnation &amp; punishment.
First, the Lord Christ whom they have
skorned, provoked and perfecuted,
both in himselfe and in his members,
shall be their Iudge, and shall give the
sentence against them. And all his
Saints whom they have mocked, mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>used,
proudly insulted over, despight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
handled, and evill intreated, and
put to death, shall sit as assessors with
Christ in judgement, and with their
voyces shall approve and applaud the
sentence of condemnation, as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures
testifie, <hi>Mat. 22. 28. &amp; 1 Cor. 6.
2.</hi> and shall judge the evill angels, <hi>v.</hi> 3.
Now for malicious proud skorners
full of envy, to be judged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
by those who they have most
of all others hated, skorned and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
with despight, is worse than a
thousand deaths, as experience teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.
Secondly, their torment unto
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:107490:59"/>
which they shall bee adjudged is said
to be in everlasting fire, in that Lake
of hell burning with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 25 41. which of all tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
that men by sense can discerne,
or reason conceive is the greatest and
most intollerable, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 22. And yet
as if that were not enough, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
saith, that they shall have a worm
inwardly gnawing them which shall
never dye, even the worme of Devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish
malice, rancour and envy, which
shall make them fret and rage against
the Lord Christ, and against his Saints
gnawing their tongues for griefe:
For the sight of their glory shall be to
them inwardly as great a torment, as
the torture of fire and brimstone are
outwardly unto them. Thirdly, they
shall have no light of comfort or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshing
from God, but shall be impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned
in the dungeon of everlasting
darknesse, for the blacknesse of darknes
is reserved for them for ever, <hi>Iude v.</hi> 13
which is a thing most horrid to the
eyes. Also the sound of horror and a
dolefull noyse shall fill their eares, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
weeping and wailing and gnash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:107490:59"/>
of teeth, <hi>Matth. 13. 42. &amp; 25. 30.
Luk.</hi> 16. 24. And all the world shall
not yeeld them a drop of water to
coole their tongues when they are tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
in that flame. Fourthly, their
misery and torment shall bee endlesse,
easelesse, and remedilesse, when they
have endured it many thousands and
millions of yeares and ages, more in
number then the stars of Heaven, and
drops of water in the Sea, and sands
by the sea shore; they shall bee as far
from any end as they were at the first
beginning. Now we know that when
men suffer any paine or misery, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
hope of any end thereof, it is made
by this meanes most grievous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable,
though in it selfe it be not
so great. And therefore the extremity
of torment to them who are cut off
from all hope of ease or end, must needs
exceed all conceipt and utterance, and
bee more than can by tongue bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>How can their sins committed in the
short time of their life deserve such an
endlesse torment in so great extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:107490:60"/>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>Very well, For first their sinnes
being committed against an infinite
Majesty, and having offended the
infinite God, and provoked his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
wrath, do by the rule of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
and justice deserve an infinite pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as the elect Saints, shall
in the last Resurrection be all filled up
to the full with holinesse, and with
the image of Christ, and shall every
one have as much as his vessell can
conteine, so that hee can desire no
more, Even so wicked reprobates
after the last judgement shall be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
into the image of the Devill,
and filled up with malice and rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
God to the brimme, insomuch
that they shall blaspheme and curse
God, for tying them in everlasting
chaines, that they can doe no more
mischiefe, and gnash their teeth with
anger against themselves, because
they have no more provoked the
Lord by transcendent wickednesse,
so far shall they be from relenting and
from remorse and repentance for their
sins. And therefore the more and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:107490:60"/>
the longer they suffer the torments of
hell, the more they deserve to suffer
them for ever with increase, if it were
possible. That they are past all hope
and possibility of repentance, may
easily bee proved by that which the
Scriptures testifie of Apostatas and
such as sinne against the holy Ghost,
to wit, <hi>that it is impossible to renew
them by repentance,</hi> Heb. 6. 6. <hi>and it
is a vaine thing to pray for them,</hi> 1 Iohn
5. 16. for their hearts are hardned to
commit all iniquity with greedinesse:
And therefore much more the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
in hell being turned into the
image of the Devill, are past hope of
repentance, and must needs be harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
in eternall malice and impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
to the utmost.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest:</speaker>
               <p>Is there no difference of glory among
the Saints in Heaven, and of torment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
the damned in hell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>The Apostle saith, that as one Star
differeth from another in glory; so it
is in the resurrection of the Saints to
glory, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 41. But though some
of the Saints are capable of more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:107490:61"/>
then others, because they have
beene more excellent members of
Christ in the state of Grace, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments
of great good to the
Church, as appeares, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 3. and
<hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 28. And some reprobates
are more capacious vessels of wrath, as
they have more outragiously and des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pightfully
provoked God in the time
of their life; and both these shall bee
filled up to the utmost fulnes of their
measure, the one sort with glory, the
other with shame and wrath, and so
they shall have the one more glory,
the other more misery: Yet hee that
hath the least glory, shal have as much
as he can conceive or desire, and hee
who hath the least torment and mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
shall have as much as his vessell can
conteine, and as hee is capable of, and
can beare. This may be made plain by a
familiar similitude. If divers bottles or
earthen vessels of divers measures and
different capacity beeplunged into the
deep sea with open mouths; every
vessell will be filled to the brim, that
it cannot conteine one drop more, the
least as well as the greatest; and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:107490:61"/>
though the greatest conteines more;
yet the least is as full, as it is,
even to the utmost. So it is both
in the Saints glorified in Heaven,
and the wicked tormented in Hell.
Though some are like vessels more
capacious, and being filled with
glory, or with misery, have more
than others: Yet the least Saint
is as full as hee can bee of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
and can desire no more; and
the least among the damned is
filled up with torment and with
the wrath of God to the utmost,
and hath as much as his vessell
can hold. The one wants no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
but hath a fulnesse of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
to make him, as blessed, as
hee can desire, for ever. And the
other hath so much torment, as
makes him to the utmost extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
miserable: And as there is no
possibility of the falling away of
the Saints from their glory in
the least degree. So it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible
to ease the damned of the
least graine of his heavy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable
misery; but Gods wrath
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:107490:62"/>
shall cleave to them for ever, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide
on them to the utmost, world
without end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quest.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing now I have lead you on by
Questions to the utmost ends both of
the godly Elect, and wicked Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates:
Now tell mee what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Answ.</speaker>
               <p>No more but this: That, as God
hath set before us Life and Death;
For the godly, Life eternall in the
fruition of himselfe in Glory; but
for the wicked and ungodly eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
Death, misery and torment in
Hell: So wee by following hard
after God by Faith in Iesus Christ,
and making his glory, the marke
which wee shoote at in the whole
course of our Lives, and the maine
end of all our labours, may bee
free from all danger and feare of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
Death in Hell, and may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine
the inheritance of Heavenly
glory, and with Christ our Head,
and all his Elect Saints, may see
God and enjoy all his goodnesse,
as our portion for ever, World with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:107490:62"/>
end. To this blessed God who
hath vouchsafed thus farre to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale
himselfe unto us, and to shew
us the right way, by which wee
may come to him, bee all glory,
honour and praise giuen, and
ascribed by us and his whole
Church, now and for ever.
<hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <closer>Trin-uni Deo gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
