<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fifth letter, concerning the sacred Trinity in answer to what is entituled, the Arians vindication of himself against Dr. Wallis's fourth letter on the Trinity / by John Wallis ...</title>
            <author>Wallis, John, 1616-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-08">2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67389</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18175</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12212195</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12212195</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56328</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A67389)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56328)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 904:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fifth letter, concerning the sacred Trinity in answer to what is entituled, the Arians vindication of himself against Dr. Wallis's fourth letter on the Trinity / by John Wallis ...</title>
                  <author>Wallis, John, 1616-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freke, William, 1662-1744. --  Arians vindication of himself against Dr. Wallis's fourth letter on the Trinity.</term>
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56328:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56328:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Fifth LETTER, Concerning the Sacred Trinity; IN ANSWER To what is Entituled, The <hi>Arians</hi> Vindication of himself against D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Wallis</hi>'s Fourth Letter ON THE TRINITY.</p>
            <p>By <hi>IOHN WALLIS,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> in <hi>Cheapside,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="5" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:56328:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56328:2"/>
            <head>A FIFTH LETTER Concerning the Sacred Trinity.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have met with an Answer to my <hi>Fourth Letter.</hi> It is not Long, and my Reply shall be but short. There is very little in it concerning the Merits of the Cause, (save that he resolves to hold the Conclusion:) and as to Personal Reflections, or Disdainful Expressions, I do not think fit to trouble the Reader with a long Reply. For those, I think, do not hurt me so much, as him that useth them.</p>
            <p>He is not pleased, <hi>pag.</hi> 1. that I said, <hi>I had Argued Calmly,</hi> without <hi>Scurrillous Language,</hi> or <hi>Reproachful Terms.</hi> And I appeal to the Reader,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56328:3"/>
whether it be not so. Nor doth he deny it. And if his Language were so too, he needed not to have <hi>made the Reader an Apology,</hi> to <hi>excuse his Expressions,</hi> that he might avoid <hi>the Character</hi> of a <hi>Common Railer,</hi> p. 1.</p>
            <p>But, he says, <hi>Abating the little Subtilties and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices, incomparably witty,</hi> there is not <hi>the least Grain of weight in my Letter.</hi> Of this the Reader is to be Judge, both as to the <hi>Weight,</hi> and as to the <hi>Wit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He says, <hi>It seems, a</hi> Socinian <hi>wrote against me.</hi> (True. And <hi>it seems</hi> he knew it: For he cites him.) <hi>And that himself wrote as an</hi> Arian. I think he should rather have said, He wrote, first as a <hi>Socinian</hi> (in his <hi>first</hi> Ten pages,) and then as an <hi>Arian,</hi> (in the <hi>other</hi> Ten.) For I do not find any thing, till toward the end of his Tenth page, whereby I could judge him other than a direct <hi>Socinian.</hi> And I think it will so appear to any other Reader.</p>
            <p>He takes to himself the name of <hi>Unitarian;</hi> by which I do not find the <hi>Arians</hi> were wont to be called. But it is a new Name which the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians</hi> have taken up, to distinguish themselves both from <hi>Us,</hi> and from the <hi>Arians.</hi> For the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> are rather <hi>Pluritarians,</hi> as holding more Gods than One. And the Book to which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56328:3"/>
refers us, <hi>p.</hi> 4. is intituled, <hi>The History of the</hi> Unitarians, <hi>otherwise called</hi> Socinians. And, in <hi>p.</hi> 11. where he first mentions the <hi>Arians,</hi> he doth introduce it with a Preface, minding me, that <hi>I write against Arians as well as Socinians:</hi> As having, till then, spoke for the <hi>Socinians</hi> only, not for the <hi>Arians.</hi> And even in his tenth page, (toward the beginning of it) what had been said of the <hi>Socinians</hi> by name, and of <hi>Socinus</hi> in particular, he takes to himself, as if one of that Party. <hi>He seems</hi> (saith he of me) <hi>to insinuate an aspersion on US, that WE believe not Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He tells us now, <hi>p. 3. He doth believe them;</hi> and I will suppose also, that he doth believe <hi>the Soul's Immortality.</hi> But, when he there says, that <hi>I bring a World of Arguments to prove the Immortality of the Soul;</hi> he mistakes again. For those Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were brought against <hi>Socinus,</hi> not to prove the Soul's <hi>Immortality;</hi> but, that <hi>the Soul, in its separate condition, was capable of Pain or Pleasure:</hi> which <hi>Socinus</hi> denied.</p>
            <p>For requital to this, he tells me, <hi>he had a good mind to prove the Existence of a Deity, for that he had heard of some men of the Profession of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>that have almost been Atheists at the heart.</hi> And truly if he should do so, I should not think it much amiss: For I have heard, the same sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of some <hi>Socinians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:56328:4"/>
He now tells me, <hi>p. 2. He never was a</hi> Socinian <hi>in his Life.</hi> Of what he had been in the former part of <hi>his Life,</hi> I had said nothing. (For I knew no more what it was, than who he is.) But <hi>(p.</hi> 37.) of what he was <hi>in the beginning of his Discourse.</hi> And 'tis plain he there writes like a direct <hi>Socinian</hi> (as was shewed but now,) though as an <hi>Arian</hi> some time after.</p>
            <p>He tells me <hi>(p.</hi> 2.) that <hi>he is neither the</hi> Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, <hi>nor his Friend, who assisted in his first Book.</hi> Neither did I say, that he is: but, that he might be for ought I knew. But whether he be or not, 'tis the same thing to me; for I am yet to fight in the dark with I know not whom.</p>
            <p>He says, <hi>He is not concerned to defend</hi> Socinus, <hi>or any man who hath dropt imprudent words.</hi> Nor did I require it of him. And, <hi>whether he were, or were not the same man</hi> who wrote before; yet, since here <hi>he acts another Person,</hi> I left it free for him (p. 1, 2.) <hi>to decline, if he pleased,</hi> what was said before; <hi>to grant what was there denied, or deny what was there granted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, he thinks, p. 1. <hi>I should not charge him with writing Contradictions, because such things may possibly be found in the others Answer.</hi> Nor do I. (This is only a piece of his wonted Artifice of <hi>Mis-reciting</hi> me.) I tell him indeed, it is hard to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56328:4"/>
please them both, when they do not agree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst themselves? And I did observe, (and argue from it) what he grants, though the other had denied it. But I never charge him with what the other had said. And (if he look it over again) he will find, that I did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front him (to shew thence a contradiction) with what the other had said: But did confront what himself had said in his ten first pages, with what he says in the other ten. And 'tis mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest, that in the first ten, he acts the <hi>Socinian;</hi> and in the latter ten, the <hi>Arian.</hi> But, in whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the twain he acts his own part, it was not easie to determine; till he now tells us, he is an <hi>Arian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had argued, <hi>p.</hi> 8, 14. That <hi>the Trinity are Persons, as really, and as properly, and fully perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally distinct, as Three Angels.</hi> And <hi>each Person (both Son and Holy-Ghost</hi> by name) <hi>compleat and intire in himself, with as compleat Personal distinction as that in Men and Angels.</hi> From whence when I inferred his <hi>owning the Personality of the Holy-Ghost:</hi> He fearing, it seems, he had over-shot himself, now tells us, p. 4. <hi>just as much as becomes on</hi> Arian. But if he <hi>own</hi> him to be as much a <hi>Person,</hi> as a <hi>Man,</hi> or <hi>Angel</hi> is a <hi>Person:</hi> it is as much, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps more, than we need contend for in this point.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:56328:5"/>
I had charged him also with <hi>mis-reciting</hi> me in many other things. As when I am introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced (very often) as talking of <hi>Two Gods, Three Gods, Personal Gods,</hi> of <hi>adding several Persons to our one God,</hi> and the like; (according as here also, he says, <hi>p.</hi> 7. that <hi>I say, you your self own Two Gods, and why may not I then Three?)</hi> when he knows very well, this is not my Language; nor is any thing of all this said by me. To this he now says, <hi>p. 5. 'Tis true enough he doth so;</hi> but that <hi>he doth it by Inference.</hi> But he should then speak it as <hi>his Inference,</hi> not cite it as <hi>my words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might have taken notice (amongst a great many gross mistakes,) that where I had men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, the <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> to be <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> he mis-recites it, <hi>p.</hi> 4. King of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> as if the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> had taken upon them to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and not that of <hi>Ireland.</hi> But of this, and a many more, I passed over, without reflecting on it. Because, in his Language, he is so very negligent and careless, (and otherwise obnotions) that it were endless to reflect on all.</p>
            <p>But I was obliged to take notice (because it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56328:5"/>
quite alters my Argument) of what he says, <hi>p.</hi> 4. that <hi>I say, Three sides make one Cube,</hi> &amp;c. which is neither true, nor are they my words. I argued not from <hi>three sides,</hi> but from the <hi>three Dimensions</hi> of a Cube. This he calls <hi>Trifling;</hi> and would perswade us that <hi>side</hi> and <hi>dimension,</hi> differ no more than <hi>Muting</hi> and—his other word, which is fitter for his mouth than mine. But though <hi>he</hi> perhaps know-no difference between them; yet he should not have cited it as <hi>my words</hi> (and say, that <hi>I say so,</hi> when I did not.) For I ought to know better; and that a <hi>Cube</hi> hath <hi>six sides,</hi> though but <hi>Three Dimensions.</hi> Nor did I argue from the <hi>six sides,</hi> but from the <hi>Three Dimensions.</hi> Yet I can forgive him this (rather than when he doth it willfully) though it mis-recite my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Because I believe it to be out of <hi>pure Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,</hi> not of <hi>Malice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He doth not like, <hi>p.</hi> 6. either <hi>This,</hi> or any other <hi>Simile</hi>'s; and would have me <hi>no more to insist upon them.</hi> (But he must excuse me from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his advice herein, unless he understood it better, than, by what was now said, he seems to do.) Because, <hi>if he be not mistaken</hi> (as I think he is) <hi>they are very far from my purpose.</hi> That is, He thinks, they do not prove the Trinity. True: These, alone, do not prove it (nor was it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56328:6"/>
they should.) But they prove (what they were brought to prove) that <hi>it is not a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction,</hi> or <hi>Inconsistent with Reason, that there may be three somewhats (which we call Persons) that are but one God.</hi> And thus much he had before granted, and doth now again confirm it, <hi>p. 3, 4. 'Tis true indeed</hi> (he says) <hi>I cannot say that there is a Contradiction in holding that there may be three Persons in God. For,</hi> saith he, <hi>There be two sorts of Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions; The one Express, the other Implyed. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not say, there is a Contradiction in holding it: Because I have not the Definition of the word</hi> God <hi>so exact, as to raise an implied contradiction: And, for an express contradiction, I do not pretend to it.</hi> If therefore there be no <hi>Contradiction,</hi> either <hi>Express,</hi> or <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied:</hi> It is what I was to prove.</p>
            <p>But, saith he, <hi>The dispute shall not end here. He will be allowed the Privilege</hi> (and no body doth deny it him,) <hi>to fetch in the First Commandment, to define the word God.</hi> With all my heart. I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver against it. (For what he says, more than once, <hi>p.</hi> 3, 4. that <hi>I meanly cry, he flies to Scripture,</hi> is but another piece of his wonted Art of <hi>mis-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing.</hi> There is nothing to that purpose in any thing of mine.) I do sometime blame him for <hi>changing the state of the Question:</hi> As, when he would have me <hi>prove by Reason,</hi> that <hi>It is so:</hi> I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56328:6"/>
tell him, That is not the Question, (nor is that to be proved by Reason:) The Question is, whether there is any thing <hi>in Reason,</hi> why <hi>it cannot be so.</hi> Now, let him keep to the Question; and then, if he think he can prove, from <hi>Scripture,</hi> that it is <hi>Inconsistent with Reason,</hi> for <hi>Three some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whats to be One God;</hi> or, that it is a <hi>Contradiction,</hi> for God the <hi>Creator,</hi> and God the <hi>Redeemer,</hi> and God the <hi>Sanctifier,</hi> to be <hi>the same God;</hi> or, that it is <hi>Impossible</hi> for the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the God of <hi>Isaac,</hi> and the God of <hi>Iacob,</hi> to be <hi>One and the same God:</hi> Let him try his skill. And, let him make what use he can of the <hi>First Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,</hi> to <hi>Define the word God,</hi> so as to prove this a <hi>Contradiction.</hi> But, when he had claimed this <hi>Privilege,</hi> (and no body doth deny it) He makes no use of it for any such Definition.</p>
            <p>The truth is, I had already granted him, from that Commandment, <hi>(p.</hi> 23, 24, 25, 28, 29.) more than he was willing I should grant: That <hi>we are to have NO OTHER GOD</hi> (Great or Little, Equal or Unequal,) but <hi>the Lord God of Israel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes, says he; There is one <hi>Supreme God,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Creature-God; But that this is not to have Two Personal Gods.</hi> How so? If these be <hi>Two Gods,</hi> and each of them a <hi>Person, (compleat and entire of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56328:7"/>
himself; as really, and properly, and fully, and perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally distinct, as a Man or Angel,</hi> as he had before told us at <hi>p.</hi> 8. 14.) they must needs be <hi>Two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal Gods.</hi> But we, according to the First Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, acknowledge but <hi>One</hi> God; and those <hi>three somewhats</hi> (whom in a metaphorical sense we call <hi>Persons)</hi> not so to be distinct as to become <hi>Three Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He hopes however to avoid the First Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, by saying that, though they be <hi>Two Gods,</hi> they are not <hi>two Gods Co-equal,</hi> p. 5. and that they <hi>worship the Son, not: with supreme Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship; with Mediation, not Adoration,</hi> p. 6. What he means by his <hi>two Worships;</hi> of <hi>Mediation,</hi> and <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> I do not well understand: unless they be new Names for <hi>Doulia</hi> and <hi>Latria.</hi> Nor do I remember, that I have before heard of a <hi>worship of Mediation.</hi> That Christ is our <hi>Mediator,</hi> I know; but did not know that he is our <hi>Worshipper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what doth he think of the <hi>Israelites,</hi> when they <hi>Worshipped</hi> the <hi>Golden Calf?</hi> Surely they did not think this <hi>Calf</hi> to be <hi>Co-equal</hi> with the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme God.</hi> Nor did they think it to be <hi>(Deus na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus)</hi> a God by <hi>Nature;</hi> but <hi>(Deus factus)</hi> a <hi>Made</hi> God: (for themselves had <hi>made</hi> it, just before:) Yet I never knew, that this did excuse them from <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:56328:7"/>
He doth not own Christ to be <hi>the True God,</hi> (for such there is but One, <hi>the only true God,)</hi> nor yet a <hi>false God;</hi> but a <hi>Mean</hi> between both, <hi>p.</hi> 6. Now 'tis true, the <hi>Heathen</hi> had (their <hi>Deos medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xumos)</hi> their <hi>Middling Gods:</hi> But I never knew that we could <hi>worship</hi> such, without <hi>Idolatry. Thou shalt Worship the Lord thy God</hi> (the Supreme God) <hi>and Him ONLY shalt thou serve,</hi> was our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Doctrine, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 10. And St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly calls him <hi>the True God,</hi> 1 Joh. 8. 20. (not a <hi>Middling</hi> God, between True and False) and therefore the <hi>same</hi> God with the Father, the <hi>Only true God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To that Character of <hi>Christ,</hi> Rev. 1. 8, 11. <hi>I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end, (the First and the Last) saith the Lord, which IS and WAS and is TO COME, the Almighty.</hi> He says, <hi>This stile is given him in opposition to Gods simpler one, I AM.</hi> But he should have observed, that the same title is, at <hi>ver.</hi> 4. given to God, in Contradistinction to Christ, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. And if it were there a Character of the Supreme God, it is so here. And if he think the simpler term <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I AM,</hi> to be more expressive of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme God; we have that also Emphatically given to Christ, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>He
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56328:8"/>
which IS,</hi> or <hi>the Being, over all;</hi> the Supreme Being.</p>
            <p>To what further I had brought, <hi>p.</hi> 30, 31, 32, 33. to prove him to be the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> the <hi>same God with the Father,</hi> (not a <hi>Middling,</hi> or <hi>Titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> God,) he makes no Reply: which therefore stands as it was; nor need I repeat it, because it may be read there. And it is so full and clear, that I need add no more to it.</p>
            <p>To what I had said of <hi>Ioh. 17. 3. To know Thee</hi> (not <hi>Thee Only,</hi> or <hi>Only Thee,) the Only True God.</hi> He saith, <hi>He hath Answered already.</hi> And I have already Replied; nor need I repeat it. Their Argument from thence is just in this form: The God of <hi>Abraham</hi> is the <hi>only true God;</hi> therefore, not the God of <hi>Isaac,</hi> or the God of <hi>Iacob.</hi> Yes, say I, the God of <hi>Isaac,</hi> and the God of <hi>Israel,</hi> is the <hi>same God,</hi> but under ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther consideration. So here; God the <hi>Creator</hi> (or God the Father) is the <hi>Only true God;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not God the <hi>Redeemer,</hi> nor God the <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier.</hi> Yes; God the <hi>Redeemer,</hi> and God the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifier,</hi> is <hi>the same</hi> God, the <hi>only true God.</hi> In like manner, <hi>Ier. 16. 14, 15. It shall no more be said, The Lord liveth that brought up the Children of Israel out of the land of Egypt; But, The Lord li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, that brought up the Children of Israel out of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56328:8"/>
North Country.</hi> Now, saith the First Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>I am the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of the land of Egypt; Thou shalt have No Other God but Me:</hi> Therefore not <hi>the God which brought them out of the North Country.</hi> Yes, say I, even <hi>this</hi> God also. Which is not <hi>another</hi> God; but <hi>the same</hi> God; though <hi>considered</hi> as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>another</hi> Benefit.</p>
            <p>There be many other things, both in his first and second Paper (his <hi>Answer</hi> and his <hi>Vindication)</hi> which lie very open to be <hi>Reflected</hi> on, if it were worth the while: But I think, I have said e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough already; and, he thinks, <hi>too much,</hi> (that I have been too <hi>stiff,</hi> too <hi>hard</hi> with him, <hi>p.</hi> 8.) which things I shall therefore omit, to save my self, and the Reader, the labour.</p>
            <p>But three things he calls me to account for omitting; <hi>His Reproof of my false Idea of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonality of God, the Impossibility and Blasphemy of his Incarnation, and of the Death of God,</hi> p. 8. Now when I had proved the things to be <hi>True;</hi> I thought that had been a sufficient Answer, to his calling them <hi>False, Impossible,</hi> and <hi>Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous.</hi> For they are never the more so, for his <hi>calling</hi> them so. And I know not what further Answer he should expect, unless he would have me say, 'Tis <hi>foul-mouthed Blasphemy</hi> in him, to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56328:9"/>
call it <hi>Blasphemy.</hi> But if I should answer him all along at this rate, according as his language deserves; we should, instead of Disputing fall to right down <hi>Railing;</hi> which is the <hi>Character</hi> he was afraid of, <hi>pag.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>However (to gratify him once more,) That by <hi>the Word,</hi> Joh. 1. is meant, <hi>Christ,</hi> himself owns: and, That <hi>this Word was God from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning;</hi> That <hi>he made the World, and all things;</hi> and that <hi>without him was not any thing made which was made;</hi> (and therefore, say I, <hi>Himself was not made;</hi> unless our <hi>Arian</hi> would have us think, <hi>He made Himself)</hi> That <hi>this God,</hi> is the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> we have proved at large, (if he deny it to be proved, we must leave it to the Reader to judge of the Arguments:) and <hi>this Word was made Flesh.</hi> (I hope I need not tell him, that to be <hi>made Flesh,</hi> and to be <hi>Incarnate,</hi> is all one; for every one understands this who know that <hi>Caro carnis</hi> is Latin for <hi>Flesh.)</hi> Therefore this is no <hi>Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again; That <hi>God in Christ suffered and died;</hi> and that <hi>we are Redeemed by the Blood of God,</hi> he had before told us, <hi>p.</hi> 13, 14. That this is the <hi>True God,</hi> we have proved at large (as was but now said;) Therefore the <hi>Death of God</hi> (that is, of him that was God as well as Man,) is <hi>no Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:56328:9"/>
Yet again; I do not take his <hi>Reproof</hi> (as he calls it) to be a <hi>Proof,</hi> that <hi>my Idea of Personality</hi> is <hi>False.</hi> And therefore I did not think it deserved an Answer; having proved the thing before. Yet I thought I had Answered it (as much as it need to be answered) when (at my <hi>pag.</hi> 36.) I told him (nor doth he deny it) that <hi>he seemed well pleased at his</hi> p. 20. <hi>that I owned the word Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to be but Metaphorical; though at his</hi> p. 7. (which is the Reproof he means) <hi>he did not like it.</hi> For tid after <hi>pag.</hi> 7. he acted the <hi>Socinian,</hi> and did not come to act the <hi>Arian,</hi> till afterward; and then he seemed, at <hi>p.</hi> 20. to like it well enough.</p>
            <p>I shall yet add somewhat more upon that point, which if it may not satisfy him, (who seems to intimate <hi>p.</hi> 8. that he <hi>will not</hi> be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,) may give some further satisfaction to the Reader.</p>
            <p>The word Person <hi>(persona)</hi> is originally a Latin word; and doth not properly signify a <hi>Man</hi> (so as that <hi>another person</hi> must needs imply <hi>another Man,)</hi> for then the word <hi>Homo</hi> would have served, and they needed not have taken in the word <hi>Persona:</hi> But rather, one <hi>so Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiated.</hi> And the <hi>same Man,</hi> if considered in <hi>other Circumstances</hi> (considerably different,) is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted <hi>another Person.</hi> And that this is the true
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56328:10"/>
notion of the word <hi>Person,</hi> appears by those no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Phrases, <hi>personam induere, personam deponere, personam agere, personam sustinere, sustineo unus tres personas,</hi> and many the like in approved Latin Authors. Thus the same <hi>Man</hi> may at once su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stain the <hi>Person</hi> of a <hi>King</hi> and of a <hi>Father;</hi> if he be invested both with <hi>Regal</hi> and <hi>Paternal</hi> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Now because the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Father,</hi> are for the most part not only different <hi>Persons</hi> but different <hi>Men</hi> also (and the like in other cases) hence it comes to pass, that <hi>another Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> is sometimes supposed to imply <hi>another Man:</hi> but not always, nor is that the proper sense of the word. It is Englished in our Dictionaries, by <hi>the state, quality, or condition, whereby one Man differs from another:</hi> and so, as the <hi>Condition</hi> alters, the <hi>Person</hi> alters, though the <hi>Man</hi> be the same. Our School-men of later Ages, do sometimes apply the word <hi>Persona</hi> to <hi>Angels</hi> as well as <hi>Men;</hi> but even that is but <hi>Metaphorical;</hi> nor do I find that it ever was so used, in approved Latin Authors, either for Angels, <hi>Genii,</hi> or their Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Gods; but for the different <hi>state</hi> or <hi>condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> only.</p>
            <p>Now when the same <hi>Man</hi> doth thus sustain two <hi>Persons,</hi> as that of a <hi>King,</hi> and that of a <hi>Father;</hi> he may as to one thing act as a <hi>King,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:56328:10"/>
by his <hi>Regal</hi> Authority; as to another thing as a <hi>Father,</hi> by his <hi>Paternal</hi> Authority. And these <hi>Authorities,</hi> may be in <hi>subordination</hi> one to the other, though the <hi>Man</hi> be the same. And what is done in either capacity, may indifferently be said to be done by the <hi>Man,</hi> or by the <hi>King:</hi> (as that <hi>David,</hi> or the <hi>King,</hi> pardoned <hi>Absolom;)</hi> and in like manner, by the <hi>Man,</hi> or by the <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being the true and proper notion of the word <hi>Person,</hi> we are next to consider what it is to signify in the present case. Where we are to consider, that the word <hi>Person</hi> is not applied in Scripture to <hi>these three</hi> so called: It is not there said, <hi>These three Persons are one,</hi> but only <hi>These three are one.</hi> 'Tis but the Church's usage that gives to these <hi>three somewhats,</hi> the name of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore our <hi>Arian</hi> was much mistaken, when he tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 20. that the <hi>word Person is the Hinge of the Controversy.</hi> The Hinge of the Controversy, is that notion concerning these <hi>three somewhats,</hi> which the Fathers (who first used it) did intend to design by the name <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</hi> So that we are not from the word <hi>Person</hi> to determine what was that <hi>Notion;</hi> but, from that <hi>Notion</hi> which they would express, to determine
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56328:11"/>
in what sense the word <hi>Person</hi> is here used. And if the word <hi>Person</hi> do not well fit that sense; all that can be thence inferred, is no more, but that they have made use of an Unfit Name to express their Notion. It is no more but as if a <hi>Cruel</hi> Pope take the name of <hi>Clement;</hi> or a wicked one the name of <hi>Pius;</hi> or if a Man be named <hi>Willson,</hi> whose Father's name was <hi>Thomas.</hi> And in all such cases, <hi>certitudo Rei tollit errorem Nominis.</hi> And if we know who is the <hi>Man</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed by such a <hi>Name,</hi> 'tis a Ridiculous exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, to say, This is not the <hi>Man,</hi> because that <hi>Name</hi> doth well agree with his <hi>Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Two of these Three being represent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Scripture, as <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Son;</hi> and this <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> said to <hi>Beget</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and all these in a sense <hi>metaphorical;</hi> (not in such sense as those words do properly signifie amongst Men;) they thought it not unfit (in continuation of the same Metaphor) to call them <hi>Persons.</hi> Because as the word <hi>Person</hi> doth <hi>properly</hi> agree to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Son</hi> in a <hi>proper</hi> sense; so doth the word <hi>Person</hi> in a <hi>metaphorical</hi> sense, to the <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Son</hi> so taken <hi>metaphorically;</hi> and the word <hi>Beget,</hi> by a like Metaphor.</p>
            <p>When therefore it is certain, that the Notion which the Ancient Fathers had concerning these
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56328:11"/>
               <hi>Three,</hi> which in a metaphorical sense they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Person,</hi> was this, That there is a <hi>Distinction</hi> between them, greater than that of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Attributes,</hi> but not so great as to make them <hi>Three Gods:</hi> it is manifest that they took the Metaphor, not from that abusive sense of the word <hi>Person,</hi> when (amongst us) it is put for <hi>Man;</hi> but from that proper sense of the word <hi>Persona,</hi> wherein it signifies the <hi>State, Condition, Office,</hi> or <hi>Relation</hi> of a Man, as variously <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstantiated</hi> with reference to others; whereof the <hi>same Man</hi> may sustain <hi>more than One.</hi> As when <hi>David,</hi> was the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Iesse,</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> of Israel. So if we say of any, that he is a <hi>Person</hi> of <hi>Honour,</hi> a <hi>Person</hi> of <hi>Worth,</hi> and a <hi>Person</hi> of <hi>Interest:</hi> That same <hi>Man</hi> may be all this, without becoming <hi>Three Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this our <hi>Arian</hi> may call this (if he please) a <hi>Quirk,</hi> a <hi>Criticism,</hi> an <hi>undermining the very Idea of the word Person,</hi> as he did in his, <hi>p.</hi> 7, 15, 17. (or may neglect it, if he pleases:) But the sober Reader (who understands it better) will have better thoughts of it.</p>
            <p>And therefore I shall not take his advice, <hi>p.</hi> 7, 8. to say that <hi>God is the name of an Office,</hi> that so he might <hi>know how to attack me,</hi> (as he says,) which while I talk so <hi>warily,</hi> he knows
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56328:12"/>
not how to do. I say, <hi>God</hi> is the name of the <hi>Nature;</hi> but if he will have <hi>Christ</hi> to be the name of an <hi>Office</hi> (the Mediatory Office,) and the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter,</hi> or even the <hi>Creator,</hi> the <hi>Redeemer,</hi> the <hi>Sanctifier,</hi> to be <hi>names of Work or Office,</hi> it will not be much amiss.</p>
            <p>Now, when I had said this Doctrine of ours is <hi>as old at least as the New Testament,</hi> (because I can prove it from thence;) he will have it <hi>(p.</hi> 5.) no older <hi>than the disputes of</hi> Alexander <hi>and</hi> Athanasius; <hi>which the Primitive Church knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of.</hi> But he barrs <hi>Quotations</hi> all along. And therefore I must not prove it (to be known to the Church before that time,) but leave it to the Judgment of Readers versed in Church-History, <hi>whose word must pass in this case;</hi> his or mine.</p>
            <p>To his Question, <hi>p. 6. Did the Iews ever hear of it before Christianity?</hi> I think they had some Intimations of it, as they had of the Resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: But not so clearly (either of them) as to be generally understood of all; nor so fully as in the New Testament. And I think it was from those notices of it amongst the Jews, that not only <hi>Plato</hi> derived much of his <hi>Philosophy,</hi> but other <hi>Heathens</hi> also much of their <hi>Mythology;</hi> though they did much disguise, and sometimes
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56328:12"/>
               <hi>Ridicule</hi> the notices they had thence, as our <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> now doth that of the Trinity. But this is not the business now before us.</p>
            <p>Toward the close, he is so kind as not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire <hi>Arianism to be imposed on others, any more than Trinitarianism on him,</hi> p. 8. But neither is this business before us; who are but <hi>Disputants,</hi> not <hi>Law-makers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But so constant he means to be to his cause, that he will <hi>be content to be perswaded out of his Name with his Opinion.</hi> (I think there is reason why he should change his <hi>Opinion,</hi> but as to the changing of his <hi>Name,</hi> he may use his discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.) But having said much (that he might not be thought to desert it) he thinks it <hi>advisable</hi> to <hi>drop the cause.</hi> Which he may, if he please, and leave it to the Reader to judge of what is said.</p>
            <p>I conclude as he doth; <hi>It is impossible but of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences will come; but wo unto him through whom they come. It were better for him that a Mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Febr. 14. 1690/1.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
I. Wallis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:56328:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Advertisement.</head>
            <p>THE Life of Faith, in Two Sermons to the University of <hi>Oxford,</hi> at St. <hi>Mary</hi>'s <hi>Christ-Church, Oxford;</hi> On <hi>Ianuary</hi> 6. 168frac34;, and <hi>Iune</hi> 29. following: By the same Author, Dr. <hi>Iohn Wallis.</hi> Sold by <hi>Tho. Parkhurst</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapside.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56328:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
