<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Irish footman's poetry, or, George the rvnner against Henry the walker, in defence of Iohn the Swimmer being a sur-rejoinder to the rejoinder of the rusty ironmonger who endeavored to defile the cleare streames of the water-poet's Helicon / the author George Richardson ...</title>
            <author>Richardson, George, fl. 1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2003-11">2003-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67888</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2346</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11950177</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11950177</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51368</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A67888)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51368)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 516:32 or 546:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Irish footman's poetry, or, George the rvnner against Henry the walker, in defence of Iohn the Swimmer being a sur-rejoinder to the rejoinder of the rusty ironmonger who endeavored to defile the cleare streames of the water-poet's Helicon / the author George Richardson ...</title>
                  <author>Richardson, George, fl. 1641.</author>
                  <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to George Richardson by Hazlitt.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Taylor by Wing.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 546:8 identified as Wing R1383 (number cancelled).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library and Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2000-00</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2001-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-02</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Oxford)</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-02</date>
            <label>TCP Staff (Oxford)</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2002-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51368:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51368:1"/>
            <p>THE IRISH FOOTMAN'S POETRY. OR GEORGE THE RVNNER, AGAINST HENRY THE WALKER, In defence of <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Swimmer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being A Sur-rejoinder to the Rejoinder of the rusty Ironmonger, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to defile the cleare streames of the Water-Poet's <hi>Helicon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author GEORGE RICHARDSON, an <hi>Hibernian Pedestrian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the yeare 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:51368:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51368:2"/>
            <head>TO GEORGE RICHARDSON HIS CVRRANT FRIEND IN any part of the Kings Dominions.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NO more (friend <hi>George</hi>) shall wee see</l>
               <l>Thee marching in the Infantr'ie,</l>
               <l>Now, thou hast gotten greater force,</l>
               <l>And mounted on the winged Horse,</l>
               <l>After no charriot thou shalt runne</l>
               <l>Henceforth, but that of Phaeton.</l>
               <signed>H. F.</signed>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>To <hi>GEORGE RICHARDSON</hi> the Pedestrian Poet.</head>
               <l>WHen first thy lines I read, I did admire</l>
               <l>Them like the learning of Promethean fire;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:51368:3"/>For he, who knowes thee have so little Art</l>
               <l>Could thinke that nature should so much impart</l>
               <l>To raise thee to the height to vindicate</l>
               <l>Th'Aquatique Poet, from the furious hate</l>
               <l>Of weavers, tinkers, (through the nose that whistle)</l>
               <l>Ironmongers, and Brethren of the bristle?</l>
               <l>Now trust me <hi>George,</hi> this work deserves such praise,</l>
               <l>That not to us but unto after dayes</l>
               <l>'T will say thou wer`t a Poet of a maw,</l>
               <l>As great, as thy great namesake of the Law.</l>
               <signed>W. B.</signed>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>To my ingenuous Countryman the Authour.</head>
               <l>'TIs stranger you would goe swift pac'd steps forsak</l>
               <l>And rest a strangers taske to undertake</l>
               <l>Doubtles you meane to ride hence forth; this matter,</l>
               <l>Deserves a horse, if not to ride by water.</l>
               <signed>T. LL.</signed>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>GEORGE RICHARDSON</hi> the Authour to the most ingenious aquatique Poet <hi>Mr: JOHN TAYLOR.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>SIr though a stranger to your selfe, your worth</l>
               <l>Is knowne to me, by what you have set forth;</l>
               <l>And though I cannot judge, yet I admire</l>
               <l>The lively flames of your Phaebean fire;</l>
               <l>Which wise-men doe approve, none doe deprave,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51368:3"/>But such as know not fancy, as this slave;</l>
               <l>Rusty, as his old iron, dull, as stone,</l>
               <l>Or th'anvill, that his ware is wrought upon.</l>
               <l>Who stupid slave (by what hee never writ</l>
               <l>But bought for's money) your undoubted wit,</l>
               <l>Would call in question, Sir, my infant muse</l>
               <l>(Seing this slave persist in his abuse;</l>
               <l>And knowing, 'twould a great dishonour bee</l>
               <l>For you to match your ingenuity</l>
               <l>With his notorious folly,) speedily</l>
               <l>Did undertake to make a swift reply.</l>
               <l>Which (soone as my employment did allow</l>
               <l>Mee time) in two houres space, I did run through.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Upon the title of <hi>Walkers</hi> Booke.</head>
               <l>BEhold the Master peice of <hi>Walker</hi>'s wit,</l>
               <l>Fancying his friend the Divell here at shit.</l>
               <l>Who first with malice did inspire his breast,</l>
               <l>And then his first Bookes matter did suggest.</l>
               <l>But t'is some silly fiend (as sure as day)</l>
               <l>The same perhaps was made an Asse i'th play</l>
               <l>Long since, but I'me deceiv'd, there's much brave wit</l>
               <l>I'th play, but <hi>Walkers</hi> bookes have none of it.</l>
               <l>What are they fit for then, that onely raile?</l>
               <l>Naught, but to wipe his shitten Divels taile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>1. His view of the transformed Divell.</head>
               <l>VVHat wondrous raptures this our Author here</l>
               <l>Doth dreame of wine, who hardly ere dranke beere,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51368:4"/>Or any thing so mighty <hi>Horace</hi>'s <hi>Lire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tels us what drinke doth most, what least inspire?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2. His Pedegree.</head>
               <l>A Monstrous Birth! sprong from the sheaves of wheat,</l>
               <l>Tresh'd out he should have said, for sure the great</l>
               <l>Father of this brave Sparke some tough blade was,</l>
               <l>That cudgelled the corne, and slash'd the grasse;</l>
               <l>For such his base demeanour speakes him, I</l>
               <l>Doe not detract from the old family</l>
               <l>Of Bredsall all this while, nor doe I know</l>
               <l>Whether he bee extracted thence, or no.</l>
               <l>Oft 'tis of worthy families the fate,</l>
               <l>To send some Children forth degenerate.</l>
               <l>But by his manners hee should rather bee</l>
               <l>Of that Ape Carriers affinity</l>
               <l>Hight <hi>Richard Walker,</hi> but call'd Cherry-lickam,</l>
               <l>Whom with his well taught-beast I saw at Wickam</l>
               <l>Doing rare trickes, with many a lofty straine</l>
               <l>For <hi>England</hi>s King, but clapt his Arse at <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Told money, which his Master cannot doe;</l>
               <l>Yet hee a Walker is, and Wanderer too.</l>
               <l>But lets admit our Libeller to bee</l>
               <l>Sprong from the wheaten Bredsall family,</l>
               <l>And that the Golden-sheaves that doe belong</l>
               <l>Vnto that family, this Ironmong-</l>
               <l>Er may justly challenge for his owne, yet hee</l>
               <l>Hath armes, which better fit his quality.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51368:4"/>
               <head>The Armes of his owne atcheivement.</head>
               <l>A Gridiron passant, on which lies</l>
               <l>A Libeller doth simbolize</l>
               <l>A Cart, that doth up Holborne passe,</l>
               <l>A sable trivet next, wee place</l>
               <l>In cheif, which you may easily</l>
               <l>Conceive, doth Tiburne signifie,</l>
               <l>To seeke a Rope weel'e not take paines,</l>
               <l>For worst delinquents hang in Chaines,</l>
               <l>Then for supporters, there shall stand</l>
               <l>Two men as true as steele, in hand</l>
               <l>They rusty Iron forkes shall weild,</l>
               <l>Thus you may blazonize his sheild.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2. His Disposition.</head>
               <l>IS it not vaine? to tax his muse, that writ</l>
               <l>Of a bad Subject to discover it</l>
               <l>Vnto the heedles World; that when they see,</l>
               <l>The thing attir'd in it's deformity,</l>
               <l>They then may loath it, that before appear'd</l>
               <l>Pleasing to them, before the mist was clear'd.</l>
               <l>Taylor his whore, if rightly understood</l>
               <l>Deserves much honour, 'twas his Countrie's good</l>
               <l>That set his muse on worke, the rogue set forth</l>
               <l>In <hi>Spanish,</hi> is a Booke of matchlesse worth.</l>
               <l>Which honest men approve, hee that doth looke</l>
               <l>Awry on it, is Subject of the Booke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51368:5"/>
               <head>4. The Encounter.</head>
               <l>I Know 'tis not your custome, to abuse</l>
               <l>The peoples eares, with fancies of your muse;</l>
               <l>For where there's no invention, straines of wit</l>
               <l>Can have no birth, were you endu'd with it</l>
               <l>What monsters you'd beget alreadi's knowne</l>
               <l>By fathering of these are not your owne.</l>
               <l>But what you publish here, if wee admit</l>
               <l>To bee your owne, Taylor those workes hath writ,</l>
               <l>That a just Catalogue of them will fill,</l>
               <l>More leaves, then you have stained with your quill,</l>
               <l>Leave then your ostentation, time ne're saw,</l>
               <l>An Eagle dar'd to combate by a Daw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5. His Religion.</head>
               <head> 6. His Hypocrisie.</head>
               <l>I'Ve made a scrutinie, but cannot find</l>
               <l>One word in Taylors Booke shews him inclin'd</l>
               <l>To Popery, 'tis true hee cann't approve</l>
               <l>Of Brownists, nor the Familists of love,</l>
               <l>Of Anabaptists, nor of Adamites,</l>
               <l>Nor those instruct their audience, when the lights</l>
               <l>Are out, and by their owne example too</l>
               <l>As well as precept, teach them what to doe;</l>
               <l>Though Ir'nmongers or Feltmakers they bee,</l>
               <l>Or Coblers, or what els fraternity.</l>
               <l>This being all, 'tis straing hee not invites</l>
               <l>Your spleene, that hath describ'd the Adamites,</l>
               <l>The Brownists conventicle too that writ,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51368:5"/>But 'tis your envy to brave Taylors wit,</l>
               <l>Hee onely is accus'd, although they bee</l>
               <l>Guilty of as much Popery as hee.</l>
               <l>Your faith I doe not question, nor will make</l>
               <l>Much matter of argument, what side you take.</l>
               <l>But Taylor's guilty of Hipocrisie,</l>
               <l>Because hee did comply with miserie.</l>
               <l>A powerfull reason! shame to vent such stuffe</l>
               <l>Snuffers are sweeter ware, with unquencht snuffe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7. The Church persecuted by water.</head>
               <l>A Title (which doth promise at the least,</l>
               <l>A copious treatise) like that pregnant beast,</l>
               <l>That travell'd with a mountaine, yet brought forth</l>
               <l>A litle molehill, see the lesser worth!</l>
               <l>Of this poore fellow, who can scarce discerne</l>
               <l>A difference, 'twixt him, did guide the sterne</l>
               <l>Of the great Barke oth'Church, and him that neere</l>
               <l>A bigger vessell then an oare did steere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8. His weakenesse in judgement</head>
               <l>NOw I doe pitty thee, that dares to tax</l>
               <l>Anothers judgemen? when more time 'twill aske</l>
               <l>Then was to teach the Asse to speake, assign'd,</l>
               <l>To render thy dull wits halfe so refin'd,</l>
               <l>As the well-tuter'd Ape, that's Pupill to</l>
               <l>Thy name-sake <hi>Walker</hi>; yet with much adoe</l>
               <l>Tha'st made an Anagram of thine owne name,</l>
               <l>And an AEnigma to thou think'st, what fame?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51368:6"/>Will not be due to thee? well thou maist scoren</l>
               <l>The Dung-hill Pamphlets thou set'st forth t'adorne</l>
               <l>With th'honoured subscription of the name,</l>
               <l>That's grac'd, with such an heavenly Anagram.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>9. His horrible lies.</head>
               <l>ONe Distichon is all the verse ha's writ</l>
               <l>There's just as many faults, as lines in it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>10. My sincerity to <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>IF you affirme this with sincerity,</l>
               <l>Im'e confident in it wee doe agree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>11. His humble Petition.</head>
               <l>VVHat forward impudence is this? to dare</l>
               <l>Before those noble Senators to appeare</l>
               <l>Clad in such ragges? if ought 'gainst Church or State,</l>
               <l>Hee hath offended, with an equall hate</l>
               <l>I shall pursue him, or transgress'd the lawes,</l>
               <l>And made unto himselfe a guilty cause,</l>
               <l>Or that it shall appeare, in the least word,</l>
               <l>Hee hath <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aduc'd, that lov'd, and honour'd Lord;</l>
               <l>But if o'th contrary it shall appeare,</l>
               <l>His conscience and his judgement, were more clear,</l>
               <l>And that hee did nor Church, nor State traduce,</l>
               <l>Nor that most noble Lord; with least abuse;</l>
               <l>Then Caesar-like, when <hi>Horace</hi> did acquite</l>
               <l>Himselfe, before him; then, when 'gainst all right,</l>
               <l>A base officious Tribune did accuse</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51368:6"/>The harmeles recreation of his muse;</l>
               <l>As, that in mistique Hieroglyphickes, hee</l>
               <l>Had plotted 'gainst the State, some teachery;</l>
               <l>Great Caesar gave the Poet, higher place</l>
               <l>In's favour, and the Tribune, the disgrace</l>
               <l>To weare a paire of Asses eares; so now,</l>
               <l>When these great Senators, on Taylor's brow</l>
               <l>Read innocence, his merrit they shall raise,</l>
               <l>By giving thee the whip, and him the bayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>12. The Conclusion.</head>
               <l>ANd now friend <hi>Walker</hi> this, but to prepare</l>
               <l>My muse to encounter, if you dare,</l>
               <l>With a foote-Poet, enter in the sand,</l>
               <l>You, as you have lost by water may by land.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <l>ALthough in <hi>Ireland</hi> I was born and bred</l>
            <l>In <hi>Englands</hi> Church I nourisht am and fed</l>
            <l>Therefore let no dull Brownists apprehend</l>
            <l>That in defence of Popery I contend;</l>
            <l>I doe esteeme both Sects as most a curst</l>
            <l>But of the twayn I thinke the Brownist worst.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
