<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of the Sabbath and the Lords Day Wherein the difference both in their institution and their due observation is briefly handled. By Christopher Dow, B.D.</title>
            <author>Dow, Christopher, B.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7088</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110113</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845728</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845728</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10649</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A69228)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10649)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1411:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of the Sabbath and the Lords Day Wherein the difference both in their institution and their due observation is briefly handled. By Christopher Dow, B.D.</title>
                  <author>Dow, Christopher, B.D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Flesher for John Clark, and are to be sold at his shop under S. Peters Church in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC XXXVI. [1636]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Variant: title page has "intsitution".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sunday --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10649:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10649:1"/>
A DISCOVRSE OF THE SABBATH AND THE LORDS DAY.
<hi>WHEREIN</hi> THE DIFFERENCE BOTH IN THEIR INTSI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TUTION and their due OBSERVATION is briefly handled.</p>
            <p>BY CHRISTOPHER DOW, B. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by M. FLESHER for JOHN CLARK, and are to be ſold at his ſhop under <hi>S. Peters Church</hi> in <hi>Cornhill. MDC XXXVI.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10649:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10649:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſubſtance of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, being at firſt, the materialls of ſome let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters written for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of a private friend, was afterwards drawne together into the forme in which it now appeares, and found the favour, from ſome unto whom it was communicated, to bee deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Preſſe; for which end it hath lyen in the Licenſers hand, now above a yeare expecting the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Prelate who upon ſpeciall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion then offered, (as it appeares) by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, undertook this argument: Which having performed, like himſelfe, with ſuch variety of learning and profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of judgement, this Pamphlet of
<pb facs="tcp:10649:3"/>
mine may now juſtly ſeeme as unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to follow, as heretofore it was unable and unworthy to leade the way: yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the brevity of it might make it paſſe and finde acceptance with ſome; and that, being of a mean ſtraine, it might better meete with common capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, then larger and more elaborate tractates; I was willing it ſhould ſee the light, and that in its owne garbe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any poliſhing or alteration. And ſo I commend thee and it to Gods bleſſing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>PErlegi hunc tractatum Theologicum, cuititulus eſt <hi>[A diſcourſe of the Sabbath, and of the Lords day, &amp;c.]</hi> in quo nihil reperio ſanae doctrinae, aut bonis moribus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarium, quominus cum utilitate publicâ imprimi poſſit, ita tamen, ut ſi non intra tres menſes proximè ſequentes typis mandetur, haec licentia ſit omnino irrita.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ex Aedibus Lambethanis <date>Novemb. 18. 1635.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>GUIL. BRAY.</signed>
R. P. D. Arch. Cant. Capel. Domeſticus.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10649:3"/>
            <head>A DISCOVRSE OF THE SABBATH AND LORDS DAY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat men may not bee decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with ſhewes, and miſtake <hi>Iudaiſine</hi> for <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> or that they, who ſo miſtaking, uſe to diſrelliſh all things which ſuit not with the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of their <hi>Catechiſmes,</hi> may not thinke they have ingroſſed all Religion and Piety to themſelves, and they thereby incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to proceed in their hard cenſures of thoſe that concurre not with them: And that the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and religious care, which is eminent in the Governours of our Church and State, may appeare in their true luſtre, and outſhine thoſe miſts, wherewith ſome ſeeke to obſcure them: And that it may appeare alſo that they whoſe chiefeſt care, next to their duty to God, is to yeeld all ready and cheerefull obedience to <hi>Gods Vicegerent,</hi> and to thoſe <hi>Reverend Fathers</hi> which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10649:4"/>
under God, and His <hi>Sacred. Majeſty</hi> have the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſight of this <hi>Church,</hi> are not hood-winkt in their obedience, or blindly led to yeeld to their Commands without reſpect to religion or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as if they had rather obey <hi>them</hi> then <hi>God;</hi> I have adventured upon that obloquie, which hath beene the lot of ſuch as (though upon never ſo good grounds) diſſent from theſe men in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. And this I the rather doe in this ſubject, for as much as in it I have not onely the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſacred Scriptures, (which are the rule of things to be beleeved and done) but, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent alſo of the whole <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> neither the <hi>Ancient Fathers</hi> nor the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> (to omit the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Doctrine though in this caſe not to be condemned, is of little cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with thoſe whom I diſſent from) ever teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other Doctrine then that which I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the defence of. For whereas in other things which they diſlike among us, they have for Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons the principall Authors of the Reformation abroad, and the Prime Doctors among them, whoſe learning and piety, much admired by them, may ſeeme to pleade for their over-earneſt, and heedleſſe embracing of their <hi>Principles:</hi> In theſe <hi>Sabbatarian Paradoxes,</hi> they are ſingular and left alone, without the Patronage of thoſe whom otherwiſe they ſo much admire, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the example of any <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendome.</hi> And I beleeve further (being ledd thereunto by their doctrine, delivered in their Writings ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, and by the generall and conſtant relation,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:10649:4"/>
of all that have knowne their practiſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared it with ours) that there is not a <hi>State</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> who have made better proviſion for the due obſervance of the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> and the decent performance of the ſacred Acts of Gods Worſhip, then are to bee found in the <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> and <hi>Temporall Lawes</hi> of this <hi>Realme,</hi> nor where ſuch <hi>Lawes</hi> are more duely executed by thoſe in Authority, or more generally obſerved or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by all, then they are at this day among us. Theſe conſiderations have animated mee to this worke, hoping thereby to ſettle the mindes of ſuch as are contrary minded rather for want of due conſideration, then out of wilſulneſſe and contempt of Authority.</p>
            <p>Hee that goes about to vindicate the juſt liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the uſe of lawfull recreations on the Sunday, ſhall finde himſelfe upon a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſadvantage. 1. In regard of the precon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived opinion among weake people, of their pietie and religious zeale which hold the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And 2. in that the ſtrict obſervance of that day, is by ſome made a prime <hi>character</hi> of a <hi>good Chriſtian,</hi> to diſtinguiſh him from a <hi>carnall World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Queſtion</hi> in hand accounted as an infallible marke to know the ſtate of Religion; which ſtands or falls according, as it is either way determined. It behoves mee therefore to walke with a wary and ſure foot, and following the truth to ſtrike an equall courſe betweene an <hi>over nice ſtrictneſſe,</hi> and a <hi>profane licence:</hi> and ſo to ſpeake in this cauſe, as that the <hi>ſoberly religious</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:10649:5"/>
ſhall have no juſt cauſe to complaine; nor the <hi>profane</hi> be incouraged to go on in licentiouſneſſe. Either of which wayes as it is eaſie to offend, ſo in whether of the two a man offends moſt, is as uneaſie to determine; the one letting looſe, the other enſnaring mens conſciences; the one ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up the kingdome of Heaven, and making the way thither more narrow then it is; the other making it broader, and enlarging the mouth of Hell. My aime and endeavour ſhall bee to avoid both.</p>
            <p>Among thoſe things which have occaſioned the generall prevailing of the <hi>Opinion,</hi> That the <hi>Sunday</hi> or <hi>Lords Day</hi> ought to bee obſerved with ſuch <hi>ſtrictneſſe</hi> as will admit no works which may be called <hi>Ours,</hi> that is, (as they call them) <hi>workes of our particular Callings,</hi> and much leſſe <hi>Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> it is none of the leaſt that now of a long time among us (contrary to the uſe of the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> yea and of our owne in the memory of our <hi>Fathers)</hi> it hath loſt its <hi>Chriſten name,</hi> and entertained the <hi>Iewiſh,</hi> being vulgarly knowen and called by the name of the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> Whence it comes to paſſe that men (prone more to reſpect names then things) never heeding the difference betweene the old <hi>Sabbath</hi> and our <hi>Sunday,</hi> or thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it to bee little or none at all, take thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture, which ſo ſeverely prohibit all work upon the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> as if they did no leſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to <hi>us</hi> now, then heretofore to the <hi>Iewes:</hi> and by this meanes, thoſe precepts, threatnings, and promiſes which concerned the obſervation of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:10649:5"/>
               <hi>Sabbath,</hi> are preſſed upon us point blanck. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as indeed they concerne us onely indirectly, and cannot without fetching a compaſſe, be alledged at all for our <hi>Sunday.</hi> Now the Scripture being ſo expreſſe (as it is apprehended) for the ſtrict obſervance of our <hi>Sunday</hi> under the name of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> no marvell if men have made it a prime <hi>Caſe</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and that ſo many <hi>ſcruples</hi> are dayly raiſed, and ſo many <hi>traditions</hi> broached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>beginning</hi> and <hi>ending</hi> of the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> about the <hi>works</hi> of a mans particular <hi>Calling,</hi> what they are, and how farre <hi>lawfull</hi> on that <hi>Day:</hi> what are the proper <hi>duties</hi> of the <hi>Day,</hi> and the like? For the cleare reſolution therefore of this <hi>Queſtion; Whether the uſe of Recreations may ſtand with the due obſervation of the Lords Day,</hi> it is convenient that I have ſome recourſe to the Sabbath. Where becauſe I love not <hi>Cramben ſaepiùs coctam apponere,</hi> or to ſtuffe my diſcourſe with a tedious explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe things which are commonly known; and every where to be found, I will with as much brevity as the cauſe will ſuffer, inquire into theſe 4. particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Whether, and how farre forth the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement concerning the Sabbath is moral, and perpetuall, and ſo belonging to Chriſtians.</item>
               <item>2. When and by whom the Lords day was inſtituted.</item>
               <item>3. What workes the lews might doe on their Sabbath.</item>
               <item>4. Whether, and what liberty Chriſtians now have on the Sunday more then they had, and how farre that liberty is to be extended?</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:10649:6"/>
               <hi>To begin with the firſt.</hi> The <hi>law</hi> which God gave unto his people the <hi>Iewes</hi> (according to the <hi>three-fold variety</hi> of the <hi>object,</hi> or things preſcribed) is <hi>three-fold, Morall, Ceremoniall,</hi> and <hi>Iudiciall.</hi> The <hi>Morall</hi> is that which concernes the <hi>manners</hi> of men, <note place="margin">What the Morall law is.</note> and belongs to them as men: and this commands thoſe things which are in themſelves acceptable, and well-pleaſing to God, and thoſe which hee will have all men every where, and at all times to obſerve, as the perpetuall, and unchangeable rule of living, being the expreſſe image of the minde of God, according to which, hee (who is the Law-giver) judges it meete and right, that the reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able creatures ſhould order their lives. The <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">What the ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all law is.</note> belongs to men, as joyned together in that <hi>Society</hi> which is called the <hi>Church,</hi> and this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines thoſe <hi>precepts</hi> which concerne the <hi>externall worſhip</hi> of God, and were given by him to the <hi>Iewiſh Church,</hi> in accommodation to the times, in which the <hi>Church</hi> was <hi>under age,</hi> and <hi>under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> and therefore inſtituted for the <hi>ſignifying, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figuring,</hi> and <hi>ſealing</hi> of the truth of the <hi>promiſes</hi> made to them, to be fulfilled in the exhibition of our <hi>Saviour:</hi> and withall for the preſervation of <hi>order,</hi> and <hi>decencie</hi> in their <hi>Eccleſiaſticall meetings,</hi> and <hi>performances.</hi> The <hi>judiciall</hi> belongs to men as <note place="margin">What the judiciall law is.</note> joyned in a <hi>civill Society</hi> or <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth,</hi> contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the forme of <hi>civill government,</hi> to be uſed by them, tending to their good, as they were a <hi>Society,</hi> and to the preſervation, and exacting of the <hi>eut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worſhip</hi> of God, and the <hi>diſcipline</hi> thereof, as it was commanded in the <hi>Morall</hi> and <hi>Ceremoniall</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:10649:6"/>
Lawes. So that the <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> Law determined <note place="margin">Aquin. 1. 2. qu. 101.</note> the <hi>Morall</hi> in order to God; the <hi>Politicall</hi> or <hi>judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall</hi> in order to men in a <hi>civill ſociety;</hi> and both in accommodation to that <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> And theſe though they have in them ſomething which is <hi>juris moralis,</hi> and ſo farre forth are contained under the <hi>Morall precepts,</hi> yet being fitted to ſerve that <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> which was to be held in expectation of the <hi>Meſsias;</hi> when the time came that he was <hi>actually exhibited,</hi> and ſo the promiſe fulfilled, the <hi>ſhadowes</hi> were then of no longer uſe, <note place="margin">Col. 2. 17.</note> the <hi>body</hi> being come: and therefore at the time of the <hi>death</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they were abrogated <hi>de jure,</hi> ſo that they became <hi>unneceſſary,</hi> and <hi>unprofitable,</hi> and had their power of <hi>obligation</hi> taken away: And afterward when by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> doctrine <hi>Chriſtians</hi> came to underſtand that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was the <hi>end of the Law,</hi> and when the <hi>Temple</hi> (the ſeate of their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the place deſtined to the uſe of thoſe <hi>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies)</hi> was deſtroyed, they were <hi>de facto</hi> actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and fully taken away: and thoſe things, which before the <hi>death</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> were commanded, and in that <hi>interim,</hi> betweene his <hi>death</hi> and the <hi>deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of the <hi>Temple</hi> (which was the ſpace allotted for the <hi>ſolemne funeralls</hi> of the <hi>Iewiſh Synagogue)</hi> were tolerable, though already dead, became from that time forward deadly and intolerable. So that, onely the <hi>Morall</hi> Law remaines now in force, for the practiſe of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> The <hi>ceremoniall</hi> and <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall</hi> (excepting in that wherein they are redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible to this) are antiquated, and out of date. Now the precepts of the <hi>Morall</hi> Law are ſummarily
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10649:7"/>
comprehended in the <hi>Decalogue</hi> or <hi>ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> which had this prerogative peculiar to them, that they were delivered (not by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but) by <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, and by him written in <hi>tables</hi> of <hi>ſtone,</hi> and preſerved in the <hi>Arke;</hi> to ſhew their dignity above others, and to note out the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity of obſervance, which was due unto them. Where, before wee apply theſe things to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe, two things are to be noted. Firſt, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aq. 1. 2. q.</hi> 100. Moral pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts not all equally belonging to the law of nature.</note> That howſoever all the precepts of the <hi>Morall</hi> law belong to the Law of <hi>Nature</hi> (as being agreeable to reaſon, which is the rule of Humane actions) and are in that reſpect of perpetuall obſervance; yet all of them are not of the ſame ranke, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long in the ſame degree and manner to the law of <hi>Nature.</hi> There are ſome things which by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct <note place="margin">Aq. ibid.</note> of <hi>nature,</hi> and naturall light of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, wee preſently ſee to be <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad,</hi> and which are ſo plaine, that without any great conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, they may by the <hi>firſt principles,</hi> or <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon notions</hi> implanted in us, be either approved, or rejected, and theſe are abſolutely of the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>nature.</hi> Others there are that require more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of <hi>circumſtances,</hi> and the uſe of <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> to apprehend, and judge of them: and theſe are ſo of the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>nature,</hi> that notwithſtanding they require the helpe of <hi>diſcipline,</hi> by which thoſe which are ignorant, and not able by diligent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration or diſcourſe, to attaine to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them, may be inſtructed by the wiſe and learned. And laſtly, there are ſome, to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge whereof humane reaſon ſtands in neede of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10649:7"/>
               <hi>Divine</hi> Inſtruction. And theſe two latter ſorts, eſpecially the laſt, though they in ſome ſort be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Law of Nature (and were haply at our firſt Creation, written in the tables of mans heart, in more plaine Characters, and more eaſie to be read then now ſince the fall, they are) may, in reſpect of the other, be termed <hi>morall (non ratione naturae, ſed diſciplinae)</hi> not in regard of <hi>nature</hi> dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but in regard of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> informing <hi>nature. Secondly,</hi> that the <hi>fourth Commandement</hi> (as it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes the externall obſervation of the <hi>ſeaventh day)</hi> is not <hi>morall</hi> either of theſe wayes. Whence S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Inter em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia illa 10. praecepta ſolum ibi quod de Sabbato po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum eſt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurate ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervandum praecipitur. Aug. ep 118 cap. 12. Caetera ibi praecepta propriè ſicut praecepta ſunt ſine ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la figura a ſignificatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Idem Ibid.</note> ſaith, That <hi>among all thoſe ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, that onely of the Sabbath is figuratively to be obſerved;</hi> whereas <hi>(as hee after ſaith) Wee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the other Commandements there properly as they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded without any figurative ſignification.</hi> And generally the <hi>Ancients</hi> (as <hi>Calvin</hi> hath truly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved) called this Precept <note n="b" place="margin">Inſt. l. 2. &amp; 8 §. 28. Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratile ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teres nuncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare ſolent. Dinudia tantum ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parte rem attingunt. Id. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>a ſhadow,</hi> which <hi>(as he there ſaith)</hi> was <hi>truly,</hi> but not <hi>fully</hi> ſaid of them. And therefore they do better, and more fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the nature of this <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement,</hi> which ſay it is <note n="c" place="margin">Sabbati praeceptum eſt partim Morale, partim Ceremoniale, unde into contine<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er aliquid ater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, et aliquid temporarium. Mart. Theſ. in Exod. 2.</note> 
               <hi>partly morall,</hi> and <hi>partly ceremoniall.</hi> So <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and generally all <hi>Divines</hi> both <hi>reformed</hi> and others, uſe now to ſpeake. Now if any ſhall therefore thinke it unworthy a place in the <hi>Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue,</hi> and to be rankt with thoſe precepts which are <hi>morall,</hi> and of perpetuall obſervance; <note n="d" place="margin">Aquin. 2. 2. q. 122. art. 4 ad primum &amp; ſecundum. Vidaeundem 1. 2. q. 100 a. 5. ad ſecundum.</note> 
               <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> may ſeeme to give them full ſatisfaction, who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10649:8"/>
ſaith, 1. that the Precept concerning the Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> is put among the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the <hi>Decalogue</hi> for that which is <hi>moral</hi> in it. 2. That this Precept as <hi>Ceremoniall,</hi> ought rather to have a place in the <hi>Decalogue</hi> then any other: The other <hi>Ceremonies</hi> being ſignes of ſome <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular effects</hi> of God; but this of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was a ſigne of a <hi>generall benefit, viz.</hi> the <hi>Creation</hi> of the <note place="margin">Medul. Theol l. 2. c 15 <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Vniverſe:</hi> So that that which <hi>Ameſius</hi> will have a moſt certaine rule, and received among all the beſt <hi>Divines</hi> (as he calls them) That all, and onely the <hi>Morall</hi> precepts were delivered by the voyce of God himſelfe, and by Him written in the <hi>tables</hi> of <hi>ſtone,</hi> is not true, unleſſe Saint <hi>Auguſtine, Calvin, Martyr,</hi> &amp;c. be in his eſteeme none of the beſt Divines. Yet perhaps wee may admit that rule ſo farre as to ſay, That <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Morall Precepts</hi> are contayned in the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> and that every <hi>Precept</hi> there contayned is <hi>Morall,</hi> though <hi>all</hi> of every Precept be not ſo, but may have ſomething that is <hi>ceremoniall</hi> annexed to it: which haply God thought good to place among the <hi>morall precepts,</hi> to intimate the perpetuall neceſſity of having ſome <hi>ceremonies</hi> in the Church; though that <hi>ceremonie</hi> be not neceſſarily perpetuall, but (with the reſt of that nature) to expire at the death of Chriſt: which though wee admit, yet cannot any juſtly charge us, that wee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh any of the <hi>tenne words;</hi> or that wee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punge <hi>one Commandement</hi> out of the <hi>Decalogue;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4 13.</note> in as much as wee affirme, that onely which was <hi>ceremoniall</hi> in this <hi>Commandement</hi> to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10649:8"/>
and out of date, and that there is in it a <hi>morality</hi> ſtill remaining, which retaines its full power of obligation, and exacts the ſame obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, under the ſame penalty, which it did at its firſt promulgation or inſcription in the heart of <hi>Adam.</hi> In which reſpect, the <hi>Church</hi> hath good cauſe ſtill to uſe her accuſtomed Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phona at the repeating of this <hi>Commandement,</hi> as well as at any of the reſt, and to pray <hi>Lord have mercy upon us, and encline our hearts to keepe this law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here, becauſe ſome who love to have this <hi>Commandement</hi> termed <hi>morall</hi> (though thereby they intend no more then what hath beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready granted) uſe ſo to argue, as if they did not acknowledge it at all to be <hi>ceremoniall;</hi> it will not be amiſſe, before wee proceed any further, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere ſome of the principall arguments that are brought to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And I wil begin with that of our <hi>Saviour, Math.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1.</note> 5. 17. <hi>Thinke not that I came to deſtroy the Law or the Prophets; I came not to deſtroy, but to fulfill.</hi> Which words (in their opinion) make ſtrongly for the <hi>morality</hi> and <hi>perpetuall obligation</hi> of the <hi>fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement:</hi> For from hence they argue to this purpoſe. That which our Saviour did not <hi>deſtroy,</hi> but <hi>fulfill,</hi> is ſtill in force; but hee did not <hi>deſtroy</hi> the law contayned in the <hi>Decalogue:</hi> Therefore it is ſtill in force.</p>
            <p>For anſwere hereunto, I ſay, That in this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment two things are by them ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> they ſuppoſe, that by the <hi>Law</hi> in this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10649:9"/>
place, is meant only the <hi>law</hi> contained in the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue</hi> or <hi>ten Commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That our Saviours <hi>fulfilling,</hi> and not <hi>deſtroying</hi> this law, was the <hi>ratifying</hi> and <hi>perpetua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of the obſervation of it under the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If wee grant them both theſe, wee ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> for altering the day from the <hi>ſeventh</hi> to the <hi>eight</hi> or <hi>firſt day of the week,</hi> which cannot ſtand with this expoſition of our Saviours ſpeech, who, in the words following, ſaith expreſly, <hi>That not one jot or title ſhall paſſe from the Law.</hi> But both theſe are beſide the meaning and intent of our Saviour, as will eaſily appeare to any that (with indifferency) doth conſider his words. For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> which our Saviour here ſpeakes of, is of larger extent and latitude, and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends not onely the <hi>Decalogue</hi> or <hi>law morall,</hi> but the <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> and <hi>judiciall</hi> alſo: As being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed put for the <hi>Pentateuch</hi> or <hi>five bookes</hi> of <hi>Moſes:</hi> And ſo, <hi>The Law and the Prophets,</hi> as much as, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 26. 29 31. Mal<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onat. in Mat. 7. 12.</note> 
               <hi>and the Prophets:</hi> Which formes of ſpeech, are uſed as a <hi>Periphraſis</hi> of the <hi>old Teſtament,</hi> of which theſe two are the maine eſſentiall parts: The <hi>Bookes</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo containing and deſcribing the Law, that they reſerre whatſoever elſe they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine unto that, receive their <hi>denomination</hi> from it, as from the principall ſubject of them. The <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> that is, <hi>their Bookes,</hi> comprehend all the reſt of the <hi>old Teſtament,</hi> which the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> divide in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>former</hi> and <hi>latter Prophets,</hi> and the <hi>Hagiogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Fra<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. Iu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ words">
                     <desc>〈◊…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> All which (though they be not <hi>Propheſies)</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:10649:9"/>
being written by <hi>divine inſpiration,</hi> and by <hi>holy men</hi> as they were moved by the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> may juſtly be termed, <hi>The word of Prophecy,</hi> and paſſe <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.</note> under the name of the <hi>Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>Law</hi> is taken in this ſenſe, is manifeſt by the uſe of the ſame phraſe elſe where: Where, not only the duties commanded in the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> but <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>faith in him,</hi> is ſaid to be taught and witneſſed by the <hi>Law:</hi> to which purpoſe the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> uſeth the ſame phraſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 28. 23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 21. Now, what word in all the <hi>Decalogue</hi> gives witneſſe to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or perſwades the <hi>faith,</hi> which is required in him? Certainly, (however ſome have found not onely the <hi>faith in Chriſt,</hi> but the <hi>Sacraments</hi> alſo of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the <hi>Decalogue</hi> yet,) there is no one word there which imports any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>Yea, the very context evinces thus much: for our Saviour, having thus prefaced his expoſition of the <hi>Law,</hi> keeps not himſelfe within the bounds of the <hi>Moral Law;</hi> as appeares <hi>verſe</hi> 18. And therefore <hi>Interpreters</hi> generally upon this place, ſhew how our Saviour did not <hi>deſtroy</hi> but <hi>fulfill</hi> the <hi>Ceremoniall Law</hi> alſo, as well as the <hi>Morall,</hi> which were altogether needleſſe, if by the <hi>Law,</hi> that onely were underſtood.</p>
            <p>Now, the <hi>Law</hi> being (as it muſt needs be) thus largely taken, any man may eaſily perceive that the <hi>not deſtroying</hi> but <hi>fulfilling</hi> of it, is not the <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying</hi> and the <hi>perpetuating</hi> of the obſervation of it under the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> for who ſees not, that upon this ground they might conclude for <hi>Circumciſion,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:10649:10"/>
and the <hi>legall Paſſeover</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> with all their <hi>typicall Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> as well as for the <hi>Sabbath?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is; our Saviour as hee was to <hi>fulfill</hi> not onely the <hi>Morall</hi> but the <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> and <hi>Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall</hi> Law alſo: ſo he ſpeakes of all, and did indeed, <hi>not deſtroy</hi> but, <hi>fulfill</hi> them all, though in a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent manner.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He fulfilled the <hi>whole Law,</hi> by his actuall and perſonall obedience to it, and by ſupplying the defects of it, that it, being unable to juſtifie us in it ſelfe, might, by the helpe of his grace and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of faith in him, bee able to performe that <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 3, 4</note> which otherwiſe it could not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He fulfilled the <hi>Ceremoniall Law,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall</hi> too, ſo farr as it was <hi>typicall;</hi> beſides his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to them, by a reall exhibition of that whereof they were <hi>ſhadowes.</hi> And though by this meanes, their obſervation (according to the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Law) ceaſed, yet did hee not hereby <hi>deſtroy,</hi> but <hi>perfect</hi> them; according to that of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> which was a <hi>legall Ceremony. Doe we then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>make voide</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 31.</note> 
               <hi>the Law through faith? God forbid: yea, we eſtabliſh the Law.</hi> This place then, expounded according to the trueſt meaning and intent of our Saviour, makes nothing for the <hi>totall morality</hi> of the <hi>fourth Commandement,</hi> nor is in the leaſt, contradictory to what I have delivered concerning it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they argue from the Inſtitution of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> which was (ſay they) in the <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> in the time of mans <hi>innocencie,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:10649:10"/>
when there was no need of <hi>Ceremony;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was <hi>morall</hi> and <hi>perpetuall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwere, 1. That it is not univerſally true, that whatſoever precept was given to <hi>Adam</hi> in Innocency, was therefore <hi>Morall</hi> and <hi>perpetuall;</hi> for then the <hi>Symbolicall</hi> Precept of not <hi>eating</hi> of the <hi>forbidden</hi> fruit, muſt be ſuch; which no man, (I ſuppoſe) will affirme. 2. If it be true (which <hi>Willet</hi> hath affirmed, and that by <hi>ten reaſons</hi> which <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Willet</hi> on Gen. 3. 23.</note> he there alledgeth) that <hi>Adam</hi> fell the ſame day that he was <hi>created,</hi> then did he fall before the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the <hi>Precept</hi> for the obſervation of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and had it not in the ſtate of <hi>Innocencie.</hi> But the truth is, this is a meere conjecture diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table any way, ſo as a man may better oppoſe whatſoever is affirmed, then ſolidly conclude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing. 3. If it bee not falſe that the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was then <hi>inſtituted,</hi> yet it hath and may, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good reaſon be doubted of. That place which is brought for it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2. doth not convincingly prove it. And if the reaſons, which are alledged for the <hi>prolepſis</hi> in that place, bee, without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, conſidered, their opinion who ſo expound it will not ſeeme improbable, as 1. That there is no mention any where made of it, to have beene obſerved by the <hi>Patriarchs.</hi> 2. Where it is firſt ſpoken of, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. it is ſpoken of as a new thing not knowne to have beene obſerved before. 3. In that it is called a <hi>ſigne</hi> betweene <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that he was their <hi>ſanctifier</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exo. 31. 13 Deut. 5. 15. Ezck. 20. 12.</note> and <hi>deliverer</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which it could not bee if it were given to all <hi>Nations</hi> in <hi>Adam.</hi> But laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10649:11"/>
granting the whole Argument. I would faine know how that day, that was then inſtituted and ſanctified, could ceaſe, and another be ſubſtituted. How could it bee <hi>Morall</hi> and <hi>perpetuall,</hi> and yet determine with the <hi>Iewiſh Church?</hi> The words which are brought as the <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> ſay; <hi>God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the ſeventh</hi> (N. B.) and for that cauſe, <hi>God</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2 3.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed the ſeventh day,</hi> and <hi>ſanctified</hi> it, viz. <hi>that ſeventh day</hi> on which hee reſted. The Text doth not ſay, God reſted the <hi>ſeventh day,</hi> and <hi>therefore he would have one of the ſeven to be ſanctified;</hi> That is but the <hi>expoſition</hi> or <hi>gloſſe,</hi> not the <hi>Text;</hi> the word of <hi>man,</hi> not of <hi>God.</hi> But ſome may haply ſay, That the particular day was alterable, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on good ground was altered. This I grant, but ſay withall, that he which holds the <hi>Sabbath</hi> to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted before the fall, and for that cauſe <hi>Morall</hi> and <hi>perpetuall,</hi> cannot ſo ſay, but either hee muſt wave his owne Principles, or cry up the Jewiſh Sabbath <hi>poſtliminiò.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, they argue from that of our Saviour <hi>(Matth.</hi> 24. 20.) who foreſhewing the deſtruction of Jeruſalem to his Diſciples, adviſeth them to pray, that their ſlight bee not in the Winter, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the <hi>Sabbath Day.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>If (ſay they) this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept had beene Ceremoniall, then had it beene all one to fly on the Sabbath day, as on any other day: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all Ceremonies were before that time (which was not till forty yeares after Chriſts Aſcenſion) to bee abrogated. But in that Chriſt doth allow this feare of flying on the Sabbath Day more then on any other day of the weeke, hee ſhewes plainely that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:10649:11"/>
the force of the Sabbath was not abrogated by his reſurrection, and therefore no Ceremony.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus they argue. To which it were anſwere <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Williams</hi> p. 297. <hi>Dod.</hi> p. 130. <hi>Elton.</hi> p. 90.</note> ſufficient to ſhew that hereby they ſtill ruſh upon the ſame rocke, and while they labour to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh a needleſſe <hi>morality</hi> of the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> they unawares bring in <hi>Iudaiſme.</hi> For the <hi>Sabbath day</hi> there, cannot with any ſhew of reaſon bee taken (though now a dayes it is too common ſo to take it) for the <hi>Lords Day:</hi> and if our Saviour did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend by bidding his Diſciples pray that their flight might not happen on the <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> to intimate the neceſſity of the obſervation of that Day by <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> Then did S. <hi>Paul</hi> croſſe <note place="margin">Coloſ. 2. 16</note> our Saviours intent in numbring that among the ſhadowes which vaniſhed at Chriſts death; and then hath alſo the Church of Chriſt ever ſince erred in ſo accounting it, and condemning the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of it, with an <hi>Anathema</hi> to thoſe that in <note place="margin">Concil. Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic. can. 29. In Mat. Hom. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> this point ſhall be found to <hi>Iudaize.</hi> S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> is ſo farre from thinking that the <hi>Sabbath</hi> which our Sauiour there ſpeaks of, did belong to <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that upon that ground hee expounds that ſpeech of our Saviour as ſpoken not to his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> but to the <hi>Iewes. Thou ſeeſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that he ſpeakes to the Iewes—for the Apoſtles were not to keepe the Sabbath, &amp;c.</hi> But grant that it were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the Diſciples; yet can no ſuch thing bee thence collected as they would have. For our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour had good ground ſo to adviſe his Diſciples, notwithſtanding God at that time required no keeping of the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> For though the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10649:12"/>
of the Law (and this among the reſt) were dead with Chriſt, yet were they not buried (as I have ſhewed) nor the practiſe of them deadly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 21. 20. Non fuerunt tanquam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abolica Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiunt ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia fugienda, etiam cum ipſa gratia iam coeperat revelari quae umbris tali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus fuerat praenunciata, ſed permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenda pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eis, max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imè qui ex illo populo cui data ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, venerant. Poſtea vero tanquam cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honere ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſunt a Chriſtiau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s omnibus ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reparabiliter deſerenda. Aug. ep 19. <hi>And a little before in the ſame Chapter,</hi>—<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſet fides que priùs ictis obſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiambus praenun<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iata, poſt mortem &amp; reſurrectione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Domini revelata eſt, amiſerunt tanquam vitam officii <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Verum tamen ſicut defuncta corpora neceſſariorum officiis deducenda <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>ant quodammodo ad ſepultueam.—Non autem deſerenda continuo vel inimicorum merſibus pro. j<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ienda <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oind<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> quiſquis Chriſtianorum quamvis ex Iudaeis ſimiliter ea celebrare voluerit, tanquam ſopitos cineres <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, non erit pius deductor vel, bajulus corporis, ſed impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſepu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae uiolat<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> till the Temple was deſtroyed: till which time, even the Apoſtles themſelves were zealous of the Law, and retentive of their old Ceremonies: to which weakneſſe of theirs, our Saviour there accommodates his ſpeech, willing rather that their owne experience in the deſtruction of the Temple ſhould teach them that harſh leſſon of the aboliſhing of the <hi>Legall Ceremonies,</hi> then by a praemature urging it, to ſtartle ſuch as were yet weake in faith, or hinder others of that Nation from beleeving in Him. Beſides; be it that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did hold themſelves freed from the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> yet being among thoſe who ſtill made conſcience of it, even to ſuperſtition, (as did the unconverted Jewes) it could not but prove very incommodious to their ſpeedy and farre flight (which the greatneſſe and ſuddenneſſe of the danger required) in as much as thereby they ſhould expoſe themſelves to the fury of thoſe who were no leſſe zealous in compelling o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, then ſuperſtitious in obſerving it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. In theſe reſpects our Saviour might well admoniſh his Diſciples to pray that their flight might not bee on the <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> and yet not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:10649:12"/>
teach them to <hi>obſerve</hi> the <hi>Sabbath</hi> after his death, or that while the obſervation of it laſted, they ſhould thinke themſelves ſo tied in conſcience of it, that they might not on that day flie farre to ſave their lives: and much leſſe to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the <hi>Morality</hi> of the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> which neither He, nor his Apoſtles, nor the following ages of the Church, (till within theſe few yeares) ever deſigned by the name of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> without ſome difference added to diſtinguiſh it from that of the Jewes. For though we finde it ſometimes called <hi>our Sabbath,</hi> or the <hi>Sabbath of Chriſtians,</hi> in regard that in the maine end of it, it ſucceeded that, yet generally the <hi>Sabbath</hi> ſimply put, and without addition, notes the <hi>Iewiſh Sabbath,</hi> or the <hi>Day</hi> on which it was celebrated, which is our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday;</hi> and the day before that which we keepe, which is therefore called by the Evangeliſts and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>one,</hi> or the <hi>firſt day</hi> from the <note place="margin">Matt. 28. 1. Mar. 16. 1. Iohn 20. 1. 1. Cor. 16 2 Revel. 1. 10</note> 
               <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and by S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> the <hi>Lords Day:</hi> by which name, or that which the ſame day had among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> (viz. the <hi>Sunday)</hi> it hath ever ſince been knowne in the Chriſtian world.</p>
            <p>But I will leave theſe, and now returne thither whence (for the anſwering of theſe objections) I have digreſſed. And having ſeene the nature and ſeverall degrees of Morall Precepts; and in generall, that the <hi>fourth Commandement</hi> hath in it ſomewhat <hi>not moral,</hi> That I may apply theſe things to our preſent purpoſe, and manifeſt the truth thereof: I will more particularly inquire into the nature of that <hi>Commandement,</hi> and in it diſtinctly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:10649:13"/>
conſider theſe 4. things. Firſt, <hi>A Day,</hi> or <hi>time</hi> ſet apart for Gods ſervice. Secondly, the <hi>ſeventh day,</hi> or one in the revolution of <hi>ſeven.</hi> Thirdly, the particular <hi>ſeventh</hi> there mentioned, namely the <hi>ſeventh</hi> from the <hi>Creation.</hi> Fourthly, the ſtrict <note place="margin">Some time to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to God, moral</note> 
               <hi>ſurceaſe</hi> or <hi>reſt</hi> from ordinary labours on that day.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe. It cannot be denied, but that the very Law of Nature it ſelfe (to uſe the words of a <hi>Worthy</hi> of our Church) requireth no <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hook</hi> p. 378</note> 
               <q>leſſe the ſanctification of <hi>times,</hi> then of <hi>places, perſons,</hi> and <hi>things.</hi> For which cauſe it hath pleaſed God heretofore as of the reſt, ſo of <hi>times</hi> likewiſe, to exact ſome parts by way of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall homage.</q> And that (as <hi>Aquinas)</hi> it is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, <note place="margin">Morale eſt quantum ad hoc, quod homo depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat aliquod tempus vitae ſuae ad va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> di. vinis, &amp;c. Aqui<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. 22. q. 122.</note> that man ſhould depute ſome time of his life for the ſervice of God. For there is in man a kind of naturall inclination, that to every thing neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary there bee a time aſſigned: as to our bodily refection, ſleepe and the like: Whence alſo to the ſpiritnall refection of the ſoule, whereby the ſoule is refreſhed in God, by the dictate of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon, a man deputes ſome time. And ſo to have ſome times for holy Offices comes under the <hi>Morall Law,</hi> and is abſolutely of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> written in the heart of every man, being invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in that principle which even depraved na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath ever acknowledged; <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>God is to be worſhipped.</hi> And therefore <hi>Ameſius</hi> hath well <note place="margin">Medul. T<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eol. l. 2. c. 15. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> obſerved that thus farre the time of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip falls under that precept which exacts the worſhip it ſelfe: and as God when he created the world, is ſaid to have concreated time with it:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:10649:13"/>
ſo when he ordained religious actions, he appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alſo to the ſame, a time for them, as a neceſſary circumſtance, without which they could not be performed. And as the <hi>time</hi> in which ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are done, ſo that ſome <hi>Day,</hi> or <hi>Dayes</hi> ſhould be deſtinated and ſet apart for the more <hi>ſolemne performance</hi> of thoſe <hi>actions,</hi> may ſeeme to be a dictate of the ſame <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>nature:</hi> in as much as the <hi>Heathens</hi> who had no other guide but the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> had their ſolemne <hi>Feaſts</hi> and <hi>ſet Dayes</hi> in all ages conſecrated to the worſhip of their Gods; whereby they manifeſted (though not the knowledge of the true God, yet) their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of that Principle, <hi>That God is to be worſhipped,</hi> and the conveniencie of aſſigning ſome <hi>Dayes</hi> peculiarly to that end.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond: That <hi>one day</hi> in the revolution of <hi>ſeaven</hi> ſhould be thus ſet a part: this cannot be ſaid to be abſolutely of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>nature: Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> being ignorant of this, without the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>written Law,</hi> in which God hath revealed his pleaſure, concerning the <hi>Quota pars,</hi> or how much of our time hee requires to be conſecrated to Him: And this will eaſily appeare to any that doth without prejudice conſider it. For it is an eaſie thing to give an eſtimate of what <hi>Principles</hi> are <hi>naturall</hi> and written in the hearts of all men; and what are gotten by <hi>inſtruction, diſcipline,</hi> and <hi>information:</hi> Now men may by the light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from the creature, climbe up to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Creator, and from the nature of God conclude his worſhip, and from the nature of his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:10649:14"/>
Worſhip, conclude a time (as to all other things) to be due to it. But to goe further, and to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what part of our time, wee cannot. For it will not follow that becauſe <hi>ſome time</hi> is due, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>ſeaventh day,</hi> more then the <hi>eighth</hi> of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moneth, which was obſerved by the <hi>Graecians</hi> in <note place="margin">Plutarch in v<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Theſci.</note> honour of <hi>Neptune,</hi> or any other day, above, or under that number. And for this cauſe it is (ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome)</hi> that in the giving of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement <note place="margin">S. Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 6. p. 542. Edit. Savill. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 15. &amp; 14. 18.</note> concerning the <hi>Sabbath</hi> (which hee calls <hi>a Precept not made knowne to us by our conſcience)</hi> God added a reaſon, as <hi>becauſe Ged reſted the ſeventh day from all his worke;</hi> and againe; <hi>becauſe thou waſt a ſervant in Egypt, &amp;c.</hi> Whereas in thoſe Precepts that are purely morall, as when he ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt doe no murther,</hi> hee onely gives the precept, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving any reaſon at all. Why ſo? <hi>(ſaith that Father,)</hi> becauſe our <hi>conſcience</hi> had taught us this before; ſo that God ſpeakes, as to thoſe that knew and underſtood reaſon ſufficient for the Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Neither doth <hi>Euſebius</hi> (though alledged by <note place="margin">De praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangel 13. c. 7.</note> ſome to that purpoſe) any way contradict this, when he ſaith, That not onely the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> but all almoſt, both <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and <hi>Poets</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the <hi>ſeaventh day</hi> to be <hi>ſacred:</hi> For here it is not queſtioned, whether the <hi>Gentiles</hi> which want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the law of God to informe them, did hold the <hi>ſeaventh day</hi> as hallowed, but whether they were induced by the inſtinct of <hi>nature</hi> ſo to account it; or that ſo accounting it, they held themſelves bound to conſecrate <hi>that,</hi> more then any <hi>other</hi> to the worſhip of God: The <hi>Gentiles</hi> (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> at
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10649:14"/>
large declares) came to the knowledge of it from the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and did in that, as in other things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their <hi>Imitators,</hi> and receive it into their manners. Or upon ſome other ground or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition they might account the number of <hi>ſeaven</hi> to be ſacred; as becauſe by that number the <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> (which they honoured as their chiefeſt <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties)</hi> were terminated: for which cauſe (we know) by their names they intituled their dayes. But what ever were the motive, as it is without all queſtion, that the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as well as the <hi>Iewes,</hi> held the number of <hi>ſeaven</hi> in great veneration, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting <note place="margin">S. Aug. de civit lib. 11. c. 31. Hieron. in Amo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.</note> it the number of perfection, and full of myſteries; So it is as unqueſtionable, that by the light of nature they knew not that that part of our time was to be ſeparated to Gods ſervice. And therefore <hi>Zanchius</hi> ſpeakes more inconſiderately <note place="margin">Zanch. in quartum Praecep.</note> then beſeemes his learning, when hee ſaith, That <hi>Nature</hi> teacheth all men to conſecrate <hi>one day of ſeaven</hi> to the externall worſhip of God: Which, <note place="margin">Med. Theo. l. 2. 6. 15. n. 6.</note> others (and among them <hi>Ameſius)</hi> better conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring acknowledge to be onely of <hi>poſitive</hi> right, and <hi>morall,</hi> not in regard of <hi>nature,</hi> but of <hi>diſcipline,</hi> as comming under that ranke of <hi>morall</hi> Precepts, which neede inſtruction to helpe naturall reaſon to know, and judge of them. Now, albeit <hi>Calvine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtit l. 2. c. 8. D. Calvins</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of one in ſeaven.</note> (who in this as in other things, wants not his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers) thinks the <hi>ſeaventh day,</hi> not to be ſo ſtood on, as that he would tye the Chriſtian world pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely to that: Yet there are many grave and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Divines, both Ancient and Moderne, that judge the inſtitution of one Day in ſeaven to be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:10649:15"/>
ſo farre morall, as that it doth binde the Church perpetually and immutably. Thus among the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. Eccl. Pol. p. 379.</note> Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> upon thoſe words, <hi>And God bleſſed the ſeaventh day and hallowed it, </hi>
               <bibl>Geneſ. 2. 3.</bibl> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Here,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>from the beginning God inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates to us this Doctrine, inſtructing us to ſeparate and lay aſide one day in the compaſſe of every weeke for ſpirituall exerciſes.</hi> And among our <hi>moderne Writers</hi> that admired <hi>Hooker,</hi> ſaith. <hi>That wee are bound to account the ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of one day in ſeven, a duty which Gods immutable law doth exact for ever.</hi>
               </q> Thus hee, with many others, whoſe judgements I honour, yet dare not herein wholly ſubſcribe to them neither: For the <hi>Law</hi> exacting the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>one day</hi> in <hi>ſeaven,</hi> being onely <hi>poſitive</hi> (as muſt needs be granted) cannot containe in it ſelfe any perpetuall obligation. For all Lawes of that nature (though made by God himſelfe) admit mutation (at leaſt) when the <hi>matter</hi> concerning which, or the condition of the <hi>Perſons,</hi> to whom they were given, is changed: Now the <hi>Day,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which this Precept was given, together with the State of the Church, to which it was given, being changed, I ſee no reaſon, why the proportion of <hi>one in ſeaven,</hi> ſhould be ſimply and in it ſelfe immutable; Yet thus much, I willingly grant them, that (ſome time to be ſet apart for Gods worſhip, being abſolutely of the Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) that proportion of time, which God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe made choyce of for his owne People, is the fitteſt that can be imagined: and Nature infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by God, cannot but acknowledge His <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:10649:15"/>
and <hi>goodneſſe</hi> in this choyce, in that hee hath ſo attempered it, that neither the long ſpace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene can make us forget our duty to him, nor the quicke returne of it hinder our providing for the neceſſities of nature. And hereupon the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> hath taken it as an obligation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them, and that (as it is in our <hi>Church</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> of the place and time of Prayer. <hi>Part.</hi>
               </note> Homily) <q>Gods will and commandement was to have a ſolemne time, and ſtanding day in the weeke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the people ſhould come together, and have in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance his wonderfull Benefits, and render him thanks for them as appertaineth to loving, kinde, and obedient people.</q> Thus farre then, this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement extends to us Chriſtians, as well as to the Jewes, in as much as to conſecrate ſome part of our time to God, is <hi>morall,</hi> and a <hi>ſeaventh</hi> part, though not <hi>morall,</hi> yet <hi>fitly choſen,</hi> and appointed by God, and obſerved by the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (not as ſimply immutable, yet) as moſt worthy to be retayned.</p>
            <p>For the third particular. The particular <hi>ſeventh day</hi> there mentioned, that is, the <hi>ſeaventh day from the Creation;</hi> This cannot be ſaid to be <hi>Morall</hi> any way, but is <hi>ceremoniall</hi> and temporary, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired with the diſſolution of the <hi>Iewiſh Church.</hi> And this is generally confeſſed by all, whom the hereſie of <hi>Iudaiſme</hi> hath not infected: and the mutation of the Day approved by the practiſe of the <hi>Chriſtian world</hi> ever ſince the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> times, is a ſufficient diſclaime to the <hi>morality</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>For one of theſe three muſt needs hence be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred. Eyther that that which is <hi>morall</hi> may bee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:10649:16"/>
changed; or that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath now for this ſixteen hundred years <hi>erred</hi> in the <hi>change</hi> of it; orlaſtly, that the particular day preſcribed to the Jews was <hi>Ceremoniall,</hi> and not perpetuall. The firſt, no man will ſay that vnderſtands the nature of <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> precepts, and their dependance upon the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>nature,</hi> which is one and the ſame with all men every where, and in all ages, and in that regard immutable. And he deſerves not the name of a Chriſtian that dares affirme the <hi>ſecond.</hi> It remaines therefore that we pitch upon the <hi>third,</hi> &amp; confeſſe that herein that <hi>Commandement</hi> was <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> &amp; not perpetuall. But beſides the practice of the Church we have the warrant of the <hi>Apoſtle S. Paul.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 2. 16. 17.</note> who ranks the <hi>Sabbath</hi> among the <hi>ſhadows</hi> of things to come whereof the <hi>body</hi> is <hi>Chriſt.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Now the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Speach againſt <hi>Trash.</hi> p. 72</note> 
                  <hi>had</hi> (they are the words of the late learned Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter) the ſhadowes vaniſh: that which was to come, when it is come to what end any fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of it? it ceaſeth too. So that to hold the ſhadow of the Sabbath is to continue, is to hold that Chriſt the body is not yet come.</hi>
               </q> Neyther can the force of this <note place="margin">Elten. <hi>p</hi> 91 <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>lliams <hi>p.</hi> 299. Ameſ loco ſupra cu.</note> place be avoyded by ſaying that the Iewes had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sabbaths</hi> that were there meant, as the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths</hi> of <hi>weekes,</hi> and <hi>the firſt</hi> and <hi>laſt dayes</hi> of their great <hi>feaſts</hi> which were called <hi>Sabbaths.</hi> For the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeakes indefinitely of the <hi>Sabbath dayes,</hi> &amp; hath not there left any ground to rayſe any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction upon, or to ſhew that he aymed onely at them more then this. That he ſpeakes there in the <hi>plurall number</hi> will not <hi>helpe</hi> this ſhift, but rather <hi>croſſe</hi> it: it <hi>helpes</hi> it not, becauſe we know it is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10649:16"/>
in the new Teſtament to uſe that number when the Sabbath in queſtion is ſpoken of: it <hi>croſſeth</hi> it rather in that being in the <hi>plurall number</hi> it may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeme to comprehend all their <hi>Sabbaths</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they were: and ſo to be far from excluding this. The place then is cleare, and alone ſufficient to prove the point in hand: To which I will one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adde; that the reaſon drawn from the example of God, who reſted upon the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, namely, when the <hi>Creation</hi> was finiſhed, endured onely till the time of the <hi>new Creation</hi> in which al things were <hi>made new</hi> by <hi>Chriſt;</hi> at which time it ceaſed, or at leaſt, a ſecond reaſon taken from that <hi>new Creation</hi> comming in place, the former both reaſon &amp; day (become now old) are <hi>paſſed away, and behold all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 17.</note> 
               <hi>things are become new.</hi> For this worke of <hi>redemption</hi> or <hi>new Creation</hi> being the greater may deſervedly take place of the other. And as the <hi>Prophet Ieremy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 16 14. 15.</note> ſpeaking of the <hi>deliverance</hi> that God would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe his people from the <hi>Babiloniſh captivity,</hi> ſaith: <q>
                  <hi>Behold the dayes ſhall come (ſaith the Lord) that it ſhall no more be ſaid; the Lord liveth that brought up the Children of Iſrael out of Egypt: but the Lord liveth which brought up the children of Iſrael from the land of the North, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> So may wee ſay of the <hi>day</hi> appointed for his <hi>worſhip;</hi> that the <hi>day</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he finiſhed the worke of <hi>Creation</hi> ſhall no more be obſerved, but the <hi>day</hi> wherein our <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt</hi> by his reſurrection from the dead finiſhed the worke of our <hi>redemption,</hi> and begun a new life to be finiſhed in all his members, who (as S. <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 3.</note> tels us) are by his <hi>reſurrection</hi> begotten vnto a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:10649:17"/>
hope of an eternall Inheritance.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt thing in this Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and that which denominated the <hi>day</hi> is the <hi>reſting</hi> from ordinary labours. And this in regard of the divers ends it had admits a diverſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. 1. This reſt may be conſidered as a means without which the dutyes of Gods worſhip cannot be performed. For ſeeing the generall &amp; publique dutyes of piety and devotion, and our owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate buſineſſes cannot both bee followed at once, there muſt be ſuch a <hi>ceſſation</hi> from ordinary la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours on that day, wherein men are to performe thoſe dutyes, as that thereby they be not <hi>hindered</hi> in the performance thereof: in which regardthoſe workes that in themſelves, and at other times are not prohibited, are on that day vnlawfull, ſo farre <note place="margin">Aq. 2. 2. q. 112. 4.</note> as they hinder a man from applying himſelf to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine dutyes: and therein are contrary to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of that <hi>precept,</hi> which requires the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of them. And therefore when God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands a day to be dedicated to Him, he doth like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the ſame command ſuch a reſt as a meanes neceſſary to that end. So that, thus farre it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected with, &amp; participates of the <hi>morality</hi> of that <hi>Precept</hi> that enjoynes the dutyes for which it was appointed; &amp; in this conſideration we are no leſſe bound at this day, to <hi>reſt</hi> from our labours on <hi>the dayes</hi> devoted to Gods ſolemne worſhip, then were the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and (as Uenerable <hi>Hooker</hi> ſayth) <q>The voluntary ſcandalous contempt of that reſt from <note place="margin">p. 385.</note> labour wherewith God is publikely ſerved, we cannot too ſeverely correct and bridle.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:10649:17"/>
Another end of this <hi>reſt</hi> is mentioned. <hi>Deut. 5. 14. viz:</hi> that there might be a time of <hi>reſt</hi> allowed to <hi>ſervants</hi> and labourers for their refreſhment. And this no leſſe concernes <hi>us,</hi> then it did <hi>them;</hi> for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of nature requires ſome time of remiſſion from labour: and religion teacheth us, to be <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull even to our beaſts,</hi> and much more to our <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 12. 10.</note> who are our brethren. But this is not ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected with the obſervance of the day of Gods publique worſhip, but that it may at other times be ſupplyed, yet is then ſo far requiſite, as it makes for the ſolemne performances of the duties of the day, that all, as well ſervants, as others, may joyne together in the ſervice of God: which while they doe, they at once enjoy the refreſhment of their bodyes, and freedome to refreſh their ſoules, with holy and religious exerciſes.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>reſt,</hi> as it was preſcribed to the <hi>Iews,</hi> had yet a further end, in regard of which, it was exacted ſo ſtrictly, and beyond that which eyther the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne ſervice of God, or the neceſſary refreſhment of labouring perſons did require. And that was <hi>figurative</hi> for the ſignifying of things <hi>paſt, preſent,</hi> and <hi>future.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>Things paſt;</hi> and ſo it was a memoriall of Gods <hi>reſting</hi> from his worke of <hi>Creation:</hi> and as the day which they obſerved, ſo the ſtrict <hi>reſt</hi> upon that day ſerved as a ſign of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon benefit of <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi> which they thereby acknowledged to bee Gods work, when they celebrated that day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God reſted from creating, &amp; ſanctified it by an holy and totall ſurceaſe from their owne workes.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:10649:18"/>
And this end is aſſigned by God himſelfe, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed <note place="margin">Ex. 20. 11.</note> to the commandement as a principal reaſon of the inſtitution of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly; it was a memoriall likewiſe of their <hi>deliverance</hi> out of Egypt, ſo expreſſely ſaid to bee <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 15. where, in the repetition of the Law, this reaſon, is added inſtead of the former, &amp; God is therefore ſayd to command them to keepe the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> that they might remember their <hi>ſervitude</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and their <hi>deliverance</hi> from thence.</p>
            <p>Againe; the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was a <hi>ſigne</hi> alſo of their <hi>preſent condition,</hi> and a note to diſtinguiſh them from all other people, they being then the onely peculiar people of God, whom hee had ſeparated, and ſanctified to himſelfe: For a <hi>ſigne</hi> of which <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar ſanctification</hi> they were commanded to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> as we read <hi>Exod. 31. 13. &amp; Ezech.</hi> 20. 12.</p>
            <p>3. Laſtly; the <hi>reſt</hi> of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was a <hi>Type</hi> whereby was prefigured that <hi>reſt</hi> which remained <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 9 Vid. Aqum. in loc. ver. 4.</note> for the people of God, to be purchaſed for them by Chriſt. Into which reſt they which believe do enter, and ſhall have the full poſſeſſion thereof in the Kingdome of glory, when, after all their works finiſhed, they ſhall <hi>reſt</hi> from their labours. And <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 13</note> this <hi>reſt</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> deſigning by the name of a <hi>Sabbatiſme,</hi> intimates the prefiguring of it by that <hi>Sabbath</hi> which the people of God under the Law were to obſerve. So that, as the place of this Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall, and eternall <hi>reſt,</hi> was ſhadowed out by the <hi>promiſed Land,</hi> ſo the <hi>reſt</hi> it ſelfe for the nature, &amp; condition of it was no leſſe preſignified by their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:10649:18"/>
uſuall <hi>Sabbaths.</hi> Now in relation to theſe good things which were thus vailed under the outward obſervation of this <hi>reſt,</hi> it was very requiſite that the <hi>reſt</hi> whereby they were repreſented, ſhould be, as ſtrict as might be; for the more exact the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure <note place="margin">Figurae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet eſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actae, alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui non bene ſignificant. <hi>Bellarm. t. 2. l. 3. c.</hi> 10</note> is, the better it ſignifies; and the more ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the reſt was obſerved, the more lively was the repreſentation of thoſe things, which it aymed at. To this if we add the condition of thoſe, to whom it was enjoyned, we ſhall have the compleate rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why it was with that ſtrictneſſe commanded and exacted, &amp; the violation of it with ſuch ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity puniſhed.</p>
            <p>For firſt, the <hi>Iewes</hi> though the people of God, &amp; heire &amp; Lord of all, yet being, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 1.</note> a <hi>child, differed not from a ſervant,</hi> and as ſervants were to be held in bondage under the ſtrict yoke of outward obſervances, &amp; of this among the reſt, till the fulneſſe of time came, when God ſent forth <note place="margin">V. 45.</note> his Sonne made of a woman, made under the law, to redeem them that were vnder the law, that wee might receive the adoption of ſonnes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Iews</hi> by reaſon of their long abode in a place of continuall ſervile toyle, could not ſuddainely be weaned and drawne unto contrary offices, without ſome impreſſion of terror; whence the ſeverity with which this duty, was enjoyned, and the violation thereof puniſhed, was to them moſt neceſſary. And beſides, we know, that there is nothing more needfull, then to puniſh with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity the firſt tranſgreſſors of thoſe Lawes that require a more exact obſervation for many ages to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:10649:19"/>
come. Theſe conſiderations then being peculiar unto them, that <hi>ſtrict reſt</hi> which was thereupon exacted, being but <hi>accidentally annexed</hi> to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ſanctification of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> cannot belong unto us by vertue of that command by which it was enjoyned them. And this is confeſſed even by thoſe that ſtand moſt for the obſervation of the <hi>Sabbath:</hi> who grant that the <hi>ſtrictneſſe of the reſt</hi> on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was <hi>Ceremoniall,</hi> and did belong to the <hi>Iewes</hi> onely and is abrogated by the <hi>death</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Elton.</note> So <hi>Elton.</hi> And <hi>Ameſius. It may be granted, that there</hi> 
               <note place="margin">P. 98.</note> 
               <hi>was ſomewhat a more ſtrict obſervation of the Sabbath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Poteſt qui dem concedi actionem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquam ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſervatienem Sabbati illis temporibus ſuiſſe impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratam, pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elagoglae &amp; ſcivitutis tempori ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, quae omnibus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis non obtinet. Med. Theol. l. 2. c. 15. n. 23. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins caſes.</hi> l. 2. <hi>c.</hi> 16. § 1.</note> 
               <hi>commanded in thoſe times, as fitted to the pedagogy and time of ſervitade, which obteynes not in all ages.</hi> So he, and generally the moſt of thoſe which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the Doctrine of the <hi>Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To give a briefe and full reſolution to the firſt queſtion propounded. <hi>viz. whether, and how farre forth the fourth Commandement concerning the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath is morall, and perpetuall, and ſo belonging to us Chriſtians</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the former part, I ſay the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement is <hi>partly morall,</hi> and <hi>partly Ceremoniall.</hi> To the <hi>latter</hi> I ſay. Firſt, it is <hi>morall,</hi> and perpetuall that ſome time be dedicated to the ſolemne, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique worſhip and ſervice of God. Secondly, that <hi>one</hi> day in the revolution of <hi>ſeaven,</hi> be conſecrated to this end, is not <hi>morall;</hi> yet very <hi>convenient</hi> and fitly obſerved, and retayned by the Church of Chriſt. Thirdly; that the particular <hi>ſeaventh day,</hi> which the <hi>Iewes</hi> obſerved, is neither <hi>morall,</hi> nor ſit to bee obſerved, being altogether abrogated and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:10649:19"/>
out of date, ever ſince the death of Chriſt. Laſtly; the reſting from ordinary labours, as it is conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the dutyes of Gods worſhip, and a means without which, they cannot be performed, is no leſſe neceſſary on the dayes conſecrated to that end now, then heretofore; but as it concerned the <hi>Iewiſh Sabbath,</hi> it is together with the <hi>Sabbath</hi> abrogated. So that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are not bound either to reſt on that day, which the <hi>Iewes</hi> did, or to reſt on their owne <hi>Sabbaths</hi> or dayes conſecrated to Gods ſervice, with the ſame ſtrictneſſe, which was enjoyned the <hi>Iewes</hi> on theirs. Thus much ſhall ſerve to have ſpoken of the firſt generall queſtion.</p>
            <p>Having explained the nature of the <hi>fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement</hi> touching the <hi>Iewiſh Sabbath:</hi> I come now to ſpeake of the <hi>Lords Day;</hi> in which, that which was <hi>Morall</hi> in that Commandement, is and ever hath beene obſerved by <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> The <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> of which, when and by whom it was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſecond generall part of our inquirie.</p>
            <p>And here all Divines are not of one opinion. Some ground <hi>this</hi> no leſſe then the <hi>Iewiſh Sabbath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams of the Church. P. 301.</note> upon the <hi>fourth Commandement,</hi> which <hi>(ſay they)</hi> includes both the <hi>Sabbath</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and of the <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> Becauſe the <hi>Lord</hi> doth not ſay, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that thou keepe holy the ſeventh Day,</hi> but <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that thou keepe holy the Sabbath Day;</hi> that is, the <hi>Day of reſt:</hi> which, before the comming of Chriſt, was the <hi>ſeventh</hi> from the <hi>Creation;</hi> but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, the <hi>firſt day</hi> of the weeke, or <hi>Lords Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe men while they over greedily ſeeke
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:10649:20"/>
after a <hi>divine foundation</hi> for the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> doe not conſider that they ſtretch the Precept beyond the intent of the Lawgiver. For though it bee granted that the Lord doth not ſay, <hi>Remember to keepe holy the ſeventh day,</hi> but the <hi>day</hi> of <hi>ceaſing</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determinately, yet ſeeing in the following expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which God added, it is determined unto that <hi>particular ſeventh,</hi> which was the <hi>ſeventh</hi> from the <hi>Creation,</hi> to which it expreſly is refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as to the ſpeciall reaſon of the Inſtitution: the <hi>Sabbath</hi> there cannot without forcing, and manifeſt abſurdity, bee ſaid to bee as the <hi>Genus</hi> to the <hi>Iewiſh,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath,</hi> and to include both. For is it not manifeſtly abſurd, and unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming a rationall man, and much more the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Supreame Law-giver, to ſay; <hi>God in ſixe dayes made heaven and earth, and reſted the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, and for that cauſe ſanctified the ſeventh Day; Ergo,</hi> Hee will have men in imitation of him to reſt ſometime <hi>(viz. before the comming of Chriſt)</hi> on that day whereon hee reſted, and ſometime <hi>(viz. after Chriſts comming)</hi> to reſt on the day in which hee began to worke. Neither can this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity bee ſalved (as ſome have endeavoured to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cleaver</hi> Declar. of Chriſtian Sabbath. pag. 99.</note> doe) by ſaying, there is alwayes more meant in the Precepts and prohibitions, then in words are expreſſed: for thoſe things which are ſo meant without particular expreſſion, muſt either be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily connected with, or ſome way ſubordinat to that which is expreſſed, that ſo it may be inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in it. Sure I am, it ought no way to be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as (we ſee) this is by Gods owne expoſition
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:10649:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of himſelfe, and the reaſon which hee alledgeth, which can no way agree both to the Jewiſh Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and the Lords Day.</p>
            <p>Again, others urge the Inſtitution of the Lords <note place="margin">Eſion p. 90. Dod p. 127.</note> Day, as founded upon Gods ſanctification of the ſeventh Day at the Creation, which being before all Ceremonies, muſt (ſay they) needes binde Chriſtians, as well as the Jewes. But this labours of the ſame weakneſſe, and abſurdity, which the other did. For what day did God ſanctifie there? Surely not the firſt day of the Weeke, but the ſeventh from the Creation, which they muſt with the Jewes cry up againe, if they will have their argument hold good. But beſides this, the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this foundation appeares in that (as hath beene ſhewed) they cannot prove that God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and commanded it to bee obſerved from that time forward; but onely that <hi>Moſes</hi> there, relating the ſtory of the Creation, intimates the reaſon of Gods after Commanding his people to reſt upon that Day. And laſtly, granting that to be the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> (which cannot be proved) and that not the <hi>ſeaventh day from the Creation</hi> (as the words expreſly ſay) but <hi>a ſeaventh,</hi> or <hi>one</hi> in <hi>ſeaven,</hi> were thereby intended to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, &amp; to belong to us Chriſtians: If all this be granted, here will yet be but a partiall foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and no compleat <hi>inſtitution</hi> of that particular day which we obſerve: for, all this notwithſtanding, why might not the <hi>ſecond, third, fourth,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have beene obſerved, and yet that inſtitution of one in ſeaven no way violated?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:10649:21"/>
Others therefore (no doubt eſpying the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe  of it)<note place="margin">Ameſius Medul. Theol l. 2 c. 15 n 27.</note> forſake this hold, and ſeeke for autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to prove it, to be of <hi>Divine Inſtitution,</hi> out of the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> And among theſe <hi>Ameſius</hi> will have it to bee done by <hi>Chriſt himſelfe:</hi> laying this for a ground worke, that <hi>He alone could change the day of the Sabbath, that was Lord of it,</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſt.</hi> So that according to him, Chriſt was the Author of this change, and that either <hi>mediately</hi> by his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> whom he aſſiſted by his Spirit in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of it, no leſſe then he did in the doctrine which they taught: or elſe, (as hee holds to bee moſt probable) <hi>immediately,</hi> and in his <hi>owne perſon;</hi> and the probability of this he labours to prove by divers Arguments; wherein hee doth (as one hath well obſerved in the like caſe) as if one ſhould demand a Legacy, by force and vertue of ſome written Teſtament wherein there being no ſuch thing ſpecified, he pleades, that there it muſt needs be, and bringeth arguments from the love and good will, which alwayes the Teſtator bore him; imagining that theſe or the like proofes will evince a Teſtament, to have that in it which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men by reading, can no where finde. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely it is a bold and a ſtrange courſe, for men to adventure to argue, that God muſt needs have done the thing, which they imagine was to bee done: whereas in matters that concerne the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God, the moſt dutifull, and ſafe way on our part, is to ſearch what God hath done, and with meekereſſe to admire that, rather, then to diſpute what he, in congruity of reaſon, ought to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:10649:21"/>
doe. Hee might therefore have ſpared all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons he brings, and in ſtead thereof, to have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged one place out of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> which doth command the <hi>change</hi> of the <hi>Day,</hi> eſpecially ſeeing he denies it, (and that for many reaſons by him there urged) to bee an <hi>unwritten Tradition:</hi> which ſeeing hee doth not, nor indeede can doe, what doth he elſe by all his arguments, but endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to lay an aſperſion of imperfection upon the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and of neglect in <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe of that office, which as the great Prophet of his <hi>Church</hi> belonged to him? As if unleſſe hee had beene as carefull to appoint the obſervation of this day, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was to appoint the old <hi>Sabbath,</hi> hee could not <hi>(abſit verbo blaſphemia)</hi> be as faithfull in the houſe of God, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was. But farre be ſuch blaſphemous thoughts from us, farre be it from us to meaſure the faithfulneſſe of our bleſſed Saviour by our phanſies: or to judge him unfaithfull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did omit that which our ſhallow conceits judge neceſſary and fit for him to doe. Wee know that the <hi>high Prieſt of our profeſsion, Chriſt Ieſus, was</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb 3. 2.</note> 
               <hi>faithfull to him that appointed him, as alſo Moſes was faithfull in all his houſe.</hi> And this <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> of his was by him ſufficiently demonſtrated, in that hee fully declared the will of his Father to the world, in all things to be beleeved and done, and ſhewed <hi>how,</hi> and <hi>what</hi> worſhip Chriſtians muſt give unto God, though the circumſtances of that worſhip as <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place</hi> (in as much as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the particular deſigning of either) hee left to be determined by the <hi>Church,</hi> whom he promiſed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:10649:22"/>
to be with to the end of the world. And as he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to be leſſe faithfull in the houſe of <hi>God,</hi> then <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Salomon</hi> (who provided the one a <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> the other a <hi>Temple)</hi> becauſe he did not appoint <hi>ſet places</hi> for Gods worſhip; ſo neither can hee be juſtly taxed for not appointing the <hi>ſet times</hi> for the ſame; theſe two circumſtances of time and place, being of equall neceſſity and uſe, and joyned together by God himſelfe, <hi>Lev. 19. 30. Yee ſhall keepe my Sabbaths, and reverence my Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie. I am the Lord.</hi> Neither is the difference of <hi>Places</hi> more taken away now under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> then of <hi>Times.</hi> But as the true worſhippers of God are not tyed to worſhip either in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> or any <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.</note> other peculiar place, but may worſhip him in <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and truth in all places,</hi> lifting up <hi>pure hands:</hi> ſo <note place="margin">I Tim. 2. 8.</note> neither are they tyed to any ſpeciall <hi>time</hi> or <hi>day,</hi> but may <hi>pray continually,</hi> and at all times. And <note place="margin">I Theſ. 5. 17.</note> therefore they who are ſo indifferent for the <hi>place,</hi> that they can be content to account a <hi>Wood,</hi> a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor,</hi> or a <hi>Barne,</hi> place good enough for Chriſtians to meete in for the performance of Gods publick worſhip, have no reaſon to complaine for want of a <hi>ſet day,</hi> or <hi>time,</hi> for the ſame purpoſe. The truth <note place="margin">Difference of times and places how taken away un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpell.</note> is, that that peculiar bleſſing which God once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon the <hi>Sabbath</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> &amp; thereby differenced them from all others, is enlarged to all <hi>times &amp; places;</hi> and any day and place may, by the Church, be dedicated and ſet apart for Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and being ſo dedicated, &amp; ſet apart, they inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that <hi>holineſſe</hi> which was once peculiar unto the, in relation to the duties then &amp; there performed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:10649:22"/>
to God, who in regard of the abundance of grace vouchſafed now in the time of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> may be ſaid to be more preſent at ſuch times, and in ſuch places, then heretofore in thoſe of his own aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But it was not neceſſary that <hi>Chriſt himſelf,</hi> or his <hi>Apoſtles from him,</hi> ſhould by expreſſe <hi>precept</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly deſigne, either of theſe: if any think ſuch <note place="margin">Ameſ. loco ſupracit. n 30.</note> precept to be neceſſary, let them ſhew the place of Scripture, where ſuch precept is to be found, or elſe confeſſe the Scripture to be deficient in things neceſſary, and ſo forſake their colours of <hi>reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and paſſe over into the Campe of the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts.</hi> If they be aſhamed of this, let them learne and confeſſe: That, however it be neceſſary that ſome time be dedicated to Gods ſervice, yet the determination to this or that particular day, is not neceſſary to be defined by Scripture: which they may perhaps the more eaſily be brought to ſee, if they conſider, that in this it is no otherwiſe, then it is with other things of equall neceſſity with this in the generall (as the Sacraments, Faſting, and Prayer it ſelfe) which yet for the particular, <hi>when,</hi> and <hi>how often</hi> they are to be uſed, is not any where in <hi>Scripture</hi> defined, nor neceſſary ſo to be.</p>
            <p>But ſome who will have the <hi>Lords day</hi> ſo called, <note place="margin">Dod p. 133.</note> becauſe Chriſt himſelfe inſtituted it, ſay, <q>
                  <hi>That, the Apoſtles, by the authority of that Spirit, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way aſsiſted them in their miniſteriall office, did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the day, and themſelves kept, and ordained it to be kept in all Churches, as may appeare</hi> 1. Cor. 16. 1. <hi>Where he ſaith, Every firſt day of the weeke, when yee meete together, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> But certainly, it is moſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:10649:23"/>
evident, even to a vulgar conſideration, that no ſuch thing doth appeare out of that place. For, what doth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſay there? That hee would have Chriſtians <hi>meete</hi> every firſt day of the weeke, to ſerve God? No ſurely, there is not a word of <hi>meeting</hi> in the text, but what is foyſted in, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the credulous Reader. That which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, is, That on that day hee would have every one lay by him in ſtore, as God hath proſpered him. This implies neither the meeting together of the Church on that day, nor the performance of any religious duty; but onely a <hi>repoſiting</hi> or <hi>lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up,</hi> and that not in a <hi>common banke,</hi> but every man (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>by himſelfe.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">See Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> upon that place, who ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. and a little after, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> Againe, grant that S. <hi>Paul</hi> (as he did not) had enjoyned Chriſtians to <hi>meete</hi> on that <hi>day:</hi> and at their meeting to make a <hi>Collection</hi> for the poore; yet could not this ſerve for a ſufficient inſtitution of that <hi>Day</hi> to ſucceede the Jewes <hi>Sabbath:</hi> unleſſe ſuch <hi>collections</hi> did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve in them all the ſervice of God, on that day to be done, or were ſo connected with them, that they could not bee ſeparated: which no man, I ſuppoſe, will affirme. To leave theſe therefore, who out of an over-weening conceit of the day, are willing to catch at any ſhadow that may ſeeme to countenance it, and gaine to it the reputation of <hi>Divine inſtitution;</hi> Let us pitch upon that which is certaine, which though it riſe not ſo high, as an immediately-divine authority, yet is ſufficient to ground our practiſe upon, and to exact the due ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Day.</p>
            <p>Firſt, then it is moſt certaine, that our Bleſſed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:10649:23"/>
Saviour did honour this day with his moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 28. 1 Mar. 16. 1. Ioh. 20. 1.</note> reſurrection, and by his often <note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 20. 19. 26.</note> apparitions upon it to his Diſciples: and thereby (as it were) pointed out this day to his Diſciples, as worthy to be made choice of to be celebrated in honour of him: who on that day began his glorious exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, after his triumph over Principalities and <note place="margin">Col. 2. 14. 15.</note> powers, upon his Croſſe whom he there ſpoyled, having nayled to it, and thereby cancelled, the hand-writing of Ordinances that was againſt us; that is, the obligation to obſerve the Jewiſh rites and ceremonies, and among theſe their <hi>Sabbath:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 18.</note> which from that time forward, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> would <note place="margin">Ad Januar. epiſt. 119. c. 13. Dies Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minica Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectione Domini declaratus eſt, et ex illo habere caepit feſtivitatein ſuam. Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrare dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus eſt. Ibid. c 9. Domini re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſcitatio promiſit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis aeternum diem &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecravit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum diem. Id. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Apoſtoli. Serm. 15.</note> have no man to judge <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in: who as they were freed from it by the death of Chriſt, ſo by his reſurrection they had ground ſufficient mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to direct them to the obſervation of a new Feſtivall. Whence S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lords Day was declared—to Chriſtians by the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Lord, and from that time began to be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated.</hi> So that for ought that appeares, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our did not command the firſt day of the weeke to be obſerved. Hee did (to uſe the words of the ſame Father) <hi>Vouchſafe to demonſtrate, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate it;</hi> or (as he elſe-where ſpeakes) <hi>The raiſing againe of our Lord, promiſed us an everlaſting Day, and conſecrated for us the Lords Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it is no leſſe certaine that the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> (upon this ground no doubt) did <hi>obſerve this Day,</hi> and had thereon their holy aſſemblies, as <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7. And that for the ſame cauſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle deſigned it for the ſtoring up of their almes,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:10649:24"/>
that the memory of the benefits which on that day they obtained, might make them more readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contribute to the neceſſities of their brethren, as S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> hath obſerved upon 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. And laſtly, that in the time of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> it ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the name of the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> as appeares <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel</hi> 1. 10.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that the ages of the Church immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after the Apoſtles (whether by conſtitution, or onely in imitation of them, is not knowne, nor much materiall) did obſerve this Day, as the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians Feſtivall;</hi> ſtiling it the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed the ſame practiſe by continuall ſucceſſion even to this day: as the late learned <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Speech againſt <hi>Traske. p.</hi> 74.</note> ſhewes, avowing it on his credit, <hi>That there is not an Eccleſiaſticall Writer in whom it is not to be found.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee finde thus much then without contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. That it hath been the practiſe of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, to obſerve the Sunday or Lords <note place="margin">* Pet. Mart. Theſ. in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. 20. Non erravit Chriſtiana Eccleſia, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loco Sabbati flatuit ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervandum Diem domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicum, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus iaſacris ſitteris men tio habetur, quamvis de ejus obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatione prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum non <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Day, and that ever ſince, yea in the very Apoſtles times: a practiſe warranted by the example of the Apoſtles, and the honour vouchſafed to that day by our Bleſſed Saviour himſelfe. Whence we may conclude with a late learned Divine, <hi>That the Chriſtian Church did not erre, when in ſtead of the Sabbath it appointed the Lords Day to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; of which, there is mention made in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, though there be no Precept for the obſervation of it.</hi> In which words of his, I will obſerve <hi>three things.</hi> Firſt, that he ſaith, <hi>[the Church]</hi> not the Apoſtles, or Apoſtolicall men: (for though
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:10649:24"/>
that be moſt probable, and hath for it the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and for that it hath beene <note place="margin">Serm. de Temp. 251. Quod uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa tenet Eccleſia, nec Conci<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t inſtitutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentum eſt, non niſi au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolica tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſſime cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur.—Id. de Bap. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Don. l. 9. c. 24. &amp; l. 5. c. 23.</note> ever obſerved by the Church, it may juſtly be aſcribed to them, yet) becauſe if they did it, they did it not as therein reporting the <hi>immediate</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Field</hi> of the Church <hi>P.</hi> 377.</note> 
               <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Chriſt,</hi> nor by any power that was <hi>properly Apoſtolicall,</hi> but by vertue of their Paſtorall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and office, which was common to them with their Succeſſours, it may be termed an <hi>Ordinance of the Church,</hi> and it little concernes us to know whether it were delivered by the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or their next after-commers.</p>
            <p>Secondly. The <note n="b" place="margin">Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantiae Diei Dominicae in novâ le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, ſuccedit obſervantia Sabbati, non ex ui praeceptiet legis, ſed ex conſtitutione Eccleſiae, &amp; conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne populi Chriſtiani. Aquin. 2. 2. q. 122. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Church appointed this Day,</hi> but whether at the firſt by expreſſe conſtitution it were commanded, or by cuſtome onely obſerved, it appeares not. <hi>Aquinas</hi> attributes it to both: and how ever, thus much is out of queſtion, that this Cuſtome or Conſtitution was afterward by many <note n="c" place="margin">Concil. Nican can. 20. La<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. Con. 19. Aureſion. 3. Can. 21. Matiſe. Can. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Canons</hi> of the Church, and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of Chriſtian <note n="d" place="margin">Euſch. de vitâ Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan. jl. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 18.</note> Emperours ratified and approved, and many things ordained tending to the right &amp; due obſervance of it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That the <hi>Chriſtian Church did not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in erre,</hi> as having ſufficient to warrant it out of Scripture, though there be no Precept for it. Yea, and if the Scripture did yeeld no example of this practiſe, or other ground for it in particular, yet had not the Church <hi>erred</hi> in ordaining it. For things pertaining to <hi>order</hi> &amp; <hi>decencie</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> (ſuch as is among others, the particular determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:10649:25"/>
of the ſet times of Gods worſhip) being undetermined in the word of God, are in the power of the Church to be ordered; ſo as they be done according to the generall Lawes of nature, and without contradiction to any poſitive Law in Scripture. Neither is it derogatorie to the word <note place="margin">S. Auguſt. Epiſt. 86 ad <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>lan.</note> of God, or any whit detracting from the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, to affirme that (though it ſufficiently and abundantly containe in it all things neceſſary to ſalvation, yet) it hath left a number of other things, free to be ordered at the diſcretion of the <hi>Church.</hi> And as to take from the Scripture, the ſufficient determination of things neceſſary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, were an injurie, and an impairing of that honour which God challengeth to his word; and the Church of God hath ever deſervedly yeelded to it; ſo it were no leſſe injurie to the Church of Chriſt, to abridge it of the power of determining of this and ſuch like things, which being not of abſolute neceſſity, are yet convenient and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. For this prerogative &amp; power, the Church of God hath ever obtained and enjoyed, (even <note place="margin">See <hi>Hooker</hi> p. 92. p. 95. &amp; p. 121.</note> when it was moſt obliged to hold to the letter of the Law, preſcribing the Ceremonies belonging to the ſervice of God) that it might without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of adding to, or altering the law of God, from time to time appoint ſundry rites and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, not any where preſcribed in the Law. Such were the appointment of the <hi>houres,</hi> for the <hi>dayly ſacrifices;</hi> the building of <hi>Synagogues</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the land, to heare the word of God, and to pray in, when they came not up to <hi>Ieruſaleme</hi> the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:10649:25"/>
Feaſt of the <hi>Dedication</hi> which was ſolemniſed even by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and yet never ſpoken of in the <note place="margin">Ioh. 10. 22.</note> Law: and many more which the Church, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any particular command, onely following the light of reaſon, in her diſcretion judged meete. And certainly, the Church of Chriſt hath not now leſſe power, or priviledge then the Jewiſh Church then had, to which it is no way inferiour, but farre ſuperiour in regard of the meaſure of grace, and the preſence of the ſpirit of Chriſt, by which it is aſſiſted, as in other things, ſo in ordaining Lawes for the edification of the Church.</p>
            <p>Now leaſt any ſhould thinke it a matter of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differencie to obey, or diſobey the Orders of the Church, which are thus conſtituted without the expreſſe command of God in Scripture, and that the tranſgreſſions of ſuch Conſtitutions are no ſinnes; I will cloſe this point with that which worthy <hi>Hooker</hi> (from whom I have borrowed the <note place="margin">Eccl. Poll. 3. § 9 p. 107.</note> greateſt part of this laſt diſcourſe) hath judiciouſly and fully delivered to this purpoſe. <hi>Vnto Lawes thus made</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and received by a whole Church, they which live within the boſome of that Church, muſt not thinke it a matter indifferent either to yeeld, or not to yeeld obedience. Is it a ſmall offence to deſpiſe the Church of God? My ſonne keepe thy Fathers comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 22. Pro. 6. 20.</note> (ſaith Salomon) <hi>and forget not thy mothers inſtruction, binde them both alwayes about thine heart! It doth not ſtand with the duty which wee owe to our Heavenly Father, that to the Ordinance of our Mother the Church, we ſhould ſhew ourſelves diſobedient. Let us not ſay we keepe the commandements of the one, when
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:10649:26"/>
wee breake the Law of the other: for unleſſe we obſerve both, wee obey neither—Yea that which is more, the Lawes thus made God himſelfe doth in ſuch ſort authorize, that to deſpiſe them, is to deſpiſe in them Him.</hi> Thus hee with much more to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Which I therefore thought good to adde, that no man might think that while I aſcribe it to its true Originall, I goe about to impaire the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of it, or to withdraw any thing from the due obſervance of it. And thus I have done with this ſecond Queſtion, <hi>viz. When and by whom the Sunday or Lords Day was inſtituted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things thus diſcuſſed and cleared, it may now ſeeme ſuperfluous to enquire into the <hi>liberty</hi> that wee Chriſtians have, how farre it may juſtly be extended in regard of ordinary labours upon the Sunday. For if it be granted that the <hi>ſtrict reſt</hi> on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was <hi>Ceremoniall,</hi> and abrogated with the Day; and that the Day which we keepe is not by vertue of the <hi>fourth Commandement,</hi> but by the <hi>cuſtome</hi> or <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> It wil not be hard for any to conclude, that Chriſtians are not bound to reſt on that day from all works, further then the duties of the day, and they who enjoyned it require. Yet for more full ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I will adde ſome-what more particularly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe two Queſtions that remaine: To enquire then firſt, <hi>What works the lewes might doe or their Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This wil eaſily be diſpatcht, in as much as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Scripture is very plaine, and little or no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of opinion among Divines: Yet will it
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:10649:26"/>
not be altogether needleſſe, in regard that the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty we now have under the Goſpell, when it is compared with theirs under the Law, will the better appeare.</p>
            <p>Now theſe <hi>workes</hi> are fitly reduced under three <note place="margin">See D <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> on Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. 20.</note> heads. The firſt of which are <hi>Workes of neceſsity,</hi> ſuch as could not well be deferred or prevented. Of which ſort are reckoned divers, which how ever Phariſaicall ſuperſtition had prevailed with the people to ſcruple at, yet were never, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Law-giver, prohibited them, as may appeare by the doctrine &amp; practiſe of our <hi>Saviour;</hi> who was both wayes the <hi>beſt expoſitor</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> and who both wayes came, not to deſtroy, but to <hi>fulfill</hi> it. And among thoſe thus allowed by <note place="margin">Math. 5. 17 Math. 12 1 Luk. 13. 15 Luk. 14 5.</note> our Saviour we finde, the <hi>providing of foode</hi> in the caſe of hunger; the <hi>watering</hi> (and by the like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the foddering) of <hi>cattell,</hi> the <hi>ſaving</hi> them from <hi>imminent danger.</hi> Whence by <hi>analogie</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity of reaſon, wee may conclude the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of many more things of the like nature: as that of <hi>Mattathias</hi> and his company, reſolving <note place="margin">1 Macc. 2. 41.</note> to fight upon the <hi>Sabbath</hi> to ſave their lives. So the <hi>quenching</hi> of an houſe on fire, the <hi>ſaving of corne,</hi> and other neceſſary ſubſtance from periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the like. To which wee may adde <hi>workes communis honeſtatis,</hi> as the <hi>decent attiring</hi> of our ſelves, and all other workes which neceſſity of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath impoſed upon men, and thereby allowed as fit to be done.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort of workes permitted them; <note place="margin">Luk. 13. 11 Iohn 5. 8.</note> were <hi>workes of mercie and charity:</hi> as to <hi>viſite the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:10649:27"/>
ſicke, heale the diſeaſed,</hi> and the like: which wee finde approved by our <hi>Saviours</hi> often practiſe; and together with thoſe before-mentioned, juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by that <hi>axiome</hi> of his: <hi>The Sabbath was made</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mar. 2. 27.</note> 
               <hi>for man, and not man for the Sabbath:</hi> that is, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Eraſmus</hi>'s Gloſſe) <hi>it is fit that the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aequum eſt ut Sabbati obſervatio cedat homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num utilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, et non ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Sabbati cauſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>m Parap<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in locum. <hi>Hoſea. 6. 6. Acts</hi> 13. 27</note> 
               <hi>of the Sabbath ſhould give place to mans benefit, and not that man ſhould periſh for the Sabbath:</hi> as alſo by that of the <hi>Prophet</hi> by him cited: <hi>God will have mercy and not Sacrifice:</hi> that is, rather have the miſeries of men relceved, then the letter of the Law obſerved.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt ſort of works, were <hi>workes of piety,</hi> belonging to the ſervice of God, as to reade the Law, to teach the people, to circumciſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to offer Sacrifice, with their attendants, as to make fires for them, to ſlay and prepare the beaſts: for theſe workes though ſervile in themſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing directed to the ſervice of God were ſacred, and no way violating the <hi>Sabbaths reſt.</hi> So our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <note place="margin">Math. 12. 5.</note> teſtifies that notwithſtanding theſe workes, done by the Prieſts in the Temple, yet the <hi>Prieſts were blameleſſe,</hi> and not tranſgreſſours of the Law: And the Jewes had it among their traditions, that <note place="margin">Hinc defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitio eſt Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daicarum traditionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: In templo nuneſſe Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. F<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Lu ca<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>oc.</note> 
               <hi>in the Temple there was no Sabbath.</hi> Intimating that the <hi>Sabbaths reſt</hi> muſt give place to thoſe things which were to be done by the Prieſt in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for the ſervice of God. Having ſeene what might be done on the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> let us now ſee, whether, and what liberty Chriſtians now have on the <hi>Sunday,</hi> and how farre that liberty is to be extended, which is the laſt part of our Inquirie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:10649:27"/>
And here though ſome few (tranſported with <note place="margin">True Church. P 300.</note> a heedleſſe zeale of maintayning the dignity of this day) have not ſtrucke to affirme that the <hi>Iewes had as much liberty as we have, &amp; that we are as much reſtrained, as they were:</hi> Yet the moſt, even of the ſtricteſt, and moſt preciſe exactors of the <hi>Sundayes reſt,</hi> doe grant a liberty which Chriſtians now have, more then the <hi>Iewes</hi> had. But <hi>what liberty this is, wherein it conſiſts, &amp; how far to be extended,</hi> is not on all hands agreed upon.</p>
            <p>Some there are who when they come to define this liberty, they pin it up within ſo narow a room, that it proves either none at all or to no purpoſe. <hi>Ameſius</hi> ſaith; <hi>There is nothing can be brought out of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Med. Theel. l. 2. c. 15. n. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Scripture co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſtrist obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Sabath, which was commanded to the Iewes, which doth not in the ſame manner belong to all Chriſtians, except the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Praeter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſionem ignis, et cibi communis apparatum.</note> 
               <hi>kindling of fires, and the dreſſing of ordinary dyet.</hi> And theſe, he thinkes it probable too, that the <hi>Iewes</hi> might ordinarily doe on their Sabbath, <hi>though upon ſpeciall occaſions, they were forbidden them:</hi> ſo that he ſeemes to retract that liberty which before he granted them. But others doe <note place="margin">Elton. <hi>p.</hi> 101. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins caſes. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> freely grant theſe, and ſome few like them, as making of beds, carrying of burthens (to wit, on ſpeciall, and urgent occaſions) and theſe they allow by this name of <hi>workes</hi> of Chriſtian liberty. <hi>Egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giam vero libertatem!</hi> A great liberty (no doubt) and worthy that precious blood by which it was purchaſed!</p>
            <p>But two things may here be demanded. Firſt, how it will appeare that Chriſtians have this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty?
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:10649:28"/>
And here (for ought I can ſee) we muſt be contented to take their own authority: for Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they alledge none to purpoſe. Thoſe two places which are cited by <hi>Elton</hi> on this occaſion ſpeak no ſuch thing; &amp; beſides, that which is there <note place="margin">Mat. 12. 1. 2. 3. Mark. 2. 27</note> ſayd (whatever it be) proves no peculiar liberty belonging to Chriſtians, which the <hi>Iewes</hi> had not. For in them our Saviour juſtifies his Diſciples from tranſgreſſing the <hi>Sabbath</hi> which was then in force, but doth not ſhew what might be done af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, when by his death the <hi>Sabbath</hi> ſhould be abrogated. If they alledge that our Saviour bad the <hi>ſicke man</hi> on the Sabbath <hi>to take up his bed,</hi> (which may ſeeme to have ſome reference to <hi>making of beds,</hi> or <hi>carrying of burthens)</hi> It may be anſwered, that our Saviour doth not there ſhew what might ordinarily be done; but by his authority gives a <hi>ſpeciall diſpenſation</hi> to the ſicke man to take up his bed &amp;c. without which diſpenſation, the man could not have beene excuſed from breaking the Sabbath. So that here is no certainty (according <note place="margin">See <hi>Fran Lucas</hi> Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. upon the place.</note> to their principles) for any thing to be done, which the Jewes might not doe, but that men muſt (for all their pretended liberty) either <hi>Iudaize,</hi> or elſe adventure for this ſmall liberty with a doubting conſcience.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It may alſo be demanded. How wee ſhall know that onely this liberty is allowed <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians?</hi> This alſo we muſt take upon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their credit. For reaſon or Scripture they alledge none at all. And if they, without either reaſon or Scripture ſhall take upon them to give lawes to the Church
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:10649:28"/>
of God, and preſcribe bounds to Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; I ſee no cauſe, why wee may not upon ſolid grounds of Scripture and reaſon, aſſert that liberty which of right belongs to us, as purchaſed by the all precious blood of our deare, and Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <p>And this will appeare if we conſider what <hi>reſt</hi> or <hi>ceſsation</hi> from labours is on this day required: Firſt then, for that it is a day of Gods publique, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne worſhip to bee performed by the whole Church, which cannot (as hath beene ſhewed) be performed, unleſſe there bee a <hi>vacation</hi> from ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and common worked, <hi>a vacation</hi> therefore and <hi>reſting</hi> from theſe, as they are <hi>impediments</hi> to Gods ſervice, is on that day required, as neceſſary. Yet not ſo neceſſary, no not in the times of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique aſſemblyes, but that the workes which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity impoſeth upon men, and rarer occaſions in mens particular affaires, ſubject to manifeſt detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Ho<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ker. p. 385.</note> unleſſe they be preſently followed, may, with very good conſcience draw men aſide ſometime fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ordinary rule; conſidering the favourable diſpenſation, which our Saviour grounds upon this <hi>Axiome. The Sabbbath was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath.</hi> Which rule, if it held for the <hi>Iews</hi> on their Sabbath, is certainely no leſſe in force at this day for Chriſtians. In the uſe of which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, ſome cautions muſt bee obſerved, As firſt that men pretend not neceſſity or charity, when it is covetouſneſſe or a <hi>careleſſe neglect</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> of Gods publique worſhip; upon which ground no doubt, it was that the <hi>Emperor Leo</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:10649:29"/>
that liberty which by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">Concil. Matiſc. 2. can. 1.</note> to <hi>Husbandmen:</hi> and the Counſell of <hi>Matiſcon</hi> forbids men to frame a neceſſary to themſelves of yoking their Oxen; therein allowing both a juſt diſpenſation in neceſſity, &amp; forbidding the unjuſt pretence of neceſſity where none is.</p>
            <p>Secondly, men muſt take heed that they do not by their negligence, or improvidence and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſ draw a neceſſity upon themſelves: in which regard the word <hi>(Remember)</hi> which God prefixed to the <hi>fourth Commandement</hi> is yet in force, to exact our care and mindfulneſſe ſo to provide before hand, that the dutyes to which this day is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, bee not by our default omitted, or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that being neceſſarily hindered or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to omit the ſolemne &amp; publique dutyes of the Day, we do (as much as may be) by private devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; meditations make ſupply of that defect.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſuch is the reverence that is due to the ſolemne &amp; publique dutyes of devotion, that they require not onely a ſurceaſe from other workes &amp; thoughts for the time of their performance, but alſo a decent preparation before-hand; that <hi>wee looke to our feete, when we enter into the houſe of God, &amp; put off our ſhooes</hi> before we <hi>ſtand upon holy ground:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 5. 1. Exod. 3. 5.</note> that ſo our thoughts and affections, which are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally bent upon the world, and not eaſily with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne from it, may be rayſed to a diſpoſition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting ſo ſacred an employment. In which reſpect it is convenient, if not neceſſary, that til <hi>the publike ſervice of God be ended,</hi> men intangle not themſelves
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:10649:29"/>
with unneceſſary buſineſſes, or give themſelves to <hi>ſportings</hi> or <hi>recreations,</hi> whereby their mindes ſhould be hindered from the right preparing of themſelves, or due performance of thoſe holydu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes.</p>
            <p>Laſtly it is good and commendable to ſpend the reſt of that day in holy meditations, private prayer, reading and calling to minde what wee have read, or heard; Theſe workes, as they are at all times profitable and beſeeming Chriſtians; ſo on that day they are moſt ſeaſonable and ſuitable to thoſe publique actions of Devotion which are the proper worke of the Day. Thus S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Serm. de. Temp. 251.</note> exhorteth his Auditors on this day to <hi>ſequeſter themſelves from worldly buſineſſes,</hi> that they may be employed in theſe works; and the Councill of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſcon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Concil. Matiſc. 2. can. 1. Can. 23.</note> yea and our owne <hi>Church Canons</hi> preſcribe the ſpending of this day (and other <hi>holy-dayes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to Gods ſervice) in theſe and the like religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous imployments. And therefore they who thus ſpend the <hi>Lords day</hi> (if it be done without ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or judging other mens liberty) cannot there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore juſtly be condemned.</p>
            <p>Now by this it is eaſie to judge of our liberty. Firſt then, here is a liberty <hi>in caſe of neceſsity,</hi> though thereby the ſolemne dutyes of Gods worſhip bee hindered. Secondly, a liberty in things <hi>not abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſsary,</hi> ſo as thereby the ſervice of God, &amp; the due preparation thereto be not hindered: under which the uſe of honeſt and ſeemly recreations, after the publike dutyes of the Day are finiſhed, may be comprehended. For though it cannot be
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:10649:30"/>
denied that a man may commendably ſpend the whole day in workes of piety and devotion, yet that cannot preſcribe to all Chriſtians, or infringe their liberty. For it is one thinge to <hi>exhorte</hi> to a thing <hi>as commendable,</hi> another to <hi>urge</hi> it as <hi>neceſsary;</hi> one thing to ſay, this or that is a good worke, and is wel done at this or that time, another, to enjoyn it by way of <hi>Precept,</hi> ſo as at ſuch time it may not be omitted, nor other worke permitted. And the reaſon is, becauſe Gods <hi>affirmative Precepts,</hi> though they warrant, and commend the workes that they enjoyne, and make them good and commendable, whenſoever they are performed; yet they bind not preciſely to any determinate time for their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: For example we are commanded to <hi>pray</hi> and that <hi>continually,</hi> ſo that he that is moſt frequent <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.</note> in prayer, obſerves this <hi>Precept beſt,</hi> and deſerves the praiſe of a devout and religious man: &amp; yet he that prayes not at this or at that time, when haply, another doth, cannot therefore be ſayd to ſin, and much leſſe bee counted irreligious or profane. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> prayed &amp; gave thanks unto God at midnight, <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 62.</note> &amp; ſo did S. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> and ſurely thoſe Godly Soules were bleſſedly employed: but ſhall wee <note place="margin">Acts 16. 25.</note> therefore condemne him who doth not the like? S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo being to depart from <hi>Troas,</hi> continued his Sermon till <hi>midnight</hi> on the <hi>Sunday,</hi> and no <note place="margin">Acts 20. 7.</note> doubt, but he did well; yet no man will therefore preſcribe the like length to every <hi>Sunday Sermon.</hi> The caſe is the ſame in this buſineſſe we have in hand: for we doe not preſently affixe theſe duties to the day, which wee ſay may be commendably
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:10649:30"/>
on that day performed; nor on the other ſide, doe we diſallow the ſpending of the <hi>whole Sunday</hi> in holy and religious actions; becauſe we dare not ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidly tye all men ſo to do, or lay it upon them by way of <hi>Precept,</hi> as if God had expreſly commanded that time to be no otherwiſe ſpent. There is a good and a ſafe uſe of that diſtinction of <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Counſells;</hi> (though the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> abuſe it to the patroniſing of their imaginary workes of <hi>ſuper ero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation)</hi> and things in themſelves good without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to any determinate time, we may wiſh, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, and counſell men to performe at any time, when wee cannot by Precept impoſe them upon all. Wee know our Saviour commended ſome things to his Diſciples with a <hi>Let him that is able to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 19. 12</note> 
               <hi>receive it, recieve it</hi> adviſing and exciting all to that, which nowing the infirmity of many, hee would not exact by his authority as neceſſary to be performed by all. And in this caſe wee may doe well to imitate him conſidering that it is no where enjoyned in Scripture, and that ſuch is the condition of many, that they are not capable of ſuch an injunction, as namely thoſe who by reaſon of their mean <hi>education</hi> or <hi>naturall parts</hi> are not fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for long meditation requiſite for the ſpending of the vacant time of the Day, and to whom in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their hard labour in the weeke dayes, it is a mercy to permit ſome bodily <hi>recreation</hi> on this day; which certainely cannot be diſpleaſing to him who hath ſaid, <hi>I will have mercy &amp; not Sacrifice.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12. 7.</note> And if they, who uſe to judge the uſe of all recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation on this day ſinfull, <hi>had known what that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:10649:31"/>
they would not have condemned the guiltleſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any thinke that God hath ſo commanded: let him produce the place of Scripture, and I will quickly recant. The places which are uſually al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for that purpoſe, and wherewith men are ſo frighted and thundred againſt out of the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, being intended for the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and that in regard of that ſpeciall <hi>poſitive Precept,</hi> given for the <hi>ſtrict reſt</hi> upon <hi>their Sabbath,</hi> cannot with any <note place="margin">Eſay 58. 13 Exod. 20. 10.</note> ſhew of reaſon, bee extended to <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> when both <hi>Day</hi> and <hi>Precept,</hi> are out of date.</p>
            <p>But haply ſome may yet further contend, that though the <hi>Day</hi> bee changed, yet the <hi>equity</hi> of it ſtill remaines, and that they may argue thence <hi>(à pari,</hi> or (as ſome thinke) <hi>à minori)</hi> as from the leſſe to the greater. That if the <hi>Iewes</hi> upon their <hi>Sabbath</hi> which was inſtituted in memory of the <hi>Creation,</hi> and of their <hi>deliverance</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ought to doe <hi>no worke,</hi> nor ſo much as to ſpeake their <hi>owne words,</hi> and that for the <hi>whole day:</hi> then by the like reaſon, nay much rather ought <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſo to doe on their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or <hi>Sunday</hi> which is conſecrated to the memory of a farre more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worke, the worke of our <hi>Redemption,</hi> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of our <hi>Saviour.</hi> Here, in this kinde of reaſoning there is ſome truth, but (as it is too common) it is over-ſtrayned, and ſo is but a meere colour to countenance that, for which it is brought, and not any ſolid foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereon to build it. The truth is, Chriſtians have as much (if not more) cauſe to celebrate the <hi>Redemption</hi> of mankind by a ſolemne <hi>weekely
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:10649:31"/>
Commemoration,</hi> as ever the <hi>Iewes</hi> had to celebrate the <hi>Creation</hi> of the world, or their <hi>deliverance</hi> out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> and this may ſerve as a good ground to juſtifie the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> and the <hi>Churches practiſe</hi> in obſerving it: But this truth is overſtrained being applied to the <hi>manner of Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration,</hi> which was peculiar to the Jewes, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to the then-State of the Church, which was (as hath beene ſhewed) to be held un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the yoke of a ſtrict <hi>outward reſt,</hi> in expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for the prefiguring of that <hi>eternall reſt,</hi> which now Chriſt hath actually purchaſed; and therefore injuriouſly laid upon <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who are freed from that yoke, under which they groaned: And they may as well upon the ſame ground conclude againſt <hi>making of fires, and dreſsing of meate</hi> upon the Sunday, and make the gathering of a <hi>few ſticks</hi> upon that Day to deſerve no leſſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 15. Aut ſimus Chriſtiani, &amp; Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum cola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, aut ſimus Iudaei, &amp; Sabbatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſervemus. S. Aug. ep. 86</note> now, then hee ſuffered for doing the like upon the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> So that wee may ſay to thoſe who thus argue (as hee in Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> upon farre better ground then he did) <hi>Either let us be Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and keepe the Lords Day, or let us bee Iewes, and obſerve the Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is it not reaſon that God ſhould have <hi>one whole day</hi> in <hi>ſeven,</hi> given unto him now, as well as heretofore? Yes certainely; but yet with ſuch difference, as ſuites with the different condition of the Church that now is, from that which then was, that being guided by the <hi>ſpirit of feare,</hi> this of <hi>love,</hi> that in a ſtate of <hi>bondage,</hi> under the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable <note place="margin">2. Tim. 1. 7<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> burthen of legall <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> this in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:10649:32"/>
a ſtate of <hi>liberty,</hi> and under Chriſts <hi>eaſie yoake:</hi> In a word, they <hi>Iewes,</hi> and we <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> and this being conſidered, we may be ſaid to give God a Day, no leſſe now, then they then, though in that Day wee doe not ſo ſtrictly obſerve the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ceremoniall reſt, as they were bound to doe</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſay, that our Church is ſo farre from abridging God of <hi>one</hi> day in <hi>ſeven,</hi> that it gives more, as having appointed and conſecrated di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Holy dayes</hi> to the ſame ſolemne and publike worſhip of God, which is enjoyned to bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med upon the <hi>Lords Day.</hi> For theſe (though they may admit ſome difference in regard of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall dignity, in as much as thoſe benefits commemorated in them are greater or leſſer yet) in regard of their eſſentials they are equall, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all of them dedicated to the honour of the ſame God, in memory of ſome great and ſpeciall benefits vouchſafed to the Church, and therefore doe goe <hi>pari paſſu</hi> in our <hi>Canons,</hi> and in our anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 13. Act for Vniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Statutes,</hi> which require the ſame obſervance of both under the ſame penalty. And therefore thoſe who ſtand ſo much for a <hi>whole Day</hi> of <hi>ſeven</hi> to be conſecrated to God, if the worſhip of God were all they affected, might ſee that there is a compenſation made for the defect which they ſo much complaine of in our obſervation on the <hi>Lords Day;</hi> and they themſelves might doe well to take advantage, by a religious obſervation of theſe dayes, to make up their failings on the <hi>Lords Day:</hi> But this they are ſo farre from, that they
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:10649:32"/>
account the obſervation of theſe dayes a breach of the fourth Commandement, and thinke it a ſin <note place="margin">Ameſ. med. Theol. lib. 2 cap. 15.</note> to make more <hi>Holy dayes</hi> then one in <hi>ſeven.</hi> In which regard, it cannot be judged altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, if I here take occaſion to vindicate the practiſe of our Church, from their unjuſt cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <p>And in the firſt place, I may returne their own Argument upon them, and ſay; Is it not reaſon that God ſhould, now under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> have <hi>more ſet dayes</hi> to commemorate his benefits then <hi>one</hi> in <hi>ſeven,</hi> as well as under the <hi>Law?</hi> Vnder the Law, we know, they had, beſide their weekly <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> the <hi>Paſſeover, Pentecoſt,</hi> and the Feaſt of <hi>Tabernacles;</hi> and not onely thoſe which had Gods expreſſe command for their Inſtitution, but the Feaſt of <hi>Purim,</hi> and of the <hi>Dedication,</hi> which (as I have before ſhewed) were ordained by the Church, without any expreſſe command of God, and obſerved by our Saviour himſelfe, whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample alone (if any thing) is ſufficient to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt us from ſcrupling at the like now in the time of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if they will not runne cleane coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to their owne principles, and deny the <hi>mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of the <hi>fourth Commandement</hi> altogether, they muſt acknowledge thus much (at leaſt) to bee <hi>moral:</hi> That <hi>there ought to be a certaine part of our time given to God, and ſome dayes ſet apart for his publique worſhip:</hi> Now theſe (being left undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the word of God) if it bee not in the power of the Church to determine them, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:10649:33"/>
how that precept ſhould be obſerved: And if the Churchupon this ground, have reaſon and power to appoint any one Day, why not more? ſeeing her power is not limited or reſtrained within any other bounds but thoſe generalls, of <hi>decency</hi> and <hi>order:</hi> which I preſume no man will ſay are tranſgreſſed in the ordination of thoſe <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 40.</note> 
               <hi>Holy dayes</hi> which are obſerved among us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to this that ſuch times are in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall commanded by God; wee may adde two things more, which being well conſidered will abundantly diſcharge the obſervation of ſuch dayes from ſuperſtition: and thoſe are,</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the duties therein required are no other then ſuch, as according to the word of God, ought to bee performed by all Chriſtians: For what elſe is required on thoſe dayes but the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne prayers and prayſes of God in the Church, joyned with the hearing of his Word, and a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall commemoration of his benefits, which as on thoſe dayes were received? And which of all theſe is not required in the word of God? And if it bee lawfull, yea commanded, that wee ſhould performe thoſe duties <hi>at all times</hi> and upon <hi>all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions,</hi> they cannot at any time whenſoever they <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5. 17, 18.</note> are performed, juſtly bee termed <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> or (which muſt follow by conſequence) <hi>unlawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The other thing to bee conſidered is, That the grounds and occaſions of the Churches de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of theſe duties unto thoſe ſpeciall dayes which wee obſerve, are ſuch as deſerve no leſſe. As being <hi>reall, great,</hi> and <hi>generall benefits</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:10649:33"/>
vouchſafed by God unto his Church.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they are <hi>true</hi> and <hi>reall,</hi> not imaginary fictions founded upon the fained actions, or falle martyrdomes of <hi>titular Saints,</hi> ſuch as are many in the <hi>Romiſh Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, they are <hi>great,</hi> not ordinary or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon benefits, and therefore require a more then ordinary acknowledgement.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they are <hi>generall;</hi> the good whereof redounds, not to a few, but to the whole <hi>body of the Church;</hi> and ſo, if our acknowledgement bee anſwerable, it muſt be publike and ſolemne, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed joyntly by all thoſe that are partakers of the benefits.</p>
            <p>Now, if wee ſhall runne thorough the whole <hi>Kalender,</hi> take an impartiall view of all our <hi>Holy dayes,</hi> wee ſhall not find ſo much as one among them all, of which thus much may not truely bee affirmed.</p>
            <p>For they may almoſt bee ranked under two heads. Firſt, ſuch <hi>memorable ſteps</hi> in the ſtory of our bleſſed <hi>Saviour,</hi> as by which the great worke of our <hi>redemption</hi> advanced unto its happy accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment. Secondly, the memorialls of that <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> which he afterwards manifeſted to the world by his holy <hi>Apoſtles, Evangeliſts</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> whom he honoured ſo much as to make them <hi>founders</hi> of that <hi>Kingdome</hi> which coſt him his deareſt blood, &amp; to count them worthy to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer death for his ſake. Concerning the former, I ſuppoſe there is none but will ſay in the words of the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> (as our vulgar tranſlation reades
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:10649:34"/>
them) <hi>The mercifull and gratious Lord hath ſo done his marvellous workes, that they ought to be had in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 111. 4</note> And what better meanes can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed then the appointing of <hi>ſet ſolemne dayes</hi> for <note place="margin">Eiſſc. Dco) beneſicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ejus ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemmtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ſeſtis et diebus <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>a. tuus dica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſque memoriam ne volumine temporum ingrata ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reparobli<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io <hi>Aug. de Civ.</hi> l. 10. c. 4.</note> their commemoration, I cannot ſee: And this was the Churches aime in appointing theſe dayes: So S. <hi>Auſtine, We</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>dedicate and conſecrate to God the memory of his benefits in ſolemne feaſts and ſet dayes, leaſt in the revolution of times ingratefull forgetfulneſſe ſhould creepe upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of the latter: For if our <hi>Saviour</hi> appeared ſo <hi>glorious in them,</hi> and <hi>by them</hi> conveighed ſo <hi>great and generall bleſsings</hi> to his <hi>Church,</hi> what reaſon can bee alleadged why the <hi>Church</hi> may not retaine an <hi>annuall honourable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of them</hi> to the glory of <hi>him</hi> whoſe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they were? The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us that <hi>the righteous ſhall bee had in everlaſting remembrance.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 112. 6.</note> And the <hi>Wiſeman, That the memory of the juſt ſhall be bleſſed.</hi> And therefore, to have <hi>ſome dayes</hi> in <note place="margin">Prov. 10. 8.</note> which the memories of thoſe, who were in their generations moſt famous for righteouſneſſe, may, with bleſſing, be perpetuated, is but their due and agreeable to his will who hath granted them that honour: ſo that we may juſtly ſolemnize the dayes wherein thoſe <hi>barning</hi> and <hi>ſhining lights</hi> firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to the world; or the dayes of their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hence, which were the dayes of their <hi>happy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auguration</hi> into the <hi>Kingdome of glory,</hi> when they, both left to the <hi>Church militant</hi> the glorious exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their <hi>Chriſtian fortitude,</hi> and became an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of new joy to the <hi>Church triumphant,</hi> by the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:10649:34"/>
acceſſion of <hi>new Citizens</hi> to that heavenly <hi>ſociety.</hi> Either of which, afford matter ſufficient of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne joy and rejoycing to the Church, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of praiſe and thankſgiving unto God.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, to convince them yet farther out of <note place="margin">4.</note> their owne principles: They allow the <hi>Church</hi> power, in the times of <hi>great calamities,</hi> either fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or felt, to appoint ſolemne dayes of <hi>faſting</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dies illi ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipro Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batis extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <hi>Ameſ. med. theol. l. 2. c. 15. Reade</hi> M. Maſon <hi>of Chriſtian humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> p. 66. Edit. 2.</note> and <hi>humiliation;</hi> and thoſe dayes they will have held as <hi>Sabbaths extraordinary,</hi> and that therein men are bound to abſtein from their <hi>bodily labours,</hi> according to the ſame ſtreitneſſe that they are bound to obſerve the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> I would gladly then know ſome reaſon why the Church ſhould want power to ordeine the <hi>like dayes</hi> for the celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>ſpeciall benefits,</hi> to be obſerved (not as <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths</hi> which are now antiquated and no preſidents for us <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but) with ſuch a <hi>ceſſation</hi> from la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, as is neceſſary for the performance of the publike worſhip of God, and fit to accompany ſuch ſolemnities of publike joy and rejoycing, to which <hi>Reſt</hi> is more naturally requiſite, then to the times of <hi>ſorow</hi> and <hi>humiliation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is not the having of ſuch dayes that ſome <note place="margin">Poſſunt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem dies qual ſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pie converti in occaſiones cultum Dei promovendi <hi>Ameſ. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. Elton p.</hi> 117.</note> ſcruple at, or the duties required in them, for they much deſire to have ſome dayes beſides the <hi>Lords day</hi> to meet together for the hearing of the <hi>Word,</hi> and for the <hi>words</hi> ſake can be contented to endure the Liturgie of the Church. But the things which they diſlike are; firſt the <hi>obligation</hi> that we put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on men for the obſervance of them; for they would have the <hi>appointment</hi> and <hi>obſervation</hi> of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:10649:35"/>
them to bee held a thing <hi>indifferent</hi> and no duty <hi>binding conſcience.</hi> Secondly, they diſlike the names that we give them, in that we ſtyle them <hi>the dayes of ſuch or ſuch a Saint,</hi> which to them <note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> ſeemes to favour of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> neither would they have them called <hi>holy dayes,</hi> or accounted more <hi>holy</hi> then others; foraſmuch as ſuch difference of dayes belonged to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and is now under the <hi>Goſpell</hi> taken away.</p>
            <p>To theſe I anſwer, firſt, for the <hi>obligation</hi> of the <hi>Churches commands,</hi> and that it is not a thing indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to obey or diſobey them, I have already ſpoken ſo much as may ſatisfie thoſe that are not <note place="margin">pag. 45.</note> ſtudious of contention, I onely adde now upon this occaſion; that it ſeemes to me very ridiculous, to grant the Church a power of ordeining ſuch times, and yet to require that the <hi>obſervation</hi> of them ſo ordeined be held a thing <hi>indifferent.</hi> For if their <hi>ordinance</hi> lay no tye upon men, but leave things notwithſtanding ſtill indifferent, their power ſurely, is to no purpoſe and nothing worth.</p>
            <p>Touching the <hi>names</hi> that we give them. I ſay, firſt that the <hi>feſtivalls</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> are dedicated, not to them by whoſe names they are called, but to God. To him, and not them, our prayers are directed; to him our praiſes, though for them, and with reference to thoſe bleſſings, which by them are vouchſafed unto us; Wee honour him as the author of all that good which either they, or we, by them, are partakers of: We honour them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as his inſtruments, and as thoſe who having beene <hi>imitators</hi> of our <hi>bleſſed Saviour,</hi> are worthy
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:10649:35"/>
patternes of our imitation. To this purpoſe wee finde the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Smyrna</hi> anſwering the like ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny raiſed againſt them by the <hi>Iewes,</hi> upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of their affection which they expreſſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <note place="margin">—Ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes not nec Chriſte un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere qui pro totius ſervandoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mundi ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te paſſus eſt nec alium quenquam colere poſſe. Nam hunc qui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam filu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res vero tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſcipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los &amp; imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatores Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini digne propter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperabile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inrege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptorem benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimus, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; nos conſortes &amp; diſcipulos fieri opta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>Euſeb. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Hiſt. l. 4. c. 15. Rom. 14. Gal 4. 5. Col.</hi> 2.</note> that glorious <hi>Martyr Polycarpus. Theſe men</hi> (ſay they) <hi>are ignorant that we cannot ever leave Chriſt who ſuffered for the ſalvation of the whole world nor can we worſhip any other. For him we adore as the Son of God; as for the Martyrs, we worthily love them as diſciples and imitators of him their Lord, for their inſuperable affection toward their King and Maſter, whoſe partners alſo we deſire to be, and to become their diſciples.</hi> And thus much they might eaſily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer themſelves out of our <hi>Church Liturgy,</hi> where there is no one word in any <hi>office</hi> appointed for any <hi>Saints day,</hi> that gives the leaſt ground or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to this ſcruple.</p>
            <p>The other imputation of <hi>Iudaiſme</hi> which they taxe us with, becauſe we ſtyle our Chriſtian feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valls, <hi>holy dayes,</hi> hath as weake a foundation as the former. For I willingly grant them what they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge for the countenancing of this objection, That now under the Goſpell the <hi>difference</hi> of <hi>times</hi> and <hi>dayes</hi> is no leſſe taken away then of <hi>meates;</hi> That is, as we have now no <hi>meats</hi> that are <hi>uncleane</hi> either in themſelves, or by reaſon of any poſitive precept given to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> but that they may bee eaten with <hi>thankſgiving;</hi> ſo neither is there any <hi>day</hi> or <hi>time</hi> which in <hi>it ſelfe,</hi> or by reaſon of any ſuch <hi>Iudaicall precept,</hi> is now to be accounted more <hi>holy</hi> then others; all this is evident from the places which they alleadge for this purpoſe: Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:10649:36"/>
wee conclude, that none of the <hi>Iewiſh Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valls</hi> (not the <hi>Sabbath</hi> it ſelfe) ought to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> nor (which is more) any <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Feſtivall</hi> to be obſerved, after the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or with their rites and Ceremonies. And this may juſtly taxe them who ſtand either for the <hi>Iewiſh Sabbath,</hi> or which turne the <hi>Lords day</hi> into a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> exacting the ſame <hi>ſtrictneſſe</hi> of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance in regard of the outward <hi>Ceremoniall Reſt.</hi> But it can no way prejudice the Church, in conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crating dayes to the ſervice of God, or in account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them (though in themſelves, and ſetting aſide the Ordinance of the Church, they are all alike <note place="margin">See p. 31.</note> yet) in relation to the duties to be performed in them, more holy then others. And this they muſt grant, unleſſe they will affirme one of theſe three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the <hi>workes</hi> of God now under the <note place="margin">1</note> 
               <hi>Goſpel</hi> are not ſo <hi>great,</hi> ſo <hi>glorious,</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo worthy of <hi>ſet times</hi> for their <hi>ſolemne remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,</hi> as heretofore under the <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or that the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> hath now leſſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer <note place="margin">2</note> in appointing dayes for the <hi>ſolemne worſhip</hi> of God, in relation to thoſe <hi>glorious works</hi> of his, then the <hi>Iewiſh Synagogue</hi> once had.</p>
            <p>Or laſtly, That the worſhip which wee Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans now performe to God is not ſo <hi>holy,</hi> as that <note place="margin">3</note> in the time of the <hi>Iewiſh Synagogue,</hi> and ſo leſſe able to <hi>ſanctifie</hi> the dayes in which they are per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <p>But every one of theſe being moſt abſurd; I conclude, that to <hi>conſecrate</hi> certaine dayes, beſides
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:10649:36"/>
the <hi>Lords day,</hi> to the ſolemne worſhip of God, in memory of his <hi>ſpeciall bleſsings</hi> vouchſafed to the Church on ſuch dayes, and to account ſuch dayes, ſo conſecrated, <hi>more holy</hi> then others, is lawfull and free from all ſuperſtition and Judaiſme. And however, that they who would faine affixe ſo <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary holineſſe</hi> to the <hi>Lords day,</hi> ſhould of all men have abſtained from this laſt imputation, till they had better proved the immediately divine inſtitution of the Lords day.</p>
            <p>But I have too long digreſſed; yet not without cauſe, in as much as they, who ſeeme ſo zealous for the giving to God his due time, refuſe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding to give him that, which the <hi>regular piety</hi> of the <hi>Ancient</hi> and our owne <hi>Mother Church</hi> hath ever, upon ſo ſound reaſon, conſecrated to him. I returne now to anſwere another objection which they frame againſt the extending of our <hi>Chriſtian liberty,</hi> to the uſe of <hi>recreations</hi> on the <hi>Lords day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The liberty of Chriſtians (ſay they) ought to be <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> and not in <hi>carnall</hi> and <hi>common</hi> things; and therefore cannot bee extended to patronize <hi>recreations,</hi> or <hi>ordinary labours</hi> on the <hi>Sunday,</hi> but that they are as <hi>unlawfull</hi> on that day as ever they were on the <hi>Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwere, that Chriſtian liberty, as it reſpects the things from which we are freed, is not <hi>meerely ſpirituall,</hi> but extends it ſelfe, to <hi>carnall</hi> and <hi>common</hi> things alſo; for thereby wee are freed not onely from the guilt, and condemnation of ſinne, and the raigning power of it, which are things <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vituall;</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:10649:37"/>
but alſo from the ſervitude of the <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Law,</hi> which among other reſpects which it had, was as a <hi>Schoole-Maſter,</hi> or <hi>Tutour,</hi> whereby the Church in her nonage or infancie, was to bee kept under the <hi>Elements of the world,</hi> (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 3.</note> calls them) that is, tyed to the obſervation of <hi>dayes, and moneths, and yeares and meates and drinks;</hi> which being in themſelves indifferent, were yet forbidden the Church of thoſe times, that their <hi>bondage</hi> under theſe might nouriſh in them the hope and expectation of the promiſed <hi>Meſsias,</hi> in whom they were to have deliverance, and ſo lead, or rather drive them to beleeve in Him. Now <hi>when the fulneſſe of time was come,</hi> and that Chriſt was exhibited, the Church being then no longer <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 4.</note> 
               <hi>under age,</hi> is not ſubject to thoſe obſervances, but for any tye of that <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> now upon it, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes the <hi>free uſe</hi> and <hi>exerciſe</hi> of theſe things as <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</hi> As then there were many things, which, in themſelves, and to us, now are indifferent, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to the Jewes; ſo as they might not eate of all <hi>meates,</hi> though otherwiſe wholſome, they might not weare all kinde of <hi>garments,</hi> though uſefull and profitable, &amp;c. So there were ſome <hi>workes</hi> in themſelves not ſinfull, nor at other times unlawfull, prohibited to be done at ſome <hi>ſpeciall times,</hi> in regard of the peculiar obſervance then due to thoſe <hi>times,</hi> which now, when thoſe times ceaſe to be obſerved, can by no meanes bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſinfull, or unlawfull. Granting therefore that <hi>ordinary labours,</hi> and all <hi>bodily recreations</hi> were on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> unlawfull, yet being in themſelves
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:10649:37"/>
not ſinfull, and ſo under the Goſpell indifferent, they cannot be ſo upon our <hi>Sunday.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwere further, that I know no reaſon why <hi>honeſt recreations, moderate feaſting,</hi> and ſuch like expreſſions of rejoycing, may not fitly be counted a part of the externall obſervance and ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this day; in as much as it is ſolemnized in memory of the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> and ſo our <hi>redemption</hi> fully wrought, to which we may (with S. <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> apply that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, This is the Day which the Lord hath made, wee will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and be glad in it.</hi> And as on the day of his <hi>Paſsion,</hi> and other dayes appointed for <hi>ſolemne hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation,</hi> we expreſſe the ſorrow of our hearts by our mourning and neglected <hi>attire,</hi> by <hi>Faſting,</hi> and abridging our ſelves of thoſe delights, which uſe to refreſh our natures; at which times <hi>The voyce of the Vyoll, and of the Harpe, the voyce of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome, and the voyce of the Bride</hi> are unſeaſonable; ſo on the day of his <hi>reſurrection</hi> to expreſſe our joy, and rejoycing by our <hi>arraying</hi> our ſelves in our <hi>beſt attire,</hi> by <hi>Feaſting,</hi> and other acts of cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is moſt agreeable to the ſolemnity of that Day, Of which we may ſay in the words of <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> and <hi>Ezra, This Day is holy unto the Lord your God, mourne not nor weepe—but—eate of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nehem. 8. 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>fat, and drinke of the ſweet, and ſend portions to them for whom nothing is prepared, for this Day is holy unto the Lord.</hi> And however ſome men will have eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>faſting day</hi> a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and every <hi>Lords Day</hi> a <hi>faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing day</hi> (not allowing either the dreſſing, or libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall uſe of Gods creatures, and therefore judging it
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:10649:38"/>
inconvenient to celebrate marriages on that day) yet the Church of God in better times condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">Die Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nico jejuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re neſas ducimus, Tertull. de Cor. Mil. c. 3 co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cil. Gangr. Can. 18. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiag. 4. Can. 64. Iuſtellus in cod. Ca<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. not. in Can. 70.</note> 
               <hi>Faſting</hi> on the <hi>Lords Day</hi> as unlawfull, and moſt incongruous and diſagreeable to the uſe of that Day, which was ordained as a <hi>Feſtivall,</hi> and day of mirth and rejoycing: For which end alſo the Church in her moſt ancient times, had on that Day their <hi>Agapae</hi> or <hi>Love-feaſts,</hi> as for the refreſhing of the poore, and for the nouriſhing of mutuall love and amity, ſo alſo for the unanimous expreſſion of joy in all ſober mirth, and in the free (though temperate) uſe of Gods creatures. Upon which ground (doubtleſſe) wee may conclude the lawfulneſſe of the uſe of ſuch <hi>recreations, feaſtings,</hi> and other teſtifications of <hi>rejoycing</hi> upon the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> as are in themſelves <hi>honeſt,</hi> and are ſo uſed as they prove <hi>no hinderances</hi> to the ſervice of God, which is the proper <hi>worke</hi> of the Day.</p>
            <p>Beſides, even the <hi>Iewes</hi> themſelves (though out of ſuperſtition, they did for the moſt part over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe this Precept of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> abſtaining from thoſe things, which they might have done, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any violation of Gods commandement, yet) accounted their <hi>Sabbath</hi> a <hi>Feaſt,</hi> not a <hi>Faſt;</hi> a day of <hi>rejoycing,</hi> and not of <hi>ſorrow,</hi> or <hi>humiliation;</hi> and judged it not unlawfull to make <hi>Feaſts</hi> upon that Day, as is evident by that Feaſt made upon the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> by a chiefe <hi>Phariſee</hi> (one of their ſtricteſt <hi>Sabbatarians)</hi> whereat our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelfe (who <note place="margin">Luk. 14. 1.</note> was no <hi>Sabbath-breaker)</hi> vouchſafed his preſence among many others that were invited. And <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Addit. 4. in Exod. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Burgenſis</hi> (himſelfe a <hi>Iew)</hi> reports, that the <hi>Iewes</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:10649:38"/>
held themſelves bound to eate <hi>three meales</hi> that day, which on other dayes they uſed not. And <hi>Syranus</hi> (another of the ſame Nation) ſaith, That the <hi>Hebrew Doctors</hi> held that the word <hi>Remember</hi> was prefixed to this <hi>Commandement,</hi> that if they had any <hi>pretious garment,</hi> or any other thing of <hi>price,</hi> They ſhould <hi>remember</hi> to keepe it till the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> to give it at firſt a <hi>Sabbath-dayes wearing.</hi> I am not of their minde, but thinke that <hi>word</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed for higher, and more important reaſons: yet I verily beleeve that their conceit did ſpeak their uſuall cuſtome of apparelling themſelves in their <hi>moſt coſtly</hi> and <hi>beſt garments,</hi> as beſt befitting the joy of that <hi>high Feſtivall,</hi> which (as one hath well obſerved) hath this ſingular priviledge to be a day <note place="margin">Ainſworth in Gen. 2. 3.</note> of <hi>reſt</hi> and <hi>holineſſe;</hi> of delight, and Feaſting unto the world; and therefore (ſaith hee) <hi>This day is not deſcribed by evening and morning, as were the other ſix which conſiſted of light and darkneſſe: but</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay 60 20 Rev. 21. 25</note> 
               <hi>this is all day, or light, figuring out our perpetuall joyes.</hi> And, no queſtion, but, that Day which was the memoriall of Gods <hi>reſting</hi> from his <hi>worke,</hi> when <hi>he rejoyced in the works of his hands,</hi> (ſo the <hi>Chaldee Paraphraſt</hi> expounds Gods <hi>reſting on the ſeaventh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 104. 31 Gen. 2. 2.</note> 
               <hi>day)</hi> and of the <hi>deliverance</hi> from the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Bondage was celebrated with <hi>mirth,</hi> and <hi>rejoyoing:</hi> ſo that I can hardly be induced to thinke, that on their <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, they were bound to abſtaine from all kinde of <hi>recreations,</hi> but that they did, or, at leaſt, might uſe ſuch expreſſions of joy &amp; mirth, as at their other <hi>Feſtivalls</hi> were uſuall among them; as feaſting, ſinging, dancing, and the like:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:10649:39"/>
which, I conceive, were no way forbidden in the <hi>commandement,</hi> which onely ſeemes to ayme at <hi>workes of toyle</hi> or ſuch as are <hi>ſervile,</hi> or undertaken for profit or gaine, or at leaſt that might hinder them in the ſervice of God: and not to exclude all <hi>recreations,</hi> which (though they may, haply, in a large ſenſe be termed <hi>workes,</hi> yet) being ſuch as doe <hi>refreſh,</hi> not <hi>weary</hi> nature, and being ſo uſed, as that the worſhip of God might notwithſtanding be duly and ſolemnly performed, cannot be ſaid to croſſe the intent of the <hi>Law,</hi> which was the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and ſolemne ſervice of God, and the teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their freedome from <hi>Egyptian</hi> ſervitude.</p>
            <p>But let this paſſe as a private conceit, yet ſure I am, that <hi>Toſtatus</hi> (whom Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> approves) <note place="margin">Toſtatus Qu. 12. in Exod. <hi>Exo.</hi> 16. 29</note> ſaith, <hi>They were not bound to attend all the day upon Gods ſervice.</hi> And the ſame Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe words: <hi>Abide yee every man in his place; Let no man goe out of his place on the ſeaventh day,</hi> ſaith, <hi>They were not to goe forth, that is, with intent to gather Manna, which lay round about the Hoaſt, or to doe any other buſineſſe: they were not forbidden all kinde of walking, and going out for their ſolace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation.</hi> Certainly then Chriſtians cannot juſtly be blamed, if on the <hi>Lords day</hi> God be ſolemnly and decently ſerved at fit times, and no other worke entertained to the hinderance of this, though <hi>every moment</hi> of that Day be not ſpent in performance of the acts of Gods worſhip, nor the vacant ſpace obſerved with a <hi>ſuperſtitious reſt,</hi> which ſhall exclude all other works, and all, even <hi>lawfull recreations,</hi> which to exact at the hands of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:10649:39"/>
Chriſtians, what is it but to ſurpaſſe the Jewes in ſuperſtition about the Sabbath, and having only changed the day, in diſhonour and contempt of the Jewes, to require notwithſtanding the ſame Ceremoniality of obſervance? which what fruits it hath had, or can have, I cannot ſee, ſave the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendring of endleſſe ſcruples, and inextricable doubts, and the needleſſe wounding of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of many well-meaning people, when they have no ſure guide to direct their practiſe, and when that which is required is beyond the ability of mortalls to performe. For I will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to the conſciences of theſe rigid <hi>Task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters,</hi> whether ever they, or any other did yet, or could poſſibly keepe the <hi>Lords day,</hi> in that <hi>ſtrict manner</hi> as they urge it? But, haply this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle moves them, who being taught that it is <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible</hi> to keepe Gods <hi>Commandements,</hi> will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the rather be induced to thinke, it is <hi>comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> becauſe they are unable to keepe it. Yet ſure our <hi>Saviour</hi> would never have ſtiled his <hi>yoke eaſie,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 30.</note> and his burthen <hi>light,</hi> had this ſtrict obſervance of the <hi>Lords Day</hi> beene a part of it, and <hi>Gods Commandements,</hi> ſo as hee now under the Goſpel requires them to bee done, and with the aſſiſtance of his grace, wherewith he ſeconds them (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever men raſhly ſay of them) <hi>are not grievous,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5. 3..</note> much leſſe impoſſible to be done.</p>
            <p>To ſet downe briefly and plainely, that which in more words hath beene hitherto driven at: and it is but this. There are three things conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the <hi>Sunday,</hi> or <hi>Lords day.</hi> 1. <hi>A Day.</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:10649:40"/>
2. <hi>That Day.</hi> 3. <hi>The manner of celebrating it.</hi> The firſt is Gods immediate precept. The other two not ſo, but mediate and by the <hi>power</hi> he hath given to his <hi>Church.</hi> Firſt God commanded <hi>ſome time</hi> wherein men ſetting aſide all worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and thoughts, ſhould apply themſelves to the duties of his ſolemne and publique Worſhip, and this is the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> or that which is <hi>Morall,</hi> in the <hi>fourth Commandement.</hi> Secondly, the <hi>Cuſtome</hi> or <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> warranted by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> practiſe, and the honour vouchſafed unto it by our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelfe, determined that time or day to the <hi>Sunday,</hi> or firſt day of the week; &amp; ſecondly, preſcribed <hi>how</hi> and <hi>when,</hi> for the decent time and manner of performing thoſe duties.</p>
            <p>By theſe our liberty is limited, which muſt not be (without neceſſity) extended to the violation of either of them: Hence then, 1. Hee ſinnes that doth not ſeparate <hi>ſome time</hi> for God, &amp;c. as violating the <hi>immediate precept</hi> of GOD in the <hi>fourth Commandement.</hi> 2. He ſinnes no leſſe, that for this end obſerves not the <hi>Sunday,</hi> and that in that decent manner, which the nature of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the authority of the <hi>Church</hi> hath enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and this hee doth in two reſpects. Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee violates Gods <hi>mediate Command,</hi> who hath authorized the Church in his right, and by his power to ordaine ſuch things; ſo that, to neglect the Church, in this caſe is, to neglect God. Secondly, becauſe the <hi>immediate Precept</hi> of God is wrapt up in the <hi>Precept of the Church:</hi> by which, that which by him was left <hi>indefinite,</hi> is defined, and determined.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:10649:40"/>
But that liberty either for ordinary <hi>labours,</hi> or honeſt <hi>recreations,</hi> which may ſtand with the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of theſe <hi>Precepts,</hi> no man can juſtly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſinfull, unleſſe hee can produce (not the phanſies of ſome Zelotes, or the opinion of this or that man, though accounted never ſo good or learned, but) ſome other <hi>Precept</hi> given by God, or thoſe whom God hath commanded us to obey: For it is an undoubted Maxime, which the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> delivers; <hi>Where no Law is, there is no tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4 15.</note> The prohibition of the Law only is that, whereby things are exempted from our power and liberty, which otherwiſe (except in caſe of ſcandall) remaines intire.</p>
            <p>And this alone is ſufficient to terminate this <hi>Diſpute,</hi> upon which wee will joyne iſſue with thoſe that are contrary minded, being not more confident that they can ſhew no <hi>binding Precept</hi> for the reſtraining of our <hi>Chriſtian liberty</hi> in this caſe, then willing to retract what hath beene ſaid, if they ſhall prove themſelves able to doe it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
