<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The negotiations of Thomas Woolsey, the great Cardinall of England containing his life and death, viz. (1) the originall of his promotion, (2) the continuance in his magnificence, (3) his fall, death, and buriall / composed by one of his owne servants, being his gentleman-vsher.</title>
            <author>Cavendish, George, 1500-1561?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 256 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-10">2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1619</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223198</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12043163</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12043163</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53022</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A69688)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53022)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 86:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The negotiations of Thomas Woolsey, the great Cardinall of England containing his life and death, viz. (1) the originall of his promotion, (2) the continuance in his magnificence, (3) his fall, death, and buriall / composed by one of his owne servants, being his gentleman-vsher.</title>
                  <author>Cavendish, George, 1500-1561?</author>
                  <author>Cavendish, William, Sir, 1505?-1557.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13], 118 p., [4] leaves of plates : ill., port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Sheeres,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Formerly attributed to Sir William Cavendish.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [8].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wolsey, Thomas, 1475?-1530.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:53022:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>CARDINAL WOLSEY. OB. 1330. FROM THE ORIGINAL OF HOLBEIN. IN THE COLLECTION AT CHRIST CHURCH, OXFORD.</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Cardinal Wolsey</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53022:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NEGOTIATIONS OF <hi>THOMAS WOOLSEY,</hi> The great Cardinall of <hi>England,</hi> Containing his life and Death, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The Originall of his promotion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Continuance in his Magnificence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>His Fall, Death, and Buriall.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Compoſed by one of his owne Servants, being his Gentleman-Vſher.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>William Sheeres.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:53022:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53022:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ſeemeth no wiſedome to credit every light tale, blazed abroad in the mouthes of vulgars, for wee daily heare how with their blaſphemous Trumpe they ſpread abroad innumerable Lyes, without either ſhame or honeſty, which <hi>prima facie</hi> ſheweth forth a viſage of Truth, as though it were an abſolute verity, though indeed nothing leſſe; And amongſt the better ſort, thoſe bablings are of no validity.</p>
            <p>I have read the allegations of divers worthy Authours againſt ſuch falſe ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and opinions of the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who delight in nothing more, then to heare ſtrange things, and to ſee new al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations of Authority, rejoycing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb facs="tcp:53022:3"/>
in ſuch Novelties, which afterwards do produce Repentance. Thus may all men of underſtanding conceive the madneſs of the rude multitude, and not give too much credence to every ſudden rumour, untill the truth be perfectly knowne by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of ſome approved and credible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that commonly have the beſt Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
            <p>I have heard, and alſo ſeen ſet forth in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers printed Books, ſome untrue imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, after the death of divers perſons (who in their lives were in great eſtimation) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented rather to bring their honeſt names in queſtion then otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as I intend to write here ſome ſpeciall proceedings of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Woolſey,</hi> the great Archbiſhop, his aſcending unto honour and great promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his continuance in it, and ſudden fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from the ſame. A great part whereof ſhall be of mine owne knowledge, and ſome part from credible perſons infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations.</p>
            <p>This Cardinall was my Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<pb facs="tcp:53022:3"/>
whom in his life-time I ſerved, and ſo remained with him in his fall continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, during the time of all his troubles, both in the South and North parts untill hee dyed. In all which time I punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally obſerved all his demeanours, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in his great Triumph and glorious eſtate.</p>
            <p>And ſince his departure I have heard divers ſurmiſed and imagined Tales con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his proceedings, and dealings, which I my ſelfe have certainly knowne to bee moſt untrue, unto which I could have ſufficiently anſwered according to truth; But conceiving it to be much better to be ſilent, then to reply againſt their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, whereby I might perhaps have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kindled a great flame of diſpleaſure, then have quenched one ſparke of their untrue reports; Therefore I did referre the truth thereof to the Almighty, who knows the truth of all things.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, whatſoever any man hath conceived of him in his life, or ſince his death; Thus much I dare ſay without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb facs="tcp:53022:4"/>
to any, that in my judgement I never ſaw this Realme in better obedience, and quiet, then it was in the time of his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, nor Iuſtice better adminiſtred without partiality, as I could juſtly prove, if I ſhould not be taxed with too much affection.</p>
            <p>I will therefore here deſiſt to ſpeake any further by the way of Apologie, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed. Now to ſpeake of his Originall, and aſcending through Fortunes favour to high dignity and abundance of wealth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:53022:4"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho pleaſeth to reade this Hiſtory adviſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may well perceive the immutability of honour, the tottering ſtate of earthly Dignity, the deceipt of flattering friends, and the inſtability of Princes favours.</p>
            <p>This great Cardinall having experience of all this, witneſſe his fleeting from Honour, the loſſe of Friends, Riches and Dignities, being forgotten of his Prince, whilſt Fortune ſmiled, having ſaciety of all theſe; And ſhee bending her brow, deprived him of all Terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall Joyes, who by twenty yeares ſtudy and paines, had obtained ſo great wealth and dignitie, and in leſſe then one yeare loſt all.</p>
            <p>And thus was his honour laid in the Duſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:53022:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53022:5"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. I.</label> OF the Cardinall his Originall, and who hee was.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. II.</label> Of the Cardinall his ſpeedy diſpatch to the Emperous <hi>Maximilian.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. III.</label> Of King <hi>Henry</hi> his invading <hi>France</hi> in his owne perſon with the Cardinals aſſiſtance.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. IV.</label> The Kings promoting his Almoner being made Cardinall and Lord Chancellor of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. V.</label> Of the Order and Offices of his Houſe and Chappell:</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:53022:6"/>
                  <label>CHAP. VI.</label> Of his ſecond Embaſſage to the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VII.</label> Of the manner of his going to <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VIII.</label> Of the Cardinals magnificence in his houſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. IX.</label> Of the originall Inſtrument of the Cardinals fall, Miſtris <hi>Anne Bullen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. X.</label> Of Miſtris <hi>Anne Bullen</hi> her favour with the King.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XI.</label> Of the variance betweene the <hi>French</hi> King and the Duke of <hi>Burbon,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XII.</label> Of the Duke of <hi>Burbons</hi> ſtratagem and victory wherein the <hi>French</hi> King was taken priſoner.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XIII.</label> Of the <hi>French</hi> Kings redemption out of captivity, and the Cardinals Embaſſage into <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:53022:6"/>
                  <label>CHAP. XIV.</label> Of the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadours entertainement and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XV.</label> Of the Kings diſcovery of his love to Miſtris <hi>Anne Bullen</hi> to the Cardinall with his diſlike, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XVI.</label> A new Court erected to determine the Kings caſe, two Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals being Iudges, and of the iſſue.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XVII.</label> Of certaine paſſages conducing to the Cardinals fall.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XVIII.</label> The Cardinall accuſed of high treaſon in the Parliament houſe, and Maſter <hi>Cromwels</hi> defence for him.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XIX.</label> Of the Cardinals fall, and how hee was arreſted of high treaſon.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. XX.</label> Of the Cardinals entertainement by the Earle of <hi>Shrewſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> and of his death and buriall.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:53022:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53022:7"/>
            <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the Cardinall his Originall, and who he was.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ruth it is Cardinall <hi>Woolſey</hi> was an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt poore mans ſonne in the towne of <hi>Ipſwich</hi> in the county of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> and there borne, who being but a child was very apt to learne, wherefore by means of his parents and other his good friends, hee was maintained at the Vniverſitie of <hi>Oxford,</hi> where in a ſhort time hee proſpered ſo well, that in a ſmall time (as hee told mee with his owne mouth) he was made Batchelour of Arts when he was but fifteene yeares of age, and was moſt commonly called the Boy Batchelour. Thus proſpering <note place="margin">He was Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelour of Arts at 15. years of Age.</note> in learning, he was made fellow of <hi>Magdalene</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> after that he was made Maſter of <hi>Magdalene</hi> Schoole, at which time were the Lord Marqueſſe <hi>Dorſet</hi> ſons there at Schoole, committing unto him as well their education as their inſtructions and learning.</p>
            <p>It pleaſed this Lord Marqueſſe againſt <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> to ſend as well for the Schoolemaſter as for the Schollers home
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53022:8"/>
to his houſe, for their recreation in that pleaſant and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Forreſt. They being a while there, the Lord Marqueſſe their Father perceiving them to bee well im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in learning for the time. Hee was ſo well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, that he having a Benefice in his gift (being at that preſent voyd) gave the Schoole Maſter the ſame, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his diligence. After <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> at his departure to the Vniverſity, and hee having the preſentation thereof repaired to the ordinary for his Inſtitution. And being then furniſhed with all his Inſtruments at the Ordinaries hands for his preferment made haſt without any further delay to his Benefice to take poſſeſſion thereof. Now you ſhall underſtand that the Schoole-maſter had not beene long there, but one Sir <hi>Iames Pawlet</hi> Knight dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Country thereabouts, tooke an occaſion of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure againſt him, but upon what ground I know not; Inſomuch that Sir <hi>Iames</hi> was ſo bold as to ſet the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter by the heeles during his diſpleaſure, which affront was afterwards neither forgotten, nor forgiven; For when the Schoolemaſter mounted ſo high as to be Lord Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> hee was not forgetfull of his old diſpleaſure moſt cruelly miniſtred unto him by Sir <hi>Iames,</hi> but ſent for him, and after a very ſharpe reproofe enjoyned him not to depart out of <hi>London</hi> without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe firſt obtained, ſo that he continued in the middle Temple the ſpace of five or ſix yeares, who afterwards lay in the Gatehouſe next the Stayres, which he re-edefied and ſumptuouſly beautified the ſame all over on the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, with the Cardinalls Armes, his hat, his Cognizance and Badges, with other deviſes in ſo glorious a manner as hee thought thereby to have appeaſed his old diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>This may be a good preſident for men in Authoritie, which worke their owne wills without wit, to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that greatneſſe may decay. And thoſe whom they doe puniſh more of humour then juſtice may afterwards he advanced to great honour (as this Cardinall was) and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53022:8"/>
they abaſed as low as this Sir <hi>Iames</hi> was, which ſeeke revenge. Who would have thought that when Sir <hi>Iam's Pawlet</hi> puniſhed this poore Schoolemaſter that ever hee ſhould have mounted to ſo great dignitie as to bee Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour of <hi>England,</hi> conſidering his meane parentage and friends. Theſe be the wonderfull workes of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. And I would wiſh that all men in authoritie would feare God in all ages in the time of their triumph and greatneſſe. conſidering that advancement and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie are not permanent, but many times ſlide and vaniſh ſuddenly away, as Princes pleaſures alters and change, or as all living creatures muſt of neceſſitie pay the debt due to nature which no earthly creature can reſiſt.</p>
            <p>Shortly after it chanced the ſayd Lord Marqueſſe dyed, after whoſe deceaſe the Schoole-maſter thinking him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe but a weake beneficed man, and that hee had left his fellowſhip in the Colledge, for (as I underſtand) if a fellow of that houſe be once promoted to a Benefice, hee ſhall by the rules of the ſame houſe bee diſmiſſed of his fellowſhip; and now being alſo deſtitute of his ſinguler good Lord, as well as of his fellowſhip which was moſt of his reliefe; thought long to be provided of ſome other helpe to defende him from all ſuch ſtormes as hee might meet with. In his travell thereabouts hee grew acquainted with a very great and ancient Knight, who had a great place in <hi>Callis</hi> under King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh. This Knight he ſerved and behaved himſelfe ſo diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that he obtained the ſpeciall favour of his ſaid Maſter. In ſo much that for his wit and gravitie hee committed all the care and charge of his ſaid office to his ſaid Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine. And as I underſtand his office was the Treaſurer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>Callis,</hi> who in regard of his great age ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was diſcharged of his ſaid office, and ſo returned into <hi>England,</hi> intending to live a more private life. But through his inſtant labour and good favour his Chaplaine was preferred to bee the Kings Chaplaine. And when hee had once caſt Anchor in the Port of promotion how
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53022:9"/>
hee then beſtirred himſelfe I ſhall now declare.</p>
            <p>Hee having then juſt occaſion to be daily in ſight of the King in his Cloſet, not ſpending the reſt of the day in idleneſſe would attend thoſe men whom hee thought to beare moſt rule in the councell, and were moſt in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with the King which at that time was Doctor <hi>Fox</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> and Lord Privie Seale; And alſo Sir <hi>Thomas Lovell</hi> Knight, a very ſage and wiſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour being Maſter of the Wardes and Conſtable of the Tower.</p>
            <p>Theſe ancient and grave Councellours in proceſſe of time perceiving this Chaplaine to be a man of a very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute wit, thought him a meete Inſtrument to be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in greater affaires.</p>
            <p>Not long after it happened that the King had an ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent occaſion to ſend an Ambaſſadour to <hi>Maximillian</hi> the Emperour, who lay at that preſent in the Low Countries at <hi>Flanders</hi> and not farre from <hi>Callis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Lovell</hi> whom the King moſt eſteemed as the chiefeſt of his Counſell, one day adviſing and debating with themſelves upon this Ambaſſage; and by this time they ſaw they had a convenient occaſion to preferre the Kings Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, whoſe excellent eloquence and learning they high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commended unto the Kings highneſſe, who giving eare unto them, and being a Prince of an excellent judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and modeſty, hee commanded them to bring his Chaplaine (whom they ſo commended) before his Grace, and being come, his Majeſtie (to prove his ability) entered into diſcourſe with him, concerning matters of State, whereby the King had ſo well informed himſelfe that he found him to be a man of a ſharpe with and of ſuch excellent parts, that hee thought him worthy to bee put in truſt with matters of greater conſequence.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:53022:9"/>
            <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the Cardinall his ſpeedy diſpatch in his firſt Ambaſſage to the Emperour Maximillian.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He King being now reſolved to imploy him in this Ambaſſage commanded him thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to prepare himſelfe for his journey; and for his diſpatch wiſht him to repaire to his Grace and his Councell, of whom he ſhould receive his Commiſſion and inſtruction. By meanes whereof hee had then a fit occaſion to repaire from time to time into the Kings preſence, who had thereby daily experience of his ſingular wiſedome and ſound judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thus having his diſpatch, he tooke his leave of the King at <hi>Richmond,</hi> about foure of the clocke in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, where he lancheth forth in <hi>Graves-end Barge</hi> with a proſperous winde and tyde; and his happie ſpeed was ſuch, that hee arrived at <hi>Graves-end</hi> in little more then three houres: where he tarried no longer then the Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horſes were provided, and he travelled ſo ſpeedily, that he came to <hi>Dover</hi> the next morning, where the Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers were under ſaile to paſſe to <hi>Callis;</hi> So that long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noone he arrived there, and having Poſt-horſes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, departed from thence without tarrying, making ſuch haſtie ſpeede that he was that night with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: who underſtanding of the arrivall of the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Ambaſſadour, would in no wiſe delay time but ſent for him incontinently, for his affection to the King of <hi>England</hi> was ſuch, that he was glad of any opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to doe him a curteſie.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Ambaſſadour</hi> declares the ſumme of his Embaſſie unto the Emperour, of whom he craved ſpeedie expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was granted him, ſo that the next day hee was clearely diſpatched, and all the Kings requeſts fully accompliſhed and granted. At which time hee made no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53022:10"/>
further ſtay, but tooke Poſt-horſes that night and rode without intermiſſion to <hi>Callis,</hi> being conducted thither by divers Nobles appointed by the Emperour; and at the opening of the gates of <hi>Callis</hi> he came thither, where the Paſſengers were readie to returne for <hi>England:</hi> inſomuch that he arrived at <hi>Dover</hi> betweene tenne and eleaven of the clock in the fore-noone.</p>
            <p>And having Poſt-horſes in a readineſſe, came to the Court at <hi>Richmond</hi> that ſame night, where (taking his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe untill morning) he preſented himſelfe unto his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie at his firſt comming out of his Bed-chamber to his Cloſet to Maſſe, whom when he ſaw he checked for that he was not in his journey.</p>
            <p>Sir quoth hee, If it may pleaſe your Highneſſe, I have alreadie beene with the Emperour and diſpatched your affaires I truſt to your Graces contentation; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon preſented the King with his Letters of Credence from the Emperour. The King wondring at his ſpeedie returne (he being ſo well furniſhed with all his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings) for the preſent diſſembled his admiration and imagination in that matter, and demaunding of him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he encountred with his Purſevant which he ſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him with Letters, imagining him to be ſcarce out of <hi>London,</hi> which concerned very materiall paſſages which were omitted in their Conſultation, which the King ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſired ſhould have been diſpatched in his Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</p>
            <p>Yes forſooth (quoth he) I met with him yeſterday by the way, and though I had no knowledge thereof, yet notwithſtanding I have beene ſo bold (upon mine owne diſcretion) perceiving the matter to be very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsary, in that behalfe I diſpatched the ſame. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as I have beene ſo bold to exceede my Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I moſt humbly crave your Royall remiſſion and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
            <p>The King inwardly rejoycing, replyed, We doe not onely pardon you, but give you our Princely thankes,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53022:10"/>
both for your good exploit and happie expedition. And diſmiſsed him for that preſent, and bad him returne to him againe after dinner, for a further relation of his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage, and ſo the King went to Maſse.</p>
            <p>It is not to be doubted but this Ambaſsadour had all this while viſited his great Friends, the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Lovell;</hi> to whom he had declared the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of his Ambaſsage; and alſo his Majeſties commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of him did not a little rejoyce the worthy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, foraſmuch as he was of their preferment. And ſhortly after the King gave him for his diligent ſervice the Deanrie of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> which was in thoſe dayes one of the greateſt promotions that he gave under the degree of a Biſhop. And he grew more and more in eſtimation and authoritie, and was afterwards promoted to be <hi>Almaner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now not long after when Death (that favoureth no Eſtates, nor <hi>King</hi> nor <hi>Kezar)</hi> had taken away the wiſe King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Seaventh</hi> out of this preſent life; It was a wonder to ſee what practices and devices were then u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed about the young Prince <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eight;</hi> The great proviſion that was then made for the Funerall of the one, and for the Coronation of the other, by the now-Queene <hi>Katharine,</hi> and Mother after the Queenes High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that now is, whoſe vertuous life Ieſu long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
            <p>After the ſolemnizations and coſtly tryumphes, our naturall, young, couragious, luſty Prince, and Soveraigne Lord King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eight</hi> entring into his flower and luſty youth, tooke upon him the Royall Scepter and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Diademe of this fertile Nation, the two and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of Aprill, <hi>Anno Dom</hi> 1509. which at that time flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed with all abundance of riches, whereof the King was moſt ineſtimably furniſhed, called then the golden world.</p>
            <p>Now ſhortly after the <hi>Almaner</hi> ſeeing he had a plaine path-way to promotion, behaved himſelfe ſo politickly, that he was made one of the Kings Privie Councell, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53022:11"/>
increaſed in favour daily: to whom he gave a houſe at <hi>Bridewell</hi> neer <hi>Fleete-ſtreet,</hi> where he kept his houſe for his family, and ſo he daily attended upon the King being in ſpeciall favour.</p>
            <p>His ſentences in the Star-chamber were ever ſo pithie &amp; wittie, that upon all occaſions they aſſigned him for the fluent eloquence of his tongue, to be the Expoſitor to the King in all their proceedings. In whom the King recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo great content, that he called him ſtill nearer to his perſon; and the rather becauſe he was moſt ready to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Kings owne will and pleaſure, having no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Caſe.</p>
            <p>Now the King being young, and much given to his pleaſure, his old Councellors adviſed him to have recourſe ſometimes to the Councell about his weightie affaires; but the <hi>Almaner</hi> on the contrary, perſwaded him to mind his pleaſure, and he would take his care and charge upon himſelfe, (if his Majeſtie would countenance him with his authoritie) which the King liked well. And thus none was like to the <hi>Almaner</hi> in favour with the King.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of King</hi> Henries <hi>invading</hi> France <hi>in his owne perſon with the Cardinals aſſiſtance.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus the <hi>Almaner</hi> continuing in high favour, till at laſt many preſents, gifts, and rewards came in ſo plentifully, that I dare ſay he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nothing, for hee had all things in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance that might either pleaſe his fancie or inrich his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, for the times ſo favourably ſmiled upon him, but to what end you ſhall hereafter heare. Therefore let all men to whom fortune extendeth her favour and grace, take heed they truſt not her ſubtill and faire promiſes, for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour thereof ſhe carryeth an envious gall; for when
<pb facs="tcp:53022:11"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:53022:12"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Thomas Wolsey</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53022:12"/>
ſhe ſeeth her ſervant in higheſt authority, ſhe turneth her favour and pleaſant countenance into frownes.</p>
            <p>This Almoner clyming up Fortunes wheele, that no man was in eſtimation with the King but onely he for his witty qualities and wiſdome.</p>
            <p>Hee had an eſpeciall gift of Naturall Eloquence and a fyled tongue to pronounce the ſame, that hee was able <note place="margin">He was natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent.</note> therewith to perſwade and allure all men to his purpoſes, in the time of his continuance in fortunes favour.</p>
            <p>In the fift yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, it chanced that the Realme of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> was <note place="margin">King <hi>Henry</hi> in the fifth yeare of his raigne inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> at variance, but upon what ground or occaſion, I know not, Inſomuch that the King was fully reſolved in his owne perſon to invade <hi>France</hi> with a puiſſant Army; It was therefore thought very neceſſary, that his royall enterpriſes ſhould be ſpeedily provided and furniſhed in every degree, in things apt and convenient for the ſame; For expedition thereof the King thought no mans wit ſo meete for policie and painfull travell as the Almo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to whom he committed his whole affiance, and truſt therein; And he being nothing ſcrupulous in any thing <note place="margin">The King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieth upon the Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners policie.</note> that the King would command, although it ſeemed very difficult, tooke upon him the whole charge of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and proceeded ſo therein, that he brought all things to good effect in direct order for all manner of victuals and proviſion convenient for ſo noble a voyage and Army.</p>
            <p>All things being thus prepared by him in order, the King not intending to neglect or delay any time, but with noble and valiant courage to advance his royall enterprize, paſſed the Seas betweene <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Callis,</hi> where hee proſperouſly arrived. And after he had there made his arrivall, and landed all his proviſion and munition, and <note place="margin">He beſieged the ſtrong Towne of <hi>Turwine.</hi>
               </note> ſate in Conſultation about his weighty affaires marched forth in good order of battell, till he came to the ſtrong Towne of <hi>Turwine,</hi> to the which hee laid ſtrong ſiege, and made a ſharpe aſſault, ſo that in ſhort ſpace it was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53022:13"/>
yeelded unto him, unto which place the Emperour <hi>Maximillian</hi> reſorted unto him with a great Army like a mighty Prince, taking of the King wages.</p>
            <p>Thus after the King had taken this ſtrong Towne, and taken poſſeſſion thereof, &amp; ſet all things in good order for the defence and preſervation thereof to his Majeſties uſe, then hee retyred from thence, and marched towards <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">He beſiegeth the Towne? of <hi>Turney.</hi>
               </note> and there layd ſiege in like manner to which he gave ſo fierce aſſault, that the Enemies were conſtrained to render the Towne to his Majeſtie. At which time the King gave unto the Almoner the Biſhopricke of the ſame Sea towards his paines and diligence ſuſteined in that journey. And when he had eſtabliſhed all things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his princely minde and pleaſure, and furniſhed the ſame with men and Captaines of Warre for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Towne hee prepared for his returne to <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now you ſhall underſtand by the way, that whilſt the King was abſent with a great power in <hi>France</hi> the Scottiſh King invaded <hi>England</hi> againſt whom the <note place="margin">The Scots in the Kings ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence invade <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> Queene ſent a great Army, the Earle of Surrey being generall, where he overthrew the Scots at <hi>Blamſton</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hoddenfield,</hi> where the King of Scots was ſlaine with divers of his Nobility, and eighteene thouſand men, and they tooke all his munition for warre.</p>
            <p>By this time the King returned into <hi>England,</hi> and tooke with him divers Noble perſonages of <hi>France</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing priſoners; As the Duke of <hi>Longuido,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> with divers others that were taken in a skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh.</p>
            <p>And thus God gave him victory at home, and victory abroad, being in the fift yeere of his raigne, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> one thouſand five hundred and thirteene.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:53022:13"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Henry VIII</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:53022:14"/>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53022:14"/>
            <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>The Kings promoting his Almoner, being made Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, and Lord Chancellor of</hi> England.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He King being returned into <hi>England,</hi> the Sea of <hi>Lincolne</hi> became voyd by the death of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Smith</hi> late Biſhop there, which Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricke the King gave to the Almoner Elect of <hi>Turney,</hi> who was not negligent to take poſſeſſion thereof, but made all ſpeed for his Conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ſolemnization thereof being ended, hee found a way to get into his hands all his predeceſſors goods, whereof I have ſeene divers parts that furniſhed his houſe.</p>
            <p>It was not long after but Doctor <hi>Bambrige</hi> Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Yorke</hi> dyed at <hi>Rohan</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> being there the Kings Ambaſſadour, unto which Sea the King preſented the laſt new Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> ſo that he had three Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks in his hands at one time, all in one yeare given him. Then prepared he againe for his tranſlation from the Sea of Lincolne to that of <hi>Yorke,</hi> as he did before to his Inſtallation.</p>
            <p>After which Solemnization done, and being then Archbiſhop and <hi>Primus Angliae,</hi> thought himſelfe ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to compare with that of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon advance his Croſſes in the Courts, and every other place, aſwell in the Precinct and Iuriſdiction of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> as any other place; And foraſmuch as <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> claimeth a ſuperioritie over <hi>Yorke,</hi> aſwell as over any other Biſhopricke within <hi>England,</hi> and for that cauſe claimeth an acknowledgement, as in ancient obedience of <hi>Yorke</hi> to abate advancement of his Croſſes, to the Croſſes of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding <hi>Yorke</hi> not deſiſting to beare the ſame
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53022:15"/>
although <hi>Canterburie</hi> gave <hi>Yorke</hi> a cheeke for the ſame, and told him it was preſumption, by reaſon whereof there ingendered ſome grudge betweene them; But ſhortly after he obtained to be made Cardinall and <hi>Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus de Literis</hi> unto whom the Pope ſent the Cardinalls Cap, and certaine Bulls for his authority in that behalfe, whereupon he was Inſtalled at Weſtminſter in great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, which was executed by all biſhops with their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, Cappes, and other ornaments; And after all this he was made Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Canterbury</hi> who was the Chancellour was diſmiſſed.</p>
            <p>Now he being in the Chancelourſhip, and endowed with the promotions of Archbiſhop and Cardinall <hi>de Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera,</hi> thought himſelfe ſo fully furniſhed; that he was now able to ſurmount <hi>Canterbury</hi> in all Iuriſdictions; And in all Eccleſiaſtical powers to Convocate <hi>Canterbury</hi> and all other Biſhops, &amp; ſpiritual perſons to aſſemble at his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, where he would aſſigne and take upon him the converſion of all Miniſters, and others within their Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions, and viſited all the ſpirituall houſes in their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſſe, and all manner of ſpirituall Miniſters, as Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, Scribes, Apparators, and all other neceſſarie Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers to furniſh his Courts, and did convent by conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whom he pleaſed through this Realme and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and all other perſons to the glory of his Dignitie. Then had he two great Croſſes of ſilver, whereof one was of his Archbiſhopricke, and the other of his Legaſie, borne before him whereſoever he rode or went by two of the talleſt Prieſts that he could get in this Realme.</p>
            <p>And to the increaſe of his gaine he had in his hand the Biſhopricke of <hi>Durham,</hi> and S. <hi>Albons</hi> in Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum; Alſo when Doctor <hi>Fox</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> dyed, he did ſurrender <hi>Durham</hi> to the King, and took himſelfe to <hi>Winchester.</hi> He had alſo, as it were in Farme the Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricks of <hi>Bath, Worceſter,</hi> and <hi>Hereford,</hi> for the Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bents of them were ſtrangers. Hee had alſo attending upon him men of great poſseſſions, and the talleſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53022:15"/>
Yeomen for his guard in the Realme.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the Orders and Offices of his houſe and Chappell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd firſt for his Houſe you ſhall underſtand that he had in his Hall three Boards kept with three ſeverall Officers (that is to ſay) a Steward, that was alwayes a Prieſt, a Treaſurer, that was ever a Knight, and a Controller that was an Eſquire; Alſo a Confeſſor, a Doctor; Three Marſhalls, three Vſhers in the Hall, beſides two Almoners and Groomes.</p>
            <p>Then had he in the hall-kitchin two Clarkes, a Clarke Comptroller, and a Surveyor over the Dreſſer; A Clarke in the Spycerie which kept continually a Meſſe together in the Hall; Alſo he had in the Hall-kitchin two Cookes and labourers, and children, twelve perſons; Foure men of the Scullery, two yeomen of the Paſtry, with two other Paſt-layers under the yeomen.</p>
            <p>Then had he in his Kitchin a maſter Cooke, who went daily in Velvet or Satin, with a gold chaine, beſides two other Cookes, and ſix Labourers in the ſame Roome.</p>
            <p>In the Larder one Yeoman and a Groome; In the Scul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery one Yeoman and two Groomes; In the Buttery two yeomen, and two groomes; In the Ewry ſo many; In the Sellar, three Yeomen, three Pages; In the Chandery, two yeomen; In the Wayfary two yeomen; In the Wardrop of Beds, the Maſter of the Wardrop, and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty perſons beſides; in the Laundery, a yeoman and a groome, and thirteene Pages, two yeomen Purveyours, and a groome Purveyor; In the Bakehouſe two yeomen and groomes; In the Woodyard, one yeoman and a groome; In the Barne one yeoman; Porters at the Gate,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53022:16"/>
two Yeomen and two Groomes; A Yeoman in his Barge, and a Maſter of his Horſe; a Clarke of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and a Yeoman of the ſame; a Farrier, and a yeoman of the Stirrop; a Maltlour and ſixteene Groomes, every one of them keeping foure Geldings.</p>
            <p>Now will I declare unto you the Officers of his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell <note place="margin">The Officers of his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</note> and ſinging men of the ſame. Firſt hee had there a Deane, a great Divine, and a man of excellent learning, and a ſub-Deane a Repeatout of the Quire, a Goſpeller, an Epiſtler of the ſinging Prieſts, a Maſter of the children; In the Veſtrey a yeoman, and two groomes, beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Retainers that came thither at principall Feaſts.</p>
            <p>And for the furniture of his Chappell, it paſſeth my weake capacitie to declare the number of the coſtly Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, and rich Iewels that were occupied in the ſame; For I have ſeene in proceſſion about the Hall, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie foure rich Copes of one ſettle worne, beſides the rich Candleſticks, and other neceſſarie Ornaments to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now you ſhall underſtand that hee had two Croſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers, <note place="margin">Officersin his privie Chamber.</note> and two Pillar-bearers in his great Chamber, and his privie Chamber, all theſe perſons; The chiefe Chamberlaine, a Vice-chamberlaine, a gentleman Vſher, beſide one of his privie Chamber; Hee had alſo twelve Wayters, and ſix gentlemen Wayters; Alſo he had nine or tenne Lords, who had each of them two or three men to waite upon him, except the Earle of <hi>Darby</hi> who had five men.</p>
            <p>Then he had gentlemen-Cup-bearers, and Carvers, and of the Sewers, both of the great Chamber, and of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie chamber fortie perſons; Sixe yeomen Vſhers, eight groomes of his Chamber; Alſo he had of Almes, who were daily wayters of his Boord at Dinner; Twelve Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Chaplaines, beſides them of his, which I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver rehearſed; a Clarke of his Cloſet, and two Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and two clarkes of his Signet; Foure Councellours learned in the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53022:16"/>
And for that he was Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> it was neceſſarie to have officers of the Chancerie to attend him for the better furniture of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he had a Ryding Clarke, a clerke of the Crowne, a clarke of the Hamper, a Chafer; Then had hee a clarke of the Checke, aſwell upon the Chaplaines, as upon the yeomen of the Chamber; He had alſo foure Foot-men garniſhed with rich running Coates, whenſoever he had any journey. Then he had a Herauld of Armes, a Serje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant of armes; a Phiſitian, an Apothecarie; Foure Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrells, a keeper of his Tents, an Armourer; An Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of his Wards, an Inſtructor of his Wardrop of Roabes, a Keeper of his Chamber continually; Hee had alſo in his houſe a Surveyor of <hi>Yorke,</hi> a Clerke of the Greene-cloth. All theſe were daily attending downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying and upriſing. And at meat hee had Eight continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Boards for the Chamberlaines and gentlemen Officers, having a Meaſe of young Lords, and another of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; Beſides this, there was never a Gentleman or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, or other worthy perſon, but hee kept ſome two, ſome three perſons to waite upon them; And all other at the leaſt had one which did amount to a great number of perſons.</p>
            <p>Now having declared the order according to the Cheine Roll, uſe his houſe, and what Officers he had dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attending to furniſh the ſame, beſides retainers and other perſons being ſuitors dined in the Hall. And when ſhall wee ſee any more ſuch Subjects that ſhall keepe ſuch a Noble houſe; Therefore here is an end of his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the number of perſons in the Cheyne were Eight hundred perſons.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53022:17"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of his ſecond Embaſſage to the Emperour</hi> Charles <hi>the Fifth.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> After he was thus furniſhed in manner as I have before rehearſed unto you; Hee was ſent twice on Embaſſage to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, that now raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and Father to King <hi>Philip</hi> now, our Lord and Soveraigne; Foraſmuch as the old Emperour <hi>Maximillian</hi> was dead, and for divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther urgent occaſions touching his Majeſtie; It was thought fit that about ſuch weightie matters, and to ſo noble a Prince the Cardinall was moſt meete to be ſent on this Embaſſage, and he being one ready to take the charge thereof upon him, was furniſhed in every reſpect moſt like a great Prince, which was much to the honour of his Majeſtie, and of this Realme; For firſt he proceeded forth like to a Cardinall having all things correſpondent, his Gentlemen being very many in number were clothed in livery Coats of Crimſon Velvet of the beſt, and chaines of gold about their necks; And his yeomen and all his meane officers were clad in fine Scarlet guarded with blacke Velvet one hand breadth. Thus furniſhed, he was twice ſent in this manner to the Emperour in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> then lying at <hi>Bridges,</hi> whom he did moſt nobly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine, diſcharging all his owne charges, and his mens. There was no houſe in the Towne of <hi>Bridges,</hi> wherein any of my Lords Gentlemen were lodged or had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, but that the owners of the houſes were comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Emperours Officers upon the paine of their lives to take no money for any thing that the Cardinals men did take of any kind of victuals; No, although they were diſpoſed to make coſtly Banquets, further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53022:17"/>
their ſaid hoaſts that they ſhould want nothing which they honeſtly required, or deſired to have.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Emperours Officers every night went through the Towne from houſe to houſe, where any Engliſhmen had recourſe or lodged, and ſerved their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very for all night, which was done on this manner. Firſt the Officers brought into the houſe a Caſteele of fine Manchet, then two ſilver pots of Wine, and a pound of Sugar, white lights, and yellow lights, a Bowle of ſilver, and a Goblet to drinke in, and every night a ſtaffe Torch. This was their order of their Livery every night; And then in the morning when the Officers came to fetch away their ſtuffe, they would accompt for the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemens coſts the day before.</p>
            <p>Thus the Emperour entertained the Cardinall, and his traine during the time of his Embaſſie. And that done, he returned into <hi>England</hi> with great Triumph, being no leſſe in eſtimation with the King then he was before, but rather much more, for he encreaſed daily in the Kings favour by reaſon of wits and readineſſe to doe the King pleaſure in all things.</p>
            <p>In the one and twentieth yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighths raine, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1529. This Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth came into <hi>England,</hi> who was nobly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of the manner of his going to</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>Hall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow muſt I declare the manner of his going to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall in the Terme time. Firſt, when he came out of his privie Chamber, hee moſt commonly heard two Maſſes in his Chappell or Chamber. And I heard one of his Chaplaines ſay ſince (that was a man of credit, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53022:18"/>
excellent learning) that what buſineſſe ſoever the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall had in the day time, that hee never went to bed with any part of his ſervice unſaid; no not ſo much as one Collect, in which I thinke he deceived many a man: then going into his Chamber againe, hee demanded of ſome of his ſervants if they were in readineſse, and had furniſhed his chamber of Preſence, and wayting Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: he being then advertiſed, came out of his Privie Chamber about eight of the clocke, readie apparelled, and in Red like a Cardinall, his upper veſture was all of Scarlet, or elſe of fine Crimſon Taffata, or crimſon Sattin ingraned, his Pillion Scarlet, with a blacke Velvet tippet of Sables about his necke, holding in his hand, an Orenge the meate or ſubſtance thereof being taken out and filled againe with a part of Sponge, with Vineger and other Confections againſt peſtilent Aires, the which hee moſt commonly held to his noſe, when he came to the preſſes, or when he was peſtered with many ſuitors; And before him was borne the broad Seale of <hi>England,</hi> and the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls Hat, by ſome Lord, or ſome Gentleman of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip right ſolemnly; And as ſoone as he was entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Chamber of Preſence, where there were daily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on him aſwell Noblemen of this Realme, as other worthy Gentlemen of his owne Familie, his two great Croſſes were there attending upon him; Then cry the Gentlemen Vſhers that goe before him bare-headed. On Maſters before, and make roome for my Lord. Thus went he downe into the Hall with a Serjeant of Armes before him, bearing a great Maſe of Siluer, and two Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen carrying two great Plates of Silver; And when he came to the Hall doore there his Mule ſtood trapped all in crimſon Velvet, with a Saddle of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Then was attending him, when he was mounted his two Croſſe-bearers, his two Pillow-bearers, all upon great horſes, all in fine Scarlet, then he marched on with a traine of Gentrie, having foure Foot-men about him, bearing every one of them a Pole-axe in his hand; And
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53022:18"/>
thus paſſed he forth till he came to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and there alighted and went in this manner up to the Chancerie, and ſtayed a while at a Barre, made for him beneath the Chancery, and there he communed ſometimes with the Judges, and ſometimes with other perſons, and then went up to the Chancerie, and ſate there till eleven of the clocke, to heare ſuits, and to determine cauſes; And from thence he would goe into the Starre-chamber as occaſion ſerved him; hee neither ſpared high nor low, but did judge every one according to right.</p>
            <p>Every Sunday hee would reſort to the Court being then at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> with his former rehearſed traine and Triumph, taking his Barge at his owne ſtaires, furniſhed with Yeomen ſtanding upon the ſayles, and his Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men within and about, and landed at the three Cranes in the Vine-tree, and from thence he rode upon his Mule with his Croſſes, his Pillars, his Hat, and his broad Seale carryed before him on horſe-backe along Thames-ſtreet untill he came to Billingſgate, and there hee tooke his Barge, and ſo went to <hi>Greenwich,</hi> where hee was Nobly entertained of the Lords in the Kings houſe, being there with ſtaves in their hands, as the Treaſurer, Comptroller, with many others, and conveyed into the Kings Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſo went home againe in the like Triumph.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of the Cardinals magnificence in his houſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ee lived a long ſeaſon Ruling all things in this Realme appertaining to the King by his wiſedome, and all other matters of forraine Regions with whom the King had any occaſion to meddle. All Ambaſſadours of forraine Potentates were ever diſpoſed by the Cardinals wiſdome to whom they had continuall acceſſe for their diſpatch.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:53022:19"/>
His houſe was alwayes reſorted unto like a Kings houſe with Noblemen and Gentlemen; And when it <note place="margin">Great reſort to his houſe as to the King.</note> pleaſed the Kings Majeſtie (as many times it did) hee would for his recreation reſort unto the Cardinals houſe, againſt whoſe comming there wanted no preparation or goodly furnitures, with victuals of the fineſt ſort that could be had for money or friendſhip.</p>
            <p>Such pleaſures were here deviſed for the Kings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, <note place="margin">His enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of the King in a Maſque.</note> as could be invented or imagined; Banquets ſet with Maſquers and Mummers, in ſuch coſtly manner, that it was glorious to behold, there wanted no Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells meete to dance with the Maſquers, or to garniſh the place for the time with variety of other paſtimes. Then was there divers kinds of Muſick, and many choyce men and women Singers appointed to ſing, who had excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent voyces. I have ſeene the King come ſuddenly thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a Maſque, with a dozen Maſquers all in garments like Shepheards made of fine cloth of gold and ſilver wyre, and ſix Torch-bearers, beſides their drummers and others attending on them with Vizards, and clothed all in Sattin. And before his entring into the Hall, you ſhall underſtand that hee came by water to the water-gate without any noiſe, where were laid divers Chambers and Gunnes charged with ſhott, and at his landing they were diſcharged, which made ſuch a rattling noyſe in the Ayre, that it was like thunder; It made all the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Gentlemen and Ladies to muſe what it ſhould meane comming ſo ſuddenly, they ſitting quietly at a Banquet. In this ſort you ſhall underſtand, that the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles were ſet in the Chamber of Preſence covered, and my Lord Cardinall ſitting under his cloth of State, and there having all his ſervice alone; And then was there ſet a Lady and a Nobleman, a Gentleman and a Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, throughout all the Tables in the Chambers on the one ſide, which were made all joyning, as it were, but one Table. All which order was done by my Lord <hi>Sands,</hi> then Lord Chamberlaine to the King, and by Sir <hi>Henry</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53022:19"/>
               <hi>Guilford,</hi> then Comptroller of the Kings houſe.</p>
            <p>Then immediatly after this great ſhot of Gunnes, the Cardinall deſired the Lord Chamberlaine to ſee what it did meane, as though he knew nothing of the matter; They then looked out of the window into the Thames, and returning againe told him, that they thought they were Noblemen and ſtrangers arrived at the Bridge, and comming as Ambaſſadours from ſome forraine Prince; With that ſaid the Cardinall, I deſire you, becauſe you can ſpeake French, to take the paines to goe into the Hall, there to receive them into the Chamber, where they ſhall ſee us, and all thoſe Noble perſonages being merry at our Banquet, deſiring them to ſit downe with us, and take part of our Fare.</p>
            <p>Then went they incontinently into the Hall, where <note place="margin">The King &amp; his Company conducted into the chamber.</note> they were received with twenty Torches, and conveyed up into the Chamber with ſuch a number of Drums and Flutes, as I have ſeldome ſeene together at one time and place.</p>
            <p>Then at their arrivall into the Chamber, they went two and two together directly before the Cardinall where he ſate, and ſaluted them very reverently; To whom the Lord Chamberlaine for them ſaid; Sir, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they are ſtrangers, and cannot ſpeake Engliſh, they have deſired mee to declare unto you, that they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving underſtanding of this your triumphant Banquet, were aſſembled ſuch a number of faire Dames, they could doe no leſſe (under the ſupportation of your Grace) then to view as well their incomparable beauties, as to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company them at Mumchance, and after that to dance with them, ſo to beget their better acquaintance.</p>
            <p>And furthermore they require of your Grace, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to accompliſh this cauſe of their comming.</p>
            <p>When the Cardinall ſaid he was willing, and very well content they ſhould doe ſo.</p>
            <p>Then went the Maſquers and firſt ſaluted all the <note place="margin">The Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quers ſalute the Ladies.</note> Dames, and then returned to the moſt worthieſt, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53022:20"/>
there opened the great Cup of gold filled with crownes, and other peeces to caſt at.</p>
            <p>Thus peruſing all the Gentlewomen, of ſome they wonne, and to ſome they loſt. And having viewed all the Ladyes, they returned to the Cardinall with great Reverence, pouring downe all their gold, which was above two hundred crownes. At all quoth the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and caſting the Dye he wonne it, whereat was made <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall caſts at two hundred crownes.</note> great joy.</p>
            <p>Then quoth the Cardinall to my Lord Chamberlaine; I pray you goe tell them, that to me it ſeemeth that there ſhould be a Nobleman amongſt them, that better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to ſit in this place then I, to whom I ſhould glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurrender the ſame, according to my duty if I knew him.</p>
            <p>Then ſpake my Lord Chamberlaine to them in French, declaring my Lord Cardinalls words, and they rounding him againe in the eare, the Lord Chamberlaine ſaid unto my Lord Cardinall;</p>
            <p>Sir (quoth he) they confeſſe that among them is ſuch a Noble perſonage, whom if your Grace can point out from the reſt, he is contented to diſcloſe himſelfe, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of your place moſt willingly.</p>
            <p>With that the Cardinall taking good adviſe, went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and at the laſt (quoth he) it ſeemeth to mee, that the Gentleman with the blacke beard ſhould be he, and with that he roſe out of his Chaire, and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſame to the Gentleman with the blacke Beard, with the Cup in his hand; But the Cardinall was miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, for the perſon to whom he then offered his Chaire <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</note> was Sir <hi>Edward Nevill,</hi> a comely Knight, and of a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſonage, who did more reſemble his Majeſties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then any other in that Maſque.</p>
            <p>The King ſeeing the Cardinall ſo deceived in his choyce, could not forbeare laughing, but pulled downe his Vizard, and Sir <hi>Edward Nevills</hi> alſo, with ſuch a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant countenance and cheere, that all the Noble Eſtates
<pb facs="tcp:53022:20"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:53022:21"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Anne Boleyn</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53022:21"/>
deſired his Highneſſe to take his place; To whom the King made anſwer, that he would firſt goe and ſhift him; And thereupon went into the Cardinalls Bedchamber, where was a great fire prepared for him, and there hee new apparelled himſelfe with rich and Princely gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; And in the Kings abſence, the diſhes of the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet was cleane taken away, and the Tables covered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <note place="margin">The Tables furniſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with a new Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</note> with new and perfumed cloathes every man ſitting ſtill untill the Kings Majeſtie with his Maſquers came in among them, every man new apparelled.</p>
            <p>Then the King tooke his ſeat under the cloath of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, commanding every perſon to ſit ſtill as they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; And then came in a new Banquet before his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of two hundred diſhes, and ſo they paſſed the night in Banquetting, and dancing untill morning, which much rejoyced the Cardinall, to ſee his Soveraigne Lord ſo pleaſant at his houſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of the originall Instrument of the Cardinalls fall: Miſtris</hi> Anne Bullen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow you ſhall underſtand that the young Lord of <hi>Northumberland</hi> attended upon my Lord Cardinall, who when the Cardinall went to Court, would ever have conference with Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris <hi>Anne Bullen,</hi> who then was one of the Maides of Honour to Queene <hi>Katharine,</hi> inſomuch, that at laſt they were contracted together, which when the King heard, he was much moved thereat (for hee had a private affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to her himſelfe) which was not yet diſcovered to any, and then adviſed the Cardinall to ſend for the Earle of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> his Father, and take order to diſſolve the Contract made betweene the ſaid parties, which the Lord Cardinall did after a ſharpe reprehenſion, in regard
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53022:22"/>
he was Contracted without the King and his Fathers knowledge; Hee ſent for his Father, who came up to <hi>London</hi> very ſpeedily, and came firſt to my Lord Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, as all great Perſonages did, that in ſuch ſort were ſent for, of whom they were advertiſed of the cauſe of their ſending for; And when the Earle was come, hee <note place="margin">The Earle come to the Cardinall.</note> was preſently brought to the Cardinall into the Gallery. After whoſe meeting, my Lord Cardinall and he were in ſecret communication a long ſpace; after their long diſcourſe, and drinking a cup of Wine, the Earle depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and at his going away, he ſate downe at the Gallery end in the Hall upon a forme, and being ſet, called his Sonne unto him, and ſaid;</p>
            <p>Sonne (quoth he) even as thou art, and ever haſt been <note place="margin">His ſharpe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of his Sonne.</note> a proud, diſdainfull, and very unthrifty Maſter, ſo thou haſt now declared thy ſelfe, wherefore what joy, what pleaſure, what comfort, or what ſolace can I conceive in thee? That thus without diſcretion haſt abuſed thy ſelfe, having neither regard to me thy Naturall Father, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy naturall Soveraigne Lord, to whom all honeſt and loyall Subjects beare faithfull obedience, nor yet to the proſperitie of thy owne eſtate; But haſt ſo unadviſedly enſnared thy ſelfe to her for whom thou haſt purchaſed the Kings high diſpleaſure intollerable for any Subject to ſuſteine. And but that the King doth conſider the lightneſſe of thy head, and wilfull qualities of thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon his diſpleaſure and indignation, were ſufficient to caſt me, and all my poſteritie into utter ruine and deſtruction. But hee being my ſingular good Lord, and favourable Prince, and my Lord Cardinall my very good friend, hath, and doth cleerely excuſe me in thy lewdneſſe, and doe rather lament thy folly, then maligne thee, and hath adviſed an order to be taken for thee, to whom both I and you are more bound, then we conceive of. I pray to God that this may be a ſufficient Admonition unto thee, to uſe thy ſelfe more wiſely hereafter; For aſſure thy ſelfe, that if thou doſt not amend thy prodigalitie. Thou wilt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53022:22"/>
be the laſt Earle of our houſe; For thy naturall inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thou art Maſterfull and prodigall to conſume all that thy Progenitors have with great travell gathered and kept together with honour. But having the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie my ſingular good Lord, I truſt (I aſſure thee) ſo to order my ſucceſſion, that thou ſhalt conſume thereof but a little.</p>
            <p>For I doe not intend (I tell thee) truly to make thee <note place="margin">The Earle doth intend to diſ-inhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it him.</note> Heire, for (thankes be to God) I have more boyes, that I truſt will uſe themſelves much better, and prove more like to wiſe and honeſt men, of whom I will chooſe the moſt likely to ſucceed mee.</p>
            <p>Now good Maſters and Gentlemen (quoth he) unto <note place="margin">He ſpeakes to the ſervants.</note> us, it may be your chances hereafter, when I am dead, to ſee thoſe things that I have ſpoken to my Sonne prove as true as I now ſpeake them, yet in the meane time I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you all to be his friends, and tell him his faults in what he doth amiſſe, wherein you ſhall ſhew your ſelves friendly to him, and ſo I take my leave of you; And ſon goe your wayes unto my Lord your Maſter, and ſerve him diligently; And ſo parted and went downe into the Hall, and ſo tooke his Barge.</p>
            <p>Then after long and large debating the matter about <note place="margin">He goes to the King.</note> the Lord <hi>Percies</hi> aſſurance to Miſtris <hi>Anne Bullen,</hi> it was deviſed that the Contract ſhould bee infringed, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; And that the Lord <hi>Piercy</hi> ſhould marry one of the Earle of <hi>Shrewsburies</hi> Daughters. And ſo indeed not long after he did, whereby the former Contract was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract between Lord <hi>Percy</hi> and Miſtris <hi>Anne Bullen</hi> diſſolved. She much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at.</note> and diſſolved, wherewith Miſtris <hi>Anne</hi> was greatly diſpleaſed, promiſing, that if ever it lay in her power ſhe would doe the Cardinall ſome diſpleaſure, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſhe afterwards did. But yet he was not altogether to be blamed, for he did nothing but what the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; whereby the Lord <hi>Piercy</hi> was charged to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd her company. And ſo was ſhe for a time diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <note place="margin">Shee is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged the Court.</note> the Court, and ſent home to her Father, whereat ſhe was much troubled and perplexed. For all this time ſhe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53022:23"/>
knew nothing of the Kings intended purpoſe. But wee may ſee when Fortune doth begin to frowne, how ſhee can compaſſe a matter of diſpleaſure, through a farre fetcht Marke; Now therefore of the grudge how it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, that in proceſſe of time wrought the Cardinals utter deſtruction.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of Miſtris</hi> Anne Bullen <hi>her favour with the King.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H Lord, what a great God art thou, that workeſt thy wonders ſo ſecretly, that they are not perceived, untill they bee brought to paſſe and finiſhed.</p>
            <p>Attend now good Reader to this ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry following, and note every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and thou ſhalt at the end perceive a wonderfull worke of God againſt ſuch as forget him and his benefits.</p>
            <p>Therefore, I ſay, conſider after this my Lord <hi>Percyes</hi> troubleſome buſineſſe was over, and all things brought to an end; Then Miſtris <hi>Anne Bullen</hi> was againe admitted <note place="margin">Her admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance againe to Court.</note> to the Court, where ſhe flouriſhed in great eſtimation and favour, having alwayes a prime grudge againſt my Lord Cardinall for breaking the Contract betweene the Lord <hi>Peircy</hi> and her ſelfe ſuppoſing it had beene his owne deviſe and no others. And ſhe at laſt knowing the Kings pleaſure, and the depth of his ſecrets, then began to looke very haughtily and ſtout, lacking no manner of rich apparell, or Jewels that money could purchaſe.</p>
            <p>It was therefore imagined by many through the Court, that ſhe being in ſuch favour, might doe much with the King, and obtaine any ſuit of him for her friends. All this while ſhe being in this eſtimation in all places, there
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53022:23"/>
was no doubt but good Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> having this Gentlewoman daily attending upon her, both heard by report, and ſaw with her eyes how all things tended againſt her good Ladiſhip, although ſhe ſeemed neither to Miſtris <hi>Anne Bullen,</hi> nor the King to carry any ſparke of diſcontent, or diſpleaſure, but accepted all things in <note place="margin">Queene <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine</hi> her patience.</note> good part, and with great wiſdome, and much patience diſſembled the ſame, having Miſtris <hi>Anne Bullen</hi> in more eſtimation for the Kings ſake, then when ſhe was with her before, declaring her ſelfe indeed to be a very patient <hi>Griſſell,</hi> as by her long patience in all her troubles ſhall hereafter moſt plainly appeare.</p>
            <p>For the King was now ſo enamoured of this young Gentlewoman, that he knew not how ſufficiently to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance her.</p>
            <p>This being perceived by all the great Lords of the Court, who bore a ſecret grudge againſt my Lord Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, for that they could not rule in the Kingdome as they would for him, becauſe he was <hi>Dominus fac totum</hi> with the King, and rul'd aſwell the great Lords, as the meane ſubjects; whereat they tooke an occaſion to worke him out of the Kings favour, and conſequently themſelves into more eſtimation.</p>
            <p>And after long and ſecret conſultation with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves how to bring this matter to paſſe. They knew ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">A plot of the Nobility a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Cardinall.</note> well that it was ſomewhat difficult for them to doe abſolutely of themſelves; Wherefore they perceiving the great affection and love the King bare to Miſtris <hi>Anne Bullen,</hi> ſuppoſing in their judgements, that ſhe would be a fit Inſtrument to bring their earneſt intentions to paſſe, therefore they often conſulted with her to that purpoſe, and ſhe having both a very good wit, and alſo an inward grudge and diſpleaſure againſt my Lord Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, was ever as ready to accompliſh their deſires, as they were themſelves, wherefore there was no more to doe but onely to imagine an occaſion to worke their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice by ſome pretended circumſtances. Then did they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53022:24"/>
daily invent divers deviſes how to effect their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but the enterpriſe thereof was ſo dangerous, that though they would faine have attempted the matter with the King, yet durſt they not, for they knew the great zeale the King did beare unto the Cardinall, and this they knew very well, that if the matter they ſhould propound againſt him was not grounded upon a juſt and urgent cauſe, the Kings love was ſuch towards him, and his wit ſuch withall, that hee could with his policie vanquiſh all their enterpriſes, and then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, requite them in the like nature, to their utter ruine.</p>
            <p>Therefore they were compelled to forbeare their plots till they might have ſome better ground to worke upon. And now the Cardinall perceiving the great zeale the King bore to this Gentlewoman, framed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to pleaſe her, as well as the King. To that end therefore hee prepares great Banquets and Feaſts to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine the King and her at his owne houſe; Shee all <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to get her favour.</note> this while diſſembling the ſecret grudge in her breaſt; Now the Cardinall began to grow into wonderfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions not heard of before in <hi>England,</hi> and the love betweene this glorious Lady and the King, grew to ſuch perfection, that divers things were imagined, whereof I forbeare here to ſpeake, untill I come to the proper place.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:53022:24"/>
            <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Of the Variance betweene the French King, and the Duke of Burbon, who fled to the Citie of</hi> Pavia, <hi>where the King beſieged him.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hen began a certaine grudge betweene the French King, and the Duke of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> to breake out; Inſomuch that the Duke being now at variance with the houſe of France, was compelled for ſafeguard of his life to flye, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his Countrie, fearing the Kings malice and indignation.</p>
            <p>The Cardinall having intelligence hereof, contrived <note place="margin">A plot of the Cardinall.</note> that the King our Soveraigne Lord ſhould obtaine the Duke to be his Generall in his warres againſt the French King, with whom our King had then an occaſion of warre, and the rather, becauſe the Duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> was fled to the Emperour to invite him unto a like purpoſe, <note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> fled to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</note> where he moved the King in this matter. And after the King was adviſed thereof, and conceived the Cardinals invention, he muſed more and more of this matter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it came into a Conſultation amongſt the Councell, ſo that it was concluded that an Ambaſſadour ſhould be ſent to the Emperour about this matter; And it was fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">King <hi>Henry</hi> joyneth his forces with the Emperor againſt the French King. The Duke the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Generall.</note> concluded, that the King and the Emperour ſhould joyne in thoſe wars againſt the French King, and that the Duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> ſhould be the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, and Generall in the field, who had a number of good ſouldiers over and beſides the Emperours Army which was not ſmall, and that the King ſhould pay the Duke monethly wages for himſelfe and his retinue.</p>
            <p>For which purpoſe <hi>Iohn Ruſſell,</hi> who was afterwards Created Earle of <hi>Bedford</hi> lay continually beyond the Seas in a ſecret place, both to receive money from the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53022:25"/>
King, and to pay the ſame monthly to the Duke, ſo that the Duke began the warres with the French King in his owne Territories and Dukedome which the King had gotten into his owne hands, being not perfectly knowne to the Dukes enemies, that he had any aide from our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne <note place="margin">The French King in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with an Army.</note> Lord, and thus hee wrought the French King much diſpleaſure, in aſmuch that the French King was conſtrained to prepare a preſent Army, and in his owne perſon to reſiſt the Dukes power. And battell being joyned, the King drove him to take <hi>Pavia,</hi> a ſtrong <note place="margin">The Duke flies to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> and is there beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the French King.</note> Towne in <hi>Italie</hi> with his hoaſt of men for his ſecuritie, where the King encamped himſelfe wonderfully ſtrong, intending to cloſe the Duke within the Towne, leſt hee ſhould iſſue out, and skirmiſh with him.</p>
            <p>The French King in his Campe ſent ſecretly into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> a private perſon (being a very witty man) to treat of <note place="margin">The French. Ambaſſadour treats of peace with <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> a Peace between his Maſter, and our Soveraigne Lord, his name was <hi>Iohn Iokin,</hi> who was kept as ſecretly as might be, no man having intelligence of his arrivall; For hee was no French man borne, but an <hi>Italian,</hi> a man of no great eſtimation in France, nor knowne to bee much in his Maſters favour, but taken to be a Merchant; And for his ſubtile wit, was elected to treate of ſuch an Embaſſage as the French King had given him in Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Iokin</hi> was ſecretly conveyed to <hi>Richmond,</hi> and there ſtayed untill ſuch time as the Cardinall reſorted thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to him, where after Eaſter terme was ended, he kept his feaſt of Whitſontide very ſolemnely; In which ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon my Lord Cardinall cauſed this <hi>Iokin</hi> divers times to dine with him, who ſeemed to bee both witty, and of good behaviour, he continued long in <hi>England</hi> after this, till at the laſt (as it ſhould ſeeme) hee had brought the <note place="margin">Command ſent to Sir <hi>Iohn Ruſſell</hi> to detaine the Kings pay.</note> matter, which he had in Commiſſion to paſſe; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the King ſent out immediatly a reſtraint unto Sir <hi>Iohn Ruſſell,</hi> that he ſhould retaine that moneth pay ſtill in his hands, untill the Kings pleaſure ſhould bee further made knowne, which ſhould have beene paid to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53022:25"/>
Duke, being then encamped within the Towne of <hi>Pavia.</hi> For want of which money the Duke and his men were much diſmayed, when they ſaw no money come as it was wont to doe, and being in this dangerous caſe where victuals began to be ſcant, and very deare, they imagined many wayes what ſhould be the reaſon that the Kings money came not, ſome ſaid this, and ſome ſaid that, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſting nothing leſſe then the true cauſe thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of the Duke of</hi> Burbons <hi>Stratagem and Victorie, wherein the French King was taken priſoner.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow the Duke and his Souldiers were in great <note place="margin">The Duke &amp; his ſouldiers in extreme want.</note> miſerie for want of Victuals and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, which they could by no meanes get within the Towne; Hereupon the Captaines and Souldiers began to grudge and murmure, being for want of Victuals all like to periſh, and being in this extremitie came before the Duke, and ſaid, Sir, we muſt of force and neceſſitie yeeld to our enemies; And better were it for us ſo to doe, then to ſtarve like dogges. But when the Duke heard this, he replied with weeping teares; Sirs, (quoth he) you have proued your ſelves va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant <note place="margin">The Dukes loving adviſe, A generall conſent.</note> men, and of noble hearts in this ſervice; and for your neceſſitie, whereof I my ſelfe doe participate, I do not a little lament; But I ſhall deſire you, as you are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in heart and courage, ſo to take patience for two or three dayes, and if ſuccour come not then from the King of <hi>England,</hi> (as I doubt nothing leſſe) I will then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to you all to put our ſelves and lives unto the mercy of our Enemies; whereunto they all agreed, and tarried till two dayes were paſt, expecting reliefe from the King; Then the Duke ſeeing no remedy, called his noble Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53022:26"/>
and Souldiers before him, and weeping, ſaid; You Noblemen and Captaines, we muſt yeeld our ſelves unto our Enemies, or elſe famiſh, and to yeeld the Towne and our ſelves, I know well the crueltie of our Enemies, as for my part I paſſe not for their cruelties, for I ſhall ſuffer death (I know very well) moſt cruelly, if I come once into their hands; It is not therefore for my ſelfe that I doe lament, it is for your ſakes, it is for your lives, and for the ſafegard of your perſons, for ſo that you might eſcape your enemies hands, I would willingly ſuffer death; good Companions, and noble Souldiers, (I doe require you all) conſidering the miſerable cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and dangers we are in at this preſent to ſell our lives moſt dearely, rather then to be murdered like beaſts; Therefore if you all conſent with me, we will take upon <note place="margin">The Dukes ſubtile de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe.</note> us this night to give our Enemies aſſault, and by that meanes we may either eſcape, or elſe give them an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, for it were better to dye in the field like men, then to live priſoners miſerably in captivity, to which they all agreed.</p>
            <p>Then (quoth the Duke) you all perceive the enemies Campe is ſtrong, and there is no way to enter upon them but one, and that entrie is planted with great Ordnance and ſtrength of men, ſo that it is impoſſible to attaine to our enemies, that way to fight with them in their Campe; And alſo now of late you perceive they have had but ſmall doubt of us, in regard they have kept but ſlender Watch.</p>
            <p>Therefore mine adviſe is, there ſhall iſſue out of the Towne, in the dead time of the night from us a certaine number of you, that bee the moſt likely to aſſault the Campe, and they ſhall give the aſſault ſecretly againſt the place of the entry, which is moſt ſtrong and invincible, which force and valiant aſſault ſhall bee to them of the Campe ſo doubtfull, that they will turne the ſtrength of the entry, that lyeth ouer againſt your aſſault, to beate you from your purpoſe. Then will I enter out at the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53022:26"/>
Poſterne gate, and come to the place of their ſtrength newly turned, and there ere they be aware will I enter and fight with them in the Campe, and win their Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which they have newly turned, and beat them with their owne peeces, and then may you come and joyne with me in the field; So this deviſe pleaſed them all wonderfull wel, &amp; they did then prepare themſelves al that day for that deviſe, and kept themſelves ſecret and cloſe without any noyſe or ſhot of peeces in the Towne, which gave the enemie the leſſe feare of the aſſault, for at night they went all to their Tents, and couched quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nothing miſtruſting what after happened; So in the dead of the night, when they all were at reſt, the aſſailents iſſued out of the Towne, and there accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Dukes appointment, they gave ſo cruell and fierce an aſſault, that they in the Campe had much adoe to withſtand them. And then (as the Duke before decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) they within were compelled to turne the ſhot that <note place="margin">They iſſue out in the night.</note> lay at the entry againſt the aſſault; Then iſſued out the Duke, and with him about fifteene or ſixteene hundred men or more, ſecretly in the night. The enemy being ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant <note place="margin">The Duke iſſues out with 150. or 160. men. He flew the enemies, and tooke the gunnes. He wonne the field.</note> of his comming untill he entred the Field, and at his entry he tooke all the Ordnance that lay there, and ſlew the Gunners, then charged the Peeces againſt the enemies, and ſlew them wonderfully, and cut downe their Tents and Pavillions. and murthered many therein ere they were aware of his comming, ſuſpecting nothing leſſe then his entry, ſo that hee wonne the field ere the King could ariſe; So the King was taken in his lodging, before he was harneſſed. And when the Duke had won the field, the French King taken, and his men ſlaine, his Tents robbed and ſpoiled, and the Kings coffers ſearcht, The Duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> found the league under the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> newly made betweene the King of <hi>England</hi> and the French King, whereby hee perceived the impediment of his money which ſhould have come to him from the King, having upon due ſearch of this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53022:27"/>
matter further intelligence, that all this buſineſſe was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by the Cardinall of <hi>England.</hi> Whereupon the Duke <note place="margin">He intended to ſack <hi>Rome,</hi> but was there ſlaine.</note> conceived ſuch indignation againſt the Cardinall, that he went immediatly to <hi>Rome,</hi> and there intended to ſacke the Towne, and to have taken the Pope; But at the firſt aſſault of the Towne, the Duke was the firſt man that was there ſlaine, notwithſtanding the Captaines conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued their aſſaults. And at laſt many of the Towne fled with the Pope to the Caſtle of <hi>Angell,</hi> where hee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in great calamity.</p>
            <p>I have written this Hiſtorie more at large, becauſe it was thought of all this miſchiefe, wherefore you may ſee whatſoever a man doth purpoſe, be he Prince or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, yet God diſpatcheth all things at his pleaſure and will; It being a folly for any wiſe man to take upon him any weighty enterpriſe of his owne will without cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon God for his grace and aſſiſtance in all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
            <p>I have ſeene Princes, either when they would call a Parliament, or any other great Aſsembly, that they would firſt call to God moſt reverently for his grace therein. And now I ſee the contrarie, as it ſeemes they truſt more to their owne mindes and wills, then to Gods good grace, And even thereafter oftentimes doe their matters take effect; Wherefore not onely in this Hiſtory, but divers others, may be perceived moſt evident exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Yet I ſee no man almoſt in authoritie, or high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate regard the ſame, which is the greater pitty, and the more to be lamented. Now here I deſiſt to ſpeake any further of this matter; and to proceed to others.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:53022:27"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of the French Kings redemption out of captivity, and the Cardinals Embaſſage into France.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>pon the taking of the French King, there were divers Conſultations and various opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions amongſt the Counſell: Some hold that our Soveraigne Lord the King could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the Realme of <hi>France,</hi> he might eaſily conquer the ſame, for as much as the King with the moſt part of the Noble-men of <hi>France</hi> were in captivity. <note place="margin">Eaſie to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> Some ſaid againe, that the King our Maſter ought to have had the French King priſoner, foraſmuch as hee was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by our Kings Champion, and Captaine Generall the <note place="margin">King <hi>Henry</hi> ought to have the French King captive.</note> Duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> and the Emperour. Inſomuch that the King was adviſed thereby to occaſion of warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Emperour, becauſe hee kept the King of <hi>France</hi> out of our Kings poſſeſſion, with divers imaginations and deviſes as their fantaſies ſerved, which were too long here to relate.</p>
            <p>Thus were they in long conſideration, whereof every <note place="margin">Divers Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours from <hi>Fuance</hi> to King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to take order for their Kings releaſe.</note> man in the Court talked as his fanſie ſerved him, untill at the laſt divers Ambaſſadours from the Realme of <hi>France</hi> came to the King our Lord, deſiring him to take order with the Emperour for the French Kings delivery, as his Highneſſe wiſdome ſhould thinke beſt, wherein my Lord Cardinall bore great rule. So that after great deliberation and adviſe taken, it was thought good by the Cardinall that the Emperour ſhould deliver the French King out of his ward upon ſufficient pledges.</p>
            <p>And afterwards it was thought meet, that the Kings two ſonnes (that is to ſay) the Dolphin and the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> ſhould be delivered in hoſtage for ſecurity of the Emperour, and the King our Soveraigne Lord, upon all
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53022:28"/>
ſuch demands and requeſts as ſhould bee demanded of the French King, as well by the Emperour as by our Soveraigne Lord.</p>
            <p>The Cardinall lamenting the French Kings captivity, and the Popes great adverſity (who yet remained in the Caſtle) Angell, either as priſoner, or elſe for defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his enemies, endeavored and laboured all that hee <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth the peace of the Pope, and the French King.</note> could with the King and his Counſell to take ſome order for the quietneſſe of them both.</p>
            <p>At the laſt as you heard before, divers of the great States and Lords of the Councell with my Lady <hi>Anne</hi> lay in continuall waite to ſpy a convenient occaſion to take the Cardinall in a ſnare.</p>
            <p>Therefore they conſulted with the Cardinall, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed him that they thought it a neceſſary time for him <note place="margin">The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell adviſed the Cardinal to goe of the Embaſſage to <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> to take upon him the Kings Commiſſion, to travell beyond the ſeas, and by his wiſdome to compaſſe a preſent peace amongſt theſe great Princes and Potentates, encouraging him thereto, and alleadging that it was more meet for his wiſdome, diſcretion, and authority to bring ſo weighty a matter to paſſe then any other within this Realme, their intent was no other but to get him from the King that they might adventure by the helpe of their chiefe Miſtreſſes <note place="margin">This was a plot.</note> to deprave him unto the King, and ſo in his abſence bring him into his diſgrace, or at the leaſt to be in leſſe eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Well the matter was ſo handled that the Cardinall was commanded to prepare himſelfe for the journey which <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall doth prepare for his Iourney.</note> hee tooke upon him, but whether willingly or not I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay. But this I know, that hee made ſo ſhort abode after the perfect reſolution thereof, that hee cauſed all things to be prepared ſpeedily for his journey. And every one of his ſervants were appointed that ſhould attend him in the ſame.</p>
            <p>When all things were concluded and provided for this noble Iourney, hee advanced forwards in the name of God. My Lord had with him ſuch of the Lords and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53022:28"/>
Biſhops as were not of the Conſpiracie.</p>
            <p>Then marched hee forward from his new houſe at Weſtminſter through all <hi>London,</hi> over <hi>London</hi> bridge, having a great many of Gentlemen in a ranke before him in. Velvet Coats, and the moſt part of them with chains of gold about their necks. And all his yeomen followed him with noble men, and great mens ſervants all in Oringe-tawny coats, and the Cardinals hat with <hi>T.</hi> and <hi>C.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Cardinall</hi> embroydered upon them, as well upon his owne ſervants coats, as all the reſt of the Gentlemen, and his ſumpter Mules which were twenty and more in number: And when all his carriages and carts and other his traine were paſſed before, he rode very ſumptuouſly like a Cardinall with the reſt of his traine on his Mule with his ſpare Mule, and his ſpare horſe covered with crimſon Velvet, and gilt ſtirrops, following him. And before him hee had his two great ſilver Croſſes, his two Pillars of ſilver, the Kings broad Seale of <hi>England,</hi> and his Cardinals hat, and a Gentleman carrying his Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, otherwiſe called his Cloak-bagge, which was <note place="margin">See his Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence.</note> made of fine ſcarlet all embroydered very richly with gold. Thus hee paſſed through <hi>London</hi> as I ſaid before, and all the way in his ſaid Iourney hee was thus furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, having his Harbengers in every place before which prepared lodgings for him and his ſaid traine.</p>
            <p>The firſt Iourney hee made was two miles beyond <hi>Debtford</hi> in Kent unto Sir <hi>Richard Wiltſhires</hi> houſe, the reſt of his traine were lodged in <hi>Debtford,</hi> and in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey thereabouts.</p>
            <p>The next day hee marched to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> where hee lay in the Biſhops Pallace, and the reſt were lodged in the Citie</p>
            <p>The third day hee rode from thence to <hi>Feverſham,</hi> and there lodged in the <hi>Abbey,</hi> and his traine in the Towne, and ſome about in the countrey.</p>
            <p>The fourth day he rode to <hi>Canterbury,</hi> where he was <note place="margin">He came to <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </note> kindly entertained by the Biſhop of the Citie, and there
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53022:29"/>
he continued foure or five dayes. In which ſeaſon was the Iubilee, and a great Faire in the Towne, by reaſon it was the feaſt of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> their Patron, upon which day there was a ſolemne proceſſion wherein my Lord Cardinall was in his Legantine Ornaments, with his hat upon his head, who commanded the Monks and the Quire to ſing the Latine after this ſort: <hi>Sancta Maria or a pro</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth the Monkes to pray for the Pope.</note> 
               <hi>Papa noſtra Clemente,</hi> and in this manner peruſed the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine through: My Lord Cardinall kneeling at a ſtoole be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Quire doore prepared for him, with Carpets and Cuſhions: All the Monkes and the Quire ſtood in the body ſinging the Letany. At which time I ſaw my Lord Cardinall weepe tenderly, the which <hi>James,</hi> I, and <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall wept.</note> others conceived to bee for griefe, that the Pope was in ſuch calamity and danger of the Lance Knights.</p>
            <p>The next day I was ſent with Letters from my Lord to a Cardinall in <hi>Callice</hi> in poſt, ſo that I was the ſame night in <hi>Callice.</hi> At my arrivall I found ſtanding upon the <note place="margin">He arrived at <hi>Callice.</hi>
               </note> Peere without the Lanthorne-gate all the Councell of the Towne, to whom I delivered up my meſſage, and my Letters before I entered the Towne, where I lay untill my Lord came thither, who arrived two dayes after my comming thither before eight of the clock in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and was received of all the noble Officers and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the Towne, and the Major of the ſtaple with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, the Clarkes being in rich Copes having many rich Croſſes.</p>
            <p>In the Lanthorne-gate a ſtoole with Cuſhions and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets was ſet for him where hee kneeled, and made his prayers: At which time they fenced him in with Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zures of ſilver, and ſprinkled water, that done they paſſed on before him in proceſſion, untill hee came unto Saint <hi>Maries Church,</hi> where at the high Altar turning him to the people hee gave them his Benediction and pardon, and <note place="margin">He gave the people par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note> then hee repaired with a great number of Noblemen and Gentlemen to a place in the Towne, called the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, where he kept his houſe ſo long as he abode in the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53022:29"/>
Towne, going immediatly into his naked Bed, becauſe he was ſome what troubled with ſickneſſe by reaſon of his paſſage by Sea.</p>
            <p>That night he called unto him <hi>Mounſier de Bees,</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> with divers other Gallants and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who had dyned with him that day, and having ſome further conſultation with my Lord Cardinall, he and the reſt of the Gentlemen departed againe to <hi>Bulloigne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus my Lord was daily viſited with one or other of the French Nobility.</p>
            <p>When all his traine and carriage was landed, and all things prepared for his journey, his Grace called all his Noblemen and Gentlemen into the Privie Chamber, where being aſſembled before him, he ſaid; I have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calls all his followers into his privy Chamber.</note> you hither to declare unto you, that I would have you both conſider the dutie you owe to me, and the good will I ſemblably beare to you for the ſame. Your intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſervice is to further the Authority I have by Commiſſion from the King, which diligent obſervance of yours, I will hereafter recommend to his Majeſtie, as alſo to ſhew you the Nature of the French-men, and withall to inſtruct you with Reverence, you ſhall uſe me <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to his followers.</note> for the high honour of the Kings Majeſtie, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme you how you ſhall entertaine, and accompany the Frenchmen, when you meet at any time.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt point you ſhall underſtand for divers weighty affaires of his graces and for meere ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his royall dignity, hee hath aſſigned mee in this Journey to bee his Lieutenant, what reverence therefore belongeth to mee for the ſame I will ſhew you.</p>
            <p>By vertue therefore of my Commiſſion and Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantſhip, I aſſume and take upon mee to bee eſteemed in all honour and degrees of ſervice as unto his highnes is <note place="margin">Their duty to him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</note> meet and due, and that by mee nothing bee neglected that to his State is due and appertinent, for my part you ſhall ſee that I will not omit one jot thereof: Therefore
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53022:30"/>
one of your chiefe cauſes of your Aſſembly at this time is to informe you that you bee not ignorant of your duty in this; I wiſh you therefore as you would have my favour, and alſo charge you all in the Kings name, that you doe not forget the ſame in time and place, but that every of you doe obſerve his duty to mee accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as you will at your returne avoide the Kings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, or deſerve his Highneſſe thankes; the which I will ſet forth at our returne, as each of you ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
            <p>Now to the ſecond point the nature of the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The nature of the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </note> is ſuch that at their firſt meeting they will bee as familiar with you, as if they had knowne you by long acquaintance, and will commune with you in their <hi>French</hi> tongue as if they knew every word, therefore uſe them in a kind manner and bee as familiar with them as they are with you; if they ſpeake to you in their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall tongue ſpeake to them in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for if you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not them, no more ſhall they you. Then ſpeaking merrily to one of the Gentlemen being a <hi>Welſhman, Rice,</hi> (quoth hee) ſpeake thou welſh to them and doubt not, but thy ſpeech will be more difficult to them then their <hi>French</hi> ſhall bee to thee. Moreover hee ſaid unto them all, let your entertainement and behaviour bee according to all Gentlemens in humility, that it may bee reported after our departure from thence, that you were Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of very good behaviour and humility; That all men may know, you underſtand your duties to your King. and to your Maſter. Thus ſhall you not onely obtaine to your ſelves great commendations and praiſes; But alſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advance your Prince and Countrey.</p>
            <p>Now being admoniſhed of theſe things prepare your ſelves againſt tomorrow, for then we purpoſe to ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Therefore we his ſervants being thus inſtructed, and all things being in a readineſſe proceeded forwards the next day being <hi>Mary Magdalens</hi> day, my Lord Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and his traine goe from <hi>Callis.</hi>
               </note> advanced out of <hi>Callis</hi> with ſuch a number of black
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53022:30"/>
Coats as hath beene ſeldome ſeene, with the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour went all the Peeres of <hi>Callis,</hi> and <hi>Groynes.</hi> All o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gentlemen, beſides thoſe of his traine were gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with black Velvet coats and Chaines of gold. Thus paſſed he forward, with his troope before three in a Ranke, which compaſſe extended three quarters of a mile in length, having his Croſſes, and all other his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed <note place="margin">His troops 3. inranke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended three quarters of a mile.</note> glorious furniture carried before him, as I have formerly related except the Broad Seale, the which hee left with Doctor <hi>Taylor,</hi> then Maſter of the Rolls untill his returne.</p>
            <p>Thus paſſing on his way, we had ſcarce gone a mile, but it began to raigne ſo vehemently, that I have not ſeen the like for the time, which endured untill we came <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine</hi> meets my Lord.</note> to <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> and ere we came to <hi>Standingfield,</hi> the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of <hi>Lorraine</hi> a goodly young Gentleman gave my Lord a meeting, and received him with much joy and reverence, and ſo paſſed forth with my Lord in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication untill wee came neere the ſaid <hi>Standingfield,</hi> which is a religious place ſtanding betweene the Engliſh, French, and Imperiall Dominions, being a Newter, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of neither of them. Then there we waited for my Lord <hi>le Count Brian</hi> Captaine of <hi>Picardy,</hi> with a great <note place="margin">Captaine of <hi>Picardy.</hi>
               </note> number of Stradigatts or Arboncies ſtanding in array in a great peece of greene Oates, all in harneſſe upon light horſes, paſſing on with my Lord in a wing into <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loigne,</hi> and ſo after into <hi>Picardy,</hi> for my Lord doubted that the Emperour would lay ſome Ambuſhment to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray him, for which cauſe he commanded them to attend <note place="margin">The French king ſent a Convoy.</note> my Lord for the ſafety of his owne perſon, to conduct him from the danger of his enemies.</p>
            <p>Thus rode hee accompanied untill hee came nigh to <hi>Bulloigne</hi> within an Engliſh mile, where all the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Citizens of <hi>Bulloigne</hi> came and met him, having a learned man that made an Oration in Latine to him, unto the which my Lord made anſwer, and that done, <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Bees</hi> Captaine of <hi>Bulloigne</hi> with his retinue met
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53022:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:53022:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:53022:32"/>
him on horſeback with all his Aſſemblie. Thus he march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Towne, lighting at the Abbey gate, from whence he was conveyed into the Abbey with proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and there they preſented him with the Image of <note place="margin">His enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment in <hi>Bulloigne.</hi>
               </note> our Lady, commonly called our Lady of <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> where was alwayes great offerings; That done, he gave his bleſſing to the people, with certaine dayes of pardon; Then went he into the Abbey to his lodging, but all his traine were lodged in the high baſe Towne.</p>
            <p>The next day after he had heard Maſſe, he rode to <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terell,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Alſo at <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terell.</hi>
               </note> where he was in like manner ſaluted by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull of the Towne all in livery alike, where alſo a learned Oration was made to him in Latine, which his <note place="margin">A Latine Oration.</note> Grace anſwered againe in Latine. And as hee entered in at the gate, there was a Canopie of Silke imbroydered with like Letters, as his men had on their coates. And when he was alighted, his Footmen had it as due to their Office. There was alſo made Pageants for joy of his <note place="margin">Pageants made for joy.</note> comming, who was called in the French tongue, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ever he rode or came, <hi>Le Cardinall de Patifagus,</hi> and in Latine <hi>Cardinalus Patifagus,</hi> who was accompanied all that night with the Gentlemen of the Country there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts.</p>
            <p>The next day he tooke his journey towards <hi>Abovile,</hi> where he was in like manner entertained, and conveyed <note place="margin">His enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment at <hi>Abovile.</hi>
               </note> into the Towne, and moſt honourably welcommed with divers kindes of Pageants both coſtly, and wittily contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to every turning of the ſtreetes: as he rode through the Towne, having a Canopie borne over him, richer then at <hi>Muterill,</hi> and ſo conveyed him to his lodging which was a faire houſe newly built with Brick, at which houſe the French King <hi>Lowis</hi> was married to the Kings Siſter, which was married after to the Duke of <hi>Suffolke.</hi> In this Towne of <hi>Abovile</hi> hee remained eight or nine dayes, where reſorted unto him divers of the French Kings Counſell, every day continually feaſting, and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and the other Lords.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:53022:32"/>
At the time of his departing out of the Towne, he rode to a Caſtle beyond the water, called by ſome, <hi>Le Channell Percequeine,</hi> ſtanding &amp; adjoyning to the ſaid water upon a great Hill and Rock, within the which there was a Coledge of Prieſts; The ſcituation whereof was much like to the Caſtle of <hi>Windſor</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and there he was received with a ſolemne proceſſion, conveying him firſt to the Church, and then to the Caſtle upon the Bridge over the water of <hi>Some,</hi> where King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth met with the French King, as you may reade at large in the Chronicles of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord was no ſooner ſeated in his lodging, but <note place="margin">I left my Lord and rode to <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to ſee the King.</note> I heard, that the <hi>French</hi> King would come that day to the City of <hi>Amience</hi> which was not above ſix <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles from thence. And being deſirous to ſee his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thither, I tooke with mee two of my Lords Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and rode preſently thither: And being but ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers wee tooke up our lodging at the ſigne of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, directly over againſt the weſt dore of the Cathedrall Church <hi>de noſtre Dame,</hi> where wee ſtayed in expectation of the Kings comming: And about foure of the clock came <hi>Madame Regent</hi> the Kings Mother riding in a very rich Charriot, and with her within was the Queene of <note place="margin">Firſt came <hi>Madam Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Navarre,</hi> her Daughter, attended with a hundred or more of Ladies and Gentlewomen following, every one riding upon a white Palfrey, alſo her guard which was no ſmall number. And within two dayes after the King <note place="margin">Two dayes after the King, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Swi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Burgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, French,</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh.</hi>
               </note> came in with a great Shot of Gunnes, &amp; there was divers Pageants made onely for joy of his comming, having about his perſon and before him a great number of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen and Gentlemen in three companies: The firſt, were of <hi>Swithers</hi> and <hi>Burgonians</hi> with gunnes; The ſecond, were <hi>Frenchmen</hi> with Bowes; The third, were <hi>le Carpe-fall Scottiſhmen,</hi> who were more comely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons then all the reſt. The <hi>French</hi> guard and <hi>Scottiſh</hi> had all one Livery, being apparalled with rich Coates of white Cloath with a rich guard of ſilver Bullione of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53022:33"/>
a handfull broad: The King came riding on a rich Jennet, and did alight at the ſaid great Church and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed with proceſſion to the Biſhops Pallace where hee was lodged. The next morning, I rode againe to <hi>Picegueny</hi> to attend upon my Lord, and when I came, my Lord was ready to goe on horſebacke to ride to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Amience,</hi> and paſſing on his way, hee was ſaluted by divers Noble perſonages making him Orations in Latine, to whom my Lord made anſwer <hi>ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then was word brought him that the King was ready to meete him, wherefore hee had no other ſhift, but to light at an old Chappell that ſtood hard by the <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall put on rich rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> high way, and there hee newly apparrelled himſelfe in rich array; and ſo mounted againe upon an other Mule very richly trapped with a foote cloath of crimſon vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet purled with gold and fringed about the edges with a fringe of gold very coſtly, his ſtirrops of ſilver guilt, the Boſſes of the ſame, and the checkes of his Mules bit were all guilt with fine gold, and by that time hee was mounted againe in this gorgious manner; the King was come very neere within leſſe then an <hi>Engliſh</hi> quarter of a mile his guard ſtanding in array upon the top of an high hill expecting my Lords comming; to whom my Lord made as much haſt as conveniently hee could un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till hee came within a paire of Buts length, and there hee ſtayed. The King perceiving that, cauſed <hi>Monſieur van de Mount</hi> to iſſue from him, and to ride to my Lord Cardinall to know the cauſe of his tarrying, and ſo <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur van de Mount</hi> being mounted upon a very faire Jennet tooke his race with his horſe till hee came even to my Lord, and then hee cauſed his horſe to come aloft twice or thrice ſo neere my Lords Mule, that hee was in doubt of his horſe and ſo alighted, and in humble reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence did his Meſſage to my Lord, that done hee repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the King. <note place="margin">The <hi>French</hi> King and the Cardinall meet.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And then the King advanced forwards, ſeeing my
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53022:33"/>
Lord doe the like, and in the mid way, they meet em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing each other with amiable countenances. Then came into the place all Noblemen and Gentlemen on both parts who made a mighty preſſe.</p>
            <p>Then the Kings Officers cried <hi>penant de la vant march march:</hi> So the King with the Lord Cardinall on his right <note place="margin">They March, the Cardinall on the Kings right hand.</note> hand rode towards <hi>Amience;</hi> Every <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man being accompained with an other of <hi>France.</hi> The traine of theſe two great Princes was two miles in length, that is to ſay from the place of their meeting unto <hi>Amience</hi> where they were nobly received with Gunnes and Pageants, untill the King had brought my Lord to his lodging, and then departed for that night. The King being lodged in the Biſhops Pallace: And the next day after dinner, my Lord rode with a great traine of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Noblemen and Gentlemen unto the Court to the King, at which time, the King kept his Bed, yet nevertheleſſe, my Lord came into his Bedcham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber where on the one ſide of the Bed ſat the Kings Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and on the other ſide, the Cardinall of <hi>Lorraine</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with divers other Gentlemen of <hi>France,</hi> and after ſome communication, and drinking of wine with the Kings Mother, my Lord departed and returned to his owne lodging accompanied with divers other Lords and Gentlemen.</p>
            <p>Thus continued my Lord at <hi>Amience</hi> and alſo the King <note place="margin">The King and Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall at <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> 14. dayes.</note> 14. dayes feaſting each other divers times, and there one day at Maſſe, the King and my Lord received the holy <hi>Sacrament,</hi> as alſo the Queene <hi>Regent</hi> and the Queene of <hi>Navarre,</hi> after that it was determined, that the King and my Lord ſhould remove, and ſo they rode to a City cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Campaine</hi> which was more then 20. miles from <note place="margin">They remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mience</hi> to <hi>Campaines.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Amience,</hi> unto which Towne I was ſent to provide lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for my Lord, and in my travell, I having occaſion to ſtay by the way at a little Village to ſhoe my horſe; There came to me a ſervant from the Caſtle, there per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving mee to bee an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> and one of my Lord
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53022:34"/>
Legates ſervants (as they then called my Lord) deſired mee to goe into the Caſtle to the Lord his Maſter, whom hee thought would bee very glad to ſee mee, to whom I conſented, becauſe I deſired acquaintance with ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, eſpecially with men of authority and honourable ranck; ſo I went with him, who conducted mee to the Caſtle, and at my firſt entrance, I was among the Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who kept the firſt ward being very tall men and comely perſons, who ſaluted me very kindly; and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cauſe of my comming, they advertiſed their Lord and Maſter: and forthwith the Lord of the Caſtle came out unto mee, whoſe name was <hi>Monſieur Crookeſly</hi> a Nobleman borne; and at his comming, hee embraced <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Monſieur Crookeſley</hi> his going to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite the King and the Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinall to his Caſtle.</note> mee, ſaying, that I was heartily welcome, and thanked mee; that was ſo gentle as to viſit him, and his Caſtle, ſaying that hee was preparing to meet the King, and my Lord Cardinall, and to invite them to his Caſtle: and when hee had ſhewed mee the ſtrength of his Caſtle, and the Walls which were 14. foot broad, and I had ſeeh all the houſes, hee brought mee downe into a faire inner Court where his Jennet ſtood ready for him with 12. other of the faireſt Jennets that ever I ſaw, eſpeccially his owne, which was a Mare: which Jennet he told mee, hee had 400. crownes offered for her; Upon theſe 12. Jennets were mounted 12. goodly Gentlemen, called Pages of honour, they rode all bare-headed in Coates of cloath of gold guarded with black velvet, and they had all of them boots of read <hi>Spaniſh</hi> leather.</p>
            <p>Then tooke he his leave of me, commanding his Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals ſervant nobly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</note> and other of his Gentlemen to conduct me to his Lady to dinner; So they led me up to the Gatehouſe, wher then their Lady and Miſtris lay for the time that the King and the Cardinall ſhould tarry there. And after a ſhort time the Lady <hi>Crookeſley</hi> came out of her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber into the dyning roome, where I attended her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, who did receive me very Nobly, like her ſelfe, ſhe having a traine of twelve Gentlemen that did attend on
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53022:34"/>
her. Foraſmuch (quoth ſhe) as you are an Engliſh Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, whoſe cuſtome is to kiſſe all Ladies and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women in your Countrey without offence, yet it is not ſo in this Realme; Notwithſtanding, I will be ſo bold as <note place="margin">The Lady ſalutes him her ſelfe.</note> to kiſſe you, and ſo ſhall you ſalute all my Maides. After this we went to dinner, being as nobly ſerved as ever I ſaw any in <hi>England,</hi> paſſing all dinner time in pleaſing diſcourſes.</p>
            <p>And ſhortly after dinner I tooke my leave, and was conſtrained that night to lye ſhort of <hi>Campanie,</hi> at a great walled Towne called <hi>Moundrodrey,</hi> the Suburbes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of my Lord of <hi>Suffolke</hi> had lately burned; and early in the morning I came to <hi>Campanie,</hi> being Saturday, and Market day, where at my firſt comming I tooke up my Inne over againſt the Market place, and being ſet at din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in a faire Chamber that looked out into the ſtreet, I heard a great noiſe and clattering of Bills; and looking out, I ſaw the Officers of the Towne bringing a Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to execution, and with a Sword cut off his head. I demanded what was the offence, they anſwered me, for killing of Red Deare in the Forreſt neere adjoyning. And incontinently they held the poore mans head upon a Pole in the Market place betweene the Stagges hornes, and his foure quarters ſet up in foure places of the Forreſt.</p>
            <p>Having prepared my Cardinals lodgings in the great Caſtle of the Towne, and ſeene it furniſhed, my Lord had the one halfe aſſigned, and the King the other halfe, and in like manner they divided the Gallery betweene them; <note place="margin">The French King the Lord Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and the Queene Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent lodged all in one Caſtle.</note> And in the middeſt thereof, there was made a ſtrong Wall with a Window and a Doore, where the King and my Lord did often meet and talke, and divers times goe one to the other through the ſame Doore. Alſo there was lodged in the ſame Caſtle Madam Regent the Kings Mother, and all the Ladies and Gentlewomen that did attend on her.</p>
            <p>Not long after came the Lord Chancellour of <hi>France,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:53022:35"/>
a very witty man, with all the Kings grave Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, where they tooke great paines daily in conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. At which time I heard my Lord Cardinall fall out <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall fell out with the Chancellour of <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> with the Chancellour of <hi>France,</hi> laying to his charge, that he went about to hinder the League which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his comming concluded upon, by the King our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Lord, and the French King their Maſter. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that my Lord ſtomacked him ſtoutly, and told him it was not he that ſhould infringe the amiable friendſhip. And if the French King his Maſter being there preſent would follow his the Chancellours counſell, hee ſhould not faile ſhortly after his returne to feele the ſmart, what it was to maintaine Warre againſt the King of <hi>England,</hi> and thereof hee ſhould be well aſſured; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that his angry ſpeech and bold countenance made them all doubt how to quiet him to the counſell, who <note place="margin">The Cardinal departs in anger.</note> was then departed in a great fury.</p>
            <p>Now here was ſending, here was comming, here was intreating, and here was great ſubmiſſion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion <note place="margin">Great means uſed to bring him again to conſultation.</note> made unto him to reduce him to his former communication, who would in no wayes relent untill <hi>Madame Regent</hi> came to him her ſelfe, who handled the matter ſo well that ſhee brought him to his former com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and by that meanes, hee brought all things to paſſe, that before hee could not compaſſe, which was more out of feare then affection the <hi>French</hi> King had to the matter in hand; for now hee had got the heades of all the Councell under his girdle.</p>
            <p>The next morning early after this conflict, the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall aroſe about 4. of the clock, and ſate him downe to write Letters into <hi>England</hi> unto the King, commanding one of his Chaplaines to prepare him ready; Inſomuch that the Chaplaine ſtood ready in his Veſtures untill foure of the clocke in the afternoone. All which ſeaſon my Lord never roſe to eate any meate, but continually writ Letters with his owne hand; And about foure of the <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall writes Letters into <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> clocke in the afternoone he made an end of writing,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53022:35"/>
commanding one <hi>Chriſtopher Gunner</hi> the Kings Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant to <note place="margin">He ſends poſt into <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> prepare himſelfe without delay to ride Poſt into <hi>England</hi> with his Letters whom he diſpatcht away ere ever he dranke. That done, he went to Maſſe and Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins, and other devotions with his Chaplaine, as he was accuſtomed to doe, and then went to walke in a Garden the ſpace of an houre and more, and then ſaid Evening ſong, and ſo went to dinner and ſupper, making no long ſtay, and ſo went to bed.</p>
            <p>The next night following, my Lord cauſed a great ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to be made, or rather a Banquet for <hi>Madam Regent</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall feaſts two Queens.</note> and the Queene of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and other Noble Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Lords and Ladies. At which ſupper was <hi>Madam Lewis,</hi> one of the Daughters of <hi>Lewis</hi> the laſt King, whoſe ſiſter lately dyed, theſe two Siſters were of their Mother Inheritours of the Dutchie of <hi>Brittaine.</hi> And foraſmuch as King <hi>Francis</hi> had married one of the Siſters by which he had one Moytie of the ſaid Dutchie, hee kept the ſaid <hi>Madam Lewis</hi> the other Siſter without Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to the intent the whole Dutchie might deſcend to him or his ſucceſſours after his death for lacke of iſſue of her.</p>
            <p>But now let us returne to the Supper or Banquet, where all thoſe noble perſonages were highly feaſted. And at the middeſt of the ſaid Banquet the French King <note place="margin">In comes the French King, and the King of <hi>Navarre.</hi>
               </note> and the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> came ſuddenly in, who tooke their places in the loweſt part thereof; There was not onely plenty of fine meates, but alſo much mirth and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace aſwell in merry communication, as alſo the noyſe of my Lords Muſique, who played there all that night ſo cunningly, that the two Kings tooke great delight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, inſomuch that the French King deſired my Lord to lend them unto him for the next night. And after the Supper or Banquet ended, the Lords fell to dancing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <note place="margin">The French King much taken with my Lords Muſicke.</note> whom one <hi>Madam Fountaine</hi> had the praiſe. And thus paſſed they the moſt part of the night ere they parted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:53022:36"/>
The next day the King tooke my Lords Muſicke, and rode to a Noblemans houſe, where was ſome living Image to whom he had vowed a nights pilgrimage. And to performe his devotion when he came there (which was in the night) he danced and cauſed others to doe the ſame, and the next morning he returned to <hi>Campanie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King being at <hi>Campanie,</hi> gave order that a wild <note place="margin">The French King hunted the wild Boare.</note> Bore ſhould be lodged for him in the Forreſt, whether my Lord Cardinall went with him to ſee him hunt the wild Bore, where the Lady <hi>Regent</hi> with a number of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Damſels were ſtanding in Chariots looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the toyle, amongſt theſe Ladyes ſtood my Lord Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, to regard the hunting in the Lady <hi>Regents</hi> Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot. And within the Toyle was the King with divers Ladyes of <hi>France</hi> ready furniſhed for the high and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous enterprize of hunting of this perilous wilde Swine.</p>
            <p>The King being in his Doublet and Hoſe all of ſheepes colour cloth richly trimmed, in his ſlippe a brace of very great Gray-hounds, who were armed as their manner there is to defend them from the violence of the Beaſts tuskes. And the reſt of the Kings Gentlemen that were appointed to hunt, were likewiſe in their Doublets and Hoſe, holding each of them a very ſharpe Bores ſpeare. Then the King commanded the Keepers to uncouch the Boare; And that every perſon within the Toyle ſhould goe to a ſtanding, among whom were divers Gentlemen of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Boare preſently iſſued out of his denne, and being purſued by a hound came into the plaine, where he ſtayed a while gazing upon the people, and the hound drawing neere him, he eſpied a Buſh upon a Banke; under the buſh lay two Frenchmen, who fled thither, thinking there to be ſafe; But the Bore ſmelling them, and thruſting his head into the Buſh, theſe two men came away from thence, as men uſe to fly from the danger of death.</p>
            <p>Then was the Boare by violence of the Hunters driven
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53022:36"/>
from thence, who 'ran ſtraite to one of my Lords Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men being a very tall man, who had in his hand an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Javelin, with which he defended himſelfe a great while. But the Bore continued foaming at him with his great Tuskes; at the laſt the Boare broke in ſunder his Javelin, ſo that he was glad to draw his ſword, and therewith ſtood upon his guard untill the Hunters came and reſcued him, and put the Boare once againe to flight to an other Gentleman of <hi>England,</hi> one Maſter <hi>Ratcliffe,</hi> who was ſonne and heire to the Lord <hi>Fitzwalter,</hi> now Earle of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> who by his Boares ſpeare reſcued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. There were many other paſſages, but I forbeare prolixitie, and returne to the matter in hand.</p>
            <p>Many dayes were ſpent in conſultation, and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Chriſtopher Gunners</hi> returne, who was formerly ſent poſt into <hi>England</hi> with Letters, as I ſaid before; At laſt he returned with Letters, upon receipt whereof, my <note place="margin">Preparation to returne into <hi>Bngland.</hi>
               </note> Lord prepared with all expedition to returne to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That mourning that my Lord intended to remove be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Maſſe in his Cloſet, he Conſecrated the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of <hi>France,</hi> a Cardinall, and put his Hat on his head, and his cap of Scarlet, and then tooke his journey, <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he came away made the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of <hi>France</hi> a Cardinall.</note> and returned into <hi>England</hi> with all the expedition hee could, and came to <hi>Sayne,</hi> and was there nobly entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of my Lord <hi>Stanes,</hi> who was captaine of that place, and from thence went to <hi>Callis,</hi> where he ſtayed a while for ſhipping of his goods. And in the meane time hee eſtabliſhed a worke to be there kept for all Nations. But how long, or in what ſort it continued, I know not; For I never heard of any great good it did, or of any Aſſembly of Merchants or traffique of Merchandize that were brought thither for ſo great and mighty a matter, as was intended for the good of the Towne; This being eſtabliſhed, he tooke ſhipping for <hi>Dover,</hi> and from thence rode poſt to Court.</p>
            <p>The King being then in his progreſſe at Sir <hi>Henry Wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ats</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:53022:37"/>
houſe in Kent, of whom I and other of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants thought hee ſhould have beene nobly entertained, as well of the King himſelfe as of the Nobles: But wee were all deceived in our expectations: Notwithſtanding <note place="margin">He arrives at the court.</note> he went immediatly to the King after his returne, with whom hee had long talke, and continued two or three dayes after in the Court, and then retyred to his houſe at Weſtminſter where he remained till Michaelmas Term, which was within a fort-night after, and there hee exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his place of Chancellorſhip, as hee had done before.</p>
            <p>And immediatly after the beginning of the Terme hee cauſed to be aſſembled in the Starre-chamber all the noble men, Iudges and Iuſtices of the peace of every ſhire throughout <hi>England,</hi> and were at <hi>Weſtminſter-</hi>Hall then preſent. And there hee made a long Oration, declaring the cauſe of his Embaſſage into <hi>France,</hi> and of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall maketh an oration in the Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber.</note> therein, ſaying that hee had concluded ſuch an Amity and peace, as never was heard of in this Realme, betweene our Soveraigne Lord the Kings Majeſty, the Emperour and the French King; for a perpetuall peace which ſhall bee confirmed in writing, under the ſeales of both Realmes engraven in gold: Offering further that our King ſhould receive yearly by that name out of the <note place="margin">A perpetuall peace made with France.</note> dutchy of <hi>Normandy,</hi> all the charges and loſſes hee had ſuſtained in the warres.</p>
            <p>And alſo for as much as there was a reſtraint made of the French Queenes Dowry (whom the Duke of Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke had married) for many yeares together during the warres: It was concluded that ſhee ſhould not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſame according to her juſt right, but alſo the Arrerages being unpaid during the ſaid reſtraint ſhould be perfected ſhortly after. The reſort of Ambaſſadours out of <hi>France</hi> ſhould bee ſuch a great number of Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Gentlemen to confirme the ſame as hath not bin ſeene heretofore repaire hither out of one Realme.</p>
            <p>This peace thus concluded, there ſhall be ſuch an ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53022:37"/>
betweene them of each Realme, and entercourſe of Merchandiſe, that it ſhall bee ſeene to all men to bee but one Monarchie. Gentlemen and others may travell from one countrey to an other for their recreations and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And Merchants of either countrey may traffike ſafely without feare of danger. So that this Realme ſhall ever after flouriſh.</p>
            <p>Therefore may all Engliſhmen well rejoyce and ſet forth the truth of this Embaſſie in the Countrey. Now my Maſters I beſeech you and require you in the Kings behalfe, that you ſhew your ſelves as loving and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſubjects in whom the King may much rejoyce, &amp;c. And ſo hee ended his Oration, and brake up the Court for that time.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XIIII. <hi>Of the French Ambaſſadours entertainment and diſpatch.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow the great long looked for Ambaſſadours are arrived, being in number eight perſons of the Nobleſt and moſt worthy Gentlemen in all <hi>France,</hi> who were nobly received from place to place, and ſo conveyed through <hi>London</hi> to the Biſhops Palace in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, where they were lodged, to whom divers Noblemen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted and gave them noble preſents (eſpecially the Maior of the Citie of <hi>London)</hi> as Wines, Sugars, Beeves, Muttons, Capons, wild Fowle, waxe, and other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things in abundance for the expences of his houſe.</p>
            <p>They reſorted to the Court being then at <hi>Greenewich</hi> on Sunday, and were received of the Kings Majeſtie of <note place="margin">The Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh our King in the order of France.</note> whom they were entertained highly.</p>
            <p>They had a Commiſſion to eſtabliſh our Kings High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the order of <hi>France,</hi> to whom they brought for that intent a coller of fine gold, with a Michell hanging
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53022:38"/>
thereat, and Robes to the ſaid order appertaining, which were of blew velvet, and richly embroydered, wherein I ſaw the King paſſe to the Cloſet, and after in the ſame to Maſſe.</p>
            <p>And to gratifie the French King for his great honour, <note place="margin">The King of England ſent Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſe into <hi>France</hi> to eſtabliſh the French King in the order of the Garter.</note> hee ſent incontinently noblemen here in <hi>England</hi> of the order of the Garter, which Garter the Herauld carried into <hi>France</hi> unto the French King, to eſtabliſh him in the order of the Garter, with a rich Coller and Garter, and Robes according to the ſame: The French Ambaſſadors ſtill remayning here, untill the returne of the Engliſh.</p>
            <p>All things being then determined and concluded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the perpetuall peace; upon ſolemne Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Oathes contained in certaine Inſtruments concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame. It was concluded there ſhould be a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Maſſe ſong in the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Pauls</hi> in <hi>London</hi> by the Cardinall, the King being preſent at the ſame in his traverſe to performe all things determined.</p>
            <p>And for the preparation thereof, there was a Gallery from the Weſt-doore of <hi>Pauls</hi> Church through the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the ſame up to the Quite, and ſo to the high Altar into the Traverſe. My Lord Cardinall prepared himſelfe to ſing the Maſſe, aſſociated with twenty foure Miters of Biſhops and Abbots, who attended him with ſuch Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, as to him were then due by reaſon of his Legative Prerogative.</p>
            <p>And after the laſt <hi>Agnus</hi> the King roſe out of the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and kneeled upon a Carpet and Cuſhions before the high Altar, and the like did the great Maſter of <hi>France</hi> chiefe Ambaſſadour, that here preſented the Kings perſon <note place="margin">The King of England and France Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours receive the Sacraments to confirme the perpetual peace.</note> of <hi>France,</hi> betweene whom the Lord Cardinall divided the bleſſed Sacrament, as a perfect oath and bond for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the ſaid Covenants, of the ſaid perpetual peace.</p>
            <p>That done, the King went againe into the Travers, this Maſſe being ended, which was ſolemnely ſung both by the Quite of the ſame Church, and all the Kings Chappell.</p>
            <p>Then my Lord tooke and read the Articles of peace
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53022:38"/>
openly before the King and all other, both Engliſh and <note place="margin">The Articles of peace read by the Cardinall.</note> French, and there in ſight of all the people the King put his hand to the gold Seale, and ſubſcribed with his owne hand, and delivered the ſame to the grand Maſte of <hi>France,</hi> as his deed, who ſemblably did the like; that <note place="margin">The King ſubſcribeth and ſealeth.</note> done they departed and rode home with the Cardinall, and dined with him, paſſing all the day after in conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of weighty affaires touching the Articles and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſaid peace.</p>
            <p>Then the King departed to <hi>Greenwich</hi> by water, at <note place="margin">The French Nobility conveyed to <hi>Richmond.</hi>
               </note> whoſe departure it was concluded by the Kings deviſe, that all the Frenchmen ſhould remove to <hi>Richmond</hi> and hunt there: And from thence to <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, and there to hunt likewiſe. And the Lord Cardinall there to make a Banquet or Supper or both, and from thence they ſhould ride to <hi>Windſor,</hi> and there hunt: And after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the King at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> and there to banquet with him before their departure.</p>
            <p>This determined they all repaired to their lodgings, then was there no more to doe, but to make preparation in all things for the entertainment of this great Aſſembly at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court at the time appointed by my Lord Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, who called before him all his chiefe Officers, as Stewards, Treaſurers, Clarkes, and Comptrollers of his Kitchin, to whom hee declared his whole mind touching the entertainment of the French-men at <hi>Hampton</hi> court, to whom hee alſo gave command, neither to ſpare for any coſt or expence, nor paines to make them ſuch a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Banquet, as they might not onely wonder at it here; but alſo make a glorious report to the great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our King and this Realme.</p>
            <p>Thus having made knowne his pleaſure, to accompliſh his commandement, they ſent out all the Carriers Purvey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors and other perſons to my Lords friends to prepare: Alſo they ſent to all expert Cooks, and cunning perſons in the art of cookery in <hi>London,</hi> or elſe where that might be gotten to beautifie the noble Feaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:53022:39"/>
Then the Purveyours provided, and my Lords friends ſent in ſuch proviſion that it was a wonder to ſee it.</p>
            <p>The Cooks they wrought both day and night in many curious deviſes, where was no lacke of gold, ſilver, or any other coſtly thing: the Yeomen and Grooms of his Wardrobe were buſied in hanging the Chambers with coſtly Hangings, and furniſhing the ſame with beds of ſilke and other furniture for the ſame in every degree.</p>
            <p>Then my Lord ſent mee being his Gentleman Vſher, and two other of my fellowes to foreſee all things touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">The rooms richly hung.</note> our roomes to bee richly garniſhed, wherein our paines was not ſmall. But daily wee travelled up and downe from Chamber to Chamber to ſee things fitted.</p>
            <p>Then wrought Ioyners, Carpenters, Painters, and all other Artificers needfull, that there was nothing wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to adorne this noble Feaſt: There was carriage and re-carriage of plate, ſtuffe, and other rich emploiments, ſo that there was nothing lacking that could be deviſed or imagined for the purpoſe. There were alſo provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded two hundred and eighty beds with all manner of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture to them, too long here to be related. <note place="margin">200. and 80. beds prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The day aſſigned to the French-men being come, they were ready aſſembled before the houre of their appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherfore the Officers cauſed them to ride to <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>north,</hi> a Parke of the Kings within three miles of <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Court, there to ſpend the time in hunting till night, which they did, and then returned, and every of them were conveyed to their ſeverall Chambers having in them good fires and ſtore of wine, where they remayned till Supper was ready. <note place="margin">The ordering of the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetting rooms.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Chambers where they ſupped and banquetted, were adorned thus.</p>
            <p>Firſt the great wayting Chamber was hung with very rich cloath of Arras, and ſo all the reſt ſome better then others, and furniſhed with tall yeomen to ſerve: There were ſet Tables round about the Chambers, Banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe covered: Alſo a Cubbard garniſhed with white
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:53022:39"/>
plate, having alſo in the ſame chamber foure great plates to give the more light, ſet with great lights, agreat fire of wood and coales.</p>
            <p>The next Chamber was the Chamber of preſence, richly hanged alſo with cloath of <hi>Arras,</hi> and a ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous cloath of State furniſhed with many goodly Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen to ſerve. The Tables were ordered in manner as the other were, ſave onely the high table was remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved beneath the cloath of State, towards the midſt of the Chamber with ſix desks of plate, garniſhed all over with fine gold, ſaving one paire of Candleſticks of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and guilt, with lights in the ſame, the Cubberd was barred about that no man could come very neere it, for there were divers peeces of great ſtore of plate to uſe, beſides the plates that hung on the Walles to give light, were ſilver and guilt with wax lights.</p>
            <p>Now were all things in readines, and ſupper fit, the principall Officers cauſed the Trumpets to blow, to warne them to ſupper. Then the Officers conducted <note place="margin">The <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note> the Noblemen where they were to ſup, and they being ſet the ſervice came up, in ſuch aboundance both coſtly and full of deviſes with ſuch a pleaſant noiſe of muſique, that the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> (as it ſeemed) were wrapt up in a heavenly Paradice. You muſt underſtand, that my Lord Cardinall was not there all this while. But the <hi>French Monſieurs</hi> were very merry, with their rich fare and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious cates and knackes. But before the ſecond courſe, my Lord Cardinall came in booted and ſpurred ſuddenly <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall comes in ere the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond courſe.</note> amongſt them, at whoſe comming there was great joy every man riſing from his place, whom my Lord Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall cauſed to ſit ſtill and keepe their places, and being in his riding apparrell, called for his chaire and ſat him downe in the midſt of the high Table, and was there as merry and pleaſant as ever I ſaw him in my life.</p>
            <p>Preſently after came up the ſecond courſe, which was above 100. ſeverall deviſes, which were ſo goodly and coſtly, that I thinke, the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> never ſaw the like.</p>
            <p>But the rareſt curioſity of all the reſt, they all won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at (which indeed was worthy of wonder) were
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53022:40"/>
caſtles with Images in the ſame like Saint <hi>Paules</hi> Church for the Modell of it, there were beaſts, birdes, fowles, perſonages moſt excellently made, ſome figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with ſwordes, ſome with gunnes, other with croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes, ſome dancing with Ladies, ſome on horſeback with compleat armour, juſtling with long and ſharpe ſpeares, with many more ſtrange deviſes, which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deſcribe: Amongſt all, I noted, there was a cheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board made of ſpice plate with men of the ſame, and of good proportion.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> are very expert at that ſport. My Lord Cardinall gave that ſame to a <hi>French</hi> Gentleman, commanding, that there ſhould bee made a good caſe to convey the ſame into his Country.</p>
            <p>Then called my Lord for a great boule of gold filled with Hipocras, and putting of his cap ſaid, I drinke a <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall drinks a health to both Kings.</note> health to the King my Soveraigne Lord, and next unto the King your Maſter. And when hee had drunke a harty draught, hee deſired the grand Maſter to pledge him a cup, which cup was worth 500. Markes; And ſo all the Lords in order pledged theſe great Princes.</p>
            <p>Then went the cup merrily about, ſo that many of the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> were led to their beds; then went my Lord into his privy Chamber making a ſhort ſupper or rather a ſhort repaſt, and then returned againe into the preſence Chamber amongſt the <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> behaving himſelfe in ſuch a loving ſort and ſo familiarly towards them, that they could not ſufficiently commend him.</p>
            <p>And while they were in communication and paſtime, all their livery were ſerved to theirs Chambers, every Chamber had a Baſon and Ewer of ſilver, &amp; a great livery pot with plenty of wine and ſufficient of every thing.</p>
            <p>Thus furniſhed was every roome about the houſe, when all was done, then were they conducted to their lodgings.</p>
            <p>In the morning after they had heard Maſſe, they ſtayed &amp; dyned with my Lord, and ſo departed towards <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor:</hi> And as ſoone as they were gone, my Lord retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>London,</hi> becauſe it was the midſt of the Tearme.</p>
            <p>You muſt conceive, the King was privy to this mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53022:40"/>
feaſt, who then intended farre to exceede the ſame, which I referre to the <hi>French mens</hi> returne. Now the King had given command to his Officers to provide a farre more ſumptuous Banquet for the Strangers, then they had at the Cardinals, which was not neglected. After the return of theſe Strangers from <hi>Windſor</hi> which place they much commended for the ſcituation thereof, the King invited them to the Court where they dyned, and after dynner, they danced, and had their paſtime till ſupper time.</p>
            <p>Then was the Banquet Chamber in the little Yard at <hi>Greenewich</hi> furniſhed for the entertainement of theſe <note place="margin">His Majeſtie invites the Stangers to the Court.</note> Strangers, to which place they were conducted by the greateſt perſonages then being in the Court, where they did both ſup and banquet, but to deſcribe to you the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hereof, the variety of coſtly diſhes, and the curious deviſes my weake ability and ſhallow capacity would much ecclipſe the magnificence thereof. But thus much take notice of that although, that Banquet at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court was marveilous ſumptuous, yet this Banquet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled the ſame as much, as gold doth ſilver in value. And for my part I never ſaw the like.</p>
            <p>In the midſt of the Banquet, there was turning at the Barriers of luſty gent: in compleat Armour very gorgious on foote and the like on horſebacke: And after all this, there was ſuch an excellent interlude made in Latine, that I never ſaw nor heard the like, the Actours Apparrell being ſo gorgious, and of ſuch ſtrange de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes, that it paſſeth my poore capacity to relate them.</p>
            <p>This being ended, there came a great company of Ladies and Gentlewomen, the chiefeſt beauties in the Realme of <hi>England</hi> being as richly attired as coſt could make, or art deviſe to ſet forth their geſtures propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or beauties, that they ſeemed to the Beholders, rather like celeſtiall Angels then terreſtiall Creatures, and in my judgement worthy of admiration, with whom the gent: of <hi>France</hi> danced and masked every man chooſing his Lady as his fancy ſerved: That done and the Maſquers departed; came in an other Maſque
<pb facs="tcp:53022:41"/>
of Ladies and Gentlewomen ſo richly attired, as I can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not expreſſe; Theſe Ladies Maſquers tooke each of them one of the <hi>French men</hi> to dance, and here note that theſe Noble women ſpoke all of them good <hi>French,</hi> which delighted them much to heare the Ladies ſpeake to them in their owne language.</p>
            <p>Thus triumphantly did they ſpend the whole night from five of the clocke at the night, unto two or three of the clock in the morning, at which time the Gallants drew all to their lodgings to take their reſt.</p>
            <p>As neither health, wealth, nor pleaſure can alwayes laſt, ſo ended this triumphant Banquet, which being paſt, ſeemed in the morning to the Beholders, as a phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique dreame.</p>
            <p>Now after all this ſolemne banquetting, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared <note place="margin">Their prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> with Bagge and Baggage to returne. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon repaired to the King, and in order, every man tooke his leave of his Majeſty, and the Nobles, by whom the King ſent his princely pleaſure and commendations to the King their Maſter, thanking them for their paines. And after great communication had with the <note place="margin">They take leave of the King.</note> great Maſter of that Ambaſſage, hee bad them adue.</p>
            <p>Then they came to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to my Lord Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall to doe the like, of whom hee received the Kings reward, which I ſhall hereafter relate.</p>
            <p>Firſt, every man of honour and eſtimation had plate, <note place="margin">The Kings reward.</note> ſome to the value of 2. or 300. pounds, and ſome of 400. pounds, beſides the great guifts before received of his Majeſty; As gownes of velvet with rich furres, great chaines of gold, and ſome had goodly horſes of great value, with divers other guifts of great value, which I cannot call to remembrance; but the worſt of them had <note place="margin">And alſo of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> the ſumme of 20. crownes, and thus being nobly rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my Lord after humble commendations to the <hi>French</hi> King bad them farewell, and ſo they departed.</p>
            <p>The next day, they were conveyed to <hi>Dover</hi> to the Sea ſide, withall their furniture being accompanied with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Engliſh</hi> yong gallants, and what report of their royall entertainement, they made in their owne Country I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:53022:41"/>
            <head>CHAP. 15. <hi>Of the Kings diſcovery of his love to Miſtris</hi> Anne Bulloigne <hi>to the Cardinall, with the Cardinals diſlike, and alſo the opinions of all the learned Biſhops in</hi> England <hi>and forraigne <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter this beganne new matters which trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the heads and imaginations of all the Court, wherewith all their ſtomacks were full, but little digeſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> the long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed affection of the King to Miſtris <hi>Anne Bulloigne</hi> now brake out, which his Majeſty diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed to the Cardinall, whoſe often perſwaſions on his knees tooke no effect.</p>
            <p>My Lord thereupon being compelled to declare to his Majeſty his opinion and wiſedome in the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kings deſires, thought it not ſafe for him to wade too farre alone, or to give raſh judgement in ſo weighty a matter, but deſired leave of the King to aske Counſell of men of ancient and famous learning both in the Divine and Civill Lawes.</p>
            <p>Now this being obtained, he by his Legatine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſent out his Commiſſions for the Biſhops of this Realme, who not long after aſſembled all at <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> before my Lord Cardinall. And not only theſe <hi>Prelates,</hi> but alſo the moſt learned men of both <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities,</hi> and ſome from divers Cathedrall Colledges in this Realme, who were thought ſufficiently able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve this doubtfull queſtion.</p>
            <p>At this learned aſſembly was the Kings Caſe conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53022:42"/>
of, debated, argued and judged from day to day. <note place="margin">The Kings Caſe diſcuſſed by an aſſembly of Biſhops.</note> But in concluſion when theſe ancient Fathers of Law and Divinity parted, they were all of one judgement, and that contrary to the expectation of moſt men. And I heard ſome of the moſt famous and learned amongſt them ſay, the Kings Caſe was too obſcure for any man, and the poynts therein were doubtfull to have any reſolution therein, and ſo at that time with a generall conſent departed, without any Reſolution or judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>In this aſſembly of Biſhops and divers other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, it was thought very expedient that the King ſhould ſend out his Commiſſioners into all Vniverſities in Chriſtendome, as well heere in <hi>England,</hi> as For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Regions, there to have this Caſe argued ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially, and to bring with them from thence every definition of their opinions of the ſame, under the Seale of every Vniverſity, and thus for this time were their determinations.</p>
            <p>And thereupon divers Commiſſioners were preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appoynted for this deſigne: So ſome were ſent to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> ſome to <hi>Oxford,</hi> ſome to <hi>Lorraigne,</hi> others to <hi>Paris,</hi> ſome to <hi>Orleance,</hi> others to <hi>Padua,</hi> all at <note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners ſent to all the forraigne Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities.</note> the proper coſts and charges of the King, which in the whole amounted to a great ſumme of mony: and all went out of this Real me, beſides the charge of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage to thoſe famous and notable perſons of all the Vniverſities, eſpecially ſuch as bare the rule, or had the cuſtody of the Vniverſity Seales, were fed by the Commiſſioners with ſuch great ſummes of mony, that they did eaſily condiſcend to their requeſts, and grant their deſires.</p>
            <p>By reaſon whereof all the Commiſſioners returned with their purpoſe, furniſhed according to their Commiſſions under the Seale of every ſeverall Univerſity, whereat there was no ſmall joy
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53022:42"/>
conceived of the principall parties. Inſomuch that ever after the Commiſſioners were had in great eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and highly advanced, and liberally rewarded farre beyond their worthy deſerts. Notwithſtanding they proſpered, and the matter went ſtill forward, having now as they thought, a ſure ſtaffe to leane upon.</p>
            <p>Theſe proceedings being declared unto my Lord <note place="margin">The Cardinal ſends againe for the biſhop.</note> Cardinall, hee ſent agayne for the Biſhops, to whom he declared the effect of theſe Commiſſioners paynes, and for aſſurance thereof, ſhewed them the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of each Vniverſity under their ſeverall Seales, and the buſineſſe being thus handled, they went agayne to conſultation how things ſhould bee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p>At laſt it was concluded that it was very meete the King ſhould ſend unto the Pope his Holineſſe, the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of both Vniverſities of <hi>England,</hi> and alſo For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Vniverſities, which were manifeſtly authorized by their common Seales. And it was alſo thought fit the opinions of the worthy Prelates of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be ſent to the Pope, compriſed in an Inſtrument which was not long time in finiſhing.</p>
            <p>Nor was it long after that the Ambaſſadours were aſſigned for this deſigne, who tooke their journey ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, having certayne inſtruments, that if the Pope would not thereupon conſent to give judgement definitively in the Kings Caſe, then to require an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Embaſſadors ſent to th' pope</note> Commiſſion from his Holineſſe to be granted to his Legate, to eſtabliſh a Court heere in <hi>England,</hi> for that purpoſe only, to be directed to my Lord Cardinall Legate of <hi>England,</hi> and to Cardinall <hi>Campain</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bath,</hi> which the King gave him at a certayne time, when hee was ſent Embaſſdour hither from the Pope his Holineſſe, to determine and rightly
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53022:43"/>
judge according to their Conſciences. To the which, <note place="margin">The Pope doth grant their ſuite.</note> after long ſuite made, and for the good will of the ſaid Cardinall, the Pope granted their Suite.</p>
            <p>Then they returned into <hi>England,</hi> relating unto the King that his Graces pleaſure ſhould be now brought to paſſe ſubſtantially, being never more likely, conſidering the ſtate of the Iudges.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Long was the expectation on both ſides for the comming</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Pope ſends his Le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gate into <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>over of the</hi> Legat <hi>from</hi> Rome, <hi>who at last arrived in</hi> England <hi>with his Commiſſion, and beeing much troubled with the Gout, his journey was long and tedious ere hee could get to</hi> London, <hi>who ſhould have beene moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly received at</hi> Black-heath; <hi>but hee deſired not to bee ſo entertained with Pompe and vaine-glory; and therefore he came very privately on his owne Horſe without</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-Barre <hi>called</hi> Bath-place, <hi>where he lay: The Houſe being farniſhed of all manner of Proviſion of my Lords. So after ſome deliberation and conſultation in the ordering of the Kings buſineſſe now in hand by his Commiſsion and Articles of his Ambaſſage, which beeing read, it was determined that the King and the good Queene his lawfull Wife, ſhould be judged at</hi> Bride-wel <hi>and in</hi> Blackfriers, <hi>and ſome place thereabouts the Court to bee kept for the diſputation and determination of the cauſes and differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces betweene the King and the Queene, where they were to repaire before theſe two Legates, who ſat as Iudges; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom the King and Queene were cited and ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to appeare; which was a ſtrange ſight, and the neweſt deviſe that ever was heard or read of in any Story or Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle: A King and a Queene to be compelled to appear in a Court as common perſons within their owne Realme and Dominions, and to abide the judgments and decrees of their Subjects, beeing a Prerogative belonging to the royall Diadem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:53022:43"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:53022:44"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Catherine d'Autriche</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:53022:44"/>
            <head>CHAP. 16. <hi>A new Court erected to determine the Kings caſe, two Cardinals being Iudges, having power to convent the King and Queene, the iſſue thereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a wonderfull thing to conſider the ſtrength of Princes Wils when they are bent to have their pleaſure fulfilled, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no reaſonable perſwaſions wil ſerve the turne; how little doe they regard the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſequels that may enſue aſwell to themſelves as to their Subjects. And amongſt all things there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that makes them more wilful then Carnall Love, and various affecting of voluptuous deſires, wherein nothing could be of greater experience then to ſee what inventions were furniſhed, what Lawes were enacted, what coſtly Edifices of noble and ancient Monaſteries were there over-throwne, what diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of opinions then aroſe, what extortions were then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, how many learned and good men were then put to Death, and what alterations of good ancient Lawes, Cuſtomes, and Charitable foundations were turned from the reliefe of the poore, to the utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and deſolation, almoſt to the ſubverſion of this noble Realme.</p>
            <p>It is a thouſand pitties to underſtand the things that ſince have hapned to this Land, the proofe whereof hath taught all us Engliſh-men lamentable experience. If mens eyes be not blind they may ſee, and if their eares be not ſtopped they may heare; and if pitty bee not exiled, their hearts may relent and lament at the ſequell of this inordinate Love, although it laſted but a while. <hi>O Lord God with-hold thine indignation from us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:53022:45"/>
You ſhall underſtand as I ſayd before, that there was a Court erected at Black-Fryers London, where theſe two Cardinals ſate as Judges: Now will I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe unto you the order of the Court.</p>
            <p>Firſt, there were many tables and benches ſet in manner of a Conſiſtory, one ſeate beeing higher than another for the Judges aloft, above them three degrees high was a Cloth of Eſtate hanged, and a Chaire Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all under the ſame, wherein ſate the King, and ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance off ſate the Queene, and at the Iudges feete ſate the Scribes and Officers for the execution of the Proceſſe; the chiefe Scribe was Doctor <hi>Stevens</hi> after Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and the Apparatour who was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Doctor of the Court, who was one <hi>Cooke</hi> of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</hi> Then before the King, and the Iudges ſate the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> Doctor <hi>Warham,</hi> and all other Biſhops, there ſtood at both ends within, Counſellors Learned in the Spirituall Lawes, as well on the Kings ſide, as the Queenes ſide. Doctor <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Kings Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.</note> afterwards Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Hall</hi> after Biſhop of <hi>Worcester,</hi> with divers others, and Proctors in the ſame Law, were Doctor <hi>Peter,</hi> who was afterwards chiefe Secretarie, and Doctor <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunmill</hi> with divers others. <note place="margin">Queenes Counſell.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now on the other ſide, there were Counſell for the Queene, Doctor <hi>Fiſher</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Standiſh,</hi> Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph</hi> in <hi>Wales,</hi> two brave Noble Divines, eſpecially the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> a very Godly man, whoſe death many Noble men and <note place="margin">The Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> loſt his head for the Queens ſake.</note> many worthy Divines much lamented, who loſt his head about this cauſe ere it was ended upon <hi>Tower hill,</hi> as alſo another ancient Doctor called Doctor <hi>Ridley,</hi> a little man but a great Divine. The Court being thus or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred as is before expreſſed, the Iudges commanded the cryer to proclaim ſilence, whilſt the commiſſion was both read to the Court &amp; to the people there aſſembled:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:53022:45"/>
that done, and ſilence beeing agayne proclaimed, the Scribes commaunded the Cryer to call <hi>King Henry of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The King and Queene called by the Cryer.</note> 
               <hi>England,</hi> whereunto the King anſwered and ſayd, <hi>here;</hi> Then called he agayne the Queene of <hi>England,</hi> by the name of <hi>Katherine Queene of England, come into the Court, &amp;c.</hi> Who made no anſwer thereunto, but roſe immediately out of her Chayre where ſhe ſate: and becauſe ſhee could not come to the King directly, by reaſon of the diſtance, therefore ſhee came round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Court to the King, and kneeled downe at his feete ſaying theſe words in broken <hi>Engliſh as followeth: viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, quoth ſhee, I beſeech you doe mee Iuſtice and <note place="margin">The Queene on her knees pleads for her ſelfe.</note> right, and take ſome pitty upon mee for I am a poore woman and a ſtranger, borne out of your Dominions, having here no indifferent Counſell, and leſſe aſſurance of friendſhip: alas Sir how have I offended you, what offence have I given you, intending to abridge me of life in this ſort, I take God to witnes, I have been to you a true and loyall wife, ever conformable to your will and Pleaſure, never did I contrary or gainſay your minde, but alwayes ſubmitted my ſelfe in all things, wherein you had any delight or dalliance, whether it were little or much, without grudging or any ſigne of diſcontent: I have loved for your ſake all men whom you have loved, whether I had cauſe or not, were they friends or foes, I have beene your wife this twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares, by whom you had many Children: And when I firſt came to your Bed, I take God to witneſſe, I was a Virgin, whether it were true or no, I put it to your Conſcience, if there bee any cauſe that you can alleadge, either of diſhoneſty, or of any other matter, lawfull to put mee from you, I am willing to depart with ſhame and rebuke, but if there bee none, then I pray you let me have Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice at your hands.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:53022:46"/>
               <hi>The King your Father was a man of ſuch an excellent</hi> 
               <note place="margin">She commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth K <hi>Henry</hi> the 7.</note> 
               <hi>wit in his time, that he was accounted a ſecond</hi> Salomon, <hi>and the King of</hi> Spaine <hi>my father</hi> Ferdinand, <hi>was taken for one of the wiſeſt Kings that raigned in</hi> Spaine <hi>theſe many yeares. So they were both wiſe men and noble Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and it is no queſtion but they had wiſe Counſellours of eyther Realme, as be now at this day, who thought at the marriage of you and me, to heare what new deviſes are now invented againſt me, to cauſe me to ſtand to the order of this Court. And I conceive you doe mee much wrong, may you condemne me for not anſwering, having no Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell but ſuch as you have aſſigned me: You muſt conſider that they cannot be indifferent on my part, being your owne Subjects, and ſuch as you have made choyce of out off your owne Councell whereunto they are privy, and dare not diſcloſe your pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore I moſt humbly beſeech you to ſpare me untill I know how my friends in</hi> Spaine <hi>will adviſe me: But if you will not, then let your pleaſure be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And with that ſhe roſe, making a low Curteſie to the King, and departed from thence: all the people thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſhe would have returned againe to her former Seate; but ſhe went preſently out of the Court leaning upon the arme of one of her Servants, who was her ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall receiver, one Mr. <hi>Griffith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King ſeeing that we was ready to goe out of the Court, commaunded the Cryer to call her againe by theſe words, <hi>Katherine Queene of England, come into the Court.</hi> Loe, quoth M. <hi>Griffith,</hi> you are called again: Goe on, quoth ſhe, it is no matter, It is no indifferent <note place="margin">She goes out of the Court.</note> Court for me, therefore I will not tarry; goe on your way; and ſo they departed without any further anſwer at that time, or any appearance in any other Court after that.</p>
            <p>The King ſeeing ſhe was departed thus, and conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her words, ſayd to the <hi>Audience</hi> theſe few words in effect.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:53022:46"/>
Forasmuch, quoth hee as the Queene is gone, I wil <note place="margin">The Kings commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Qu. in her abſence</note> in her abſence declare unto you all: ſhee hath beene to me a true obedient wife, and as comfortable as I could wiſh or deſire, ſhee hath all the virtues and good qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities that belong to a woman of her Dignity, or in any of meaner eſtate, her conditions will well declare the ſame.</p>
            <p>Then quoth my Lord Cardinal, I humbly beſeech your Highneſſe to declare unto this Audience whether I have been the firſt and chiefe moover of this matter unto your Highneſſe, or no, for I am much ſuſpected of all men.</p>
            <p>My Lord Cardinall quoth the King, you have rather <note place="margin">The King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares himſelf to the whole Court.</note> adviſed me to the contrary then been any mover of the ſame. The ſpeciall cauſe that moved me in this matter, is a certaine ſcruple that pricked my conſcience, upon certaine words ſpoken by the Biſhop of <hi>Bayon</hi> the French Ambaſſadour, who came hither to conſult of a Marriage between the Princeſſe our daughter the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> ſecond Sonne to the King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and upon reſolution, and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, hee deſired reſpite to advertiſe the King his Maſter thereof, whether our daughter <hi>Mary</hi> ſhould be legitimate in reſpect of my marriage with this woman beeing ſometimes my Brothers wife, which words (I pondering) begot ſuch a ſcruple in my conſcience that I was much troubled at it, whereby I thought my ſelfe in danger of Gods heavie diſpleaſure, and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and the rather becauſe he ſent us no iſſue Male, for all the iſſue Male that I have had by my wife dyed <note place="margin">All the Kings Iſſue Male by the Queen dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> incontinently after they came into the world, which cauſed me to feare Gods diſpleaſure in the particular. Thus my conſcience being toſſed in that waves of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome doubts, and partly in deſpaire to have any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iſſue, then I had already by this Lady my now wife: It behooved mee to conſider the eſtate of this
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53022:47"/>
Realme and the danger it ſtands in for lack of a Prince to ſucceed mee, I thought it therefore good, in releaſe of this mighty burthen on my Conſcience, as alſo for the quiet eſtate of this Realme, to attempt a tryall in <note place="margin">The chiefe point in the Kings caſe:</note> the Law herein: Whether I might lawfully take ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wife without ſtaine of carnal concupiſcence, by which God may ſend more iſſue, in caſe this my firſt copulation was not good: I not having any diſpleaſure in the perſon, or age of the Queen, with whom I could bee well contented to continue, (if our Marriage may ſtand with the Law of God) as with any woman alive, <note place="margin">The King af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes he hath no diſlike of the Queene,</note> in which point conſiſteth all the doubt that wee goe about, now to know by the Learned wiſedome of you our Prelates and Paſtors, of this Realm and Dominion now here aſſembled for that purpoſe, to whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences and learning I have committed the care and Judgement, according to which I will (God willing) bee well contented to ſubmit my ſelfe, and obey the ſame: And when my Conſcience was ſo troubled, I mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it to you my Lord of <hi>Lincolne</hi> in confeſſion, then beeing my Ghoſtly Father: And forasmuch, as you were then in ſome doubt, you moved me to aske Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the reſt of the Biſhops, whereupon I moved it to you my Lord Cardinall to have your licence, foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as you are Metropolitan, to put this matter in queſtion, and ſo I did to all you my Lords, to which you all granted under your Seales, which is heere to <note place="margin">The King produceth the Licence ſealed by the Card. and the reſt of the Biſhops.</note> ſhew, that is truth quoth the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and I doubt not but my Brothers will acknowledge the ſame. No Sir, not ſo, under correction, quoth the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> for you have not my hand and Seale, no quoth the King, is not this your hand and Seale, and ſhewed it to him in the Inſtrument with Seales? no forſooth quoth the Biſhop, how ſay you to that, quoth the King, to the Biſhop of <hi>Canterburie?</hi> Sir, It is his hand and Seale, quoth the Biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:53022:47"/>
No my Lord quoth the Biſhop of <hi>Rochester,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed you were in hand with mee to have both my hand and Seale, as other of the Lords had done, but I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <note place="margin">The Biſhop of Rocheſter doth denie that he ever ſealed or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</note> that I would never conſent to any ſuch act, for it was much againſt my Conſcience. And therefore my hand and Seale ſhall never bee ſet to ſuch an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (God willing) with many other words to that purpoſe: You ſay truth quoth the Biſhop of <hi>Cantorbury,</hi> ſuch words you uſed, but you were fully reſolved at the laſt that I ſhould ſubſcribe your name, and put to your ſeale, and you would allow of the ſame, all which quoth the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> under correction my Lord is untrue: Well quoth the King, wee will not ſtand in argument with you, you are but one: And ſo the King aroſe up, and the Court was adjourned until <note place="margin">The Court adiourn'd</note> the next day, at which time the Cardinalls ſate again, and the Counſell on both ſides were there preſent to anſwere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Kings Counſell alleadge the matrimonie not good,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Kings counſel alledg the Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not good nor lawfull.</note> 
               <hi>nor lawful at the beginning: Becauſe of the Carnall copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation that Prince</hi> Arthur <hi>had with the Queene: This matter was very narrowly ſcanned on that ſide, and to prove the Carnall Copulation they had many Reaſons and fimilitudes of truth, and beeing anſwered negatively a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine on the other ſide, it ſeemed that al their former alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, were doubtfull to bee tryed, and that no man knew. Yes quoth the Biſhop of</hi> Rocheſter, <hi>I know the truth, how can you know the truth quoth the Cardinall, more</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Queenes Counſel ſpeak</note> 
               <hi>than any other perſon: Yes forſooth my Lord quoth hee, I know that God is the Truth it ſelfe, and never ſaith but</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Biſhop of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</note> 
               <hi>truth, and he ſaith thus.</hi> Quos Deus conjunxit, homo non ſeparet. <hi>And for as much as this marriage was joyned and made by God to a good intent, therefore I ſayd I knew the truth and that man cannot breake upon any wilfull action that which God hath made and conſtituted: So much doe all faithfullmen know, quoth my Lord Cardinall, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:53022:48"/>
               <hi>as you, therefore this reaſon is not ſufficient in this caſe, for the Kings Counſell doe alleadge many preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to prove that it was not lawfull at the beginning</hi> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go <hi>it was not ordained by God, for God doth nothing without a good end, Therefore it is not to be doubted, but if the preſumptions be true which they alleadge to be moſt true, then the Conjunction neither was nor could bee of God. Therefore I ſay unto you my Lord of</hi> Rocheſter, <hi>you know not the truth unleſſe you can avoide their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions upon juſt reaſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then quoth Doctor</hi> Ridley, <hi>it is a great ſhame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Doctor Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley.</note> 
               <hi>to this honourable preſence, that any ſuch preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhould be alleadged in this open Court, what quoth my Lord Cardinall</hi> Domine Doctor Reverende. <hi>No my Lord there belongs no reverence to this matter, for an unreverent matter may bee unreverently anſwered: And ſo left off, rnd then they proceeded to other matters. Thus paſſed this Court from Seſſion to Seſſion, and day to day,</hi> till <note place="margin">The King ſent for the Cardinall.</note> a certaine day the King ſent for the Cardinal <hi>to Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> who went into the privie Chamber to him where hee was, about an hower, and then departed from the King, and went to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in his Barge, the Biſhop of <hi>Carlile</hi> being with him ſayed, it is a hot day today, yea quoth the Cardinall, if you had been as well cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed <note place="margin">The Cardinal returnes and goes home to bed.</note> as I have beene within this hower, you would ſay you were very hot: my Lord no ſooner came home but he went to bed, where he had not lyen above two howers, but my Lord of <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> Miſtris <hi>Anne Bullens</hi> Father, came to ſpeake with him from the King: my Lord commanded he ſhould be broght to his beds ſide, who told him it was the Kings minde he ſhould foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with goe with the Cardinall to the Queene, being then at <hi>Bridewell</hi> in her chamber, and to perſwade her through their wiſedomes to put the whole matter into the Kings own hands, by her conſent, which ſhould be much better for her honour, then ſtand to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:53022:48"/>
the tryall at Law, and thereby bee condemned, which would tend much to her diſhonour and diſcredit.</p>
            <p>To performe the Kings pleaſure, my Lord ſaid hee was ready, and ſo prepared to goe, but quoth he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to my Lord of <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> you and others of the Lords of the Counſell, have put fancies into the head of the King, whereby you trouble all the Realme, but at the length you will get but ſmall thanks both of God and the world, with many other earneſt words and reaſons, which did cauſe my Lord of <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> to bee ſilent kneeling by my Lords beds-ſide, and in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion departed.</p>
            <p>And then my Lord roſe and tooke his barge and went to <hi>Bathhouſe</hi> to Card. <hi>Campaines,</hi> and ſo went together to <hi>Bridewell</hi> to the Queenes lodgings, ſhe being then in her Chamber of Preſence, they told the Gentleman-Uſher that they came to ſpeake with the Queens grace, who told the Queen the Cardinalls were come to ſpeak <note place="margin">The two Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls went on a meſſage from the King to the Queen.</note> with her, then ſhee roſe up having a ſcane of red ſilke about her neck (beeing at worke with her maides) and came to the Cardinalls, where they ſtaied attending her comming, at whoſe approach quoth ſhe. Alack my Lords, I am ſorrie that you have atended on me ſo long what is your pleaſures with me: If it pleaſe your grace, quoth the Cardinall, to go to your privie Chamber, we will ſhew you the cauſe of our comming.</p>
            <p>My Lord ſaid ſhee, if you have any thing to ſay to mee, ſpeak it openly before all theſe folke, for I feare nothing that you can ſay to me or againſt mee, but that I am willing all the world ſhould both ſee &amp; heare it, <hi>and therefore ſpeake your mindes openly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then began my Lord to ſpeake to her in Latin: nay good my Lord ſpeak to me in Engliſh, quoth ſhe, although I doe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Cardinal declares the cauſe of their going.</note> 
               <hi>underſtand ſome Latin, Forſooth quoth my Lord, good Madam, if it pleaſe your Grace, wee come both to know your mind what you are diſpoſed to do in this matter, and</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:53022:49"/>
to declare to you ſecretly our Counſels and opinions, which wee doe for very zeale and obedience to your Grace.</p>
            <p>My Lords quoth ſhee, I thanke you for your good <note place="margin">Queens an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</note> wills, but to make anſwer to your requeſts I cannot ſo ſuddenly, for I was ſet amongſt my maids at worke, little thinking of any ſuch matter, wherein is requiſite ſome deliberation, and a better head then mine to make anſwere, for I need Counſell in this caſe which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes me ſo neare, and friends here I have none, they are in <hi>Spaine in my owne Countrey:</hi> Alſo my Lords, I am a poore woman of too weake Capacitie to anſwere ſuch noble perſons of wiſedome as you are, in ſo weighty a matter. And therefore I pray you be good to mee a woman deſtitute of friendſhippe heere in a forraigne Region, and your Counſell I alſo ſhall bee glad to heare, and therewith ſhee tooke my Lord by the hand and led him into her Privie Chamber, with the other Cardinall, where they ſtayed a while, and I heard her voice loud, but what ſhee ſaid I know not.</p>
            <p>This done, they went to the King, and made a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation unto him of the paſſages betweene the Queene and them, and ſo they departed.</p>
            <p>This ſtrange caſe proceeded and went forwards from Court day to Court day, untill it came to that, that every man expected to hear Iudgement given, at which time all their proceedings were openly read in Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, That done, the Kings Counſell at the Barre mooved for Iudgement, quoth Cardinall <note place="margin">Cardinall Campains re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to give Iudgement.</note> 
               <hi>Campaines,</hi> I will not give judgement untill I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the whole proceedings to the Pope, whoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and Commandment I will in this Caſe obſerve: The matter is too high for us to give haſty judgement, conſidering the perſons and the doubtfull occaſions al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, and alſo whoſe Commiſſioners wee are by whoſe authority we ſit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:53022:49"/>
It is good reaſon therefore that wee make our chiefe <note place="margin">He makes a ſpeech.</note> Lord of Counſell in the ſame before wee proceede to judgement definitive: I came not to pleaſe for any Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, Reward, or feare of any perſon alive, be he King or otherwiſe, I have no ſuch reſpect to the perſon, that I ſhould offend my Conſcience. And the party Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant will make no anſwere here; but rather doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale from us; I am an old man both weake and ſickly, and looke every day for Death; what ſhal it avayle me to put my Soule in danger of Gods diſpleaſure to my utter damnation, for the favour of any Prince in this World. My being here is onely to ſee Juſtice admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred according to my Conſcience.</p>
            <p>The Defendant ſuppoſeth that wee bee not indifferent Judges, conſidering the Kings high dignity and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority within his Realme. And wee beeing both his Subjects, ſhee thinkes wee will not doe her juſtice: and therefore to avoyd all theſe <hi>Ambiguities,</hi> I adjourn the Court for the Time according to the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> from whence our jurisdiction is derived: For if wee ſhould goe further then our Commiſſion doth warrant us, it were but a folly and blame worthy; becauſe then wee ſhalbe breakers of the Orders from whom we have (as I ſayd) our authority derived; and ſo the Court was diſſolved and no more done.</p>
            <p>Thereupon by the Kings Commandment ſtept up the Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> and with a haughty countenance <note place="margin">The Duke of Suffolke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals.</note> uttered theſe words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It was never thus in England untill we had Cardinals amongſt us.</hi> Which Words were ſet forth with ſuch vehemency, that all men marvailed what he intended, the Duke further expreſſing ſome opprobrious Words.</p>
            <p>My Lord Cardinall perceiving his vehemency, ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſayd: Sir, of all men in this Realme you have leaſt cauſe to diſprayſe Cardinals, for if I poore Cardinall <note place="margin">The Cardinals mild anſwere.</note>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:53022:50"/>
had not beene, you ſhould not at this preſent have had a head on your ſhoulders, wherewith to make ſuch a brag in diſpute of us, who wiſh you no harme; ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have given you ſuch cauſe to be offended with us. I would have you thinke my Lord, I and my Brother wiſh the King as much happineſſe, and the Realme as much honour, Wealth, and peace, as you, or any other Subject of what degree ſoever hee be within this Realme, and would as gladly accompliſh his lawfull deſires.</p>
            <p>And now my Lord, I pray you ſhew mee what you <note place="margin">His reaſon why hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not to Iudgment.</note> would doe in ſuch a Caſe as this, if you were one of the Kings Commiſſioners in a forraigne Region about ſome weighty matter, the conſultation whereof was very doubtfull to be decided; would you not advertiſe the Kings Majeſty ere you went through with the ſame: I doubt not but you would; and therefore abate your malice and ſpight, and conſider wee are Commiſſioners for a Time, and cannot by vertue of a Commiſſion proceed to judgement without the knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the head of the authority and lycence obtayned from him, who is the Pope.</p>
            <p>Therefore doe wee neyther more nor leſſe then our Commiſſion allows us: and if any man wil be offended with us, hee is an unwiſe man: Therefore pacifie your ſelfe my Lord, and ſpeake like a man of Honour and Wiſedome, (or hold your peace) ſpeake not reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully of your friends, you beſt know what friendſhip I have ſhowne you: I never did reveale to any perſon till <note place="margin">The Duke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harted diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented.</note> now, eyther to mine owne prayſe, or your diſhonour. Whereupon the Duke went his way, and ſayd no more, being much diſcontented.</p>
            <p>This matter continued thus a long Seaſon, and the <note place="margin">The King of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. The Cardinals commiſſion his excuſe.</note> King was in diſpleaſure againſt my Lord Cardinal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Suit had no better ſucceſſe to his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the Cardinal excuſed himſelf by his
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53022:50"/>
Commiſſion which gave him no authority to proceed to judgement without the knowledge of the Pope, who reſerved the ſame to himſelf. At laſt they were adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed by a Poſt that they ſhould take deliberation in the matter untill his Councell were opened, which ſhould not be til <hi>Bartholmew-tide</hi> next.</p>
            <p>The king thinking it would be too long ere it would bee determined, ſent an Ambaſſador to the Pope to perſwade him to ſhew ſo much favor to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as that it might be ſooner determined.</p>
            <p>On this Embaſſage went Doctor <hi>Stephen Gardener,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dr. Gardener ſent Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor to th' pope</note> then called by the name of Doctor <hi>Steven,</hi> Secretary to the King, afeer wards Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi> This Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour ſtayed there till the latter end of Summer, of whoſe returne you ſhall hereafter heare.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 17. <hi>Of certaine paſſages conducing to the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals fall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OW the King commaunded the Queene to be removed from the Court, and ſent to another; place &amp; preſently after the King rod on Progreſſe, and had in his Company Miſtris <hi>Anne Bolloigne;</hi> in which time Cardinall <hi>Campadnes</hi> made ſuite to bee diſcharged, and ſent home to <hi>Rome:</hi> &amp; in the interim returned Mr. Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and it was concluded that my Lord ſhould come to the King to <hi>Grafton in Northampton-ſhire;</hi> as alſo <note place="margin">The Cardinal ſent for to the Court.</note> Cardiall <hi>Campaines</hi> beeing a ſtranger, ſhould bee conducted thither by my Lord Cardinall. And ſo the next Sunday there were divers opinions
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:53022:51"/>
that the King would not ſpeak with my Lord; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon there were many great Wagers layd.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Prelates being come to the Court, and lighting, expected to be received of the great Officers as the manner was, but they found the contrary: Nevertheleſſe becauſe the Cardinall <hi>Campaine</hi> was a ſtranger, the Officers met him with ſtaves in their hands in the outward Court, and ſo conveyed him to his lodging prepared for him; and after my Lord had brought him to his lodging he departed, thinking to have gone to his Chamber as hee was wont to do. But it was told him hee had no lodging or Chamber ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted <note place="margin">He found but ſmall content.</note> for him in the Court; which newes did much aſtoniſh him.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Henry Norris</hi> who was then Groome of the ſtoole, came unto him, and deſired him to take his Chamber for a while untill an other was provided for him, for I aſſure you, quoth he, here is but little room in this Houſe for the King, and therefore I humbly beſeech your Grace accept of mine for a Seaſon. My Lord thanking him for his curteſie, went to his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where hee ſhifted his riding apparrell.</p>
            <p>In the meane time came divers Noblemen of his friends to welcome him to the Court, by whom my Lord was advertiſed of all things touching the Kings favour or diſpleaſure; and being thus informed of the Cauſe thereof, hee was more able to excuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>So my Lord made him ready, and went to the Chamber of Preſence with the other Cardinall, where the Lords of the Councell ſtood all of a Row in order in the Chamber, and all the Lords ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted them both: And there were preſent many Gentlemen which came on purpoſe to obſerve the <note place="margin">Great ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the K. diſpleaſure.</note> meeting and countenance of the King to my Lord Cardinall: Then immediatly after, the King
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:53022:51"/>
came into the Chamber of Preſence ſtanding under the Cloath of State.</p>
            <p>Then my Lord Cardinall tooke Cardinall <hi>Campaine</hi> by the hand, and kneeled downe before the King, but what hee ſayd unto him, I know not, but his Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was amiable, and his Majeſty ſtooped downe, and with both his hands tooke him up, and then tooke him by the hand, and went to the Window with him, and there talked with him a good while.</p>
            <p>Then to have beheld the Countenance of the Lords and Noblemen that had layd Wagers, it would have made you ſmile, eſpecially thoſe that had layd their money that the King would not ſpeake with him.</p>
            <p>Thus were they deceived, for the King was in earneſt diſcourſe with him, inſomuch that I could heare the King ſay, how can this be, is not this your hand, and pulled a Letter out of his owne boſome and ſhewed the ſame to my Lord. And as I perceived, my Lord ſo anſwered the ſame, that the King had no more to ſay; but ſayd to my Lord, goe to your Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and take my Lord Cardinall to keepe you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and after Dinner I will ſpeake further with you, and ſo they departed. And the King that day dined with Miſtris <hi>Anne Bulloign</hi> in her Chamber.</p>
            <p>Then was there ſet up in the Preſence Chamber a Table for my Lord, and other Lords of the Councell, where they dined together; and ſitting at Dinner tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of divers matters, The King ſhould doe well, quoth my Lord Cardinall, to ſend his Biſhops and Chaplaines home to their Cures and Benefices. Yea marry, quoth my Lord of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> and ſo it were meete for you to doe alſo. I would be very well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented therewith, quoth my Lord, if it were the Kings pleaſure to lycence mee with his Graces
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:53022:52"/>
leave to goe to my Cure at <hi>Wincheſter:</hi> Nay quoth my Lord of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> to your Benefice at <hi>Yorke;</hi> where your greateſt Honour and Charge is. Even as it ſhall pleaſe the King, quoth my Lord Cardinall; and ſo they fell upon other Diſcourſes. For indeed the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility were loath hee ſhould be ſo neere the King, as to continue at <hi>Winchester.</hi> Immediately after Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they fell to Councell till the Waiters had alſo dined.</p>
            <p>I heard it reported by thoſe that waited on the King at dinner, that Miſtres <hi>Anne Bulloigne</hi> was offended as much as ſhe durſt, that the King did ſo graciouſly <note place="margin">Miſtris Anne Bulloigne of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended for the Cardinalls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaynment.</note> entertaine my Lord Cardinall. Saying, <hi>Sir, Is it not a marvailous thing to ſee into what great debt and danger hee hath brought you, with all your Subjects?</hi> How ſo, quoth the King? <hi>Forſooth, quoth ſhee, there is not a man in all your whole Realme of England, worth a hundred pounds, but hee hath indebted you to him, (meaning of Loane, which the King had of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">She complains of him.</note> 
               <hi>his Subjects.</hi> Well, well, quoth the King, for that matter there was no blame in him, for I know that matter better then you, or any elſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nay, quoth ſhee, beſides that, what exploits hath hee wrought in ſeverall parts and places of this Realme, to your great ſlaunder and diſgrace? There is never a Nobleman, but if hee had done halfe ſo much as hee hath done, were well worthy to looſe his head. Yea, if my Lord of</hi> Norfolke, <hi>my Lord of</hi> Suffolke, <hi>my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or any other man had done much leſſe then hee hath done, they ſhould have lost their heads ere this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then I perceive (quoth the King) you are none of my Lord Cardinals friends. <hi>Why Sir, quoth ſhee, I have no cauſe, nor any that love you? No more hath your Grace, if you did well conſider his indirect and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull doings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By that time the Waiters had dyned and tooke up
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:53022:52"/>
the Table and ſo for that time ended their Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>You may perceive by this how the old malice was not forgotten: but begins to kindle and be ſet on fire, which was ſtirred by his auncient enemies, whom I have formerly named in this treatiſe.</p>
            <p>The King for that time departed from Miſtris <hi>Anne Bulloigne,</hi> and came to the Chamber of Preſence, and called for my Lord, and in the great window had a long diſcourſe with hin, but of what I know not, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the King tooke him by the hand and led him into the privie Chamber, and ſate in Conſultation with him all alone without any other of the Lords, till it was darke night, which blanked all his enemies ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoer, who had no other way but by Miſtris <hi>Anne Bulloigne,</hi> in whom was all their truſt and affiance, for the accompliſhment of their enterpriſes, for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her they feared all their purpoſes would bee fruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</p>
            <p>Now at night was warning given me, that there was no roome for my Lord to lodge in the Court, ſo that I was forced to provide my Lord a lodging in the Countrey about <hi>Eaſton</hi> at one <hi>Mr. Empstons houſe,</hi> where my Lord came to ſupper by torch-light, beeing late before my Lord parted from the King, who willed him to reſort to him in the morning, for that he would talke further with him about the ſame matter, and in the morning my Lord came againe, at whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Kings Majeſty was ready to ride, willing my Lord to conſult with the Lords in his abſence, and ſaid he would not talke with him, commanding my Lord to depart with Cardinall <hi>Campaine</hi> who had <note place="margin">The King would not talke with the Cardinall.</note> already taken his leave of the King.</p>
            <p>This ſuddaine departure of the Kings, was the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall labour of <hi>Miſtris Anne Bulloigne who rode with him purpoſely to draw him away, becauſe he ſhould not</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:53022:53"/>
returne till the departure of the Cardinalls. The King rode that morning to viewe a peice of ground, to make a Parke of, which was afterwards and is at this time, called <hi>Harewell Parke,</hi> where Miſtris <hi>Anne</hi> had provided him a place to dine in, fearing his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne before my Lord Cardinals departure,</p>
            <p>So my Lord rode away after dinner with Cardinall <hi>Campaine,</hi> who tooke his jorney towards <hi>Rome,</hi> with the Kings reward, but what it was I am not certaine.</p>
            <p>After their departure, it was told the King, that <hi>Cardinall Campaine</hi> was departed and had great Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with him of my Lord Cardinalls of <hi>England</hi> to bee conveyed in great ſums to <hi>Rome,</hi> whither they ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hee would ſecretly repaire out of this Realme. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that they cauſed a Poſt to ride after the Cardinall to ſearch him, who overtooke him at <hi>Callis,</hi> and ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him untill ſearch was made, but there was found <note place="margin">They ſearch the Cardinall at Callis.</note> no more then was received of the King for a reward.</p>
            <p>Now after Cardinall <hi>Campaine</hi> was gone, <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellmas terme</hi> drew on, againſt which time my Lord <hi>Cardinall</hi> repaired to his houſe at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and when the Terme began, hee went into the Hall in ſuch manner as he was acuſtomed to doe, and ſate in the <hi>Chancery,</hi> being then Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> after which day he never ſate more, the next day hee ſtayed at home for the comming of my Lord of <hi>Norfolk and Suffolke,</hi> who came not that day, but the next: And did declare unto my Lord that it was the Kings pleaſure he ſhould ſurrender up the great <hi>Seale</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The King ſends for the great Seale.</note> into their hands, and that he ſhould depart unto <hi>Aſhur,</hi> which is a houſe near unto <hi>Hampton Court</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing unto the <hi>Biſhopricke of Wincheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Cardinall demanded of them to ſee their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion that gave them ſuch authority, who anſwered again, they were ſufficient Commiſſioners, and had Authority to doe no leſſe from the Kings owne mouth,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:53022:53"/>
notwithſtanding, he would in no wiſe agree to their demand in that behalfe, without further knowledge of their Authority, telling them that the great Seale <note place="margin">He refuſeth to deliver up the broad Seal</note> was delivered to him by the Kings owne perſon to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Miniſtration thereof, together with the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellorſhip during the term of his life, whereof for ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he had the Kings Letters, Patents to ſhew, which matter was much debated between him and the Dukes with many great words which he tooke patiently, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the Dukes were faine to depart without their purpoſe at that time, and returned to <hi>Windſor to</hi> the King, and the next day they returned to my Lord with the Kings Letters, whereupon in obedience to the Kings command, my Lord delivered to them the broad Seale, which they brought to <hi>Windſor to the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then my Lord called his Officers before him and tooke account of all things they had in their charge, and in his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Card. ſets his houſe in order.</note> 
               <hi>Gallery were ſet divers Tables upon which were layed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and great ſtore of rich ſtuffes, as whole pieces of ſilke of all colours, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>elvets, Sattins, Muskes, Taffaties, Grogarams, Scarlets, and divers rich Commodities. Alſo there were</hi> 1000. <hi>pieces of fine Hollands, and the hangings of the Gallery with cloath of Gold, and cloath of Silver, and rich cloath of Bodkin of divers colours, which were hanged in expectation of the Kings comming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo of one ſide of the Gallery were hanged the rich ſuits of Copes of his owne providing, which were made for Colledges at</hi> Oxford <hi>and</hi> Ipſwich, <hi>they were the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt that ever I ſaw in all my life; Then had he two cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers adjoyning to the Gallery, the one moſt commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the guilt Chamber, the other the Councell Chamber, wherein were ſet two broad and long Tables, whereupon was ſet ſuch abundance of Plate of all ſorts, as was almoſt incredible to be believed, a great part being al of clean gold, and upon every table and cupboard where the Plate was ſet</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:53022:54"/>
were bookes importing every kinde of plate and every piece with the contents and the weight thereof.</p>
            <p>Thus were all things furniſhed and prepared giving the charge of the ſaid ſtuffe, with other things remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in every office, to be delivered to the King, as he gave charge, all things beeing ordered as is before rehearſed, my Lord prepared to depart and reſolved to goe by water, but before his going: Sir <hi>William Gaſcoigne</hi> beeing his Treaſurer came unto him and ſaid, Sir quoth he, I am ſorry for your Grace, for I heare you are ſtraight to goe to the <hi>Tower;</hi> Is this the beſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort quoth my Lord, you can give to your maſter in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity? It hath alwaies beene your inclination to bee light of credit, and much lighter in reporting of lyes, I would you ſhould know Sir <hi>William and all</hi> thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters too, that it is untrue, for I never deſerved to come there: Although it hath pleaſed the King to take my houſe ready furniſhed for his pleaſure, at this time I would all the world ſhould know, I have nothing but it is of right for him, and of him I received all that I have: It is therefore convenient and reaſon to tender the ſame to him againe.</p>
            <p>Then my Lord with his traine of Gentlemen and yeomen which was no ſmall company, took his barge at his privie ſtairs, and went by water to <hi>Putney,</hi> at which time upon the water were abundance of boates filled with people, expecting to have ſeene my Lord Cardinall goe to the <hi>Tower,</hi> which they longed to ſee. Oh wondring and new-fangled world, is it not a time to conſider the mutability of this uncertaine world! for the common people ever deſire things for novelties ſake, which after turne to their ſmall profit or advantage. For if you mark the ſequell, they had ſmall cauſe to rejoyce at his fall, I cannot ſee but all men in favour are envyed by the common people, though they doe mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſter Iuſtice truly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:53022:54"/>
Thus continued my Lord at <hi>Aſhur,</hi> 3. or 4. weekes without either Beds, ſheets, Table-cloaths or diſhes to eate their meate in, or wherewith to buy any. But there was good ſtore of all kind of victualls, &amp; of beere and wine plenty, but afterwards my Lord borrowed ſome Plate and diſhes of the Biſhop of <hi>Carlile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus continued my Lord in this ſtrange eſtate till after <hi>Alhollantide,</hi> and beeing one day at dinner; Mr. <hi>Crumwell</hi> told him that he ought in Conſcience to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the true and good ſervice, that he and other of his ſervants had done him, who never forſooke him in weale nor woe, then quoth my Lord alas <hi>Tom:</hi> you know I have nothing to give you nor them; which makes me both aſhamed and ſorry that I have nothing to requite your faithfull ſervices, whereupon Maſter <hi>Cromwell</hi> told my Lord that he had abundance of Chaplaines that were preferred by his Grace to Benefices of ſome 1000. pound, and others 500 pound, ſome more and ſome leſſe, and wee your poore ſervants who take more paines in one dayes ſervice, then all your idle Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains have done in a yeare, and therefore if they will not impart liberally to you in your great indigence, it is pitty they ſhould live, and all the world will have them in iudignation for their great ingratitude to their Maſter.</p>
            <p>Afterwards my Lord commanded me to call all his Gentlemen and Yeomen up into the great Chamber, commanding all the Gentlemen to ſtand on the right hand, and the Yeomen on the left ſide, at laſt my <hi>Lord</hi> came out in his Rochet, upon a Violet gowne like a Biſhop, who went with his Chaplins to the upper end of the Chamber where was a great windowe, behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his goodly number of ſervants, who could not ſpeake to them untill the tears ran downe his checks, which beeing perceived of his ſervants, cauſed foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of teares <hi>to guſh out of their ſorrowfull</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:53022:55"/>
               <hi>eyes in ſuch ſort as would cauſe my heart to relent.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">He ſpeaks to them all.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>At laſt my Lord ſpake to them to this effect and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſaying, moſt faithfull Gentlemen and true-hearted Yeomen, I much lament that in my proſperity I did not ſo much for you as I might have done, and was in my power to doe, I conſider that if in my proſperity I ſhould have preferred you to the King, then ſhould I have incurred the Kings Servants diſpleaſure, who would not ſpare to report behinde my back that there could no office in the Court eſcape the Cardinall and his ſervants, and by that meanes I ſhould have run into open ſlander of all the world, but now it is come to paſſe: that it hath pleaſed the King to take all that I have into his hands, ſo that I have now nothing to give you, for I have nothing left me but the bare cloaths on my back, with many other words in their phraſe, and ſo he giving them all hearty thanks, went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and afterwards many of his ſervants departed from him, ſome to their wives, ſome to their friends, Maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> Cromwell <hi>to</hi> London, <hi>it beeing then the beginning of the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 18. <hi>The Cardinall is accuſed of high Treaſon in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Houſe, againſt which accuſation Mr.</hi> Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well <hi>(late ſervant to him) being a Burgeſſe in the Parliament made defence.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He aforeſaid Maſter <hi>Cromwell</hi> after his departure from my Lord, deviſed with himſelfe to bee one of the Burgeſſes of the Parliament: And being at <hi>London</hi> hee chanced to meete one Sir <hi>Thomas Ruſſell</hi> Knight, a ſpeciall friend of his, whoſe ſon was one of the Burgeſſes of the Parliament, of whom by
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:53022:55"/>
meanes he obteyned his roome, and ſo put his feete into the Parliament houſe, and 3. dayes after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pature from my Lord, hee came againe to <hi>Aſhur,</hi> and I beeing there with my Lord, he ſaid unto mee with a pleaſant Countenance: I have adventured my feet where I will bee better regarded, ere the Parliament be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved: And after hee had ſome talke with my Lord, he made haſte to <hi>London,</hi> becauſe he would not bee abſent from the Parliament, to the intent he might acquaint my Lord what was there objected againſt him, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <note place="margin">He informed his Lord what was objected againſt him.</note> the better to make his defence, inſomuch that there was nothing at any time objected againſt my Lord, but hee was readie to make anſwere thereunto, by meanes whereof he beeing earneſt in his Maſters behalfe was reputed the moſt faithfull ſervant to his Maſter of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and was generally of all men highly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>Then was there brought a Bill of Articles into the Parliament houſe to have my Lord condempned of high <note place="margin">Articles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinall diſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled by Mr. Cromwell.</note> Treaſon, againſt which Bill Maſter <hi>Cromwell</hi> did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh ſo diſcreetly and with ſuch witty perſwaſions, that the ſame would take no effect; Then were his enemies conſtrained to indite him of a Premunire, &amp; al was to intitle the King to all his goods and poſſeſſions, which hee had obteyned and purchaſed for the maintenance of <note place="margin">They charge him with a Premunire.</note> his Colledges of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> which were both moſt ſumptuous buildings. To the Judges that were ſent to take my Lords anſwere here in hee thus <note place="margin">Iudges ſent to examine the Cardinall. His anſwere.</note> anſwered.</p>
            <p>My Lords Judges quoth hee; the King knoweth, whether I have offended or no in uſing my Preogative for the which I am indicted, I have the Kings licence in my Coffer to ſhew under his hand and broad Seale, for the executing and uſing thereof in moſt large man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the which now are in the hands of mine enemies, but becauſe I wil not here ſtand to contend with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:53022:56"/>
in his owne caſe, I will here preſently before <note place="margin">The Cardinal doth ſubmit to the King.</note> you confeſſe the Indictment, and put my ſelfe wholy to the mercy and grace of the King, truſting that he hath a conſcience and reaſon to conſider the truth, and my humble ſubmiſſion and obedience wherein I might wel ſtand to my triall with Juſtice. Thus much may you ſay to his Highneſſe, that I wholie ſubmit my ſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his obedience in all things to his Princely will and pleaſure whom I never diſobeyed or repugned, but was alwaies contented and glad to pleaſe him before God, whom I ought moſt chiefly to have believed and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which I now repent: I moſt heartily deſire you to have me commended to him, for whom I ſhall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my life pray to God to ſend him much proſperitie, honour and victory over his enemies. And ſo they left him.</p>
            <p>After which Mr. <hi>Shelley</hi> the Judge was ſent to ſpeak with my Lord, who underſtanding he was come iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of his privie Chamber and came to him to know his buſineſſe, who after due ſalutation did declare unto him that the Kings pleaſure was to demand my Lords houſe called <hi>Yorke-place</hi> neare <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> belonging to the Biſhopricke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> And that you doe paſſe the <note place="margin">The King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands Yorke houſe.</note> ſame according to the Lawes of this Realme, his Highneſſe hath ſent for all his Iudges and learned Counſell to know their opinions for your aſſurance thereof, who bee fully reſolved that your grace muſt make a Recognizance and before a Iudge acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confeſſe the right thereof to belong to the King and his Succeſſors, and ſo his Highneſſe ſhall bee aſſured thereof.</p>
            <p>Wherefore it hath pleaſed the King to ſend mee hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take of you the Recognizance, having in your Grace ſuch affiance that you will not refuſe to doe ſo, therefore I doe deſire to know your Graces plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure therein.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:53022:56"/>
Maſter <hi>Shelley</hi> quoth my Lord, I know the King of <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals anſwere.</note> his owne nature is of a Royall ſpirit, not requiring more then reaſon ſhall leade him to by the Lawe. And therefore I counſell you and all other Iudges and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men of his Counſell to put no more into his head then Law, that may ſtand with Conſcience for when you tell him, that although this bee Lawe, yet it is not Conſcience, for Law without conſcience is not fit to bee miniſtred by a King nor his Counſell, nor by any of his Miniſters, for every Counſell to a King ought to have reſpect to Conſcience, before the rigour of the Law: <hi>Laus est facere quod decet, non quod licet.</hi> The King ought for his Royall dignitie and prerogative to mitigate the rigour of the Lawe, and therefore in his Princely place hee hath conſtituted a Chancellour, to order for him the ſame, and therefore the Court of Chauncery hath beene commonly called the Court of Conſcience, for that it hath juriſdiction to command the Law in every caſe, to deſiſt from the rigour of the execution: And now I ſay to you Maſter <hi>Shelley,</hi> have I a power, or may I with Conſcience give that away which is now mine for mee and my Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors? if this bee Law and Conſcience, I pray you ſhew me your opinion.</p>
            <p>Forſooth quoth hee, there is no great conſcience in it, but having regard to the Kings great power, it may the better ſtand with Conſcience, who is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to rcompence the Church of <hi>Yorke</hi> with the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble value.</p>
            <p>That I know well quoth my <hi>Lord,</hi> but there is no ſuch condition, but onely a bare and ſimple departure of others rights, if every Biſhop ſhould doe ſo, then might every Prelate give away the Patrimony of the Church, and ſo in proces of timeleave nothing for their Succeſſors to maintain their dignities, which would be but little to the Kings honour.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:53022:57"/>
Well quoth my Lord, let me ſee your Commiſſion which was ſhewed to him, then quoth my Lord, tell his Highneſſe that I am his moſt faithfull Subject and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient beadeſman, whoſe command I will in no wife diſobey, but will in all things fulfill his pleaſure, as you the Fathers of the Law ſay I may. Therefore I charge your Conſcience to diſcharge mee, and ſhew his Highnes from mee that I muſt deſire his Majeſty to remember, there is both heaven and hell, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Clarke took and wrote the Recognizance and after ſome ſecret talke they departed.</p>
            <p>Thus continued my Lord at <hi>Aſhur,</hi> receiving day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meſſages from the Court, ſome good, and ſome bad, but more ill then good, for his enemies perceiving the good affection the King bare alwaies to him, deviſed a means to diſquiet his patience, thinking thereby to give him occaſion to fret and chafe, that death ſhould rather enſue then otherwiſe, which they moſt deſired, for they feared him more after his fall, <hi>then they did in his proſperitie. Fearing hee ſhould by reaſon of the Kings favour riſe againe, and bee againe in favour, and great at the Court, they his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies might bee in danger of their lives, for their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty wrongfully miniſtered unto him, and by their maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſurmiſes invented and brought to paſſe against him, And did continually finde new matters againſt him to make him vexe and frett, but hee was a wiſe man, and did arme himſelfe with much pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>At Chriſtmas hee fell very ſore ſicke most likely</hi> 
               <note place="margin">He fell ſicke.</note> to dye, the King hearing thereof was very ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <note place="margin">The King ſends his Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</note> and ſent <hi>Doctor Butts</hi> his Phyſitian unto him, who found him very dangerouſly ſicke in Bedde, and returned to the King. The King demanded ſaying, have you ſeene yonder man? yes Sir quoth hee, how doe you like him quoth the King? Sir
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:53022:57"/>
quoth he, if you will have him dead, I will warrant you he wilbe dead within theſe foure dayes, if hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no comfort from you ſhortly</p>
            <p>Marry God forbid, quoth the King, that hee ſhould dye, for I would not looſe him for twenty Thouſand pounds. I pray you goe to him, and doe youre care to him.</p>
            <p>Then muſt your Grace, quoth Doctor <hi>Buts,</hi> ſend him ſome comfortable meſſage; So I will, quoth the King by you; therefore make ſpeed to him againe, and you ſhall deliver him this Ring from me for a Token. <hi>In the which Ring was the Kings Image engraven with a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Th' King ſends his ring in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of favour.</note> 
               <hi>Ruby as like the King, as might be deviſed;</hi> This Ring hee knoweth well, for hee gave mee the ſame; and tell him that I am not offended with him in my heart for any thing. And that ſhalbe known ſhortly; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bid him pluck up his heart, &amp; be of good comfort: And I charge you come not from him till you have brought him out of the danger of Death, if it bee poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
            <p>Then ſpake the King to Miſtris <hi>Anne Bulloign,</hi> good <note place="margin">And miſtris Anne Bulloign her Tablet.</note> Sweet heart as you love me, ſend the Cardinall a To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at my Requeſt, and in ſo doing you ſhall deſerve our Thankes: Shee being diſpoſed not to offend the King, would not diſobey his loving Requeſt; but tooke incontinently her Tablet of gold that hung at her ſide, and delivered it to Doctor <hi>Buts,</hi> with very gentle and loving Words; and ſo hee departed to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhur</hi> with ſpeed; and after him the King ſent Doctor <hi>Cromer,</hi> Doctor <hi>Clement,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Wotton</hi> to conſult and adviſe with Doctor <hi>Buts</hi> for my Lords re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
            <p>Now after Doctor <hi>Buts</hi> had beene with him, and delivered him the Tokens from the King and Miſtris <hi>Anne Bulloigne,</hi> with the moſt comfortable Words he could deviſe on the Kings and Miſtris <hi>Annes</hi> behalfe,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:53022:58"/>
Hee advanced himſelfe in his Bed, and received the Tokens very joyfully, giving him many thankes for his paines and good comfort, Hee told him further, that the Kings pleaſure was, that hee ſhould miniſter unto him for his Health. And for the better and more aſſured wayes, hee hath alſo ſent Doctor <hi>Cromer,</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Clement,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Wotton,</hi> all to joyne for your recovery. Therefore my Lord, quoth Doctor <hi>Buts,</hi> it were well they were called to viſite you, and to conſult with them for your diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>At which motion my Lord was contented, and ſent for them to heare their judgements; but hee truſted more to Doctor <hi>Cromer,</hi> then all the reſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was the very meanes to bring him from <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> and gave him partly his exhibition in <hi>Paris.</hi> To be ſhort, in foure dayes they ſet him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <note place="margin">In foure dayes they cured him.</note> upon his feete, and hee had gotten him a good ſtomacke to meate. All this done, and my Lord in a right good way of amendment, they tooke their leaves and departed, to whom my Lord offered his Reward; but they refuſed, ſaying, the King hath given a ſpeciall Commandment that they ſhould take nothing of him, for at their returne he would reward them of his owne coſt.</p>
            <p>After this, my Lord continued at <hi>Aſhur</hi> till <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-maſſe,</hi> before and againſt which Feaſt, the King cauſed to be ſent to my Lord three or foure loads of ſtuffe; and moſt thereof, except Beds and Kitchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuffe, <note place="margin">The Kingſent three or foure loads of houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſtuffe.</note> was loaded in Standars, wherein was both plate and rich Hangings, and Chappell ſtuffe, which was done without the knowledge of the Lords of the Councell; for all which, hee rendered the King moſt humble and hearty thankes: And afterwards made ſuite unto the King to be removed from <hi>Aſhur</hi> to <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> which requeſt was granted.</p>
            <p>The Houſe of <hi>Richmond</hi> a little before was repaired
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:53022:58"/>
by my L. to his great coſt, for the K. had made an exchang with him for <hi>Hampton-court.</hi> Had the Lords of the Counſell knowne of theſe favours from the King to the Cardinall, they would have perſwaded the King to the contrary, for they feared leaſt his now abode neere the King, might move the King at ſome ſeaſon to reſort un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and to call him home againe, conſidering the great and daily affection the King bare unto him. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they moved the King that my Lord might goe downe to the <hi>North,</hi> to his benefice there, where hee might bee a good ſtay (as they alleadged) to the Countrey, to which the King condiſcended thinking no leſſe but that all had been true according to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, beeing with ſuch colour of deep conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the King was ſtraitway perſwaded to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, whereupon my Lord of <hi>Norfolke</hi> by Maſter <hi>Cromwell</hi> who daily did reſort to my Lord, that hee ſhould ſay to him that he muſt goe home to his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, well then <hi>Thomas</hi> quoth my Lord, wee will goe then to <hi>Wincheſter:</hi> I will then quoth Maſter <hi>Cromwell</hi> tell my Lord of <hi>Norfolke what you ſay,</hi> and ſo hee did at his next meeting of him: what ſhould he doe there quoth the Duke? let him goe to the rich Biſhoprick of <hi>Yorke;</hi> where his greateſt honour and charge lyeth, and ſo ſhew to him: The Lords who were not his friends perceiving that my Lord was diſpoſed to plant himſelfe ſo nigh the King, thought then to withdraw his appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite from <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> moved the King to give my Lord a penſion of fowre thouſand markes out of <hi>Winchester,</hi> and all the reſt to be diſtributed amongſt the Nobilitie and his ſervants: And ſo likewiſe to divide the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of Saint <hi>Albons,</hi> whereof ſome had 200. pound, and al his Revenues of his Lands belonging to his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge at <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Ipſwich</hi> the King tooke into his owne hands; whereof Maſter <hi>Cromwell</hi> had the receit and government before by my Lords aſſignment, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:53022:59"/>
it was thought very neceſſary that he ſhould have the ſame ſtill, who executed all things ſo well and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly, that he was had in great eſtimation for his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour therein.</p>
            <p>Now it came to paſſe that thoſe to whom the King had given any annuities or fees for term of life, or by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent could not be good but onely for and during my Lords life, for as much as the King had no longer eſtate therein, but what hee had by my Lords attainder in the Premunire: And to make their eſtate good and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, there was no other way but to obtaine my Lords confirmation of their patents: And to bring this about there was no other meanes but by Maſter <hi>Cromwell</hi> who was thought the fitteſt Inſtrument for this purpoſe, and for his paines therein he was worthily rewarded: and his demeanor, his honeſty and wiſedome was ſuch, that the King tooke great notice of him, as you ſhall hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heare.</p>
            <p>Still the Lords thought long till my Lord was remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved further off the Kings way, wherefore among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Lords, my Lord of <hi>Norfolke</hi> ſaid, Maſter <hi>Cromwell,</hi> me thinkes the Cardinall thy Maſter makes no haſt to goe <hi>Northwards,</hi> tell him, if hee goe not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, I will tear him with my teeth: Therefore I would adviſe him to prepare away with ſpeed, or elſe I will ſet him forwards. Theſe words reported Mr. <hi>Cromwel</hi> to my Lord at his next repaire, which was then at <hi>Richmond,</hi> having obteyned licence of the King to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from <hi>Aſhur</hi> to <hi>Richmond,</hi> and in the evening my Lord being accuſtomed to walke in the Garden, and I <hi>being with him ſtanding in an Alley, I eſpied certaine I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of Beaſts counterfeited in Timber, which I went nearer to take the better view of them, among whom I there ſaw ſtand a dunne Cow, whereat I moſt muſed of all thoſe beaſts: My Lord then ſuddenly came upon mee unawares, and ſpeaking to me ſaid, what have you ſpied there where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:53022:59"/>
you looke ſo earneſtly?</p>
            <p>Forſooth, quoth I, if it pleaſe your Grace I here behold theſe Images which I ſuppoſe were ordained to be ſet up in the kings Palace, but amongſt them all I have moſt conſidered this <hi>Cowe</hi> which ſeemes to mee the Artificers Maſter-piece. Yea marry quoth my Lord, <note place="margin">A Propheſie.</note> upon this Cowe hangs a certaine Propheſie which perhaps you never heard of, I will ſhew you, there is a ſaying,</p>
            <q>
               <l>When the Cowe doth ride the Bull, <note place="margin">When the cow rides the bull, Then Prieſt beware thy ſcull.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Then Prieſt beware thy Scull.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which ſaying, neither my Lord that declared it nor I that heard it underſtood the effect, although the compaſſe thereof was working, and then like to bee brought to paſſe: this Cowe the King gave by reaſon of the Earledome of <hi>Richmond</hi> which was Inheritance: This Propheſie was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards expounded in this manner, The dunne Cow, becauſe it is the Kings beaſt, betokens the King, and the Bull betokens Miſtris <hi>Anne</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</note> 
               <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> who after was Queene, her Father gave the blacke Bulls head in his Cognizance, and was his Beaſt, ſo that when the King had marryed Queene <hi>Anne,</hi> it was thought of all men to bee fulfilled, for what a number of Prieſts Religious and ſecular loſt their heads for offending of thoſe Lawes made, to bring this matter to paſſe, is not unknowne to all the world, therefore it may well be judged that this propheſie is fulfilled. <note place="margin">And fulfilled by the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls fall.</note>
            </p>
            <p>You have heard what words the Duke of <hi>Norfolke</hi> ſpake to Maſter <hi>Cromwell</hi> touching my Lords going into the <hi>North,</hi> then ſaid my Lord, <hi>Tom:</hi> It is time to bee going, therefore I pray you goe to the King, and tell him I would
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:53022:60"/>
goe to my Benefice at <hi>Yorke,</hi> but for lacke of moneyes deſiring his Grace to helpe him to ſome, and you may ſay that the laſt mony I had from his Grace was too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to pay my debts, and to compell me to pay the reſt of my debts were too much extremitie, ſeeing all my goods are taken from mee: Alſo ſhew my Lord of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk</hi> and the reſt of the Counſell, that I would depart if I had money. Sir quoth Maſter <hi>Cromwell,</hi> I ſhall doe my beſt, &amp; ſo after other communication departed and came to <hi>London,</hi> then in the beginning of <hi>Lent,</hi> my Lord removed his lodging into the <hi>Charterhouſ</hi> at <hi>Richmond</hi> where he lay in a lodging that Dr. <hi>Collet</hi> made for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and every after-noon for the time of his reſidence there would he ſit in contemplation with ſome one of the moſt auncient Fathers there, who converted him to diſpoſe the vain glory of this world, <hi>and there they gave unto him ſhirts of haire to wear next his bodie, which hee were divers times after.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Shirt: of hair.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Lords aſſigned that my Lord ſhould have 1000. Markes penſion out of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> for his going downe <note place="margin">A thouſand mark penſion to the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> into the <hi>North,</hi> which when the King heard of, hee commanded that it ſhould be forthwith paid unto Mr. <hi>Cromwell.</hi> And the King commanded Maſter <hi>Cromwell</hi> to repaire to him againe when he had received the ſaid Sum, which he accordingly did: To whom his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie ſaid, ſhew your Lord that I have ſent him tenne <note place="margin">The King ſent him 10000. p.</note> thouſand pounds of my benevolence, and tell him hee ſhall not lacke, bid him bee of good comfort. Maſter <hi>Cromwell,</hi> on my Lords behalfe thanked the King for his royall liberalitie towards my Lord, and with that departed to <hi>Richmond,</hi> to whom he delivered the mony and the joyfull tidings, wherein my Lord did not a little rejoyce, forthwith there was a preparation made for his going, hee had with him in his traine one hundred and ſixtie perſons, having <note place="margin">The Cardinal goeth to his Biſhoprick of Yorke.</note> with him twelve Cartes to carrie his goods
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:53022:60"/>
which hee ſent from his Colledge at <hi>Oxford</hi> beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cartes of his daily carriage of his neceſſaries for his buildings, hee kept his ſolempne feaſt of <hi>Easter</hi> at <hi>Peterborow,</hi> and upon <hi>Palme-Sunday,</hi> he bare his palm and went on proceſſion with the Monkes, and upon Thurſday hee made his Mandy, having 59, poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <note place="margin">At Peterbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe hee did waſh 59. poor mens feete.</note> whoſe feete hee waſhed and kiſſed, and after he had dried them, hee gave every one of them twelve pence and three ells of good Canvas to make them ſhirts, and each of them a paire of new ſhooes and a caske of Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herring, on <hi>Eaſter-day</hi> hee roſe to the Reſurrection, and that day he went in proceſſion in his Cardinals ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtments, and having his hat on his head, and ſung the high maſſe there himſelfe ſolempnlie, after his maſſe he gave his Benediction to all the hearers with cleane re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. <hi>From Peterborow hee tooke his journey into the North, but made ſome ſtay by the way, and many paſſages hapned in his journey too tedious here to relate. At the laſt he came to</hi> Stoby <hi>where he continued til after Michaelmas exerciſing many deeds of charity, moſt commonly every ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day if the weather ſerved would he goe to ſome poor Pariſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church thereabouts, and there would ſay the divine ſervice and either ſaid or heard maſſe, &amp; then cauſed one of his Chaplins to preach the word of God to the people, &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards hee would dine in ſome honeſt houſe in the Town,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Charity to the poore.</note> 
               <hi>where ſhould be diſtributed to the poor, alms aswell of meat and drinke, as mony to ſupply the want of meat and drink, if the number of poor did exceed: thus with other good deeds practiſing himſelfe during the time of his abode there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween partie and partie, being at variance: About Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas after heremoved from thence to</hi> Caywod <hi>Caſtle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> 7. <hi>miles of the City of Yorke, where he had much honour and love from all men high and lowe, where he kept a plentifull houſe for all commers, alſo hee builded and</hi> repaired the Caſtle which was much decayed, having at the leaſt three hundred perſons daily in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:53022:61"/>
worke to whom he paid Wages lying there: Where all the Doctors and Prebends of the Church of <hi>Yorke</hi> did repaire to my Lord according to their duties, as unto the chiefe Head, Patron, and Father of their Spirituall dignities, who did moſt joyfully well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him into thoſe parts, <hi>Saying, it was no ſmall comfort unto them, to ſee their Head among them, who had beene ſo long abſent from them, being like unto Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe and comfortleſſe Children for want of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; and that they truſted ſhortly to ſee him amongſt them in his owne Church. To whom hee made anſwere, That it was the moſt eſpeciall cauſe of his comming, to bee amongſt them as a Father, and a naturall brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, quoth they, <hi>you muſt underſtand the Ordinances and Rules of our Church, whereof, although you bee the Head and ſole Governour, yet you are not ſo well acquainted as we be therein: Therfore, if it pleaſe your Grace, wee ſhall (under favour) open unto you ſome part of our ancient Lawes and Cuſtomes of our Church, that our head Prelate and Paſtor as you now are, might</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Order in the Cathedral at Yorke.</note> 
               <hi>not come above our Quire doore, untill by due Order he be inſtalled. Nor if you ſhould happen to dye before your inſtallation, you ſhould not be buried above in the Quire, but below in the neather part of the body of the Church. Therefore wee humbly deſire and beſeech you, in the name of all our Brethren, that you would vouchſafe to doe therein, as our ancient Fathers your Predeceſſours have done, and that you will not breake the laudable Cuſtoms of our Church; To the which we are obliged by Oath at our firſt admittance to obſerve that, and divers others, which in our Chapter doth remaine upon Record.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe Records</hi> (quoth my Lord) <hi>would I faine ſee, and then ſhall you know further of mine adviſe and mind in this buſineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A day was ſigned to bring their Records to my
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:53022:61"/>
Lord, at which time they reſorted to my Lord with their Regiſter and Bookes of Records, wherein were fairely Written their Inſtitutions and Rules, which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Miniſter of their Church was moſt principally and chiefly bound to obſerve and infallibly keepe and maintaine.</p>
            <p>When my Lord had read the Records, hee did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be at the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Yorke</hi> the next Munday after <hi>Alholland-tide,</hi> againſt which Time due preparation was made for the ſame; but not in ſo ſumptuous a wiſe as were his predeceſſors before him: Nor yet in ſuch ſort as the fame and common report was afterwards made of him, to his great ſlander. And to the falſe Reporters no ſmall diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty to become a divulger of ſuch notorious lies I am ſure they did: For I my ſelfe was ſent by my Lord to <note place="margin">Preparation for the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals inſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at York.</note> 
               <hi>Yorke,</hi> to ſee that all things there ſhould bee ordered and provided for that Solemnity, in a very decent forme to the honour of that ancient and worthy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery of <hi>Yorke</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It came to paſſe that upon <hi>Alholland-day,</hi> one of the head and principall Officers of the ſaid Cathedrall Church which ſhould have had moſt doing at my Lords Inſtallation, was with my Lord at <hi>Caywood,</hi> and ſitting at Dinner, they fell into Communication of this matter, and the Order and Ceremony thereof: Hee ſaying that my Lord Cardinall ſhould goe a foote from a Chappell which ſtands without the Gates of the City called Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his Chappell, unto the Minſter upon cloath, which ſhould bee diſtributed to the poore after his ſaid paſſage to the Church. Which my Lord hearing, replied and ſaid, although per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps our Predeceſſors have gone upon cloath, yet we intend to go on foot without any ſuch Pompe or glory in the vampes of our hoſen. And therfore gave order
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:53022:62"/>
to his Servants to goe as humbly thither as might bee without any ſumptuous apparrell; for I intend on Sunday to come to you to bee inſtalled, and to make but one Dinner for you at the cloſe, and the next day to dine with the Major, and ſo returne againe hither.</p>
            <p>The day beeing not unknowne to all the Country, the Gentlemen, Abbots, and Priors, ſuch proviſion <note place="margin">Store of good proviſion ſent in by the Country.</note> ſent in, that it was almoſt incredible for ſtore and variety.</p>
            <p>The Common people held my Lord in great eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation for his purity and liberality, and alſo for his familiar geſture and good behaviour amongſt them. By meanes whereof hee gained much love of all the people in the North parts of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 19. <hi>Of the Cardinals fall, and how hee was arreſted of high Treaſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat chanced before his laſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles at <hi>Caywood</hi> as a ſigne or token from God, of that which ſhould follow, I will now, God willing, declare. My L. enemies being then at Court about the King, in good eſtimation, and honorable dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities; ſeeing now my Lord in great favour, and fearing the King would now call him home againe, they therefore did plot amongſt
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:53022:62"/>
themſelves to diſpatch him by meanes of ſome ſiniſter Treaſon, or to bring him into the Kings great indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by ſome other meanes.</p>
            <p>This was their daily ſtudy and conſultation, having for their eſpeciall helpe and furtherance as many vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant attendants upon him, as the Poets faine <hi>Argus</hi> had eyes.</p>
            <p>The King with theſe their continuall complaints, was mooved to much indignation, and thought it good that the Cardinall ſhould come up, and to ſtand to his Triall in his owne perſon; which his enemies did not like of. Notwithſtanding, hee was ſent for, and after this ſort.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they deviſed that Sir <hi>Walter Welch</hi> Knight, one of the Kings privy Chamber ſhould bee ſent downe with a Commiſſion into the North, and the Earle of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> who was ſometimes brought up in the Houſe of my Lord, being joyned in Commiſſion with him, ſhould arreſt my Lord of high Treaſon. This being reſolved upon, Sir <hi>Walter Welch</hi> prepared for his journy, with his Commiſſion and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine inſtruments annexed to the ſame and tooke horſe at the Court Gate upon <hi>Alholland-day,</hi> towards my Lord of <hi>Northumberland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now will I declare what I promiſed before of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſigne or token of my Lords trouble enſuing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon <hi>All-hallow-day</hi> my Lord ſitting at dinner, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at his Boards end divers of his Chaplaines to beare him Company for want of other Gueſts; you <note place="margin">The Cardnals croſſe in the fall, brake Dr. Bonners head.</note> ſhall now underſtand that my Lords great Croſſe which ſtood by fell, and in the fall broke Doctor <hi>Bonners</hi> head, inaſmuch that ſome blood ran downe. My Lord perceiving the fall thereof, demaunded of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:53022:63"/>
thoſe that ſtood by him what was the matter that they ſtood ſo amazed, I ſhewed him of the fall of his great croſſe upon Dr. <hi>Bonners</hi> head: Quoth my Lord, hath it drawne any blood? yea quoth I, with that he caſt his head aſide and ſoberly ſaid <hi>(Malum Omen)</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſuddenly ſaid grace, and roſe from table and went to his Bed-chamber, but what he did there I cannot tell. Now marke how my Lord expounded the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof (in his fancie) to meat <hi>Pontefract</hi> after his fall. Firſt that the great Croſſe that he bare as Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Yorke</hi> betokened himſelfe, and Doctor <hi>Auſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> the Phyſitian who overthrew the Croſſe, was hee that accuſed my Lord, whereby his enemies caught an occaſion to overthrowe him, it fell on Doctor <hi>Bonners</hi> head, who was then maſter of my Lords faculties, and ſpirituall juriſdiction, who was then dampnified by the fall thereof, and moreover the drawing of blood betokeueth death, which did ſuddenly after follow.</p>
            <p>Now the appointed time drew neere for Inſtallation and ſitting at dinner; the friday before the monday that he ſhould have been inſtalled at <hi>Yorke:</hi> The Earle of <hi>Northumberland</hi> and M. <hi>Welſh</hi> with a great company of Gent of the Earls houſe, and of the Country whom they had gathered in the Kings name, to accompany them, (yet not knowing to what end) came to the hall of <hi>Caywood</hi> (the Officers being at dinner) and my <note place="margin">The Earle of Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Mr. Welſh come to Caywood-hal.</note> Lord not fullie dined, nor knowing any thing of the Earles being come.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing that the Earle did, after hee had ſet the hall in order, he commanded the Porter to deliver the keyes of the gates to him, which he would in no wiſe doe, although he was threatned and commanded in the Kings name to make deliverance thereof to one of the Earles ſervants, which he ſtill refuſed, ſaying to the Earle, that the keyes were delivered to him by his Lord and maſter, both by oath and other command.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:53022:63"/>
Now ſome of the Gent. that ſtood by the Earle hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the porter ſpeake ſo ſtoutly ſaid, hee is a good fellow and a faithfull ſervant to his maſter, and ſpeaks like an honeſt man, therefore give him your charge, and let him keep the keyes ſtill: then ſaid my L. thou ſhalt wel and truly keep the keys to the uſe of our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord the King, and you ſhall let none paſſe in nor out of the Gates, but ſuch as from time to time you ſhal be commanded by us, being the Kings Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners during our ſtay here, and with that oath he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the keyes of the Earle, and Maſter <hi>Welches</hi> hands, but of all theſe doings knew my Lord nothing, for they had ſtopped the ſtayers that none ſhould goe to my L. chamber, and they that came down could not goe up againe. At the length one eſcaped up and ſhewed my Lord that the Earle of <hi>Northumberland</hi> was in the hall, whereat my Lord wondred, and at the firſt believed him not, till he heard it confirmed by another: Then quoth my Lord, I am ſorry wee have dined, for I feare our Officers have not provided fiſh enough for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of him, with ſome honourable cheere fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his eſtate and Dignity; And with that my Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe from the Table and commanded to let the cloath lye that the Earle might ſee how far forth they were at <note place="margin">The Cardinal and the Earle meete.</note> their dinners, and as he was going downe ſtayres, he encountred with my Lord of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> to whom my Lord ſaid you are heartily welcome my Lord, and ſo they embraced each other: Then quoth my Lord Cardinal, if you had loved mee, you would have ſent me word before of your comming, that I might have entertained you according to your honour. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding you ſhal have ſuch cheer as I can make you for the preſent, with a right good will, truſting you will accept thereof in good part, hoping hereafter to ſee you oftner when I ſhal be more able to entertain you: this
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:53022:64"/>
ſaid, my Lord tooke him by the hand, and led him to his Chamber, whom followed all, the Earls ſervants, and they being there all alone, ſaving I which kept the doore as my Office required being <hi>Gentleman-vſher,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Earl doth arreſt the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall.</note> theſe two Lords ſtanding at a window, the Earle trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ſaid: I arreſt you of high Treaſon, with which words, my Lord was well nigh aſtoniſhed, ſtanding ſtill a good ſpace without ſpeaking one word.</p>
            <p>But at the laſt, quoth my Lord, what authority have you to arreſt mee, quoth the Earle, I have a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſo to doe: ſhew it me, quoth my Lord, that I may ſee the contents therof: nay Sir that you may not quoth the Earle. Then quoth my Lord, hold you contented, for I will not obey your arreſt, for there hath been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween your Anceſtors and my Predeceſſors great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and debate, and therefore unleſſe I ſee your authority I will not obey you. <note place="margin">Maſter Welſh arreſts Doctor Auſtin of high Treaſon.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Even as they were debating the matter in the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſo likewiſe was Maſter <hi>Welſh</hi> buſie in arreſting Dr. <hi>Auſtine</hi> at the door, ſaying, go in thou Traytor, or I ſhall make thee: with that I opened the Portall dore, and did thruſt in Doctor <hi>Auſtine</hi> before him with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. The matter on both ſides aſtoniſhed me very much, marveyling what all this ſhould meane, untill at the laſt, Maſter <hi>Welſh</hi> being entered my Lord Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, began to pluck of his hood being of the ſame cloath his cloake was, which hood he wore to the intent hee ſhould not be known, who kneeled down to my Lord; to whom my Lord ſaid come hither Gentleman; and let me ſpeake with you, commanding him to ſtand up, and ſaid thus. My Lord of <hi>Northumberland</hi> hath arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted mee, but by what authority I know not, if you be privie thereunto joyned with him therein, I pray you ſhew me. Indeed my Lord if it pleaſe your Grace, quoth Maſter <hi>Welſh,</hi> I pray have me excuſed; there is annexed
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:53022:64"/>
to our Commisſion certain inſtructions, as you may not ſee nor be privie too: why quoth my Lord, be your Inſtructions ſuch as I may not ſee nor be privie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, yet paradventure if I be privie unto them, I may helpe you the better to performe them, for it is not unknown to you, that I have been of Counſell in as wei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty matters as theſe are, and I doubt not, but I ſhall doe well enough, for my part, prove my ſelfe a true man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the expectations of my cruel enemies, I ſee the matter whereupon it groweth, well there is no more to doe I trowe, you art of the Privie Chamber, your name is Mr. <hi>Welſh,</hi> I am contented to yeeld to you, but not to the Earle, without I ſee his Commiſſion, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo you are a ſufficient Commiſſioner in this behalf, being one of the privie Chamber: Therefore put your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in execution, ſpare me not, I will obey you and the King, for I feare not the crueltie of mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, no more then I doe the truth of my Allegiance, wherein I take God to witneſſe, I never offended his Majeſty in word or deede, and therein I dare ſtand face to face with any, having a difference without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality.</p>
            <p>Then came my Lord of <hi>Northumberland</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded mee to avoide the Chamber: And being loath to depart from my Maſter, I ſtood ſtill and would not remove, to whom he ſpake againe and ſaid, there is no remedie you muſt depart, with that I looked upon my Maſter, as who would have ſaid ſhall I goe, and perceiving by his countenance that it was not for me to ſtay, <hi>I</hi> departed and went into an other chamber, where were many Gentlemen and others to heare newes, to whom I made a report of what I heard and ſaw, which was great heauineſſe to them all. <note place="margin">The Earle takes the keys from my L.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Then the Earle called into his Chamber diuers of his owne ſervants, and after he and Maſter <hi>Welſh</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:53022:65"/>
had taken the keyes from my Lord, hee committed the keeping of my Lord unto five Gentlemen, and then they went about the houſe, and put all things in order, intending to depart the next day, and to certifie the King and the reſt of the Lords, what they had done.</p>
            <p>Then went they buſie about to Convey Doctor <hi>Austine</hi> away to <hi>London</hi> with as much ſpeede and privacy as they could poſſible, ſending with him di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers perſons to conduct him, who was bound to his horſe like a Traytor.</p>
            <p>And this being done, when it was neere night, the Commiſſioners ſending two Groomes of my Lords to attend him in his Chamber (where hee lay all night) the reſt of the Earles men watched in the Chamber, and all the houſe was watched, and the gates ſafe kept, that no man could paſſe or repaſſe untill next morning.</p>
            <p>About eight of the clocke next morning, the Earle ſent for me into his Chamber, and commaunded mee to goe to my Lord; and as I was going, I met with Maſter <hi>Welſh,</hi> who called me unto him, and ſhewed me how the Kings Majeſty bare unto me his principall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for my love and diligent Service that I had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to my Lord: wherefore, quoth hee, the Kings pleaſure is, that you ſhalbe about him as chiefe, in whom his Highneſſe putteth great confidence and truſt; and thereupon gave mee in Writing the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: Which when I had read, I ſayd I was content to obey his Majeſties pleaſure, and would bee ſworne to the performance thereof; whereupon hee gave mee my Oath.</p>
            <p>That done, I reſorted to my Lord, whom I found ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in a Chaire, the Table being ready ſpread for him. But ſo ſoone as hee perceived me come in, he fell into
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:53022:65"/>
ſuch a wofull lamentation, that would have forced a flinty-heart to mourne.</p>
            <p>I then comforted him aſwell as I could, but hee would not; for quoth hee, I am much grieved that I have nothing to reward you, and the reſt of my true and faithfull Servants, for all the good Service that they and you have done mee, for which I doe much lament.</p>
            <p>Upon Sunday following, the Earle and Maſter <hi>Welſh</hi> appoynted to ſet forward, for my Lords Horſe and ours were brought ready into the inner Court, where we mounted, and comming towards the Gate ready to ride out, the Porter had no ſooner opened the ſame, but we ſaw without ready attending a great number of Gentlemen and their Servants, ſuch as the Earle had appointed for that Service to attend and Conduct my Lord to <hi>Pomfrait</hi> that night.</p>
            <p>But to tell you the Truth, there were alſo many of the people of the Country aſſembled at the Gate, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting his departure, in number above three Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, who after the opening of the Gate that they had a ſight of him, cryed out with a loud voyce, <hi>God ſave your Grace, God ſave your Grace;</hi> the foule Evil take them that have taken you from us; wee pray God that vengeance may light upon them. And thus they ran after him through the Towne of <hi>Caywood,</hi> for he was there very well beloved both of rich and poore.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:53022:66"/>
            <head>CHAP. 20. <hi>Of the Cardinals entertainment at the Earle of Shrewsburies, and of his death and buriall at Leiceſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter our departure from <hi>Cawood,</hi> we came to <hi>Doncaster,</hi> the third day wee came to <hi>Sheffield-parke,</hi> where my Lord of <hi>Shrews<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> lived within the lodge, and the Earle and his Lady, and a great company of Gentlewomen and Servants ſtood without the Gate to attend my Lords comming; at whoſe alightning the Earle received him with much honour, and imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him, ſaying theſe words; <hi>My Lord you are moſt heartily welcome to my poore lodge, and I am glad to ſee you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here my Lord ſtayed a fortnight, and was moſt nobly entertayned; he ſpent moſt of his time and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed his minde to prayers continually in great devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It came to paſſe as hee ſate one day at dinner, I beeing there, perceived his colour divers times to change; I asked him if hee was not well; who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered me with a loud voyce: I am ſuddenly taken with a Thing at my ſtomacke as cold as a Whet-ſtone, and am not well: Therefore take up the Table, and make a ſhort dinner, and returne to mee againe ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly. I made but a little ſtay, but came to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, where I found him ſtill ſitting very ill at eaſe: Hee deſired me to goe to the <hi>Apothecarie</hi> and aske him if hee had any thing would breake Winde upwards: Hee told me hee had: Then I went and ſhewed the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:53022:66"/>
ſame to my Lord, who did command mee to give him ſome thereof, and ſo I did, and it made him breake winde exceedingly: Loe quoth he, you may ſee it was but winde, for now I thanke God I am well eaſed, and ſo he aroſe from the Table and went to praiers, as hee u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed every day after dinner.</p>
            <p>In the afternoon my Lord of <hi>Shrewſbury</hi> ſent for mee to him, to whom he ſaid, foraſmuch as I have always perceived you to be a man in whom your Lord putteth great affiance, and I my ſelfe knowing you to bee a man very honeſt, with many words of commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and praiſe more then becommeth mee to rehearſe, he ſaid, your Lord and Maſter hath often deſired me to write unto the King that he might anſwere his accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before his enemies: And this day I have received Letters from his Majeſtie by Sir <hi>William Kingſton</hi> whereby I perceive that the King hath him in good o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and upon my requeſt hath ſent for him by the ſaid Sr. <hi>William Kingſton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therfore now I would have you play your part wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with him in ſuch ſort as he may take it quietly and in good part, for he is alwaies full of ſorrow and much heavineſſe at my being with him, that I fear he would take it ill if I bring him tidings thereof: And therein doth hee not well, for I aſſure you that the King is his very good Lord, and hath given me moſt hearty thanks for his entertainment: And therefore goe your way to him and perſwade him I may find him in quiet at my comming, for <hi>I</hi> will not tarry long after you.</p>
            <p>Sir quoth I, and if it pleaſe your Lordſhip I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to the beſt of my Power, to accompliſh your Lordſhips command: But Sir, I doubt when I name this Sir <hi>William Kingſton,</hi> that he will miſtruſt ſome il, becauſe he is Conſtable of the Tower, and Captaine of the guard, having in his company 24. of the Guard to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:53022:67"/>
accompanie him: That is nothing quoth the Earle, what if he be Conſtable of the Tower and Captaine of the Guard? he is the fitteſt man for his wiſedome and diſcretion to be ſent about ſuch a buſineſſe, and for the Guard it is onely to defend him from thoſe that might intend him any ill. Beſides that, the Guard are for the moſt part ſuch of his old ſervants as the King hath tooke into his ſervice to attend him moſt juſtly. Well Sir quoth I, I ſhall doe what I can, and ſo departed and went to my Lord and found him in the Gallery with his Staffe and his Beades in his hands, and ſeeing mee come, he asked me what newes, forſooth quoth I, the beſt newes that ever you heard, if you can take it well I pray God it bee true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then quoth hee; my Lord of <hi>Shrewſbury</hi> ſaid, I your moſt aſſured friend, hath ſo provided by his letters to the King, that his Majeſtie hath ſent for you by Maſter <hi>Kingston,</hi> and 24. of the Guard to conduct you to his Highneſſe, Maſter <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> quoth hee, and clapped his hand on his Thigh and <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls cauſleſſe feares.</note> gave a great ſigh.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe your Grace (quoth I) I would you would take all things well, it would be much better for you, content your ſelfe for Gods ſake, and thinke that God and your good friends have wrought for you, according to your own deſires: And (as I conceive) you have much more cauſe to rejoyce then lament or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt the matter, for I aſſure you that your friends are <note place="margin">Enemies.</note> more affraid of you then you need be of them: And his Majeſtie to ſhew his love to you, hath ſent Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> to honour you, with as much honour as is your Graces due, and to convey you in ſuch eaſie jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys as is fitting for you, and you ſhall command him to do, and that you ſhall have your requeſt. And I humbly entreat you to imprint this my perſwaſion in your Highneſſe diſcretion and to be of good cheere,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:53022:67"/>
wherewith you ſhall comfort your ſelfe, and give your frinds and poore ſervants great comfort and content.</p>
            <p>Well quoth he, I perceive more then you can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, or doe know, preſently after came my Lord to acquaint him with that I had ſo lately related, my L. Cardinall thanked the Earle for his great love, and called for Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> who came to him preſently, and kneeling down before him ſaluted him in the kings <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſalutes Mr. Kingſton</note> behalfe, whom my Lord bareheaded offered to take up, but he would not, then quoth my Lord, Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> I pray you ſtand up and leave your kneeling to me, for I am a wretch repleat with miſery, not eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming my ſelfe, but as a meere abject utterly caſt away, but without deſert God he knowes, therefore good Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> ſtand up.</p>
            <p>Then Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> ſaid, the Kings Majeſtie hath him commended unto you. I thanke his Highneſſe quoth my Lord, I hope he is in good health. Yea quoth Maſter <hi>Kingſton,</hi> and he hath him commended unto you, and commanded me to bid you be of good cheere, <note place="margin">Mr. Kingſton tells him he is in the Kings favour.</note> for hee beareth you as much good will as ever hee did.</p>
            <p>And whereas Report hath been made unto him, that you ſhould commit againſt his Majeſtie certain heynos crimes which he thinketh to be, but yet hee for mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Juſtice in ſuch Caſes requiſite, could doe no leſſe then ſend for you that you might have your triall, miſtruſting nothing your truth and wiſedome, but that you ſhall be able to acquit your ſelfe of all complaints and accuſations extended againſt you: And you may take your journey to him at your pleaſure, commanding me to attend you.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Kingston</hi> quoth my Lord, I thanke you for your good newes: And Sir hereof aſſure your ſelfe, if I were as able and luſty as ever I was to ride, I would
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:53022:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
goe with you poſt: But alas I am a diſeaſed man having a ſluxe (at which time it was apparant that he had poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned himſelf) it hath made me very weake, but the Comfortable news you bring is of purpoſe (I doubt) to bring me into a fooles Paradiſe, for I know what is provided for me. <hi>Notwithſtanding,</hi> I thanke you for your good will, and paines taken about mee, and I ſhall with ſpeed make readie to ride with you.</p>
            <p>After this I was commanded to make all things rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die for our departure the morrow after.</p>
            <p>When my Lord went to bed, he fell very ſick of the Laske, which cauſed him to goe to ſtoole from time to <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal near death</note> time all that night, inſomuch that from that time till morning, hee had 50. ſtooles: And the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he voided was very blacke, which the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians called <hi>Aduſtine,</hi> whoſe opinions were that he had not above 4. or 5. daies to live.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Notwithstanding,</hi> he would have ridden with Mr. <hi>Kingſton</hi> the next day, had not the Earle of <hi>Shrewſbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> adviſed him to the contrarie, but the next day hee took his journey with Maſter <hi>Kingſton,</hi> and them of the Guard, who eſpying him could not abſtaine from wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, conſidering he was their old Maſter, and now in ſuch a miſerable caſe, whom my Lord tooke by the hand, and would as hee rode by the way ſometimes talke with one, and ſometimes with an other, till he came to a houſe of my Lords ſtanding in the way called <hi>Hardwick</hi> hall, where he lay all that night very ill at caſe. The next day he came to <hi>Nottingham,</hi> and the <hi>next</hi> day to <hi>Leiceſter abbey,</hi> and the <hi>next</hi> day he <hi>waxed very ſick that he had almoſt fallen from his horſe, ſo that it was night ere he got to</hi> Leiceſter abbey, <hi>where at his comming in at the Gates, the Abbot with all their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent met him with many lighted Torches, whom they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably received and welcommed with geat reverence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To whom my Lord ſaid, Father Abbot, I am come to</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:53022:68"/>
lay my bones amongſt you, riding ſtill on his mule till he came to the ſtairs of his Chamber where hee alighted: Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> holding him by the arme led him up the ſtaires, who told me after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that he never felt ſo heavie a burthen in all his life, and as ſoone as he was in his Chamber he went ſtraight to bed, this was upon Satterday, and ſo he continued.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Monday</hi> in the morning as I ſtood by is bedſide about eight of the clock in the morning, the windowes being cloſe ſhut, and having wax lights burning upon the Cupboard, I thought I perceived him drawing on towards death. Hee perceiving my ſhadow upon the bedſide asked who was there. Sir quoth I, tis I, how doe you quoth he, well? I Sir quoth I, if I might ſee your Grace well, what is it a clock quoth hee? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered it was about eight of the Clock, quoth he that cannot be, rehearſing eight of the clocke ſo many times. Nay quoth he that cannot be, for at eight of the clock you ſhall ſee your maſters time draw neere that I muſt depart this world: with that quoth Doctor <hi>Palmes</hi> a worthy Gentleman ſtanding by, bid me aske him if hee would bee ſhriven to make him readie for God, what ever chanced to fall out, which I did: but he was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry angry with me, and asked what I had to doe to aske him ſuch a queſtion? till at the laſt Maſter Doctor took my part and talked with him in Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin and pacified him.</p>
            <p>After dinner M. <hi>Kingſton</hi> ſent for me and ſaid, Sir, The King hath ſent unto mee Letters by Mr. <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> our old companion who hath bin in trouble
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:53022:69"/>
in the Tower for mony that my Lord ſhould have at his departure: A great part of which money cannot bee found, wherefore the King at Maſter <hi>Vincents</hi> requeſt for the declaration of the truth hath ſent him hither with his Graces Letters, that I ſhould examine my Lord &amp; have your Counſell therein, that he may take it well and in good part. And this is the cauſe of my ſending for you, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I deſire your Counſel therein for acquitall of this poor Gentleman Maſter <hi>Vincent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir quoth I, according to my duty you ſhall, and by my adviſe you ſhall reſort unto him in your own perſon to viſit him, and in communication breake the matter unto him: And if he will not tell you the truth therein, then may you certifie the King thereof; But in any caſe name not nor ſpeake of my fellowe <hi>Vincent:</hi> Alſo I would not have you to detract the time, for hee is very ſicke, and I feare that he will not live paſt a day or two, and accordingly Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> went to my Lord and demanded the money, ſaying that my Lord of <hi>Northumberland</hi> found a book at <hi>Caywood-houſe</hi> that you had but lately borrowed 10000. pounds, &amp; there is not ſo much as one penny to be found who hath made the King privie to the ſame, wherefore the King hath written to me, to know what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thereof, for it were pitty that it ſhould bee holden from you both. Therefore I require you in the Kings name to tell me the truth, that I may make a juſt report thereof unto his Majeſtie of your anſwer?</p>
            <p>With that quoth my Lord, oh good Lord, how much doth it grieve me that the King ſhould think
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:53022:69"/>
any ſuch thing in me, that I ſhould deceive him of one pennie, ſeeing I have nothing nor never had <hi>(God be my Iudge)</hi> that I ever eſteemed ſo much mine owne as his Majeſties, having but the bare uſe of it during my life, and after my death to leave it wholy to him; wherein his Majeſtie hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented mee. But for this money that you demand of me, I aſſure you it is none of my own, for I bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed it of diverſe of my friends to bury me, and to beſtow amongſt my ſervants, who have taken great pains about mee, notwithſtanding if it bee your pleaſure to know, I muſt bee content, yet I beſeech his Majeſtie to ſee it ſatiſfied for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my Conſcience to them that I owed it to, who be they quoth Maſter <hi>Kingſton?</hi> That ſhal I tell you quoth my Lord, I borrowd two hundred pounds of <hi>Iohn Allen</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> another 200. p. of Sir <hi>Richard Greſham,</hi> and 200. pound of the Maſter of the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and alſo 200. pound of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Highden</hi> Dean of my Colledge at <hi>Oxford,</hi> 200 pound of the Treaſurer of the Church, and 200. pound of Maſter <hi>Ellis</hi> my Chaplain: And an other 200. pound of a Prieſt, I hope the King will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore <note place="margin">Divers ſoms of money bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed by the Cardnal a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before hee dyed.</note> it againe, forasmuch as it is none of mine.</p>
            <p>Sir quoth Maſter <hi>Kingſton,</hi> there is no doubt in the King whom you need not diſtruſt, but Sir I pray you where is the money quoth hee, I will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale it I warrant you, but I will declare it unto you before I dye by the grace of God, have a litle patience with me I pray you, for the money is ſafe enough in an honeſt mans hands, who will not keep one penny thereof from the King.</p>
            <p>So Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> departed for that time, my
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:53022:70"/>
Lord being very weake, and about fowre of the clock in the next morning, as I conceived, I asked him how he did, well quoth he if I had any meate, <note place="margin">The Cardinal deſires meate.</note> I pray you give me ſome.</p>
            <p>Sir quoth I, there is none ready, then he ſaid (you are much too blame) for you ſhould have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies meate for me in readineſſe, whenſoever that my ſtomack ſerves me, I pray you get ſome ready for mee, for I meane to make my ſelfe ſtrong to day to the intent I may goe to confeſſion and make mee ready for God, quoth I, I will call up the Cookes to prepare ſome meate, And alſo I will call Maſter <hi>Palmer</hi> that he may diſcourſe with you till your meate be ready, with a good will quoth my Lord, and ſo I called Maſter <hi>Palmer</hi> who roſe and came to my Lord.</p>
            <p>Then I went and acquainted Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> that my Lord was very ſicke and not like to live. In good faith quoth Maſter <hi>Kingſton,</hi> you are much too blame to make him beleeve he is ſicker then he is. Well Sir quoth I, you cannot ſay but I gave you warning as I am bound to doe, upon which words he aroſe and came unto him, but before he came my Lord Cardinall had eaten a ſpoonfull or two of Callis made of Chickin, and after that he was in his confeſſion the ſpace of an hower: And then Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> came to him and bad him good morrow, and asked him how he did, Sir quoth he, I watch but Gods pleaſure to render up my poore ſoule to him. I pray you have me heartily commended unto his Royall Majeſtie, and beſeech him on my behalfe to call to his Princely remembrance all matters that have bin between us from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:53022:70"/>
and the progreſſe: And eſpecially betweene good Queene <hi>Katherin</hi> and him, and then ſhall his Graces Conſcience know whether I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him or not.</p>
            <p>Hee is a Prince of a moſt Royall carriage and hath a Princely heart, and rather then hee will miſſe or want any part of his will, he will endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the one halfe of his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>I do aſſure you I have often kneeled before him ſometimes three houres together to perſwade him from his will and appetite, but could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile: And Maſter <hi>Kingſton,</hi> had I but ſerved God as diligently as I have ſerved the King, he would not have given me over in my gray haires. But this is the juſt reward that I muſt receive for my diligent paines and ſtuddy, not regarding my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to God, but onely to my Prince, Therefore let me adviſe you, if you be one of the Privie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, as by your wiſedome you are fit, take heede what you put in the Kings head, for you can never put it out againe.</p>
            <p>And I deſire you further to requeſt his Grace in <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals adviſe.</note> Gods name, that he have a vigilant eye to ſuppreſſe the helliſh <hi>Luthrans,</hi> that they increaſ not through his great negligence, in ſuch a ſort as he be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to take up Armes to ſubdue them, as the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> was; whoſe Commons being infected with <hi>Wickliffs</hi> hereſies, the King was inforced to take that courſe.</p>
            <p>Let him conſider the Story of King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, the ſecond ſonne of his Progenitor, who lived in the time of <hi>Wickliffs</hi> Seditions and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies: Did not the Commons I pray you in his time
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:53022:71"/>
riſe againſt the Nobilitie and chiefe governours of this Realme, and at the laſt ſome of them were put to death without Juſtice or mercie, and under pretence of having all things common, did they not fall to ſpoyling and robbing, and at laſt tooke the Kings perſon, and carried him about the Citie making him obedient to their procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations?</p>
            <p>Did not alſo the Trayterous Heretiques Sir <hi>Iohn Old-Caſtle,</hi> Lord <hi>Cobham</hi> pitch a field with Heretiques againſt King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, where the King was in perſon and fought againſt them, to whom God gave the victory?</p>
            <p>Alas, if theſe be not plaine preſidents and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient perſwaſions to admoniſh a Prince: Then God wil take away from us our prudent Rulers, &amp; leave us to the hands of our enemies. And then will enſue miſchiefe upon miſchiefe, Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, Barrenneſſe and ſcarcitie for want of good Orders in the Common-wealth, from which God of his tender mercy defend us.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> farewell, I wiſh all things may have good ſucceſſe, my time drawes on, I may not tarry with you, I pray you remember my words.</p>
            <p>Now began the time to draw neere, for hee drew his ſpeech at length, and his tongue began to faile him, his eyes perfectly ſet in his head, his ſight failed him. Then wee began to put him in minde of <hi>Christs</hi> paſſion, and cauſed the Yeoman of the Guard to ſtand by privately to ſee him dye, and beare witneſſe of his words and his departure, who heard all his communications.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:53022:71"/>
And then preſentlie the clocke ſtrooke eight, at which time he gave up the Ghoſt, and thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted he this life, one of us looking upon an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall gave up the Ghoſt.</note> ſuppoſing he propheſied of his departure.</p>
            <p>We ſent for the Abbot of the houſe to annoint him, who ſpeedily came as hee was ending his life, who ſaid certaine praiers before that the life was out of his bodie:</p>
            <p>Here is the end and fall of pride, for I aſſure you he was in his time the proudeſt man alive, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving more regard to the honour of his Perſon then to his ſpirituall function, wherein he ſhould have expreſſed more meekeneſſe and humility: For Pride and Ambition are both linked together; and Ambition is like <hi>Choller,</hi> which is an humor that makes men active, earneſt, and full of alacrity &amp; ſtirring, if it bee not ſtopped or hindred in its courſe: But if it be ſtopped, and cannot have its way, it becommeth duſt, and thereby maligne and venemous. So Ambitions and proud men, if they find the way open for their riſing and advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſtill get forwards; they are rather buſie then dangerous: But if they bee checked in their deſires, they become ſecretly diſcontent, and look upon men and matters with an evill eye, and are beſt pleaſed when things goe backewards: but I forbeare to ſpeake any further herein.</p>
            <p>The Cardinall beeing departed, Maſter King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton ſent poſt to <hi>London</hi> one of the Guard, then was Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> and the Abbot in conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about the Funerall, which was ſolempnized the day after, for Maſter Kingſton would not ſtay the returne of the Poſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:53022:72"/>
They thought good that the Major of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> and his Brethren ſhould ſee him perſonally dead, to prevent falſe reports that hee was alive And in the Interim, whilſt the Major was ſent for, his Bones were laid in the Coffin, and his ſhirt of haire and his over ſhirt of fine holland were taken off and were put into the Coffin together, with all ſuch ornaments wherewith he was inveſted, when hee was made Arehbiſhop, as <hi>Miter, Croſſe, Ring</hi> and <hi>Pall,</hi> with all other things due to his orders.</p>
            <p>Thus hee lay all that day with his Coffin opon and bare faced: that all that deſired might ſee him. And about 3. of the Clock he was buried of the Abbot with great ſolemnity. And being in the Church, his corpes were ſet in the Ladies Chappel <note place="margin">The Cardinal is buried in St Maries Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter.</note> with many Tapers or poor men about him holding Torches in their hands, who watched the Corps all that night, whilſt the Canons ſung divers dir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and other divine Oriſons.</p>
            <p>And at 4. of the Clock the next morning, the Cardinalls ſervants and Maſter <hi>Kingſton</hi> came to the Church to the execution of many Ceremonies in ſuch manner as is uſuall to Biſhops burialls: And ſo he went to Maſſe, where the Abbot did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and divers others: And then went to burie the Corpes in the middle of the ſaid Chappell, by this time it was fire of the Clocke, being St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> day.</p>
            <p>Then we prepared for our journey to the Court, where wee attended his Majeſtie, the next day I was ſent for to the King, conducted by Maſter <hi>Norris,</hi> where the King was in his night gowne
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:53022:72"/>
of Rochet velvet furred with ſables, before whom I kneeled the ſpace of an houre, during which time his Majeſtie examined me of divers particulars concerning my Lord Cardinall wiſhing rather then twenty thouſand pounds that he had lived.</p>
            <p>He asked me concerning the fifteen hundred pounds which Maſter <hi>Kingston</hi> moved to my Lord. Quoth I, I thinke I can perfectly tell your Grace where it is and who hath it, can you quoth the K. I pray you tell mee, and you ſhall not bee unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded.</p>
            <p>Sir quoth I, after the departure of Maſter <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> from my Lord at <hi>Ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oby,</hi> who had the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy thereof leaving it with my L. in divers baggs he delivered it to a certaine Prieſt ſafelie to bee kept to his uſe, is this true quoth the King? yea quoth I, without doubt, the Prieſt will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie it before mee, for I was at the deliverie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, who hath gotten divers other rich Ornaments, which are not Regiſtred in the book of my Lords inventorie or other writings, whereby any man is able to charghim there with but my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Then ſaid the King, let me alone for keeping this ſecret between me and you. Howbeit three may keepe Counſell if two be away: And if I knew my Cap were privie to my Counſell, <hi>I</hi> would caſt it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fire and burne it: And for your honeſty and Truth, you ſhall bee our ſervant in our Chamber, as you were with your Maſter.</p>
            <p>Therefore goe you your wayes to Sir <hi>Iohn Gage</hi> our Vice-Chamberlain, to whom wee have ſpoken alreadie, to admit you our ſervant in our Chamber, and then goe to the Lord of <hi>Norfolke</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:53022:73"/>
and hee ſhall pay you your whole yeares wages which is ten pounds, is not it ſo quoth the King? Yea forſooth and if it pleaſe your Grace quoth I. And withall ſaid the King, you ſhall receive a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Duke of <hi>Norfolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So I received tenne pounds of the Duke for my wages, and twenty pounds for my reward, and his Majeſtie gave me a Cart and ſix horſes the beſt that I could choſe out of my Lords horſes to carry my goods and five marks for my charge home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53022:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
