<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Parables reflecting upon the times</title>
            <author>Howell, James, 1594?-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2004-05">2004-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3099</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11502</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12254158</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12254158</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57275-01</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A70279)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57275-01)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 149:9 or 239:E67, no 16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Parables reflecting upon the times</title>
                  <author>Howell, James, 1594?-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Political allegory dealing with events between 1603 and 1640.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to James Howell. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Title page vignette.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library and Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Allegories.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Early Stuarts, 1603-1649 --  Fiction.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57275-01:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57275-01:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Parables, REFLECTING <hi>Upon the</hi> TIMES.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed at PARIS, MDCXLIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:57275-01:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57275-01:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the choicest of my Noble Friends, <hi>Sir—D. Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst many other Barbarismes which like an impetuous Torrent have lately rush'd in upon us, The interception and opening of Letters is none of the least, For it hath quite bereft all ingenious Spirits of that correspondencie and sweet communication of fancie, which hath been alwayes esteemed the best fuell of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the very marrow of friendship. And truely, in my judgement, this custom may be termed not onely a <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risme,</hi> but the basest kind of <hi>Burglary</hi> that can be, 'tis worse then picking of a lock, or breaking into a roome by violence for he who doth so, robs us peradventur of some outward pelf or baggage offortune; but he who breaks open ones private let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or seale, may be said to plunder his very brains, and rob him of his most precious meditations. We are reduced here to that servile condition, or rather to such a height of slavery, that we have nothing left which may entitle us free rationall creatures; the <hi>thought</hi> it self cannot say 'tis free, much lesse the <hi>tongue</hi> or <hi>pen.</hi> Which makes me impart unto You the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verses of these turbulent times, under the following fables. I know you are an exquisite Astronomer. I know the deep inspection you have in all parts of Philosophy, I know you are
<pb facs="tcp:57275-01:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a good Herald, and I have found in your study sundry books of architecture, and Comments upon <hi>Vitruvius.</hi> The unfold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of these <hi>Apologues</hi> will put you to it in all these, and will require your second, if not your third Thoughts, and when you have concocted them well, I beleeve, (else I am much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in your Genius) they will afford you some entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and doe the arrand upon which they are sent, which is, to communicate unto you the most materiall passages of this long'd for Parlement, &amp; of these sad confusions, which have so unhing'd, distorted, transvers'd, tumbled and dislocated all things, that <hi>England</hi> may be termed now, in comparison of what it was, no other then an <hi>Anagram of a Kingdom.</hi> One thing I promise you, in the perusall of these Parables, that you shall find no gingles in them, or any thing sordid or scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous, the common dialect and disease of these times. So I leave you to the gard and guidance of</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>Vertue,</hi> who doe still advance</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Votaries,</hi> maugre the frownes of <hi>Chance.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your constant servant,
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="parables">
            <div type="parable">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57275-01:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The great CONJUNCTION, OR, <hi>Parlement of</hi> STARS.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon a time, the <hi>Stars</hi> complained to <hi>Apollo,</hi> that he dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played his beames too much upon some malignant <hi>Planets;</hi> That the <hi>Moone</hi> had too great a share of his influence, and that he was carryed away too much by her motion: They complained also, that the constellation of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra</hi> (which holds the ballance of Justice) had but a dim light, and that the <hi>Astrean</hi> Court was grown altogether destructive, with divers other grievances. <hi>Apollo</hi> hereupon, commanded <hi>Mercury</hi> to summon a generall Synod, where some out of every <hi>Asterisme</hi> throughout the whole Firmament were to meet; <hi>Apollo</hi> told them, I am placed here by the finger of the Almighty, to be Monarch of the <hi>Skie,</hi> to be the Measurer of <hi>Time,</hi> and I goe upon his errand round about the world every foure and tweny houres: I am also the Fountaine of <hi>Heate</hi> and <hi>Light,</hi> which, though I use to dispence and diffuse in equall proportions throughout the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse; yet there is difference 'twixt objects: a <hi>Castle</hi> hath more of my light then a <hi>Cottage,</hi> and the <hi>Cedar</hi> hath more of me then the <hi>Shrub:</hi> But touching the <hi>Moon,</hi> (the second great <hi>Luminary</hi>) I would have you know, that she is dearest unto mee, therefore let none repine that I cherish her with my beames, and confer more light on her then any other. Touching the malignant <hi>Planets,</hi> or any other <hi>Star,</hi> of what magnitude soever, that moves not in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular motion, or hath run any <hi>excentrique exorbitant</hi> course, or that would have made me to move out of the <hi>Zodiak,</hi> I put them over unto you, that upon due examination and proof, they may be <hi>unspher'd</hi> or extinguished. But I would have this done with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; I would have you to keep as neer as you can betweene the <hi>Tropiques</hi> and temperate <hi>Zones:</hi> I would have things reduced
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57275-01:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to their true Principles, reformed, not ruin'd; I would have the spirit of malice and lying, the spirit of partiality and injustice, the spirit of tyranny and rigour, the base spirit of feare and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie to be farre from this glorious <hi>Syderean</hi> Synod; I would have all private interests reflecting upon revenge or profit, to be utterly banished hence: Moreover, I would not have you to make grievances, where no grievances are, or dangers, where no dangers are; I would have no <hi>creation</hi> of dangers; I would have you to husband time as parsimoniously as you can, lest by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too long together, and amusing the world with such tedious hopes of redresse of grievances, you prove your selfe the greatest grievance at last, and so from <hi>Starres,</hi> become <hi>Comets:</hi> Lastly, I would have you be cautious how you tamper with my Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power, and chop Logicke with mee in that point; you know what became of <hi>Him,</hi> who once presumed to meddle with my Chariot. Hereupon the whole Host of <hi>Heaven</hi> being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stellated thus into one great <hi>Body,</hi> fell into a serious deliberation of things; and <hi>Apollo</hi> himselfe continued his presence, and sate amongst them in his full <hi>lustre,</hi> but in the meane time, whilest they were in the midst of their consultations, many odde <hi>Aspects, Oppositions,</hi> and <hi>Conjunctions</hi> hapned betweene them: for some of the <hi>Sporades,</hi> but specially those mongrel small vulgar <hi>stars,</hi> which make up the <hi>Galaxia</hi> (the milkie way in <hi>Heaven</hi>) gather in a tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous disorderly manner about the body of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit many strange insolencies, which caused <hi>Apollo</hi> (taking young<note place="margin">The <hi>Prince</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Phosphorous</hi> the <hi>Morning-Star</hi> with him) to retire himselfe, and in a just indignation to withdraw his <hi>Light</hi> from the <hi>Synod:</hi> so all began to be involv'd in a strange kind of confusion and obscurity; they groaped in the dark, not knowing which way to move, or what course to take, all things went <hi>Cancer-like</hi> retrograde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the <hi>Sunne</hi> detained his <hi>beames</hi> and <hi>irradiations</hi> from them.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>MORALL.</head>
                  <p>Such as the <hi>Sunne</hi> is in the Frmament, a <hi>Monarch</hi> is in his Kingdome: for, as the Wisest of men saith; <hi>In the light of the Kings Countenance there is life;</hi> and I believe that to be the <hi>Morall</hi> of this <hi>Astrean Fable.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="parable">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:57275-01:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>OR,</hi> The Great Councell of <hi>BIRDS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>UPon a time the <hi>Birds</hi> met in Councell, for redresse of some extravagancies that had <hi>flowne</hi> unto the <hi>volatill Empire;</hi> Nor was it the first time that <hi>Birds</hi> met thus; for the <hi>Phrygian Fabler</hi> tells us of divers meetings of theirs: And after him we read that <hi>Apollonius Thyaneus,</hi> undertook the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of their language, and to be their <hi>Drogoman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They thus assembled in one great <hi>Covie</hi> by the call of the <hi>Eagle</hi> their unquestioned hereditary King, and by vertue of his Royall Authority, complaints were brought, that divers <hi>Cormorants</hi> and <hi>Harpies,</hi> with other <hi>Birds</hi> of prey, had got in amongst them, who did much annoy and invade the publique liberty: sundry other <hi>Birds</hi> were questioned, which caused <hi>some</hi> to take a timely flight<note place="margin">Finch, &amp;c</note> into another ayre.</p>
               <p>As they were thus consulting for advancement of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<note place="margin">Mechanick Mariners.</note> good, many <hi>Rooks, Horne-Owles</hi> and <hi>Sea-Gulls</hi> flock'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and fluttered about the place they were assembled in, where they kept a hideous noyse, and committed many outrages, and nothing could satisfie them, but the <hi>Griffons</hi> head, which was therefore chopt off, and offered up as a sacrifice to make them<note place="margin">E. Straff.</note> leave their chattering, and to appease their fury for the time.</p>
               <p>They fell foule afterwards upon the <hi>Pies,</hi> who were used to be<note place="margin">Bishops.</note> much reverenced, and to sit upon the highest <hi>pearch</hi> in that great Assembly: they called them Idolatrous and inauspitious <hi>Birds,</hi> they hated their mixt colour, repined at their long traine, they tore their white feathers, and were ready to peck out their very eyes: they did what they could to put them in <hi>Owles</hi> feathers (as the poore <hi>Sheep</hi> was in the <hi>Woolfs</hi> skin) to make them the more hated, and to be star'd and hooted at wheresoever they passed. The <hi>Pies</hi> being thus scar'd, presented a Petition to the royall <hi>Eagle,</hi> and to this his great Counsell, that they might be secured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire safely thither to sit and consult, according to the ancient
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57275-01:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Lawes of the <hi>Volatill Empire</hi> continued so many ages without controllment or question: in which Petition they inserted a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test</hi> or <hi>Caveat,</hi> that no publique act should passe in the interim. This Supplication, both for matter and form, was excepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst, and cryed up to be high Treason, specially that indefinite <hi>Protest</hi> they had made, that no Act whatsoever should be of any validity without them, which was alledged to derogate from the High Law-making power of that great Counsell, and rended to retard and disturb the great Affairs which were then in agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: so the poore <hi>Pies,</hi> as if by that Petition they had like the <hi>Black-bird</hi> voyded Lime to catch themselves, for <hi>Turdus cacat sibi malum,</hi> were suddenly hurried away into a Cage, and after ten long Moneths canvassing of the point, they were <hi>unpearch'd,</hi> and rendred for ever uncapable to be members of that Court, they were struck dumb and voice-lesse, and suddenly blowne up away thence, though without any force of <hi>powder,</hi> as once was plotted against them. But this was done when a thin number of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse <hi>Birds</hi> had kept still together, and stuck close against them, and after that the <hi>Bill</hi> concerning them had been once ejected, which they humbly conceived by the ancient order of that Court could not be re-admitted in the same Session. They peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned from the place they were cooped in, that for heavens sake, for the honour of that noble Counsell, for Truth and Justice sake, they being as free-born Denisons of the ayrie <hi>Region,</hi> as any other <hi>Volatills</hi> whatsoever, their charge might be perfected, that so they might be brought to a legall triall and not forced to languish in such captivitie. They pleaded to have done nothing but what they had precedents for: And touching the <hi>Caveat</hi> they had inserted, it was a thing usuall in every inferiour Court of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, and had they forborn to have done it, they had <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> their own nest,</hi> and done wrong to their successors. It was affirmed they had been members of that Body politique, long before those <hi>lower pearch'd Birds,</hi> who now would cast them out; and that they had been their best friends to introduce them to have any thing to doe in that generall Counsell: they prayed they might not be so cruelly used, as the <hi>Solan goose,</hi> and <hi>Redshanke</hi> had used them,<note place="margin">Scot.</note>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:57275-01:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
who were not content to <hi>braile</hi> and <hi>clip</hi> their wings onely, but to <hi>seare</hi> them so, that they should never grow again; to handle them so unmercifully, was not the way to make their adversaries <hi>Birds of Paradice:</hi> In fine, they advised them to remember what the sick <hi>Kite's</hi> mother answered him, when he desired her to pray to the gods for him, <hi>How canst thou, said she, expect any good from the gods, whose Temples thou hast so violated?</hi> At last, upon the importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and pitifulnesse of their Petitions, the accusation of <hi>Treason,</hi> which kept such a noyse at first, being declined against them, they were released in the morning, but cooped up again before night: and after the revolution of foure full Moones, they were restored again to a conditionall liberty, under which they remaine till this day.</p>
               <p>There wants not some, who affirm, that in that great Counsell of <hi>Birds,</hi> there were some <hi>Decoyes</hi> (and 'tis well known <hi>where De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyes</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Holland.</note> were first bred) who called in, not onely these mongrill ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streperous <hi>Birds</hi> from abroad to commit such outrages as were spoken of before, but drew after them also many of the greatest <hi>Birds,</hi> who sate in that Assembly, to follow them whither they listed: Others, who were of a more <hi>generous</hi> extraction, disdained to be such <hi>Buzzards,</hi> as to be carried away hood-wincked in that manner, to be <hi>Birds of their feather.</hi> Thus a visible faction was hatched in this great Counsell, as if the said <hi>Decoyes</hi> had disgor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and let fall some graines of <hi>Hemlock</hi> seeds amongst them to distemper their braines. Or, as if some <hi>Spinturnix,</hi> that fatall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiary <hi>Bird,</hi> or some ill-boding <hi>Scritch-Owle,</hi> which as stories tell us appeared once at <hi>Rome,</hi> in a famous, though unfortunate great Councell (when there was a schisme in the Popedome) had appeared likewise here. There wanted not also amongst them some <hi>Amphibious Birds,</hi> as the <hi>Barnacle,</hi> which is neither Fish nor Fowle; and the cunning <hi>Batt,</hi> who sometimes professeth himself a <hi>Bird,</hi> sometimes a <hi>Mouse.</hi> I will not say there were any <hi>Paphla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonian Birds</hi> amongst them, who are known to have double hearts: But 'tis certaine, that in this confusion there were some malevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Birds,</hi> and many of them so young, that they were scarce <hi>fledg'd,</hi> who like the <hi>Waspe</hi> in the Fable, conspired to fire the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57275-01:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Eagles</hi> nest, (and a <hi>Waspe</hi> may sometimes doe mischiefe to an <hi>Eagle,</hi> as a <hi>Mouse</hi> to an <hi>Elephant.</hi>) Moreover, some of these light brained <hi>Birds</hi> flew so high, that they seemed to arrogate to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and exercise royall power, but foolishly; for we know what became of the <hi>Crow</hi> upon the <hi>Ram's</hi> back, when she thought to imitate the <hi>Eagle:</hi> And it was observed that <hi>they</hi> were most eager to attempt those high insolences against Jove's Bird, <hi>who had been stark naked, and as bare as</hi> Cootes, unlesse he had feathered them; so that the little <hi>Ant</hi> was more gratefull to <hi>Esops Bird,</hi> then those <hi>Birds</hi> were to the <hi>Eagle,</hi> their liege Lord. But the high-borne <hi>Bird</hi> with the two <hi>golden wings,</hi> the noble <hi>Faulcons,</hi> the <hi>Martlets,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">M. Hert.</note> the <hi>Ravens,</hi> the <hi>Swan,</hi> the <hi>Chough,</hi> and all the ancient <hi>Birds</hi> of the<note place="margin">E. South.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">E. Westm.</note> 
                  <hi>mountains</hi> remained faithfull and firme to the <hi>Eagle,</hi> and scorned<note place="margin">E. Worce.</note> to be carried away by such <hi>Decoyes;</hi> As also the generous <hi>Ostri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">E. Dover.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Wales.</note> who unlesse they had had an extraordinary stomach, could<note place="margin">Digbies.</note> not have digested such <hi>yron</hi> pills as were offered them. Amongst other great <hi>Birds</hi> which banded against the <hi>Eagle,</hi> the flying <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">E. Pemb.</note> 
                  <hi>green</hi> and <hi>white,</hi> were busy, specially the <hi>white;</hi> And for the<note place="margin">E. Warw.</note> 
                  <hi>Green,</hi> considering he was an ancient <hi>bird</hi> of the <hi>Mountains,</hi> and that his Progenitors had been so renowned for their rare loyalty to the Crown, every one wondred that he should be drawn so far by the foresayed <hi>Decoyes,</hi> as to be the first of his race that should clap his wings against his Soveraign Liege Lord.</p>
               <p>The foresaid destractions continued still, and increased more and more in that generall convolation of <hi>Birds;</hi> therefore the <hi>Turtle</hi> would stay there no longer, there was so much <hi>gall</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them: the <hi>Pelican</hi> flew away, he saw <hi>Piety</hi> so vilified; the <hi>Dove</hi> was weary of their company, she found no <hi>simplicity</hi> and plain dealing amongst them: And the <hi>Kings-Fisher,</hi> the <hi>Halcyon,</hi> (the Embleme of <hi>Peace</hi>) quite forsook them, he found so much<note place="margin">Arondelle.</note> jarring, dissentions, and bandings on all sides; the <hi>Swallow</hi> also, who had so ancient and honourable a ranke amongst them, got into another ayre, he fore-saw the weather was like to be so foul:<note place="margin">Her <hi>Majesty</hi>
                  </note> And lastly, <hi>Philomela,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Volatills,</hi> who was partner of the <hi>Eagle's</hi> nest, abandoned them quite, and put a Sea 'twixt her and them; nay, the <hi>Eagle</hi> himself withdrew his royall presence
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57275-01:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
from them; so the <hi>Decoyes</hi> afore-said carried all before them, and comported themselves by their <hi>Orders</hi> in that hight, as if like the <hi>Lapwing,</hi> every one had a <hi>Crowne</hi> on his head; they so inchanted in a manner, all the common sort of <hi>Oppidan, rurall,</hi> and <hi>Sea-birds,</hi> and infused such a credulity into them, that they believed them to have an inerring <hi>spirit,</hi> and what came from them, was as true as the <hi>Pentateuch:</hi> Moreover, it was shrewdly suspected, that there was a pernicious plot amongst them to let in the <hi>Stork,</hi> who is never seen to stay long in any <hi>Monarchie.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>MORALL.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moderation</hi> is that Golden Rule whereby all great Counsells should square their deliberations, and nothing can tend more to their Honour or dishonour, in point of Wisdome: Moreover, in a Successive hereditary Monarchy, when subjects assume <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Power,</hi> and barre the Holy <hi>Church</hi> of her <hi>Rights,</hi> and that <hi>Reverence</hi> which is due to her chief Professors, It is the most compendious way to bring all things to confusion, and consequently to an inevitable ruine; or some fatall Change.</p>
                  <p>And this I hold to be the chiefest <hi>Morall</hi> of this Apologue of <hi>Birds.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="parable">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The gathering together, or <hi>Parlement</hi> of FLOWERS.</head>
               <p>UPon a time, The <hi>Flowers</hi> assembled, and met in one gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Counsell, by the authority and summons of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign <hi>Rose,</hi> their undoubted naturall King, who had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the <hi>Lilly</hi> for his royall spouse. The dew of Heaven fell plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully upon this happy conjunction, which made them to <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon,</hi> to propagate and prosper exceedingly, in so much, that the sweet fragrant <hi>odor</hi> which they did cast, diffused it self over all the earth. To this meeting came the <hi>Violet,</hi> the <hi>Gilliflower, Rose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary,</hi> the <hi>Tulyp, Lavender</hi> and <hi>Thyme,</hi> the <hi>Cinquefoyle</hi> (though of<note place="margin">M. Ham.</note> a forren growth) had an honourable ranke amongst them, and as some observed got too much credit with the royall <hi>Rose.</hi> The <hi>Flowers</hi> of the <hi>field</hi> were admitted also to this great Counsell; the <hi>Couslip,</hi> the <hi>Honysuckle</hi> and <hi>Daisie</hi> had their Delegates there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, to consult of a Reformation of certain abuses which had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>rooting</hi> in the Common wealth of <hi>Flowers,</hi> and being all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57275-01:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the <hi>Rose,</hi> they had priviledge to speak all things with free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; Complaints were made that much <hi>Cockle</hi> and <hi>Darnell,</hi> with other noxious <hi>Herbs</hi> and <hi>Tares</hi> were crept in amongst them, that the <hi>Poppie</hi> did <hi>pullulat</hi> too much, with divers other grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The successe of this Senat, this great <hi>Bed</hi> or <hi>Posie</hi> of living <hi>Flowers,</hi> was like to prove very prosperous, but that the <hi>herb Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony, Wormwood, Wolfebane, Rue,</hi> and <hi>Melampod</hi> (the emblems of Sedition, <hi>Malice, Feare, Ambition</hi> and <hi>Iealousie</hi>) thrust in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, and much distempered their proceedings: These brought in with them the <hi>Burr,</hi> which exceedingly retarded and intangled all businesses; and it was thought, that the <hi>Thistle</hi> was<note place="margin">cot.</note> too meddling amongst them, which made matters grow to that acrimony and confusion, as if the <hi>herb Morsus diaboli</hi> had got in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them. Amongst many other good-morrowes, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to the <hi>Rose,</hi> that he should part with his <hi>prickles,</hi> and transmit his strength that way to be disposed of by them; the <hi>Rose</hi> liked not this bold request of theirs, though couched in very smooth language, but answered, I have hitherto condescended to every thing you have propounded, much more then any of my Predecessors ever did; but touching these <hi>prickles,</hi> which God and nature hath given mee, and are inherent in me and my stock from the beginning, though they be but excressencies, yet you know they fortifie and arme me, <hi>Armat Spina Rosam,</hi> And by them I protect you and your <hi>rights</hi> from violence, and what <hi>protection I pray can there be without strength?</hi> therefore I will by no means part with them to enfeeble my regall Power, but will retain them still, and bequeath them to my Posterity, which I would be loth to betray in this point; nor doe I much value what that silly <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sected</hi> Animal, the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Bees</hi> tells me sometimes, when hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming up and down my leaves, he would buzze this fond belief in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, how it added much to his Majestie, that nature gives him no <hi>sting,</hi> as all other <hi>Bees</hi> have because he should rely altogether upon the love and loyalty of his subjects. No; I will take warning by the <hi>Eagle,</hi> the King of <hi>Volatills,</hi> and by the <hi>Lyon,</hi> King of <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drupedals,</hi> who (as the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Moralists</hi> reports) when by fayre<note place="margin">Plut.</note> insinuations the one had parted with his <hi>tallons,</hi> the other with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57275-01:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his <hi>teeth</hi> and <hi>ongles,</hi> wherein their might, and consequently their Majesty consisted, grew afterwards contemptible to all creatures, and quite lost that naturall alleaigeance and awe which was due unto the one from all <hi>birds,</hi> and to the other, from all <hi>beasts</hi> of <hi>field</hi> and <hi>forest.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>MORALL.</head>
                  <p>Every naturall borne Monarch, hath an inherent inalienable strength in himselfe, which is the common <hi>Militia</hi> of his Kingdome; for, though the peoples love (which oftentimes is got by an Apple, and lost by a Peare) be a good Cittadell, yet there must be a concurrence of some visible settled force besides, which no earthly power may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of without his royall commands: and for him to transmit this strength to any other, is the only way to render him inglorious and despicable, both at home and abroad<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And thus you have the spirit of these Flowers, and <hi>Morall</hi> of the <hi>Fabl.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="parable">
               <head>The Assembly of <hi>Architects</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere was an ancient goodly <hi>Palace,</hi> composed of divers pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and partition'd into sundry <hi>Chambers, Halls</hi> and <hi>Courts</hi> which were supported by mixt <hi>Pillars,</hi> partly <hi>Corinthian, partly Ionique,</hi> but principally by the <hi>Dorique,</hi> the King of <hi>Columnes,</hi> having the firmest <hi>Pedestall:</hi> Some tooke exceptions, and alledged, that some of the said <hi>Courts</hi> were too high, and some of the <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> in this <hi>Structure</hi> were too wide. The Lord of this <hi>Palace</hi> call'd together the best <hi>Masons</hi> and <hi>Architects,</hi> to advise with him (not without him) for mending of those faults, the better contrivance of the roomes, and to reduce the <hi>Building</hi> to a just proportion. They solemnely met, and falling to consultation hereof, they found that the <hi>Chamber</hi> which was spangled with <hi>Stars,</hi> and where his private Councell of <hi>State</hi> did use to sit, were too wide; they thought that the <hi>Court</hi> erected on the <hi>North side,</hi> and that learned <hi>Court</hi> where <hi>Ecclesiasticall</hi> matters were scanned, was too <hi>high;</hi> These, with that peculiar <hi>Court</hi> which was erected for the support of Honour, they went about in lieu of rectifying, to ruinate and raze to the very ground; and some of these <hi>Masons</hi> (for indeed they were rather <hi>Masons</hi> then true <hi>Architects</hi>) were so precise and over criticall, that they seem'd to find fault with the position of the <hi>Chappell</hi> that belong'd to this <hi>Palace,</hi> because, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth it stood <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West,</hi> which situation, only in regard it was ancient, they held to be a superstitious posture; They seem'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57275-01:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
at the decencie, riches and ornaments of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with divers other frivolous exceptions. The Lord of the <hi>Palace</hi> said little to that, but touching the errors and disproportions in the foresaid <hi>Courts</hi> and <hi>Chambers,</hi> he was very willing they should be amended, and reduced to a true dimension and symmetrie; and that all other roomes should be searched, and swept cleane: but hee would be loth to see those ancient pieces quite demolish'd, for that would hazard the fall of the maine Fabrique, his princely hereditary pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony (descended upon him from so many wise <hi>Oeconomists</hi> and royall <hi>Progenitors</hi>) in regard of the <hi>juncture</hi> and <hi>contignation</hi> those parts had with the whole frame. To mend a thing by demolishing it, is as curing a sicke body by knocking him in the head: he told them it was easier far to pull downe, then build up; one may batter to pieces in one houre, that which cannot be built in age: That everlasting <hi>Villaine,</hi> who burnt the <hi>Ephesian</hi> Temple, destroyed, as it were in a trice, what was a rearing up ten long <hi>Olympiads:</hi> He wish'd them further to be very cautious how they meddled with the <hi>Angulars</hi> and <hi>Basis</hi> of that royall <hi>Structure;</hi> for so they might prove as wise as those <hi>Architects, who tooke out some of the foundation stones, to repaire the roofe.</hi> Last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he told them, that if they intended to pull downe any part of his now standing <hi>Palace,</hi> they should be well advised before hand of the fashion whereof those new pieces should be, which they purposed to reare up in the roome of the old.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>MORALL.</head>
                  <p>Innovations are of dangerous consequence in all things, specially in a settled well temper'd <hi>State;</hi> therefore there should be great heed taken, before any ancient <hi>Court</hi> of Judicature, erected as a Pillar to support Justice by the wisedome of our Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, be quite put downe; for it may shake the whole Frame of Government, and intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a change; and changes in Government are commonly fatall, for seldome comes a better. And this I hold to be the aime of this <hi>Apologue.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="parable">
               <head>The Insurrection of the <hi>Winds.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT fortuned, that the <hi>Winds</hi> banded against <hi>Eolus:</hi> And <hi>Boreas</hi> (the <hi>North-wind</hi>) began to bluster first, and would <hi>blow where</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:57275-01:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>he listed,</hi> he grew so boisterous, that as he is call'd <hi>Scopa viarum,</hi> the high-way Beesome, he seem'd to sweep all before him <hi>Southward,</hi> insomuch, that uniting all his strength into one body, hee made towards <hi>Eolus</hi> in a hostile armed manner, and so obtained of him what he desired. After his example (and an odde example it was) the <hi>West-wind,</hi> his fellow subject rose up, alledging, that though he blew from the <hi>left-side</hi> of Heaven, yet hee deserved to be as much favoured as <hi>Boreas.</hi> In regard he drove a far richer trade, and blew upon a more fertile Countrey, which brought in much more benefit to the rest of <hi>Eolus</hi> his Dominions; therefore hee would have his liberties also assur'd him, which hee pretended were as ancient as the others: And he puft with such an impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous violence, that his blasts brought with them (God wot) divers showres of blood, and whole Cataracts of calamities<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And as it is observed in the course of Naturall things, that one mischiefe sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome marcheth alone, but ushers in another, and hath alwayes its concomitants, so these <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Western</hi> gusts, as one wave useth to drive on another, made all the winds in the compasse, both <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laterall</hi> and <hi>cardinall,</hi> to rise up and rebell against <hi>Eolus,</hi> even under that very Clime, and in those Horizons, where he kept his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall residence and royall <hi>Court.</hi> And this popular <hi>wind</hi> (for 'twas no other, take it all joyntly in one puffe) did rage with that vehemencie, that it turn'd every where into fearefull flames of fire, (issuing out of a kind of <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> which by its reper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussions, and furious arietations, did a world of mischiefe, as if it had been that incendiary <hi>Prester wind,</hi> or rather an <hi>Haraucana,</hi> that <hi>Indian</hi> gust, which alwayes brings the Divell along with it (as those Savages believe) had blowne here, For, <hi>surely God was not in this wind.</hi> Yet some were so simple, to thinke that this <hi>wind</hi> proceeded from divine <hi>inspirations;</hi> nay, they came to that height of prophanenesse, as to father it upon the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> though no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be more different to his sweet motions, nothing so directly opposite to his soft gentle <hi>breeses</hi> and <hi>eventilations;</hi> for no holy consecrated thing could stand before this <hi>Diabolicall wind,</hi> downe went all <hi>Crosses</hi> it met withall; it batter'd downe <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Chappell</hi> windowes (and I feare the walls and steeples
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57275-01:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
will next to wracke) It was so violent, that it overturn'd all stone Tables that stood <hi>Eastward;</hi> it blew away all the decent Vests and Ornaments of the <hi>Church;</hi> the <hi>Bishops Mitre<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> (an order con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary with Christianity it selfe) did quake like an <hi>Aspen</hi> leafe before it; nay, it shrewdly shooke the very Imperiall Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Crowne which stood on <hi>Eolus</hi> his head, so that he was like to become <hi>Ludibrium Ventorum.</hi> But the highest <hi>Deity</hi> of heaven, <hi>He who walketh upon the wings of the wind, and makes weight for them, and gathereth them in his fist when he pleaseth,</hi> hating such an odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous rebellion, <hi>rebuked</hi> these tumultuous <hi>winds,</hi> he caused a conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ayre, to rush in and mingle with them, and infect them with new diseases; besides whispers of jealousies, doubts and diffidence blew and buzz'd more and more amongst them, so that they could not trust one another, insomuch, that it made them to fall into confusion amongst themselves, which is the common fate of all rebellions. So <hi>Eolus</hi> recovered his <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and as they say, there is no <hi>wind</hi> but blowes some body good; so this turn'd much to the advantage of <hi>Eolus,</hi> for he grew ever after more firme and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter establish'd in his regall power, because hee put a competent guard in those Climes whence all these boistrous <hi>winds</hi> burst forth, and so secur'd himselfe ever after, that they could not blow where they listed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rebellion suppress'd, makes the Prince the stronger:</hi> And so you have the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall <hi>Morall all</hi> of this <hi>Parable</hi> in briefe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>Postscript.</head>
               <p>SIr, I long to receive your opinion of these rambling pieces of fancy, you may, peradventure, have more, when the times are open: surely the wind will not hold still in this unluckie hole, for it is too violent to last: It begins (thanks be to God) to sift already, and amongst those multitudes, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the change, I am one that lyeth at the <hi>Cape of good Hope,</hi> though a long time under hatches. Howsoever, though all the winds in the Compasse blow upon me, I am arm'd and resolv'd to beare the brunt, and to welcome the Will of God. If you desire a further intimation of things, I referre you to a Discourse, call'd <hi>The True Informer,</hi> who will give you no vulgar sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, <hi>So I am</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Yours as at first inalterable.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57275-01:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
