<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iohn Taylor being yet unhanged sends greeting to Iohn Booker that hanged him lately in a picture, in a traiterous, slanderous, and foolish London pamphlet called A cable-rope double-twisted</title>
            <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2005-12">2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A71179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T434</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14479</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11921082</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11921082</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50967</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A71179)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50967)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 232:E21, no 19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iohn Taylor being yet unhanged sends greeting to Iohn Booker that hanged him lately in a picture, in a traiterous, slanderous, and foolish London pamphlet called A cable-rope double-twisted</title>
                  <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L. Lichfield]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A scurrilous denunciation of Booker and all his works, in Taylor's usual style.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Booker, John, 1603-1667. --  No mercurius aquaticus, but a cable-rope double-twisted for John Taylor.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50967:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50967:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IOHN TAYLOR Being yet <hi>unhanged,</hi> sends greeting, to IOHN BOOKER That <hi>hanged</hi> him lately in a Picture, in a traiterous, slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous, and foolish <hi>London</hi> Pamphlet, called <hi>A Cable-Rope double-twisted.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Thou <hi>Booker</hi> hang'st me pictur'd in a Boat,</l>
               <l>Whereby thou shew'dst thy selfe the Hangman's Groom,</l>
               <l>The Hangman shall hang thee, and men shall note,</l>
               <l>That under <hi>Tyburne</hi> thou shalt have a Tombe:</l>
               <l>And lowsie Ballad-makers Rimes shall sing,</l>
               <l>There lies a Rebell, that revil'd his King:</l>
               <l>Thou hang'st my Picture, but I do foresee,</l>
               <l>That (in revenge) the Hangman shall hang thee.</l>
            </q>
            <q>Gallogras Choka Cur dog Weasando Suffocatiorum.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:50967:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ellfare an old Friend in a corner, but I have found an old corner in a Friend, that in these hard times hath sent me a True Loves Knot made of a Cable-Rope double-twisted, and withall hath most Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically, Mathematically, Aquatically, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blematically hanged me in a Boat at <hi>London,</hi> and after that (most strangely and transubstantially) he sends me a Rope to <hi>Oxford.</hi> This is <hi>Booker's</hi> Ass-tronomicall Legerdemain, to hang a man first and send him a Rope afterwards, for the which courtesie I will send him a few small Lines, which he may twist at his leasure, and hang himselfe after at his pleasure. But this <hi>prelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> is silly simple stuffe, for though it may be suitable to <hi>Booker's</hi> ridiculous Non-sense railing and reviling, yet it neither becomes me to write, or my Readers to spend time in reading my writings if they were not better seasoned with salt, poudered with pepper, sharpened with vineger, and made fit, and of some acute rellish for the pallates of such capacities, as can make a distinction betwixt A Very Knave, and A merry Knave.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Booker,</hi> all the world may perceive the implacability and inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teracy of thy malice for thou canst not be contented, to hang me, but thou persistest so uncharitably towards me as not onely to send me a Rope, but to revile me, with the learned Titles of Rogue, Prick-lowse, Pagan, Metropolitan Villain, and such other pretty Sirnames, which he learned from the Fish-wives scoulding Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge at <hi>Billingsgate,</hi> and that <hi>he should be loath to fowle his fingers to answer any Pamphlet that comes from</hi> Oxford, <hi>but that through his sides the honour of a Parliament is wounded:</hi> to which I answer, that Parliament at this time is a meer Conventicle, or not the shade of a shadow of what it should be, and thou thy selfe dost ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest the imbecility of it, in that it had no other fortifications but such rotten paper-walls as thy sides to defend it from the shot of a Scholars or a Scullars pen; Sirtha, I would have thee know, that we at <hi>Oxford</hi> are true Protestant pen-proofe, and the King, Queen,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50967:2"/>
Princes, Peeres, Clergy, Vniversity, Army, Magistrates, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, are slander-proofe, so that neither your rebellious fighting, or reviling writing, can wound, blemish or sully the Majestique lustre of Royalty, in the Soveraigne, or the obedient expression of duty in the Subject.</p>
            <p>But thou with thy Consorts, <hi>May, Wither, Britannicus,</hi> the <hi>Scout,</hi> the <hi>Dove,</hi> and all the Rabble of lying and reviling Rebells, cannot so much as scratch or touch my reputation, much lesse can they wound either <hi>Aulicus</hi> or <hi>Naworth,</hi> and least of all can they batter with Elder-guns and paper-bullets either majesty or loyalty.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> (or <hi>Robert</hi>) whom your sawcinesse is pleased to call plain <hi>Rupert,</hi> as if his Highnesse and your Knaveship were all fellowes at foot-ball, you are so stupified in impudence and unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly ignorance, that you give that illustrious Prince, the scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, Turkish Titles and Tearmes of <hi>Saladine</hi> and <hi>Saracen,</hi> with many other such base expressions: I do hold it a great happinesse to that noble Prince, that he hath worthily deserved to be feared and admired by you and all the rest of your rebellious and Traiterous Factions; you have some reason to be angry with him, because he hath so often beaten you, (although he never did any harme to any honest man, true Subject, or Protestant; yet such a stinckard as <hi>John Booker,</hi> Thou, that art a thing, that out of thy imperious Clerkship to some Justices of Peace, to foure or five of which thou wast a directing Gizzard, under their wing, a vermin made up of the fag-ends of fellonious cheating, filching, whoring, roguing, man-slaughtering, and murdering <hi>Mittimusses</hi>; thy apparrell one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made of the shreads of Warrants, thy diet out of the Scraps of roasted Recognizances, and thy whole life an imitation of Binding over and With-drawing, this hath been thy Trade of old, thou whilom Vnder-Stewards man to one of the Innes of Court, where thou didst fatten and batten with scraps, rumps and kidnies, and scraping of Trenchers, and lately a <hi>Guild-hall</hi> Publican or Toll-ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer for the maintenance of damned Rebellion against God and the King.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>Booker,</hi> this Thing, this Nothing, this any thing (except a good thing) doth flirt poyson, and with stinking calumnies against the sacred Honour of Princes, Religion, piety, and humanity, revile the King, Queen, and all that sincerely love or obey either God or them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50967:3"/>
If they were a Parliament, which thou so manifestest, they would shew some fruits of a Parliament, in hanging thee, with all thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (Knaves and Libellers) that do make a dayly and weekly Trade to vilifie their Soveraigne, with the Queen and loyall Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. There is a Statute unrepealed yet, that makes it no lesse than High Treason, or Treason in the highest degree; and that Act be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing still in force, me thinkes, should stop your mouth with a hempen cullisse or Caudle. But your nick-name Parliament doth not onely maintain and retain a scattered Heard of scribling Villaines, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so they do allow most respect, favour, countenance and meanes to him that can lye, raile and slander most: therefore I conclude, if they were a Parliament, the sacred Name and Honour of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty should not be suffered to be abused so transcendently (beyond all presidents) but that they would by Law and Parliamentary Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority send yee all to <hi>Gregories</hi> market, and feed Crowes with your traiterous mischievous Heads, and filthy, treacherous, rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, stinking, quartered carcases: therefore no Parliament.</p>
            <p>But do thou and all the rest of the Generation of Vipers cast ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so many of your Traiterous slanders upon his sacred Majesty and his pious sincerity, yet his Royall and Christian constancy is so firme, that you do all justly deserve an universall hanging, in not believing and belying his fixed and (never to be violated) true Protestations, His Majesty is so well grounded in His Religion, that He is resolved to maintain, defend, live and die in the Protestant Faith, of which Faith His Father (of blessed Memory) and himselfe have been De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders above fourty yeares, and which Faith you and your Faction have been Defilers almost foure yeares.</p>
            <p>I wish you had the manners to forbeare taxing His Majesty with Papistry, till such time as you know Him to be no Protestant. Indeed He is in minde and body compacted of such an unyeilding constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which your loyalty may call stubbornesse) that He will not bend or bow to your new-found Doctrine, so that there is no hope that you will ever be able to make a zealous Brownist, or devout Anabaptist of Him; therefore I advise you to be quiet, and let him be a Protestant still, for you labour in vain, and it is neither in the power of you, or the Devill your Master, to alter Him from being constant, pious, just, mercifull, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou railest most delicately, against learning and the Vniversity,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50967:3"/>
which in one word or two I will answer with an old said Saw, <hi>Art hath no enemy but ignorance,</hi> as for the King, Queen, Peeres, Clergy, Vniversity, Cavaliery, Infantry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their own worths and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are their vindications, so that I will not presume to say thou canst wound their Honours, either through my weak sides, or any wayes else that thy hellish brain can invent, therefore Ile let them alone to defend themselves, and turne once more towards thee in mine own defence.</p>
            <p>As when <hi>Christopher Columbus</hi> (an <hi>Italian</hi>) first discovered some small part of the (then unknown) <hi>America, Vespusius</hi> (a <hi>Spaniard</hi>) sailing the year after, with the Chart or Card, Compasse, Mappes, and Mariners, that formerly <hi>Columbus</hi> had used, the said <hi>Vespusius</hi> discovered more Land, as the golden <hi>Peru,</hi> and other vast Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, and at his returne (being at dinner with <hi>Columbus</hi> and others) <hi>Vespusius</hi> bragged that he had onely found out that new and rich World, at which words the <hi>Italian</hi> took an Egge in his hand, ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Vespusius,</hi> if he could make the Egge stand on one end upon the Table, to which he answered, he could not do it, then the other said that he could do it, and presently he put the Egges end into the Salt, and it stood upright; then the <hi>Spaniard</hi> said, that he could do that tricke as well as he, to which the <hi>Italian</hi> replied, so you could finde <hi>America</hi> when I have shewn you the way. And much like hast thou <hi>Booker</hi> answered my Book, called [<hi>No Mercurius Auli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi>] thou hast (like an Asse) yoaked thy selfe with my Heifer, for thou hast not the wit to plough without her, you play with your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-grammaticall foolery in Anagrammatizing my name, (as <hi>John Tayler, Joyn Halter</hi>) and fillest thy patched Pamphet with questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning and cavilling, at changing [<hi>o</hi>] into [<hi>e</hi>] with such skimble scamble, simple, froathy stuffe, as would serve to give a knowing hide-bound Dog a comfortable stoole or two.</p>
            <p>But as they are, and the condition they now are in, they have no other way of supportation, but what proceeds from the blacke mouthes of your zealous, Atheisticall, long-winded Preachers (or Tautologicall prating Lecturers) with the aide of you and your holy Tribe of accursed Pamphlet mongers; it is you that with your Spirituall and Temporall damnable Devotions, and infernall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, that do uphold the usurped Dignity of that Idoll <hi>Dagon</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; it is you that bring oile to quench the flames of this afflicted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50967:4"/>
Kingdome; it is you that have bewitched, besotted, and picked the purses of as many as believed you; it is you (and your instigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) that have raised and defended this unparallelld and unnaturall Rebellion; it is you that (by Innovations in the Church) have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most made the glorious Protestant Religion invisible, and (to cover your Villanies) with hypocriticall and odious Lyes, you charge the King and his Honourable Counsell with Popery, it is you that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the New Assembly in their Synodicall Consultations, in fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and forging a new <hi>Alcaron,</hi> or a <hi>Talmud</hi>; it is you that have made Knaves and Fooles believe all this; it is you that have ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, imprisoned, robbed or murdered as many as would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve all this, and my hope is to live to see you hanged for all this.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is no marvaile if they maintain you, for you are the onely props that uphold them, when you give over Lying then their Honour will lie in the dust, and when they fall you will be in danger of sterving; for as <hi>Phocas</hi> by the murder of his Master <hi>Mauritius</hi> (the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour) gat the Empire to himselfe, but was held in an odious estimation amongst all good men, so that his usurped ill-got estate stood tottering, and his life in dayly hazard (by the friends of the Assassinated Emperour) at the same time, the Bishop of <hi>Rome (Boniface</hi>) ambitiously sought to be Chiefe and Vniversall Bishop over all Christian Churches, which pride of his was opposed by all the godly and zealous Bishops in the World: but at last, the Murderer <hi>Phocas</hi> and the aspiring Pope made a bargain, which was that the Pope should by his dreadfull Thunderbolts of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation affright the People into obedience with the Emperour, so the Emperour (by force of Armes) would bestow the Primacy of the whole Earth on the Pope, this match was made, and the most significant application of it is, that by as good right as <hi>Phocas</hi> reigned, by the like right doth <hi>Bookers</hi> Parliament rule, and by the same right do those fore-mentioned Villaines and they maintain and defend each other, by Murder, Sacrililedge, Ambition, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, Rebellion, and ruine of this ancient, famous, late-flourishing, and now most wretched and miserable <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Maremaid</hi> Taverne (thou saist) is turned Ale-house (for want of wine) but if any of the Planets told thee so, tell them they lyed, for there is sufficient of Wine in that House to make all the true Subjects in your Army as drunke as Beasts.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:50967:4"/>
Thou taxest <hi>Naworth</hi> and me with being blinde, that we could not see but mistake, and take <hi>Jupiter</hi> for <hi>Mars,</hi> this mistake might be an escape or fault in Printing, and my Book was too small to have an <hi>Errata</hi> annexed to it. I answer, that <hi>Naworth</hi> did no more know of the writing or printing of my Book, than thou and thy Comrades do know how or when to be true Protestants or loyall Subjects; but all the world may perceive thee to be starke blinde in thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, that couldst not know the King from <hi>John Taylor,</hi> just as when a man casts a stone at a Dogge, the foolish Curre runnes and bites the stone and never mindes the Caster; why, thou ignorant blinde Buzzard, it was I, yea, it was I alone, without either any or the least assistance from <hi>Naworth, Aulicus,</hi> or any other that wrote the Book called [<hi>No Mercurius Aulicus</hi>] wherein I told you truly of your mistaking, villanous Prediction; I tell thee again, thou mis-believing Infidell, it was I that galled and spur-galled thee to the quicke, and thou (like a blinde Iade) couldst not see me alone that did it, but thou must fall a snapping and snarling at the King, the Queen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with others, who never had such a thought as to thinke upon so villanous a poysonous Vermin as thou art. Thou shouldst onely have medled with me that mumbled thee; but 'tis the old tricke of your Pulpiteers and Pamphleteers, to draw the more attention, and entice Coxcombs and Knaves to buy your dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable roguish riffe raffe, to mix and blend some slanderous Lyes, and Traiterous Ieeres against our Soveraigne, and his most gracious Government: for it is a Rule amongst you, that if there be no Treason in the Sermon, or Lying Calumniations in the printed Pamphlet, the one will never be liked and rewarded, nor the other be bought and sold.</p>
            <p>And now Sirtha, I will tell thee of an Anagram of my Name, that describes or emblems my couragious undaunted disposition, as <hi>John Taylor, O harty Lion.</hi> It may be <hi>Ioyn Halter</hi> may fall out to thee, and I may be the man that may joyne it, but be of good comfort if the Dog killer do not mistake thee for a dangerous Curre; then I am resolved to give order to the Hangman for thee. Thou sayest, <hi>Thou wilt be silent hereafter, and that to answer</hi> AULICUS, NAVVORTH, <hi>or my Selfe, were to relieve us.</hi> Sir, I know I have put thee to silence, I have ramm'd up thy bawling chaps, for any more medling with me, but thou medlest most mischievously with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50967:5"/>
the Planets, and makest most Traiterous Expositions of them; the Starres and twelve Signes will reward thy lying sophisticating Calculations, with their malevolent Influences. Also thou recitest (to a damnable purpose) the story of <hi>Saul, Agag,</hi> and the murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Protestants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> when all men of judgement do know that <hi>Ireland</hi> durst not rebell as long as the Earle of <hi>Strafford's</hi> head was upon his shoulders: but those that thirsted his blood, did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so thirst for the Rebellion there and here too, and all the murders and outrages in <hi>Ireland</hi> were occasioned by the <hi>Brownists</hi> and <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists,</hi> which Villaines urged the Papists so violently to infest that Kingdome. Should I answer every Bable, fable, or knavery in thy pestilent Pamphlet, all my truths and refutations would not lye in one poore sheet, to which this my rejoynder is limited, but for a conclusion I will send thee a Medicine, a requitall of the Cordiall thou sentst from <hi>London</hi> to me. I wish thee not to refuse it, for it will cure Diseases in any Rebell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Recipe</hi>
               <list>
                  <item> Of <hi>Sayes</hi> good workes two hand-fulls.</item>
                  <item>Legall Protestations anna one Scruple.</item>
                  <item>The Close Committees Loyalty anna one Scruple.</item>
                  <item>Rebells obedience anna one Scruple.</item>
                  <item>Anabaptisticall duty anna two Graines.</item>
                  <item>Brownisticall zeale anna two Graines.</item>
                  <item>Schismaticall holinesse anna two Graines.</item>
                  <item>Sacrilegious sanctity anna two Graines.</item>
                  <item>Hypocrites purity anna two Graines.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Whites</hi> conscience anna two Graines.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Burges</hi> his chastity anna two Graines.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Case</hi> and <hi>Sedwickes</hi> Divinity one Dramme.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Let all these be bound up together in a <hi>Holland</hi> clowt as bigge as the palme of your hand, and tie it fast with the Line of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, let it be watred with the teares of oppressed and distressed Protestants, who are either undone or imprisoned for being true Subjects, then take them and beat them well in the Morter of Common Calamity, with the Pestle of the Publique Faith; when it is well beaten, mix it with the Braines of <hi>Boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, May, Wither, Mercurius Britanicus, Prinne,</hi> and two or three hundred Knaves Braines more, it is an approved Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine for the encrease of Rebellion, for the grumbling in the gizzard, the flux of the Tongue, or the melancholly mubble-fubbles, provided it be taken fasting (upon a full stomacke) at five of the clocke in the morning after Dinner</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:50967:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
