<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The country-man's guide or plain directions for ordering. Curing. Breeding choice, use, and feeding. Of horses, cows, sheep, hoggs, &amp;c. Adorn'd with sculptuers, shewing the proper places in the bodies of the said several beasts, where the said distempers do usually happen. Published for the publick good, by W.W.</title>
            <author>Winstanley, William, 1628?-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-06">2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A71265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3057B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222313</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833496</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833496</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37973</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A71265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37973)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2203:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The country-man's guide or plain directions for ordering. Curing. Breeding choice, use, and feeding. Of horses, cows, sheep, hoggs, &amp;c. Adorn'd with sculptuers, shewing the proper places in the bodies of the said several beasts, where the said distempers do usually happen. Published for the publick good, by W.W.</title>
                  <author>Winstanley, William, 1628?-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], p. 1, 142, [6] p., [4] leaves of plates   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for S. Lee, stationer, over against the post-office in Lombard-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.W. = William Winstanley.</note>
                  <note>The words "ordering. ... Breeding" are gathered by a right brace on the title page; the words "choice, ... feeding." are gathered by a left brace.</note>
                  <note>With an index and errata at end of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Domestick animals --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Horses --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Swine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sheep --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Cows --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>Andrew Kuster</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>Andrew Kuster</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Country-Man's GUIDE: OR Plain Directions FOR
<list>
                  <item>Ordering,</item>
                  <item>Curing,</item>
                  <item>Breeding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </item>
                  <item>Choice,</item>
                  <item>Uſe, And Feeding,</item>
               </list>
Of Horſes, Cows, Sheep, Hoggs, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Adorn'd with Sculptures, ſhewing the proper places in the Bodies of the ſaid ſeveral, Beaſts, where the ſaid Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers do uſually happen.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the Publick Good, by <hi>W.W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for S. <hi>Lee,</hi> Stationer, over againſt the Poſt-Office in <hi>Lombard-street.</hi> 1679.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>HAving been importuned by divers of my Country-friends to publiſh the enſuing Rules and Directions, for the better ordering and curing of moſt ſorts of Cattle of their Diſtempers and Maladies, that ſo the whole Kingdom might receive a general Benefit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; I have at length taken upon me ſo to do, though not with a little Regret, as being very ſenſible how ill Entertainment this ſmall Manual may receive from the hands of ſome particular perſons, who (I doubt not) will not ſpare ſpending their cenſorious Judgments concerning it, to the depreſſion of it, as much as in them lyes. But in regard it is not likely any may do ſo, without being obliged thereto by their own private Intereſt and Advantage, and never any thing comprehending the whole of this having been before publiſhed at ſo ſmall a price.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:37973:4"/>I ſhall not therefore wholly wave this my good deſign to my Country, ſeeing there is no other reaſon for it, than that this little Book may be prejudicial to the Monopoly that ſome Horſe-Doctors have contracted to themſelves, but proceed as chearfully as I can therein, for the best advantage to my Country-men. The Book conſiſts of divers Choice Obſervations and Experiences of divers skilful <hi>Engliſh</hi> men. The whole is made very eaſie to the apprehenſion of the Reader by the Table preceding the Book, wherein every Diſeaſe is figured, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers the Figures in the Cuts placed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Table. And is further illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and found out by the Alphabetical Table at the end of this Book. That this ſmall Endeavour therefore may anſwer the Deſign it was intended for, is the only Deſire of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>The Readers Hearty Well-wiſher</hi> W.W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Country mans directory ſhewing the ſeverall places in the body of a Horſe where the ſeaverall diſeaſes vſuall happ<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_diseases">
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:5"/>
            <head>A Table of ſeveral Diſeaſes incident to Horſes; with a Relation to the Printed Cut or Portraiture of a Horſe in the Firſt Page of this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 THE Head-Ach, Staggers, or Madneſs.</item>
               <item>2 Mad, or Raging Love</item>
               <item>3 Coldneſs, or Chilneſs in the Head.</item>
               <item>4 Rhume, Catarh, Glanders, or Running of the Noſe.</item>
               <item>5 Pin in the Eye.</item>
               <item>6 Web in the Eye.</item>
               <item>7 Watring of the Eyes.</item>
               <item>8 Pain in the Eye.</item>
               <item>9 Sore or Wounded Eyes.</item>
               <item>10 Eye-Scars.</item>
               <item>11 Worms in the Noſe.</item>
               <item>12 Tooth-Ach.</item>
               <item>13 Canker in the Mouth or Tongue</item>
               <item>14 Want of Palat.</item>
               <item>15 Fever or Plague.</item>
               <item>16 Squinacy, or Swelling in the Throat.</item>
               <item>17 Waxing-Kernel, Struma, Choaking, or the Strangles.</item>
               <item>18 Diſtemper of the Neck.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37973:6"/>19 Galled Neck.</item>
               <item>20 Crick in the Neck.</item>
               <item>21 Diſtempers of the Lungs.</item>
               <item>22 Short-windedneſs, or Purſiveneſs.</item>
               <item>23 Cough.</item>
               <item>24 Ulcers, or Apoſthumes of the Breaſt.</item>
               <item>25 Faintneſs.</item>
               <item>26 Over-heated.</item>
               <item>27 Ague.</item>
               <item>28 Venemous Creatures ſwallowed.</item>
               <item>29 Stomach or Appetite loſt.</item>
               <item>30 Henn-dung ſwallowed.</item>
               <item>31 Cholick, or Griping in the Gutts.</item>
               <item>32 Belly-Ach.</item>
               <item>33 Obſtruction in the Arſe-Gutt.</item>
               <item>34 Falling of the Fundament.</item>
               <item>35 Worms.</item>
               <item>36 Flux, or Looſeneſs of the Belly.</item>
               <item>37 Bloody-Flux.</item>
               <item>38 The Yellow-Jaundiſe.</item>
               <item>39 Stopping of Urine.</item>
               <item>40 Difficulty in making Water.</item>
               <item>41 Strangury.</item>
               <item>42 Wolf, or over-growing of the Fleſh.</item>
               <item>43 Rupture prevented.</item>
               <item>44 Rupture cured.</item>
               <item>45 Biting of the Spider-Mouſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </item>
               <item>46 Swelling of the Codds.</item>
               <item>47 Warts.</item>
               <item>48 Chaps in the Feet.</item>
               <item>49 Old Wounds, or Swelling in the Back.</item>
               <item>50 Bruiſed-Back.</item>
               <item>51 Galled-Back.</item>
               <item>52 Biting of Flyes.</item>
               <item>53 To drive away the Flyes.</item>
               <item>54 Stiffneſs in the Joynts.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37973:6"/>55 Broken-Loyns.</item>
               <item>56 Swelling of the Flanks.</item>
               <item>57 Scabby or Mangy.</item>
               <item>58 Wrecking of the Sinews.</item>
               <item>59 Swelling of the Knees.</item>
               <item>60 Knees cleft and broken.</item>
               <item>61 Over-growing of the Knee-pan.</item>
               <item>62 Farcions, Farcy or Leproſy of the Legs or elſewhere.</item>
               <item>63 Chops between the Joynts and Legs.</item>
               <item>64 String-hall.</item>
               <item>65 Mallender.</item>
               <item>66 Spavin.</item>
               <item>67 Biting of a Mad-Dog.</item>
               <item>68 Biting of Water-Snakes.</item>
               <item>69 Ring-bone.</item>
               <item>70 Fiſtula.</item>
               <item>71 Over-growing of the Hoof.</item>
               <item>72 Figg.</item>
               <item>73 Foundred.</item>
               <item>74 Prickt with a Nail.</item>
               <item>75 Limping oe Halting.</item>
               <item>76 The Shee-Wolf, or Boyls and Knobs on the Foot.</item>
               <item>77 Scratches.</item>
               <item>78 Over-reaching.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37973:7"/>
            <head>INTRODUCTION: OR, General Inſtructions FOR THE Breeding, Ordering, or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aging of Horſes, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>I Shall begin with the Horſe in the firſt place, as being a Creature uſeful for Peaſants, ſerviceable for Princes, Noblemen, Prelates; and in general, to all ſtates and conditions of men: In a word, as being ſuch a Beaſt, as hath not its like, conſidering its Beauty, Courage, Uſe, Convenience and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37973:7"/>The patient Carter that loves his Beaſts, ſeldom or never ſtrikes them; but uſes them ſo to the ſound of his Whip, that they are ruled by his Voice and Call; Nor doth he force them to draw or labour beyond their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. In the morning he currieth them cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;<note rend="inter">General order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Horſes.</note>
and, in the Summer, ſometimes in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon. He watereth them not, but in due time, after they have reſted. In the Summer, he often waſhes their feet with cold water, and ſometimes with wine, or the Lees of wine, to ſtrengthen them; and alſo with Piſs, when they are weary and tired with labour; and at night, carefully ſtops their feet with dung: And in caſe they be over-heat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<note rend="inter">Over-heated</note>
or have no ſtomach to eat, then he waſhes their mouth with Vinegar and Salt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and gives them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hay nor Fodder, Oats nor Straw, but what is pure and clean: Nor doth he permit them to be unſhod or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nailed. He taketh care alſo that the Harneſs, Saddles, Collers, Bridles, or any other neceſſary implement be not bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37973:8"/>
torn or ſpoiled. He ought alſo to be skilful in ſewing with wax-thread, and to ſtuff the Pannels and Saddles with Flocks.<note rend="inter">The Carter ought to be skilled in mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saddles, &amp;c.</note>
In ſhort, he ought to underſtand the Art of the Harneſs-maker, Sadler, and of the Farrier; and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto he muſt alwaies have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him his Knapſack or Budget (and the Waggoner ought to have ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient place or Box in his Cart or Waggon, wherein he may put his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and Iron-work, to make the Horſes neceſſaries for their ſhooing.</p>
            <p>He muſt alſo carefully obſerve what is wanting, or what is out of order; as, if any any of his Horſes limpeth, he muſt obſerve which foot is affected, and where the pain lyes; and ſometimes he ſtops the foot pained, with dung. He muſt alſo well obſerve when the Beaſts get new Hoofs, and in the <hi>Lent</hi> let the horn grow out. And if they have a hot mouth, inſomuch that they cough, then he muſt cover them. And if they have got the Rheum, or Catharrine la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring (occaſioned by Rain and bad weather) then he cauſes them to eat
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37973:8"/>
Fenigreek, or Anniſe mixt with their food: And when they begin to grow old, and to change apparently, he will conſider the love which the Horſes bear one to another, and accordingly he will place them in the ſtable, which every morning in the Summer ought to be made clean;<note rend="inter">The Stable to be kept clean.</note>
ſo that no Dung remain therein, and every evening freſh Straw put in. He muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo take care, if his Horſes grow thin, or lean, to make them fat again, with Beans boiled in Water, and Oats mingled with them, or Beans boyled with Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, Panick, and mixed with Bean-flower, or Meal, and a little Salt. He ought alſo to ſleep in the ſtable, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to prevent the danger of their ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, breaking looſe, biting or kicking one another. He muſt be very careful of putting his Light in the Stable, that no ill accident of Fire or damage may happen thereby. He ought alſo to be careful in keeping and putting all his Materials in a readineſs till the next morning, that when he goes to Plough, and puts out his Horſes, nothing may be wanting. If he hath any Mares, he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37973:9"/>
muſt place them by themſelves, or put them in another Plough or Cart. In caſe any of his Horſes fall ſick, or be any waies hurt or wounded, then he muſt ſeparate him from the other Horſes, and let him ſtand by himſelf.</p>
            <p>In caſe a Horſe hath any Diſeaſe, the beſt diligence ought to be uſed, and that with ſpeed, according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of the Diſtemper; and if he will not endure to be rid,<note rend="inter">How to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age a Horſe.</note>
or will not paſs in or through any way or paſſage, then you muſt hang a little ſtone in his Ear; but if that will not help, then blind fold him, or put fire under his Tail, or ſomething that may prick him: and if he will not endure that, then you muſt hang on his head a ſtone with a hole in it, when you have mounted him; and when he begins to ſtand up an end, ſtrike him with a little Rod or Whip upon the fore-leggs; and in caſe he lyes down<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then hinder him with blows and threatnings: and if he be head-ſtrong,<note rend="inter">Head-ſtrong.</note>
make a ſmall piece of Line faſt to his Stones, which muſt be ſo long as to come between the fore-leggs,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37973:9"/>
in the hand of the Rider, to be held by him, to pull and jerk, when the Horſe is not willing to go forwards; for by theſe means he may be broke off his head-ſtrong tricks, and be made conſtantly to keep his way. If it be a Gelding,<note rend="inter">Gelding.</note>
then ſtrike him upon the Buttocks with a long ſtick, which is drawn out of the fire, and burnt on the end: or ſtrike him with a rod or Swtich between the Ears. In caſe the Horſe be difficult to ſhooe, and hard and troubleſome to keep in the ſtable, then put in one, or in both his Ears a round Stone, and ſhut the Ears with both hands, and by this means he will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as tame as a Lamb. It is alſo the duty of the Carter too, carefully to rule his Stone-horſes and Mares, that no miſchance may befal them. And, though it is frequent to drive Horſes at ſome particular times into green Meadows, and pure Marſh-ground, yet the Marſh-ground makes their hoofs and ſight to grow tender, and cauſes them to get water in their feet. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhould think it would be better to let them feed upon the Mountains,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37973:10"/>
which are continually moiſt, and not alwaies dry; and ſuch as are not woody places, and are clear from ſtumps of Trees.<note rend="inter">Difference in the manner of breeding Mares and Stone-hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</note>
Upon which ground there grows rather fine and ſweet, than long, courſe, and hard graſs. But, although the Mare be not ſo ſtout and merry as the Stone-horſe, nevertheleſs, ſhe doth exceed him in running, and holds it longer, and is not ſo chargeable to keep as the Stone-horſe. For ſhe doth not eat any good Hay, being for the moſt part contented with the Meadows, that are good enough for her all the year long. 'Tis true, that in the Winter, when the Snow lyes upon the ground, and when much Rain falls, you are obliged to put her into the Stable; and give her good Hay; and you muſt obſerve in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer-time, to keep her well provided with good Graſs, and clear Waters, but never upon Mountains, which are too rough and ſharp for her; Firſt, Becauſe ſhe hath but bad feeding there. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Becauſe thoſe that are big with Foal, ought not to climb up the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37973:10"/>
by reaſon they cannot go up without great labour, nor come down again without danger of aborting or miſchieving themſelves.</p>
            <p>You ought not to permit the Mare to be covered by the Stone-horſe, but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſecond year, if you would keep a good generation; and this not at any other time but about the middle of <hi>March,</hi> that the Mare may in the ſame ſeaſon of the year in which ſhe was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, feed her Colt with fine and young Graſs after <hi>May.</hi> For at the end of eleven or twelve months the Colt is brought forth. Beſides, then their Milk encreaſes the faſter, which occaſions the bringing of the better Colts, and ſuch as prove according to your deſire. When the Stone-horſe ſtays ſo long before he covers the Mare, he is much ſtronger, and full of mature, and not thin running ſeed. Beſides, he then covers the Mare with greater deſire, and ſo engenders greater, ſtouter, and ſtronger Colts.</p>
            <div type="subsection">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:37973:11"/>
               <head>To know when a Mare deſires to be covered.</head>
               <p>You muſt know, that the Mare is hot, and deſires to be covered when ſhe hath not any whitiſh ſlime upon her nature, and when her nature is more ſwollen, than it uſes to be, and then ſhe is more hot than ordinary, and eats not ſo much as before. And then you may ſet the Stone-Horſe by her twice a day, to wit, in the evening, and in the morning before you water her; and this no longer then 10 days, which being paſt, in caſe ſhe deſires the Stone-Horſe no more, as being full, then ſet her alone, and lead the Stone-Horſe away, that he may not hinder her from conceiving her by his hot and fiery humours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Age of a Stone-horſe that covers a Mare, and of a Mare when ſhe ought to be covered.</head>
               <p>The Stone-Horſe which is to cover the Mare, ought to be above three
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37973:11"/>
years old, and is fit for it till his twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth year. Though, the Mare may be covered when ſhe is two years old, and ſhe may in her third year bring up her Colt, and feed it well. But after ſhe is ten years old, ſhe is not ſo ſerviceable in that kind; for, ſuch Horſes as are broughr ſorth by a cold Mare, are not couragious, but dull and heavy. The Stone-horſe ought to be well fed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the time that he is to cover the Mare, againſt which time you muſt make him fat with barley, Fitches and peaſe, that he may the better ſatisfie the Mare. For the more merry and ſtronger he is in covering the Mare, the ſtronger Colts he will engender. If he is not ſtout nor merry, then rub the nature of the Mare with a new and clean ſponge, and rub the Mouth of the Stone-horſe therewith. In caſe the Mare will not ſuffer the Stone-horſe, then bruiſe a Sea-Onion, and rub her nature therewith, and that will heat her.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Colts of ſuch Colour as you fancy.</head>
               <p>If you will have the Colt of ſuch Colour as you fancy, place before the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37973:12"/>
eye of the Mare, or throw over the Mare a Coverture of ſuch colour as you deſire, when ſhe is covered by the Horſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>The Quality of a Mare to be covered.</head>
               <p>The Mare, which you deſire may have a good generation of Colts, muſt not be under two years old nor above ten or twelve years, conſidering that being of a colder temper than the Horſe, ſhe is alſo weaker; ſhe ought alſo to be handſome of body and pleaſant to behold. The rump and the back broad, well fed, and ſuch an one as hath not laboured long.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Mares that are full, not to be put to labour.</head>
               <p>when ſhe is Big ſhe muſt be fed, and not put to labour, nor be left in the cold, but in the Stable while it rains, to the end, ſhe may go her full time without danger.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37973:12"/>
               <head>How to order a Mare that hath Caſt.</head>
               <p>In caſe the Mare caſts her Colt before the time, then you muſt pound Oak-fern, and give it her to drink (mingled with lukewarm water) through a horn; but if ſhe hath caſt well, you may touch the Colt with your hand gently, but a ſmall preſſure or blow will hurt &amp; bruiſe it. As ſoon as ſhe hath foaled in the Stable, you muſt comfort her with a potion of lukewarm water mixt with Salt and Flower, giving it to her in the evening and morning (at leaſt) for the ſpace of three daies. Next, you muſt give her good Hay and Grain ſufficient and keep her clean with ſtrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that ſhe may afterwards reſt at Leiſure. For this Entertainment affords Fleſh to the Colts and makes them ſtrong.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37973:13"/>
               <head>Marks of a good Colt.</head>
               <p>A good Colt, Horſe, or Stone-horſe, is known by big bones, a good ſhape, a little head, and ſo dry or lean, that he hath ſcarce any thing but skin and bones; that hath little ſharp and ſtreight Ears; great, ſwelling, black, and clean Eyes; very large Noſtrils; thin and lean cheeks; the mouth ſplit alike on both ſides; the Neck ſomewhat long and arch-like; thin about the head, a ſhort, broad back; the Main curled, thick and long, hanging down on the right ſide, a broad Breaſt, ſtanding out before, and full of Muſcles, great Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, round in the Sides, double Back, cloſe tite Belly; the Stones eaven and ſmall, broad and ſunk, or depreſſed members, a long Tail, with thick and curled Hair; bigg-boned leggs, which are alſo dry, lean, and not loaden with fleſh, but long and ſtreight; round and little knees, not turn'd inwards; rough and round buttocks, big and long thighs, full of brawns and muſcles, black hoof, hollow, round, and ſomewhat rais'd towards the knuckles, and of a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37973:13"/>
ſmall Crown. In a word, ſuch an one as is joyful, quick, pleaſant, and neither vicious nor ſick, (for ſuch are obedient and proper for labour) ſuch as is not ſtubborn, affrighted, greedy, nor lazy in eating, that does not dung much, nor lye down in the water. Moreover, that your Horſe be of a Bay-colour, dark-red, dapple-gray, or pale-colour, (which is the beſt token of a ſtrong or ſtout Horſe.) And finally, to ſpeak of the virtue and handſomeneſs of a Horſe, he ought to have the Eyes, Ligaments and Limbs of an Oxe, the ſtrength and feet of a Mule<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the hoofs and thighs of an Aſs, the throat and neck of a Wolf, the ears and tail of a Fox, the breaſt and main of a woman, the courage of a Lion, the ſight and agility of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, the pace of a Cat, the ſwiftneſs of a Hare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>p or tread high, the trotting from the gallop eaſie and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant; light <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> running, quick and nimble in leaping, and docible at the hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:37973:14"/>
               <head>The Age of a Horſe.</head>
               <p>The Country-man ought alſo to have skill in knowing the Age of the Horſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he may let him work according to his ſtrength: The Age of the Horſe is diſcerned by his feet and hoofs, but moſt eſpecially by his Teeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>The Teeth of the Horſe.</head>
               <p>The Horſe hath commonly eight and twenty Teeth, although <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeaks of thirty: he begins to get Teeth the firſt three months, and at the end of the year he has above and below on each ſide ſix Teeth. After thirty months two alter above, and two below; and within three years and an half he gets on each ſide four Teeth more. When he is four years old the Dogg teeth fall out, and in their places come other Teeth. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſixth year, the great Cheek-teeth or Eye-teeth fall out; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſixth year others grow in their room. The ſame ſixth year he hath all his Teeth, which are altogether made hollow; but after that time you cannot
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37973:14"/>
eaſily diſcern how old the Horſe is: In or about the Twelfth year you may perceive a ſtrange vnuſuall blackneſs in the teeth, and obſerve, that the older an Horſe is, the longer his teeth grow, except ſometimes when by overhard ſcrawnching or biting they ſhorten more and more. In the tenth year the Temples of the head, begin to ſink and grow hollow; ſometimes rhe Eye-brows alſo grow gray, and then the Horſe ſhews in his fore-head a ſad and ſorrowfull Countenance, hangs down his head, is heavy; has pale Eyes, and gray haire in many other places; and this happens ordinarily to thoſe of a Bay Colour, and Cheſnut Brown, and ſuch as come neereſt to black. The ſpeckled becomes white, the white turnes to dapple-gray, and ſometimes a browniſh colour. He has alſo many wrincles on the upper Lipp, according to the number of which vſually the years of the Horſes age are counted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>The Curing of Diſeaſes in Horſes.</head>
               <p>Further, it concerns the Country man to be carefull of the Health of his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37973:15"/>
Horſes, which may live at leaſt till Twenty years of age and do good ſervice all the while. If he findes them in good health, though lean, he is to give them kiln dried Wheat, or twice as much bruiſed or pounded Barley. He ought to rub them well over every day, in regard it does them much more good to be often rubbed and handled then to eat much.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Lean-Horſe.</head>
               <p>Beſides, a lean Horſe may be made fat with little Kidney-Beans boiled, mingled with Oats; But if the Horſe be ſo weak that he cannot ſwallow it down, then you muſt ſtrengthen and comfort him with a good deal of the yolk of Eggs, and ſugar, which he muſt ſwallow downe. Beſides which, Luke-warm water mingled with ſalt and Flower of Barley being given to the Horſe in the morning and at night, is an excellent thing to make him very fatt. Likewiſe it is very good to give the Horſe fower times a day a little Panick or Rice, mingled with Bean-Flower and ſalt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he may not vomit up again which he takes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="section">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:37973:15"/>
            <head>THE Country-Man's GUIDE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Head-ach, Staggers, and Madneſs</head>
               <p>THE great Head-ach, and Madneſs of a Horſe, is cured by continual rubing of Ladies-mark &amp; Semel (a kind of Bread ſo called) Lettuce-blades cut ſmall, and freſh Straw ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with it. You muſt alſo let him bleed out of the vein of the brains, or the temples, or of both, and put him in a dark and low Stable. The ſigns of his having a pain in the head, you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve by the water which drops from him, by the ſlack hanging of his Ears;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37973:16"/>
and that his neck and head is heavy, and hanging downwards.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="subsection">
               <head>II. Mad, or Raging Love.</head>
               <p>It falls out ſometimes, that the Mares are vexed with a kind of Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>viz.</hi> when they ſee their ſhape in beholding themſelves in the water and grow ſo amorous thereof, that they forget to eat and to drink, and dry up with inward heat. The marks of this Madneſs, are, that they run along the Roads, as if they were pricked with Spurs, often looking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, as if they did deſire and ſeek ſomething. They recover of this Sickneſs, being led again to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; for when they behold therein, how ill-favoured they be, they forget the firſt ſhape which they did behold in the water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Coldneſs, or Chilneſs in the Head.</head>
               <p>A Horſe which has got a Cold, or Chilneſs, is cured by drinking the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37973:16"/>
warm blood of a Pigg, boyl'd with Wine or Maſtick, and Wine-root boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Honey, or common Oil, with Pepper. He gets this Diſtemper when he is put in a cold place, being hot and ſweating; inſomuch that the ſinews ſhrink, and the skin groweth hard; therefore you are to place ſuch a Horſe in a very hot place, well cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a warm coverture, which reacheth to the ground; and you are to lay under his belly ſeven or eight great hot ſtones, and to quench them oftentimes with warm water; and this heat will cauſe him to ſweat, and cure the Diſtemper or Glanders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Rheume, Catharre, Glanders, or Running of the Noſe.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Rheume or Catharre, &amp;c. take Operment and Brimſtone beaten together, throw them upon burning coals, and let the ſmoak enter into the noſtrils of the horſe, to the end that the ſtiff humours which are in the brains, may diſſolve and diſtill down.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="subsection">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37973:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Pin in the Eye.</head>
               <p>The Pin in the Eye you muſt lift up with an Ivory-Needle, and then cut it clear off with a pair of ſmall Ciſſars: or take Powder of a green Agedeſte, or Rats-bane, and lay it upon the Eye, that it may eat the Nail.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Webb in the Eye.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Webb in the Eye, or Running Eyes, the beſt Remedy is an Eye-water made of the Juice of Bittony, pounded in a wooden Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, or the Juice of Houſleek, or the blade of the herb Celendine, pound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Mortar, and laid thereupon with cold Water, or rather with Wine, after you have let the horſe blood in the vein of the Eye affected. Theſe means you muſt continue to uſe many daies in the morning, and at night. You may alſo blow into the Eye, through a Quill, the powder of the grate of the Fiſh called Sepia, or whole ſeed of the herb Rocket; or lay thereupon the Ear of a little Lamb,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37973:17"/>
until it hath by its vertue taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the fleſh, and cleanſed it; or the powder of the yolk of an Egg, and Salt burnt together, and put into the Eye: or the powder of Sal-Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack, Myrrh, Saffron, and ſcraping of the grates of Sepia.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Watring of the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Watering Eyes are cured by a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine made of Frankincenſe, Myrrh, Starch, and White-honey: or with a head lace made of Frankincenſe and Maſtick, bruiſed ſmall, and rubb'd with the white of an Egg, and laid upon the forehead; which being left thereupon a conſiderable time, the Eyes will weep no more. Then you muſt take off the band or head-lace, with warm Water and Oil beaten to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Pain in the Eye.</head>
               <p>All pains of the Eys are healed, if you chafe or anoint them with the Juice of Lambs-tongue and Honey mixt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="subsection">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37973:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Sore or Wounded Eyes.</head>
               <p>Sore or Wounded Eyes are healed, by laying upon them a Poulteſs of the crum of Bread, moiſtened in freſh Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or roaſted, or of boyled Bread ſoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in White-wine. But in caſe this will not help, then you muſt open the head or chief vein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Eye-Scarrs, or Wounds.</head>
               <p>The Scarrs or Wounds of the Eyes are healed with Faſting-ſpittle and Salt, if often anointed therewith: or by bruiſed grates of Sepia, and melted Salt: or by bruiſed ſeed of wild Parſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nips, being ſpread over the Eyes in a Linnen Cloth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> Flying Worm.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Flying-Worm, or Worms in the Noſe; you are to open the vein in the temples of the head; make a deep hole under the throat with an hot Iron; put a Tent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and lay Flax therupon, which is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37973:18"/>
made wet in the white of Eggs, and let him thus ſtand reſting in the Stable for three daies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XII.</hi> Tooth-Ach</head>
               <p>The Colt hath many times pains in his Teeth and Gums, when he begins firſt to get Teeth, and then you muſt ſoak in ſtrong Vinegar, the beſt Chalk that you can get, and rub the cheeks therewith outwardly; and eſpecially in that place where he feels the pain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> Canker; or little Bubbles or Swellings of the Tongue.</head>
               <p>The Canker in the Mouth, or under the Tongue, which hinders the horſe from eating, becauſe the Tongue is ſwollen, may be cured by cauſing him to eat Peaſe and Beans, or the husks or ſhells of the ſame; for by the eating of them the Botch or Swelling goes away. But in caſe this Diſtemper com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth again, then it muſt be drawn out of the hollowneſs of the Palat, and then be cut off dextrouſly with a pair of Ciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars near to the Palat.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="subsection">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:37973:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> Falling, or want of the Palat.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Falling of the Palat of the Mouth; take the fleſh away with a thin little Iron ſo far, that the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours may run out by degrees: next rub and cleanſe the Palat with Syrop of Roſes mixt with the Juice of Lemon, and toaſted Cheeſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XV.</hi> Fever.</head>
               <p>The horſe gets a Fever generally when he is ſuddenly watered after he hath wrought very hard, which is almoſt like to the ſwelling in the Neck, or the King's-Evil: for the ſame hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens as well to Beaſts as to Men, by the great coldneſs of the Water, when the Throat is enflamed or heated, whereby the horſe loſes his Stomach and Reſt, and his Ears become cold. Then you may immediately find remedy againſt this in this manner: Lay the Ear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Neck and the Chine of the horſe, and cut open the hardneſs, which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37973:19"/>
is like a white Sinew, the length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies with a Lancet; take this white fleſh off, and put therein a Linnen cloth, which is made wet in the White of Eggs, and cover the horſe imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately with a horſe-cloth, leading him backward and forward, till his Ears grow warm again; and give him a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of Water, Salt and Flower: After he hath eaten ſome good Hay, let him reſt three daies, to foment the place, with things belonging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, for to ſtir the humours; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards lay thereupon a Poulteſs of theſe things following.</p>
               <p>Bird lime three ounces, Barley-flower a convenient quantity; being boiled together ſo long in Red Wine, to the groſneſs or conſiſtency of a Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs: And when the matter or filth is gathered together, and is ready to break out, then you muſt prick it; and when the matter is run out, put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hollowneſs the lint or ſcrapings of Linnen, made wet in Water, Oil and Salt. This Sickneſs muſt be cured immediately; for if it continue long, then there is not any hope of recovery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="subsection">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:37973:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> Squinacy, Or Swelling in the Throat.</head>
               <p>The Swelling in the Throat, or Squi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, otherwiſe pain in the Throat, and ſwelling of the Tongue, requires firſt, letting of blood on the vein un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Tongue, or of the Palat; and next, a fomenting of the whole Mouth and Tongue, with warm Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; next, an anointment of the Gall of a Bull, or of Salt, and Wine-Stone, pounded in Wine-Vinegar. The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you muſt make in manner fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. Take
<list>
                     <item>Anniſeeds, one ounce.</item>
                     <item>Old Oil, two pound.</item>
                     <item>Red-Wine, half a pint.</item>
                     <item>Fat Figgs, of each nine.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Let it be all together ſoaked well, and make a Decoction thereof, into which you muſt put rubbed Saltpetre, and Salt a convenient quantity; ſtrain it, and make it a potion.</p>
               <p>Which you are to pour into the Throat of the horſe twice a day, to wit, in the morning, and at night a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37973:20"/>
a pint. Next, you muſt give him to eat, green Barley, or Barley-flower, with which you muſt mingle Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petre; if you let the horſe bleed, it muſt be done in the Palat of the mouth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVII.</hi> Waxen Kernels, Struma, Choaking or Strangling.</head>
               <p>The Waxen Kernel, Struma, or Choak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is engendred under the throat of the horſe, and falls down from a cold brain, you are to prick him under the throat; next to cover his head with a linnen cloth, and to rub often with ſweet-butter the whole throat, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the place where the ſwellings lye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVIII.</hi> Diſtemper of the Neck.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Diſtemper of the Neck, pierce the fleſh in five places on both ſides of the throat with an hot Iron, as ſharp as an Awl; put into each hole an Hoggs-briſtle, and let the ſame ſtick therein for a whole fortnight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="subsection">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:37973:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XIX.</hi> Galled Neck.</head>
               <p>When the Neck or the Back is galled, by the preſſing of the Saddle, then you ought to lay upon the wound the leaves of black <hi>(Brionia.)</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XX.</hi> Crick in the Neck.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Crick in the Neck, waſh the place with luke-warm Wine, next lay ſome Tow of Flax dipt in the White of an Egg.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXI.</hi> Diſtemper of the Lungs.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Diſtemper of the Lungs, take a Snake, cut off the head and taile, the reſt cut into ſmall pieces, and roaſt it on a ſpit; gather together the fat or greaſe, that drops from the ſame, and uſe it againſt the Diſtemper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="subsection">
               <pb facs="tcp:37973:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXII.</hi> Purſineſs, or Short windneſs.</head>
               <p>The Purſie, or Short-winded horſe, ro wit, which cannot well take his breath; and though he is ſpurred and ſtruck, he will not go on, but coughs very much, drawing his breath pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully: Nay, in eating alſo he doth not ceaſe from coughing. This Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper is very hard to be cured. It is true, as long as the Diſtemper is new, and occaſioned by duſt of a duſt-raiſing wind, or by eating any uncleanneſs in his forrage, there is ſome remedy againſt this Diſtemper, to wit, the letting of Blood on the Shoulders, and by chafing or anointing the horſe on the breaſt, and the back with the warm blood of the Beaſt, mingled with Wine and Oil of Elephant; when you have continued that five daies together, then the five following daies, you muſt let him fetch through the Noſtrils, Lye mingled with Oil: Next, give him to drink this potion, which is made out of the following kinds.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:37973:22"/>Take Roaſt Muſtard-ſeed.</item>
                  <item>Living Brimſtone.</item>
                  <item>Paradiſe-corn; of each a like convenient quantity, being pounded ſmall, and boiled together in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theglin to a Decoction.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Or make a thick Compoſition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and of that you muſt cauſe him eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day to take as much as the bigneſs of a Walnut, with thick Red-wine, which is very good and excellent; or make a potion of the following things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Galingal.</item>
                  <item>Ginger.</item>
                  <item>Clove, or July-flowers.</item>
                  <item>Cummin.</item>
                  <item>Fennil.</item>
                  <item>Eggs.</item>
                  <item>Saffron, a little mingled with Wine; of all take a convenient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity for a potion.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And pour it into the mouth of the horſe, holding his head up high, that he may ſwallow it down the more eaſily, without permitting him to let
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37973:22"/>
his head fall down, at leaſt for the ſpace of a good half hour, to the end, that the potion may run through all his guts; Next give him green graſs; or reed, or willow leaves to eat to qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify the heat of the potion, but the horſe muſt in the mean time eat nothing half a day before, or afterwards. Next, lead the horſe gently backwards and forwards with the halter: or mount upon him, and ride him gently, to the end, that he may not vomit up the potion. This is a means to heal a horſe that is purſy and ſhort-winded, if the diſtemper is not too old; but if it be an old evil, then you may help it with brand-marks, and by cutting up the noſtrills, for the heat of the fire, will hinder this ſhortneſs of breath, and cauſe the breath the better to enter in and to iſſue through the noſtrills; give him alſo often times grapes to eat, and ſweet wine to drink. Moreover, there is another excellent remedy, (to wit) a potion made of <hi>Agaricus</hi> and <hi>Fenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greek</hi> ſoaked in red wine: or the blood of a little dog, which is not above ten dayes old, the ſame being given the horſe to drink: or the root of wild
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37973:23"/>
Cucumbers, and Gall Nuts, pounded with Honey-water, and making a potion thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="subsection">
               <head>XXIII. <hi>Cough.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Cough is occaſioned by many reaſons; ſometimes it proceeds from the lungs, and other parts of the body therabouts; and ſometimes out of other inward, and moſt low members, which have the operations; there is not any thing better againſt this diſtemper, then the ſnipping or cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the noſtrills of the beaſt. And in caſe, that he doeth not mend, then you ought to pour into his throat a good draught of this following potion.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Fenigreek and</item>
                  <item>Flax-ſeed, of each a meaſure,</item>
                  <item>Gum-Dragon,</item>
                  <item>Frankincenſe,</item>
                  <item>Myrrha,</item>
                  <item>Sugar.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:37973:23"/>The Bran of ſmall Peaſe, or Fitches, of each an ounce, being all together bruiſed ſmall and ſifted.</p>
               <p>Lay it a ſoaking a whole night in warm water.</p>
               <p>And the next day you muſt give the horſe to drink thereof, according as has been ſaid; this you muſt continue, adding thereunto Oil of Roſes, until he is well recovered; ſome lay five whole Eggs a mollifying for a whole night in ſtrong Vineger, and the next morning, when they obſerve that the ſhell is become ſoft, they cauſe the horſe to ſwallow it down. Farther, you ought never to bleed the beaſt in any place whatſoever; but you muſt at the ſame time continue to give him Gum Dragon with ſweet Oil.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIV.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers, or Apoſthumes of the Breaſt.</head>
               <p>The Ulcers or Apoſthumes of the breaſt cauſe horſes to die immediately; therefore as ſoon as the waxing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37973:24"/>
Kernell of the breaſt ſwells up, you muſt draw out the ſwelling without ceaſing: but in caſe a vein breaketh thereby, then you are to tie both ends together with a Silk thred, for the greater the ſwelling grows the more matter or filth it will gather together, and haſten his death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXV.</hi> Faintneſs.</head>
               <p>Againſt the faintneſs and pain of the heart, it is good to keep the horſe very warm and to give him this potion.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Herb Mercury a pound.</item>
                  <item>Gum-Dragon 4 ounces.</item>
                  <item>Myrrh 2 ounces.</item>
                  <item>Bruiſed Melilot 1 ounce.</item>
                  <item>Saffron half an ounce.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Fine Frankincenſe a convenient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, all together pounded and mixt to a powder.</p>
               <p>Which you are to keep for uſe, and at each time take Oil of Roſes, two Cruiſes; Water, half a pint; of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37973:24"/>
aforeſaid powder two good ſpoonfulls; Honey, two ſpoonfulls for a potion.</p>
               <p>This potion muſt be uſed for ſome dayes, untill the horſe beginneth to mend.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVI.</hi> Over heated.</head>
               <p>You muſt give to the horſe, that is heated, in the winter, (through an horn) the following potion.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Red-wine, half a pint.</item>
                  <item>Oil, three ounces.</item>
                  <item>But in the Summer,</item>
                  <item>Take Red wine, half a pint.</item>
                  <item>Oil, two ounces, for a potion.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVII.</hi> The Ague.</head>
               <p>You may know (amongſt other tokens) that a horſe hath the ague, when he can not make water, his Ears Cold hanging and ſtinking:</p>
               <p>The Ague of an horſe is cured by letting him bleed on the vein, which is found in the calf or thick part of the leg, 4 fingers or thereabouts under the buttocks, or elſe you may let him blood
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37973:25"/>
on the vein of the neck, and if you obſerve, that a potion is neceſſary, then you muſt ſqueeze juice out of an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Purſlain, and mix it with Gum-Dragon, fine Frankincenſe, and ſome few Damask-roſes, which give him to drink with a little Metheglin, or Honey-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVIII.</hi> Venemous Creatures ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed down.</head>
               <p>In caſe the horſe in eating Hay or graſs, hath ſwallowed down any vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous beaſt, as a Spider, a certain kind of Lizard, Earth Spider, Snale, or Dirt-Grubber, (Bupreſtis) then you muſt make him run, until he ſweats, next you muſt bleed him on the Palat, and let him ſwallow down the blood; You muſt give him to eat boiled Beans.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIX.</hi> Loſt Appetite or Stomach.</head>
               <p>If he hath loſt his Stomach, waſh his mouth with Vinegar and Salt, and give him no Forrage, nor Oats, Hay, Chaff, or Straw, but what is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="subsection">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:37973:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXX.</hi> Hen-Dung Swallowed.</head>
               <p>If the horſe hath accidently ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed down the dung of an Hen, which brings Gripings of the Guts, then you are to uſe this following Medicine.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Dried Ladys-Mark, 2 ounces.</item>
                  <item>Honey and Wine, a convenient quantity for a potion.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Give him this to drink, and then lead him backwards and forwards untill his belly beginneth to make a noiſe and rumble, and then he is clear from his Malady.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXI.</hi> Cholick, or Griping in the Guts.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Cholick or griping in the guts.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Black Pepper, two ounces.</item>
                  <item>The Juice and the Root of Jews-Ear.</item>
                  <item>Parsley.</item>
                  <item>Fenicle.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:37973:26"/>Marjoram, of each an ounce.</item>
                  <item>Sage, half an ounce.</item>
                  <item>Live-Honey, about 2 quarts.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Boil it, ſcum it well, and make it of the bigneſs of an Haſlenut, to little cakes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>Which you muſt give the horſe to drink with good wine about half a pint.</p>
               <p>And on that day, when he hath the Cholick, then take Fennil-ſeed three or four ſpoonsfull, and with a convenient quantity of wine, you ſhall preſently give it to the horſe to drink, and then cover him and make him ſweat well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXII.</hi> Pain in the Belly.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Griping, or pain in the Belly; you ſhall take tame, or wild Rhue-ſeed, pound it very ſmall, and with warm Wine make a potion thereof; you may alſo put therein Cumin and Fennil-ſeed, of each alike quantity; next keep the horſe warm, and well covered, in a cloſe place; but before you give him this potion, you muſt mount upon him, and ride him (to and fro) rather along high places, than upon eaven ground:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37973:26"/>
And when he is in the Stable again, then cover him with a good woollen cloth; &amp; if he grows cold again, then you muſt anoint his fundament with Oil, until it is heated, and breaks wind. Farther, it would do well alſo, to put a Rod which is thick enough, and half a foot long in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his fundament, well anointed with common Oil, and made faſt to the trunk of the fundament that it cannot go out, and then mount upon the horſe, and ride him to and fro. You muſt alſo give him to eat that which is of a warm nature, and let him drink Water, boiled with Cumin and Fennil-ſeed, of each a like quantity, adding thereunto Wheaten-meal a ſufficient quantity, and in a cloſe place keep him warm and well covered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIII.</hi> Obſtruction or Oppilation.</head>
               <p>The Obſtruction or Oppilation is cured by potions and clyſters: the potion muſt be thus: give him daily powder of wild Rhue, with the ſeed, ſoaked in good Red Wine. Or
<list>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:37973:27"/>Take Aniſe-ſeed, and the Juice of Poppeys, and Flower-de-luce Root, a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient quantity: This all together be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well pounded and beaten ſmall, you muſt add ſome Sugar-candy.</item>
                     <item>Red-Wine, half an ounce.</item>
                     <item>Oil of Olives, of each three ounces for a potion.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>This you muſt give him at three times, for three daies one after another. Or a Gliſter made after this manner.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Marſh-Mallows. and</item>
                  <item>Caſhe, 2 ounces.</item>
                  <item>Juice of flower-de-luce a convenient quantity adding thereunto</item>
                  <item>Oil of Bay-Berries.</item>
                  <item>Wine and Rhue, of each 3 ounces.</item>
                  <item>Pigeon-Dung.</item>
                  <item>Salt-petre, of each an ounce for a Clyſter.</item>
               </list>
               <p>After the Clyſter is applied, you muſt lead the Beaſt gently to and fro. Some
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37973:27"/>
Horſe-Courſers have found this following receipt to be good in this Diſtemper.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Honey, nine ſpoonfulls.</item>
                  <item>Pepper-Corns, nine.</item>
                  <item>Hares-Dung, a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, adding thereunto a Decoctum of Fitches; or Red-Colworts, as much as is requiſite for a portion.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIV.</hi> Falling of the Fundament.</head>
               <p>If the Fundament be faln, take fine bruiſed Salt, ſpread it upon the hinder-gut, and put it between the Rupture; next take a piece of Bacon, and put it therein, in the form of a ſtick, pell, and lay thereupon Mask, or Mallows, until it is healed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXV.</hi> Worms.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Worms, give the horſe to drink Water, in which Rye has been boiled; or with ſome Brimſtone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Bread; or burnt Aſhes of the wood of Olive-tree: Or take powder
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37973:28"/>
of dry Wormwood; with the ſeed, raw <hi>Lupinum</hi> of each an equal quantity; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all together mingled in white Wine for a potion.</p>
               <p>For to give it to the horſe at three ſeveral times. After theſe three daies, you muſt make a Cliſter of theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take of Wormwood and Rhue a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient quantity.</item>
                  <item>Adding thereunto two Ox-Galls, ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them.</item>
                  <item>Alloes, one ounce; For a Cliſter.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVI.</hi> Flux, or Looſeneſs of the Belly.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Flux, or Looſeneſs of the Belly, there a is very good certain po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion made of powder of Gall-nuts, with white Wine and Starch mingled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Or, in caſe that the Looſeneſs is occaſioned by Cold, then give the horſe to eat ſops ſoaked in Red-wine, and Roſe-water. Farther, anoint his Loins and Belly with Claret-wine, Oil, and a little Salt mixt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="subsection">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:37973:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVII.</hi> Bloody-Flux.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Bloody-Flux, which is occaſioned by the Forrage, let the horſe bleed on the vein of the ſhoulder; next, make a Decoction of Wheat, with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalted Greaſe, and powder of dry Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nado's skales; ſtrain it, and make a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, and give the horſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to drink every morning, and let him not work all the time. Likewiſe, you muſt make a Plaiſter to lay upon the back, &amp; on the Loins, of a <hi>Thouſand-knot,</hi> (an herb ſo called) <hi>Bolus,</hi> and the Blood of the ſick Beaſt, with ſtrong Vinegar, or courſe Claret mixt therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVIII.</hi> Jaundiſe.</head>
               <p>In the Jaundiſe, this following po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a ſpecial Remedy.</p>
               <p>Take Tares; and the ſeed of Ladies-mark, one pound.</p>
               <p>Let it boil together with Hops and good Honey, a ſufficient quantity well ſtirred and mingled together for a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:37973:29"/>Give him of this to drink for eight daies together, every day half a pint.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIX.</hi> Stoppage of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</head>
               <p>In caſe the horſe cannot make water, which appears by the ſwelling of the Bladder, and round about the Yard, then you muſt give him to drink a Pottage made of theſe following Ingredients.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take one pint of White-wine.</item>
                  <item>The White of ten Eggs mixt with Puſhed Garlick a convenient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Or the Juice of red Cabbage, or Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worts, mingled with White-wine. In the mean time you are to withhold from him all Oats and Barley, and to feed him with Hay only, and ſuch herbs as are convenient, according to the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the year, if you can get them. Farther, it will be good to put into the ſheat, through which the Piſs paſſeth, a remedy or Phyſick made of Honey that is boiled with Sugar, or a living Fly, Louſe, or Wood-louſe; or a little piece of Frankincenſe, and to lay upon the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and reins, Oil mingled with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37973:29"/>
Wine; or to annoint the Yard with pounded Wormwood boiled in Vinegar; and alſo to pour a pail of cold water upon his Stones. Theſe means are good, when the Piſs has burnt the aforeſaid parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XL.</hi> Difficulty in making Water.</head>
               <p>Againſt difficulty in making of water, it is an approved Remedy, to take five or nine Spaniſh-Flyes, that are whole, wraping them up in a Linnen Cloth, which you muſt bind faſt on the thighs of the horſe, and happen what will, you muſt let it lye thereupon a long while, for that promotes the Urin; but you muſt have a care that you do not give it to the horſe to drink, when it is beaten to powder, nor in Clyſters. It is good alſo to rub his Stones with a Decoction of an herb called Creſſes, or Noſe-ſmart, Pellitory of the wall, and Garlick.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLI.</hi> Strangury.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Strangury, or difficulty in making water, look before Sect. 39. of the inability of making water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="subsection">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:37973:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XLII.</hi> Wolf, or over growing of the Fleſh.</head>
               <p>Againſt the She-wolf, the growing and over-growing of the Fleſh, which grows under the belly of the horſe, you are to cut the place, and to prick it with a Lancet, and next to anoint it in the morning, and at night, with an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of white Mallows <hi>(Dialthea.)</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIII.</hi> Rupture prevented.</head>
               <p>Againſt Burſteneſs or Rupture, Farriers ſay that there is not any better remedy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> than this following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Aſhes of Vine-branches or Olives, ſeven ounces.</item>
                  <item>Oil of Olives.</item>
                  <item>Honey.</item>
                  <item>The Juice of Plantain, of each three ounces.</item>
                  <item>Freſh Butter.</item>
                  <item>Rhue, of each one ounce.</item>
                  <item>Onion bruiſed or pounded with white Wine, or</item>
                  <item>Decoction of <hi>Cicero,</hi> a convenient quantity mingled.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:37973:30"/>Which will ſerve to give the horſe at three divers times, on three ſeveral daies together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIV.</hi> Rupture cured.</head>
               <p>If the horſe is burſt or broken by being over-laden, and too much burdened, then lay upon his Loins a Plaiſter which is made of theſe following Ingredients.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Pitch.</item>
                  <item>Powder of Bolus.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sanguis Draconis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Maſtick, fine Frankincenſe, of each an ounce for a Plaiſter.</item>
               </list>
               <p>You muſt lay the plaiſter hot upon the ſore part, and let it lie thereupon, until it falleth it ſelf, when you touch it, for then the horſe is well again.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLV.</hi> Biting of the Spider-mouſe.</head>
               <p>The Spider-mouſe <hi>(Mus Francus)</hi> oftentimes by his biting kills an horſe. It is a Creature as big in body as a mouſe, of Colour like a little weaſel, of a long back, and of a ſhort tail, it takes
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37973:31"/>
eſpecially hold of the Stones, and makes four ſmall wounds; Thus to cure the venemous biting, you muſt immediately pour into the noſtrils of the horſe, bruiſed or pounded laurell or Bay-leaf, with water, and lay upon the biting or wounded place pounded cumin and garlick, but if it ſwelleth, then you muſt foment the piace with pickle or with a Decoction of Myrrh, and ſpread thereupon powder of burnt barley, or ſhells of Pomgranat. Look alſo in the 23 chapter of the Ox or Cow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLVI.</hi> Swoln Codds.</head>
               <p>Againſt the ſwelling of the Cods, make a Poltis of ſtrong white wine vinegar and Salt, anoint there-with the Stones twice a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLVII.</hi> Warts in the feet.</head>
               <p>Againſt the hard Knobs or Warts on the feet by much going, lay thereupon green Cabbage or Coleworts, with old greaſe or ſuet of hoggs, and mount on the horſe, ride him gently, and the phyſick will penetrate and heal the part affected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="subsection">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:37973:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXVIII.</hi> Chaps in the Feet.</head>
               <p>The Chaps in the feet are cured, by burning the ſame, with a round hot iron at the ends: for this burning hinders the Chap from growing bigger. Next you muſt anoint them with Bacon, waſhed in divers waters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or with Oil of Bay-berries mixt with Vinegar, Maſtick, Frankincenſe, and the yoalk of an Egg.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIX.</hi> Of old Swellings.</head>
               <p>Againſt hard and old Swellings, make an Ointment of theſe things following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Roſin, and Wax, of each a pound.</item>
                  <item>Ammoniack, and black Pitch, of each half a pound.</item>
                  <item>Galbanum, two ounces of common Oil, a ſufficient quantity, which being mingled altogether, make it to a Searcloth, and lay it on the part grieved.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>L.</hi> Bruiſed Back.</head>
               <p>When the horſe is hurt on the back by the Saddle, or otherwiſe, open it firſt, and lay thereupon for three daies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37973:32"/>
tow or Flax dipped in the white of Eggs; but if the pace is ſwoln and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, then you may cure it with Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, Pellitory, Wormwood, Bear-foot, or Southernwood bruiſed and boiled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with freſh or unſalted Greaſe, and laid upon the wounded place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LI.</hi> Galled-Back.</head>
               <p>Againſt a Galled Back.</p>
               <p>Take two Onions, boil them in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a Decoction.</p>
               <p>This you are to put as hot as the horſe can ſuffer it, upon the ſore part, and all the ſwelling will go away in one night. Or otherwiſe: Take beaten Salt, mingled with Vinegar and yoalks of Eggs, and therewith anoint it: or waſh the place with white Wine Vinegar, and lay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon fine Lime mingled with Honey, continuing theſe remedies ſo long till the fleſh is grown again; and the bones are covered therewith again; &amp; that the hair may grow again, bruiſe burnt ſhells of Haſle-nuts, and mingle them with Oil, and anoint the place therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="subsection">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:37973:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LII.</hi> Biting of Flyes.</head>
               <p>To preſerve horſes (in hot weather) from the biting of the Flyes, you muſt rub their hair with the juice of Courd-bliſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LIII.</hi> To drive away the Flyes.</head>
               <p>You may alſo drive away the Flyes from the ulceration, if you lay thereupon Pitch and Oil, or Greaſe mingled and melted together, and ſpread thereupon Peaſe-flower.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LIV.</hi> Stiffneſs in the Joints.</head>
               <p>When a horſe hath either ſtrained or ſtiffened his joynts, he may be cured with the ſame remedy, which is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before in the healing or curing of Faintneſs. Sect. 25.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LV.</hi> Broken Loins.</head>
               <p>Againſt broken Loins, and ſtraining of the ſame; ſee what hath been ſaid in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the cure of the bloody Flux. Sect. 37.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LVI</hi> Swelling of the Flank.</head>
               <p>When the horſe is ſick, his Rump and whole body being ſwoln, by eating of bad Oats or Hay, you muſt make him this potion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:37973:33"/>Take the innermoſt ſtomach-skins of three Chickens, let them be well dried in an Oven; break them to pieces, and add thereto fine powder of Frankincenſe, one ounce; Pepper, half an ounce; Honey, four ſpoonfuls, with half a pint of luke-warm Wine mingled for a potion.</p>
               <p>Let the horſe drink this to mollifie his belly, give him through a pipe that is ſomewhat thick and long, a Clyſter of the Decoction of the herb mercury, Pellitory, and other mollifying herbs adding thereunto Honey, Oil Sage, and Salt. This done, anoint the belly with Oil, let the horſe be rubbed behind by two men with a round ſtaf or cudgell, then mount upon him, and let him trot gently a long while, not only until he be rid of his Clyſter, but alſo of his dung, and then he will ſoon recover again and be freed from his pain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LVII.</hi> Scabby, or Mangy.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Scab, you muſt let him bleed out of the Limbs that are conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for that, and near the place, where the evil lyes. It will be neceſſary to purge the horſe with powder of will Cucumber-roots, mixt with Salt-petre
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37973:33"/>
and given the horſe with wine through a horn: this Phyſick being oftentimes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, purges away the bad humours; for an outward Phyſick or Remedy, take <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur vivum,</hi> or living Brimſtone, Tar and Jews-Gum <hi>(Aſphaltum)</hi> break and mingle theſe matters in freſh-boiled Butter: with this ointment you muſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes let him be anointed all over the body, in the greateſt heat of the Sun, except you will rather uſe this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Medicine.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Roſin-Pitch.</item>
                  <item>Bird lime; or</item>
                  <item>Cum, of each four ounces.</item>
                  <item>Strong Vinegar, about a pint, mingle it well together, to an ointment; with Mans Urine and luke-warm water.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Adding thereunto
<list>
                     <item>Freſh or unſalted Greaſe; and</item>
                     <item>Old Oil, of each three ounces; make it to an ointment or a Searcloth.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LVIII.</hi> Sinew-ſtruck.</head>
               <p>Sinew-ſtruck, is when the knees or joints be wrenched, or out of joint by running in a deſert place; and that the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:37973:34"/>
horſe hath ſet his foot wrong upon the ground; and this is cured with an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, made of theſe following Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Hoggs-greaſe or Suet, 4 ounces.</item>
                  <item>Fenigreek.</item>
                  <item>Flax-ſeed, of each one ounce.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Boil this together, until it is much leſſened, and grown thick for an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>If you ſhould think it to be better firſt to waſh the horſe all over or to foment him with piſs and lukewarm water, and then chafe him with a chafing ointment: the juice of Colian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-ſeed, adding thereto Vinegar and Tar and Wax is an excellent remedy againſt this evil. And forget not that you chafe and ſmear him alwayes againſt the lying of the hair.</p>
               <p>Beſides, there is another ſpecial remedy againſt this, to wit, firſt to curry the ſcabby place til it bleeds, and next to waſh it with a Lye of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ingredients.</p>
               <p>Take Aſhes of Aſhen-Tree, 3 ounces, Beans 2 ounces Lime 1 ounce, not boiled but ſoaked to a Lye, waſh the place therewith.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:37973:34"/>After the waſhing, you muſt chafe the place with an ointment, made of Allom, Coalts-foot, Hellebore, Quick-ſilver, Brim-ſtone and Hogs-greaſe, or Suet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LIX.</hi> Swoln Knees.</head>
               <p>Againſt ſwollen knees.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take burnt Copper, half a pound.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bolus (Synople)</hi> a conv. quantity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </item>
                  <item>Salt, a little, melted in a pint of ſtrong Vinegar.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LX.</hi> Cleft and Wounded Knees.</head>
               <p>When the Knees are cleft &amp; wounded.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take common Oil.</item>
                  <item>Flax-ſeed.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Burnt Rye-ſtraw (of each a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient quantity) mingle it together to an ointment; and to anoint the wound therewith in the morning, and at night, till it is healed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXI.</hi> Overgrowing of the Knee pan.</head>
               <p>Againſt the over-grown bone, or the over-growing of the knee-pan, you muſt firſt cut off the hair; and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37973:35"/>
lay thereupon bruiſed and boyled roots of white Mallows, next put a plaiſter thereupon made of Mallow-roots, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard-ſeed and Oxe-dung being altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther boyled in vinegar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXII.</hi> Farcions, or Leproſie of the Leggs.</head>
               <p>For to cure the Leproſy of the Leggs, you muſt firſt cut off the hair, and then for four daies continually, in the morning, and at night chafe the place with Juniper-Oil; In the mean time, the horſe muſt not be rid to the water, before the hair is is grown again, Beſides it may be cured by a long and oblique burning of an hot Iron.</p>
               <p>Another way to heal this evill, is to take roots of white Thiſtle cut in ſmall ſlices and being given to the horſe, to eat amongſt his oats he will without doubt be well and recover again within a fortnight or three weeks at leaſt. This means is very eaſy, and ſo much the more becauſe the horſe eats it heartily.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXIII.</hi> Chaps between the Joints &amp; Leggs.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Chaps, which appear between the joynts of the leggs and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37973:35"/>
the claws of the feet; you muſt cut off the hair, and waſh the place with wine, next chafe it with an ointment made of ſoot of a chimney, and <hi>ſpaniſh green,</hi> bruized and boyled together, at laſt adding thereto lime, as much as is requiſite, but if the chaps be too deep, then burn them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXIV.</hi> String-halt.</head>
               <p>The String-halt is thus healed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cut the skin; after the length of the hair, and according to the bigneſs of the wound, lay a little Cloth thereupon dipped in wine, and ſpread thereupon powder of <hi>Spaniſh-green,</hi> until they be</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXV.</hi> Mallender.</head>
               <p>The Mallender muſt after the hair is cut off, be waſhed with a Decoction of Mallows, Sheep-greaſe, and Brimſtone, and then the relick or remainder to be laid thereupon: when it is taken off again, you muſt make an ointment of, of this following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Gum-Arabick.</item>
                  <item>Turpentine.</item>
                  <item>New Wax, of each a like quantity,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37973:36"/>
mingled together a convenient quantity to an ointment.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXVI.</hi> Spavin.</head>
               <p>Againſt the ſpavins appearing within the knee-ham, you muſt let the great vein of the thigh ſwell up, and to tap blood out of the ſame, burn it in the length and breadth, and heal, in ſuch manner as hereafter will be ſaid concerning the overgrowing of the hoof of an horſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXVII.</hi> Biting of a Mad Dog.</head>
               <p>Againſt the biting of a mad Dog, this is an excellent remedy, At leaſt before the 9 days, Take Henbane-ſeed burnt and mingled with old Hogs-greaſe, and laid upon the biting, or the ſame being bruiſed mixt with old wine and and given the horſe to drink. Like-wiſe Eglantine or ſweet briar root pounded ſmall, and ſpread over the wound, or given to drink with good old wine. Likewiſe Elder-berry or ſeed or Juice of Elder-leaves, or of Aſh-tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="subsection">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:37973:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXVIII.</hi> Biting of a Water-Snake.</head>
               <p>Againſt the biting of water-ſnakes, Take a living Cock ſplit aſunder in the midſt of the belly, and lay it warm upon the wound, And then immediately you muſt give the horſe a potion of ſtrong Wine yellow Lilly powder and ſalt: or roots, leaves and fruits of wild vine burnt to aſhes, and apply it with good white Wine, or take immediately a kind of wild Bugloſs which is called <hi>Echium,</hi> ſqueeze a pint of Juice thereout. After it is aſperſed with white Wine or <hi>Carduus Benedictus</hi> water, in caſe you ſee that the leaves give not Juice e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, then pour what you have into the mouth of the horſe, next take the preſſings out of which the Juice is preſt, and put it and bind it upon and about the biting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXIX.</hi> Ringbone.</head>
               <p>If your horſe have the Ringbone waſh it with ſtrong Vinegar, then ſpread thereupon very fine powder of Opement <hi>Arſenicum,</hi> and unquenched Lime, being burnt together in a pot to aſhes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="subsection">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:37973:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXX.</hi> Fiſtula.</head>
               <p>Againſt a Fiſtula, make uſe of the laſt medicine, burn it, and put therein a remedy of unſlack'd Lime, until the cruſt falls out.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXI.</hi> Overgrowing of the Hoofs.</head>
               <p>Againſt the overgrowing of the hoofs burn it and cut it length-ways and ſide-ways, and put therupon a Poulteſs pap of freſh Cow-dung, fried over the fire with Oil; lay this once thereupon and order then the horſe in like manner, as hath been before directed for the healing of overgrowing bones, Sect. 61.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="subsection">
               <head>LXXII. <hi>Figg.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Againſt the fig<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you muſt cut the horn of the foot, ſo far, till there be convenient room, between the hoof and the fig, then lay thereupon a ſponge, tie it faſt, untill the form of the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the fig, be eaten away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="subsection">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:37973:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXIII.</hi> Founders.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Founders, or overgrowing of the hoof, called by French Javard.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Old Onions.</item>
                  <item>Cabbage or Coleworts bliſter.</item>
                  <item>Garlick and pepper, of each a convenient quantity for a plaiſter or Poulteſs, and lay it thereupon.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXIV.</hi> Pricking with a Nail.</head>
               <p>When the horſe is prickt with a nail, then you muſt draw out the nail, and cleanſe and waſh the Ulcer or wound, and drop thereinto melted brimſtone, or fill it with an ointment made of the following ingredients.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Honey.</item>
                  <item>Oil.</item>
                  <item>Greaſe.</item>
                  <item>Turpentine.</item>
                  <item>Wax, and (Salt of each a ſufficient quantity, being melted all together to an ointment.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:37973:38"/>And when it is very hot, dip ſome cotton therein: or lay upon the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded place within in the nail of the foot, leaves of Wool-blade rubbed or beaten between two ſtones. But if the pricking of the nail is one or two days old, then you muſt hold the foot of the horſe in ſalted warm water, &amp; bind upon the foot a plaiſter made of bread or crumbs of bread, Hogs-greaſe, and Salt water, or ſmall buiſed ſalt and ſtrong vinegar; or powder of gall, Maſtick, or Myrtle, next put the horſe ſhooe on again, and fill the whole hole of the, foot with Hoggs greaſe (letting it drop therein and thereupon) and let it be ſhut up as is neceſſary; and let the horſe be ſhod again, likewiſe fill the place of the nail with pitch, and chafe it oftentimes with hogs-greaſe as before.</p>
               <p>Now to keep the hoof in its ſtrength lay upon it a plaiſter of boiled Mallows, bruiſed and mingled with Honey and crums of bread, put in the hole of the foot the herb Salendine, and Shepherds-Purſe, and thereupon bind the dung of the ſame horſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="subsection">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:37973:38"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXV.</hi> Limping or Halting.</head>
               <p>In caſe the horſe limps or halteth, becauſe the Sinews are ſhrunk.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Rhue.</item>
                  <item>Bird-lime, of each a pound.</item>
                  <item>Copperas.</item>
                  <item>White-lead of each half a pound make thereof an ointment.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXVI.</hi> The Wolf, or Boils and Knobs of the Foot.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Shee-wolf, or Boils or Knobs on the foot; you muſt open them when you ſee they are full of matter, and then lay upon the Sore or Ulcer a plaiſter of Gooſe-dung, Wine, White-wine Vinegar and Salt; having great care that there do not remain any bad matter in the bottom.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="subsection">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:37973:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXVII.</hi> Scabbineſs, Scurvineſs, or Kibe-heels.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Scabbineſs or Scurvineſs, which is called Scratches on the heel; take off the skin, and chafe the place with an ointment of the following Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Vinegar.</item>
                  <item>Rheniſh Turpentine.</item>
                  <item>New Wax.</item>
                  <item>Rhue of each. boil it together to an ointment.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXVIII.</hi> Over-ſtepping.</head>
               <p>In caſe the horſe ſteping over with his hinder feet, hurts his forefeet, then you muſt cut off the hair of the wounded place, rub it with Salt, and bind there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon a plate of Lead; afterwards take it off, and waſh the place with Wine.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:39"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:40"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Country mans directory ſhewing the ſeverall places in the body of an Ox or Cow where the ſeverall diſeaſes vſually happen</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_diseases">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:37973:40"/>
            <head>A TABLE of ſeveral DISEASES incident to the OXE or COW, With relation to the Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Cut or Portraiture of an Oxe in the 65 Page of this BOOK.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> DIſeaſes in the Horn, or Wearied Horns.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Scaled Horns.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Split Horns.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Broken Horns.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Hairs ſtanding upright.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Lice or Tickets.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Scab, Itch, or Mange.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Eating Sore in the Neck.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Apoſthumes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Boils or Mattering <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:37973:41"/>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Hide-bound on the Legs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Hide-bound on the Ribs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Bewitched.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Head-ach, or Pain in the Head.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> Humour or Rheum.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> Swollen Eyes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> Weeping Eyes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> Running Eyes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19.</hi> Sharp Tears.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20.</hi> Mattering Eyes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21.</hi> Dark Eyes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22.</hi> Nail of the Eyes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23.</hi> Spots or Webs in the Eyes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24.</hi> White on the Eye.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25.</hi> Wart upon the Eye-lids.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26.</hi> Falling of the Pallate, or Swollen Pallate.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>27.</hi> Cleft or Split Tongue.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28.</hi> Knobs under the Tongue.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29.</hi> Carnils under the Tongue.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30.</hi> Swelling in the Throat.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>31.</hi> To prevent Impoſthumes in the Neck.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32.</hi> The Neck Bruiſed.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>33.</hi> The Neck deprived of Skin.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>34.</hi> The Neck deprived of Hair.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>35.</hi> Hardened Neck.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>36.</hi> Swollen Neck.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>37.</hi> Shoulder out of Joynt.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:37973:41"/>
                  <hi>38.</hi> Crumpled or Shrunken Shoulder.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>39.</hi> Diſeaſe in the Lungs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>40.</hi> The ſame.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>41.</hi> Cough.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>42.</hi> Difficult Taking of Breath.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>43.</hi> Slow or Laſie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>44.</hi> Wearineſs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>45.</hi> Ague.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>46.</hi> Beating of the Heart.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>47.</hi> Stomach loſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>48.</hi> Horſe-leech Swallowed down.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>49.</hi> Swallowing of Grubs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>50.</hi> Dublone.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>51.</hi> Pain of the Belly.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>52.</hi> Griping in the Guts (Cholick.)</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>53.</hi> Obſtruction, or Opilation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>54.</hi> Looſneſs and Bloody Flux.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>55.</hi> Spoiled Arſe-Guts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>56.</hi> Pain of the Loins.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>57.</hi> Pain of the Reins, Inflamation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>58.</hi> Inflamation of Muſcles.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>59.</hi> Piſſing of Blood.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>60.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nableneſs of making Water.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>61.</hi> Stone of the Bladder.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>62.</hi> Stone of the Yard.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>63.</hi> Hardned Yard.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>64.</hi> Swollen Cods.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>65.</hi> Limping or Lame.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>66.</hi> Leg out of Joynt, or Wrinched.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:37973:42"/>
                  <hi>67.</hi> Broken Leg.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>68.</hi> Biting of Serpents.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>69.</hi> Stinging of the Hornet.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>70.</hi> Kibe on the Heel.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>71.</hi> Swollen Foot.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>72.</hi> Crumped Foot.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>73.</hi> Foot out of Joynt, or Wrinch<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Foot.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>74.</hi> Wounded Foot.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>75.</hi> Wounded Claw.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>76.</hi> Broken Claw.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>77.</hi> Looſe Claw.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>78.</hi> Claw fallen off.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:37973:42"/>
            <head>Of the Cow and Calf.</head>
            <p>TOuching the Cow and Calf, it is to be noted in the firſt place, That the Cow ought not to be ſuffered to come to the Bull before ſhe is in her third year, and not longer: For if you let her be covered before, ſhe will not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to grow to her full Strength and Bigneſs, but will bring forth ſmall and weak Calves. Likewiſe, If you let her be covered after twelve years, the Calf will not be ſo ſtrong nor ſo well made. The moſt proper times for the Cow to be covered in,<note rend="inter">The Cow when to be covered.</note>
are <hi>May</hi> and Hay time, when the Herb is in its beſt force and vigour. For at this time generally ſhe deſires the Bull moſt; which you may obſerve, when the Claws of her Feet are ſwollen, and alſo by her conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Lowing. If the Cow is covered
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37973:43"/>
about this time, ſhe will caſt her C<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> about ten Moneths afterwards; abo<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> which time the new Graſs will coming forth, which will renew h<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Milk; and tend to the better nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of the Calf. That the Cow ma<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the better conceive, you muſt lea<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> her lean to the Bull, though on th<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> contrary, the Bull ought at the ſam<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> time to be fat and well knuckled, o<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> full of joynts. The Bull alſo ought t<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> be rather long than tall, of red Hair<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> broad Shoulders, thick Bones, ſmall Body (yet round) broad Breaſt, ſhort Head, broad Forehead, black Eyes ſhort Horns, long and rough Tail In caſe the Cow will not admit the Bull, or that the Bull deſires her not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you may create them an appetite, by holding before their Noſtrils burnt Harts-tail, or by uſing another mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which we ſhall take notice of in <hi>chap.</hi> 28. concerning the Horſe. During the time that the Cow is full, you muſt keep her from leaping over Ditches, and from running through Hedges or Buſhes of Thorns or Bryers: Beſides, you muſt keep her a while in the Cow-houſe before ſhe caſts, with good
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:37973:43"/>
Fodder, without milking her at any time; for the Milk which ſhe then gives is not good, but becomes as hard as a Stone. You muſt take ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial care to give her very clear Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which ſhe loves as much as a Horſe loves muddy thick Water (for you muſt obſerve by the way, that <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tis a token of a good Horſe when he ſtirs the Water with his Fore-foot) before he drinks.</p>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Of the Calf.</head>
               <p>NOw concerning the young Calf; You muſt leave it by the Cow after ſhe has caſt with a good ſtrew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of freſh Straw, renewing it often for five or ſix days together, at which time you may remove the Calf to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place, and carry it to the Cow from time to time to ſuck. But if you find that the Calf will not ſuck; but bubbles with the Teat, not being able to draw Milk, you muſt look under the Tongue, and if you find there a whitiſh fleſhly ſubſtance growing over the Tongue, much like to the Pip, you muſt cut it off with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:37973:44"/>
wounding the Tongue, with ſmall well cutting Ciſſers, and waſh the place with Water and Salt, and well bruiſed Garlick broken, which always prevents the Death of the Calf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which remedy the Calf often dies of this Diſtemper.</p>
               <p>You ought alſo to be very careful in driving away the Lice which trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Calf and hinder his growth, as doth the Scabs, which is occaſioned thereby, which may be eaſily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned when the Skin wrinkles. Theſe two Diſtempers are cured by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing the Calf with Butter, and will wholly be prevented, if you rub the Calf twice a day with a handful of Straw, and do not ſuffer his Piſs to lie under him. And you muſt be ſure to keep him with freſh Strewing, keeping his Dung from him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>When to geld a Calf.</head>
               <p>THe Calf muſt be gelt in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before he goes into the field, and before he is two years old, and not later; for this is the beſt time for his growing large. When the Calf is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:37973:44"/>
gelt, you muſt give him Hay chopt or cut ſmall, mingled with <hi>Bread,</hi> until he gets his former ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite. You ought not to geld him in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of hot or cold weather,<note rend="inter">The Gelding of a Calf.</note>
or in the decreaſe of the Moon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Marks of a good Cow.</head>
               <p>AS for the Cow, ſhe ought to be of a middle ſize, <hi>viz.</hi> long of bigneſs, broad rump, black Hair, or ſpeckled, or with white and black ſpots; the Winde-pipe great and hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down, of a great Belly, broad Forehead,<note rend="inter">Marks of a Cow.</note>
black and great Eyes, the Horns not ſhort nor thin, but even and black, rough Ears, hollow Cheek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, great Mouth, open and drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Noſtrils, hanging down Lips, long thick Neck, broad Shoulders, with a long Tail to her Heels; ſmall ſhort, and even Claws on the Feet: broad Breaſt, great and long Teats.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:37973:45"/>
               <head>Concerning the Oxe.</head>
               <p>THe Oxe Is inclined to as many Diſtempers as the Horſe; and to preſerve him from the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Diſtempers, the Ancients did purge him at the end of each ſeaſon of the year,<note rend="inter">Of the Oxe.</note>
for three days together; ſome with Lupin and Berries of <hi>Cyprus</hi> pounded together, and ſoaked one night under the blew Heaven, in Spring-water: Others with Drugs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtom and diverſity of the Countries.</p>
               <p>You may underſtand that he is Sick when he eats nothing, although he hath much fine Fodder lying before him. There is nothing better thus to cleanſe the moſt inward parts and to purge him, than to let him often eat the remainder of Olives, out of which the Oyl has been preſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>All kind of Sickneſſes.</head>
               <p>Aſſoon then as you ſee the Oxe to be Sick, of what ſickneſs ſoever it
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37973:45"/>
be, then you muſt give him the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Purge made of Sea-onion, Rhamnus and Common Salt boiled in Water, and make it luke-warm with the ſame Water. But you muſt neither give him to eat nor to drink, before this Purge hath done its oporation. But to preſerve him the whole year along from Sickneſs, you muſt give him in the beginning of the Spring, of the Summer, Harveſt, and the Winter, a potion made of Leaves of Capers and <hi>Cypeſs</hi> ſoaked in Water, and let it ſtand one night a ſoaking in a pot, and continue this for three mornings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>All ſorts of Pain.</head>
               <p>Againſt all outward pain, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be in the Body, which diſables the Beaſt from going or acting with eaſe, you muſt foment the place, and lay thereupon a Poltis of Cammomlie, Flax-ſeed, and the Hetb Melilot.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="subsection">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:37973:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Wearied Horns.</head>
               <p>If the Horns of the Oxe are wearied by drawing, then to comfort them, is by force to make the Horn faſt in its place, and next annoint it, as alſo the uppermoſt parts of the Head, for five or ſix days together, with an Ointment of bruiſed Cumin, Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, Honey, and Bolus Armenius, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all together mingled and boiled. Next you muſt waſh the Horn with a Decoctum of Wine, wherein a good deal of Sage and Lavender has been boiled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Scaled Horns <hi>Or, 3.</hi> Split Horns.</head>
               <p>In caſe the Horn is ſcaled, then you muſt foment it firſt with Vinegar, Salt, and Oyl, mixt together; and next lay thereupon old melted Hogs Greaſe or Suet, and new Pitch, or annoit him with this on the wounded place for five or ſix days, and then the Horn will grow ſoft, and the Clefts will go away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="subsection">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:37973:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Broken Horn.</head>
               <p>In caſe his Horn is broken, then take Turpentine 6 Ounces, Gum Arabick one Ounce; boil this to an Ointment, and rub with this the Horn round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout for ten or twelve days together, which time being expired, bruiſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Bolus, mingled with the White of Eggs, and ſpread it upon the Tow or Flax, and lay it upon the wounded place, and let it lie thereupon for three days together: Thus when the Tow begins to dry, then take it off, and ſpread in the place bruiſed Sage, and the Horn will be healed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Hair ſtanding upright.</head>
               <p>When the Hair of the Oxe or Cow ſtands upright over the whole Body, and he is not ſo merry as he uſes to be, but of a ſad look, his Neck hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downwards, his Mouth foamy, having a heavy gate, the Back-bone and alſo the whole Back ſtiff, eating without Stomach, and chewing but little. This Sickneſs may be cured
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37973:47"/>
in the beginning, but being inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate, it can in no wiſe, or at leaſt very ſeldom be helped. For which cure take Sea-Onion, or Wild-Onion, and cut ſmall Roots of Mellons bruiſed, of each three Ounces, courſe Salt three handfuls, let it be ſoaked in a pot of ſtrong Wine, or in Vinegar, to a potion. Of this you may give the Oxe or Cow every day half a pint.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Lice or Ticks.</head>
               <p>Againſt Lice or Ticks, you muſt uſe a Decoctum of wild Olives and Salt, and take away the little Bliſters which he has under his Tongue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> The Scab, Itch or Mange.</head>
               <p>The Scab, Itch, or Mange, is cured with Common Oyl, and Oyl of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lives mingled together, or take Oxe-Gall, the Powder of living Brimſtone, Myrrhe, Oyl, and Vinegar, with ſome Plum-Allum, being rub'd ſmall and mingled together. Or chafe him with his Piſs, with old Salt-butter, with Turpentine, or with White Rozen melted in White Wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="subsection">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:37973:47"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Eating Sore in the Neck.</head>
               <p>Againſt an Eating Sore; or (Scab) rub him with bruiſed Garlick, with Powder of Brimſtone and Vinegar, with broken Gall-nuts, or with White Andoren, mixt with Soot.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Apoſthumes or Sores.</head>
               <p>In caſe he hath Apoſthumes or Sores, then you muſt annoint them with bruſed Mallow in White Wine; alſo upon the Sore parts, unleſs there be great reaſon to the contrary: It is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe very good to lay ſmall bruiſed Powder of Gall-nuts; likewiſe the Juice of Andoren is very good in this caſe, being mixt with the Soot of an Oven.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Boils or Mattering <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers.</head>
               <p>Boils or Ulcers are made ripe with Leaven, Lilly-root, with Sea-Onion and Vinegar, letting him blood and cleanſing him with his warm Piſs, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting therein Wicks dipt in Tar; all
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37973:48"/>
which ſpread upon a Linnen Cloth which has lain in the Greaſe of Goats or of Oxen, and lay it to the part affected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Hide-bound on the Legs.</head>
               <p>If the Skin ſticks to the Bones, then you muſt foment it, either with Wine alone, or ſuch as is mixt with Oyl.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Hide-bound on the Ribs.</head>
               <p>In caſe he is too lean, that the Skin ſeems to cleave to the Ribs, then fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his Hide, againſt the grain of the Hair, with Wine and Oyl in a warm place, or in the Sun; next annoint him with the Dregs of Wine and Hogs Suet, being mixt together into an Ointment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Bewitched.</head>
               <p>The Oxe and Cow is often bewitched, as well as the Horſe, the ſigns of this are, that he is melancholly, grows dry and lean; therefore you ſhall give him in through the Noſtrils Jews Gum Brimſtone, Juniper-berries, being all
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:37973:48"/>
together ſoaked and broken in warm Water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Head-ach.</head>
               <p>Againſt Head-ach, bruiſe Garlick in Wine, and let him draw that up through the Noſtrils, next foment the whole Head with a decoctum of Laurel, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender, Mariblam, or Margelins Nuts, and Rue Bliſters ſodden in Wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>15.</hi> Humour or Rheum.</head>
               <p>When he contracts any Humour or Rheum, becauſe of ſuperfluity of Flegm or Snot, which is apparent when his Eyes run, and that he has no Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and lets his Ears hang down, then waſh his Mouth with Rhue brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in White Wine, or rub his Mouth with Garlick and ſmall beaten Salt, and waſh it next with Wine: Some cleanſe theſe Flegms with bruiſed Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel-leaves, and the Rinds of Granat-Apples; others put into his Noſtrils Myrrhe and Wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="subsection">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:37973:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>16.</hi> Swollen Eyes.</head>
               <p>Againſt ſwollen Eyes, put upon them a Plaiſter of Wheaten-meal, mixt with Honey, or Honey-water. But if they are ſwollen with Humour or Rheume; then let him blood under the Tongue, and pour into him well cleanſed Juice of Ladies Mark, Sage and Savin, or againſt bad ſwollen Eyes, make an Eye-water of bruiſed Wheat mingled with Honey-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>17.</hi> Weeping Eyes.</head>
               <p>Againſt Weeping Eyes and Moiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that drops upon his Cheeks, take Pap of Wheaten-meal, and make thereof a Plaiſter for to lay upon the Eyes. Againſt this Diſtemper alſo Wild Parſnips being bruiſed with Stalk and Root together, and mixt with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for to annoint the Eyes therewith, is very effectual.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>18.</hi> Running Eyes.</head>
               <p>Againſt Running Eyes, blow into
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:37973:49"/>
them fine bruiſed Copperas, or Vitriol and Thutia.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>19.</hi> Sharp Tears.</head>
               <p>Againſt Sharp Tears <hi>(Epiphorae)</hi> of the Eyes, that is, that the Oxe hath but his half Sight; whether it be in one or in both Eyes, you muſt let him blood under the Eyes, and the Sight will be bettered; but you muſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually drop Honey into his Eyes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he is perfectly cured.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>20.</hi> Mattering Eyes.</head>
               <p>Againſt Eyes that Matter like a Wound, which happeneth by continual Humour, which fall down from the Brains, take Saffron and fine Frankincenſe, of each two ounces, Myrrhe one ounce, break it in Rain Water, and mingle it to an Eye-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>21.</hi> Dark and Cloudy Eyes.</head>
               <p>In caſe he hath a Dark and Cloudy Eye, then blow into it fine Powder of Cinnamon, Sugar-candy, and of dried Bones.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="subsection">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:37973:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>22.</hi> Shales or Nail of the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Shales or Nail of the Eyes, you muſt make him an Eye-Water of Stone-ſalt (Sal Armoniack) ſoaked in Honey; or annoint alſo the Eyes with a mixture of Oyl of Olives and Pitch, being well incorporated, to prevent the danger of Flies which are apt to come about the Honey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>23.</hi> Spots or Webs in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Againſt Spots or Webs in the Eyes, which is nothing but a ſuperfluity, which through great Cold or long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, grows upon the Eyes, in which there is a Humour, which is called Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriſh; upon which ſwimmeth one, which is ſomewhat Glaſſie. To cure this Diſtemper, take Ardtvel and pound it long in a Woodden Mortar, and annoint the Eyes with the Juice which comes out from it. But if you cannot get that, then take the Leaves and Berries of Straw-berries, and make thereof Juice as before: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue with one of theſe Remedies in the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:37973:50"/>
Morning and at the Evening for many days together, then the Spots ſhall decreaſe and go away. And obſerve that you do inſtead of Water take Wine thereto, it would be better and more convenient.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>24.</hi> White on the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Againſt the White on the Eyes, put a Plaiſter thereupon of Chryſtal Salt <hi>(Sal Gemmae)</hi> and Maſtick pounded ſmall, and mixt on the Eyes together with Honey, continuing the ſame of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>25.</hi> Warts upon the Eye-lids.</head>
               <p>In caſe he hath Warts upon the Eye-lids, then foment the place with the Gall of any Beaſt whatſoever, or (which is better) cut the Warts off with a pair of Ciſſers, or take them off with a Thread tied on ſtiff; next an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the place with Alloes, Vinegar, and Gall, boiled together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="subsection">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:37973:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>26.</hi> Swollen Pallate, or Falling of the Pallate.</head>
               <p>If the Pallate is ſwollen, then you muſt open it immediately with a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, or red-hot Iron, to the end that the corrupted Blood may run out; next give him ſome Herbs, and often Hay to eat: but if it is ſo ſwollen, that he loſes his ſtomach and his taſte, and is often ſick, then you muſt open the Vein of the Pallate, and not give him any thing to eat but Garlick which is peelled, bruiſed, and ſoaked with Leaves or other Green, until he recovereth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>27.</hi> Split Tongue.</head>
               <p>If the Tongue is ſplit beneath, then annoint the cleft twice a day with an Ointment of Alloes, Rock-Allum, and Honey of Roſes, being mixt together. Next waſh it with Wine, wherein Sage and other drying Herbs are boiled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="subsection">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:37973:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>28.</hi> Knobs under the Tongue.</head>
               <p>If the Oxe has a little Knob which is fleſhy under the Tongue, then you muſt cut it off, and next rub the place with Salt and Garlick pounded toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then waſh his Mouth with Wine, and with little Tongs take gently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſmall Worms which begin to come under the Tongue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>29.</hi> Carnils under the Tongue.</head>
               <p>In caſe he has Carnils under his Tongue, and is much ſwollen, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen it with a fiery-hot Iron, or ſharp Lancet, next rub it with Salt and Oyl, until the bad humour is run out, at laſt give him to eat ſome young Herbs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>30.</hi> Swollen Almonds.</head>
               <p>Againſt the ſwelling of the Throat, which is occaſioned by a Cold Brain, cover the Head with ſome Coverture, and rub oftentimes the whole Throat with freſh Butter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="subsection">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:37973:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>31.</hi> To prevent Impoſthumes in the Neck.</head>
               <p>If the Neck is ſwollen, and you are affraid of a Swelling with Matter and Filth, then open it with a red hot I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and put into the hole the Root of Hogs-bread, of Nettles, renewing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes the ſame; it is very neceſſary in this caſe, that you give him to drink a good Cruce full of a Decoctum of Italian...... and let him bleed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>32.</hi> Bruiſed Neck.</head>
               <p>If the Neck is hurt, ſwollen, and hanging down, then let him blood at one of his Ears; but if it is in the midſt of both Ears, lay upon the Swelling a Plaiſter of melted Oxe marrow, and Cocks-Greaſe, of each half an Ounce in Oyland Tar, or melted Pitch, and rub the Swollen parts with the Sword of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, whereon there is not any Fat, and is of a Barrow Hog, being warmed a little, continuing it five or ſix morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="subsection">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:37973:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>33.</hi> Neck deprived of Skin.</head>
               <p>If his Neck be deprived of Skin, put upon it a Plaiſter of Oxe-marrow, taken out of the Thigh-bones, Rue and the Greaſe of a Buck, and Hogs-ſuet, of each an ounce, being melted and mixt together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>34.</hi> Neck deprived of Hair.</head>
               <p>If his Neck is deprived of Hair, and bare, then annoint the place with this following Ointment, take Honey ſix Ounces, Maſtick four Ounces, boil them together to an Ointment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>35.</hi> Hardened Neck.</head>
               <p>If his Neck is hardened, let him ſtand ſome days without labouring, in the mean time you muſt annoint the hard place with an Ointment of Butter, Oyl, Bacon, and new Wax, of each an ounce, being melted and mixt together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="subsection">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:37973:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>36.</hi> Swollen Neck.</head>
               <p>If his Neck be Swollen, then make him an Ointment of Alaud-roots, that are pounded and boiled in raw Honey Bucks or Sheep-Rue, Hogs-ſuet, new Wax; annoint the Neck with this three times a day; in the morning, at noon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and at night.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>37.</hi> Shoulders out of Joynt.</head>
               <p>If the Shoulders be disjoynted, or out of Joynt, then put the Bones a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in their place, and bind them faſt with Tablets of light Wood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>38.</hi> Crumpled Shoulders.</head>
               <p>If his Shoulder is crumpled, then you muſt blood him on the hinder foot, on the far ſide, but if they are both ſhrunk in, then you muſt blood him on both Legs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>39.</hi> Diſtemper in the Lungs.</head>
               <p>The Diſtemper in the Lungs is ſuch
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:37973:53"/>
a mortal Diſtemper, as well to the Oxen as to the Kine, that there is not any Remedy againſt it, but that you waſh the Manger, out of which they have eaten, with hot water and well-ſcent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Herbs, before you tie the others thereunto, which in the mean time muſt be kept in an other Stable. They get this Sickneſs by eating bad Herbs and corrupted Hay; and through great ſuperfluity of Blood; but for the moſt part by Horſe-piſs, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when you keep the Cow-houſe Clowſie. Therefore you ſhould nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let Horſes nor Mares come into the Cow-houſe; but Aſſes may, and do much good; for the Breath of the Aſſes keeps them from Diſtempers in the Lungs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>40.</hi> Lung-Sickneſs.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Lung-ſickneſs give him the Juice of Liquoriſh with ſweet Wine, or put into his Ears the Root of Hazle-tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>41.</hi> Cough.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Cough, let him drink a
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:37973:54"/>
decoctum of Hyſop, and eat Liquoriſ<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Roots, being bruiſed with clean Wheat Some make them drink ſeven days to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether a decoctum of ....</p>
               <p>The Cough of the Oxen muſt as dili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gently be cured, as the Cough of the Horſes; and you muſt not let the ſame laſt long, or grow too cold; the beſt way is, to ſeek remedy againſt in the beginning: Therefore you mu<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> powre into his mouth, through a Hor<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> or otherwiſe, an half Meaſure of Barle<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Flower, and an whole Egg without Shill, being boiled in a Can of Wine or take Poppies bruiſed in warm Water with dried Bean-meal, that is broke<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to ſhales, or very ſmall pieces; an<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Meal of Peaſe, being all well mingle together; and give them that to eat early in the morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Old Cough.</head>
               <p>Againſt an old Cough, the following Remedy is very good, Take dry of freſh <hi>Hyſop,</hi> two hands full, boyl them in common Water (as much as is ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſary) ſtrain it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and add to it two thirds of Starch; mingle it together and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:37973:54"/>
give it to the Beaſt. You may alſo mix with it Hyſop Water, a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctum of Hyſop and Mint. Againſt the ſame Diſtemper is good alſo the Juice of Liquoriſh, being well ſqueezed out, and given the Beaſt with Oyl of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lives. Nay, the Cough will never be grown ſo old but it may be cured and driven away with the Roots of Liquoriſh well cleanſed and waſht, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in a Decoctum with Wheaten-meal. The ſame vertue have alſo the ſmall Peaſe, or little Fitches, being given him to eat or being ſet before him with Honey-water, when he Coughs moſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>42.</hi> Difficulty of fetching Breath.</head>
               <p>Againſt difficulty of fetching Breath, put through his Ear, or the great Skin of his Throat, the Herb called Black Hellebore or Lions Paw.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>43.</hi> Heavy and Lazy.</head>
               <p>If he is Lazy, then give him every month bruiſed Fitches, ſoaked in the Water which he drinks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="subsection">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:37973:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>44.</hi> Wearineſs.</head>
               <p>To preſerve him from growing wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry too ſoon, you muſt rub his Horns with Turpentine and Oyl mingled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: But have a care that you do not rub him with this on the Mouth or Noſtrils, for thoſe parts will be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>45.</hi> Ague.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Ague, which the Beaſt gets in hot Weather, which appears by melancholly, ſwollen Eyes, and extraordinary Heat, and is perceived by the touching of the Hide; you muſt open the Vein of the Fore-head or of the Ears, and give him cool Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as Lettice, and other ſuch Herbs, and give him cool Water to drink.</p>
               <p>Againſt another kind of Ague (which you may know by his great Diſquiet or want of Reſt) trembling over the whole Body; through the great Heat in the midſt of his Fore-head, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the root of his Horns, and by his Ears alſo, by his hot Mouth, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:37973:55"/>
his exceſſive Sweat, by his little eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and licking, and drawing of a dry Tongue; by the heavineſs or melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly of the Head, cunning and half-ſhut Eyes, his Mouth very moiſt and full of Slabber, long fetching of Breath, nevertheleſs with great pain, and often turning.) On the firſt day that you are aware of the Sickneſs, let him faſt the whole day; the next day you ſhall let him bleed a little under his Tail: five days afterwards you muſt nouriſh him with a Decoctum made of Burs, Oyl, and Pickle. You muſt proffer him <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ways before all other, green or moiſt Food, viz. ſmall tops of Lettice and other young Sprouts, which you know will pleaſe the Beaſt. VVaſh him alſo three times a day in the Mouth with a Sponge, that is made wet in Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar; next you ſhall give him three times very cold Water to drink, and let him not ſeed in the paſture till the Ague hath left him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>46.</hi> Beating of the Heart.</head>
               <p>In caſe he is troubled with Beating of the Heart, and a deſire to vomit,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:37973:56"/>
then rub him in the Mouth with Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, or bruiſed Leeks, and let him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſwallow them down, either alone or with a pint of Wine; eſpecially againſt the Griping in the Guts (Chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick) and rumbling of the Belly (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as we ſhall ſhew in its due place) <hi>Sect.</hi> 52.</p>
               <p>In caſe he has loſt his Stomach, you muſt give him raw Eggs, beaten with Honey and Salt, mingled with his Fodder, or give him in his drink Andoren bruiſed ſmall with Oyl and Wine, or bruiſe the Leaves of Parſley ..... Sage, and Rue; and give him this to drink with White Wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>47.</hi> Stomach Loſt.</head>
               <p>For to excite him to a Stomach, when he has loſt his Taſte, by great wearineſs and heat, rub his Tongue and the Pallate of his Mouth with Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar and Salt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>48.</hi> Horſe-leech, ſwallowed down.</head>
               <p>In caſe he has ſwallowed down an Horſe-leech in drinking, which hangs
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:37973:56"/>
yet in his Throat, then let him lie down, and pour into his Mouth warm Oyl; but if it is ſunk down in his Stomach, then give him ſome Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar through a Horn.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>49.</hi> Venemous Grubs ſwallowed.</head>
               <p>If the Oxen, Kine or Horſes, feeding in the Paſture, have ſwallowed down little Grubs, which lie under the Herbs, and are called by the Latins <hi>Bupreſtis,</hi> of which they ſometimes ſwell up, burſt and die, then the Oxe-keeper muſt let them preſently drink Cows-milk, or a Decoctum of dry Figs, or of Dates boiled in Wine; and give them ſharp and ſtrong Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>50.</hi> Swelling and puffing up.</head>
               <p>The Oxen ſwell and blow up when they have eaten too much Graſs, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when the Dew lies thereupon; then you muſt take a Horn which is bored through both ſides, annoint it with common Oyl, and put it three or four fingers deep into his Fundament,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:37973:57"/>
and next lead him backwards and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, until he farteth, leaving the Horn in his Fundament; and rub his Belly with a flat piece of Wood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>51.</hi> Pain of the Belly.</head>
               <p>Againſt Pain of the Belly, give them Tracle or Mithridate, to be drunk in Wine, and the next day after let him blood under the Tongue and Noſtrils, or give him a Decoctum of Camomil and Rue pounded ſmall, letting them ſtand and reſt, at leaſt for the ſpace of ſeven or eight days; or take Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine four Ounces, mingled with a little Salt, which is an excellent Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in this Sickneſs, letting the Beaſt ſwallow it down in the form of a Bolus, Pills or Potions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>52.</hi> Cholick.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Griping or ſtinging of the Guts (Collick) and rumbling of the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which is known when he ſighs and ſtretcheth his Neck, Legs, or Belly, or that he lieth down and riſes often again, and cannot ſtay in one place;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:37973:57"/>
this evil is occaſioned by wearineſs, more in the Lent than in any other ſeaſon: in this Sickneſs you muſt let him walk, being covered with a Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Cloth, and rub him in the Mouth with Garlick or bruiſed Onion, and let him ſwallow down the ſame either with a pint of Wine, or alone; ſome add thereunto Oyl of Mace, and give him Allum and Red Cabidge, being ſoaked in Wine with Mirrh, and take away the Fleſh round about the Claws of the Feet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and prick him in the Tail, that he bleedeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>53.</hi> Opilation or Obſtruction.</head>
               <p>In caſe he is opilated or obſtructed, then to open him the Belly and the hinder parts, which are obſtructed, you muſt give him to drink in the morning two ounces of powdered Alloes with luke-warm Water; or take — Hiera two ounces, Alloes one ounce mingled: Or elſe you may, as a very excellent Remedy, give the ſick Beaſt many times the remainder of Olives, out of which the Oyl is preſs'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="subsection">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:37973:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>54.</hi> Looſeneſs of Bloody-Flux.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Looſeneſs which he gets by the eating of ſome Herbs, or other like things, which are hard to digeſt; you muſt keep him at firſt two or three days from Graſs; and in the mean time lay before him the Bliſters of Wild-Olive-trees, Horſe-tail, Way-hroad, or Plantain, and ſometimes the Berries of Night-ſhade; in the mean time you muſt not give him much to drink, and for the moſt part no drink at all; keeping him ſome days from Eating any other thing, but the Leaves of Young Orega and Purſly, and let him not drink more than three Bowls of Water a day, wherein young Sprouts of Laurel Leaves have been ſoaked. But if a greater Looſeneſs ſeizes upon him, even to the Bloody-Flux, then keep him four or five days without Meat and Drink; and give him Raiſon-Kernels ſoaked in red Wine, or Gall-nuts and Mirtle-berries, ſoaked with old Cheeſe in thick Wine. But the moſt excellent Remedy is to burn him in the midſt of his Fore-head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="subsection">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:37973:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>55.</hi> Spoil'd Arſe-gut.</head>
               <p>If the Arſe Gut be ſpoiled, take three ounces of Turpentine, and let it be put into his Fundament by a little Boy, who has a thin and long Arm; and let him be well cleanſed within. This you muſt continue five or ſix days; Hogs-ſuet is alſo good inſtead of Turpentine, for to annoint or to ſmear him therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>56.</hi> Paia of the Loins.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Pain of the Loins, which many times troubles the Oxen, make this following Pap: Take Flower of — Cole-worts-ſeed, of each three handfuls; bruiſe it together, and mingle it with cold Water to a Pap, and then put it upon the place where the Pain is: You may alſo take <hi>Cypreſs</hi> Bliſters without Stalks, three handfuls; and proceed therewith as before, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereto in the bruiſing of it, ſtrong Vinegar; or if there is any hardneſs by, take Roſin, or that which is harder, <hi>Grecian</hi> Pitch <hi>(Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoniae</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:37973:59"/>
three ounces; let it melt by the heat of the Fire, and when it is well hot, then add thereto Barley of Meal a convenient quantity; let it boil together to a Poltis, and lay it well warm upon the Rump, unto the Reins or the (Loins.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>57.</hi> Pains of the Reins Inflamation.</head>
               <p>You may perceive that the Oxe has pain in his Reins, when in Kacking or doing his Eaſement from behind, he cannot ſet his Feet on thoſe parts according to his will, but ſtumbleth aſide; when he does not lift up his Tail but lets it hang, when his Piſs ſtinks much, and all the Courſe is ſtopt and interrupted behind. If he has an Inflamation and Piſſes as red as Blood, when it continues and increaſes, then there is little Remedy to be had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; yet if it is but coloured a little reddiſh, then there is ſome hope of recovery; in this Sickneſs you ſhall let him blood out of the hinder Veins, or Mother-vein, which you find a long the ſide about the Reins. For his dirnking give him the Juice of Garlick
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:37973:59"/>
with luke-warm Water, or elſe with his own Piſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>58.</hi> Inflamation of the Brawns or Muſcle.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Inflamation of the Brawns, as well inwardly as outwardly, which proceed from the Rump and Loins, by falling upon hard and Stony places, and getting Bruiſes: Let the Oxe which is fallen, not go far from his place, as ſoon as he is come into the Stable; and waſh the parts affected with cold Water, next uſe an Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Sear-cloths, made of Oyl and Wax, which muſt not be too hot. The tokens of this Diſtemper are, that the Loins (the Reins) grow hard outwardly; the Stones leſſen and go in ſo that you can but ſee them very little, that he cannot well move his Thigh, and that he can hardly riſe when he lieth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>59.</hi> Piſſing of Blood.</head>
               <p>The Oxe Piſſeth Blood when he is over-heated or too cold, or becauſe he has eaten bad Herbs during the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:37973:60"/>
Summer, eſpecially when the Dew cleaves yet thereon: The cure againſt this is, that you give him neither Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor any other Liquor, but that you give him a potion made of theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Ingredients: Take Sea-Oinion, Hemp ſeed, of each three ounces bruiſed together, and add thereto Treacle one ounce, being all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther boiled in two pints of White Wine; at laſt adding thereunto Saffron two ounces to a potion, and this pour into the Mouth of the Oxe; Or give him againſt Piſſing of Blood the Juice of Lambs Tongue with good Oyl, next take the Powder of Wild-Gourds (Coloquints) and Wine-ſtone, mingled in Red Wine, and the White of Eggs, pouring the ſame into him through an Horn. And if you do not ſtop the Piſſing of Blood, then he will die thereof within four and twenty hours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>60.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nableneſs of Piſſing.</head>
               <p>In caſe he can hardly Piſs, then you ſhall let him Blood on the Vein of the Bladder, and next give him a draught of Honey, Oyl, and White Wine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:37973:60"/>
boiled together; and this you muſt continue three mornings one after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>61.</hi> Stone of the Bladder.</head>
               <p>If he has the Stone of the Bladder, take Sea-fenicle two ounces, Cloves a quarter of an ounce, Pepper one ounce and a half, being altogether bruiſed and mingled with lukewarm Water to a Potion. But if the Stone, when this is continued ſome days, doth not fall out, then it muſt be cut out.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>62.</hi> Stone in the Yard.</head>
               <p>In caſe he has the Stone in the Yard, then throw the Oxe down im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, hold the Yard with Tongs a little higher than where the Stone lies, open the Yard on the ſide and take out the Stone; next heal the Wound again with Turpentine, waſht four times in Horſe-tail-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="subsection">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:37973:61"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>63.</hi> Hardened Yard.</head>
               <p>If the Yard be hardened, then ſmear it twice a day with an Ointment of bruiſed White Mallow-roots and freſh Butter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>64.</hi> Swollen Cods.</head>
               <p>If his Cods are ſwollen, by what cauſe ſoever it be, then annoint them in the morning and at night with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalted Hogs-ſuet, or foment them with ſtrong Vinegar, in which fine Chalk and Oxen-dung have been ſoaked<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They hold it for a Natural Remedy, that the Gall of a Dog healeth the Swollen Cods of an Oxe, being often annointed therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>65.</hi> Limping or Halting.</head>
               <p>If he Limps and Halts, becauſe of Cold, which he has ſuffered on the Feet, then waſh them with his Piſs, which is made warm; but if it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the ſuperfluity of Blood, which in the bending of the Joynts is
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:37973:61"/>
ſunk upon the Feet, then you muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide (or reſolve it) by rubbing or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing, and by drawing Blood by cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping; but if upon this it will not go away, you muſt cleave the Claw of the Foot at the end unto the Fleſh: and thus let it run out: and bind the Joynts round about with a Leather-purſe, that no Matter may come thereunto until it is cured.</p>
               <p>In caſe he limps by having ſtrained a Vein, then you muſt annoint his Foot with Oyl and Salt; if it be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by a ſwelling of the Knee, then foment it with warm Vinegar, or with a Decoctum of Barley and Flux-ſeed: But howſoever it happens, you muſt burn it, and lay thereupon freſh But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, waſh'd in Water and Vinegar; and at laſt make an Ointment of Salt-butter and Goats ſuet or Greaſe. If it comes by a Splinter, or by a knock againſt a piece of Wood or Stone, then bathe the place with warm Piſs, and lay thereupon Oyl, old Greaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Tar melted together. Nothing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves him better from Limping, than to waſh his Feet with cold Water,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:37973:62"/>
when they are disjoyonted, and then to rub them with old Greaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>66.</hi> Leg-out of Joynt.</head>
               <p>If his Leg is out of Joynt or wrinched, put it in again, and when you have ſmeared it with Hogs-greaſe, bind it faſt with Straw.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>67.</hi> Broken Legs.</head>
               <p>For to put it in again (if broken) you muſt draw with Cords the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt parts of the ſame on both ſides perpendicularly, that ſo the disjoynted Leg may be again put together and joyned as before; this being done; you muſt untie the Cords, and bind round about it Tow of Flax, that is made wet in a mixt on of the White of Eggs, Bolus Armenius, and Sanguis Draconis; next bind it ſo faſt, that it may be joyned together again: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the binding you muſt lay Tow of Flax made wet in Wine, for to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and corroborate the Sinews; at laſt, that the uppermoſt and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt parts of the broken Leg may not
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:37973:62"/>
be hardened, or get any ill faſhion or form, as well by the binding up of the Wound, as by the Chop or Cleft of the Leg; you muſt annoint both parts with the following Ointment, <hi>viz.</hi> But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Oyl, Turpentine, of each one ounce mingled to an Ointment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>68.</hi> Biting of Serpents.</head>
               <p>In caſe he has been bit by an Earth-ſpider, Serpent or by a mad Dog, then ſmear the Wound with Scorpion-Oyl, or Sope, which has lain in Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and waſh him with a Decoctum of great Burs, or with old Pickle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>70.</hi> Stinging of Horſe-flies or Hornets.</head>
               <p>Againſt the ſtinging of Horſe-flies and Waſps, rub him with Lead-Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Salve (Cerays) being ſoaked in Water, and moiſten the place where he feeds, to drive away the Horſe-flies, with a Decoctum of Wormwood, chare him with the ſame Decoctum; but if he is ſtung, then cleanſe the place with his own ſpit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="subsection">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:37973:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>70.</hi> Kibe on the Heel.</head>
               <p>If he gets a Kibe on the Heel by great Cold, and by having wrou<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in ſuch places as are full of Snow or Frozen, and ſometimes after the Thawing alſo, and becauſe that the Joynts of the Foot have not been well waſh'd over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night with Piſs and bound up with Dung, then the Heel gets an Ulcer, and ſeems as it would go off, and leave its place; and then there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows an Inflamation, which after the Ulcer very much troubles the Oxe in going forth: Now you muſt chop ſmall that part with little Lancets, and kindle a ſmall Fire of Fewel upon the chopt part, and put thereupon a ſoft Roſe-ſalve, or a defenſive of Water Vinegar, being bound up and tied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with Straw. When the Cruſt (or the bad Fleſh) is fallen out, then you muſt ſtew the place warm with Vinegar and Piſs, and lay thereupon a Pap or Plaiſter of Melilot, or cold Hogs-ſuet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="subsection">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:37973:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>71.</hi> Swollen Foot.</head>
               <p>If his Foot is ſwollen, then make a Pap of Elder Bliſters and Hogs greaſe mixt together and boiled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>72.</hi> Crumpled or ſtiffned Foot.</head>
               <p>If his Foot is crumpled or ſtiffned, then take the Roots of white Poppeys &amp; Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows (together one pound) boil them in water, as much as is enough, pound them and ſtrain them through a Sive; add to this Hogs-Greaſe half a pound and ſtrong Wine three Bowls. Let it boil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, until the Greaſe is melted, adding thereto Flax-ſeed four ounces well broken and pounded, and let it boyl at laſt, until the Wine is ſodden away to a Pap, and put the one half part of this Pap upon the Foot, and let it lie thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for three days, and then the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der alſo three days together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="subsection">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:37973:64"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>73.</hi> Wrinched Foot.</head>
               <p>If he has wrinched the Foot, then boil Honey and Hogs-greaſe in White Wine; lay this Plaiſter upon the Foot, and let it lie thereupon for three days.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>74.</hi> Wounded Foot.</head>
               <p>In caſe he has wounded his Foot by a Thorn, Glaſs, or Nail, or any ſuch other ſharp thing, then cut the Claw off from the Foot, as near the Wound as it is poſſible; let drop there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in very hot Turpentine and Oyl, and then plaiſter the whole Foot with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and freſh Greaſe melted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>75.</hi> Claw of the Foot wounded.</head>
               <p>If the Claw of the Foot is wounded by a Stone or Iron, then cut it to the deepeſt part of the Wound with the Ciſſers of a Farrier, and let drop there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in very hot a Salve of old Hogs-greaſe and Bucks-rue, being melted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:37973:64"/>
and put thereinto Tents of Tow of Flax.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>76.</hi> Claw of the Foot ſcaled or broke.</head>
               <p>If the Claw of his Foot is ſcaled or broken, then take Honey, Turpentine. New Wax, of each one ounce to a Salve, and put that round about the Claw for fifteen days together, which time being expired, add to the former Salve theſe following Ingredients. Take Alloe, Hepaticum, Honey of Roſes, Buck Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, of each half an ounce to an Oin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and cover with this the whole Foot, after that you have fomented it with Wine, with which Honey has been mingled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>77.</hi> Looſe Claw.</head>
               <p>If the Claw of his Foot becomes looſe, then you muſt at firſt cure it with the aforeſaid Salve againſt Scaled Claws, <hi>Sect.</hi> 76. until it groweth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing faſt; next you muſt ſtew the whole Foot five or ſix days, every day three times with the following Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients: Take Honey, unquenched Lime,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:37973:65"/>
of each ſeven ounces, Vinegar or Wine a convenient quantity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>78.</hi> Foot-claw fallen off.</head>
               <p>If his Foot-claw is fallen of, then make a Salve of this following: Take Honey, Turpentine, New Wax, of each one Ounce, and annoint therewith the Nail of the Foot fifteen days, next waſh it with luke-warm Wine, which has been boiled with Honey, and put a Plaiſter thereupon made of theſe following things: Take Alloes, Allum bruiſed, Honey of Roſes, of each half an ounce, to a Plaiſter.</p>
               <p>There is alſo one Diſtemper more, which is incident to Oxen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not taken notice of in the Table or Cut, or Portraicture of a Cow; which is called, <hi>The Hip-gout,</hi> take Cow-dung, laid under Aſhes in Cabbidge or Vine-leaves, and made hot, and it will drive away the pain of the <hi>Hip-gout,</hi> being laid upon it in the form of a Plaiſter. If this be roaſted in Vinegar, it brings the bad Sores about the Chin and Throat to Diſtillation; and being fryed with Cammomile flowers, Melilots, and black Briers in a Pan, it drives away the Swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Privities.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:65"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:66"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Country mans Guide ſhewing the ſeverall places in the body of a ſheepe where diſeaſes vſually happen</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_diseases">
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:37973:66"/>
            <head>The TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. HEad-ach.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Giddineſs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Loſs of Cud.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Diſeaſes in the Eyes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Ague in Lambs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Ague in Sheep.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Rheum and Catarrhe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Diſeaſes of the Teeth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Apoſthumes or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Boils.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Boils or Scabs under the Chin of Lambs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Purſineſs or ſhort-winded.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Rot or Plague.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> St. <hi>Anthony</hi>'s Fire.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> Scab or Itch.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> Diſeaſes in the Lungs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> Cough.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> Swallowing of a Venemous Creature.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19.</hi> Swelling of the Belly.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20.</hi> Lame in the Clawes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21.</hi> Maggots, Lice, or Ticks.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22.</hi> Broken or bruiſed Joynts.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:37973:67"/>
            <head>Introduction.</head>
            <p>I Shall not particularize the many advantages which ariſe trom Sheep, as the Wooll, Fleſh, Pelt, Dung, and many others; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the firſt place, the Country-man ought to get a good Breeder, and to buy Sheep for his ſtore, that may be in all particulars anſwerable to his Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, which I need not here relate.</p>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Marks of a good Yew.</head>
               <p>The beſt Yews have generally a great Body, a long Neck, long Wooll, oright and ſhining like Silk, having a great Belly, and covered with Wooll<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and having great Paps, great Eyes with long Legs, and a long Tail.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Marks of a good Ram.</head>
               <p>The beſt ſort of Rams are high and long of Body, great Belly, well covered with Wooll, long and thick Tail, the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:37973:67"/>
Fore-head broad and thick with Hair, the Eyes black, covered round about with much Wooll, great Cods, broad Loins, great Ears, covered with Wooll; the whole Fleece of one Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, well Horned; the Tongue and the Pallate all White; for if the Tongue or undermoſt part of the Tongue ſhould be black or ſpeckled, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his Body is all White, yet the Colour of the Lambs which he produces will be Speckled, Gray, or Black, and therefore leſs eſteemed for profit: It is better that the Ram hath Horns than not, for the Ram that hath no Horns, is as a Man diſarmed, and is not ſo valiant to fight, nor ſo hot after the Yew.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>When a Yew ought to be covered.</head>
               <p>The Yew ought to be covered when ſhe is two years old, and ſhe will bring forth good Lambs until ſhe is ſeven; but a Yew that is covered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe is two years old bringeth forth weak Fruit; but if it happen that a Yew is with Lamb before ſhe be two years, then you ought to ſell
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:37973:68"/>
the Lamb; and the moſt convenient time to diſpoſe of it is in the Month of <hi>October,</hi> that the Yew (which bears five months) may bring forth her Lamb in the Spring or Lent, at which time ſhe will find Graſs ſufficient to nouriſ her Lambs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Salt Water to drink.</head>
               <p>Farther, you muſt give the Yews ſome few days before they be covered by the Ram, Salt Water to drink, and they will the better keep their Seed, and the Ram ſhall grow the more fiery and vehement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>The way to have ſuch Lambs as you pleaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </head>
               <p>If you would have your Yews bring forth Ram-Lambs, then you muſt put the Ram to the Yew in dry Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and obſerve to drive the Yew towards the blowing of the North Wind, that when they are feeding toward the North, they may take Ram; but if you will have Yew-Lambs, then you muſt let them feed towards the South Wind, and let them be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:37973:68"/>
               <head>To know what coloured Lambs a Yew will bring forth.</head>
               <p>When the Yew is big, in caſe her Tongue is black, its a ſign that ſhe will bring forth a black Lamb; and if her Tongue be white, ſhe will bring forth a white Lamb; but if the Tongue be ſpeckled, then ſhe will bring forth a ſpeckled Lamb.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Of Sickneſs in Sheep.</head>
               <p>The Sheep are inclined to many Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, as Scabs or Scurveyneſs, Cough, and the Red Water, which proceed from an exceeding Pain in the Head, and alſo the Plague: The three laſt Diſtempers are incurable; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, as if any Sheep be ſick with either of the ſaid three Diſtempers, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> occaſions infections in the reſt, thereof many of them die; all ſuch ſckneſſes are occaſioned by eating of bad Herbs, or by drinking of bad Water or ſtanding Puddles or Pools in the Fields; or becauſe the places
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:37973:69"/>
which they feed on, are wet and moiſt by frequent Showers and bad Weather; by which means they undoubtedly fall ſick in ſix weeks time.</p>
               <p>Here follows an account of all the Diſtempers incident to Sheep.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> The Head-ach.</head>
               <p>If your Sheep are troubled with the Head-ach and Staggers, which is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by Surfeits, the beſt Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is, to take Aſafettida, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it in a ſpoonful of White Wine, or bruiſe the Juice out of Sage and give it to the Sheep.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Giddineſs.</head>
               <p>Giddineſs in the Head befalls Sheep moſt commonly in the Dog-days, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, as it makes them turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout and leap; and in caſe you touch their Fore-head or Feet, you will find that they burn exceedingly. Againſt this Sickneſs you muſt let them blood in the middle of the Noſe with a piece of Horn made ſharp for that purpoſe, thruſt up as high as you can
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:37973:69"/>
poſſible; which will cauſe the Sheep preſently to fall into a ſound, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately they will come again to themſelves. This being applied, they will either be immediately well of this Diſtemper, or die very ſpeedily; yet more do recover than die. Some Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds have tried the letting of Blood in the Temples of the Head, loſing their Blood by little and little, which hath proved very ſucceſsful afterward, giving them a ſpoonful of Brandy mixt with Mithridate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Loſs of Cud.</head>
               <p>Take Leaven and Salt, and mix them with Clay, and the Piſs of a luſty young Man, and let him ſwallow it, and that will recover him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Diſeaſes in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Make an Eye-water of <hi>Eve</hi> Eye-bright and Horſe-leech, and waſh their Eyes therewith, or beat Wormwood with the Milk of a Yew, and mix it with Roſe-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="subsection">
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:37973:70"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Ague in Lambs.</head>
               <p>If a young Lamb have an Ague, or other Sickneſs, then you muſt give it to drink the Milk of its Dam, mingled with as much water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Ague in Sheep.</head>
               <p>When Sheep have an Ague, you muſt blood them on the Heels, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Claws of the Feet, or on the Ear, and keep them a good while from Water: the beſt remedy for to cure them of the Ague, is to boil in Spring Water and Wine, the <hi>Stomach</hi> of a Ram, and give the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered Sheep the Broth to drink.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Rheum or Catarrhe.</head>
               <p>The Sheep gets Humours and Rheums in the Dog days, by the great Heat of the Sun; for prevention of which, the Shepherd in ſuch hot ſeaſons ought to drive his Flock in the Fore-noon towards the Weſt, and in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon towards the Eaſt; for it is a
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:37973:70"/>
great matter that the Heads of the Sheep, as they'r feeding, be turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sun; which in the beginning of the Dog-days is often times the cauſe of this Diſtemper<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Diſeaſes in the Teeth.</head>
               <p>For Diſeaſes in the Teeth, let the Sheep blood in the Gum, or Vein of the upper Lip, and rub his Teeth with old Leaven and Sage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Apoſthumes or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers.</head>
               <p>In caſe the Sheep hath any Matter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Apoſthume or Ulcer, then you muſt prick it with a Lance, and put into the Wound Salt burnt in a Fire-ſhovel, rubbed ſmall and mingled with melted Pitch.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Boils.</head>
               <p>You may cure Boils with Allum, Sulphur, Vinegar, and Brimſtone, mixt together; or with burnt Gall-nuts, being mixt with Wine and laid upon the Sore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="subsection">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:37973:71"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Boils or Scabs under the Skin of Lambs.</head>
               <p>The Lamb many times gets Scabs under the Chin, by eating of Herbs when the Dew lies upon them; the Remedy againſt which is to take Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop and Salt, of each an ounce, well bruiſed together, and with this you muſt annoint the Pallate of the Mouth and Tongue; then waſh the Boil with Vinegar, and afterwards chafe it with Tar and Greaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Purſineſs or ſhort-winded.</head>
               <p>The Rheum or Catarrhe of the Sheep, as well as of the Horſe, ſticks ſo faſt to the Lungs that it cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved with Bleeding, nor with a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and if this Sickneſs continue, the beſt Remedy is, that the Sheep be kept without Food for a day or two; likewiſe it is convenient that whatever Hay or Fodder hath been eaten among, the Sheep, while one that hath been ſick hath been amongſt them, the Oughts thereof be taken
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:37973:71"/>
clean away; for ſuch Sheep get the ſame ſickneſs, by eating after them that are ſick. Some ſay that for this ſickneſs it is good to hang about the Neck of the Sheep a living Toad, put in a little bag of Linnen; and to let it hang nine days: Others ſay that it is good to bruiſe <hi>Lock and Noble</hi> Sage together, and make a Potion thereof with very ſtrong Vinegar: Others pour in their Mouths a ſpoonful of Brandy with Mithridate; but there is but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle help for this Diſtemper, for they often die after ſeveral Medicines have been given to them; becauſe the Lungs are quite dried up with a continual Coughing: There is no better Remedy againſt this Diſtemper than for to throw them upon their Backs in a ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unclean Gutter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Rot or Plague.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Plague there is no other Remedy for Beaſt than for Man; but for to keep them from this Diſtemper, the beſt way is, often to give them Melilot, Scitiſers, Wild Polly, or Wild Balſom.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:37973:72"/>But to prevent the Rot in thoſe Sheep that are not tainted by that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, you muſt give them Salt mingled with Brimſtone in a Fire-ſhovel, which will purge them and preſerve them from this Contagion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="subsection">
               <head>14. <hi>St.</hi> Anthony<hi>'s Fire.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Fire of St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> is by the Shepherd called <hi>Wild-fire,</hi> very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to cure, and there is no other Remedy to uſe in this Diſtemper than to bathe the Sheep with She-Goats-milk; but my Advice is to ſeparate the firſt Sheep that hath this Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per from the Flock, that the reſt be not infected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>15.</hi> Scab or Itch.</head>
               <p>Againſt Scabbineſs or Scurveyneſs in Sheep, you muſt make a Salve of theſe following Ingredients: Take Brimſtone, Cyprus Roots, of each three ounces, which you muſt incorporate with Camphire and White Roſin, Wax a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient quantity; after that you have annointed the ſcabby or ſcurvey Sheep,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:37973:72"/>
three nights one after another, then waſh it with Lie, Sea-water, or Pickel, and the Sheep will be well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>16.</hi> Diſeaſes in the Lungs.</head>
               <p>If your Sheep be diſtempered in the Lungs, you muſt give him Colts-foot, Sage, and Purſland, mixed with Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theglin, or a ſpoonful or two of Mithridate in White Wine, or a head of Garlick mixt with Vinegar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>17.</hi> Cough.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Cough, you muſt give the Sheep to drink in the morning out of a little Horn, Oyl of ſweet Almonds, mixt with White VVine, being made luke-warm; alſo let the Sheep eat the Herb Colts-foot, if the Cough come in the ſpring; but if it be in any other ſeaſon, then you may give him ſome bruiſed Fenugrick, with ſome Cummin-ſeed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>18.</hi> Swallowing of a Venemous Creature.</head>
               <p>In caſe the Sheep ſwallow down an
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:37973:73"/>
Horſe-leech, or any other Venemous Creature, you muſt pour into his Throat ſtrong Vinegar warm'd, or Oyl.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>19.</hi> Swelling of the Belly.</head>
               <p>There is an Herb which is called a Thouſand Buttons, and the Herb Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory is very unwholeſome for Sheep, whereof if they eat, the whole Belly ſwells up, voiding a thick and ſtinking humour; then the beſt Remedy is to let them blood preſently under the Tail, near the Buttock, or on the Vein of the uppermoſt Lip.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>20.</hi> Lame in the Claws.</head>
               <p>In caſe the Sheep becomes Lame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe its Claws are grown weak, by having ſtood too long in his own Dung, and that it can't go, then you muſt cut off the end of the Nail affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or Claw of the Foot affected, and lay thereupon unſlacked Lime with a Cloth, leaving it but one day there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, and the next day lay <hi>Spaniſh
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:37973:73"/>
Green</hi> thereupon; laying it on by turns, until the Claw be healed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>21.</hi> Maggots, Lice, or Ticks.</head>
               <p>The ſame Remedy is good alſo for a Sheep that hath Maggots, Lice, or Ticks, as for a Sheep that hath the Scab or Itch, as you will find in the 15th Receipt for Sheep.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>22.</hi> Broken or Bruiſed Joynts.</head>
               <p>For Broken or Bruiſed Joynts, give the Sheep a Drink made of Bettony, Mugwort, and Multowes, of each a ſpoonful of the Juice, and annoint the Wound with black Sope, or mix Bird-lime with Tallow, and lay a hot Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter on the Wound.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_diseases">
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:37973:74"/>
            <head>The Country-mans Guid, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Direction for the Breed, Ordering, and Curing of all Diſtempers in Swine.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> HEad-ach or Sleepy-evil.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The Pox in Swine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Eating of Yarro.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Diſeaſes in the Eyes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Ague or Feaver.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Meaſles prevented.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Rheum or Catarrhe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> To prevent Vomiting.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Meaſles Cured.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Plague, or Diſeaſes in the Milt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Swelling in the Neck or Throat.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Apoſthumes or Swellings in the Throat.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Impoſthumes in the Body.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Diſeaſes in the Gall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> To kill Lice or Ticks.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> Thirſt prevented.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> To prevent Greedineſs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> For a great Cough or Cold.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19.</hi> Belly-Ach.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20.</hi> Lameneſs in the Foot.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21.</hi> Flux in Swine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22.</hi> Broken Legs or Joynts.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:74"/>
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:37973:75"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:75"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e Country mans Guide ſhewing the ſeverall places in the body of a Hog where diſeaſes vſually happen</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:76"/>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:37973:76"/>
            <head>Introduction.</head>
            <p>HAving before treated of the more Tamer ſort of Cattle, I ſhall now likewiſe treat of Swine, as being the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly, and the moſt hurtful in his kind, of any common Beaſt; but neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs very much deſired, becauſe it yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſweet Fleſh, whilſt they are young, and for his Bacon, when ſalted; as being the moſt ſerviceable: and not to omit the advantage of the Hide, Briſtles, and Greaſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is requiſite in all thoſe places where there is a great number of Swine kept, that there is a Man al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for no other Imployment then to keep the Swine, and carefully to preſerve them from danger that may befall them; or that they may not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure the Corn-fields, in which they are kept, and to take care of the weaned Piggs.</p>
            <p>The Husbandman muſt take care for
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:37973:77"/>
ſuch Food that is convenient for Swine, as Acrons, Nuts, Haws, and all ſuch as the Swine uſually eat. 'Tis good that you provide entertainment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Hogs come out of the Field, at the uſual time; for by ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you ſhall make them return to their Owner without running aſtray: which certainly you may do by a due providing of Meat for them at a ſet time.</p>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Marks of a good Bore.</head>
               <p>The Bore is eſteemed the beſt that is ſhort and broad, his Mouth drawing upwards and long, having a broad and thick Breaſt, broad Shoulders, ſhort and great Thighs, white of Colour, and in a word the broadeſt and moſt four ſquare, and of a full Body, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thick Briſtles on his Back, is the beſt Bore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Marks of a good Sow.</head>
               <p>The beſt Sows are ſuch as are longeſt of Body, with a hanging Belly of broad Buttocks and long Ribs, of a
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:37973:77"/>
little Head and ſhort Legs, white Hair.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>The time of a Sow being covered.</head>
               <p>Let not the Sow be covered before ſhe is above one year old, and the Bore that covereth her muſt be three or four years old; but after the fifth year you muſt geld him for to feed him for Brawn or Bacon. The beſt time to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a Sow is, from the Increaſe until the Full Moon; after the Full Moon it is not good. The beſt time in the year is to let the Sow take the Bore at <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlemaſs,</hi> that the Piggs may be ſtrong in the Harveſt time: The Winter Piggs are more hard to bring up, and not ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural as the others that are Pigg'd in Summer. A Sow may rear Eighteen Piggs if ſhe hath ſo many Paps.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>The beſt time to Geld Pigs, and to Splay the Sow.</head>
               <p>THe beſt time to geld, is when they are a Year old, and not older; when the Moon is in the Decreaſe, in the beginning of Spring, or in the Fall of
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:37973:78"/>
the Leaf, when its moderate Weather<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in caſe you cut them when they are little, I confeſs that the Bacon will be the ſweeter, but they will not make ſo large Swine; therefore you may uſe your diſcretion to cut them from Four to Six Month's, or to a Year.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>To make a Hog Fat.</head>
               <p>THe Hogs that you intend to Fatten for Bacon, ought always to be ſet up in a particular Stye, and the darker the Stye is, the better, provided there be but ſo much light as to ſee to give them meat; there needs not ſo much care of them as other Swine; but that their Stye be made clean, and that they have food at all times lying before them in their Troughs: They are not to be brought from one place to another, though they have no Motion, and not able to move themſelves. Their is divers manner of Food, according to the Cuſtom of the Countrey, yet the beſt and moſt ſubſtantial Feeding is of dry Peaſe and Beans, though its common in many incloſed Countreys to Feed a Swine exceeding full with Whay, and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:37973:78"/>
many practiſe that way, only giving them a Buſhel of Peaſe or Beans to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>en the Fat. In ſome Countreys they <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eed after other manner, which for brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y ſake I ſhall omit; knowing that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Country-man knoweth what way is beſt for is ends in that matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Sickneſs in Swine.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THey are alſo ſubject to many Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, and you may know that the Hog is ſick, when he lets hang his Ears, and that he is duller and heavier than he is wont to be, having little or no Stomack to his Meat; but the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain way, if none of theſe Symptoms ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, is to draw out of his back a handfull of Briſtles againſt the growth of the Hair, and in caſe that the Root of the Briſtles be white and clean, then the Hog is ſound and in good health: but if that they are bloody, or ſpotted, then he his ſick.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Head-ach, or Sleepy-Evil.</head>
               <p>For the Head-ach or Sleepy-evil, you ſhall
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:37973:79"/>
let the Swine blood under the Tongue, and give him Lettice Leaves to eat, or give them Water wherein Stone Cropel is ſteeped.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The Pox in Swine.</head>
               <p>The Pox is cured by giving him Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridate in Metheglin, or by drinking the warm Blood of a Lamb; or give him Common Oyl with Pepper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Eating of Yarro.</head>
               <p>In caſe the Swine hath eaten mad Chervile, Millfoile, or Yarro, called in <hi>Latin, Cheliophilon</hi>; then give him to drink a good quantity of Water where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Wild Cowcombers are boyled, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſtand before you give it him till 'tis but luke-warm; and that will vomit him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Diſeaſes in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Are Cured with the Juice of Bittany, or Horſe Leeke, or the Blades of Sallen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine beaten in a Morter, and laid upon the Eyes, mixt with Wine or the Powder
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:37973:79"/>
of Sepia blown into the eyes, or dry the Yolk of an Egg to powder, and blow it into the Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Ague or Feaver.</head>
               <p>Againſt the Ague, let the Hog blood in the Tail.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Meaſles prevented.</head>
               <p>The Hog is eſpecially ſubject to Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſles, it proceeds from Gluttony and over-eating; now there is three eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial ſigns of Meaſles, <hi>viz.</hi> If you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behold under his tongue ſmall black Bliſters, or that he cannot ſtand on his hinder legs, or that his Briſtles be bloody, as aforeſaid; this diſtemper is prevented by carefulneſs in the feeding, and that they go into the Field, in the open Air.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Rheum or Catarrhe.</head>
               <p>Rheum or Catarrhe are cured by Bons Brimſtone in a Fire-ſhovel, and let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſmoke up the Noſe, or rub the Swines Mouth with Garlick bruiſed
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:37973:80"/>
with Salt or bruiſed Laurel Leaves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>8.</hi> To prevent Vomiting.</head>
               <p>You ſhall let him ſtand faſting, ſet up in ſome obſcure place one day and night, that he may conſume the ſuperfluous Moiſture, and recover again to his former Appetite: Some have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Medicines, but the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienc'd thing this way is the beſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Meaſles Cured.</head>
               <p>Let the Hogs that are Meaſled, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wallow in a Bath, in Sea-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and for lack of Sea-water let the Owner make a Bath of Water well boiled and ſalted; and put it into a convenient place where the Hog may wallow therein; and mingle with his meat bruiſed Garlick, and give him the Rhine of Grapes or Goosberries, or give him Roles of Leaven with his Meat.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="subsection">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:37973:80"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Plague or Diſeaſe in the Milt.</head>
               <p>Swine are much inclined to the Plague and ſwelling of the Milt, which very often ſeizeth ſuch unclean Bodies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they eat foul and unclean Meats. The beſt Cure for this Malady, is to give them Honey Combs, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever proceeds from Bees.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Swelling of the Neck.</head>
               <p>Againſt Rheum or Swellings in the Neck, the beſt Remedy is to let the Swine blood under the Tongue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Apoſthume or Swelling in the Throat.</head>
               <p>Againſt Apoſthumes or Swelling of the Throat, mix the fine Flower of Wheat with Salt, and rub the Sore there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Impoſthumes in the Body.</head>
               <p>See the 12 <hi>Chap.</hi> of the Swine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="subsection">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:37973:81"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Diſeaſes of the Gall.</head>
               <p>The over-flowing of the Gall, in many times a Diſeaſe that befalls Swine: the beſt Remedy is to give them Saffron mixt with Metheglin, or Honey and White Wine; let the Swine drink half a pint.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>15.</hi> To kill Lice or Ticks.</head>
               <p>Take Linſeed Oyl and Salt, mix them together, and rub the Swine all over therewith, and it will free him from Vermin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>16.</hi> To prevent Thirſt.</head>
               <p>Swine are ſubject to a Thirſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome have died, which moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently happen in the Dog-days: the beſt that you can do for them, is to drive them to ſome ſweet River, where they may lie down and bathe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="subsection">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:37973:81"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>17.</hi> A great Cough or Cold.</head>
               <p>The Cough in Swine is cured by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them Colts-foot and Lingwort boiled in Metheglin, or take half a pound of Honey, and a quarter of a pound of Liquoriſh, boil them in a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon of Water till half be conſumed, and let the Swine drink it luke-warm, or give the Swine Gum Dragon and ſweet Oyl.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>18.</hi> Belly-ach.</head>
               <p>The Belly-ach is cured by giving the Swine Black Pepper boiled in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>heglin, or take three ſpoonfuls of Fennile-ſeed mixt with White Wine, and give it the ſick Swine, letting him ſwill.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>19.</hi> Lameneſs.</head>
               <p>If the Swine be Lame, ſo that it be ulcerated, then drop into Wine Turpentine and Oyl very hot, or take Honey and freſh Greaſe, and ſpread them on a Plaiſter of Leather, and lay it on the Wound.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="subsection">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:37973:82"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>21.</hi> Flux.</head>
               <p>For the Flux or Looſeneſs in Swine, give them to drink Vinegar and Milk mixed together, and give them to eat <hi>Gall Nuts</hi> pounded and mixed with Starch and Wine Vinegar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>22.</hi> Broken Legs or Joynts.</head>
               <p>To cure Broken Legs or Joynts, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the place with Sheep-ſuet, and bind up the Broken Legs or Joynts with Straw; or annoint it with the following Ointment, ſweet Butter, Oyl, Turpentine, of each an ounce, mix them to an Ointment.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index_of_diseases">
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:82"/>
            <head>An Alphabetical TABLE of the Diſeaſes in Horſes, and their Cure.</head>
            <div n="A" type="subsection">
               <head>A</head>
               <list>
                  <item>AGue of a Horſe <hi>15</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Head-ach <hi>17</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Apoſthumes <hi>33</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Tooth-ach. <hi>23</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ague <hi>35</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="B" type="subsection">
               <head>B</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Belly-ach <hi>38</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Bloody Flux <hi>43</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Biting of the Spider Mouſe. <hi>47</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Bruiſed Back <hi>49</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Back galled. <hi>50</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Biting of Flies <hi>51</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Broken Loins <hi>51</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Biting of a Mad Dog <hi>58</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Biting of a Water-ſnake <hi>59</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="C" type="subsection">
               <head>C.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Colts of what Colour you will <hi>9</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Coldneſs or Chilneſs <hi>18</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Catarrhe <hi>19</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Canker <hi>23</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Cough <hi>32</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Chollick <hi>37</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Chaps in the Feet <hi>49</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Chaps between the Joynts and Legs <hi>56</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="D" type="subsection">
               <pb facs="tcp:37973:83"/>
               <head>D</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Difference in Breeding Mares and Stone-Horſes <hi>6</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Difficulty in making Water</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="E" type="subsection">
               <head>E</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Pain in the Eyes <hi>21</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Web in the Eyes <hi>20</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Watering Eyes <hi>21</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Pin in the Eyes <hi>20</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Wounded Eyes <hi>22</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Eye Scars <hi>22</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="F" type="subsection">
               <head>F</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Feaver <hi>24</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Faintneſs <hi>34</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fundament fallen <hi>41</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Flux <hi>42</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Flies droven away <hi>51</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Faſhions <hi>46</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fiſtula's <hi>60</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fidge <hi>60</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Hound-red <hi>61</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="G" type="subsection">
               <head>G</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Glanders <hi>19</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Griping of the Guts <hi>37</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="H" type="subsection">
               <head>H</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Over-heated <hi>35</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Hen Dung ſwallowed <hi>37</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="I" type="subsection">
               <head>I</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Jaundice <hi>43</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="K" type="subsection">
               <pb facs="tcp:37973:83"/>
               <head>K</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Knees ſwollen <hi>55</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Knees wounded <hi>55</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Knees over-grown <hi>55</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Kibe Heels <hi>63</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="L" type="subsection">
               <head>L</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Lean Horſe made Fat</item>
                  <item>Diſeaſe in the Lungs <hi>28</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Looſeneſs <hi>42</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Leproſie <hi>56</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lame <hi>63</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="M" type="subsection">
               <head>M</head>
               <list>
                  <item>To manage a Horſe <hi>4</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Head-ſtrong <hi>4</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>When a Mare hath a deſire to go to Horſe <hi>8</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Marks of a good Colt <hi>11</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Madneſs <hi>11</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mad Love <hi>18</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mangy <hi>52</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mallender <hi>57</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="N" type="subsection">
               <head>N</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Diſtemper in the Neck <hi>27</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Galled Neck <hi>28</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Crick in the Neck <hi>28</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="O" type="subsection">
               <head>O</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Ordering of Horſes <hi>1</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Over-heated <hi>1</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ordering a Mare that hath a Fole <hi>11</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:37973:84"/>Obſtructions <hi>39</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Opilations <hi>39</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Old Swellings <hi>49</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Over-growing of the Hooff <hi>60</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Over-ſtepping <hi>64</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="P" type="subsection">
               <head>P</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Want of Pallat <hi>24</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Pricked in Shooing <hi>61</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="R" type="subsection">
               <head>R</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Rheum <hi>19</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Running of the Noſe <hi>19</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Rupture prevented <hi>46</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Rupture cured <hi>47</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ring Bone <hi>59</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="S" type="subsection">
               <head>S</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Staggers <hi>17</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Swelling of the Throat <hi>26</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Squincy <hi>26</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Struma <hi>27</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Strangling <hi>27</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Stomach loſt <hi>36</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Stoppage of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine <hi>44</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Strangury <hi>45</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Swelling of the Cods <hi>48</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Swelling of the Flanks <hi>41</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Scabby <hi>52</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sinew-ſtruck <hi>53</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>String-halt <hi>57</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Spavin <hi>58</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:37973:84"/>Sirachis</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="T" type="subsection">
               <head>T</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The time that a Mare may be covered <hi>7, 8, 10</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="V" type="subsection">
               <head>V</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer <hi>33</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Venemous Creature ſwallowed <hi>36</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="U" type="subsection">
               <head>U</head>
               <list>
                  <item>A flying Worm <hi>22</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Waxen Kernils <hi>27</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Wind ſhort <hi>29</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Worms <hi>41</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Woolfe <hi>46</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Warts on the Feet <hi>48</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Woolfe or Boil on the Foot <hi>63</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="Y" type="subsection">
               <head>Y</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The Yalloes <hi>43</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:85"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have only given you an Alphabetical <hi>Table</hi> of the Diſeaſes in that part which treats of <hi>Horſes,</hi> and the other part which treats of <hi>Cows, Sheep,</hi> and <hi>Hogs,</hi> hath a compleat <hi>Table</hi> fore-going the particular <hi>Medicines.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 16 <hi>line</hi> 10. <hi>r.</hi> much feeding, <hi>p.</hi> 31 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>r.</hi> Ariſtolochia; <hi>p.</hi> 92 <hi>l.</hi> 4 <hi>r.</hi> Barefoot; <hi>p.</hi> 101 <hi>l.</hi> 15 <hi>r.</hi> Popes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37973:85"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
