<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mercurius publicus: comprising the sum of forraign intelligence ...[no.36 (30 Aug-6 Sept 1660)]</title>
            <title>Mercurius publicus (London, England : 1659)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A71356</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E186_34</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53403907</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53403907</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97700</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A71356)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97700)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 32:E183[6]; 32:E183[8]; 32:E183[10]; 32:E183[13]; 32:E183[15], etc)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mercurius publicus: comprising the sum of forraign intelligence ...[no.36 (30 Aug-6 Sept 1660)]</title>
                  <title>Mercurius publicus (London, England : 1659)</title>
                  <author>Muddiman, Henry, fl.1659-1666, editor.</author>
                  <author>Dury, Giles editor.</author>
                  <author>Newcomb, Thomas, d. 1681 or 2, publisher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>v.   Began with numb. 1 (29 Dec. 1659-5 Jan. 1660); ceased with numb. 33 (13-20 Aug. 1663).</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Newcomb,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from caption.</note>
                  <note>Subtitle varies: 1660, "... comprising the sum of forraign intelligence"; 1661-1663, "... comprising the sum of all affairs now in agitation."</note>
                  <note>By Henry Muddiman and Giles Dury. Cf. Nelson and Seccombe.</note>
                  <note>Printed variously by: John Macock, Thomas Newcomb, Richard Hodgkinson, D. Maxwell, Peter Lillicrap, James Cottrell.</note>
                  <note>Description based on: Numb. 16.</note>
                  <note>Numb. 43 (18-25 Oct. 1660) is a second copy of The Parliamentary intelligencer for those dates, mistakenly titled Mercurius publicus.</note>
                  <note>Thomason collection does not have complete run.</note>
                  <note>Reels listed in chronological order of serial publication; holdings dispersed throughout collection.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the originals in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Enumeration begins again at numb. 1 annually.</note>
                  <note>No issue numbered 52 in 1660, no issue numbered 44 in 1661; chronology is continuous.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Periodicals.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Periodicals.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  1648-1715 --  Periodicals.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="561" facs="tcp:97700:488" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Numb.</hi> 36 Mercurius Publicus, COMPRISING The Sum of Forraign Intelligence: WITH The Affairs now in Agitation in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> For Information of the People. Publiſhed by Order. <date>From <hi>Thurſday</hi> Auguſt <hi>30.</hi> to <hi>Thurſday</hi> Septemb. <hi>6. 1660.</hi>
               </date>
            </head>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Amſterdam, <date>Auguſt <hi>21.</hi>
                  </date>
               </head>
               <p>THe Poſt of <hi>Oſnabrug</hi> reports, that about ſix days ſince ſome of the Garriſon of <hi>Munſter,</hi> after they had been very merry the night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, made a Sally out of that City, when they were yet half drunk, taking in a ſmall Fort which the Biſhop had cauſed to be raiſed for the blocking up of the Place, and putting ſome men in it to maintain it; But as they returned back to the City, the Biſhops Horſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell in upon the rear of them, and killed about thirty men, among whom one of the Burgomaſters was found. The Biſhop had cauſed ſome of the Citizens that were killed, to be hanged up.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="562" facs="tcp:97700:489"/>
                     <head>A Letter from Major <hi>Robert Holmes,</hi> Commander of the <hi>Heneretta,</hi> ſent unto Baron <hi>Battavella</hi> in <hi>Spain.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>BEing appointed by comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd from His Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> to wait on Your Excellency with one of His Majeſties Ships, the King of Great Britain, I think it fit to let Your Excellency know<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That I am ſafely arrived upon the Coaſt, and intend to Anchor at <hi>Gatharia</hi> Road, where I hope to hear from you, and in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto have ſent my Ketch, to bring Your Excellencies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. I did intend to put in to Paſſage; but finding the entring of the Harbour ſo narrow, I dare not venture with a Ship of this concernment without Your ſpecial Order; and if Your Excellency think not this place convenient, be pleaſed to appoint any other, and I ſhall immediately ſet ſail towards it, if wind and weather will permit. The enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Letters were given me by Count <hi>Conſtang,</hi> and <hi>Monſieur de Ovietta:</hi> I ſhall humbly beg Your Excellencies pardon for not waiting on you with them my ſelf.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>My Lord, Your Excellencies moſt affectionate and humble Servant,</hi> Robert Holmes.</signed>
                        <dateline>From on Board the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neretta,</hi> off of Cape <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Chegoe,</hi>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Aug.</hi> 8. 1660.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>
                  <hi>Edinbrough,</hi> 
                  <date>Aug. 25. 1660.</date>
               </head>
               <p>On wedneſday the 22. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Glencairn,</hi> Lord Chancellor of <hi>Scotland,</hi> came into this City honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly attended by about 1000. Horſe. The <hi>Major General,</hi> Colonell <hi>Daniel,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Diſne</hi> the <hi>Engliſh Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners,</hi> with ſeveral Field-Officers, and two Troops of the
<pb n="563" facs="tcp:97700:489"/>
                  <hi>Major Generals</hi> Regiment of Horſe, went to <hi>Muſsleborough</hi> to meet his Lordſhip, and attended him thence to the Houſe deſigned for his Lordſhip in this City. At his coming in to <hi>Edinborough,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Winton</hi> rode on his right hand, and Major General <hi>Morgan</hi> on his left: He was guarded from the <hi>Water-gate</hi> to the <hi>Nether-Bow,</hi> by the Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals Regiment of Foot. The Lord Chancellor being come the Committee of three Eſtates (according to the late Proclamation) ſate on Thurſday, <hi>Aug.</hi> 23. and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation being given of ſome Remonſtrating Miniſters that were at <hi>Robert Symſon,</hi> the Collectors houſe; Orders were ſent to Captain <hi>Newman</hi> in <hi>Edinborough</hi> Caſtle, to command thence 20. Muſquetiers to <hi>Symſon</hi>'s houſe, who found the Miniſters ſubſcribing a Paper tending to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbance of this Kingdom. The Miniſters were carryed Priſoners to <hi>Edinborough</hi> Caſtle: Their names are
<list>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>James Guthrie,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Sterling.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Robert Trayle,</hi> Miniſters of <hi>Edinborough.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>John Strivling,</hi> Miniſters of <hi>Edinborough.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Alexander Moncreif,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Scooney.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>John Semple,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Carffern.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mſey,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Foulden.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Gilbert Hall,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Kirkliſton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>John Scot,</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Ornham.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>George Nairne,</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Brunt</hi> Iſland.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>John Murray,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Maffin</hi> Pariſh.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Kirk,</hi> Laird of <hi>Soudaywell.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon the Lord Chancellor with the Committee of the Three Eſtates, the very next day ſet forth this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proclamation.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="564" facs="tcp:97700:490"/>
                     <opener>GOD Save the KING. </opener>
                     <head>A Proclamation by the Committee of Eſtates convened by His Majesties ſpecial Authority, against unlawfull Meetings and ſeditious Papers.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>At <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 
                           <date>Auguſt <hi>24. 1660.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THe Committee of Eſtates in obedience to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Proclamation being met, and taking to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> conſideration the goodneſs of God, who in his great mercy hath reſtored the Kings Majeſty to the Exerciſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is Royal Government; And withall, conſidering His <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>jeſties great care of, and affection to this His Majeſties Anc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ent Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in Calling and Authorizing the ſaid Committee of Eſtates to Meet; And they finding it their duty to prevent all unlawful Meetings, which may tend to the prejudice of His Majeſties Service, or may again involve His Majeſties good Subjects into new Troubles; Have thought it fit in His Majeſties Name and Authority, to prohibite, And by theſe Preſents do prohibite and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge all unlawful and unwarrantable Meetings or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles in any place within this His Majeſties Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> without His Majeſties ſpecial Authority; And likewiſe all ſeditious Petitions and Remonſtrances, under what pretence ſoever which may tend to the diſturbance of the Peace of this Kingdom, or alienating and debauching the affections of His Majeſties Subjects from their due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to His Majeſties lawful Authority, and that under all higheſt pains. And for this effect, appoints all Sheriffs of Shires, and Magiſtrates of Burghs to be careful within their reſpective Bounds, that no ſuch pernicious and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous meetings be permitted, but that they be timeouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, hindered, made known and diſcovered to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee
<pb n="565" facs="tcp:97700:490"/>
of Eſtates. And ordain theſe preſents to be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Printed, and Publiſhed at the Mercat croſs of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> and the Head Burghs of the reſpective Shires with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Kingdom, that none pretend ignorance hereof.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Signed in the Name, and by Warrant of the Committee of Eſtates. GLENCARNE</hi> Chancellour. <hi>I. P. D.</hi> Com.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>After which was ſet forth another Proclamation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding that no Diſorders of Inſolencies be committed by any perſon whatever within this Kingdom upon any of the Engliſh Nation, under all higheſt pain, after which they adjourn'd till <hi>Tueſday</hi> following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>White-Hall.</head>
               <p>His Majeſty was graciouſly pleaſed to confer the Honour of Knight-hood upon <hi>Herbert Perrot,</hi> Eſquire, a worthy Member of the Houſe of Commons, ſerving in Parliament for the Burrough of <hi>Weobly,</hi> in the County of Herreford.</p>
               <p>On Thurſday laſt that accompliſhed Perſonage <hi>George</hi> Earl of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> entertain'd His Majeſty at his own houſe with a Supper, with whom was Their Royal Highneſſes the <hi>Dukes</hi> of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> attended by the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and other Perſons of Honour.</p>
               <p>On Friday the Lords had a Conference with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, wherein Their Lordſhips acquainted the Commons with His Majeſties Meſſage for an Adjournment from the eighth of <hi>September</hi> to the ſixth of <hi>November</hi> next.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <pb n="566" facs="tcp:97700:491"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> 
                  <date>Aug. 25.</date>
               </head>
               <p>The Daniſh Embaſſadours who lately arrived here out of <hi>Holland,</hi> are this day gone by land for <hi>Denmark.</hi> The Imperial <hi>Field-Marſhal Montecuculi,</hi> is daily expected here. Two days ago arrived here from <hi>Sweden,</hi> the <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sgrave</hi> of <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>zhach,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Anha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>; they intend to ſtay here ſome few days, to wait on the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and then to return into <hi>Germany.</hi> The confederate Forces are now at laſt broke up in <hi>Holſten,</hi> being appointed to quarter this night at <hi>Rensburgh,</hi> and to morrow at <hi>New Miniſter</hi>; and thoſe 600 horſe which were ſaid to continue in <hi>Holſten,</hi> are likewiſe to withdraw on the 21 inſtant, and to follow after the reſt. The Imperial horſe which were quartered in <hi>Mek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenburg,</hi> are already drawn together in order to their ſpeedy march out of that country, and the Foot is to follow them within a fortnight. The Ratifications of peace with the Emperor, <hi>Sweden, Poland,</hi> and <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> are mutually exchanged and delivered at <hi>Danzick,</hi> on the ſixth and eighth courant, and <hi>Elbing</hi> is to be delivered up to the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> on the 14. of this moneth. What other place will be given for it to the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> is not yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly known; Field-Marſhal <hi>Schack</hi> is made a Senator of the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and Major-General <hi>Eggerick</hi> is appointed Governour of <hi>Copenhagen.</hi> The Parliament in <hi>Sweden</hi> is to Aſſemble on the 21 of <hi>Septemb.</hi> and the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the late Kings Funeral are to be performed in the moneth <hi>October</hi> following; which when done, ſeveral Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſies are to be diſpatched thence for <hi>England, France, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and other places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>
                  <hi>Vienna,</hi> 
                  <date>25. Aug.</date>
               </head>
               <p>Letters which the laſt Poſt from <hi>Gratz,</hi> intimate, that his Imperial Majeſty was to proceed on his journey for <hi>Carin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hia</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rain</hi> at the beginning of the next moneth, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied
<pb n="567" facs="tcp:97700:491"/>
only with few of his Court, and reſolved to go ſo far as <hi>Trieſt</hi> on the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea coaſt, where the V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are a preparing of ſeveral Nav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l divertiſemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſities, to entertain his Majeſty; which it ſo, then his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties return would not he ſo ſudden as otherwiſe was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. The Venetians purſue their Lev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in theſe parts, with much eagerneſs, and get a number of good Souldiers of the <hi>Bava<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ian</hi> diſ-banded Forces into their ſervice. The Eſtates of Nether-<hi>Auſtria</hi> are to Aſſemble here the next week: We are advertiſed from <hi>Hungaria,</hi> that the Count of <hi>Serin,</hi> upon Order from his Imperial Majeſty, hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn his Forces from the Fort of <hi>Caniſcha.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Venice, <date>Auguſt <hi>6.</hi>
                  </date>
               </head>
               <p>Two of our Gallies, with many armed B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>kes, are lately arrived at <hi>Ancona</hi>; the Turkiſh Pyrates upon information hereof, retreated out of the <hi>Gulf</hi> with their Booty: But others are ſince gone to the Iſle of <hi>Elba,</hi> where they have plundred the Town of <hi>Piumbino,</hi> and carryed away many ſlaves, together with the Nuns of the Cloiſter in that place. The Turks having received a ſupply of 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 horſe in <hi>Canea,</hi> they have ſo far made their approaches to the City of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> that they begin to annoy it with ſlinging of fire into it; But ours, to relieve the place, have drawn their Forces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether about <hi>Cerigo.</hi> Here arrived lately a Turkiſh Gally, which was maſtered by 170 Slaves, who all had their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and a piece of money given them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advert">
               <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
               <p>THE Due way of Compoſing the Differences on Foot, Preſerving the Church. According to the Opinion of <hi>Herbert Thorndike</hi>: Sold by <hi>John Martin, James Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Dicas,</hi> at the <hi>Bell</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <pb n="568" facs="tcp:97700:492"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Hague,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>September</hi> 20.</date> S. N.</head>
               <p>The Lords States of the Province of Zealand, to the number of twenty ſix, having been fetched up with ſeveral Coaches to their audience with the Lords States of Holland, Monſieur <hi>Adri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Vet,</hi> Penſioner of the States of Zealand, made a very eloquent and large Speech, wherein he remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ated to them, thoſe motives and reaſons which induc'd his Principals to ſettle and eſtabliſh the Government of theſe Provinces upon their ancient Foundation, under a Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant or Captain Admiral General, for which truſt they had nominated his Highneſs the Prince of Orange, according to their reſolution taken on the ſeventh of this moneth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring the States of Holland would be pleaſed to concur with them therein: In order whereunto, a conference is to be held b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tween the Deputies of thoſe two States, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a joynt condeſcenſion to, and ratification of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. What the reſult of it will be, a ſhort time muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover. There is no certainty yet of the Ambaſſadors go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hence for England, and it is thought that they can hardly have their diſpatch theſe ſix weeks.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>An Extract of the Reſolution taken by the Lords States of the Province of <hi>Zealand</hi> on Saturday the ſeventh of <hi>Auguſt, S. N.</hi> concerning his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>We the Lords States of Zealand having moſt ſeriouſly and deliberatively <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n divers Seſſions conſidered of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the fourth Article touching their Conventions, and the reſpective eminent charges heretofore ſucceſſively held by their Highneſſes the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ces of <hi>Orange</hi> of immortal me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; and neerly reflecting on what by theſe conjunctures of times and affairs ought principally to be obſerved, as tending to the greateſt honour, welfare and ſervice, as well of this S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate in General, as of this Province in particular:
<pb n="569" facs="tcp:97700:492"/>
we doe once more declare it to be our judgement and opinion (as we have done ſeveral times heretofore) that to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned end and purpoſe, the Cheif management of the publick Concerne muſt be inveſted and entruſted with certain Eminent men and perſons of Quality and Extraction, in purſuance of thoſe ſeveral Remonſtrances, and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vigorouſly ſet forth in the beginning of the troubles and afterwards, as well by the States General, as the reſpective Provinces. And although the misfortune of many intricate occurrences happening in theſe late years, after the deceaſe of his Highneſs Prince William the ſecond, in theſe, as well as in the Neighboring Countries was a great hindrance and could not well allow, that ſuch a Reſolution as was neceſſary and much wiſhed for, touching the appointment and Election of ſuch a cheif and certain perſon, for the Government, ſhould have its deſired effect; yet finding, that by Gods Gracious and unſerchable Providence, thoſe unhappy diſtractions and troubles are ceaſed, and taking notice of a more favorable Conſtitution of affairs and opportunities as to the whole Chriſtian world in general, and theſe Provinces in particular, which to the redreſs and reſettlement of the State ought to be neglected, and conſequently reaſſuming our before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned wholſome Intention of Electing one perſon or other qualified, who moſt worthily and with the moſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence could be intruſted with the chief Government of this State in General, and of this Province in particular; We the ſaid Lords States of Zealand can find no perſon of more Credit, worth or reſpect then his Highn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs the preſent Prince of Orange, he being not onely the off-ſpring of thoſe Princes, who with the hazard of their Eſtates and blood have layd the foundation of this Commonwealth, and by their excellent and couragious conduct purchaſed ſo honorable and glorious a Liberty, which to the Admiration of all the whole world we at preſent enjoy; But being likewiſe by blood, affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Alliances annexed to the greateſt and mightieſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſtendom, by whom this State in its troubles and neceſſities hath been principally ſupported, and whoſe friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="570" facs="tcp:97700:493"/>
and Confederacies for the time to come will be of moſt concern to us; conſidering alſo his Princely Qualities and Vertues wherewith God Almighty hath been pleaſed to indow his Highneſs from his very Infancie, very well agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Government and Humor of theſe Nations, who ſeem to take a ſpecial pleaſure and wel-liking of them, and to promiſe to themſelves much Happineſs, Bleſſing and proſperity; and finally regarding, that the ſaid Prince hath a fair Eſtate, and large Poſſeſſions in moſt part of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of this State, and particularly in that of Zealand, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it can be maintained, that before all others, he is mainly intereſſed to endeavor the preſervation and welfare of this State. We therefore, being ſolemnly ſummoned and aſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as is uſual, upon this preſent Subject, have reſolved and determined, out of the alledged and other weighty reſpects and reaſons, with a general and unanimous conſent to declare;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Prince of Orange, in behalf of this Province, together with the other Confederates of the Aſſembly of their High and mighty Lordſhips the States General, ſhall be choſen and nominated Captain and Admiral General of the United Netherlands, with a convenient Commiſſion and Inſtructions to be agreed and concluded upon between the ſeveral Provinces, and a yearly revenue of 100000 Gilders for his maintenance, to be levied upon the States account, and to begin from the time the Commiſſion is iſſued out.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To which purpoſe, certain Deputies are to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by this aſſembly, to repair to the aſſembly of the Lords States General, to tender to their Lordſhips this point of electing a Governor, and with the beſt reaſons to procure their conſent, and a ſpeedy effect of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That a tender of the charge of Governor, Captain and Admiral-general of both the Provinces, be preſently made to his Highneſs the ſaid Prince of Orange, with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient Commiſſion and inſtructions to be iſſued out with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay, to which the Lords States of Holland are to be required to give their concurrence, that ſo in regard of their
<pb n="571" facs="tcp:97700:493"/>
common intereſts, and according to antient practice, this affair may be determined <hi>pari paſſu,</hi> and with joint advice; and that a Commiſſion be drawn and ſealed, as it was done in the year 1647.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Yet in caſe this appointment of the Prince for the abovementioned places ſhould not take effect with the Lords States General, and the States of Holland, contrary to the expectation, wiſh and good intention of this aſſembly, that then, upon a full report of their Deputies concerning their negotiation, this Aſſembly will take care, and order affairs ſo, as may moſt tend to the honor, welfare and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the country.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is the unanimous conſent of the ſaid Lords States of Zealand, that the beforementioned Prince of Orange ſhall not exerciſe thoſe eminent charges of General and Admiralſhip, till his Highneſs come to be eighteen years of age; which charges (during his minority) are not to be executed by any under the name of Lieutenant, but remain as now they are, which two conditions are to be expreſly inſerted in the beforementioned Commiſsion.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That preſently by an unanimous conſent and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the Members aſſembled, the dignity and place of the Firſt Noble ſhall be preſented to the Prince, he being the moſt conſpicuous and qualified Nobleman of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince; yet upon ſuch clauſes, reſtrictions and precautions, as the ſame dignity hath been heretofore conferred upon the Princes of Orange of immortal memory, without diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or prejudice of the priviledges of this Province, and other the ſeveral Members of this State.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Upon the conferring of ſuch charges, Honors and preheminences on the ſaid Prince, all poſsible care and order ſhall be taken for his Highneſs Education and Breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as may beſt befit his Princely perſon and Illuſtrious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That his Highneſs ſhall be allowed at the 16. year of his age, to have acceſs to the Council of State, according as it was practiſed by his Highneſs Grand-Father Prince <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick
<pb n="572" facs="tcp:97700:494"/>
Henry,</hi> that ſo his Highneſs may be inſtructed in the Fundamental Laws and Maximes, and the Antient and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Government of theſe Countries, and the better learn the humor and inclinations of his good people and Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="adverts">
               <head>Advertiſements of Books newly Printed and Publiſhed.</head>
               <p>☞<hi>Phil-Anglus</hi>: Some ſober inſpections made into the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and conſults of the late long Parliament: whereby occaſion is taken to ſpeak of Parliaments in former tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, &amp;c. With ſome reflexes upon Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in general. With ſome Prophetick Paragraphs. By <hi>James Howel</hi> Eſq. Sold by <hi>W. Palmer</hi> at the Palm-Tree near St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Five Seaſonable Sermons Preached before eminent Audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and Dedicated to the Kings Majeſty, by <hi>Paul Knell,</hi> Maſter in Arts of <hi>Clare</hi>-Hall in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> ſometime Chaplain to a Regiment of Curaſſiers in his late Majeſties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmy. Sold by <hi>John Place</hi> at <hi>Furnivals</hi> Inn-Gate in <hi>Holborn.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="advert">
               <head>Advertiſement.</head>
               <p>IF any man can give notice of a light Dun Mare with a bald face, and four white feet, black mane and tail, a lock of white hairs in her tail, about ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years old, and about fifteen hand high, that was taken out of a Stable in <hi>Coale Yard</hi> on Thurſday <hi>Auguſt</hi> 30. by a young man about 27. years of age, brown hair, ſomewhat l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng, of a pale complexion and round face, with a pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter on the left check. If any one apprehend him, and give notice at the Red Lion in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> the Cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Keys in St <hi>Edes,</hi> or the Holy Lamb on the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of St. <hi>Clements,</hi> they ſhall have five pound for their pains.</p>
               <p>STolen the ſecond of <hi>September,</hi> out of a Dining-Room in <hi>Holborn,</hi> one large Looking Glaſs ſet in an Ebony frame, a Landskip being drawn at the tom of the glaſs, with a Shepherdeſs, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, a G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at, and ſeveral other figures, there being a ſlaw at the top of the Glaſs, as alſo two <hi>Turkey</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, the one three yards long, and two yards and a half wide, or thereabouts; the other two yards and a half long, and a yard and a half wide, or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts. If any one give notice thereof to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. <hi>Arnold</hi> a Grocer, at the Tobacco-Roll and Sugar-Loaf next to <hi>Grais-Inn</hi>-Gate in <hi>Holborn,</hi> they ſhall have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ty ſhillings for their pains.</p>
               <p>ON Saturday l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt run away from the Lord <hi>Rich: Chriſtophilus Cornaro,</hi> a <hi>Turk</hi> Chriſtened: A <hi>French</hi> youth of 17 or 18 years of age, with flaxen hair, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle blew eyes, a mark upon his lip, and another under his right eye; of a fair complexion, one of his ears pierced, having a Pearl-coloured Cloth ſuit, trim'd with ſcarlet and blew Ribbons, a Coat of the ſame colour, with ſilver Buttons, his name <hi>Iacob David.</hi> Give notice to the Lords Lodging at the 3 Fiſhes in New <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reet in Covent Garden, a Cooks ſhop, and good ſatisfaction ſhall be given.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="adverts">
               <pb n="573" facs="tcp:97700:494"/>
               <head>Advertiſements.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Reader is deſired to take notice, That his Majeſties Printers having publiſhed the Act of Free and General Pardon, Indempuity and Oblivion, in a more contracted Form then ordinary, that it might be of ſmall price; yet notwithſtanding ſome perſons have not only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to Re-print the ſame, to their very great detriment, but have alſo committed ſeveral groſs faults, as in Page</hi> 5. <hi>they have left out</hi> (any of) <hi>Page</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 11. (or Acquittances) <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. <hi>li.</hi> 19. (the day) <hi>li.</hi> 43. (Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties) <hi>left out. Pag.</hi> 12. (of) <hi>left out, and</hi> (or perſons) <hi>too much; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe Errata there are very many other Miſtakes, which ought not to paſs in a thing of ſo great conſequence. This ſtollen falſe impreſſion may be known, by being printed in three ſheets, not of the known Letter for</hi> Acts, <hi>whereas the right is Five ſheets; All Perſons therefore, who deſire a true Copy of the Act of Indempnity, are advis'd to beware of that falſe imperfect Three ſheets, which will but deceive the Buyer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>RIchard Verney</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> of <hi>Alaxſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> in <hi>Leiceſterſhire,</hi> about a for might ſince loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Lanner from that place, ſhe hath neither Bells nor Varvels; ſhe is a wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Hawk, and her long feathers and ſarſcels are both in the blood. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> give tidings thereof to Mr <hi>Lambert</hi> at the golden Key in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> they ſhall have forty ſhillings for their pains.</p>
               <p>THe But end and the Lock of a Gunn, commonly called a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>taff Gunn, being dutch-worke, and fitted to its Barrel, with a Screw, within few ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the touch-hole, was loſt between <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Barnet</hi> on Tue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>day 21 <hi>Auguſt</hi>: if any one do bring it to Sir <hi>Eliab Harveys</hi> Houſe in <hi>Breadſtreet,</hi> he ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l have twenty ſhillings for his pains.</p>
               <p>LOſt on Sunday night laſt, out of the King Meadows near <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon Thames, in the County of <hi>Surrey</hi> one brown bay Mare three years old and upward, having a white ſtar in the forehead, a white ſnip up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the noſe, and a little white on one of her hind-feet, about 14 hands high, in good fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh. Alſo a bright bay Mare, between 14 and 15 handfuls high, about 9 ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs old, a white ſtreak down the face, a white foot behind, and the near <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e of the other hind-foot, but meanly in fleſh. If any give not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce to <hi>Henry Mudhets</hi> at the three Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons in <hi>Kingſton</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oreſaid; or to Mr. <hi>Bedſon</hi> a Tailor in <hi>New Street</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> they ſhall have forty ſhillings for their pains.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <p>On Monday the third inſtant, the Accuſation againſt. Col. <hi>Robert Worden</hi> was taken into conſideration by his Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſty ſitting in full Council, where was read a large Atteſtation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hands of Sir <hi>George Boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> and the greateſt part of the Baronets, Knights, Eſquires and Gentlemen of the County
<pb n="574" facs="tcp:97700:495"/>
Palatine of Cheſter, declaring that they ever found the ſaid Col. <hi>Worden</hi> in all his Majeſties concernments, not only faithful, but ſo induſtrious and prudent, as that no Perſon would be more acceptable for their future Truſt. Upon conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration whereof, and that ſeveral Lords of the Council af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, that in the time of the late Tyrannical Government, the ſaid Colonel was highly inſtrumental to advance his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties intereſt, and that by their communication with him, their Lives and Fortunes had been in his power; expreſsing their eſteem of him as of a Worthy and Loyal Perſon, his Majeſty declar'd that He did fully acquit him from the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation and and imputation he had ſuffered under, and that He eſteem'd him a very honeſt and Loyal Perſon, and would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngly admit him into his former favor. In earneſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of his Majeſty hath given him the honor of his hand, and his Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York</hi> hath gladly received him into his Service, as formerly, to the joy of many worthy and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Perſons, who had long known the Colonels courage and loyalty, and were ſorry a miſtake in others ſhould be get any ſuſpition upon a Perſon ſo highly deſerving.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Weſtminſter.</head>
               <p>And now we can tell News which all the good ſubjects of three Kingdoms will rejoice at; how that great Inſtrument of ſedition and Firebrand, <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> is cloſe priſoner in the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London.</hi> The particulars take impartially thus. On Friday laſt intelligence was given that <hi>Peters</hi> privily lurked about <hi>Southwark</hi>; whereupon Sir <hi>Edward Nicholas</hi> his Majeſties principal Secretary of State, ſent two Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of his Majeſties Chamber in ordinary to apprehend him: That night they entred the houſe where he lay, which was one <hi>Broad's</hi> a Quaker in S. <hi>Thomas</hi> pariſh, whoſe daughter Mrs. <hi>Peach</hi> then l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y in. The Meſſengers ſearch'd, but miſs'd <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> who (according to his cuſtom) had crept into bed to the young woman, where the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers modeſty forbad their ſearch; ſhe having been delivered but two days before. There lay <hi>Hugh</hi>; and the Meſſengers finding a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate paſſage out of that into the houſe of another Quaker call'd <hi>John Day</hi> the Cobler, (thus <hi>Quaking</hi> runs from houſe to houſe;) they ſearch'd there alſo: In the interim <hi>Peters</hi> eſcap'd from childbed, leaving behind him his Cane with a R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pier in it, a ſmall pocket-Bible, and a gray Cloak, (for poſſibly now he was in his Frock.) But on Sunday laſt
<pb n="575" facs="tcp:97700:495"/>
about ſix at night, in a place call'd the <hi>Maze,</hi> in the ſame pariſh near <hi>Horſ-way Down,</hi> at <hi>Nathanael Mun</hi> a Tape-weavers houſe, <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> again lay in. The Meſſenger Mr. <hi>Wickham</hi> coming to the door, found it not lock'd nor latch'd, but kept faſt by the Tape-weavers wife, (how faithful that ſex are to <hi>Peters!</hi>) who thruſt her back to the door, till the Meſſengers ſtrength prov'd Mrs. <hi>Mun</hi> was the weaker veſſel, and ſuddenly running up ſtairs, found that door alſo kept faſt like the other: 'tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>Hugh</hi> himſelf, whoſe ſhoulder at the door put the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger hard to it, for <hi>Peters</hi> now thought he thruſt for his life. But the Meſſenger encourag'd, in hopes 'twas <hi>Peters,</hi> whoſe ſtrength fail'd, as his fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r increaſed, at laſt the door flew open, where <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> was found (a true Quaker) trembling after an incredible manner: Yet now (in his wonted way of confidence) he ſtifly denied himſelf to be <hi>Peters,</hi> but ſaid his name was <hi>Thompſon</hi> (perhaps <hi>Hugh</hi> the ſon of <hi>Thomas</hi>) threatning the Meſſengers with an Action at Law for offering to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffirm he was <hi>Hugh Peters</hi>; and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to go down with the Meſſenger, till Mr. <hi>Arnold</hi> (ſervant to Mr. <hi>Blagge</hi> of his Majeſties Bedchamber) Mr. <hi>Hopkins</hi> a good neighbour, and Mr. <hi>Harris</hi> the honeſt Conſtable came up the ſtairs, who all expreſſed much diligence and heartineſs in aſſiſting the Meſſenger. And yet after all, he refuſed to come down (ſtill wondring they would think him <hi>Peters,</hi>) ſo as they began to force him down, and then he promiſed to go along, <hi>but firſt,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>give me leave to gather up my ſpirits</hi>; whereupon he call'd for Drink, and drank two quarts (two full qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rts) of ſmall Beer, for the Houſe had no ſtrong. Then <hi>Hugh</hi> deſired he might ſpeak privately with Mris. <hi>Mun,</hi> which they denied, unleſs hee would ſpeak in their hearing; after which hee ſaid, <hi>I will go, but I beg for the Lords ſake that you call mee not Mr.</hi> Peters, <hi>for,</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id hee, <hi>if it be known that I am</hi> Hugh Peters, <hi>the people in the ſtreet will ſtone mee.</hi> At laſt out hee came, but ſuddenly ſtept in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, ſaying, <hi>I muſt ſpeak privately with the woman of the Houſe,</hi> (a woman was his chief Confident) and now they had ſome tugg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fetch him back, in which ſtruggle, feeling his skirts hard, they unrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, and found five peeces of Gold and ſome Silver Medals, and out of his pocket they took his Alm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nack, for which hee ſtruggled more than for his Bible. Thence they forced him to the Conſtables Houſe, where they ſent for his Landlord <hi>Broad</hi> (an old Accuſer of honeſt men) who being abſent, his Son-in-law <hi>Peach,</hi> (whoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs it was that his Wife had been but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> daies delivered) came in his ſtead, who being asked if hee knew that Cloak, Cane, and Gloves, anſwered, <hi>that they belongd to that Gentleman</hi>; pointing to <hi>Peters.</hi> But <hi>Hugh</hi> ſtill with his wonted mode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y denied it, name and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll; though ſoon
<pb facs="tcp:97700:496"/>
(forgetting himſelf) hee unawares put on the Gloves, and ſaid, <hi>they were his own</hi>; and then without more trifling they brought him to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and delivered him into the cuſtody of the worthy Lieutenant Sir <hi>Iohn Robinſon</hi> (in the blood of whoſe Uncle, that ever-renowned <hi>William</hi> late Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Hugh Peters</hi> was elbow deep, and go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Archbiſhops Library of moſt choiſe Books, as well as his Majeſties Library at St. <hi>James's</hi>) which he hath now turn'd to a pocket Bible and an Almanack. All this while, and at the <hi>Tower</hi> alſo, <hi>Hugh</hi> averred his name was <hi>Thomſon,</hi> and denied himſelf to be <hi>Peters</hi> though there his Coſin Mr. <hi>Birch</hi> the Wardour knew him and called the man by his name; til at laſt in privat to Sir <hi>Iohn Robinſon</hi> he confeſſed who hee was, and then (with moſt ingenious modeſty) acchſed the Meſſenger and the reſt <hi>for taking and bringing him to the</hi> Tower <hi>by the name of</hi> Thom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. So that he who before threatned an <hi>Action</hi> againſt thoſe who offered to call him <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> doth now accuſe them for calling him <hi>Thomſon.</hi> This is St. <hi>Hugh,</hi> who when our Glorious Soveraign was led to Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, fel ſo he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vy upon his righteous ſoul, blaſpheming him upon his then Text (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. <hi>To bind their Kings in Chains, &amp;c.</hi>) and may now make himſelf the Title of his own Book (call'd <hi>Good work for a good Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi>) where among m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny other, he hath theſe ſix motions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That</hi> Pauls <hi>Church may be pull'd down to pave</hi> Thameſtreet. 2. <hi>To d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtroy Colledges, ſince there are none in the Goſpel,</hi> pag. 4. (for <hi>Hugh</hi> was expelled one.) 3. <hi>That Phyſicians ſhould take ſmall fees,</hi> pag. 33. (What was <hi>Hugh's</hi> diſeaſe?) — 4. <hi>That Adultery ſhould be puniſhed with a merciful heart</hi> pag. 52. (and not like <hi>Butchers.</hi>) 5. <hi>That all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married maids be put to ſpin,</hi> (to prevent the beſt uſe of hemp.) 6. <hi>That all Records in the Tower might be burn'd</hi>—But the Records ſtill are ſafe in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and ſo is <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> where now we leave him.</p>
               <p>Laſt Monday morning about eleven of the clock, that notorious <hi>John Harris</hi> (commonly called Major <hi>Harris</hi>) was executed in <hi>Leadenhall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainſt the Merchants houſe where he committed the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glary by a forged Warrant in the Lord High Chancellors name. This is that <hi>Harris</hi> who h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d been Conductor to <hi>Oliver Cromwels</hi> Forces, and a frequent falſe Witneſs againſt his Majeſties good Subjects.</p>
               <p>On Sunday laſt his Majeſty went to <hi>Greenwich</hi> to refreſh himſelf for ſome few hours in that <hi>Yaugh</hi> which was preſented to him from <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>; which <hi>Yaugh</hi> or Pleaſure-Boat will ſcarce be equalled by any in theſe parts of Chriſtendom.</p>
               <p>On Tueſday (<hi>September</hi> 4.) the Lord <hi>Roberts</hi> Nobly entertained his Majeſty with a ſupper at his houſe at <hi>Chelſey.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London, <hi>Printed by</hi> John Macock, <hi>and</hi> Tho: Newcomb <hi>1660.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97700:496"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
