<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proud and blasphemous cahllenge [sic] given out in denuntiation of warre, by Amurath the great Turk, against all Christendome Coming with an army of 1600000. men.</title>
            <author>Murad I, Sultan of the Turks, 1326-1389.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75306</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.6[108]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212600</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871204</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871204</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160969</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A75306)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160969)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 245:669f6[108])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proud and blasphemous cahllenge [sic] given out in denuntiation of warre, by Amurath the great Turk, against all Christendome Coming with an army of 1600000. men.</title>
                  <author>Murad I, Sultan of the Turks, 1326-1389.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>With two woodcut portraits; one "Emperour of Constantinople", the other "Emperour of Rome".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "printed Jan 29 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>War --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:160969:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <head>A PROVD AND BLASPHEMOVS CAHLLENGE Given out in denuntiation of warre, by <hi>Amurath</hi> the great Turk, againſt all Chriſtendome.</head>
            <p>Coming with an Army of 1600000, men.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Emperour of Conſtantinople.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>Emperour of Rome.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE alone the only Monarch of the world, a great and mighty God on earth, an Invincible</hi> Caeſar, <hi>King of all Kings, from the Eaſt unto the Weſt, Sultan of Babilon, Soveraigne of the moſt noble families of Perſia, and Armenia, tryumphant victor of Ieruſalem, Lord poſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of the crucified God, ſubverter, and ſworne enemy of the Chriſtians, and of all them that call upon the name of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We denounce unto thee the Emperour of Rome, and to all Nations taking part with thee, unto the great Biſhop alſo, all the Cardinalls and Biſhops, to all your ſonnes and ſubjects, we earneſtly (I ſay) by our Crowne and Empire, denounce unto you open warre.</p>
            <p>VVe give you to underſtand that our purpoſe is, with the power of thirteen King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and ſixteene hundred thouſand of men, horſe and foot, with our Turks, and Turkiſh armes, yea, with all our ſtrength and power (ſuch as neither thou, nor any of thine hath ever yet either ſeen or heard of, much leſſe had any proofe of) to beſiedge you in your chiefe and metropolitane Cities; and with fire and ſword to perſecute you, and all yours, and whoſoever ſhall give you helpe, to burne, deſtroy, and kill, and with the moſt exquiſit torments wee can deviſe to torture unto death, and ſlight ſuch Chriſtian captives, as ſhall fall into our hands, becauſe we heare that you fall out amongſt your ſelves, therefore we will regulate you.</p>
            <p>VVe will keepe you as ſlaves, and uſe you like doggs in continuall miſery, impaile your faireſt ſonnes, and daughters upon ſtakes, and to the future ſhame, and reproach of you and yours, we will after a moſt bloody, and cruell manner, rip open your women with child, and trample their children under our feet; for we are reſolved to bring into our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction you which cannot rule quietly in ſmall Countries, and by a ſtrong hand and force of Armes to keep your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes from you; as alſo to oppreſſe, roote up, and deſtroy, your Sees, together with the golden Scepter of Rome, and we will prove whether your crucified Ieſus will helpe you, and do for you as yours perſwade you. Beleove him ſtill and truſt in him, and ſee how he hath holpen his meſſengers which have put their confidence in him; for we neither beeleve, neither can we endure to heare of ſuch incomprehenſible things, that he can helpe which is dead ſo many worlds of years agoe, which could not helpe himſelfe, nor deliver his owne Country and Inheritance, from our power, over which we have a long time reigned.</p>
            <p>Theſe things, oh ye poore and miſerable of the world, we thought good to ſignifie unto you that you with your Princes and Councellors may know what you have to doe, and to looke for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Given in our moſt mighty, and Imperiall City of Conſtantinople, which our Anceſtors by force of armes tooke from yours, and having ſlaine, and taken priſoners all their Citizens, reſerved ſuch of their wives and children as they pleaſed, unto their luſt, to your perpetuall infamy and ſhame.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
