<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the tryal of Charles Bateman, chirurgeon, for high- treason, in conspiring the death of the late King and the subversion of the government &amp;c. who was tryed and found guilty, at Justice-Hall in the Old Bayly, on the 9th of December, 1685. The tryals of John Holland and William Davis, for conspiring against, violently assaulting, and without any warrantable cause, imprisoning William Chancey ... who were tryed and found guilty ... on the 10th of December, 1685. As also the tryals of John Holland, William Davis, and Agnes Wearing, for a notorious burglary and felony ... in the house of Leonel Gatford ... who were tryed and found guilty ... on the 11th of December, 1685.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75778</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42633</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875499</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875499</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152161</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A75778)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152161)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2281:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the tryal of Charles Bateman, chirurgeon, for high- treason, in conspiring the death of the late King and the subversion of the government &amp;c. who was tryed and found guilty, at Justice-Hall in the Old Bayly, on the 9th of December, 1685. The tryals of John Holland and William Davis, for conspiring against, violently assaulting, and without any warrantable cause, imprisoning William Chancey ... who were tryed and found guilty ... on the 10th of December, 1685. As also the tryals of John Holland, William Davis, and Agnes Wearing, for a notorious burglary and felony ... in the house of Leonel Gatford ... who were tryed and found guilty ... on the 11th of December, 1685.</title>
                  <author>Davis, William, d. 1685, defendant.</author>
                  <author>Wearing, Agnes, d. 1685, defendant.</author>
                  <author>Holland, John, defendant.</author>
                  <author>Bateman, Charles, d. 1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for D. Mallet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXV [1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bateman, Charles, d. 1685.</term>
               <term>Trials (Treason) --  England.</term>
               <term>Trials (Duress) --  England.</term>
               <term>Trials (Burglary) --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152161:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF THE TRYAL OF <hi>Charles Bateman,</hi> Chirurgeon, FOR High-Treaſon, IN CONSPIRING <hi>The Death of the late King</hi> And the Subverſion of the Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Who was Tryed and found Guilty, at <hi>Juſtice-Hall</hi> in the <hi>Old Bayly,</hi> on the 9th. of <hi>December,</hi> 1685.</p>
            <p>THE TRYALS OF <hi>John Holland</hi> and <hi>William Davis,</hi> For Conſpiring againſt, violently Aſſaulting, and without any warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Cauſe, Impriſoning <hi>William Chancey,</hi> Citizen and Mercer of <hi>London;</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort a Sum of Money from him; who were Tryed and found Guilty at <hi>Juſtice-Hall</hi> in the <hi>Old-Bayly,</hi> on the 10th. of <hi>December,</hi> 1685.</p>
            <p>As alſo Tryals of <hi>John Holland, William Davis,</hi> and <hi>Agnes Wearing,</hi> for a Notorious Burglary and Felony, Committed in the Houſe of <hi>Leonel Gat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> a Miniſter in <hi>Lime-ſtreet, London,</hi> and ſtealing Plate, Money and Rings, to the value of 300 <hi>l.</hi> who were Tryed and found Guilty, at <hi>Juſtice-Hall</hi> in the <hi>Old-Bayly,</hi> on the 11th of <hi>December.</hi> 1685.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>D. Mallet,</hi> MDCLXXXV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="trial_account">
            <div type="trial">
               <pb facs="tcp:152161:2"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152161:2"/>
               <head>THE TRYAL OF <hi>Charles Bateman</hi> Chirurgeon, FOR High-Treaſon: And <hi>John Holland, William Davis,</hi> and <hi>Agnes Wearing,</hi> for a Notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Felony and Burglary.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Seſſions</hi> of Peace, <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> and Goal Delivery of <hi>Newgate,</hi> for the City of <hi>London</hi> and County of <hi>Middleſex;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at <hi>Juſtice Hall</hi> in the <hi>Old Bayly,</hi> on the 9th. of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1685. <hi>Charles Bateman,</hi> againſt whom, an Indictment of <hi>High-Treaſon</hi> had been found, for Conſpiring the Death of the late King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was brought in the Cuſtody of the Keeper of <hi>Newgate</hi> in order to his Arraignment; and being ordered to hold up his hand, he deſired that he might firſt ſay ſomething for himſelf, in order to put off his Tryal, but was told by Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi> he muſt plead before he could be heard; whereupon deſiring to know whether he might have the ſame advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage after his pleading as before, as to gain longer time for his Tryal, and being anſwered he might, he held up his hand, and then the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was read:</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bateman</hi> pleaded not Guilty, and deſired his Tryal might be put off, ſaying, <hi>He was not prepared to make his Defence,</hi> and therefore prayed a longer time, ſaying, <hi>He had been cloſe Priſoner for the ſpace of ten VVeeks, and was over and above very much indiſpoſed;</hi> and further alledged, <hi>he had had no Notice nor any Pannel of the</hi> Jury; as for notice of Tryal, he was anſwered, that it was not uſual to give any in that Court, but that he ought to have expected it, and prepared for it accordingly, and as for the Pannel it was not denyed him; then he prayed a Coppy of the Indictment, but was told it could not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; and upon his further alledging his unpreparedneſs and no notice of Tryal, and the like, the King's Council urged that he had opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity enough to take notice of his Tryal, for that it was upon an Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the precedent <hi>Seſſions:</hi> Then he asked what time he might have between his Arraignment and Tryal, and was anſwered, as much as would ſtand with the conveniency of the Court; and after ſeveral hours
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152161:3"/>
Reſpite, he a ſecond time was brought to the Bar, and then upon his humble requeſt, Pen, Ink, and Paper was allowed him and his Son to aſſiſt him; and then were ſworn to try the Iſſue,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Aley</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Williams</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Cannum</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Patrick Barret</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Palmer</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Raynor.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Rhediſh</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Lilburn.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Daniel Fouls</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter Floyer</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lawrence Cole</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Cooper.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And he making no exceptions to them, then the Indictment was read.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="indictment">
                           <head>The Jurors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>THAT <hi>Charles Bateman,</hi> late of the Pariſh of St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> in the Ward of Farringdon without, <hi>Lond.</hi> Chirurgeon, as a falſe Traytor, againſt the moſt Illuſtrious and Excellent Prince, <hi>Charles</hi> the Second; late King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Defender of the Faith, and his Natural Lord; not having the fear of God in his Heart, nor weighing the Duty of his Allegience; but being moved and ſeduced by the inſtigation of the Devil, the Cordial Love, and true Due and Natural Obedience, which a true and Faithful Subject of our late Lord the King, towards him ſhould, and of Right, ought to bear, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether withdrawing and Practiſing, and with all his ſtrength, intending the Peace and common Tranquillity of this Kingdom, to diſquiet, and diſturb, and War and Rebellion againſt our late Lord the King, within this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to flir up, move, and procure, and the Government of our late Lord the King, of this Kingdom to ſubvert, and our ſaid late Lord the King, from the Stile, Title, Honour, and Kingly Name, of the Imperial Crown of this Kingdom, to depoſe and deprive, and our ſaid late Lord the King, to Death and final Deſtruction to bring and put, the <hi>30th.</hi> Day of <hi>May,</hi> in the 35th Year of his Reign, and divers other days and times, as well before as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, at the Pariſh and Ward aforeſaid, Falſely, Maliciouſly, Deviliſhly, and Traytorouſly, with divers other Rebels and Traytors to the <hi>Jurors</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kown, did Conſpire, Compaſs, imagine, and intend our ſaid late Lord the King, then his Supream and Natural Lord; not only of his Kingly State, Title, Power, and Government of his Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> to deprive and depoſe, but alſo our ſaid late Lord the King, to kill, and to Death, to bring and put, and the Antient Government of this Kingdom, to change, alter, and ſubvert; and a miſerable Slaughter amongſt the Subjects of our ſaid late Lord the King, to cauſe and procure, and Inſurrection and Rebellion, againſt our ſaid late Lord the King, to procure, and aſſiſt, and the ſame moſt Wicked, Treaſons and Traytorous Conſpiracies, Compaſſings, Imaginations and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes aforeſaid to effect, and bring to paſs. He the ſaid <hi>Charles Bateman,</hi> as a falſe Traytor, then and there, (to wit) the ſaid <hi>30th.</hi> Day of May, in the 35th. Year aforeſaid, and divers other days and times, as well before as afterwards; at the Pariſh and Ward aforeſaid, Falſely, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfully, moſt Wickedly, and Traytorouſly, Did promiſe and undertake to the ſaid other falſe Rebells and Traytors then and there being preſent: <hi>That</hi> He the ſaid
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152161:3"/>
                              <hi>Charles Bateman,</hi> would be aſſiſting and aiding, in the taking and Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the Perſon of our ſaid late Lord the King, and intaking and ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the <hi>Royal Pallace</hi> of <hi>White-Hall,</hi> againſt the Duty of his Allegience, againſt the Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and againſt the form of the Statute, in this Caſe made and provided, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Phips,</hi> Council for the King opened the Nature of it, and was ſeconded by Mr, <hi>Serjeant Selby</hi> and Mr. <hi>Charles Moloy,</hi> after which, Mr. <hi>Joſias Keeling</hi> was ſworn, whoſe Evidence was, that he had been at divers meetings and Conſults, where the methods had been propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the purpoſes aforeſaid, and more particular one time with <hi>Rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bold</hi> the <hi>Maltſter,</hi> ſince Executed for <hi>High-Treaſon,</hi> and that then, three Papers were produced by <hi>Rumbold</hi> and opened, containing the Moddel of the Deſign, to divide the City into Twenty Parts, and to raiſe Five Hundred men in each Part, to be under one Chief, and Nine or Ten Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bordinates whom he ſhould appoint, the Names of the Lanes and Streets of each Diviſion being likewiſe inſerted therein; and at that time <hi>Rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bold</hi> propoſed the Buſineſs of the <hi>Rye Houſe,</hi> ſaying, <hi>He had a Houſe very convenient to plant men in, to ſeize the King in his return from New-market,</hi> but that he ſomewhat boggled about the Killing the Poſtillion, which had been propoſed the better to ſtop the Coach, becauſe it look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed too much like an Exploit in cold Blood: He further depoſed, that he had been at divers other places where it had been diſcourſed to the ſame effect, and that Mr. <hi>Bateman</hi> was looked upon as a Perſon fixing to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage one Diviſion in order to an Inſurrection, to ſeize the <hi>Tower, City,</hi> &amp;c. This being the Sum of Mr. <hi>Keeling</hi>'s Evidence; Mr. <hi>Bateman</hi> ſaid, that what he had ſworn, did not affect or charge any Treaſon upon him; and was anſwered by the Court that it did not, and bid the Jury take notice, that what Mr. <hi>Keeling</hi> had ſworn, was only to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie in General, and did not affect the Priſoner in particular.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Thomas Lee</hi> was ſworn, and gave Evidence, that he being made acquainted with the Deſign by Mr. <hi>Goodenough, &amp;c.</hi> and how the City was to be divided into Twenty Parts and mannaged; and being asked who was a fit man to mannage one Part, he nominated Mr. <hi>Bateman,</hi> and thereupon was deſired to go to him, and ſpeak with him about it as from Mr. <hi>Goodenough;</hi> and when he came to diſcourſe him about that affair, he apprehended very plainly, that he was no ſtranger to it nor boggled to give his aſſent, and ſeemed much deſirous to ſpeak with Mr. <hi>Goodenough</hi> about it: That he likewiſe went one day to the late Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Houſe with Mr. <hi>Bateman;</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bateman,</hi> after he had had ſome Diſcourſe with one of the Duke's Servants, came to him and told him, the Duke was willing to ingage in the Buſineſs, and aſſur'd him, that he had divers Horſes kept in the Country, to be in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs when matters ſhould come to Extremity; and from thence he went with him to the <hi>King</hi>'s-<hi>Head-Tavern,</hi> and there had diſcourſe to the ſame effect; and from thence, they came to the <hi>Devil-Tavern</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> where Mr. <hi>Bateman</hi> propoſed the ſeizing the <hi>City, Tower, Savoy, White-Hall,</hi> and the Perſon of the late King, and promiſed not to be wanting therein. At another time, he met him at the <hi>Half-Moon Tavern</hi> in <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreet,</hi> where diſcourſing about the Condition th- Conſpirators
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152161:4"/>
were in. As to the intended Inſurrection, he ſaid, <hi>If he could but ſee a Cloud as big as a man</hi>'s <hi>hand, he would not be wanting to Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy his Intereſt,</hi> and that there were other Diſcourſes tending to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, but were broke off by the coming in of one <hi>John Allmeger,</hi> before whom, Mr. <hi>Bateman</hi> would not diſcourſe, becauſe he knew not of his coming.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Lee</hi> being asked the Deſign of that meeting, replyed it was upon the Account of carrying on the Conſpiracie, and that Mr. <hi>Bateman</hi> had told him, that he intended to take a houſe near the <hi>Tower,</hi> to place men in, in order to ſurprize it, and that he had held divers Conferences with ſome Sea Captains on that affair; and that he had been with them at <hi>Coffee-Houſes,</hi> &amp;c. at ſundry other times, but there to prevent Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, they ſpoke of the Deſign at a great diſtance.</p>
               <p>To this Evidence, Mr. <hi>Bateman</hi> objected that if he had been conſcous of what was laid to his Charge he was fit for <hi>Bedlam,</hi> ſaying, <hi>He won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd if he had heard him ſpeak ſuch words, he had not accuſed him ſooner;</hi> but was anſwered, that Mr. <hi>Goodenough</hi> was not to be had till after the Rebellion in the <hi>Weſt;</hi> and that <hi>Lee</hi>'s ſingle Teſtimony in Caſe of <hi>High-Treaſon</hi> in ſo high a Nature, was not ſufficient.</p>
               <p>Then Mr. <hi>Richard Goodenough</hi> was called, who being ſworn, depoſed that being in compaay with Mr. <hi>Bateman</hi> (to the beſt of his remembrance) at the <hi>Kings-Head</hi> Tavern in St. <hi>Swithings-Alley</hi> near the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> and having ſome Diſcourſe about the intended Inſurrection, and of <hi>Wade</hi> and others that had engaged to promote it. Mr. <hi>Bateman</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>approved of the Deſign, but promiſed to uſe his Intereſt in raiſing men; and not only to be aſſiſting in the Diviſion allotted him, but in ſurpriſing the</hi> City, Savoy, <hi>&amp;c. and in driving the Guards out of</hi> Town. To this he objected, that he was not at the <hi>Kings-Head</hi> with <hi>Goodenough,</hi> to which Mr. <hi>Goodenough</hi> replyed, <hi>He had not ſworn poſſitive to the place, though he verily believed that was the place; but however, as to the Diſcourſe and Words then ſpoken by Mr.</hi> Bateman <hi>he was poſſitive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Evidence being thus full againſt Mr. <hi>Bateman,</hi> and he liberty granted him to make what defence he could, he deſired that Sir <hi>Robert Adams</hi> might be heard, in relation to a falſe report the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lee</hi> had raiſed of Sir <hi>Robert</hi> and others, and Sir <hi>Robert</hi> being in Court, gave Evidence that there had been a report abroad ſaid to be raiſed by <hi>Mr. Lee,</hi> that he <hi>(viz.)</hi> Mr. <hi>Lee had beaten three Knights, and that Mr.</hi> Lee <hi>had came to him and asked his Pardon, acknowledging the thing in it ſelf was altogether falſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the ſame purpoſe Sir <hi>Simon Lewis</hi> was called, but appeared not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ames Child</hi> being called by Mr. <hi>Bateman,</hi> to teſtifie his knowledge of Mr. <hi>Lee;</hi> and being asked what he could ſay againſt him, Declared, <hi>That he knew nothing to the contrary, but Mr.</hi> Lee <hi>was an honeſt man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One <hi>Baker</hi> being called by Mr. <hi>Bateman,</hi> to teſtifie that Mr. <hi>Lee</hi> would have ſubborned him againſt him to his prejudice, ſome Years ſince, of which he had made an <hi>Affidavit</hi> before Sir. <hi>William Turner,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> not then appearing in Court, he deſired Sir <hi>William Turner</hi> to give ſome account of <hi>Baker</hi>'s Examination, which he ſaid Sir <hi>William</hi> had taken, but it being above two Years ſince, Sir <hi>William</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, <hi>He could not charge his memory with any of the Particulars contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152161:4"/>Mr. <hi>Tompkins</hi> Sir <hi>William Turner</hi>'s Clerk being called, and asked what he could ſay concerning any Examination of <hi>Baker</hi>'s taken before Sir <hi>William,</hi> that related to <hi>Lee;</hi> he ſaid, <hi>there was an Examination ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> Anno 1683. <hi>wherein Mr.</hi> Lee <hi>was mentioned; but to the beſt of his Remembrance it was returned before the King and Council, and he could not give any account of the Particulars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then Mr. <hi>Bateman</hi> deſired to know upon what Statute he was Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and was informed by the Court, That <hi>the</hi> Treaſon <hi>wherewith he ſtood charged, was Comprehended within the</hi> 25th. of Edward <hi>the</hi> 3 d. <hi>and the</hi> 13th <hi>of</hi> Car. 2. <hi>by</hi> Overt-Act; and having little more to ſay in his own Defence. After a favourable hearing of all he had materially to offer, and his Son having been allowed by the Court to aſſiſt him, in looking over his Notes, and calling his Witneſſes, by reaſon he through ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs pretended himſelf incapable. Then the <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice</hi> of the <hi>King</hi>'s-<hi>Bench</hi> Sum'd up the Evidence at large, and omitted nothing that might be for the advantage of the Priſoner, whereby the matter was fairly, fully, and clearly left to the Jury; and thereupon Mr. <hi>Bateman</hi> was taken from the Bar, after which, the other Priſoners being called and Tryed, and the Jury ready to go forth to conſider of their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, Mr. <hi>Bateman</hi>'s Daughter came in and beſought the Court, <hi>that</hi> Baker, <hi>whom ſhe ſaid ſhe had found out, might be heard againſt Mr.</hi> Lee, but Mr. <hi>Lee</hi> being gone, and the Tryal already over, the King<hi>'s</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil oppoſed it, unleſs Mr. <hi>Lee</hi> could be found (which he Could not be at that time) and the Court having deliver'd their Opinion that it was not convenient to examine any Witneſs after the Jury had received their Charge, it being a very ill preſident and of dangerous Conſequence; yet ſome of the Jury deſiring it, the Court to prevent any Objections that might be made, conſented, and <hi>Baker</hi> had leave to ſpeak, whoſe Evidence was, <hi>that being in Company with Mr.</hi> Lee, <hi>ſome time in the Year</hi> 1683. <hi>and diſcourſing about divers matters, he bad him go to the ſign of the</hi> Peacock, <hi>and to the</hi> Angel <hi>and</hi> Crown, <hi>to a</hi> Chirurgeon, <hi>and a</hi> Linnen-Draper <hi>whom he named, the former of which he remembred to be the Priſoner, and to inſinuate himſelf into their Company and diſcourſe them; and when he demanded of Mr.</hi> Lee <hi>to what end he ſhould do it, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout what he ſhould diſcourſe them, he told him it might be about State Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and by that means he would find a way to make him a great man; and when he excuſed his attempting to intrude into ſuch Company as was above him, he being but a Shooe-maker, Mr.</hi> Lee <hi>told him he knew that, he kept Company with ſuch, and ſuch men, and why could he not as well do it with thoſe he had mentioned,</hi> and of this he ſaid his Examination was taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sir <hi>William Turner;</hi> but this being nothing to the purpoſe, but was rather looked upon as a Deſign, Mr. <hi>Lee</hi> had to make a diſcovery of the Conſpiracie, if he could have procured further Evidence to have Corroborated his own, and <hi>Baker</hi> being looked upon as a broken Fellow and that he lodged near the <hi>Seſſions Houſe,</hi> and yet came not in before though often called, the conſideration of the whole matter was left to the Jury, and an Officer being ſvvorn to attend them went out, and after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout half an hours debating that, and what elſe was before them, gave in their Verdict, <hi>that</hi> Charles Bateman <hi>then at the</hi> Bar, <hi>was Guilty of the</hi> High-Treaſon <hi>as laid in the Indictment,</hi> which Verdict was accordingly Record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Priſoner re-conveyed to <hi>Newgate;</hi> and being again brought to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152161:5"/>
                  <hi>Juſtice-Hall,</hi> on <hi>Friday</hi> the 11th. of <hi>December,</hi> in order to receive Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; and upon holding up his hand, being asked <hi>What he could ſay for himſelf, why the Court ſhould not give Judgment againſt him according to the</hi> Law: <hi>He deſired to know whether Mr.</hi> Goodenough <hi>was fully pardoned, and was told, that as for the Out-lawrey he was pardoned, and that his Pardon had been allowed and approved of in that Court, and in the Court of</hi> King's-Bench, <hi>and for any thing elſe he was not Proſecuted:</hi> Then he ſaid <hi>his Opinion was altogether for Monarchy, and that he hoped he ſhould have an Advocate with the King</hi> but; had nothing more material to offer.</p>
               <p>Then Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi> after having ſpoke ſeveral things in aggravation of that great Crime, whereof, after a fair and favourable Tryal, he was Convicted; adviſed him not to flatter himſelf with hopes of Life, and thereby delay his Repentance neceſſary for his future happineſs, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the Sentence, which was, <hi>That he ſhould return to the place from whence he came, from thence be drawn to the place of Execution, there to be hang'd by the Neck, and whilſt alive be Cut down, and his Bowels to be taken out and burnt; his Head to be ſevered from his Body, and his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy divided into four Parts, and that his Head and Quarters be diſpoſed of, at the Pleaſure of the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this, he prayed a Divine might have leave to come to him, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe his Relations, which being allowed he departed the Court, and was on <hi>Friday</hi> the 18th. of <hi>December,</hi> Executed at <hi>Tyburn</hi> according to Sentence.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="trial">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152161:5"/>
               <head>The <hi>Substance</hi> of the Tryal of of <hi>John Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>William Davis,</hi> who were Tryed and committed, for Conſpiring againſt, and falſely impriſoning <hi>William Chancey, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen</hi> and <hi>Mercer</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> at <hi>Juſtice-Hall</hi> in the <hi>Old Bayly.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>On <date>the 10th of <hi>December,</hi> 1685.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>UPon an Indictment found againſt <hi>Edward Hays. William Price, John Holland,</hi> and <hi>William Davis,</hi> for Conſpiring againſt, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently Aſſaulting, and forcibly Impriſoning, for the ſpace of ſix hours the Perſon of <hi>William Chancey, Citizen</hi> and <hi>Mercer</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> againſt his will, and without any warrentable Cauſe, whom they falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Charged with uttering divers Treaſonable Words, to extort from him a Sum of money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Holland</hi> and <hi>William Davis,</hi> were brought in the Cuſtody of the Keeper of <hi>Newgate,</hi> to <hi>Juſtice-Hall</hi> in the <hi>Old-Bayly,</hi> where upon their Arraignment they pleaded not Guilty, and deſired their Tryal might be delayed, ſeeing they were not prepared to make their Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and were thereupon taken from the Bar, but on the 11th. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> 1685. the Lord Mayor, Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Tulſe,</hi> and other Aldermen, being preſent they were brought up a ſecond time, and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to look to their Challenges, but making no Exceptions the Jury was Sworn, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Meridale</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Benjamin Boltby</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Baly</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Barns</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Bromfield</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Samuel Linn</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward Hemſtead</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Longland</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Samuel Biſhop</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>James Fern</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Wheatly</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Phelps</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Indictment being read a ſecond time, the Council for the King opened the Nature of the Fact, of which the Priſoners ſtood accuſed in all it's unparralled Circumſtances, and then to proceed to Swear Mr. <hi>Chancey,</hi> who gave Evidence, that on <hi>Saturday</hi> the 28th. day of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> laſt, he was informed that a Boy had been ſent from the <hi>King</hi>'s-<hi>Arms</hi> Tavern in <hi>Lawrence-Lane London,</hi> about Four of the Clock in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, to let him know that there were two Gentlemen that deſired to ſpeak with him, whereupon he went, and being ſhewed where they were, found them to be <hi>Hays</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> the former of which he had ſome ſmall Acquaintance with, he having been once a Citizen, but as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152161:6"/>
for the latter at that time he knew him not. <hi>Hays</hi> after a Complement had paſſed, deſired to ſpeak with him in private, but <hi>Holland</hi> whom <hi>Hays</hi> called Captain <hi>Holland,</hi> was ſomewhat againſt it, ſaying, <hi>they might ſpeak what they had to ſay in his preſence,</hi> but in the end he retir'd, when <hi>Hay's</hi> in a melancholy Tone, cryed out, <hi>O! Mr.</hi> Chancey <hi>I am the unfortunateſt man alive, for being the other day in the Company of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, I chanced to let fall ſome words ſaid to be ſpoken by a Merchant in</hi> London, <hi>which proved to be</hi> Treaſon, <hi>and with which I am charged, and am now a Priſoner to the Captain, and therefore am obliged to produce you as my Author;</hi> upon this Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> being a little ſurprized, as not knoing to what it might tend; and not being conſcious of any thing of that Nature, replyed, <hi>He had never ſpoken any treaſonable Words, and that he knew not what he meant,</hi> whereupon as probable it had been agreed, <hi>Holland</hi> came in and demanded of <hi>Hays, if that was the perſon,</hi> meaning Mr. <hi>Chancey, that had ſpoke the words,</hi> to whom <hi>Hays</hi> replyed he was: At which <hi>Holland</hi> told him <hi>He was his Priſoner, and muſt go with him to</hi> White-Hall, <hi>before the Secretary of State;</hi> then Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> demanding ing to ſee his Warrent, he told him <hi>He was a Captain of the Guard,</hi> and that a Captain of the King's Guard had power without a Warrant to ſeize any perſon for High-Treaſon, with which he was charged; then Mr <hi>Chancy</hi> deſired to ſend for ſome friends, but <hi>Holland</hi> would not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to that, telling him he muſt inſtantly go with him out of the damn'd Factious City, as he term'd it, but withal that he would call at the <hi>Crown</hi> tavern without <hi>Temple-Bar;</hi> whereupon they ſtopping in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> found an opportunity to ſend a perſon to his Brother, to let him underſtand what had happened, and that he was going to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> but ſhould ſtay at the <hi>Crown</hi> Tavern, and thither he deſired he would come to him, and all the way as they were going, <hi>Holland</hi> railed and curſed <hi>Hayes,</hi> that he being one of his Majeſties Servants, ſhould be ſuch a Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an as to conceal Treaſon, but <hi>Holland</hi> underſtanding that Mr. <hi>Chancy</hi> had ſent for his Brother, and fearing the buſineſs might be diſcovered, would not ſuffer him to ſtay at the <hi>Crown</hi> Tavern nor ſend word where they were gone, but cauſed the Coach to drive to the <hi>Fountain</hi> Tavern in the <hi>Strand</hi> being nigh the <hi>Savoy,</hi> where he ſaid he could have ſeveral Files of Muſquettiers to ſecure him if need required, and there it was that after ſome threats of Soldiers, Meſſengers, and Impriſonment, and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Oaths that he would run him through if he offered to make an eſcape: <hi>Hays</hi> began to tamper with him, leting him know that the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs yet might be huſh'd up by ſtopping the Captain's mouth with a Sum of Money, ſince none but he could detect it; but finding him ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely averſe to it, and whilſt they were thus diſcourſing, word was brought up to <hi>Holland</hi> that there were two of his Kinſmen that would ſpeak with him, and accordingly they were brought in and we were ordered to take no notice of the buſineſs in hand; they diſcourſed of the Rebellion in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> he took them to be <hi>Welſh,</hi> for the ſame time (as he gueſſed) they talked that Language; they being gone, and he not willing to give any money, to <hi>White-Hall</hi> we muſt go; but Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> obſerved that <hi>Holland</hi> paid two Reckonings for a Company in the Houſe then preſent, beſide their own; when we came to <hi>VVhite-Hall-Gate, Hays</hi> cryed, and ſtamped, and deſired for God's ſake we might not go in, for if we ſhould, he and his family were certainly ruin'd, for he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152161:6"/>
had two places at Court worth Eight hundred pounds, and he ſhould looſe them both, beſides being Pis'<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon by every body if this matter ſhould come publick, therefore deſired we might go to the <hi>Swan</hi> Tavern in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which accordingly we did, there they both argued that it would be for both our Intereſt to comply with the Captain in his propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal beforementioned, that is, to give <hi>Holland</hi> Two hundred pounds, for that it was in His Breaſt alone at preſent, but if we ſhould be carryed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>Secretary,</hi> or put to the hands of a <hi>Meſſenger,</hi> it would be then out of his power; but Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> ſtill perſiſted that he would not give any thing, whereupon to <hi>White-Hall</hi> we muſt go (ſays <hi>Holland</hi>) in order to be Examined, and then the ſaid <hi>Hays</hi> declared that I was the perſon, which the Merchant ſhould ſay ſpoke thoſe Words; however he was never brought before any body, albeit he was carryed to ſeveral places in <hi>White-Hall</hi> for that: <hi>Holland</hi> pretended the <hi>Secretary</hi> was buſie; but after ſome ſtay, he ſaid he would deliver us into the hands of a <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger</hi> which he was informed was at the <hi>Fountain</hi> Tavern in the <hi>Strand,</hi> whom (as he pretended) he had ſent for when we were there before, and accordingly thither he carryed us; but there being no <hi>Meſſenger,</hi> he then ſayed he would ſend for one, and accordingly Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> thought that <hi>Halland</hi> had ſent for one, but <hi>Hays</hi> and he ſtill continued their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions to give two hundred pounds, but finding him unwilling to give any thing, Captain <hi>Holland</hi> draws up a pretended Information of High-Treaſon againſt him only, which being done, word was brought that two of the Gentlemen that were in Company with them the laſt Night were in the houſe; <hi>Holland</hi> deſired them to come in, <hi>Hays</hi> in the mean time called Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> aſide, and ſtrongly perſwaded him to comply with the Captains demands, ſaying, that if he had not money enough, he would prevail with the Captain to take his Bond, and that he himſelf would be bound with him, and then he would be no more than One hundred pounds out; however the two perſons being come in, and as was afterwards inform'd, one was Mr. <hi>William Davis,</hi> and the other Mr. <hi>William Price</hi> whereupon Mr <hi>Holland</hi> reads the Information to them, which he had juſt before written, and told him that <hi>Price</hi> was a <hi>Barriſter;</hi> then <hi>Price</hi> did affirm that the words were High-Treaſon, and perſwaded him to comply, ſaying, it was the beſt hundred pounds that ever he parted with in his life, adding if he were innocent, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays, the neglect of his buſineſs, and the charges would amount to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſum; likewiſe <hi>Davis</hi> that came in with him, perſwaded him to it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and <hi>Holland</hi> ſwore he would ſend him to Priſon without carrying him before a Juſtice of Peace; and added, that one <hi>Delawne</hi> had been in <hi>Newgate</hi> for ſeveral Years and never knew for what, and that he was like to lye there as long as he lived, and that <hi>Corniſh</hi> was hanged for only hearing a Treaſonable <hi>DECLARATION</hi> read, and that his Guilt was greater, having ſpoken words at length, finding by their Diſcourſe they would ſtick at no Oath for intereſt or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, and knowing it was <hi>Sunday</hi> Morning, and not knowing what manner of men he had to deal with, nor what they might ſwear falſely againſt him, tired by hurrying him up and down as aforeſaid, and ſomewhat affrighted with their menaces at the reiterated importunity of <hi>Hays,</hi> who pretended himſelf to be in the greateſt Conſternation ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, for fear the buſineſs ſhould come to light, and in hopes to be rid
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152161:7"/>
of his dangerous Company, that he might at leaſure conſider better what he had to do; he conſented to enter in to a Bond with <hi>Hays</hi> in the Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of 400 <hi>l.</hi> for the payment of 200, and the Bonds to be made to <hi>Holland;</hi> but this would not be accepted till he farther conſented to ſign a Warrant of Attorney, to confeſs Judgment upon the Pond. This being concluded upon, <hi>Holland</hi> ſent his Foot-boy to call up Mr.— a Neighbouring <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vener</hi> to make the Writings, it being then between Two and Three of the Clock on <hi>Sunday</hi> Morning, <hi>Who was very unwilling to riſe at ſo unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable an hour;</hi> but being told there were divers Gentlemen at the <hi>Fountain</hi> that muſt needs ſpeak with him, to draw ſome Writings upon an urgent occaſion, he at laſt went, and there found <hi>Holland, Hays Davis, Price,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Chancey,</hi> and that the Inſtructions were ready drawn up, which he took into his own Note-book, and ſo went home to draw up the Writings, where he had not been long e'r <hi>Price</hi> came to him, and told him that he muſt Date the Bond any day in <hi>Trinity Term</hi> laſt, the buſineſs ſo requiring, whereupon he Dated it the 21th. of <hi>June,</hi> ſo that it became payable the next day after it was ſigned. This the <hi>Scrivener</hi> ignorant of the Conſideration thinking pretty hard, and that a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was to be confeſſed upon it without a Defeazance, made ſome ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to do it; but <hi>Price</hi> aſſuring him it was ſo agreed for ſundry Reaſons beſt known to themſelves, he brought the Writings, and ſpared not to ſay as much in the Company, but Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> not contradicting it the Bonds were ſigned, but the Warrents of <hi>Attorney</hi> being purpoſed, he ſcrupled to ſign it, and whiſpering <hi>Holland</hi> in the Ear, ſaid, <hi>What need this, will not my Bond ſuffice?</hi> but he and his Accomplices crying out, <hi>Are not we agreed? Is it not ſo agreed?</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Hays</hi> without bogling ſigning on his part, Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> with ſome Reluctancy did the like, and then the <hi>Scrivener</hi> propoſing it was convenient to have Releaſes to Bar any former Conſideration for which the Bond might be given, they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly aſſented to it, and it was ſigned by <hi>Holland</hi> bearing Date before the Bond, whereupon the <hi>Scrivener</hi> was diſcharged, and Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> had leave to go about his buſineſs, and then Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> further depoſed that on <hi>Monday the</hi> 30th. of <hi>November, Holland</hi> ſent his Foot-boy with a Note directed to Mr. <hi>Chancey,</hi> at his houſe in St. <hi>Lawrence Lane,</hi> inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him that he had a preſent occaſion for 20 <hi>l.</hi> and that he muſt needs furniſh him with that Sum, as likewiſe with Silk to make him a Cap, a Night-Gown and a pair of Slippers, promiſing to uſe him very kindly in the payment of the reſt, and to take out part of it in Wares, which was confirmed by the Foot-boy being ſworn, but Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> by this time being better adviſed, and finding it was a Cheat, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by the <hi>Boy</hi> where his Maſter was, under pretence of furniſhing him with the money and goods he had ſent for, found means to ſecure him; who being carried before a Judge, was upon the Oath of Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> Committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and <hi>Price</hi> being ſoon after taken, was Committed to the <hi>King</hi>'s-<hi>Bench</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards together with <hi>Hays</hi> was bailed to appear at the <hi>King</hi>'s-<hi>Bench,</hi> as it was ſuggeſted to the Court. To this <hi>Holland</hi> pleaded he only took the Bonds to oblige the Partys to appear before the Secretary of State, and that he did it to ſave himſelf harmleſs, there being no Conſideration why Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> ſhould be otherwiſe obliged to him, and that he had
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152161:7"/>
made his report of the matter to a perſon of Quality, who told him he had over done his buſineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Davis</hi> pleaded that he was ignorant of the matter as to the contriving of it, and only came in by chance as he was going to his Lodging that was near the <hi>Fountain Tavern,</hi> and was deſired to ſtay as a Witneſs to the Writings; whereupon <hi>Holland</hi>'s Foot-boy being ſworn, gave Evidence, that he had ſeen <hi>Davis</hi> paſs through the <hi>King</hi>'s-<hi>Arms Tavern</hi> in St. <hi>Lawrence-Lane,</hi> when his Maſter and Mr. <hi>Hays</hi> were above with Mr. <hi>Chancey,</hi> and farther that he had after that been to look for him to come to his Maſter. This Objection being anſwered, he proceeded to intimate that Mr. <hi>Chancey</hi> was a diſaffected perſon, and that <hi>Hays</hi> had affirmed he heard him ſpeak theſe words, <hi>viz. That the Rebellion in</hi> Scotland <hi>was no Rebellion, but a mere trick to get money, or to that effect;</hi> whereupon Mr <hi>Chancey</hi> called ſeveral worthy perſons to teſtifie his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, and firſt Sir <hi>Edward Waldon</hi> with whom he had ſerved his time, who declared that he had all along behaved himſelf civilly and modeſtly, and that he ever looked upon him to be a very Loyal Perſon, and well affected to the Government; adding, that he had been ſo faithful a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that he could not enough commend him.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Robert Adams</hi> being deſired to teſtifie his knowledge on this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, declared, that he had known him many years, and that he always took him to be a very honeſt Loyal man.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Brough,</hi> the fore-man of the Grand Jury for <hi>London,</hi> teſtified the ſame as did ſome others of known <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Integrity;</hi> ſo that the Jury receiving the Charge by Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi> in which all was moſt exactly ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med up that had been ſworn againſt the Priſoners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Defence they had made for themſelves, they withdrew, and within the ſpace of half an hour gave in their Verdict, that <hi>John Holland</hi> and <hi>William Davis</hi> were Guilty of the Conſpiracie, Aſſault, and falſe Impriſonment, as laid in the Indictment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trial">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152161:8"/>
               <head>THE TRYALS OF <hi>John Holland, William Davis</hi> and <hi>Agnes Wearing,</hi> for a Felony and Burglary: Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the Houſe of Mr. <hi>Leonel Gatford,</hi> Miniſter in <hi>Lyme-ſtreet,</hi> on the 11th. of <hi>September,</hi> 1685.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JOhn Holland</hi> and <hi>William Davis,</hi> were a ſecond time Indicted for a Felony and Burglary, Committed in the Houſe of Mr. <hi>Leonel Gatford</hi> of <hi>Lyme-ſtreet London,</hi> in the Pariſh of St. <hi>Dionis Back-Church,</hi> on the 11th. of <hi>September</hi> laſt, together with <hi>Agnes Wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> as acceſſary, before and after the Felony and Burglary committed; The Goods layed in the Indictment were Sixteen ſilver Spoons, Nine ſilver Porrengers, Four ſilver Salts, Three ſilver Pots, Two ſilver Plates, Five ſilver Candleſticks, a ſilver Skimer, Four ſilver Boxes, One ſilver Tanckard, One ſilver Ladle, Six Diamond Rings, Twenty plain Rings, and other Plate of value; Thirty Guineas, Forty pounds in Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In all upward in value of Three hundred Pounds: To which Indictment, the Priſoners having ſeverally Pleaded not Guilty, put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the Jury for their Tryals.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>The Jurors were</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Wakley,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>George Reeve,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Joſhua Sabin,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Jagman,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Auſtin,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Job Harris,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gilbert Eaſt,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Martin Simpſon,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>—<hi>Maſters,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Stevens,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Newſtrop.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Oliver,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Jury Sworn and the Indictment a ſecond time read, Mr. <hi>Gatford,</hi> gave Evidence, that about ſix of the Clock in the Afternoon, going to Prayers and leaving his Wife and his Maid in his houſe (which Maid was <hi>Agnes Wearing</hi>) and returning about Eight of the Clock the ſame Evening, found his houſe rifled and his Wife much abuſed; the things mentioned in the Indictment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Being at that time ſtolen.</p>
               <p>Mrs. <hi>Gatford</hi> gave Evidence, that On <hi>Friday</hi> the 11th. of <hi>September,</hi> about Five or Six a Clock at Night, in the abſence of her Husband, ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>body knocking at the Door, ſhe ſent <hi>Agnes Wearing</hi> (the Priſoner at the Bar, being her Maid) down to ſee who it was, and ſhe returning, told her it was a Gentleman would ſpeak with her, ſhe then deſired he would
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152161:8"/>
ſend up his Name and Buſineſs, but the Maid replyed he had a Letter for her, which he ſaid he muſt deliver to her hand, however ſhe told her ſhe would not ſee him till ſhe knew his Name, but whilſt they were diſcourſing concerning it, a Perſon came up Stairs with both ends of his <hi>Wig</hi> in his mouth, and made as if he would preſent her with a Letter, but ſhe ſeeming ſhye, and telling him he was a ſtranger to her; he let go the ends of his <hi>VVigg,</hi> and ſwearing a great Oath that he was a great ſtranger to her, and clapped his hands upon her Throat and Neck, ſaying he want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed money; Commanded her on pain of Death not to make any Noiſe; and whilſt this happened, he heard her maid cry out ſoftly, Thieves, Thieves; and then taking up her upper Coat, he drew it over her Head, and ſo tyed it vvith her hands in it, calling as loud as he durſt, <hi>Jack, Jack, why don't you come up Jack?</hi> but he making as if he ſtay'd belovv to ſecure the maid, he cryed <hi>Damn her for a Bitch, Shoot her, Cut her Throat, what is her Life worth?</hi> Which Mrs. <hi>Gatford</hi> taking to be in earneſt, beſought them <hi>For Gods ſake not to kill her maid;</hi> hovvever <hi>Jack</hi> ſoon came up Stairs, vvhereupon he that firſt ſeized Mrs. <hi>Gatford,</hi> Commanded her to tell vvhere the money vvas, vvho replyed, <hi>She had none but what was in her Purſe:</hi> Then he asked vvhere her Purſe vvas, ſhe ſaid <hi>in her Pocket, then pull it out ſaid he,</hi> but her Hands being vvithin her Coats, ſhe told him ſhe could not, vvhereupon he ſaid he vvould take it out, vvhich he do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and then laying her on her Face vvith dreadful threats, that if ſhe ſtirr'd— They vvent directly to the place vvhere the money vvas, altho' in a very private place; as alſo to the Glaſs Caſe of Plate: The firſt they had ſome difficulty to find, and vvere once about to go avvay vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, but one of them knocking a Board in the Cloſet that vvas to dravv up heard it chink, and ſo by force vvrenching it up, they took the money before-mentioned, and other things not named: Having gotten their Prey, they told Mrs. <hi>Gatford</hi> She <hi>muſt go down into the Celler;</hi> to vvhich ſhe replyed <hi>She could not ſee the way,</hi> then he that came up firſt lead her, and vvhen ſhe vvas on the Top of the Stairs bid her take her firſt ſtep, vvhich ſhe did, and immediately ſlipp'd dovvn to the Bottom, and did the like on the Top of the Celler Stairs, being belovv they bound her to a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, and brought dovvn <hi>Agnes VVearing,</hi> vvhom they bound likevviſe and ſet her by her, but ſo looſe that ſhe might eaſily have unbound her ſelf; near her likevviſe they laid a piece of <hi>Red Damask,</hi> vvherevvith <hi>VVearing</hi> pretended they had blinded her, and ſo charging them not to ſtir for half an hour, nor make any noiſe, under the pain of being ſhot or run through; (for as they ſaid, they vvould ſtay half an hour to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them) and having plunder'd the Houſe they departed vvith their Booty: When as Mrs <hi>Gatford</hi> hearing all ſtill, and imagining as much, bid her maid (vvho by this time had gotten her ſelf pretty vvell at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) to cry out which ſhe feigned to do, but vvith ſo lovv a Voice, as ſhe vvas ſure ſhe could be heard by none, and therein excuſed her ſelf through the fear ſhe conceived of having her Throat Cut if they ſhould happen to return; hovvever, ſhe got ſo much her liberty, that ſhe untiy'd her miſtreſs, and then pretndned that her hands vvere tyed over her Head, vvhich vvhen her Miſtreſs vvent to help her, ſhe found the ſame vvas ſo looſe that ſhe could eaſily have untyed her ſelf.</p>
               <p>The Robery being thus Committed that Diſcovery might the better be made: It vvas for ſome days kept a little private, for vvho vvere
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152161:9"/>
the Robers was not as yet known to Mr. <hi>Gatford</hi> nor his Wife; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one Mr. <hi>Hamlin</hi>'s Evidence on this occaſion was rare and unuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al corroberating and confirming that which was more poſſitive.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hamlin</hi> being called and ſworn for the King, depoſed that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time before the Robery, going with a French Merchant to a <hi>Muſick-Houſe</hi> near <hi>Moor-Fields</hi> to look for a <hi>Laundreſs</hi> who had pawn'd one of his Cravats, that he might perſwade her to tell him where it was, and he thereby have the opportunity of Redeeming it: Having found the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whilſt his Friend was diſcourſing her, he retired and went down into the <hi>Muſick-Room,</hi> and ſat him down by <hi>Agnes Wearing</hi> (whom he then knew not) accompanyed only with an Old Woman, which made him preſs himſelf into her Company and paſs ſome Complements on her; ſhe being well habited, and making ſuch a ſuitable Return, he earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know what ſhe was, ſhe thereupon told him <hi>He was miſtaken in the Perſon he addreſſed himſelf to, for that ſhe was but a Cook-Maid;</hi> and when he found ſhe made ſome difficulty in believing it, becauſe ſhe was better habited than might well conſiſt with ſuch an Employment, ſhe told him, <hi>That he might go a long with her and be ſatisfied,</hi> to this he conſented, and went with her and the Old Woman as far as <hi>Houndsditch</hi> where the latter turned off: From thence <hi>Agnes Wearing</hi> went with him through <hi>Biſhops-Gate,</hi> and ſo to her Maſters Houſe in <hi>Lymeſtreet,</hi> and ſhewing him the Kitchen and all its Furniture, demanded, <hi>If he was confirmed in what ſhe ſaid, and ſome other words having paſſed, ſhe deſired him not to ſtay at that time, leaſt Notice ſhould be taken of it, but if he would take any other opportunity to ſend for her, either to Ale-houſe or Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, ſhe would come to him,</hi> and ſo they parted.</p>
               <p>About two days after the Robery was Committed, Mr. <hi>Hamlin</hi> being one Evening upon the <hi>Exchange</hi> with a <hi>Scotchman</hi> a Friend of his, his Friend asked him, <hi>If he knew not where to ſpend an hour or two that dull Evening,</hi> to which he replyed, <hi>He had a new Miſtreſs whoſe Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was very taking, and who had invited him to pay her a viſit,</hi> and ſo proceeded to tell him the whole Story, whereupon they agreed to go thither; and it being ſomewhat dark Mr. <hi>Hamlin</hi> left his Friend at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and knocked at her Maſters Gate, holding (to be the leſs known if any body elſe ſhould open it) the ends of his <hi>Periwig</hi> in his mouth; (the Poſture the party came in that firſt ſeized Mrs. <hi>Gatford:</hi>) Scarce had he knocked twice when <hi>Agnes Wearing</hi> opening it, and not being capable of diſcerning who he was; but ſuppoſing him to be the Perſon he was not, fell to puſhing him back, and as one in an extraordinary ſurprize, cryed out, though ſomewhat low, <hi>O! Mr.</hi> Davis <hi>what do you do here, will you ruin your ſelf and me? there is a great ado about the Robery, and I would not have you appear here this Month: Is the Plate ſecure? Have you ſhared the Money? Is Mr.</hi> Holland <hi>ſafe?</hi> and having ſaid theſe Words, (to which Mr. <hi>Hamlin</hi> conceiving ſome Robery had been Committed made her a ſuitable reply;) She thruſt him to be gone and ſhut the Gate. This Mr. <hi>Hamlin</hi> told to his Friend and divers others, and heard ſoon after of the Robery that had been Committed, and adviſed with ſeveral, whether he ſhould acquaint Mr. <hi>Gatford</hi> with what he had heard; but ſome alledging he might bring himſelf into trouble if he had no better ground for it, or no more to teſtifie than what he had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152161:9"/>
heard, whereupon he forbore it a Month or thereabouts; after that he met <hi>Agnes Wearing</hi> in <hi>Moor-Fields</hi> with <hi>Hollands</hi> Foot-boy after her, and began to renew his former Acquaintance with her, but at firſt ſhe ſeemed ſtrange and would not know him, till he remembred her of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral paſſages that had been between them, and then ſhe told him, <hi>She was fearful of lying aloan, and that ſhe was going into</hi> Spittle-Fields, <hi>to get her Siſter to lye with her;</hi> for it ſeems ſhe then was come from her place. This would not ſatisfie him, but he would needs drink with her; ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having taken a View of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and diſmiſſed the Boy, they went to a Houſe near <hi>Moor-Gate;</hi> and there he told her how ſhe had miſtaken him ſuch a Night, and what he had heard her ſpeak and obſerved, whereupon ſhe began to excuſe it and to change Colour, and in the end Confeſſed, <hi>She was miſtaken, but that there was nothing in it,</hi> or to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and ſo they parted. Mr. <hi>Hamlin</hi> not long after acquainted Mr. <hi>Gat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> what he heard from <hi>Agnes Wearing,</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> having had Notice of this from the ſaid <hi>Agnes,</hi> went to take up the ſaid <hi>Hamlin,</hi> for charging him falſely with the ſaid Robery: Then <hi>Margaret Harris</hi> being Sworn, ſaid that ſhe went to live with one Madam <hi>Walton,</hi> who lodged then at one Mr. <hi>Canes</hi> in <hi>New-ſtreet</hi> as her hired Servant about the middle of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> laſt, and that on or about the beginning of <hi>September, Davis, Holland,</hi> and one <hi>Biſhop,</hi> were together at the <hi>Dog-Tavern</hi> in, or near, <hi>Newgate-ſtreet</hi> with her Lady (for ſo ſhe called her) &amp; another Woman, which ſhe ſince believes was Mr. <hi>Gatfords</hi> Maid, making very merry there; and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the middle of the ſame month of <hi>September,</hi> ſhe was ſent out by her Lady to find out one Mr. <hi>Price,</hi> but not finding him ſhe returned to her Lady, &amp; found <hi>William Davis,</hi> whom ſhe often had ſeen there before, near her Cloſet Door, and one <hi>Humpton</hi> ſitting in the Room behind the Door, and ſhe then going near to her Lady, to give her an Account of her Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, looking over her ſhoulder, ſaw <hi>Davis</hi> take out of his Pocket a great handful of Rings; a great part of which were mourning Rings, and from amongſt them gave her Lady a Diamond Ring, ſoon after which, <hi>Davis</hi> and <hi>Humpton</hi> went away together; and then her Lady ſaid to her, <hi>Margaret, ſee here what a fine Ring Mr.</hi> Davis <hi>hath given me,</hi> which ſhe then looked upon, and obſerved the ſame to be a Diamond-Ring with ſeven Stones, in the middle one having a flaw therein fill'd up with Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and thereupon told her Lady that ſhe wondered ſhe would take it of him, for that he was a Clipper, a Shop lifter, and a very ill man, and therefore to be ſuſpected that he had ſtolen it; to which her Lady re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that ſhe did not care if he Robbed all the Shops in Town, ſo that he maintained her handſomely; upon which ſhe replyed, ſhe doubted ſhe would bring her ſelf into trouble by it, and was ſorry for it; upon that, her Lady was very angry with her, and gave her a Box on the Ear, and bid her meddle with her own buſineſs. About three or four days afterwards, her Lady ſent her to her Daughters, one Mrs. <hi>Stanly,</hi> at one <hi>Foots</hi> a Barber in <hi>Blow-Bladder-ſtreet,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Dog-Tavern</hi> before mentioned, to borrow ſome money of her; where when ſhe came, ſhe found her a Bed, &amp; gave her then an account of her buſineſs, who told her ſhe had no money; whereupon ſhe asked her if ſhe had the <hi>Gazette,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vvhich, Mrs. <hi>Stanly</hi> told her ſhe had, and there vvas a great Robe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Committed, mentioned therein, and ſhovved it to her, vvho read it, and found a Diamond-Ring vvith ſeven Stones, and other Deſcriptions
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152161:10"/>
according to what ſhe had obſerved in the Ring ſhe ſaw <hi>Davis</hi> give to her Lady therein mentioned to be ſtolen, with ſeveral other Rings, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe ſaid, that Ring which <hi>Davis</hi> had given to her Lady, was the Ring therein mentioned; and that ſhe believed that <hi>Davis</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> (for that ſhe found them often together concerned in many Crimes) had Committed the Robery, and asked Mrs. <hi>Stanelys</hi> Advice, whether ſhe had not beſt write a Letter, and put it into the <hi>Penny-Poſt,</hi> to give Mr. <hi>Gatford</hi> an account of it; Mrs. <hi>Stanely</hi> replyed, ſhe believed it to be true, but if ſhe ſhould do it without her Mothers conſent, ſhe would go nigh to kill them both; whereupon ſhe went back to her Lady, and carried the <hi>Gazette</hi> with her, and told her what diſcourſe had paſſed between her and her Daughter concerning the Ring, and gave her the <hi>Gazette,</hi> and ſhewed her the place where the Robery was mentioned, and told her of her Daughters, and her intentions, but ſhe was very angry thereat, and called them a couple of Bloody Bitches, and asked whether they had a mind to dip their hands in innocent Blood, and beat this Deponent, and Tore all the Cloaths off her Head, and gave her a blow on the Face, and made her Noſe bleed; but it ſo happened, that a Night or two afterwards ſhe apprehended her Lady was in a better humour, and therefore deſired again that ſhe would permit the Ring to be produced to the Miniſter that was Robbed, believing it to be his Ring, and offered that ſhe ſhould have the Ten Pounds; but her Lady refuſed ſo to do, and then collogued with her, and was very kind to her, and offered her Ten Pounds not to be concerned any more about it, and promiſed to keep her like a Gentlewoman whilſt ſhe lived with her, and if ſhe married ſhe vvould give her Five hundred Pound, and if ſhe continued vvith her till ſhe dyed, ſhe vvould give her Fifty Pound a Year, for One &amp; Tvven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years; to all vvhich, ſhe anſvvered very little; but about a Fortnight aftervvards on a <hi>Sunday, Davis</hi> came and demanded the Diamond Ring of her Lady, which this deponent adviſed her privately, not to let him have; however he ſate down by her Lady on the Bed-ſide, with his hand upon his Knee, and whilſt he was diſcourſing ſhe obſerved a large plain Gold Ring upon his Finger, which ſhe with his leave took off to look upon, much commending it, and deſiring that he would give it her, and looking upon it and the Poſie, which was, <hi>God above increaſe our love;</hi> ſhe read the ſame aloud, in the preſence and hearing both of her Lady and the ſaid <hi>Davis,</hi> upon which ſhe told <hi>Davis</hi> it was a good Poſie, and ſince he had promiſed to get her a Husband, he would do well to give her that Ring againſt ſhe got him, but he would not, whereupon ſhe gave it him again, but did not obſerve that her Lady did let him have the Diamond Ring again; but after he was gone, ſhe ſaid to her Lady, <hi>what think you now Madam, is it not true that</hi> Davis <hi>and</hi> Holland <hi>robbed the Parſon, for this is the Ring, and the Poſie I read to you in the other Ring is the ſame poſie, both mentioned in the</hi> Gazette; whereupon her Lady (as formerly) was very angry with her; but about two or three Nights afterwards, <hi>Davis</hi> and one <hi>Harriſon</hi> came into her Ladys Chamber, and ſiting down, <hi>Davis</hi> pulled forth a handful of Guineas and other pieces, upon ſight of which, her Lady ſaid, Mr. <hi>Davis</hi> when will you ſend me in ſome— <hi>Davis</hi> replyed, and ſwore a great Oath, that next Week he would ſend her in a Butchers Tray full; whereupon ſhe ſaid to Mr <hi>Harriſon,</hi> we ſhall have Guineas enough to Thatch a Houſe: And after they vvere
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152161:10"/>
gone, ſhe deſired leave of her Lady, that ſhe might go and diſcover this vvhole matter, othervviſe miſchief might come of it, but her Lady vvould not let her go; and one day in the morning early, ſhe deſired the maid of the Houſe to call her as if ſome perſon would ſpeak vvith her, intending by that means to have got out to make the Diſcovery, vvhich the maid did; and vvhen ſhe vvas going, her Lady lept out of her Bed and ſtopt her, and beat her very much and locked her up, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe had got the Ring, and then ſoon after favvned upon her, letting her knovv that ſhe had accuſed her unjuſtly, and repeated her former promiſes to her, to engage her to the contrary: Hovvever, tvvo days aftervvards being in <hi>October,</hi> on a <hi>Wedneſday</hi> in the Seſſions Week; ſhe again deſired to go forth, to deliver a Letter for her Father, but her Lady ſuſpecting ſhe would go tell Mr. <hi>Gatford,</hi> charged her not to do ſo upon her Salvation, and withal ſwore her upon a <hi>Maſs-Book,</hi> that ſhe ſhould not tell Mr <hi>Gatford,</hi> by which compliance ſhe got leave to go forth, and then went immediately to her Siſters, at Madam <hi>Armatages</hi> in <hi>Crain-Court</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> and informed them both, of all thoſe paſſages; and adviſed with them, whether ſhe might diſcover it notwithſtanding her Oath, who did adviſe her to go forthwith to Mr. <hi>Gatford</hi> and diſcover the whole matter, which ſhe accordingly did the ſame day, and afterwards went back to her Lady, and ſtay'd with her tho' in great danger, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der much dread; being often told by her Lady, that they would do her a miſchief; till the day before her Lady was taken and ſent to the <hi>Comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> out of which ſhe was ſoon after Bailed; and further ſaith, that ſhe ſaw her Lady have the ſaid Ring in her Boſome the day before ſhe was taken, and often heard her ſay that ſhe would through it down the Houſe of Office, before it ſhould be diſcovered: When ſhe had done, then Mr. <hi>Recorder</hi> asked her, where was that Madam <hi>Walton,</hi> ſhe had ſo often mentioned in her Evidence? To which, ſhe anſwered that ſhe was there, (pointing up to the Gallery) amongſt ſeveral other Ladys and Women: Whereupon Mr. <hi>Recorder</hi> order'd an Officer to go up im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately and wait upon her down, and thereupon ſhe was brought into Court, (very richly habited) and pretended ſhe was an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Earls Daughter, and a Woman of Quality; however ſhe was committed to Priſon upon the Evidence that had been given, and an Indictment or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to be preferr'd againſt her, and perſons bound to Proſecute the ſame, which afterwards was accordingly done, and the Indictment found, and there was a Letter likewiſe given in Evidence againſt <hi>Holland,</hi> which <hi>Holland</hi> own'd to be his hand, and was wrote to <hi>Agnes Wearing,</hi> &amp; did mention things relating to this buſineſs; and then <hi>Holland</hi>'s Foot-boy was called and Sworn, who teſtified that he had been often ſent on meſſuages by his Maſter to <hi>Agnes Wearing,</hi> and by that means was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental in having her taken by diſcovering the Lodging that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter had often provided for her, tho' ſhe had ſhifted them divers times, and being in Cuſtody upon hearing that <hi>Davis</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> were taken, ſhe cry'd out we are all concerned, and hoped they ſhould live and dye together, for ſhe was reſolved ſhe would live and dye with them.</p>
               <p>This being the Subſtance of the Evidence given againſt the Priſoners at the Bar: They were then asked by the <hi>Recorder</hi> every one of them ſingly, what they had to offer in defence of themſelves againſt this great Crime. Thus as it were miraculouſly made out againſt them, <hi>Davis</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:152161:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
endeavoured to make it appear, that he had bought the Diamond Ring and as for the Wedding-Ring, there were few Goldſmiths Shops, that afforded not Rings with the like <hi>Poſie,</hi> and did produce a perſon in Court, of whom he had bought a Diamond-Ring, but it was about Nine Months ſince, and the ſame did appear to be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of a Ring, and diſpoſed of before the Robery was committed, and the Ring he had given to his miſtreſs conſequently could not be the ſame, then he called Perſons to diſcredit <hi>Margaret Harris,</hi> by alledging her unjuſtneſs, and amongſt others, a miſtreſs with whom ſhe had formerly lived, who inſtead of accuſing her of Diſhoneſty, gave her a good Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter. <hi>Holland</hi> alledged malice in Mr. <hi>Hamlin,</hi> and that Mr. <hi>Gatford</hi> had brib'd his Foot-boy, but the former not appearing, and the Boy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath declaring the contrary, that Mr. <hi>Gatford</hi> had indeed promiſed him two Guineas to diſcover the Lodging of <hi>Agnes Wearing,</hi> the which when he had done, he would not give it him till the Tryals were over, leſt the Priſoner ſhould conſtrue that as a Bribe, to induce him to Swear againſt them; and having nothing more material to offer further in their Defence, <hi>Agnes Wearing</hi> inſiſting upon her innocence.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Recorder</hi> Sum'd up the Evidence to the Jury, very particularly, and at large, and more eſpecially after he had repeated <hi>Hamlin's</hi> Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence given againſt <hi>Holland</hi> (which he obſerved was their moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult parts, for that generally what one Priſoner ſaith of another is not Evidence) yet as this Caſe is, they might conſider the occaſion that moved <hi>Agnes Wearing</hi> to ſpeak what ſhe did, it being without any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, or any thing laid to her charge at that time ſhe could not ſpeak it out of any by Ends, or dread, but merely upon a miſtake and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, apprehending it was <hi>Davis,</hi> becauſe of his appearing to her in the ſame poſture as <hi>Davis</hi> was in, when he ſeized upon Mrs. <hi>Gatford,</hi> and then it was very plain by the whole courſe of the Evidence, that <hi>Holland, Davis,</hi> and <hi>Wearing</hi> were all well acquainted, and their familiarity began much about the time, when this Fact was Committed, and they both very fond of her, but <hi>Holland</hi> more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, he uſing all Diligence to take care of her, and conceal her, by providing ſeveral Lodgings for her in by places, and what was teſtified againſt <hi>Davis</hi> and <hi>Agnes,</hi> and what ſhe confeſſed to <hi>Hollithorn,</hi> made it plain if they did give credit to the Witneſſes; ſo that upon the whole matter, he left it to them, whether they would find all or any, and which of the Priſoners Guilty or not Guilty of this Crime, whereof they ſtood charged within the Indictment.</p>
               <p>Whereupon, the Jury after they were withdrawn ſome time, came in, and found them all three Guilty of the Indictment; and <hi>William Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis</hi> and <hi>Agnes Wearing,</hi> were Executed on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> following, and <hi>Holland</hi> Reprieved.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>This may be Printed,</hi> R. L. S.
<date>January <hi>the</hi> 9th: 1685.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
