<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian moderator: or, Persecution for religion condemned, by the light of nature. Law of God. Evidence of our own principles.</title>
            <author>Birchley, William, 1613-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4243</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E640_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206658</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865774</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865774</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118025</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A75807)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118025)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 98:E640[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian moderator: or, Persecution for religion condemned, by the light of nature. Law of God. Evidence of our own principles.</title>
                  <author>Birchley, William, 1613-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H.J.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yeer 1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Austin, who used the pseudonym William Birchley.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious tolerance --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118025:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
Chriſtian Moderator:
<hi>OR,</hi>
PERSECUTION
FOR
RELIGION
<hi>CONDEMNED,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>By the
<list>
                        <item>Light of Nature.</item>
                        <item>Law of God.</item>
                        <item>Evidence of our own Principles.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <bibl>JAMES II. XII.</bibl>
            <q>So ſpeak you and ſo do, as they that are judged by the law of liberty: for they
ſhall be judged without mercy that have ſhewed no mercy.</q>
            <q>Mille hominum ſpecies, &amp; rerum <hi>diſcolor</hi> uſus,
—per me equidem ſint omnia protinus <hi>alba.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Printed for <hi>H. J.</hi> in the yeer 1651.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:118025:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118025:2"/>
            <head>Perſecution for Religion condemned, &amp;.</head>
            <p>WHen I conſider how tenderly your Saviour Chriſt recommends
the precept of mutuall love to all that profeſſe his Name, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
it the Character of his followers. <hi>By this all men ſhall know
that you are my Diſciples, if you love one another, John</hi> 13.
35. And when I reflect how highly the great Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>
exalts the ſame Commandement, abridging into this one precious <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap>ble, the
whole duty of a Chriſtian, <hi>All the Law is fulfill'd in one word, Thou ſhalt love
thy Neighbour as thy ſelf, Gal.</hi> 5. I cannot ſufficiently wonder, to ſee moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
in this preſent age with fire and ſword perſecute each other, only upon the
account of Religion: how are we degenerated from the Primitive Believers, who
would rather have given their own lives, to perſwade their enemies to piety, then
ſought to take away the lives of their Brethren, to force them to Hypocriſie?</p>
            <p>Yet hath it pleaſed the Lord Chriſt in our daies, <hi>upon whom the ends of the world
are come,</hi> to infuſe the like tenderneſſe into the breſts of many conſcientious and
godly minded people of this Nation, (who ſeeing the deformity and unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe
of thoſe cruell Maximes, that preach ruine and deſtruction for the leaſt
difference in belief) ceaſe not to pray unto the God of heaven, and ſolicite the
Governors of the earth, that an impartiall freedome, and abſolute incoercency in
matters of Religion may be firmly and irrevocably eſtabliſht, for all that profeſſe
the Goſpell of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For incouragement of which holy deſign, woven out of the bowells of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
and for determent of thoſe tempeſtuous ſpirits, that with thunder and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
ſtrive to ſtorm mens conſciences, I have indeavoured in this ſhort diſcourſe
to demonſtrate, that Conſcience-perſecution amongſt Chriſtians is clearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant
to the <hi>Light of Nature,</hi> the <hi>Law of God,</hi> and the <hi>evidence of our own
Principles.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Demonſtrative Reaſons againſt forcing of Conſcience.</head>
               <p>1. SInce we have ſo happily ſhaken off that intollerable Yoke of Popiſh infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility
(<hi>which neither we nor our Fathers were able to bear</hi>) it is become
to us not only tyrannicall, but abſurd, to compell others to a way, that our ſelves
confeſſe may poſſibly be erronious; we ſee one Parliament repeals thoſe Articles
of faith which a former enacted; that form of worſhip which the Laws of the laſt
age introduced, is now generally exploded; nay, the very laſt Reformation, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
with ſo ſolemn a Covenant, and carried on with ſo furious a Zeal, is already
by better lights diſcovered to be meerly humane, &amp; therefore deſervedly laid aſide:
The late Synods Confeſſion of Faith (hatch'd by ſo many years ſitting) is now
learnedly examined, and indeed for a great part ſolidly confuted, by Mr. <hi>W. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi>
and other learned perſons in print; how prepoſterous is it then to conſtrain
a ſoul, not only to forſake his conſcience, which may be truth, but drive him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to his own heart, to a way that may be error!</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118025:3"/>
2. Since the Word of God is the ſole Rule of Faith, and no humane authority
ſo highly impowred, as to bind up our aſſents to whatſoever interpretation it ſhall
pleaſe to propoſe; it clearly follows, that as all the children of God have equall
intereſt in the Teſtament of their Father, ſo no one amongſt them has any right
to impoſe a force upon the judgement of his brother: One holds Baptiſm of
children to be neceſſary, another eſteems it unlawfull, a third denies both theſe O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions,
admitting well that it may, but not that it muſt be done: they conferre
Texts, look into Originall Tongues, pray inceſſantly to God, and profeſſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly
the ſincerity of their intentions; yet after all their diligences and devotions,
ſtedfaſtly remain in their former perſwaſion; truely for my part, he that ſhould
adviſe perſecution in ſuch a caſe (unleſſe his fire brought light too with it, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate
the truth) would ſcarce ſatisfie my ſuſpition, that his coals were fetcht
from the infernall pit.</p>
               <p>3. If we reflect upon the difficulties that encounter us in the way to Truth, for
<hi>ſtrait is the gate, nnd narrow is the path,</hi> and withall conſider the ſhortneſſe of
our ſight, for <hi>here we ſee but in part, and underſtand but in part:</hi> there will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
more reaſon to endeavour the mutuall aſſiſtance and ſupport, then malicious
ruine and deſtruction one of another. However, ſince all have neither equall depth
of naturall judgment, nor the ſame meaſure of ſupernaturall illumination, <hi>but the
ſpirit bloweth how and where it pleaſeth,</hi> we ought not to attempt ſo high a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption,
as to deſpiſe or perſecute our b<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>other for his innocent and blameleſſe
miſtakes, leſt we be found to fight againſt God, who is the free diſpoſer of his
gifts; we know <hi>the way of man is not in himſelf,</hi> Jer. 10. 23. but his <hi>ſteps are ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
by the Lord, Pro.</hi> 20. 24. and therefore certainly, did we bear a due reſpect to
God, we would be content to wait his leiſure, who has engaged himſelf by his
Apoſtle, <hi>Phil. 3. 15. If any man be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall in time reveal
even this unto him:</hi> let us therefore entertain ſuch an one, who proceeds in the
ſimplicity of his heart, with <hi>milk,</hi> till he grow ſtronger to digeſt <hi>ſtrong meat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. All compulſion upon the Conſcience returns us flatly to our old ſlavery
under the <hi>Prelates,</hi> nay more to the implicite faith of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> with this only
difference, that we are worſe then either, becauſe our conſciences accuſe us of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
that which we condemn in others; for whatſoever I am conſtrained to ſwear
or profeſſe more then I am convinced of, proceeds from as great a tyranny as the
High Commiſſion, and is as blind an aſſent, as can be match'd in the groſſeſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,
and dare we <hi>think that doing the ſame things we judge in others, we ſhall
eſcape the Judgement of God,</hi> Rom. 2. 3.</p>
               <p>5. Force is puniſhment, and conſequently not juſt, unleſſe the offence be vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary,
but he that believes according to the evidence of his own reaſon, is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated
to that belief, and to compell him againſt it, were to drive him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce
the moſt eſſentiall part of man his reaſon. Why ſhould we be commanded
<hi>to try the ſpirits,</hi> 1 John 4. 1. <hi>to prove all things, 1 Theſ.</hi> 5. 21. if there be not
a faculty in the ſoul to judge for her ſelf? why are we enjoyned to <hi>hold faſt that
which we find to be beſt,</hi> if after our moſt ſerious and deliberate election we ſhall
be whipt out of our conſcience by penalties? To what purpoſe do we preach poor
ſouls into juſt ſo much liberty of Scripture, as may beget their torture, and not
permit them to reſt where they find ſatisfaction; Either prohibit to ſearch at all,
or leave us ſenſible of ſome benefit by teaching; To believe what appears untrue,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118025:3"/>
ſeems to me impoſſible, to profeſſe what we believe untrue, I am ſure is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
               <p>6. As it is certain, whoſoever ſwerves from the dictate of his Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits
a grievous ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. So without queſtion they that endeavour by force
or artifice to draw any man to profeſſe or act contrary to what his ſoul believes,
are as deeply guilty of the ſame crime, <hi>When you wound the weak conſciences of
your brethren, you ſin against Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 8. 12. How dangerouſly then do they
expoſe themſelves to the juſt indignation of God, who by Oaths, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
Forfeitures, &amp;c. both drive others, and fall themſelves into eternall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition?
How deſperately do they attempt to extinguiſh the light of Nature, which
indiſpenſably obliges all men to deal with others, as they would be dealt with
themſelves, a light placed by God in clear and candid ſouls to ſhine and guide
them, but in black ones to condemn and burn them; I ſhall cloſe this diſcourſe
with the adviſe of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 14. 13. Let us therefore uſe our judgement
rather in this, that no man put a ſtumbling block before his Brother.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>2. Unanſwerable Texts of Scripture againſt coercency in Religion.</head>
               <p>NOr are theſe ſo excellent and important truths built only upon the firme
foundation of ſolid reaſon, but alſo upon the infallible authority of evident
Scripture, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 24 &amp;c. <hi>The ſervant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle
unto all men, apt to teach, for bearing, in meekneſſe inſtructing thoſe that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
minded, if God peradventure will give them repentance, to the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging
of the truth, that they may recover themſelves out of the ſnare of the
devill, who are taken captive by him at his will:</hi> and another Apoſtle forbidding
us to condemn one another, ſaith (<hi>James</hi> 4. 12) <hi>There is one Lawgiver, who is
able to ſave and to deſtroy: who art thou that judgeſt another?</hi> and in <hi>Paul</hi> to the
<hi>Romans 14. 4. Who art thou that judgeſt anothers ſervant? to his own Maſter he
ſtandeth or falleth, yea he ſhall be holden up, for God is able to make him
ſtand; one man eſteemeth one day above another, another eſteemeth every day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
let every man be fully perſwaded in his own mind, haſt thou faith? have
it to thy ſelf before God, happy is he that condemneth not himſelf in that which
he alloweth,</hi> that is, whoſe conſcience inwardly accuſeth not his outward profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
The ſame moſt zealous Preacher of the Goſpell returns ſo condeſcending and
moderate an anſwer to a caſe of a far harder ſound then we undertake to maintain,
that it ſufficiently proves he took his gentle pen from the ſoft wing of the <hi>Dove,</hi>
1 Cor. 7. 12. &amp;c. <hi>If any brother hath a wiſe that believeth not, and ſhe be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to dwell with him, let him not put her away, and the woman that hath a
husband that believeth not, and he be pleaſed to dwell with her, let her not leave
him, but if the unbelieving depart, let him depart; a brother or a ſiſter is not in
bondage in ſuch caſes, but God hath called us to peace; for what knoweſt thou
O wife, whither thou ſhalt ſave thy husband? and what knoweſt thou O man whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
thou ſhalt ſave thy wife? as God hath diſtributed to every man, as the Lord
hath called every one, ſo let him walk, and ſo ordain I in all Churches.</hi> What
can be ſaid more efficaciouſly to oblige Chriſtians, in charity and meekneſſe to
forbear one another, then ſo expreſſe an Injunction of ſo great an Apoſtle, to live
peaceably even with an Infidell? and again 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 24. He denies that even the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
themſelves have any Soveraignty over the Conſcience, but only Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118025:4"/>
to aſſiſt the conſcientious, <hi>not that we have</hi> (ſaies he to the <hi>Corinthians)
Dominion over your faith, but are helpers of your joy;</hi> therein exactly obſerving
the orders which Chriſt gave to his Apoſtles, <hi>Go and teach,</hi> not compell, <hi>and if
any one receive you not, ſhake off the duſt of your feet,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> trample upon them,
as duſt under your feet, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 14. Conſtant to which Doctrine of Meekneſſe,
our Saviour thus inſtructs his Diſciples, Mat. 23. 9. <hi>Be not called Rabbi</hi> (that is
Maſters in ſpiritual matters (<hi>for one is your Maſter, even Chriſt, and all you are
brethren.</hi> To this belongs the patient forbearing the <hi>tares,</hi> and letting them grow
together with the <hi>wheat</hi> till the time of harveſt: as alſo that admirable preſident
of mildneſſe towards the Samaritanes, who refuſed to receive even Chriſt himſelf,
whereupon the Diſciples <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> would immediately command fire from
heaven to conſume them, as in the daies of <hi>Elias,</hi> but our mercifull Lord rebuked
their zeal, with this ſweet and tender reply, <hi>You know not what manner of ſpirit
you are of, the Son of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them,</hi>
Luke 9. 54. which one example abundantly ſatisfies all objections drawn from
the practiſe of <hi>Elias, Jehu,</hi> the ſons of <hi>Levi,</hi> &amp;c. in the old Teſtament, for as
they had an expreſſe command from God to warrant their Zeal, we have an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
warrant from Chriſt to command us meekneſſe. If any one ſhall ſhuffle in
a ſuſpition, that this moderate temper was meant only for the times of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
when the Chriſtians had no temporall Power; let him firſt confeſſe that
thoſe were the beſt and pureſt times, and then ſhow a Warrant dormant under
our Saviours hand (that is in his Goſpell) to Commiſſionate his Diſciples as ſoon
as they ſhould get the Sword into their hands, to cut the throats of all diſobeyers,
and I ſubmit; but if they can cite no ſuch authority, let them freely acknowledge
that perſecution for Conſcience is an unwarrantable tyranny over the juſt privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges
and liberty of a Chriſtian.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>3. Our own Principles againſt conſtraint upon the Conſcience.</head>
               <p>COnſonant to theſe reaſons and clear Texts of Scripture, are the Principles of
all the godly and well-affected of this Nation: to begin with them to whom
we owe this liberty of diſcourſing, the unparallel'd Army, in all whoſe proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
and Declarations (eſpecially ſince managed by the prodigiouſly ſucceſſefull
hands of the two later Generalls) their <hi>Motto</hi> has been <hi>Liberty to all tender and
oppreſſed Conſciences,</hi> the glory of which ſo dazles the eys of our enemies, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courages
the hearts of our friends, that notwithſtanding whatever other diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
we ſtill find the Author of our Victory mindfull of the <hi>word,</hi> which himſelf
gave to our Army, <hi>The meek ſhall inherit the Land;</hi> Of which ſhort Texts writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
in our Enſigns, we may read a clear and perfect Commentary in the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalls
of the ſame ſtil triumphing Army. 1 <hi>Aug.</hi> 1647. when penetrating exactly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the true ſtate of the Queſtion, they prudently diſtinguiſh between quiet exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers
of their Conſciences, and active prejudicers of the Common-wealth, and
thereupon offer their earneſt deſires, <hi>that all coercive Power, and all civill Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties
for non-conformity be wholly repealed, and ſome other proviſion made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
ſuch Papiſts as ſhould diſturb the publike peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many and wonderfull are the deliverances which our good God has diſpenſed to
his ſervants, in reward of this their inclination to mercifullneſſe, yet amongſt all
the glorious appearances of the Lord for his people, none can be found more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118025:4"/>
then the renowned victory over that rigid and ſevere Kirk-army of the Scots,
<hi>September</hi> 1650. who declining the mild counſell of our Saviour, <hi>to poſſeſſe their
ſouls with patience,</hi> deſervedly loſt their lives by violence, a fatall argument, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding
manifeſtly this very controverſie in favour of meekneſſe, where the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers
of compulſion were no leſſe ingeniouſly then cruelly confuted, whileſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
to themſelves a Power to force our ſouls, they could not ſo much as defend
their own bodies.</p>
               <p>In memory of which great Salvation from the pride and fury of the <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
Prieſthood,</hi> the Parliament, as a new Covenant of Thanksgiving for ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
a mercy, in the ſame moneth enacted an aboliſhment of divers rigorous
and penall Statutes, contrived on purpoſe by the haughty Prelates, to break the
hearts of thoſe, whoſe conſciences they could not bend, which one Act has won
more hearts to acknowledge and love the authority of the Parliament, then all
their ſtupendious victories have forced bodies to confeſſe and fear their Power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
and if it be not check'd by limitations and partiality in the execution, will render
them abſolute Maſters of all that underſtand their own felicity: for what can be
imagined more welcome to a Chriſtian people newly delivered from an Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
bondage, then to ſee themſelves infranchiſed into a holy Liberty of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
ſincerely, according to their conſciences in the Worſhip of their
God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore as we are full of joy for ſo excellent an Act, by which (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
ſaith</hi>) we are called unto Liberty, <hi>ſo we are full of hopes to be perfectly
happy, by the free and univerſal obſervation thereof, without the leaſt ſelf-intereſt
or reſpect of perſons, being ſo conformable to the conſtant received Maximes and
ſolemn deliberate profeſſion of the Parliament, as appears by the</hi> Declaration <hi>of
the</hi> Lords and Commons, <hi>in anſwer to the Scotch papers,</hi> 4 Mar. 1647. <hi>where</hi> fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio
43. the Diſcipline of Eccleſiaſticall Cenſures, and all other puniſhmeuts for
matters of Religion are diſclaimed, as grounded upon Popiſh and Prelaticall
Principles, not to be revived under any image or ſhape whatſoever; <hi>and a little
after</hi> folio 63. <hi>they proceed in the ſame ſenſe,</hi> We ſhall not be afraid at the day of
Judgement, that we have been more forward to ſet Chriſt at liberty, then to caſt
him in priſon, it being better in our opinion (where the caſe is not very clear) to
leave God to deal againſt many errours, then to uſe his authority for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing
of one truth; the weapons of faſting and prayer, being both more Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
and more available in ſuch caſes, then thoſe of force and violence: <hi>and
yet more fully (if poſſible) in another</hi> Declaration <hi>in anſwer to the letters of the</hi>
Scotch Commiſſioners, 17. Feb. 1648. As for the truth and power of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
it being a thing intrinſecall between God and the ſoul, and the matters of
Faith in the Goſpell being ſuch as no naturall light doth reach unto, we conceive
there is no humane power of coertion thereunto, nor to reſtrain men from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving
what God ſuffers their judgements to be perſwaded of. <hi>Words of that
ſolid weight and precious value, as deſerve to be ingraven with letters of gold, and
religiouſly obſerved for ever by all render conſciences, as an Oracle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conformable to the aforeſaid Principles is that excellent Doctrine and adviſe
ſet down by Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> and his Brethren, in their <hi>Examen of the late Synods
Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>page 128. Liberty of Conſcience may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed,
firſt by ſeeking by violent means to alter conſcientious mens judgments,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118025:5"/>
and their preſent perſwaſion; for it is the office of him who is the Lord of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi>
to lighten and change mens minds, when and how he pleaſeth, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 15.
Let us therefore as many as be perfect be thus minded, and if in any thing you
be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal this unto you.</p>
               <p>2. By inciting another by like forcible means, to will and act againſt his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
aud much more by impriſonment, mulcts, terrours or threats, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.
15. 20. 21. For this is to make him deſtroy his ſoul, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. 23.</p>
               <p>3. We may not diſturb the peace of mens Conſciences, or make their hearts ſad
with our invectives, or menacing them cauſleſly with terrors from the Lord,
<hi>Ezechiel 13. 32. Becauſe with lies ye have made the hearts of the righteous ſad,
whom I have not made ſad, &amp;c. And in page 230. thus,</hi> But we would not have
you aſſume to your ſelves, or attribute unto others, a Power to Lord it over mens
Faith and Conſciences, eſpecially when men walk obediently towards thoſe that
are in places of Rule and Authority, and live a godly, ſober, honest, peaceable,
and unblameable life. If men will do wickedly, and defend a Liberty in Chriſt
ſo to do, let them be liable to the Sword of Juſtice for ſo doing. But far be it
from us, ſo much as by example, to draw a weak brother, a Saint and fellow-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
of the Lord, whom no man can accuſe, but for his differing judgement, to do
any thing against Conſcience, whereby he ſhould condemn himſelf, as the Apoſtle
ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. How much more ought Governours to be tender and abstemious
in the uſe of violent and coercive means, to precipitate men into ſuch perillous
and deſtructive courſes. All authority is given of God for mens welfare, and
much more for the preſervation, and not the deſtruction of the ſoul.</p>
               <p>By theſe conſiderations (I conceive) is clearly demonſtrated the freedome of a
Chriſtian ſoul in her commerce for heaven, which ſince the mercifull bounty of
God holds forth indifferently to all, the cruell covetouſneſſe of man ought not to
obſtruct to any, ſurely it is the worſt of <hi>Monopolies</hi> to lay Impoſitions upon the
way to Paradiſe; Chriſt by his death, removed the Angell that chaſed from thence
our firſt parents; and ſhall any of us take the Flaming Sword into our hands, to
ſheath it in the bowells of a poor Pilgrime, who with a ſincere heart travails to
the ſame Countrey, only becauſe he goes not in our company? In my <hi>Fathers
houſe are many Manſions,</hi> ſaies Chriſt, why may there not be as many paths that
lead to them? If <hi>they that have no Law, ſhall be judged without the Law,</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
they that unblameably miſtake the Law, ſhall be tryed according to thoſe
Expoſitions which appeared unto them, to be the meaning of the Law-giver, (for
the ſenſe is the Law, and not the letter) ſpecially having ſo gracious a Judge,
who has already declared by his Apoſtle, 2 Cor. 8. <hi>If there be firſt a willing
mind, it is accepted according to what a man hath, and not according to what he
hath not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore let us not by a ſuddain violence break into pieces the conſciences of
our brethren, but mildly thaw them into a cordiall and ingenuous unity, that
righteouſneſſe and peace may flow together in the ſame channell, and not as bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
Ice daſh one againſt another: let us patiently expect, till the Lord be pleaſed
to take off the vail from their hearts that are otherwiſe minded, and not by forcing
their judgements, add to their vail of ignorance a worſer of hypocriſie, it being
now a common experiment, that generally the iſſue of compulſionary and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
conformity cloſes in this, to make ſome few counterfeit <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118025:5"/>
great many reall <hi>Atheiſts;</hi> whence it is clearly concluded, that the only true
means of winning ſouls to God, is the Goſpellary way of meekneſſe and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
and indeed it may worthily be eſteemed the prime miracle of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi>
that a perſon ſo humble as our <hi>Saviour</hi> appeared, without the aſſiſtance of Kings
and Princes, without the enchanting words of mans wiſdome, without the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighting
threats of fines, impriſonments, and deaths, (though all theſe were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely
ſubject to his pleaſure,) ſhould conquer Powers and Principalities, ſhould
out-charm the Magick of humane eloquence, and by the admirable ſucceſſe of his
mildneſſe, condemn all thoſe politique Religions that confeſſe their own crazineſſe,
by uſing cruelty to ſupport them; whereas to reduce the diſobedient only with the
ſpirit of gentleneſſe, and admonition, or at moſt deſertion, argues indeed a Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
in the Author, and a Purity in the Ordinance: and here we may fitly apply
the words of our Lord, John 14. <hi>If it had been otherwiſe, I would have told you;</hi>
if the way of planting my Faith had been by impoſing penalties on the hearers, and
not rather by expoſing the Preachers thereof to dangers, I would have told you:
if the means of preſerving Religion had been by watering it with the bloud of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſers
to embrace it, rather then of thoſe that ſought to propogate it, I would have
told you either by my example (all the world being in the power of my Deity)
or by my Doctrine, all juſtifiable proceedings concerning the government of my
Flock, being derived from the warrant of my Word; thus we ſee our gracious
Law-maker, faithfull and conſtant to his own Principles, <hi>The Son of man
came not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them:</hi> Thus we ſee our own duty to
<hi>learn of him, for he is meek and humble of heart; let us not therefore judge one
another any more, but uſe our judgement rather in this, that no man put an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
to fall, or a ſtumbling block before his brother,</hi> Rom. 14. 13. Let us alwaies
remember the advertiſement which the beloved Diſciple gives to all his fellow-ſervants
of the Lord Chriſt, John 13. 16. <hi>The ſervant is not greater then his
Lord, if you know theſe things, happy are you if you do them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of tender Conſciences.</head>
               <p>THeſe few unpoliſht <hi>lines,</hi> which I here preſent for incouragement of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
I deſire may not be <hi>ſtretcht</hi> to draw in a wild and extravagant licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,
ſince they aim no farther then to hold up a Liberty to ſuch only as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
Chriſt, and walk before the Lord in the integrity of their heart, who by the
following marks are eaſily diſcernable from all thoſe that for their blaſphemies
in Doctrines and debauchery in manners are worthily excluded from the benefit of
this Indulgence.</p>
               <p>Suppoſing firſt, as confeſt by all underſtanding men, that tenderneſſe of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
is not the ſame thing with truth of judgement, (elſe there could be but one
only kind, becauſe truth is but one) but it ſignifies a proceeding <hi>bonâ fide,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
ſiniſter reſpects, or diſſimulation, ſeeking before all things to know God,
and fearing above all things to offend him. And ſecondly, ſince in our enquiry,
to whom belongs ſo honorable a title, we cannot pierce into the inward thoughts
of men, we muſt give ſentence as they appear to us, which rule in caſes of this
quality is in it ſelf ſufficiently certain; however, 'tis the only means God has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
our nature to guide her reſolutions in the judging of others.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118025:6"/>
The ſigns then of tender Conſciences are theſe, if they lead regular, vertuous,
and peaceable lives; if their opinions be not juſtly accuſeable of ſelf-intereſt or
licentiouſneſſe, but rather require of them a prudent and religious ſeverity againſt
the inclinations of corrupted nature; if their judgemen<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s be ſteddy, not fann'd to
a new ſenſe with every breath of wind; if they continue in the ſame perſwaſions
at their death, which is no time for diſſembling, at leaſt we ought to judge ſo,
if they not only die in their Faith, but for it, not only give away good part of
their eſtates charitably, but ſuffer all to be taken away patiently, and all this for
Chriſts ſake, or (to ſpeak more cloſely) for that which they believe to be his will
and Commandement, no higher teſtimony of a true and reall ſincerity can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
be given, or eaſily imagined; and whoſoever doubts after ſuch evidence,
(chiefly if many concur in the ſame way) deſerves to be condemned, as the moſt
paſſionate, malicious and uncharitable perſon in the world, for though one man
may value his fancy above his life or eſtate, yet it is very neer an abſolute impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility,
that many (eſpecially if they be diſcreet and rationall in other negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons)
ſhould agree to undo themſelves for a meer conceit, did they not ſeriouſly
believe, it more imports them to keep their Faith, then loſe their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</p>
               <p>By theſe rules we may eaſily conclude the admiſſion of thoſe pious and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
perſons, who were impriſoned and perſecuted by the late Prelates, into the
number of tender Conſciences, as alſo thoſe precious ſervants of the Lord, who
by a voluntary baniſhment left their friends and Countrey to plant the liberty of
the Goſpell amongſt the ſavage Heathens of <hi>America.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whilſt I was finiſhing theſe lines, a worthy friend of mine came to honour me
with the civility of a viſit, to whom reading theſe laſt two or three conſiderations,
he told me, that as he believed, the Characters I had given of a <hi>tender Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi>
were moſt evidently true, and to all unbiaſed-minds perfectly ſatisfactory,
yet they were appliable to a ſort of people in this Nation, whoſe being diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced,
is thought ſo profitable to the State, and ſo pleaſing to a certain froward
part of the Miniſtery, that he feared my reaſons might incounter ſome oppoſition,
unleſſe they met with very ingenuous and diſintereſſed readers, plainly telling me,
that the meaſures I had cut out for tender Conſciences would fit the <hi>Papists</hi> as
well as if they had been made for them, for who live more peaceably with their
neighbours, (ſayes he) who deal more juſtly with all men, then they? who are
more conſtant in their Religion, and more ſcrupulous in the obſervances of their
Law, then they? who ſuffer for their Faith more then they; nay at this time,
who beſides them? they ſubmit their underſtandings to the definitions of their
Church, and their wills to the obedience of it's Diſcipline, in Faſting, Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
and many other burthenſome duties, all which are very diſagreeable to the
Dictates of fleſh and bloud, as containing the real practiſe of the higheſt ſelf-deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
that can be imagined: and for the ſerious hour of death, I muſt confeſſe, I
have known many of us turn Papiſts upon our death-bed, but never in all my life
ſo much as once the contrary; and to ſpeak ingenuouſly, I have often obſerved,
that they who go from us to them, ſeem (which you make the only judge) more
ſpirituall, retired, and devout, then before they left us, whereas of the Papiſts that
become Proteſtants (beſides the worldly deſigns they may eaſily be thought to
have) moſt commonly they grow more licentious, both in Faith and manners, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118025:6"/>
the Prieſts, who ſeldome or never are converted, if once paſt the age of
marrying.</p>
               <p>I, who had alwaies believed the puniſhments laid upon them, were reducible to
civill crimes, though defended by them as points of Religion, reſolved to follow
thoſe ſo certain and evident Principles, which I had already framed (for diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of tender Conſciences) whitherſoever they ſhould lead me; and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired
my friend to bring me to the knowledge of ſome moderate and diſcreet Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt,
that I might examine their Tenents, not doubling their eaſie excluſion from
the priviledges of tender Conſciences, this my friend immediately did, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending
one to me, a morally honeſt and underſtanding man, though (ſayes he)
a little abuſed in his Religion, and a great deal for it; After we had met, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed
to diſcourſe with all freedome, the <hi>Recuſant</hi> began with a ſhort ſtory of the
preſent ſufferings of <hi>Papiſts;</hi> whereof (he ſaid) <hi>Some are ſequeſtred for Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency,
and thoſe of all Cavaliers</hi> (caeteris paribus) <hi>the moſt ſeverely, though of
all the moſt excuſeable, becauſe wholly depending upon the pleaſure of the late
King, and infinitely obliged to his Royall Lenity; noting it as an unanſwerable
argument of their fidelity and gratitude towards ſuch as deal with them in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
as alſo that their declining to receive the Oaths of</hi> Supremacy <hi>and</hi> Allegiance,
<hi>for which they have heretofore been ſo violently perſecuted, proceeded not from
any averſion to civill obedience, but becauſe there were mingled in thoſe oaths
certain expreſſions of a pure ſpirituall nature, repugnant to their Conſciences,
and altogether unneceſſary to the common ſecurity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others are equally puniſhed, that is their whole eſtates ſequeſtred, allowing on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
a fifth part for their wives and children, though in true reaſon they are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
juſtifiable, having never been in any Engagement, but found only in ſome
Garriſons of the King, whether they were driven for refuge, being put out
of the protection of the Parliament by publique Proclamation, their houſes eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
where rifled, their goods plunder'd, and lives endangered by the ſouldiers,
whoſe condition ſeems clearly to be within the equity of that Article of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
Propoſalls, <hi>Aug. 1647. That the Kings meniall ſervants, who never took
up Arms, but only attended on his Perſon, according to their Offices, be freed
from Compoſition;</hi> much more thoſe who had both the civill reaſon of duty,
and the unanſwerable argument of neceſſity, to plead for their diſcharge: And
(which is yet more hard) ſome Recuſants of this Claſſe, who never bare Armes,
but were only found in Garriſons, for their own perſonall ſecurity, as aforeſaid,
are now rank'd among the higheſt Delinquents, and their eſtates to be ſold, ſuch
are Sir <hi>Henry Beddingfield,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bodenham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gefford, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the ſingle Recuſants, two thirds of their eſtates are ſeized upon, only
for the cauſe of Religion, under which notion are included all ſuch as were here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore
convict of not reſorting to <hi>Common Prayers,</hi> or do now refuſe the Oath
of <hi>Abjuration,</hi> a new Oath made by the two Houſes, when the former kind of
ſervice was aboliſh't, wherein the practiſe is ſtrangely ſevere; for upon bare in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,
the eſtate of the ſuſpected is ſecured, that is his rents &amp;c. ſuſpended,
before any tryall, or legall proof, even in theſe times of peace, and being once
thus half-condemn'd, he has no other remedy to help himſelf, but by forſwearing
his Religion, and ſo by an oath a thouſand times harſher then that <hi>Ex Officio,</hi>
they draw out of his own mouth his condemnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118025:7"/>
When the Sequeſtrators have thus ſeized into their hands two thirds of the
most innocent Recuſants lands and goods, then come the Excize-men, Tax-ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers,
and other Collectors, and pinch away no ſmall part of the poor third pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
that was left them; ſo that after theſe deductions I have known ſome eſtates
of three hundred pound a year, reduced to leſſe then threeſcore, a lean pittance to
maint<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in them and their children, being perſons for the moſt part of good quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
and civill education: and as for Priests it is made as great a crime, to have
taken <hi>Orders</hi> after the rites of their Church, as to have committed the moſt hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
treaſon that can be imagined, and they are far more cruelly puniſh't, then
thoſe that murder their own Parents.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe extreme and fatall Penalties that lie upon the Recuſants meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
for their Conſcience, there are many other afflictions whereof few take notice,
which though of leſſer weight, yet being added to the former, quite ſink them
down to the bottom of ſorrow and perplexity; as their continuall fear of having
their houſes broken open, &amp; ſearch'd by <hi>Purſuivants,</hi> who enter at what hours they
pleaſe, and do there what they liſt, taking away, not only all the inſtruments of
their Religion, but oftentimes money, plate, watches, and other ſuch Popiſh I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls,
eſpecially if they be found in the ſame room with any Pictures, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
with a relative ſuperſtition.</p>
               <p>Another of their afflictions is, that they, I mean theſe ſingle Recuſants, have
no power to ſell or morgage the leaſt part of their eſtates, either to pay their juſt
debts, or defray their neceſſary expences, whereby they are diſabled for all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce,
and their credit being utterly lost, (upon which many of them now provide
even their daily bread) they muſt needs in a ſhort time be brought to a deſperate
neceſſity, if not abſolute ruine; and if any, the moſt quiet and moderate amongſt
them, ſhould deſire to tranſplant himſelf to a milder Climate, and to endeavour
to avoid the offence that is taken againſt him in his own Countrey, he cannot ſo
diſpoſe of his eſtate here, as by Bill of exchange, or any other way, to provide
the leaſt ſubſiſtence for himſelf and his Family, a ſeverity far beyond the moſt
rigid practice of the Scotch Kirk; for there (as I am informed) the perſons of
Recuſants are only baniſht out of the Kingdome, and prohibited to reſide at their
own homes above forty daies in a year, which time is allowed them for the managing
of their estates, and their eſtates allowed them for their maintainance abroad:
A proceeding which their Principles would clearly juſtifie, if they could juſtifie
their Principles: but in England, where compulſion upon the Conſcience is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryed
as the worſt of ſlaveries, to puniſh men ſo ſharply for matters of Religion,
contrary to the Principles publikely received, is a courſe that muſt needs beget
over all the world a ſtrong ſuſpition and prejudice against the honour and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
of that State, which at the ſame time can practiſe ſuch manifest contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions.</p>
               <p>To this deplorable condition (<hi>ſaid he almoſt weeping</hi>) are the Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques
now reduced, yet they bear all, not only with patience, but even ſilence;
for amongſt the printed complaints ſo frequent in theſe times, never any thing
has been ſeen to proceed from them, though alwaies the chief, and now the ſole
ſufferers for their Conſciences, except (not to be altogether wanting to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves)
ſome modest Petitions humbly addreſſed to the Parliament, though ſuch
has been their unhappineſſe, that more weighty affairs have ſtill diſappointed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118025:7"/>
their being taken into conſideration; elſe were they admitted to clear themſelves
of the miſtakes and ſcandalls unjuſtly imputed to them, they would not doubt
fully to ſatisfie all ingenuous and unpaſſionate men, nay even whomſoever, that
were but moderately prejudiced againſt them.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwered, that as every one ſees the ſeverity of the Penalties which
Papiſts ſuffer, ſo for my ſelf, I believe the tenderneſſe of their Conſciences, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they ſuffer: and upon this ground we ſee our Judges and Commi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ee-men
allow Deeds, where they find cleer proof of a valuable conſideration: but Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
and the deſtructive Principles concerning Civill Government, ſeem
to me the two points that are <hi>onely</hi> and <hi>altogether</hi> intolerable in that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Whether Papiſts be guilty of Idolatry in the Queſtion of
Angells, Saints, and Pictures.</head>
               <p>THe Papiſt here firſt took for granted, which indeed I could not deny, that if
any Opinion be probably true, perſecution in that caſe is certainly unlawfull,
becauſe otherwiſe both ſides, for both are probable, if one be, might juſtifiably
perſecute one another, to the utter deſtruction of all Society, and after returned
this anſwer to my firſt objection.</p>
               <p>We reverence indeed (<hi>ſayes he</hi>) the Angells and bleſſed Saints, with a reſpect
far more then we uſe to men, becauſe far above their Dignity, but infinitely below
the adoration we give to GOD, becauſe infinitely below his excellency. All the
miſtakes in this controverſie ariſing from hence, that the language of men has
more diſtinctiveneſſe and variety then the gestures of their bodies, and yet is far
leſſe copious then the thoughts of their minds, whence it is they ſo frequently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
to moſt different conceptions the ſelf-ſame words and poſtures of body, as
the titles of <hi>ſacred Majeſty, moſt High, moſt Mighty,</hi> given to Kings and
States, the ſtile of <hi>Grace</hi> to Dukes and Archbiſhops, of <hi>Lord</hi> to Noblemen, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls,
Ambaſſadors, &amp;c. of <hi>Worſhip</hi> to Gentlemen of quality, and ſuch as
bear any conſiderable Office in the Common-wealth; ſo kneeling to Parents, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
bare to the Parloament, and other Courts, bowing to one another, &amp;c.
all theſe very expreſſions are the ſame we uſe towards God himſelf, and paſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently,
when rightly underſtood, but to a ſcrupulous and wilfull ſpirit, how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive
would this one word <hi>Worſhipfull</hi> be, if he reflected with a little rigour
and frowardneſſe upon it? now as every old woman has capacity enough to make
a different apprehenſion betwixt going to ſpeak with one at the <hi>Lion</hi> in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi>
and going to ſee the Lion in the <hi>Tower,</hi> ſo may any the moſt ſimple Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
in the world, by a very little teaching, learn to distinguiſh the <hi>Crucifix</hi>
which he ſees in the Church, from Chriſt whom he believes to be in heaven, and
conſequently in no more danger of committing Idolatry to that Picture, then the
other of fearing to he torn in pieces by the Sign.</p>
               <p>Upon this Argument of the Papiſt, I call'd to mind what I had read my ſelf
in Scripture, how the Prophet <hi>Balaam</hi> fell flat upon the ground, and adored an
Angell, <hi>Num.</hi> 22. 31. and <hi>Joſhua</hi> gave the ſame honour to another, that ſtil'd
himſelf <hi>Captain of the Lords Hoſt,</hi> and therefore could not be the Lord, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 5.
13. nay he was commanded yet farther, to <hi>put off his ſhoes, becauſe the ground
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118025:8"/>
was holy,</hi> by the preſence of an Angell; theſe examples I confeſſe, being related
in the Bible, without the leaſt note of reproof, enforce us to admit ſeverall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
of worſhip, infinitely differing in the intention of the mind, though very
little in outward expreſſions. Now by whatſoever names we <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſhal agree
to call this behaviour of <hi>Balaam, Joſhua,</hi> and even all the Jews before the Ark and
Cherubins, I ſee plainly will fully expreſſe, and ſhrewdly juſtifie (at leaſt from
Idolatry) all the approved practiſes of the Papiſts, which truly caſt up, as far as
I can diſcern, amount to no more then a reverence towards Saints and Angells,
ſuitable to the excellency of their State, and for Churches, Altars, Pictures,
&amp;c. only to an Eccleſiaſticall kind of good manners. And by the Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
thus far ſeems to me evident, that all honor or diſhonor done to the Image,
reflects upon the Principall, ſince not one amongſt us but would condemn him
for a Malignant, that ſhould ſhoot at my <hi>Lord Generalls Picture</hi> without <hi>Temple
Bar,</hi> and if any ſhould reprove him for his temerity, we would preſently conclude
ſuch perſon wel-affected to the preſent Government, and not at all ſequeſtrable for
<hi>Idolatry,</hi> unleſſe we could prove that the abuſed and doting people ſuperſtitiouſly
adored the painted cloth, which kind of worſhip, I am ſatisfied, no Recuſant gives
even to the picture of our Savionr.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I think it probable, not certain, as the Papiſts do, that the ſecond <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement</hi>
intends not to forbid any ſuch inferiour ſpirituall civilities, becauſe
wiſe Governours contrive their Laws againſt thoſe vices, to which they ſee their
Subjects particularly enclined, and therefore downright <hi>Idolatry,</hi> by offering Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
to Gods, made with hands, and repoſing confidence in their aſſiſtance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the common ſins of thoſe times, 'tis probable we ought to interpret this <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept,</hi>
as a proviſion againſt Heatheniſh Idolatry, not againſt ſuch kind of reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
as the Jewes by Gods own appointment uſed before the Ark and Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubins.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Agreeable to this, is the Opinion of the learned Mr.</hi> Hobs <hi>in his</hi> Leviathan,
<hi>where</hi> fol. 360. <hi>he affirms that</hi> to worſhip God in ſome peculiar place, or turning
a mans face towards an Image, is not to worſhip the place or Image, but to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
them holy, that is to ſay, ſet apart from common uſe; for that is the
meaning of the word <hi>holy,</hi> which implies no new quality in the place or Image,
but only a new relation by appropriation to God, and therefore is not idolatry.
But to worſhip God, as inanimating or inhabiting ſuch place or Image, is idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
as alſo to worſhip God, not as inanimating or preſent in the place or Image,
but to the end to be put in mind of him or of ſome of his works, in caſe the place
or image be dedicated or ſet up by private authority, and not by the authority of
them that are our ſoveraigne Paſtors, is idolatry: for the Commandement is,
THOU SHALT NOT MAKE TO THY SELF ANY
GRAVEN IMAGE.</p>
               <p>Thus in my judgment doth that learned <hi>Proteſtant</hi> abſolutely clear the Papiſts
of idolatry, though perhaps he had more preciſely expreſt this laſt way of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing
the ſecond <hi>Commandement,</hi> if he had call'd it <hi>will-worſhip</hi> rather then <hi>ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi>
becauſe there is only a want of commiſſion, no exceſſe in the degree of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence:
And though afterwards he condemne praying to Saints departed, as ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,
yet it is only upon a particular ſuppoſition of his own, that there is yet no
ſuch thing as Saints in heaven.</p>
               <p>When I had read this paſſage of ſo famous an Author to the Recuſant, he to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118025:8"/>
requite my civility, immediately ſhewed me the words of the <hi>Councell of Trent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
which he ſaid differed nothing at all from Mr. <hi>Hobs,</hi> and very little from me: For
as I thought, that the exhibition of ſome inferior kind of reverence towards
Churches, and other inſtruments of piety, was probably unforbidden: So that
Councell decrees the abſolute lawfulneſſe thereof in the 25. <hi>Seſſion,</hi> where to the
Canon concerning Images are added theſe words of explanation: <hi>Not that there
is believed any divinity or vertue in them, for which they ought to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped,
or that they are to be petitioned for any thing, or any confidence ought to be
repoſed in images, as of old was done by the Gentiles, who placed their hope in
Idolls, but becauſe the honor exhibited to them is referred to the Prototypes they
repreſent, that ſo thorough the Images, which we kiſſe and before which we bare
our heads and kneel down, we may adore Chriſt and venerate his Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon occaſion of which words, the Papiſt aſſured me, that in no Councell is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
the phraſe of <hi>Religious worſhip,</hi> when they treat of theſe queſtions, nor any
thing concerning them commanded as neceſſary, but only their lawfullneſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared,
that ſuch as find benefit by their aſſiſting the memory, or exciting the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
may ſafely uſe them, the reſt may let them alone, provided they cenſure
not the practiſe of others, over whom they have no Juriſdiction, nor condemn
the judgment of the Church, who has Juriſdiction over them.</p>
               <p>And hereupon we both agreed in this collaterall obſervation, that if all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern
Controvertiſts would reſtrain their diſputes to poſitions generally received
as of Faith in the Church, of which they are members, attending only to her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions,
and not to the termes of particular Writers, the differences amongſt
Chriſtians, ſo fatall to the peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> would be both leſſe numerous, and
far more reconcileable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Whether Papiſts be guilty of Idolatry in the Euchariſt.</head>
               <p>BEfore we could proceed to the ſecond part of this Queſtion, the Recuſant
upon ſome occaſions was obliged to go into the Countrey, whence he ſent me
this following paper.</p>
               <p>Since it is concluded between us, that probability exempts from perſecution, I
ſhall endeavour to prove that the reall preſence of our Saviour in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi>
is at leaſt a probable Opinion; and in order thereunto, cite the most expreſſe and
direct termes of the holy Scripture, as firſt the promiſe of our SAVIOUR,
John. 6. 5. <hi>The bread that I will give is my fleſh, which I will give for the life of
the world,</hi> and verſe 55. <hi>My Fleſh is meat indeed, and my Bloud is drink in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</hi>
Secondly, The performance of that promiſe, in the words of Inſtitution,
<hi>Take eat, this is my Body;</hi> punctually repeated by the other three Evangeliſts,
<hi>Mat. 26. 26. Mar. 14. 22. Luke</hi> 22. 19. And thirdly, the places declaring the
uſe of this Sacrament in the Apoſtles time, 1 Cor. 10. 16. <hi>The Cup of bleſſing
which we bleſſe, is it not the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt? and the bread
which we break is it not the participation of the Body of the Lord?</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 29.
<hi>He that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
not diſcerning the Lords Body.</hi> Thus the great Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul,</hi> and all the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118025:9"/>
foure Evangeliſts unanimouſly teach the Doctrine of the Reall Preſence, and not
one ſingle place produceable that in direct termes calls the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> a ſigne or
figure of Chriſts Body, notwithſtanding the maintainers thereof admit no proof
as authenticall but the preciſe text of Scripture, yet in this ſo important contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie
they flie to logicall inferences and Philoſophicall diſcourſes, and ſo make
their own reaſon the Judge, and not the Word of God, rendring by their now and
private interpretations this great Sacrament inferior in dignity, not only to the
<hi>Paſchall Lamb,</hi> a type of Chriſt, but even to <hi>Manna,</hi> which was but a figure of
this very myſtery.</p>
               <p>Surely if we ſhal add to ſo many &amp; evident texts of Scripture, the constant iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the Fathers, and the univerſall practice of the whole Chriſtian world
for above a thouſand years (ſince ſo long is acknowledged the abſolute reigne of
our Religion) we may ſafely conclude the Doctrine of our Saviours preſence
in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> to be at leaſt probable, and conſequently Catholikes in no wiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable
of raſhneſſe or obſtinacy, in believing a Poſition ſo efficaciouſly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended
unto them.</p>
               <p>But admitting the Doctrine of non-reality to be true, (<hi>ſaid the Letter of the
Recuſant</hi>) yet ought not Catholikes to be iudged guilty of the ſin of idolatry,
becauſe their adoration is not intentionally directed to any creature, but to the
Perſon of Chriſt our Lord: and if He be not there, their worſhip is miſtaken
in the place, not in the obiect, and therefore at moſt an error of fact, and no
formall Idolatry, which no temperate Judge will impute unto ſin, much leſſe our
mercifull Redeemer, who came to ſave, not to deſtroy, who accepts of the good
meaning of his ſervants, though mingled with humane infirmities, as when <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech</hi>
miſ-took <hi>Sara</hi> from her husband, being informed by <hi>Abraham</hi> that ſhe was
his Siſter, the ſincere and conſcientious King received abſolution from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
upon this account, that he did it (ſaith the text) <hi>in the ſimplicity of his heart,</hi>
Gen. 20. 6. which ſeems an expreſſe and infallible deciſion of this Controverſie,
that men may be unhappy by being deceived, but are not guilty, unleſſe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
themſelves.</p>
               <p>This kind of reaſoning prevailed ſomewhat the more with me, becauſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology
of the <hi>reformed Churches</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> expreſſely approves it; ſaying, <hi>if an
Apoſtle had by miſtake adored ſome other man reſembling Chriſt, when he lived
on earth, his error would have excuſed him, Daillé</hi> chap. 11. As on the other ſide,
<hi>Mary Magdalens</hi> not adoring Chriſt, when he appeared to her in the habit of a
Gardener, <hi>John</hi> 20. 15. was never accuſed as a defect of devotion; wherefore
ſince the Papiſts all profeſſe not to terminate their adoration in the ſpecies of
Bread and Wine, nor any other creature, but in the bleſſed perſon of our Lord,
I conclude them erroneous in their Doctrine, but not Idolatrous in their
practiſe, to be pitied as ſouls miſled, not perſecuted as malicious.</p>
               <p>Nor can I ſatisfie my Conſcience, ſince as to this point the Opinion of the
<hi>Papiſts</hi> is no more oppoſite to us, then that of the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> why we ſhould
freely allow Communion to <hi>theſe</hi> even of ſpirituall things, and in the mean while
not afford <hi>them</hi> ſo much as the liberty to poſſeſſe their own temporall goods. The
<hi>Lutherans</hi> believe our SAVIOUR to be as really in the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> as he
was upon the Croſſe, but do not adore him; the Papiſts both believe and adore;
for my part, I ſhould clearly, either do both, or neither, at leaſt I ſhall never be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118025:9"/>
brought to this partiality, to cheriſh the one as brethren, and perſecute the other as
enemies; eſpecially when I conſider the Chriſtian proceedings of the Proteſtants in
<hi>New-England, Virginia,</hi> aud the other plantations in the <hi>Indies,</hi> where we ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor
to deſtroy the Natives, though confeſſedly Idolaters, but rather ſtrive to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
them, by holding out the truth in love.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Whether Papiſts are inconſiſtent with Civill Government.</head>
               <p>BY the next Poſt I received from the ſame hand another Letter concerning the
common objection, that Papiſts hold many Principles deſtructive to civill So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety;
wherein the Recuſant proteſting firſt ſolemnly, as in the ſight of God and
his holy Angells, to uſe all ingenuity and candor in his relation of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
Doctrine, earneſtly intreated me to give credit to his report in the matters
of <hi>Fact,</hi> and for the right, to judge freely, as I ſaw cauſe.</p>
               <p>We will divide (<hi>ſayes he</hi>) the main Queſtion into two points, as it relates ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to our equalls, or Superiours: for the firſt touching Commerce and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
we abſolutely diſclaim that ſcandalous opinion, <hi>that no Faith is to kept with
Heretikes,</hi> and flatly deny, that our Engagement, promiſe, or contract, may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
be broken by our ſelves, or diſpenſed with by any Power on earth, to the
prejudice of a third perſon, of what Religion ſoever, and for <hi>equivocation, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
reſervation,</hi> &amp;c. I am confident, though I have not here any oportunity to
look into books, that no Generall Councell mentions either any ſuch word, or any
ſuch thing; Schoolmen indeed frequently diſpute ſuch ſubtilties, which by men of
different principles and affections in Religion are eaſily miſunderſtood, and often
perverted, but amongſt <hi>Catholiques</hi> every one has liberty to deny them as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
without any prejudice to Faith: and though thoſe ſpeculations generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
encouragement, yet when they arrive at a certain degree of niceneſſe, they
rather become an innocent curioſity, then profitable euployment, and in ſuch an
infinity of Opinions, as Catholike writers have leiſure to publiſh, it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
but that thorough paſſion, unwarineſſe, or humane frailty, ſome miſtakes muſt
eſcape, and then the unhappineſſe is, that prejudiced and captious Readers apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
their whole ſtudy to find faults, forget the good and wholeſome notions they
meet, and remember nothing but the errors.</p>
               <p>As to the ſecond branch concerning our duty to Magiſtrates, we deny, <hi>ſayes the
letter,</hi> any earthly power can diſpenſe with our civill obedience, and acknowledge
our ſelves bound, not only by the Law of Nature, but by the expreſſe Word of
God, to <hi>render unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, to be ſubject not only
for feare, but conſcience ſake;</hi> What Chriſtian Prince or State is there in the
world, whom the Subjects ſerve with more fidelity then the <hi>Spaniard, French,</hi>
and <hi>Italian,</hi> all Catholike Dominions? and particularly in <hi>England,</hi> where we
are ſome of <hi>Paul,</hi> aud ſome of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and ſome of <hi>Cephas,</hi> what compariſon is
there betwixt the behaviour of <hi>Catholikes,</hi> towards <hi>H. 8. Edw.</hi> 6. and <hi>Eliz.</hi> and
the fury of <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> and indeed whereſoever they
are diſcontented; yet there is a vaſt difference, as to Government, between theſe
two caſes, to oppoſe by force the introduce men of innovations, by which the peace
muſt needs be endangered, and to attempt by force the extinguiſhment of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
Religion, whereof the people are univerſally in quiet and immemoriall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion,
the one drives others out of poſſeſſion, the other maintains himſelf in, the
one invades his neighbours rights, the other defends his own.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118025:10"/>
How many modern experiences (the eaſieſt argument to be underſtood, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
to be relied on) clearly reſolve this queſtion; if we but conſider the union
of hearts, and common intereſts of State, between the Proteſtant and Catholike
<hi>Cantons</hi> of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> where very many Churches ſerve by turns upon the ſame
day, for the exerciſe of both Religions, dividing every Sunday morning into
two parts, and aſſigning to each about three hours for their devotions, wherein
they are ſo punctuall to maintain equality, that if the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have the firſt
three hours one morning, next week they are to have the laſt; and this they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
practiſe, without enterfering or offending one another.</p>
               <p>To this ſo pregnant example (ſufficient of it ſelfe to cleare the conſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
of thoſe two Religions) I ſhall further add their fair comportment
one towards another, in many Provinces, and free Towns in <hi>Germany;</hi> but
moſt remarkable is their friendly and peaceable living together in <hi>Holland,</hi> even
during ſo long and dangerous wars with <hi>Spain; Spain</hi> the chief protector of the
Catholique Faith; <hi>Spain</hi> the moſt zealous propagator of the Pontificiall Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
to whoſe Dominion, if the united Provinces ſhould again return, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the Catholikes there might prudently promiſe to themſelves all poſſible advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages;
yet notwithſtanding ſo great occaſion of jealouſie, the <hi>States</hi> (then whom
none are more vigilant over their true Intereſt) have not only with ſecurity, but
exceeding benefit to their Common-wealth, tolerated the <hi>Catholikes</hi> of quiet
Converſation, to live freely amongſt them. And on the other ſide the <hi>Catholikes,</hi>
in gratitude for ſo favourable a treating, have exactly correſponded to the
mercy of their Magiſtrates, with a moſt conſtant, ſincere, and faithfull
obedience.</p>
               <p>To none of theſe ſuſpitions are the <hi>Recuſants of</hi> England in the leaſt meaſure
obnoxious, becauſe whatever change of Government can happen, they muſt expect
but a milder degree of diſaffection towards them, at moſt a ſufferance, no incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement,
or particular confidence; and infallibly, if the rigour of the Laws
(made upon far different motives which are now no waies preſſing) were qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to a temper of mercy, that the <hi>Catholikes</hi> might enjoy but half the Liberties
to which they were born, they would be the most quiet and uſefull Subjects of
England, ſince their Religion obliges them to obey the lawfull commands of
their Superiours, not only for fear, but conſcience. Nor did ever the very worſt
of them ſtir in any ſedition at a time when they were admitted to but half the
common rights of Engliſh-men, nor were they many that ever attempted their
own relief by endangering their Countreys peace, all the reſt ſitting quietly and
patiently under the burthens which the heavy hand of thoſe times continually
heapt upon them.</p>
               <p>Now that the crimes (though never ſo hainous) of a few diſcontented and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate
ſpirits, ſhould be imputed to their Religion, whoſe Principles expreſſely
condemn ſuch conſpiracies, ſeems extremely rigorous; but when to thoſe diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
imputations are joyned intolerable penalties, both upon our lives and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states,
and not only against the then living Catholikes, but all their Poſterity
to this very day, ſurely it muſt needs appear the moſt harſh and ſevere proceeding
that ever was practiſed in the world: wherefore I ſhall cloſe this ſecond Letter
with my humble prayers to the gracious Redeemer of our ſouls, that you would
ceaſe to impute all our faults to our Religion, and we begin to commit no other fault
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118025:10"/>
but our Religion, ſo ſhould we happily overcome our own infirmities, and fully
ſatisfie your jealouſies.</p>
               <p>When I had well peruſed this Gentlemans diſcourſe, and attentively read his
letters, I muſt freely confeſſe, I could not have believed that either the Papiſts had
ſuffered ſo much from us, or been able to ſay ſo much for themſelves, I doe not
mean in order to prove the truth of their Religion, but the unreaſonableneſſe of
our perſecution; ſince really to my underſtanding our jealouſies of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
ſeem as unneceſſary unto us, as prejudiciall to them; for I am confident there
is no Religion in the world, but by good Laws againſt breach of Peace, and due
execution of them, may be made conſiſtent with any Kingdome or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
whatſoever; who more oppoſite in belief then <hi>Chriſtians, Jewes,</hi> and
<hi>Turks,</hi> yet we ſee by experience that <hi>Jews</hi> are not inconſiſtent with the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> nor <hi>Chriſtians</hi> with that of the <hi>Turks,</hi> no not ſuch <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
as are here in queſtion, <hi>Papiſts;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As concerning the Doctrine we charge upon them, of the Popes power over
Supreme Magiſtrates, I had the fortune ſome few years ſince, to meet with a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
that clearly anſwered all my difficulties, wherein were written the <hi>negative</hi>
ſubſcriptions of many Engliſh Recuſants againſt theſe three following <hi>Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
as no part of their Faith or Religion, the Subſcribers being both in number
and quality ſufficient to repreſent the whole body of them in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That the Pope or Church hath power to abſolve any perſon or perſons from
their obedience to the civill and politicall Government eſtabliſht, or to be
eſtabliſht in this Nation in Civil and Politicall Affairs.</item>
                  <item>2. That by the command or diſpenſation of the Pope or Church, it is lawfull
to kill, deſtroy, or do any injury to any perſon or perſons living within the
Kings Dominions, becauſe that ſuch a perſon or perſons are accuſed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned,
cenſured, or excommunicated for <hi>Errour, Schiſme,</hi> or <hi>Hereſie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. That it is lawfull in it ſelf, or by diſpenſation from the Pope, to break
promiſe or oath made to any of the foreſaid perſons, under pretence that
they are Heretiques.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe they utterly diſclaim, and renounce as no part of their belief, profeſſing
under their hands their readineſſe to abjure (if the State ſhould ſo require) the
practiſe and execution of them all, which gave me ſo much the more ſatisfaction,
by how much it was beſides my expectation, nor have I now any thing to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
them upon that account.</p>
               <p>And indeed if we conſider theſe differences between us impartially, our ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
are not only confuted, but ſhamed by our own daily experience, for we truſt
<hi>Papiſts</hi> in all Negotiations, as indifferently as <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> nay even our Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers
and Merchants beyond Seas (where the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are Maſters) converſe and
traffique ſecurely with them, and yet I never heard the leaſt complaint of any one
ſingle Proteſtant's being cheated by them, upon pretence of exemption or diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,
and therefore ſince they practiſe not that part, which may ſometimes be
profitable, I cannot think they hold to no purpoſe, that which is alwaies preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:118025:11"/>
For my ſmall experience in the world, all the objection that ever I heard of
againſt the credit of our <hi>Papiſts,</hi> was their being diſabled by ſequeſtrations to pay
their debts, not taught by their Religion to deceive the Creditors.</p>
               <p>If their Doctrines were ſo deſtructive to civill Society, as our accuſations pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend,
how comes it to paſſe that all our fundamentall Laws were enacted by them,
who inveſted the Supreme Authority of this Nation with ſo honourable Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,
and yet provided ſo prudently for the juſt ſecurity of the people, againſt
the unjuſt inc<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oachments of Prerogative? from whom have all thoſe excellent
cuſtomes and Statutes of this Nation deſcended upon us? is it poſſible we ſhould
derive all the ancient Priviledges of Parliament; and Liberties of the Subject con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
in <hi>Magna Charta, &amp;c.</hi> from the times their Religion governed the Land,
and yet ſay now their Religion is inconſiſtent with the Government of the Land?
as it is very true, that ſometimes the Popes power here was abuſed to ſupport a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
intereſt, ſo it is evident to thoſe that know Hiſtory, that his mediation has
been often available, both for the preventing and reconciling of our differences,
as well with our neighbouring Kingdomes, as amongſt our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Nor is it poſſible that any Modell of Government ſhould be abſolutely proof
againſt all exceptions, but in the experience of five or ſix hundred years ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes
wil certainly happen; whence it is eaſie for a ſevere obſerver to gather obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
enough to puzzle the moſt able and politique Statiſt in the world to anſwer,
eſpecially if they be managed with dexterity and eloquence amongſt a half-witted
and ſtubborn people, who neither can guide themſelves, nor will be led by others,
not blind enough to be ignorant, where they are, and yet too ſhort-ſighted to ſee
whether they go; unhappy chiefly in this, that they are tender in the ſenſe of any
preſent evill, and wholly incapable of foreſeeing the deſtruction that followes
their impatience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hear what is charitably ſaid of Papiſts in the foreſaid</hi> Examination <hi>of the late</hi>
Synods Confeſſion of Faith (<hi>page</hi> 266.) The Papiſts believe in the ſame God
with the Proteſtants, even in the Father, the Son, and the holy Ghoſt, though
they differ in ſome Articles, or branches of Articles of their belief, and in their
way of worſhip; yea ſome of the Papiſts are regenerate, conſcientious, and
vertuous perſons.</p>
               <p>Wherefore (I humbly conceive) our Magiſtrates and Miniſters ought ſincerely to
enquire into the truth of things, and make a conſcience of judging or preaching
otherwiſe then <hi>ſecundum probata,</hi> and not upon bare jealouſies, or the blind opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the vulgar condemn any free-born member of this Nation farther then he
ſhall be proved to be guilty: Nor do I believe it reaſonable, to charge every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtifiable
action of particular <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or extravagant opinion of any private
writer amongſt them, upon the whole Body of their Religion; The Decrees of
their Councells, they profeſſe to be the only abſolute declarers of their Faith,
amongſt whoſe determinations there are faults enough, which they ſtrive to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend,
no need of impoſing upon them errors, which they flatly deny<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Let us
lay our hands upon our own hearts, we our ſelves want not our capriches and
exorbitant conceits, which ough<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not to be imputed to the whole refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
Religion, but to the imperfection of humane nature, eaſily decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
with the colour of truth, and paſſionately in love with it's owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118025:11"/>
Beſides inſtead of jealouſies and dangers, I cannot ſee but great ſecurity and
advantages would accrue to this Nation, by treating in mercy all peaceable Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts;
the Pope would be deprived of that ſpecious pretext of relieving his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed
Flock; the Princes and States of that Religion, would for honour
as well as conſcience, upon all occaſions, expreſſe their ſatisfaction to ſee
them mercifully uſed, whom for their profeſſion they account brethren,
and for their ſufferings, Martyrs. The <hi>Protestants</hi> in other Countreys would
be more aſſured of the freedome they injoy, and more hopefull of obtaining
new encreaſes of their liberty; The Papiſts of England would be bound by their
own intereſt (the ſtrongeſt obligation amongſt wiſemen) to live peaceably
and thankfully in the private exerciſe of their conſciences, and, becoming gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
by ſuch compaſſion, could not ſo reaſonably be diſtruſted, as the <hi>Prelaticall</hi> or
<hi>Presbyterian</hi> Party, who muſt needs reckon themſelves no ſmall loſers, in that
the reines of authority are taken out of their hands, which they had by turns abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
into meer whips for their brethren.</p>
               <p>Of the one we have had too long experience in their <hi>High Commiſſion,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
ſince its power was overgrown by the conſpiracy of the <hi>Starchamber;</hi> a
Court, where fines were impoſed not according to the quality of the offences, but
of the Judges, who thought it below their honour to puniſh under thouſands of
pounds for every <hi>Peccadillo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the other, though our tryall has been but ſhort, yet it was very ſmart, and
lives ſtill in the memory of <hi>England,</hi> which is every day refreſht by the preſent
practiſe of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where the <hi>Kirk</hi> has condemn'd all that differ in the leaſt
tittle from her humor, crying <hi>Anathema Maranatha</hi> upon all the Congregations
of the Saints, as appears by their <hi>Synodicall Act,</hi> ſet forth in <hi>Jan.</hi> 1650.
and ſent to their Brethren in <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> where, having firſt called our wayes
<hi>abominations,</hi> and our ſelves a <hi>perverſe generation,</hi> and branded thoſe few ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
Scots, who ſuffered themſelves to be undeceived by the reaſons and civility
of our Army, with the infamous name of <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> they proceed to the moſt
bitter, malicious, and ſcandalous words that an inraged Scot can utter, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
thus to their Party. <hi>We exhort you, and by all the power over you: we
have in the Lord, require you, carefully to avoid all familiar converſe of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
degree, above all, that you beware to joyne with them</hi> (thoſe that adhere
to the Parliament of England) <hi>in any publike or private exerciſe of Religion,
thoſe who will adventure to touch pitch, may be defiled before they be aware,
thoſe who will not abstain from the Harlots houſe, ſhall not be innocent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> take
heed</hi> (dearly beloved) <hi>of them that are led by the ſubtilty and depth of the Divell,
and among all his inſtruments, we intreat you to avoid none more then theſe
miſerable Apoſtates of our own Nation, for we conceive none more ſitted to work
miſchiefe among you then this ſort of men:</hi> and in their motives or grounds for a
Faſt in <hi>June</hi> 1651. their expreſſions againſt us are no leſſe bitter: ſee how
their zeal boyles, while they are but a kindling, while we choke the fuell in
its owne ſmoke, how will their fury run over, when the fire ſhall by
any ſucceſſe be raiſed into a flame! how will they drowne the whole
Countrey in an inuadation of more then Antichriſtian ſlavery!</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118025:12"/>
But becauſe I perceived by a paſſage in the Recuſants diſcourſe, that nothing lay
more heavy upon them then the new Oath of <hi>Abjuration</hi> made by the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian
Party in the beginning of the late troubles; I ſhall adventure humbly to
move ſome <hi>Queres</hi> thereupon, tranſcribing firſt a true Copy of the Oath it
ſelfe.</p>
               <p>J. A. B. Do abjure and renounce the Popes Supremacy and Authority over
the Catholike Church in generall, aud over my ſelf in particular, and I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
that there is not any Tranſubſtantiation in the Sacrament of the Lords
Supper, or in the Elements of Bread and Wine after Conſecration thereof, by
any perſon whatſoever; and I do believe that there is not any Purgatory; and
that the conſecrated Host, Crucifixes or Images ought not to be worſhipped, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
that any worſhip is due unto them; and I alſo believe that Salvation cannot
be merited by works, and all Doctrines in affirmation of the ſaid points, I do
abjure and renounce without any AEquivocation; mentall reſervation, or ſecret
evaſion whatſoever, taking the words by me ſpoken, according to the common and
uſuall meaning of them, So help me God.</p>
               <p>1. Whether this Oath do not flatly contradict the known Laws of the Land,
by enforcing a free-born Engliſh-man to accuſe himſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with ſo ſtrong and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
a temptation to perjury, where the choice is only this, either forſwear your
Religion, or ruine your eſtate; a ſeverity that far exceeds the tyranny of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates,
whoſe indignation ſtayed it ſelf upon the exteriour non-conformity; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
this paſſes on to conſtrain the inward belief of the mind, which God (the
ſearcher of all hearts) hath reſerved to himſelf, and all this, in Queſtions no waies
concerning either Idolatry, or the ſecurity of the State; as Purgatory, and the
Doctrine of merits, for that conſcience that is not wide enough to ſwallow all
the Oath, how great ſoever the part is that he can digeſt, it will do him no
good.</p>
               <p>2. This Oath being wholly Negative, and no Poſitive Articles eſtabliſht by
the Parliament, to be propoſed to all as the touchſtone of Faith, whether it be
conſcientious to oblige the Papiſt to ſwear away his own Religion, before we have
provided another for him?</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Whether it be conſcientious or reaſonable for us to enforce this Oath on the
Papiſts, ſince we have many godly perſons of our own party, who will not take
it, and others who will not ſwear at all: Hear what is ſaid in the</hi> Examination
<hi>of the before mentioned</hi> Synodicall Confeſſion, <hi>page</hi> 238. There is a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint
laid upon us now then in the old Teſtament, Mat. 5. 34. James 5. 12.
which hath made ſome to ſhun Oaths, though called to ſwear by the Magiſtrate
in matters lawfull. <hi>And again,</hi> that it is a ſin in thoſe, who impoſe unneceſſary,
ſubtill and enſnaring oaths, <hi>Zach.</hi> 5. 3. 4. There is a curſe gone out againſt ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,
as well as against thieves, becauſe of needleſſe ſwearing, as well as falſe
ſwearing, <hi>a Land is made to mourn,</hi> Jer. 23. 10.</p>
               <p>4. Since all theſe Negatives are not clearly ſet down in Scripture, as funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental
paints of Chriſtian Faith, but deduced from paſſages, to which the Anſwers
are believed as probable by them, as the arguments by us, why ſhould we ſo
cruelly perſecute one another for Doctrines; that are either obſcurely revealed, or
not neceſſarily enjoyned.</p>
               <p>5. How ſhall we defend the Oath againſt this Objection, that any <hi>Jew, Turk</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118025:12"/>
or <hi>Infidell</hi> may take it lawfully, according to their Principles, nay will delight
to ſwear againſt ſo many points of that Church, which (by reaſon of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining
Territories) mainly oppoſes them; nor have we any Law at all (to my
knowledge) for which Jew, Turk, Heathen, or the moſt groſſe Heatheniſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator
is ſequeſtrable, nor any penall Oath againſt the moſt extravagant blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
that a looſe wit can imagine, and a prophane tongue utter, as <hi>Ranters,
Antitrinitarians,</hi> and the like? what can be more deſtructive to the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> then the prophane and ſcandalous blaſphemies of Mr. <hi>Fry,</hi>
a late Member of Parliament, who publikely in print, not only denies, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides
that Supreme Myſtery of <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> the ſacred <hi>Trinity,</hi> calling it a
<hi>chaffy and abſurd Opinion, &amp;c.</hi> yet the mercy of the Parliament contented it ſelf
with a moderate and favourable puniſhment, excluding him only from ſitting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
them; and if his Dignity and publique Character had not rendred him
obnoxious to the crime of ſcandall, he might perhaps have remained as free
from trouble, as all the reſt of his Opinion do, who never yet have ſuffered the
leaſt moleſtation for the greateſt exorbitances that can be deviſed.</p>
               <p>In particular at the Quarter Seſſions at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> on the 24. of <hi>June</hi> 1651.
there wered five <hi>Ranters</hi> convented before Colonell <hi>Baxter,</hi> and other Juſtices,
and ſufficient proof, that they had maintained that one <hi>Robins a Glazier was a
Prophet, and that his wife was with child of the Meſſias,</hi> with ſuch other blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous
ſtuff; but four of theſe, not then abſolutely aſſerting theſe Opinions,
nor yet denying them, but evading the ſeverall queſtions demanded of them by the
Bench, were diſcharged, the fifth was committed (as he well deſerved) not for his
Opinions, but for calling the Juſtices Traytors, &amp;c. On the ſame day a gentle-woman
great with child, and ſome others, were alſo convented, for a ſuppoſed
hearing of Maſſe, on the day commonly called <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> day 1650. at the then
<hi>French Agents</hi> in Long Acre, and though there was no direct proof that they
were at <hi>Maſſe,</hi> but at Mattins or Prayers before Maſſe, yet Colonell <hi>Baxter</hi> did
maintain againſt ſome other of the Juſtices, that <hi>Mattins</hi> and <hi>Maſſe</hi> was all one,
and ſo the gentlewoman and the reſt were fined one hundred marks a piece, and
ſent to priſon, according to the rigour of the Statute in that behalfe formerly
made, the ſeverity of which laſt proceeding, and the partiality of the firſt, needs
no Comment.</p>
               <p>Why muſt the <hi>Papiſt</hi> be thus ſingled out from all the reſt, and peremptorily
forc't to this hard choice, of either forfeiting his eſtate, or forſaking his Conſcience?
if we fear their encreaſe, we overvalue their Religion, if we doubt their diſturbing
us, we undervalue our own ſtrength, abundantly ſufficient are the means which
God has put into our hands, to ſecure our ſelves from a few diſarm'd Papiſts, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly
ſufficient were this only proviſion, to exclude them from Offices of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance,
and execute ſevere puniſhment upon ſuch as ſhould actually attempt any
thing to the diſcompoſure of the State.</p>
               <p>Nor can ſuch gentleneſſe and moderation towards quiet Recuſants, be juſtly
accounted a toleration of them, becauſe (I conceive) that word ſignifies an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
equality in all civill reſpects, betwixt Subjects of different judgements in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
elſe the preſent ſufferings of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> paying their two thirds, might by
the ſame frowardneſſe be accuſed as a toleration; whereas the Penalties indeed
are altogether intolerable: Not to inflict the utmoſt ſeverity of puniſhment, is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118025:13"/>
not preſently to be reputed an allowance of the crime, God himſelf ſuffers
all the ſins we commit, but approves none of them; we our ſelves daily permit
miſchiefs to avoid in conveniences, and for that reaſon we prohibit not <hi>Maſſe</hi> in
the houſes of Ambaſſadors, nor pnniſh uſury, though the Statute it ſelf 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
8. brands it with the name of Vice, and moſt Divines hold it a deteſtable
ſin, expreſſely forbidden by the Law of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A conſcientious way of ſetling Religion propoſed.</head>
               <p>IN the ſame place where God commands children to obey their parents, he
forbids parents to provoke their children, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. And where he exacts fidelity
in ſervants, he likewiſe requires moderation in Maſters, nay more, the text in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes
even bondmen and ſlaves, enjoyning the Maſters <hi>to forbear threatning,
knowing that their Master alſo is in heaven, neither is there reſpect of perſons
with him:</hi> thus clearly doth the Word of God condemn as well harſhneſſe and
cruelty in Governours, as ſtubbornneſſe and treachery in Subjects; ſo that there
is alſo a tenderneſſe of conſcience requiſite on the Magiſtrates part, to proceed
ſincerely and purely for the good of the people, that he may truely ſay with the
Apoſtle, <hi>I ſeek not yours, but you,</hi> 2 Cor. 12. 1. and again verſe 17. <hi>Did I
make a gain of you, by any of them whom I ſent unto you?</hi> in which two
lines we are plainly advertiſed of the chiefe danger which Superiours ought care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
to avoid, that neither themſelves, nor their under-Officers make a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
of mens conſciences concerning matters of Religion.</p>
               <p>Since therefore the only tolerable deſigne of the Corrector in ſuch caſes is the
benefit of the ſufferer, it neceſſarily follows, that before we can with the leaſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
of Juſtice inflict a penalty upon any different profeſſion, we ought to uſe all
means poſſible to recover them to truth, and therefore our firſt work ſhould be
to collect a body of poſitive Articles, evidently contained in Gods Word, and
abſolutely neceſſary to mans ſalvation; it being very improper, to pen the publike
form of Faith in the Negative, becauſe my believing Chriſtian truths makes me
a Chriſtian, and not my disbelieving the errors that oppoſe it, elſe he that believes
nothing at all would be the beſt Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>In order to which collection, the moſt religious way is, that every one that will
modeſtly, may ſafely propoſe and diſcuſſe thoſe difficulties he meets with in Gods
Word, and if after all poſſible diligences of ſtudy, meditation and prayer, no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
or union follow in any point, it is an evident ſign the queſtion is either
obſcure or unneceſſary, and then provide for the peace of the Common-wealth,
and ſubmit the reſt to the pleaſure of God.</p>
               <p>When we have agreed upon a ſummary of belief, according to theſe three con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
<hi>poſitive, evident,</hi> and <hi>fundamental,</hi> (with which the <hi>Creed,</hi> commonly call'd
the Apoſtles, ſuits beſt of any I ever ſaw) then ought the Magiſtrates hold forth
in the ſpirit of love and meekneſſe, thoſe ſo clear and important verities, and
if any ſhall be found diſſenting (which I am confident will be very few) let us
follow the Apoſtles rule in puniſhing, a gentle one it is indeed, but powerfull,
2 Theſ. 3. 6. <hi>Withdraw from ſuch a one, that he may be aſhamed,</hi> and verſe 15.
<hi>eſteem him not an enemy, but correct him as a brother,</hi> at worſt, <hi>rebuke him
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118025:13"/>
ſharply,</hi> Tit. 1. 13. <hi>and after the first and ſecond admonition reject him,</hi> Tit. 3. 10.
that is, leave him to the hardneſſe of his heart: if his conſcience grow tender, it
will check; if obdutate, he will ſoon break out into lewdneſſe; and then be juſtly
puniſhable by the Law, as other criminall Malefactors; only we muſt be carefull
not to anticipate his condemnation before he be legally convinced of ſome actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
offence againſt the publique repoſe.</p>
               <p>If we ſuſpect the diſaffection of any Party, as the Papiſts, let us firſt make it
their intereſt to love their Countrey by treating them at leaſt mercifully in it, and
then we ſhall have a fair tryall of their fidelity; I do not know one example, where,
to a Prince or State that uſed them well, they have ſhown themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull.</p>
               <p>And though it be the duty of every Chriſtian to love his enemy, and do good to
thoſe that perſecute him, yet ſurely it is a <hi>hard ſaying,</hi> and the moſt ſincere profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors
of any Religion whatſoever find difficulty enough to obſerve it, even <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi>
as well as <hi>Papiſts</hi> know how to fall out with thoſe Magiſtrates that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
them, elſe how ſhall we excuſe the civill wars of <hi>France, Germany, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
&amp;c. if we have not recourſe to the harſh uſage of their Superiours; nor
need we ſeek the reaſon of theſe diſorders amongſt the Articles of any Parties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
when by the inſtinct of nature, not only man, but even the moſt triviall
creature that ſeems to have no intereſt in the world, attends with diligence to the
preſervation of it ſelf: who can blame the humble worm, that whil<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt we walk
fairly by, it proſtrates it ſelfe before us, and lowly creeps upon the ground,
if when we tread upon it, it lift its head, and ſtrive to wring it ſelf from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
our cruell feet? Notable to this purpoſe is the old example of the <hi>Privernates,</hi>
an ancient people of Italy, who having rebell'd againſt the Common-wealth of
<hi>Rome,</hi> and being almoſt quite reduced by force of Armes, they diſpatch their
Embaſſadors for terms of peace; the Senat ſternly ask them, <hi>What new peace
they could expect, who had ſo inſolently infringed the old?</hi> to which they ſtoutly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered,
<hi>We muſt now take ſuch conditions as you pleaſe to give; if they be mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,
you ſhall find us faithfull, if too heavy, we ſhall obſerve them only till we
may ſafely break them;</hi> which free and generous expreſſion induced that wiſe
Senate to aſſign them their own demands. This ſo full and pregnant inſtance I
humbly offer, as moſt worthy the imitation of our Engliſh Senate, that even to
<hi>Recuſants,</hi> who ingage to live innocently and quietly amongſt us, ſuch reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
conditions of ſubſiſtence may be allowed (ſince they are equally with our
ſelves born to the freedome of this Nation) as their conſciences be not vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated,
their ſpirits embittered, nor humane infirmity tempted to deſpair; let us
rather incourage them to come to our meetings, and freely propoſe their difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
which now they dare not, for fear of diſcovering their judgements, to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine
of their eſtates; let us uſe the ſame gentleneſſe here in <hi>England,</hi> that his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency
the <hi>Lord Generall</hi> practiſes in <hi>Scotland,</hi> towards thoſe that are not only
otherwiſe minded in Religion, but <hi>contrary minded</hi> in civill concernments, and
actually in arms to maintain their oppoſition: he invites them to conferences, and
himſelf with admirable temper and moderation manages the diſcourſe, allowing
free liberty of reply to the adverſe party, without paſſion, bitterneſſe or threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
and though he find not the event anſwerable to his endeavours, remaines at
leaſt ſatisfied in his conſcience, by having given a reaſon of his actions; and
whom can we better imitate, then ſo great an inſtrument of the liberty we all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118025:14"/>
or wherein can we follow him with ſo much praiſe both of God and man,
as in the mildneſſe of his ſpirit, by which he conquers more powerfully, then by
the ſharpneſſe of his Sword? have not the <hi>Papiſts</hi> underſtandings as well as we,
which our Arguments may rectifie? have they not ſouls to ſave, which our chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
may gain to heaven? why do we not erect a Committee to purchaſe ſouls, as
we have Contracters to ſell Lands? why is there not eſtabliſht a Committee of
<hi>Salvation,</hi> as wel as of <hi>Indempnity,</hi> where the Queſtions of Religion may be freely
diſcuſt, and the diſtreſſes of tender and innocent conſciences impartially relieved?
if men dealt mildly, and only by the Goſpell way of perſwaſion, ſurely there
would in time grow Society, Commerce, and mutuall confidence, and ſo frequent
oportunities of clearer information: when once all jealouſies and miſunderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
of one another ſhall be laid aſide, the differences amongſt Chriſtians will
ſoon be reconciled, if not to an abſolute and preciſe unity of Faith and Doctrine,
yet at leaſt to a bleſſed union of peace and love.</p>
               <p>Oh how much better and more admirably divine is the gentle method of the
Chriſtian, how to propagate it ſelf <hi>in plain evidence of the ſpirit,</hi> then the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall
Turkiſh cruelty, of taking children from their parents! or the unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<hi>Machiavillian</hi> policy of taking the inheritance from the children! or laſtly,
which is, worſe then either, the barbarous Heatheniſh tyranny of ſhedding bloud,
and tearing limb from limb meerly upon the account of Religion.</p>
               <p>Nor can I find any ſatisfaction in that ſhuffling and hypocriticall diſtinction,
invented by the Lawyers to deceive the common people, whoſe ſimplicity and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency
they eaſily beguile, by pretending that none are executed for Religion,
but for offending againſt the Laws? what can be more palpably falſe, or divel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly
malicious then this? who does not ſee but by this rule thoſe bloudy tyrants,
<hi>Nero, Diocleſian,</hi> and the reſt of the ten infamous perſecuters, muſt be canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed
for good and conſcientious Juſticers, becauſe they judged according to Law?
who does not ſee that by this rule thoſe glorious Martyrs, who watered the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
Faith with their precious bloud, muſt be accounted Traytors, becauſe they
ſuffered according to Law? nay even the curſed Jews, who crucified our bleſſed
Saviour, impiouſly alledged the ſelf ſame reaſon for themſelves, <hi>We have a Law,
and by our Law he ought to die,</hi> John 19. 7.</p>
               <p>Nor can I forbear to profeſſe how extremely unwelcome that ſcurvy news was
to me, of one <hi>Wright</hi> a Jeſuite, being drawn to Tiburn as a Traytor upon a
hurdle for his Religion, on the 19. of <hi>May</hi> 1651. becauſe I had ſo often commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
the moderation of the preſent Authority, as having never ſpilt one drop of
Bloud for Religion: and though the <hi>Sequeſtrations</hi> of all peaceable <hi>Recuſants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
were flatly againſt our Maximes, yet the preſſing neceſſities of the State, and
their purpoſe (which I alwaies believed) of taking away all penalties upon the
conſcience, after a ſhort time, when the Government ſhould be a little better ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led)
exceedingly qualified the harſhneſſe of thoſe pecuniary ſeverities; but now
with grief I muſt lay down my arms, and with ſhame revoke all my arguments
which I have hitherto uſed, to leſſen the injuſtice of our ſequeſtring for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
and pacifie the ruines of many well-affected and religious perſons, who
highly diſliked even that <hi>ſoul-money,</hi> as King <hi>James</hi> uſed to call it, wherein as I
have had no ſmall ſucceſſe: ſo now I cannot with a ſafe conſcience endeavour
any more, leaſt I ſhould cooperate to deceive the people; <hi>Sequeſtrations</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
did ſhrewdly crack, but this killing has broken quite in pieces all our Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118025:14"/>
Againſt what have we principally fought all this while, but coercency in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?
for what have we made ſo many tedious marches and Declarations, but
<hi>liberty of tender Conſciences?</hi> is this <hi>to hold forth the truth in love?</hi> is this <hi>to
inſtruct in meekneſſe,</hi> as becomes the ſervants of the Lord? let us take heed how
we fall into the hands of the living God, let us alwaies remember that voice
ſpeaking within us, <hi>They ſhall be judged without mercy, that have ſhewed no
mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides the ſharpneſſe of the ſentence, the very tryall (as I am informed) had
many ſingular and unuſuall paſſages, as that nothing was proved againſt the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner,
but that a great many years ago he had ſaid <hi>Maſſe</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and this
only by one witneſſe, and one who in open <hi>Seſſions</hi> profeſt a particular <hi>pique</hi> and
quarrell towards him, alledging an old grudge as one of the reaſons why he came
up out of the Countrey to ſwear againſt him, no diſturbance of the publique re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
nor ſo much as the leaſt breach of peace laid to his charge, but only his being
a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and in England: And that this was his only crime, is unqueſtionably clear
by the <hi>Miniſters</hi> charitable offer at the <hi>Gallows,</hi> that <hi>there was yet time enough
for him to ſave his life, if he would renounce his Religion, and become a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant;</hi>
which he reſolutely denying, as againſt his conſcience, was firſt hanged
amongſt the thieves and murderers, and then quartered as a <hi>Traytor;</hi> and yet both
Sheriff, Jury, Judge, and every one that cooperated to the execution; all ſeriouſly
profeſſe, that nothing is ſo dear to them, nothing ſo reaſonable in it ſelf, as inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercency
in matters concerning the ſalvation of our Souls. I pray God we be not
too guilty <hi>of having a form of godlineſſe, but denying the power thereof.</hi> I pray
God theſe ſevere and ungoſpellary proceedings (eſpecially this laſt of bloud, ſo
diſpleaſing to the Spectators, and unprofitable to the Authors) become not in
time a prejudice to our Brethren beyond the Seas, a diſcontenting of our friends
at home, and a ſcandall to all the world; for that very day of the Prieſts executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
I o'reheard a nimble witted man ſay theſe very words, <hi>Since we are come to this
paſſe that we can fight againſt the Covenant for Reformation of the Kirk, ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
men for Recuſants, and continue their Sequestrations, whether they continue
their Recuſancy or no, make a cloſe peace with Spain, and openly hang up Jeſuits,</hi>
SIT ANIMA MEA CUM PHILOSOPHIS.</p>
               <p>Surely it were far better to let the Papiſts for a while practiſe their kind of
Chriſtianity, then upon a ſuddain deprive them of the only Religion to which
they are accuſtomed, and ſo indanger the driving of them to <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> inſtead
of reducing them to <hi>Proteſtancy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides how eaſily may the like ſeverity be exerciſed againſt our ſelves, if any
Power diſ-affected to godlineſſe ſhould gain authority over us? it is but ſtraining the
word <hi>Recuſant</hi> a little above the common note, it is but making our holy confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences
Treaſon by Statute, and then all the precious Saints and deareſt ſervants of
the Lord, may be hang'd, drawn and quartered by Law, and yet at the ſame time
our Executioners may profeſſe (as ſeriouſly as we now ſeem to do) Liberty of
Conſcience; only they will think it reaſonable to their own interpreters, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently
intend by this charming ſound of Liberty, an abſolute and uncontroul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
freedom indeed, but to be enjoyed by none but themſelves.</p>
               <p>How do the Papiſts themſelves in <hi>France</hi> outgo us in their tender and moderate
behaviour towards the Proteſtants of their Countrey, notwithſtanding former
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118025:15"/>
provocations to jealouſie in the laſt civill warrs? nay notwithſtanding preſent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations
by our ſeverity againſt all of their profeſſion in <hi>England,</hi> they diſpute
openly and frequently together, not only the Clergy, but tradeſmen one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother:
at many of which conferences I have been preſent in <hi>Paris,</hi> where eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
one freely defended his own Opinion, ſo civilly and peaceably, that I never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned
from the place of thoſe diſcourſes, without exceeding comfort and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
thinking often with my ſelf, it were a faſhion as worthy to be tranſpoorted
into <hi>England,</hi> as any our Gallants bring from thence.</p>
               <p>At the end of the Diſpute, (which is not upon any ſolemn challenge, but caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
though very often) if either party ſeem unſatisfied, his liberty is inviolably
preſerved, without ſeizing upon a penny of his eſtate (which there is accounted
but a politique covetouſneſſe) or touching ſo much as a hair of his head, (not to
ſpeak of ſpilling his blood for a different opinion) which they deteſt as a moſt abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
cruelty, but with a courteous friendlineſſe and mutuall compaſſion, part
in as perfect charity as they met, each hoping and praying for the others converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
in the mean while the King allows a certain number of publike Churches to
<hi>Protestants,</hi> and as much liberty in private for the exerciſe of their conſciences,
as any diſagreers from the common belief of the State can reaſonably deſire.</p>
               <p>Nay, even the Spaniſh Inquiſition (ſo univerſally abhor'd) practiſes all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable
means towards the accuſed, to reduce his judgement to theirs, before they
pronounce theirs againſt him, and upon conformity immediately acquit him;
whereas our conſcience-ſequeſtrations are laid on, without any diſputing; and
hardly taken off, upon never ſo much conforming; which very thing I have
heard ſome <hi>Presbyterians</hi> object to us, though themſelves made the abjuring
Oath on purpoſe to pinch the Papiſt, yet they ſaid it was intended only for times
of war, when all other waies, either of convincing by reaſons, or convicting by
Law were obſtructed.</p>
               <p>And, proceeding upon the ſame ſubject; they alledged divers Papiſts by name,
who have not only gone to <hi>Church,</hi> but taken both the <hi>Communion,</hi> Oath of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration,</hi>
and <hi>Engagement;</hi> and all this undeniably proved by ſufficient Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
yet after ſolemn debate upon their Petitions in <hi>Haberdaſhers Hall</hi> to be no
longer puniſht, ſince they were no longer guilty, the Commiſſioners declared <hi>that
it was not expreſs'd in any Act or inſtructions from the preſent Parliament, what
ſhould amount unto, or be adjudged by them to be a Conformity;</hi> and therefore
they continue the Sequeſtrations as formerly, notwithſtanding ſuch conformity as
aforeſaid; In particular, on Wedneſday the ſecond of <hi>July</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. It was the caſe
(ſaies my Presbyterian friend) of one <hi>Smith,</hi> a ſuſpected Papiſt; who had Lands
in the <hi>Soke</hi> of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> ſequeſtred; upon his appeal at <hi>Haberdaſhers</hi> Hall,
he produced ſufficient proof that he had been ſeverall Lords daies at Church, and
had twice taken the Oath of <hi>Abjuration,</hi> but one of the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
that this was not enough, he muſt alſo take the <hi>Communion,</hi> otherwiſe muſt
continue ſequeſtred as a <hi>Papiſt:</hi> wherto <hi>Smiths</hi> Councell replied, <hi>That if it were
a mark of Papiſts not to have received the Communion, we are</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
in our Pariſh, for we have had no Communion in our Church theſe four years:</hi>
And 'tis very probable that that very <hi>Commiſſioner</hi> who made this objection, hath
not of late, and perhaps will not receive the <hi>Communion,</hi> in manner as is preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
by the Statute; and certainly it is a very ſad caſe for us to force others, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118025:15"/>
ſo great a penalty, as the ſequeſtration of their eſtates, to do that which we
will not do our ſelves: All the relief and hopes, that <hi>Smith</hi> and others in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
(who have both gone to Church, and taken the <hi>Communion</hi> and Oath of
<hi>Abjuration</hi>) have received at the ſaid Hall, is, that the ſaid Commiſſioners have
promiſed to move the Parliament, to know <hi>what ſhall amount unto a Conformity;</hi>
and it might alſo be deſired to know what Religion the Papiſts (in caſe they be
forc'd to leave their own) ſhall conform unto, ſince we have three ſeverall Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
that at preſent ſeem to have an equall power or influence: the Prelaticall or
old Proteſtant (as ſome call it) is eſtabliſht by Law; the Presbyterian carries the
vogue in the Pulpit; but the Independent has the power and countenance of the
State. Certainly the aboveſaid ſtrange proceedings muſt needs appear, both to all
the reformed Churches abroad, and to very many conſcientious people at home, as
ſavouring of a deſign to make ſure of the Papiſts eſtates, whatſoever becomes of
their ſouls.</p>
               <p>And all this while we hold forth <hi>meekneſſe,</hi> and all this while we cry up <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of Conſcience!</hi> is it poſſible we ſhould ſo far forget our principles, as to ſeize
the eſtates of our neighbours and kindred for Religion, and at the ſame time pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
to venture all our own to purchaſe freedom of Religion? is it poſſible we
ſhould expoſe our own lives in ſo long and dangerous a war, to eſtabliſh and ſecure
<hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> and at the ſame inſtant of time, hang, draw, and quarter
men for their Conſciences? how ſhall we anſwer at the day of Judgement our
ſhedding ſo much bloud to deliver our Countrey from coercency in matters of
belief, if as ſoon as the power is in our hands we emb<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e them in the bloud of
our Countreymen meerly for their Religion; have we ſo ſoon forgot thoſe ſharp
reproofs of the Apoſtle, Rom. 2. <hi>Behold you are called Jews and reſt in the Law,
and make your boaſt of God, you know his will, and approve the things that are
more excellent, you are confident that your ſelves are guides of the blind, and lights
to them which are in darkneſſe, instructers of the fooliſh, and teachers of babes,
who have the form of knowledge and of truth in the Law; you therefore, who
teach another, teach you not your ſelves? you that preach a man ſhould not ſteale,
do you ſteale? you that abhor idols do you commit ſacriledge? In the day when
God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> how can we anſwer that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
and ſelf-evident precept of nature, <hi>do as you would be done unto?</hi> God is not
mocked, he promiſes indeed, that <hi>the meek ſhall inherit the Land,</hi> but ſurely
means not ſuch as ſeem <hi>meek</hi> only to inherit the Land.</p>
               <p>Thus ſharly went on my angry <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> and I confeſſe I was extremely
aſhamed to hear him ſay ſo much reaſon, that uſed to ſpeak nothing but paſſion,
and to ſee my ſelf ſo confounded by one, that I have alwaies overcome with eaſe
upon any other ſubject, and ſhould have liked far better his obſervations (which
with grief I acknowledge to be too true and open to all the world) if they had come
from an indifferent and unfactious ſpirit, becauſe I ſuſpect they may perhaps pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
rather from envy towards the gainers, then pitty upon the loſers: for during
the violent, and therefore ſhort, Dominion of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> never were more
cruell torturers of the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> then they, never a more tyrannicall Tribunall
then their <hi>Jure divine Aſſembly,</hi> and claſſicall High Commiſſion, but the hand of
the Lord ſtopt them in their full career, and by wofull experience they now find
the truth of Gods threatnings, <hi>If you bite and devoure one another, take heed you
be not conſumed one of another,</hi> Gal. 5. 15.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:118025:16"/>
Wherefore it ſhall be my daily prayer to our great and good God, that he would
graciouſly inſpire his ſervants, who now ſit at the Helm, to prevent the like hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy
judgements upon themſelves; and ſeriouſly conſidering that both their allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
to reaſon, their duty to God, their Engagement to their own Principles, call
ſo loudly upon them, they would <hi>fulfill now our joy,</hi> and compleat the good work
ſo happily begun, by puttting the tender-conſcienced and peaceable-minded people
of this Nation into a condition of perfect ſecurity for matters of Religion,
which cannot be effected without a generall Act of Conſcience-indemnity, firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to be eſtabliſht as a fundamentall and unalterable Law of the Land, for all that
profeſſe the Goſpell of Chriſt.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>SInce there is ſcarce one whom ſomething in theſe few
ſheets will not pleaſe, nor very many whom ſomething
will not diſpleaſe, they therefore freely ſubmit themſelves,
not only to the judgement of the civill Magiſtrate, but of
every civill man; and I have (according to the Order of
Parliament) hereunto ſubſcribed my name,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Birchley.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118025:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
