<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Brief account of the behaviour, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77386</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4503A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42468</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36282018</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36282018</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150026</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A77386)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150026)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2225:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Brief account of the behaviour, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Axtel, Daniel, d. 1660.</author>
                  <author>Carew, John, d. 1660.</author>
                  <author>Cook, John, d. 1660.</author>
                  <author>Hacker, Francis, d. 1660.</author>
                  <author>Harrison, Thomas, 1609-1660.</author>
                  <author>Jones, John, d. 1660.</author>
                  <author>Peters, Hugh, 1598-1660.</author>
                  <author>Scott, Thomas, d. 1660.</author>
                  <author>Scrope, Adrian, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Title page lacking?</note>
                  <note>Alternative title information from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Contains the last speeches of those executed for being concerned in the death of Charles I.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Axtel, Daniel, d. 1660.</term>
               <term>Carew, John, d. 1660.</term>
               <term>Clement, Gregory, d. 1660.</term>
               <term>Cook, John, d. 1660.</term>
               <term>Hacker, Francis, d. 1660.</term>
               <term>Harrison, Thomas, 1609-1660.</term>
               <term>Hewlett, William, --  Captain.</term>
               <term>Jones, John, d. 1660.</term>
               <term>Peters, Hugh, 1598-1660.</term>
               <term>Scott, Thomas, d. 1660.</term>
               <term>Scrope, Adrian, d. 1660.</term>
               <term>Executions and executioners --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150026:1"/>
            <head>A
Brief Account
OF THE
BEHAVIOUR, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>BY a Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer</hi> for the
Trial of the King's Pretended Judges, began at
the <hi>Old Bailey, Octob.</hi> 10th, 1660, the aforeſaid
Perſons with many others were Sentenc'd to
Death, of which <hi>Tho. Harriſon,</hi> or Major-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<hi>Harriſon,</hi> was the Firſt that was Executed, which was
on <hi>Saturday</hi> the 13th of <hi>October</hi> following. According to
his Sentence, he was drawn on a <hi>Hurdle</hi> from <hi>Newgate</hi>
to <hi>Charing-croſs,</hi> where within certain Rales made on
Purpoſe a Gibbet was erected. When he came to the
ſight of the Gallows he was tranſported with Joy, and
his Servant asked him how he did? He anſwered, <hi>Never
better in my Life:</hi> His Servant told him, Sir, there is a
Crown of Glory ready for you; <hi>O yes!</hi> Said he, <hi>I ſee it.</hi>
When he was taken off the Sledge the Hangman deſired
him to forgive him; <hi>I do forgive thee</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>with all
my Heart, as it is a Sin againſt me;</hi> and told him, <hi>he wiſht
him all Happineſs;</hi> and further ſaid, <hi>Alas poor Man! Thou
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150026:2"/>
doſt it ignorantly; the Lord grant that this Sin may not be
laid to thy Charge;</hi> and putting his Hand into his Pocket
gave him all the Money he had; and ſo parting with his
Servant, hugging of him in his Arms, went up the
Ladder with an undaunted Countenance.</p>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>Major-Gen. Harriſon's Speech upon the Ladder.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Gentlemen!</salute>
               </opener>
               <q>
                  <p>I Did not expect to have ſpoken a Word to you at this
Time, but ſeeing there is Silence commanded I will
ſpeak ſomething of the Work God hath in Hand in our
Days.;</p>
                  <p>Many of you have been Witneſſes of the Finger of God
that hath been ſeen among us of late Years, in the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance
of his People from their Oppreſſors, and in
bringing to Judgment thoſe that were guilty of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
Blood of the Dear Servants of the Lord: And how
God did witneſs thereto by many wonderful and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
Teſtimonies, as it were immediately from Heaven;
inſomuch that many of our Enemies, who were Perſons
of no mean Quality, were forced to confeſs, <hi>That God
was with us; and if God did but ſtand Neuter they ſhould
not value us;</hi> and therefore ſeeing the Finger of God hath
been pleading this Cauſe I ſhall not need to ſpeak much
to it: In which Work I with others were engaged, for
the which I do from my Soul bleſs the Name of God,
who out of the exceeding Riches of his Grace accounted
me worthy to be inſtrumental in ſo Glorious a Work;
and though I am wrongfully charged with Murder and
Bloodſhed, yet I muſt tell you I have kept a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
both towards God, and towards Man; I never
had Malice againſt any Man, neither did I act malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
towards any Perſon, but as I judged them to be
Enemies to God and his People: And the Lord is my
Witneſs, that I have done what I did out of the Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of my Heart to the Lord. I bleſs God I have no
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150026:2"/>
Guilt upon my Conſcience, but the Spirit of God bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
Witneſs that my Actions are acceptable to the Lord
through Jeſus Chriſt; though I have been compaſſed
about with manifold Infirmities, Failings and Inperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
in my Holieſt Duties, but in this I have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
and Conſolation, that I have Peace with God, and
do ſee all my Sins waſht away in the Blood of my Dear
Saviour. And I do declare as before the Lord, that I
would not be guilty Wittingly nor Willingly of the
Blood of the meaneſt Son, no, not for Ten Thouſand
Worlds, much leſs of the Blood of ſuch as I am charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with.</p>
                  <p>I have again and again beſought the Lord with Tears
to make known his Will and Mind unto me concerning
it, and to this Day he hath rather confirmed me in the
Juſtice of it; and therefore I leave it to him, and to
him I commit my Ways; but ſome that were Eminent
in the Work did wickedly turn aſide themſelves, and
to ſet up their Neſts on high, which cauſed great Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
to the Name of God, and the Profeſſion they had
made: And the Lord knows I could have ſuffered more
than this, rather than have fallen in with them in that
Iniquity, though I was offered what I would if I
would have joined with them; my Aim in all my
Proceedings was the Glory of God, and the Good of
his People, and the Welfare of the whole Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
               </q>
               <p>The People obſerving him to tremble in his Hands and Legs,
he taking notice of it ſaid.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> By Reaſon of ſome Scoffing that I do hear,
I judge that ſome do think I am afraid to Die, by the
ſhaking I have in my Hands and Knees; I tell you no,
but it is by Reaſon of much Blood I have loſt in the
Wars, and many Wounds I have received in my Body,
which cauſed this Shaking and Weakneſs in my Nerves;
I have had it this Twelve Years; I ſpeak this to the
Praiſe and Glory of God, he hath carried me above
the Fear of Death; and I value not my Life becauſe
I go to my Father, and am aſſured I ſhall take it up
again.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150026:3"/>
                     <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> Take notice, that for being inſtrumental
in that Cauſe and Intereſt of the Son of God which hath
been pleaded amongſt us, and which God hath witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
too by Appeals and wonderful Victories, I am
brought to this Place to ſuffer Death this Day, and if I
had Ten Thouſand Lives I could freely and cheerfully
lay them down all to Witneſs to this Matter.</p>
                  <p>Oh what am I poor Worm, that I ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
Worthy to ſuffer any Thing for the Sake of my
Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt! I have gone joyfully
and willingly many a Time to lay down my Life upon
the Account of Chriſt, but never with ſo much Joy and
Freedom as at this Time: I do not lay down my Life by
conſtraint, but willingly; for if I had been minded to
have run away I might have had many Opportunities;
but being ſo clear in the Thing I durſt not turn my
Back, nor ſtep a Foot out of the Way, by Reaſon I
had been engaged in the Service of ſo Glorious and Great
a God; however Men preſume to call it by hard
Names, yet I believe e'er it be long the Lord will make
it known from Heaven that there was more of God in
it than Men are now aware of. <hi>All the Gods of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
are but Idols; they have Eyes, but ſee not; and Mouths,
but ſpeak not; and cannot ſave thoſe that truſt in them. But
my God is the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, before whom
all you here, and all Nations, are but as the Drop of a Bucket.
And he will never leave thoſe that truly truſt in him, unto
whoſe Glory I ſhall ſurely go, and ſhall ſit on the Right Hand
of Chriſt in Heaven, it may be to judge thoſe that have <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly
judged me,</hi> Matth. 25. 33, 34. 1 Cor. 6. 2.</p>
               </q>
               <p>The Sheriff minding him of the ſhortneſs of Time, if he had
any Thing to ſay to the People he might.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>He ſaid, I do deſire as from my own Soul that they
and every one may fear the Lord; that they may conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
their latter End, and ſo it may be well with them:
And even for the worſt of thoſe that have been moſt
malicious againſt me, from my Soul I would forgive
them all, ſo far as any Thing concerns me; and ſo far
as it concerns the Cauſe and Glory of God, I leave it
for him to plead; and as for the Cauſe of God, I am
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150026:3"/>
willing to juſtifie it by my Sufferings, according to the
good Pleaſure of his Will.</p>
                  <p>I have been this Morning before I came hither ſo
hurried up and down Stairs, (the meaning whereof I
knew not,) that my Spirits are almoſt ſpent, therefore
you may not expect much from me.</p>
                  <p>Oh the greatneſs of the Love of God to ſuch a Poor,
Vile, and Nothing-creature as I am! What am I that
Jeſus Chriſt ſhould ſhed his Heart's-Blood for me, that I
might be Happy to all Eternity, that I might be made
a Son of God, and an Heir of Heaven! O that Chriſt
ſhould undergo ſo great Sufferings and Reproaches for
me, and ſhould not I be willing to lay down my Life
and ſuffer Reproaches for him that hath ſo loved me!
Bleſſed be the Name of God that I have a Life to loſe
upon ſo Glorious and ſo Honourable an Account.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Then praying to himſelf with Tears, and having ended, the
Hangman pull'd down his Cap; but he thruſt it up again,
ſaying.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>I have one Word more to the Lord's People, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
to ſerve him with an upright Heart: Let them not
think hardly of any of the good Ways of God for all
this; for I have been near this Seven Years a Suffering
Perſon, and have found the Way of God to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
Way, his Word a tried Word, a Buckler to them
that truſt in him, and will make known his Glorious
Arm in the ſight of all Nations. And though we may
ſuffer hard Things, yet he hath a Gracious End, and will
make for his own Glory, and the good End of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.
Therefore be cheerful in the Lord your God, hold
faſt that which you have, and be not afraid of Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
for God will make hard and bitter Things ſweet
and eaſie to all thoſe that truſt in him: Keep cloſe to
the good Confeſſion you have made of Jeſus Chriſt, and
look to the Recompence of Reward; be not diſcouraged
by Reaſon of the Cloud that now is upon you, for the
Sun will ſhine, and God will give a Teſtimony unto
what he hath been doing in a ſhort Time.</p>
                  <p>And now I deſire to commit my Concernment into
the Hands of my Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, he that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150026:4"/>
hath delivered himſelf for the Chief of Sinners, he that
came into the World, was made Fleſh, and was Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
that hath Loved me, and Waſhed me from my Sins
in his own Blood, and is Riſen again, ſitting at the Right
Hand of God, making Interceſſion for me.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q>And as for me, Oh, who am I! Poor, Baſe, Vile
Worm, that God ſhould deal thus by me; for this will
make me come the ſooner into his Glory, and to inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
the Kingdom, and that Crown prepared for me!
Oh, I have ſerved a good Lord and Maſter, which hath
helped me from my Beginning to this Day, and hath
carried me through many Difficulties, Trials, Straits,
and Temptations, and hath always been a very preſent
Help in Time of Trouble; he hath covered my Head
many Times in the Day of Battle. By God I have leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
over a Wall, by God I have run through a Troop,
and by my God I will go through this Death, and he
will make it eaſie to me; <hi>Now into thy Hands, O Lord
Jeſus, I commit my Spirit.</hi>
                  </q> After which Sentence was
fully Executed on him, and his Head ſet on the <hi>South-Eaſt</hi>
End of <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and his Quarters upon the
City Gates.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>OBSERVATIONS.</head>
                  <p>TO commit Villany unparallell'd, and bravely to outface
Death, is the Badge of a deſperate Traytor, and an
unhappy Chriſtian. In this Man's Life I find nothing of
Repentance; as if the Murther of a King, and the Ruin
of Church and State, were of ſo ſlight a Conſequence, that
among Birds of his own Feather Treaſon becomes Merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
and his Deteſtable Death a Glorious Martyrdom.</p>
                  <p>He calls it God's Cauſe, nay, the very Intereſt of the Son
of God, his Uſurpation he terms the Fear of the Lord;
unheard-of Impudence! Can God be the Author of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?
Or can Man expect Mercy from God's Hands that
voluntarily tranſgreſſeth? <hi>Proſperum &amp; felix ſcelus virtus,
vocatur,</hi> was Heatheniſh Philoſophy, though without
Queſtion a Maxim in the Commonwealth of his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
whilſt Religion was made the Stalking-horſe to his
Rebellion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150026:4"/>
               <head>Monday following, being the 15th of October,
about the ſame Hour Mr. John Carew was
carried to the ſame Place of Execution.</head>
               <p>WHen he was brought to the Gibbet, before he went
up the Ladder, (his Hands being bound,) he exhorted
ſeveral Friends ſtanding by to be <q>faithful unto Death, and
not to be aſhamed of the Cauſe for which they ſuffered,
and they ſhould receive a Crown of Life.</q> And further
ſaid to a Friend that ſtood by, <q>that he hoped the
Truths of the Kingdom which he had Preached up and
down would not be the leſs eſteemed for that he now
came to Seal it with his Blood.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>Mr. Carew's Speech upon the Ladder.</head>
               <q>
                  <p>TRuly it is not Words, nor that which I have to
ſpeak in mine own Spirit, will Glorifie God, or
give any Advantage to your Souls, or unto me; but it
is, if I may ſpeak a few Words in the Spirit of the
Lord, and in the Power of his Might, and from an
Unfeigned Love unto Jeſus Chriſt, that would indeed
give me an open Entrance, and make my Paſſage very
Sweet, and a Bleſſing may be left behind, even upon
you. The firſt thing (indeed) that hath been very
Weighty, (and I deſire to leave it upon all, upon Saints
as well upon thoſe that are not acquainted with Jeſus
Chriſt,) that Eternity, Immortality and Eternal Life, it
is a wonderful Thing; the Thoughts and Apprehenſions
of it are able to ſwallow up a poor Soul: We little think
what it is; he that knows moſt of God, and moſt of
Chriſt, and hath the greateſt Meaſure of the Anointing,
he little, little knows what it is to Appear before the
Holy, the moſt Glorious, the moſt Righteous God of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150026:5"/>
Heaven and Earth; to ſtand before his Judgment-Seat,
before Jeſus Chriſt that is at his Right-hand; and where
all the Holy Angels are ſo aſhamed (becauſe of the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of God) that they fall down and cover their Faces,
and cry, <hi>Holy, Holy, Lord God Almighty, which art, and
waſt, and art to come.</hi> And therefore if ſuch Glorious
Creatures, if ſuch Excellent Spirits, as theſe <hi>Seraphims</hi>
and <hi>Cherubims</hi> be, if they do fall down before the Glory
and Majeſty of this moſt Excellent and Wonderful
God, how ſhould Duſt and Aſhes do? And how ſhould
they Fear and Tremble to appear before him? And
there I ſay, think of this, and of the Righteouſneſs of
God, as well as of his Glory and Majeſty, and of his
Juſtice; that when for one Sin he threw down the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
(thoſe Glorious Spirits) into Hell, and he would
take no Ranſom or Redemption for them; and though
he hath Mercy on the Sons of Men, (according to his
own Election or Purpoſe, and according to that that
he hath Purchaſed for himſelf in Chriſt Jeſus before
the Foundation of the World was laid,) yet in Time he
made his Son a Sacrifice before Men and Angels, to
bring his Choſen Ones to Glory. That he ſhould take
Pleaſure to ſend his own Son out of his Boſom, who
was the Delight of his Soul, and Bruiſe him for our
Sins; yet it pleaſed the Father to Bruiſe him. The
moſt Holy and Righteous God that had but One Son,
One only Begotten Son, (that was the Delight of his
Soul,) and ſhould take Pleaſure to Bruiſe him that we
might be Healed, and laid Stripes upon him that we
might be Healed, Oh the Heighth and Depth, Oh the
Length and Breadth of the Love of God in Chriſt Jeſus
unto poor Souls! Oh this is that the Angels do deſire
to ſtoop down and look into, and to know more of this
great Myſtery of the Love of God in Chriſt, and that God
ſhould take upon him the Nature of Man! And put him
into that Glorious Union with his own Son; and that
he ſhould leave the Angels, though Chriſt was made a
a little lower than they, for Suffering Death for us: Yet
now, becauſe the Nature of Man is united to the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head
by Vertue of that Marriage and Union, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150026:5"/>
the Sons of God, and Heirs of Glory. Thoſe
that are Adopted by Jeſus Chriſt, are brought near to
the Throne of Glory, are in a High and Glorious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
and Fellowſhip with the Father and Spirit,
owned of all the Holy Angels; and therefore they do
ſtand without the Throne, (as in ſeveral Places of the
<hi>Revelations,) and round about the Elders, and round thoſe
that were given to the Lamb,</hi> (as in the Fifth of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi>
and many other Scriptures,) they ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out;
but there is another Company within, which is
the Twenty-four Elders, and Four Living Creatures,
they fall down and worſhip God, they are nearer than
the Angels. Oh! Who hath Credited, who hath Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved,
this Report? And to whom is the Arm of the
Lord Revealed? Oh! How many Profeſſors are there in
this Day, in this Nation, that call upon the Name of
Chriſt, and that ſay they ſhall be Saved by Chriſt, and
do Live and Truſt moſt in their own Works and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,
and never come to the Knowledge and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
of this great Myſtery of the Love of God in
Chriſt? Who never received thoſe Teachings from the
Anointing, and according to the New Covenant,
where it is promiſed that they ſhall be all Taught of
God; all the Children of God ſhall be Taught of him;
and there is no one can Teach theſe but the Father;
none can draw them to the Son but the Father; and no
Man can come to the Father but through the Son:
And this great Myſtery is both by the Light and Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
of the Holy Spirit, who makes the New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
in the Soul: O that God would pour out of his
Holy Spirit, that God would pour out the Spirit of the
New Covenant, and the Spirit of the Goſpel, and the
Spirit that can declare the Myſtery of God's Word in the
Spirit; and that he hath made Manifeſt through Jeſus
Chriſt: O there is much talking and ſpeaking in the
Name of Chriſt! And how many Men ſpend little Time
in getting Evidences in the Power and Demonſtration
of the Spirit, and come to apprehend God in Chriſt,
that ſpeak of him? Oh! There are few of theſe the
Lord knows. O that the Anointing may be poured
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150026:6"/>
out more now, according to this Faith, in the Way of
this Grace, and in this Love of God, even in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting
Love of the Father, and in the Redeeming
Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, according to the purchaſed Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion
that he hath obtained through his own Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,
wherein God hath been Juſt alſo, in juſtifying
the Ungodly; and among them ſuch a poor ſimple
Piece of Duſt and Aſhes as I have been, and have to
this Day little glorified my Father; and yet I can call
him Father, through ſome Meaſure of his Spirit, and
Father, according to the Spirit of Adoption too; and can
ſay, the Lord Jeſus hath given himſelf for me; and I
take the Lord Jeſus Chriſt as the great Gift of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
deſiring to bear Witneſs of that Love, and of
that wonderful Grace and Glory, that he hath made
me Partaker of in and through him. Oh! Bleſſed be
the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who
hath called me to this Hope, and who hath made me
Partaker of this Glory, that the Saints are Enlightened
in. And now I long to ſee the Face of this Father,
and of his Son, though I have ſuch a Number of Sins
in me, and though I have an Intereſt in him, and can
call him Father at any Time without doubt, and in
full Aſſurance of Faith in the Holy Spirit; yet if Jeſus
Chriſt were not there to preſent me Faultleſs before the
Preſence of God I ſhould be afraid to appear before
him; but he is able to do it; and therefore ſaith the
Apoſtle, <hi>Now unto him that is able to Save you, and to
preſent you Faultleſs before the Preſence of his Glory with
exceeding Joy,</hi> &amp;c. I am a poor Sinful Piece, full of
Iniquity, laden with many Burdens, that have a Body
of Death that I carry about me, and I am now about
to lay it down, and my Soul ſhall enter into Eternal
Life, and be made Perfect in a Moment, through the
Mighty Power of God that hath wrought that Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Work of raiſing Chriſt from the Dead. Oh! All
my Strength, and all my Joy, and all my Life, is in
Chriſt, and in him alone: And I have a Righteouſneſs
already of his Working, according to his own Grace,
and according to his own Mighty Power, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150026:6"/>
to his own Mercy, that he hath been pleaſed to
Work in me, and ſo hath been pleaſed to keep me in
a very Wicked, and in a very Evil Day, by the Power
of his Grace. And I deſire to glorifie my Father, and
many Years have I been in that Work that hath been
of late in this Nation; few and evil hath been the
Days of my Pilgrimage, but I have deſired to ſerve the
Lord with Faithfulneſs, and in the Integrity of my
Soul, without Prejudice againſt any Creature; and it
hath been the Deſire of my Soul to approve my ſelf
Faithful towards God, and towards Man: And what
I have done I have done it in Obedience to the Lord,
that I had in my Eye, and in my Heart. There are
many Things laid upon many of thoſe that profeſs the
Kingdom and Glorious Appearance of our Lord Jeſus
Chriſt, as if they were Enemies to Magiſtracy and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry;
and as if ſo be we were for the Deſtruction of
the Laws and Properties of Mankind, therefore I ſhall
ſpeak a few Words unto that: And if indeed we were
ſuch, we were fit to be turned out of the World, as
ſome Men think they ſhould do God good Service in
ſending ſuch poor Creatures quickly from hence. There
is no ſuch thing, I deſire to bear Witneſſes to the true
MAGISTRACY, that MAGISTRACY that is
in the Word of the Lord. And that true Miniſtry,
which Miniſtry is a Miniſtry from the Anointing, that
doth bear Witneſs to the Lord Jeſus, and hath his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Spirit. That Teſtimony I deſire to bear, and that
Teſtimony I deſire to ſtand faithful in, with Integrity
to the Lord Jeſus, as King of Saints, and King of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
And therefore it is, I ſay, to have a Magiſtracy
as at the firſt, and Counſellors as at the beginning; Men
fearing God, and hating Covetouſneſs; and that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry
as doth Preach the Everlaſting Goſpel.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Here Mr. Sheriff interrupted him, ſaying, 'Tis deſired
that you ſpend the reſt of your Time in preparing your ſelf.
Another ſaid, You ſpend your ſelf, Sir, in this Diſcourſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
ſaid, It Rains. Then Mr. <hi>Carew</hi> ſaid, <hi>I will pray.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:150026:7"/>
               <head>Mr. Carew his Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Moſt Holy, and moſt Glorious and Bleſſed God, the God
and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Father of all
Glory, the God of the Spirits of all Fleſh; unto thee, unto
thee doth my Soul deſire to come through the New and
Living Way, even through Chriſt my Righteouſneſs; and in
him and through him to he offered up by the Eternal Spirit
a Living and Acceptable Sacrifice, in which thy Soul delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.
O Lord, thou knoweſt my Frame, and thou knoweſt my
Life, and what a Paſſage this is, and what a wonderful
Thing it is to enter into Glory, and what a wonderful Thing
it is to ſtand before thee, and to ſtand in thy Preſence. O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
Father, let my Soul be filled with thy Joy, and with
Peace in Believing: O let my Heart be in Heaven, while my
Body is here; and, O let me be joined unto the Lord through
thine own Spirit before this Separation be—O Lord, thou only
art able to take hold of my Heart and Spirit; poor Creatures
may ſpeak Words to thee, but Oh! It is thine own Power,
and it is thine own Spirit, that muſt take hold of the Heart;
it is thine own Spirit that muſt carry through all; and it hath
been thy Spirit (Bleſſed be thy Name) that hath carried me
through many Trials, and many Temptations, and many Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties,
that thy poor Worm hath met with in this Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
for many Years. O Bleſſed be thy Name for all the
Goodneſs, and for all thy Grace, and for all thy Preſence
that hath been with thy poor Creature far and near. Oh!
Bleſſed be thy Name that thou haſt kept me in any Meaſure
Faithful unto thee, and made me willing to lay down my
Life for thy Righteous Work and Cauſe. O Lord Bleſs, Bleſs
thy poor People; O Comfort them in this Day. Pour out Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venfold
of thy Spirit for what thou doſt take away in any of
thy Servants for thy Holy Name's ſake. O let the Cauſe and
Kingdom of Chriſt be Dear and Precious in thy Sight, and
Live always! Lord, little do theſe (poor Creatures) know,
or theſe Nations know what a Controverſie thou haſt with
them. O that thou wouldeſt be pleaſed Graciouſly to ſpare this
People; ſpare thy People however! And let them that love <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:150026:7"/>
and favour thy Righteous Cauſe, be glad for Ever and
Ever. O now Father be Dear to me; do thou receive my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits;
take me into thine own Glory; take me into thine own Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;
let me know it is my Portion, let me know there is a Crown
in the Hand of Chriſt prepared for my Soul. O Bleſſed Lord,
thou haſt honoured thy poor Creature, and brought him hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
O reward all the Labours of Love in any to him, in Bonds
or Death; and give them a double Reward into their own Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms.
Reward it ſo to them and theirs; Bleſſed be thy Name
that thou haſt brought thy poor one hither to ſuffer in thy
Cauſe. And, O Lord, let thy Spirit be poured forth upon the
Nations until the whole Earth be filled with the Knowledge of
thy Glory. And that Chriſt Jeſus may have all the Honour,
and Praiſe, and Glory, and Dominion, for Ever and Ever.
<hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am ſo exceeding Dry that my Tongue is ready to ſtick to
my Mouth; but I would fain ſpeak a little more. Oh Bleſſed
be God! Oh! How many are the Refreſhments I have had
from the Preſence of my God and Father, ſweet and ſecret
Communion betwixt him and my Soul to Day. And for that
my Soul hath ſeen of his Riches and Kindneſs; O that I
might be more like Chriſt! For I have been very unlike to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt, very unlike to my Father. But I ſhall leave all
that is unlike Chriſt behind; and all his own Workmanſhip he
will purifie and perfect through this Paſſage into Glory. O
my Dear Father, receive my Soul; O make this Paſſage ſweet,
for now I am coming to thee; Lord, help, Lord, ſpirit me; fill
me with thy Spirit; let me be ever with thee, let me know
what it is to have thee at my Right Hand, that I may not be
moved; that in my Soul going out of the Fleſh, I may be let
into the Preſence of God, and into the Arm of Jeſus Chriſt.
Oh! That my Soul may be breathed forth into the Arms of
God, into the Boſom of Jeſus Chriſt, through the Anointing of
the Spirit!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Friend that ſtood by ſaid, It is expected you ſhould
ſpeak ſomething to the Matter of your Suffering; the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Sheriff
ſaid, 'Tis not to be ſuffered. What are you,
that you put on Men to ſpeak? What are you Sir?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:150026:8"/>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Carew <hi>ſaid,</hi> Farewel my Dear Friends, Farewel; the
Lord keep you Faithful. <hi>The Friend ſaid,</hi> We part with
you with much Joy in our Souls.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Carew</hi> ſaid to the Executioner, <hi>Stay a while, I
will ſpeak one Word;</hi> and then ſaid very ſolemnly, and with
a Loud Voice,</p>
               <p>Lord Jeſus receive my Soul, Lord Jeſus, into thy Arms I
commend my Spirit; <hi>and ſo fell aſleep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Majeſty was pleas'd upon Interceſſion of his Friends
to give his Body to be Buried.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>OBSERVATIONS.</head>
                  <p>THE Scene is no ſooner prepared, and <hi>Hariſon</hi>'s Part
acted, but <hi>Carew</hi> enters, a Man that ſuck'd in Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
with his Firſt Milk, one of the Main Props on which
Fanatick Fury Built herſelf a Fantaſtick Fabrick; one
whoſe Name, like that of <hi>Felton</hi> and <hi>Ravillack,</hi> ſhall ſtand
ſtigmatiz'd to Eternity for Treaſon, Inhumane Treaſon,
againſt a Gracious Prince.</p>
                  <p>Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, the Two Eyes of this Land,
which like Two Diamonds in the Crown give a Luſtre to
Majeſty, by a pretended Zeal were almoſt dazled, and
hourly threatned to be quite put out, whilſt Gain was his
greateſt Godlineſs.</p>
                  <p>1. He impudently affirms that it was in the Fear of
the Lord he Condemned the Lord's Vicegerent; pretends
at the Firſt to be excuſed from being a Member of that
Deteſtable Synod, to palliate his Premeditated Treaſon;
but being once Seated in the Chariot of Authority, he,
<hi>Jehu</hi>-like, drove on furiouſly till he had waſh'd his
Hands in that Innocent and Sacred Blood. And ſo far was
he from repenting for his Villany, that he was ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
it was beyond his reach to ſtrike one Blow more at
Majeſty.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:150026:8"/>
               <head>The nex Day, viz. Tueſday, the 16th of October,
Mr. John Cooke, and Mr. Hugh Peters, were
carried to their Execution; but Firſt of Mr.
Cooke, the Appointed Time being at Hand.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HE asked ſeveral times if the Sheriff was not come;
ſaying,</hi> Why ſtayeth the Wheels of his Chariot? Why
do they drive ſo heavily? I am ready, Bleſſed be God; I
have nothing to do but to die.</p>
               <p>Word being brought that the Sheriff was come, he
made haſte to be gone, and his Wife ſtepping after him,
took him by the Arm, whereupon he ſaid, <hi>O do not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
me from going to Jeſus Chriſt!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then with a Cheerful Countenance taking leave
of his Friends, he went to the Sledge that carried him,
whereon alſo was carried the Head of Major-General
<hi>Thomas Harriſon,</hi> with the Face bare towards him; and
notwithſtanding that Diſmal Sight, he paſſed rejoicingly
through the Streets as one borne up by that Spirit which
Man could not caſt down. Being come to the Place of
Execution, when he was taken out of the Sledge he ſaid
<hi>This is the eaſieſt Chariot that ever I rid in in all my Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being come upon the Ladder, and the Rope put about,
his Neck, he rejoic'd, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed be the Name of God
that I am bound for the Sake of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then his Work was to addreſs himſelf to God, and to
that End ſaid, <hi>If you pleaſe I ſhall ſpeak a few Words
to God in Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>Mr. Cook's Prayer before his Speech.</head>
                  <p>MOST Glorious Majeſty, this Day is a Repreſentation
of that Great Day when all thy Poor People ſhall meet
together, Multitudes, Multitudes in the Valley of Deriſion.
Thy Poor, Poor Servant is now come to pay the Debt which
he oweth to Nature; Bleſſed be thy Name that thou haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
him for it; Bleſſed be thy name, Sweet Jeſus, Bleſſed
be thy Name. O that all thy Poor People that are here, if
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150026:9"/>
poſſible, may feel ſomething of that Divine Power and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance
of God that thy Poor Servant now feels at this Time;
Bleſſed be thy Name. I am a Poor Creature, a Poor Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
and the Lord might juſtly withdraw from me, and
leave me to Horror and Searedneſs if he ſhould deal with me
in Juſtice; but this hath not been his Method (Bleſſed be his
Name) to leave and forſake his Poor Servant. Lord, let
thy Bleſſing be upon us at this Time, and let thy Bleſſing be
upon <hi>England,</hi> and let thy Bleſſing be upon all theſe Nations,
and let thy Bleſſing be upon all that are here. Aſſiſt, O
Lord, by thy Divine Power; give us to ſee much of thy Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;
and let not this Meeting be in vain, but let every one here
receive Benefit thereby, to the Praiſe and Glory of thy Great
Name, and the Everlaſting Salvation of all our Souls, (if it
be thy Bleſſed Will,) through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Having ended his Firſt Prayer, he applies himſelf to
the Sheriff and Spectators in this following Speech.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. Sheriff and Gentlemen,</p>
                  <p>THE moſt Glorious Sight that ever was ſeen in the
World was our Lord Jeſus Chriſt upon the Croſs; and
the moſt Glorious Sight next to that is to ſee any poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
for him in his Cauſe.</p>
                  <p>I deſire to ſpeak a few Words, briefly to let you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
what a Glorious Work the Lord hath been pleaſed to
accompliſh upon my Spirit. I bleſs the Lord I have ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacked
into every Corner of my Heart, and I have ſearched
into all my Sins, Actual and Original, Secret and Open, Known
and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown, ſo far as the Lord hath diſcovered them to me
and I have confeſſed them all with a Penitential Bleeding
Heart, and Contrite Spirit; Bleſſed be his Name, he hath
been pleaſed to come in abundant Manner, and hath
been pleaſed to ſhew me that the only Remedy is the Blood
of Chriſt; and I have, Bleſſed be the Lord, applied that
Precious Blood to my Poor Soul, and have laid hold upon a
Chriſt by a True and Lively Faith; and there is a Sweet
Calm and Serenity in my Soul and Conſcience, Bleſſed, Bleſſed
be thy Name. I deſire to glorifie God, and to give him the
Glory of all, and to take Shame unto my ſelf for any Sins
that I have ever committed, that I know to be Sin, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150026:9"/>
therefore I deſire to rejoice in the God of my Salvation, <hi>as</hi>
Iſa. 61. 10. <hi>I will greatly rejoice in the Lord, my Soul
ſhall be joyful in my God, for he hath cloathed me with
the Garment of Salvation, he hath covered me with the
Robe of Righteouſneſs; as a Bridegroom decketh himſelf
with Ornaments, and as a Bride adorneth herſelf with
Jewels, even ſo the Lord delighteth in me. And as the
Earth bringeth forth her Buds, and as the Garden cauſeth
the Things that are ſown in it to ſpring forth, ſo the Lord
will cauſe Righteouſneſs and Praiſe to ſpring forth before
all Nations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Iſa. 43. 9, 10. Ye are my Witneſſes, ſaith the
Lord;</hi> I do deſire to bear a Teſtimony unto God, and to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt, for Juſtice, and Truth, and Righteouſneſs, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</p>
                  <p>The Lord knows I have no Malice upon my Heart againſt
any Man or Woman living upon the Face of the Earth; neither
againſt Jury that found me guilty, nor Court that paſſed Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence;
I deſire freely to forgive every one from the Bottom of
my Heart. And as concerning this great Diſpenſation you may
(it may be) deſire to hear ſomething of it; truly I ſay,
as to the King's Majeſty I have not any Hard Thoughts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
him, my Prayer ſhall be for him that his Throne may
be upheld by Truth, and by Mercy, for <hi>by Mercy, Prov.
23. the Throne is upheld;</hi> but I muſt needs ſay, that
Poor we have been Bought and Sold by our Brethren as <hi>Joſeph</hi>
was.</p>
                  <p>Brother hath betray'd Brother to Death, and that Scripture
is in a great Meaſure fulfill'd, <hi>Mat. 10. 21. The Father
againſt the Son, and the Son againſt the Father, and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſhall deliver up Brother to Death.</hi> I deſire for my own
Part to kiſs the Rod; and I do deſire (if it may pleaſe the
King's Majeſty) that no more Blood may be ſhed after mine;
it may be the Lord will put it into his own Breaſt.</p>
                  <p>Here is a Poor Brother coming, I am afraid that he is not fit
to die at this Time; I could wiſh that his Majeſty might ſhew
ſome Mercy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sheriff interrupted in Words to this Effect, Let
that alone, for the King's Majeſty hath Clemency enough
for all but his Father's Murtherers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:150026:10"/>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Cook <hi>reply'd,</hi> Then I ſhall proceed to ſpeak ſomething
concerning my Profeſſion and Faith, which, I Bleſs the Lord,
is founded upon the Rock Chriſt Jeſus. I do not expect
Salvation for any Thing I have ever done, but only lay hold
upon Chriſt as a Naked Chriſt, and there to bottom my Soul.</p>
                  <p>I can ſay, to the Praiſe and Glory of God, that I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured
in my Place, and to my Power, to do that which
might be to God's Glory, according to the beſt of my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.
I have ſtood for a Goſpel Magiſtracy and Miniſtry,
and that many Delays in the Law might be removed, (and that
Thing I have much ſuffer'd for;) I ſay it's good for King
and People that many Delays in Matter of Juſtice ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved,
and that Publick Juſtice might be ſpeedily and cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
adminiſtred.</p>
                  <p>And as for my Profeſſion, I am of the Congregational Way,
I deſire to own it, and am for Liberty of Conſcience, and all
that walk humbly and holily before the Lord, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
to walk in the Fear of the Lord; and believe it is a Truth,
and there can be nothing ſaid againſt it. I do confeſs I am
not convinced of any Thing I have done amiſs; as to that I
have been charged with I am not indeed, neither did I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
the Plea of the Court, That if the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
had brought the King to the Bar, and ſet him over
them again, their bringing him to the Bar had been Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
                  <p>I deſire never to repent of any Thing therein I have done,
but I deſire to own the Cauſe of God, and of Chriſt, and am
here to bear witneſs to it; and ſo far as I know any Thing
of my ſelf I can freely confeſs it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here the Sheriff interrupted him again, deſiring him
to forbear any ſuch Expreſſions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Cook <hi>reply'd,</hi> It hath not been the Manner of <hi>Engliſh</hi>
Men to inſult over a Dying Man, nor in other Countries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Galliaſſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lord Bleſs every one of us, and help us that we may
look more to the Honour and Glory of God than the Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of our own Lives: For alas! What is a Poor Miſerable
Life to us, but that therein we might give Honour and Glory
to the God of all our Mercies?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:150026:10"/>
                     <hi>And if there be any here of that Congregation to which I was
related in the time that I lived here, I would commend to them
that Scripture,</hi> Phil. 2. 7, 18. Yea, and if I be offered up
upon the Sacrifice and Service of the Faith, I Joy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice
with them all, for the ſame Cauſe alſo do ye Joy
and Rejoice with me. And, <hi>Deut. 18. Verſe</hi> 11. The
Lord God of your Fathers make you a Thouſand Times
more than you are, and Bleſs as he hath Promiſed. <hi>The
Lord be pleaſed to ſpeak Comfort to them, and to all them that
Fear the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lord keep <hi>England</hi> from Popery, and from Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and keep it from Prophaneneſs, and that there may not
be an Inundation of Antichriſt in the Land. And that is all
the Harm I wiſh unto it.</p>
                  <p>The Lord hath Forgiven me many Thouſand Talents, and
therefore I may well Forgive thoſe few Pence that are owing
unto me. I Bleſs the Lord I have nothing lying upon my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
but I can unboſom my ſelf to every one, and to the
Throne of Free Grace, in the ſimplicity of my Spirit; I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured
to do nothing but with a good Conſcience, and
through the Integrity of my Heart, though accompanied with
many Frailties.</p>
                  <p>I deſire to Bleſs the Lord; my Lot was rather in <hi>Ireland</hi>
than here; here I have been more known where I have given the
Offence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sheriff again interrupted him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Cook <hi>replies,</hi> Sir, I pray take notice of it, I think I
am the firſt Man that ever was Hanged for demanding of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
therefore I hope you will not interrupt me.</p>
                  <p>I ſuppoſe you were there, and do bear me Witneſs in your
Conſcience, that there was not any thing then that I did not
Communicate to the Court that I now ſpeak upon the Ladder.</p>
                  <p>If you will believe the Words of a dying Man, I ſay as I
muſt give an Account, I have nothing lyeth upon my Conſcience.
We muſt all meet together at the Great Day of the Lord, to give
an Account of all our Actions, (and then it will appear,) the
Lord grant we may meet with Joy and Comfort.</p>
                  <p>I have a Poor Wife and Child, and ſome Friends left, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
you that came along with me to commend to them <hi>Iſaiah
54. 4, 5, and 10, Verſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150026:11"/>
I hope the King and Parliament will conſider our Poor Friends
as to their Eſtates; you know that thoſe Lords that formerly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
under the Parliament did not loſe all their Eſtates; I
hope there will be ſome Conſideration as to Juſtice, (leſt that our
ſmall Eſtates prove a Poyſon amongſt their great deal,) and my
Poor Wife and Relations ſuffer.</p>
                  <p>The Lord grant that Mercy may be ſhewed, that Mercy and
Righteouſneſs may Magnifie and Exalt itſelf above Juſtice: I
ſhall not hold you long, I ſhall deſire in the Fear of the Lord
to give my ſelf, (as in <hi>Rom. 12. 1.) A Living Sacrifice, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and Acceptable unto God, which is but a Reaſonable
Service.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo do intreat that I may have a little time to call upon
the Lord, unleſs there be any thing more deſired, or any one that
would ask me a Queſtion.</p>
                  <p>Truly I forgive all from my Heart; I have nothing upon
my Heart to accuſe any of them withal. I Bleſs the Lord I
have a clear Conſcience; I ſay it is in the Integrity and Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity
of my Heart, (I do now appeal to the Great God, to
whom I muſt give an Account of what I have done,) knowing
that all my Guilt is waſhed away in the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt,
(and before him I hope to appear,) and have nothing elſe to
plead any thing at all for me.</p>
                  <p>And ſo I hope that I have declared my ſelf with Simplicity
and Integrity in a few Words, that you may underſtand my
Mind.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall ſpeak a few Words to the Lord in Prayer, and ſhall
not trouble you further.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When having pray'd a ſhort ſpace he was Executed,
and his Head afterwards fix'd on the North-Eaſt End of</hi>Weſtminiſter-Hall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Obſervations on Mr. Cook.</head>
                  <p>IF Treaſon ever wore a Cloak you may ſee it here now
palliated to the Life; a quaint Orator ſtruggling for
Life under the ſad Preſſures of a heavy Charge. A Man
Bred up where Law was more in force, at leaſt more
ſtudied, than the Goſpel. I am ſorry Pearls of Eloquence,
and the very Marrow of the Law, ſhould prove deſtructive
to the Owners.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150026:11"/>
Sum up all his Virtues in a Schedule, and at the End
write Traitor: Can then his Virtues make me bluſh
to write, <hi>Solus in conclavi &amp; teſte Lucerna?</hi> What he
himſelf at a Publick Meeting, <hi>&amp; Coelo ſpectante,</hi> was
not aſhamed to act, the King muſt die, and Monarchy
with him; could the dull Genius of this Nation ſuffer
it ſo tamely? <hi>Marius,</hi> that Excellent <hi>Roman,</hi> daunted
his Butcher with a Word, <hi>Et tu homo audes necare,
C. Marium.</hi> And could not Majeſty with all its Charms
daunt a Soliciting <hi>Cook?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He alledges, he was put on it, nay, fee'd to do what
he did; ſo was <hi>Judas</hi> when he Sold his Maſter: Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
is the Root of all Evil, and brought that Famous
Orator <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> a Brother of the ſame Fraternity,
to a Sore Throat, when 'twas <hi>Avaritia non excuſat
militiam.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Some Memorable Paſſages of Mr. Hugh Peters
in his Impriſonment at Newgate, and at the
Time of his Execution at Charing Croſs, <date>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
16, 1660.</date>
               </head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Peters,</hi> as is well known, was exerciſed under
great Conflict in his own Spirit during the time of
his Impriſonment, fearing (as he would often ſay) that
he ſhould not go through his Sufferings with Courage
and Comfort; and ſaid to his Friends that he was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
unprepared for D<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath, and therefore unwilling to
die; ſomething he ſaid he had committed, and other
Things omitted, which troubled him; but though it
was a Cloudy and Dark Day with him for a Seaſon, yet
the Light of God's Grace and Favour would break forth
at laſt.</p>
               <p>A Night or Two before he ſuffered Two of the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal
Clergy, who as ſome Report were the King's
Chaplains, came to give him a Viſit; they endeavoured
to make Advantage of the preſent Temptations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150026:12"/>
he was then aſſaulted, and to perſwade him to
a Repentance and Recantation of his former Activity
in the Parliament Cauſe, which they endeavoured to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force
upon him by a Promiſe of Pardon from the King
in caſe he would therein hearken to them. But told
them, <hi>He had no Cauſe in the leaſt to repent of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering
to that Intereſt; but rather that he had in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution
thereof done no more for God and his People in
theſe Nations;</hi> and with Civility diſmiſſing thoſe Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants,
he applied himſelf to ſome other Miniſters then
preſent, whom he judged more able to ſpeak a Word
in Seaſon to him under theſe great Trials, wherewith the
Lord was then pleaſed to exerciſe him.</p>
               <p>Being carried upon the Sledge to Execution, and made
to ſit therein within the Rails at <hi>Charing-Croſs,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
the Execution of Mr. <hi>Cook,</hi> one comes to him,
and upbraided him with the Death of the King, bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
him (with opprobrious Language) to repent: He
replied, <hi>Friend, you do not well to trample upon a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Man, you are greatly miſtaken, I had nothing to do in
the Death of the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When Mr. <hi>Cook</hi> was cut down, and brought to be
Quartered, one they called Colonel <hi>Turner</hi> called to the
Sheriffs Men to bring Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> near, that he might
ſee it; and by and by the Hangman came to him, all
beſmear'd in Blood, and rubbing his Bloody Hands to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
he (tauntingly) asked, Come, how do you like
this, M. <hi>Peters?</hi> How do you like this Work? To whom
he replied, <hi>I am not (I thank God) terrified at it, you may
do your worſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When he was going to his Execution he look'd about,
and eſpied a Man, to whom he gave a Piece of Gold,
(having bowed it firſt,) and deſired him to go to the
Place where his Daughter lodged, and to carry that to
her as a Token from him, and to let her know, <hi>That his
Heart was as full of Comfort as it could be, and that
before that Piece ſhould come to her Hands he ſhould be with
God in Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150026:12"/>
                  <hi>Being upon the Ladder he ſpake to the Sheriff, ſaying,</hi>
Sir, You have here ſlain one of the Servants of God before mine
Eyes, and have made me to behold it, on purpoſe to terrifie
and diſcourage me; but God made it an Ordinance to
me for my Strengthening and Encouragement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When he was going to Die he ſaid,</hi> What, Fleſh, art
thou unwilling to go to God through the Fire and Jaws of
Death? Oh! (<hi>Said he,</hi>) this is a good Day, he is come that I
long look'd for, and I ſhall be with him in Glory; <hi>and ſo
ſmil'd when he went away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> ſaid further at his Execution, either
in his Speech or Prayer, it could not be taken, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
his Voice was low at that time, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
uncivil. His Head was afterwards ſet upon <hi>London-Bridge.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Obſervations on Mr. Peters.</head>
                  <p>A State Juggler dreſt in Divinity; a meer <hi>Protous,</hi> and
yet a Regicide; a Firebrand kindled by the Devil;
by whoſe inſinuating Practices, blowing the Bellows of
Rebellion, and belching from an Impure Throat the
loathſome Vapours of Sedition, he not only poiſoned
the Kingdom, but ruined the Stately Fabrick of an
incomparable Monarchy; pretending in his Pulpit that
to be the Finger of the Lord which viſibly appears to
all Ages to be the Hand of the Devil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wedneſday, October</hi> 17th, Mr. <hi>Thomas Scot,</hi> and Mr.
<hi>Gregory Clement,</hi> were brought on ſeveral Hurdles to the
ſame Place, where being come, Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> firſt began.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150026:13"/>
               <head>Mr. Scot's Speech upon the Ladder.</head>
               <p>GEntlemen, I ſtand here a Spectacle to God, to Angels,
and Men: To God and Angels, to whom I hope I am
ſhortly a going. And now to you I owe it; to God, and the
Nation, and my ſelf, to ſay ſomething concerning each. For
my ſelf, I think it may become me to tell you how and why
I came hither; and ſomething in the general, concerning my
Capacity. In the Beginning of theſe Troubles I was (as
many others were) unſatisfied; I ſaw Liberties and Religion
in the Nation in great Danger, to my beſt Apprehenſion; I
ſaw the Approaches of Popery in great meaſure coming
in upon us: I ſaw—<hi>Upon which the Sheriff interrupted
him in theſe Words; If you will betake your ſelf to Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
you may.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Scot <hi>replied,</hi> I ſhall not ſpeak to reproach any—</p>
               <p>The Sheriff interrupted him again, ſaying, You have
but a little time, Mr. <hi>Scot,</hi> therefore betake that little
time to Prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Scot <hi>replied,</hi> 'Tis according to my Mind to ſpeak what
may be ſaid—</p>
               <p>Here the Under-Sheriff interrupted, ſaying, It hath
been denied unto your Predeceſſors, and will be denied
unto you.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Then he prayed as followeth.</head>
                  <p>HOly Lord God, the Great and Glorious God of Heaven
and Earth, King of Nations, and King of Saints; in
both which Capacities thy Poor and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy Creature
comes now to bear his Witneſs in this great Spectacle, before
Thee, Angels and Men: O Lord, were it not for Sin none
of theſe Things had befallen this Nation, nor my unworthy
ſelf; we have all tranſgreſſed, and gone aſtray from thee
by a perpetual Back-ſliding, even all of all Sorts, Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
Ranks, and Orders of Men: And among them none,
none more than thy Poor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy Creature, who acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth
the ſame here before thee, in the Face of Heaven, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150026:13"/>
in thy Preſence, to which he is very ſhortly a going; that
Glorious Grace which thou haſt been pleaſed to afford unto
his Soul in it. O Bleſſed Lord, thou haſt called him forth
as a publick Spectacle to ſome in a Condition of Shame and
Reproach, to others of Comfort, and to thy Bleſſed Self, as
one that is a Witneſs for thee, that hath ſerved thee with
all Faithfulneſs in his Truſt and Publick Capacity and
Employment. O Lord, they Diſpenſation to thy Poor Creature
hath been Wonderful, Gracious, and Merciful; and he
muſt ſay to the Praiſe of thy Free Grace—</p>
                  <p>Here the Hangman ſtooping down to take Drink,
which was reached up to him upon the Ladder, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
him; upon which Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> ſaid, <hi>Prithee let me
alone, I have not done;</hi> and then proceeded in Prayer, as
followeth.</p>
                  <p>—That this very Condition to which he is now brought
he acknowledgeth is the very Anſwer of his Prayer before
his going out of <hi>England.</hi> Thou knoweſt, Lord, he did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
times in Prayers and Tears ſeek thy Beſſed Majeſty for
Counſel, and for Advice, whether it was his Duty to ſtay
and ſuffer, or to ſhelter himſelf abroad; and if it were
thy Will to take more Honour to thy ſelf by his Suffering
than Living, thou wouldſt be pleaſed to remand him back
again, and bring him hither. And he hath obſerved thy
Providence checking of his Way, and in preſerving him all
along until he came to this. O Bleſſed Lord, thy Poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
doth acknowledge that thy Ways to his Poor Soul
have been of wonderful Grace and Mercy. But Bleſſed be
thy Glorious Name, the Great God of Heaven and Earth,
he hath been pleaſed to bear him Witneſs to himſelf, to
Angels, and to all that hear me this very Day, thy Poor
Servant that now ſtands to ſuffer had Joy and much Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation
from God, and from his Cauſe, more than ever he
had before; I ſay again, to the Praiſe of the
Free Grace of God, I Bleſs his Name he hath engaged
me in a Cauſe not to be repented of; I ſay in a Cauſe not
to be repented of—</p>
                  <p>Here the Sheriff interrupted him, ſaying, Is this your
Prayer, Mr. <hi>Scot?</hi> Deſiring him to forbear thoſe kind
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150026:14"/>
of Expreſſions. Others alſo told him that he contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted
himſelf, and ſpoke Blaſphemy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then Mr.</hi> Scot <hi>ſaid,</hi> I ſhall ſay no more but this, the
Lord I do acknowledge, that this very Morning in the Dark
Chamber I had very much of the Preſence of God, and
from thence I take Conſolation to my ſelf that his Spirit
is with me, and that he hath Sealed unto my Soul the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees
of Heaven, at leaſt perſwaded my Soul that it will be
well with me, and that I am out of all Danger, as to my
Eternal Condition; and that I ſhall Live and Reign with
him there, where all my Sin ſhall be done away, which is
the Growing Glory of my Soul; and all Tears wip'd away
alſo. O Lord, remember the Price of Blood that hath been
ſhed for the purchaſing of the Civil and Chriſtian Liberties.
And remember thy Enemies, that are not Incorrigible Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
to thy Truth and Holineſs; and give them <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to ſee their Error, and to turn to thee; a Heart Broken,
and with Humiliation, that they may ſeek God with their
whole Heart, that they may be a Holy or Immanual Nation,
a Choſen Generation, a Peculiar People, Zealous of Good
Works, Careful to ſhew forth the Virtue of him that hath
called them from Death to Life. The Lord call in all that
belong to the Election of Grace ſpeedily into that Number: Let
no Weapon formed againſt thy Church proſper; but, Lord, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<hi>Zion,</hi> if it be thy Good Pleaſure, and repair the Walls
of thy <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> O Lord, thy Cauſe lyes near the Hearts of
thy People; and I bear thee Witneſs that I have this Income
from thee as the Return of their Prayers: And that we are
ſupported to bear Witneſs for thee very Cheerfully, and with
Satisfaction. I deſire to be found of thee in Jeſus Chriſt:
I do now abhor all my Sins, and renounce my Services, and
do account them all as Dung. Lord, thou knoweſt I have
deſired to live, that I might ſerve thee better, and love thee
more: But that I may be with thy ſelf, Oh it is infinitely bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and to confirm that Teſtimony which is concerning thy
Glorious Will: And thy Will be done in Earth, as it is in
Heaven, by me and all thine, from henceforth and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.
<hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:150026:14"/>
                  <head>Obſervations on Mr. Scot.</head>
                  <q>
                     <p>MEN, whoſe Damnable Actions whilſt living, never
merited from Good Men the ſmalleſt Credit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
now to be made Sacrifices to Publick Vengeance,
ſee how Saint-like they preſent themſelves on the Stage
This Man enter'd for a Black Saint in the Calender of
Cruelty.</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Something as to Mr. Gregory Clements take as
followeth.</head>
                  <p>PErhaps ſome may think it ſtrange that there is ſo
little ſaid as to Mr. <hi>Gregory Clement,</hi> who ſuffered
with the reſt; therefore this only is to be ſaid more,
(which is known to many,) that Mr. <hi>Clement</hi> was very
ſilent both in the Time of his Impriſonment at <hi>Newgate,</hi>
and at the Time and Place of his Execution at <hi>Charing-Croſs;</hi>
only thus it is ſaid, that he expreſt his Trouble
(to ſome Friends in the Priſon) for yielding ſo far to the
Importunity of his Relations as to plead guilty to the
Indictment: And though he ſpoke little at the Place
of Execution, yet (ſo far as could be judged by ſome
diſcerning Perſons that was near him) he departed this
Life in Peace.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Day Mr. <hi>Ad. Scroop</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Jones</hi>
ſuffered together at the ſame Place.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>Collonel Scroop's Speech at Execution, <date>October
17, 1660.</date>
               </head>
               <q>
                  <p>YOU ſee an Object here that hath been in a better
Place; but howſoever the Lord Jeſus Chriſt
hath ſent me to this Place I ſhould Die, I have no
Animoſity nor Malice againſt any Man, nor ever had
I; neither have I any Evil Will to thoſe that brought
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150026:15"/>
me hither, nor to the Jury that found me Guilty, nor
Judges that paſſed Sentence, nor to him through
whoſe Means I was brought here to ſuffer. I ſay
once more the Lord forgive him; I ſhall not Name
him, for I come not hither to reflect upon any Man's
Perſon.</p>
                  <p>I will not tell you what my Breeding hath been,
becauſe it is not good for any Man (eſpecially at ſuch
a time as this) to boaſt of his Lineage or Breeding;
but this I ſhall ſay, that I was Born and Bred a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
                  <p>As for my Carriage it may be ſome that look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
me here knows what it hath been: Howſoever the
Lord knows all, and the Lord God is Judge of all, and
he will judge; I ſhall ſubmit my ſelf to his Judgment,
which is a Righteous Judgment. The Judgment of
Men may go Wrong, but God's Judgment is Right; I
ſhall ſubmit to his Way. The Lord he is the Rock of
Ages, and my Support under this great Weight that is
now upon me: I look up to him alone; the Lord Jeſus
Chriſt is my Saviour and my Redeemer; I am going
into his Arms, Bleſſed be his Name: I follow him;
he is gone before me the ſame Way; therefore it is
no Reproach or Shame to follow the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,
to Die in his Cauſe; for that is it which I judge I am
now going to do.</p>
                  <p>That which I do deſire of you (here are a great
many Spectators both on the Right Hand and on the
Left) is, that this Day may repreſent to you the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
Day of the Judgment of Chriſt, where you muſt
appear, and there every Man muſt receive according to
their Works: And at that time it will be known,
I ſay, at that time it will be known and ſeen, whoſe
Works are Righteous, and whoſe are not; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I would wiſh you, and deſire you to judge Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably
of me.</p>
               </q>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150026:15"/>
                  <head>Obſervations on Colonel Scroop.</head>
                  <p>IF Birth or Education can render a Man Accompliſht
without doubt Col. <hi>Scroop</hi> deſerves a favourable Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;
but as the ſmalleſt Spot is ſooneſt diſcerned in a
white Garment, ſo Treaſon diſhonours the higheſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction,
and leaves a Blot in the Scutcheon of Nobility.
A Candid Nature obligeth me to love the Man, yet my
own Conſcience, and that ſolemn Commandment, <hi>Fear
God and Honour the King,</hi> makes me Pity what I cannot
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtifie, and Condemn the Treaſon as a Perſon that once
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ov'd the Traitor.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>Coll. John Jones his Speech upon the Ladder,
<date>October 17, 1660.</date>
               </head>
               <p>THere is Two Things that are neceſſary now I am going
through this narrow Gate or Paſſage to the Eternal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſty;
I ſay Two Things are neceſſary as to the Occaſion of
my coming hither, to receive my Father's good Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Peace with God. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Peace with Man.</p>
               <p>I ſhall ſpeak ſomething to each of theſe; and in the firſt
Place ſpeak ſomething of the Court wherein I received the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence.
It hath been reported, as I was told, that I confeſſed
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his Fact, and confeſſed that I were guilty of Murther, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
thoſe ſeveral-Expreſſions that are in the Indictment, <hi>viz.</hi>—</p>
               <p>I deſire to clear my ſelf before the Lord, and before the
World, in that Particular; for ſhould I grant that I was guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y
in Reality and Truth of Murther and Malice, <hi>viz.</hi>— <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
ſhould belye my own Conſcience, and draw upon me a
greater Weight than I could bear; but thus far I do confeſs, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
was willing to make the Work as ſhort as I could; and be<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auſe
I would not ſtand ſo long I told them I would take the
firſt Jury that came; and when a Jury was called, then I
did Confeſs ſo much as I was convinced of as to the Matter
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Fact; I deſire you will judge charitably of this that I ſpeak
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150026:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150026:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:150026:17"/>
at this Time, as in the Preſence of the Lord, that it is not
really, (<hi>viz.</hi> that I acknowledged my ſelf guilty of Murder,
I had no ſuch Thing in my Heart.</p>
               <p>I muſt Confeſs I very freely quit his Majeſty, conſiderin<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
what he doth in this Caſe is the Part of a Loving Son to a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
eſpecially the Judges telling him that it is the Law
and I conceive that the Court did nothing but what they <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
their beſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings judged Right as to Law; therefo<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
I freely acquit the Court, though there was not enough ſaid <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
ſatisfie ſuch a Poor Creature as I am in ſo great and deep
Point as that was. As for all others, I do not know an<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
Man on the Earth to whom I do bear any Malice, but I a<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
in perfect Charity with all Men, and I hope the Lord is <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
Charity with me; and therefore as I deſire to have Forgivenes<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
my ſelf from all thoſe that I have offended, even ſo I do free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Forgive all thoſe that have in any Meaſure offended me.</p>
               <p>The next Thing is towards God, and it is that which ſhoul<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
be laſt upon my Heart: It is not expected that I ſhould give
an Account here of my State and Condition, for that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
God and my own Soul; and I do, through the Grac<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
and Goodneſs of God, firmly believe, that my Redemption i<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
wrought, and my Pardon is ſealed, and that I ſhall be imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
in my Father's Arms, and that I ſhall be tranſlated
and brought to behold the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in Glory with
Comfort, and Fulneſs of Joy.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Col. Jones his Prayer.</head>
                  <q>
                     <p>BLeſſed Lord God, thou art the great Opener, open
unto my Soul the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who will
lead me into the Ways of Truth and Life; O God Save
me, make Good all the Pledges of thy Love unto my
Soul! Oh make all the Promiſes which I have believed
all the Days of my Life, make them now Good unto
my Soul, giving me the full Enjoyment of thy ſelf: I
deſire to Bleſs and Praiſe thy Name for this Hour that
thou haſt brought me to. Oh, what am I poor Worm
that thou ſhouldſt give me this Opportunity to ſuffer
for thy Name, and to acknowledge thy Mercies before
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150026:17"/>
ſo great a Congregation at this Place. Holy Father,
Holy Father, Oh that thou wouldſt now rain down
Bleſſings from Heaven upon thy Poor Creatures that
do hear and behold this Action this Day! Oh that thou
wouldſt ſanctifie this Thing to them, and let Poor <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
be a Land of Truth and Happineſs! O Lord, let
<hi>England</hi> flouriſh! And Oh that thou wouldſt make thy
Angel of L<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ght to go before thy People: Good God, we
pray thee keep off thoſe great Judgments that hang over
the Heads of theſe Nations, becauſe they have ſinned
againſt thee: Through thy Name ſanctifie us; let not
thy Name be reproached; Dear Father, receive my
Soul, I am ready to come unto thee: Bleſſed Father,
into thy Hand I commend my Spirit, thou haſt Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
me, Bleſſed be thy Name, in that thou haſt opened
the Treaſures of thy Love unto my poor Soul. Thou
haſt given me this Hope, whereof I need not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med!
Bleſſed be thy Name my Spirit is full of Joy.
Oh Holy Father, Holy Father, I pray thee let thy Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
come down upon thy Poor People. Look upon
me, Holy Father, ſtretch out thine Arms to carry me
over this Brook; I pray thee ſtand by me, Dear Father;
I caſt my ſelf into thy Hand, I commit my Soul unto
thee.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Then ſpeaking to the Sheriff, ſaid, <q>Mr. Sheriff, I muſt
needs return you many Thanks for your Civility.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sheriff replied, I am glad to hear ſuch an Ingenious
Confeſſion, and that you make ſuch an End, and that
you have not gone into any reviling Language, as ſome
others have done before.</p>
                  <p>After this he committed his Soul to God, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Obſervations on Colonel Jones.</head>
                  <p>IF Old Age could free a Man from Puniſhment, then had
Col. <hi>Jones</hi> a good Plea in the Court of Antiquity; his
Grey Hairs pleaded much Gravity, but Reverence is not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150026:18"/>
due to Traitors; to be Zealous in a Bad Cauſe argues a
Conſcience fit for Villany.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Laſt of theſe Ten Perſons order'd for Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
were Col. Dan. Axtel, and Col. Fran. Hac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,
who on the 19th of October, Two Days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
the Death of Scroop and Jones, were drawn
upon One Sledge to Tyburn.</head>
               <p>THey were brought forth of Priſon; the Sledge being
ready for them, they took their leave of ſome Friends
that ſtood at the Door, and Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> deſired them to
be at the Place of Execution; and both entring the Sledge,
they caſt up their Eyes toward that God to whom they
were coming; then with a cheerful Countenance ſetting
themſelves down, they were drawn to <hi>Tyburn,</hi> the Place
of Execution, where a Cart was ſet ready, into which
they both aſcended, their Countenance not at all Chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
though now the King of Terror ſtared them in the
Face; the Ropes being then put about their Necks, and
a burning Fire kindled before their Faces; firſt, Col. <hi>Axtel</hi>
applies himſelf to the Sheriff in theſe following Words.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>Col. Axtel's Speech at Tyburn, <date>October 12, 1660.</date>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MR. Sheriff,</hi> I am now, as you ſee, come to the Place of
Execution, according to my Sentence: I deſire your Leave
that I may ſpeak Freely, and without Interruption, firſt to
this People, and then to God, for it is the laſt I ſhall ſpeak
in this World, and I hope it will redound to your Account.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr. Sheriff's Reply.</hi> Sir, you know what the Court pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited
you to ſpeak, and what was ſpoken at the Bar of
the Court was there deſired, therefore 'tis needleſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150026:18"/>
it here. I hope you will keep to the preſent Buſineſs
that concerns you, and not go out into Impertinencies;
and becauſe you have but a little Time, ſpend it to your
beſt Advantage, and the Good of the People, and then
you ſhall not be interrupted. Or to the ſame Effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Col.</hi> Axtel <hi>begins,</hi> I ſay the very Cauſe for which I have
engaged, is contained in this Book of God, (<hi>having the Bible
in his Hand,</hi>) both in the Civil and Religious Rights of it,
which I leave to you, <hi>giving the Book to Mr.</hi> Knowles.</p>
               <p>You ſee a Dead Man Living, and yet I hope I ſhall Live to all
Eternity, through the Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt, the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
of the Covenant of Free-Grace.</p>
               <p>I muſt truly tell you, that before theſe late Wars it pleaſed
the Lord to call me by his Grace, through the Work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry;
and afterwards keeping a Day of Humiliation in
Faſting and Prayer with Mr. <hi>Symon Aſh,</hi> Mr. <hi>Love,</hi>
Mr. <hi>Woodcock,</hi> and other Miniſters in <hi>Laurence-Lane,</hi> they
did ſo clearly State the Cauſe of the Parliament, that I was
fully convinced in my own Conſcience of the Juſtneſs of the
War, and thereupon engaged in the Parliament Service, (which
as I did and do believe) was the Cauſe of the Lord, I ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
my Life freely for it, and now Die for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then Mr. Sheriff ſaid to this Purpoſe, Sir, remember
your ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Col.</hi> Axtel <hi>proceeds;</hi> and after the Work of the Lord was
done in <hi>England,</hi> my Lot caſt me in the Service of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
and I thank the Lord I was ſerviceable to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation
in that Countrey, and have diſcharged my Duty fully accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the Truſt committed to me there.</p>
               <p>As for the Fact for which I now ſuffer, it is for Words,
only for Words, and but for Words; and the Sentence is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
reverſed in my own Conſcience, and it will be reverſed
by Jeſus Chriſt by and by. I pray God from the very Bottom
of my Soul to forgive all that have had any Hand in my Death,
both Witneſſes and Jury, and the Court that paſſed Sentence;
for conſidering the Doctrine of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,
as he hath laid it down, <hi>Matth. 5. 44. It hath been
ſaid of Old Time, Love your Neighbours and Hate your
Enemies; but I ſay unto you, Love your Enemies, and
pray for them that hate and deſpitefully uſe you, that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150026:19"/>
you may be the Children of your Father which is in
Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I deſire according to this Doctrine from the Bottom of my
Heart that God would give them true Repentance, and not lay
their Sin to their Charge, nor my Blood, which by God's Law
and Man's (I think) could not juſtly have been brought here to
ſuffer. But I bleſs God I have ſome comfortable Aſſurance
that I ſhall be imbraced in the Arms of Chriſt, and have Cauſe
to hope that his Spirit ſhall carry my Soul into the Father's
Hands.</p>
               <p>And if the Glory of this Sunſhine be ſo great, <hi>the Sun
then ſhining Bright,</hi>) how much more is the Glory of the Son
of God, who is the Sun of Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>I think it convenient to give you ſome Account of my
Faith.</p>
               <p>I believe all Things written in the Old and New Teſtament,
in the Principles and Doctrine of a Believers Faith; I believe
the Bleſſed Ordinances of Chriſt, that it is our Duty to hear
the Word preached, to ſeek unto God in Prayer, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
Family Duties, and to walk in the Communion of Saints;
and for my own Part I am a Member of a Congregation which
I judge to be the Way of Chriſt, (and were it for that only I
were to Die I could Witneſs to it,) which is a Company of
Men Born again by his Grace, that walk in the Ways of Chriſt
Blameleſs and Harmeleſs. I Believe Jeſus Chriſt died for
Poor Sinners, of whom I am Chief, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<hi>This is a faithful Saying, and worthy of all Acceptation,
that Chriſt Jeſus came into the World to ſave Sinners, of
whom I am Chief.</hi> And if the Apoſtle might ſay ſo, much
more may I.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Friends and Countreymen,</hi> I have Reaſon to bewail
my own unprofitable Life, having been very unfruitful
unto the People of the Lord; the Lord knows I have
much fault upon my Heart, were it not for the Blood
of Chriſt that cleanſeth and waſheth me, according to
his Promiſe, ſaying, <hi>I loved you, and waſhed away your
Sins in my own Blood;</hi> for there is no Remiſſion of Sins
without the Blood of Chriſt. I deſire you all to loath
and caſt off Sin; it were better to Suffer than to Sin; it is
better to Die than to Sin; nothing could grieve our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150026:19"/>
our but Sin, and therefore have a Care of that: You and
I muſt meet one Day at the Bar of Chriſt, and the Son of
God ſhall be our Judge, for God hath committed all
Judgment to the Son, <hi>That all Men ſhould Honour the Son
as they Honour the Father.</hi> This Day is a reſemblance of
that Day, therefore be ſerious: Beg as much Good to
your Immortal Souls as I expect to enjoy by and by. I
beſeech you beg of God that he would ſave your Souls,
and omit no Opportunity through the Strength of the
Lord to Believe, and put your Truſt in the Lord Jeſus
Chriſt; be ſure to Labour after Aſſurance of your Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
in him, or elſe you will be of all Men moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;
for I of Men were moſt miſerable if I had not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved,
<hi>To ſee the Goodneſs of the Lord in the Land of the
Living.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Bleſſed be the Lord that brings me into this State, let
the Way or Means be what it will; it is God's Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty
who made theſe Creatures, to diſpoſe of them
how he pleaſeth, and God hath ordained this Death for
me from all Eternity. The Lord Chriſt often prayed,
<hi>Thy Will be done;</hi> this is the Lord's Will. He hath num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
my Days, and my Times are in his Hand. Many
ſeek the Ruler's Favour, but every ones Judgment is from
the Lord. When <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaid unto Chriſt, <hi>Knoweſt thou
not that I have Power to Crucifie thee?</hi> Chriſt anſwered
him, <hi>Thou couldſt have no Power againſt me, except it were
given thee from above.</hi> Therefore I acknowedge the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
Hand of God he is Righteous, but I am Sinful,
<hi>Therefore will I bear God's Indignation; becauſe I have ſinned
againſt him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is ſaid of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>That for the Joy ſet before him,
he endured the Croſs, and deſpiſed the Shame, and is ſet
down at the Right Hand of God,</hi> where I hope to ſee him
by and by in Glory and Majeſty, and to ſee his Angels
and Believers worſhipping of him, and therefore I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe
the Shame. Our Saviour died upon the Croſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
Sin; I am a ſinful Creature, a wretched Sinner, and
ſhall I expect better than he that was my Maſter? He
who was Holy, and never had a ſinful Thought in all his
Life; and died not for himſelf, but for us, that we
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150026:20"/>
might Live through his Death; that through his Poverty
we might be made Rich. And Chriſt having done this
for his People, it ſhould not be in their Eyes thought a
deſpicable Thing that we ſhould ſuffer for him, having
been engaged in the Work of God. But Chriſt muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail
in Righteouſneſs, and he will prevail.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Now Mr. Sheriff I thank you for your Civility, and
for this leave.</p>
               <p>After this Col. <hi>Hacker</hi> ſpoke ſomething privately to
him, whereupon Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> ſaid, Mr. Sheriff, Muſt we
both Die together?</p>
               <p>Mr. Sheriff anſwered, Yes.</p>
               <p>Then Col. <hi>Hacker</hi> read a Paper which he had in his
Hand, a Copy whereof followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="unk">
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <p>FRiends and Countreymen, All that have known me in my beſt
Eſtate, have not known me to be a Man of Oratory; and
that God hath not given me the Gift of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tterance, as to others,
therefore I have only this briefly to ſay unto you that are Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators:
As the Parliament ſtated the War, I did out of
Judgment and Conſcience, join with them in the Common Cauſe,
and have through Grace have been faithful to it according to
my Meaſure. And as for that which now I am condemned for,
I do freely forgive both Judges, Jury and Witneſſes, and all
others; and I thank the Lord, to whom I am now going, at
whoſe Tribunal I muſt render an Account, I have nothing lyes
upon my Conſcience as Guilt whereof I am now Condemned,
and do not doubt but to have the Sentence reverſt. I do now
apply my ſelf unto God by Prayer, and do deſire the Hearty
Prayers of all that fear God, that I may have a ſweet Paſſage
from this Mortal Life, to that Immortal Life which God hath
prepared for all that are in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Francis Hacker.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>After the reading of this he deſired that Col. <hi>Axtel</hi>
would be both their Mouth to God in Prayer.</p>
               <p>And then Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> ſaid, <q>I deſire all that fear the
Lord to hear me with Patience, and to lift up their Hearts
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150026:20"/>
to ſeek the Lord with me, that we may have his
Strength, and the Preſence of his Spirit, from this World
to Everlaſting Life.</q>
               </p>
               <p>After he had ended his Prayer he gave the Sheriff
Thanks again for his Civility, and turning to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel
<hi>Hacker,</hi> they ſaluted and embraced each other in
their Arms, and ſaid, <hi>The Lord ſweeten our Paſſage, and
give us a happy Meeting with himſelf in Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then pulling his Cap over his Eyes, expected, as is
ſuppoſed, that the Cart ſhould be drawn away, with his
Hands lifted up he utter'd theſe Words with a Loud
and Audible Voice, <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my Spirit;</hi> but the
Cart ſtaying a little longer, he lift up his Hands the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
Time, and with the like Audible and Loud Voice
ſaid, <hi>Into thy Hands, O Father, I commend my Spirit:</hi> And
yet in regard there was no Man found to put forward
the Horſe to draw away the Cart until the Common
Hangman came down out of the Cart himſelf to do it,
the Carman, as many Witneſſes affirm, ſaying, He would
loſe his Cart and Horſe before he would have a Hand
in hanging ſuch a Man, by this he had Opportunity to
lift up his Hands, and utter the like the Third Time
alſo.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Obſervations on Mr. Axtel and Mr. Hacker.</head>
                  <p>THE laſt Actors in this Bloody Tragedy are now
entred upon the Stage, and ſeeing they were join'd
in their Lives, I thought it fit to leave them as I found
them.</p>
                  <p>Theſe were guilty of that Horrid Murther, in daring
to protect what is a Sin to think. <hi>Axtel</hi> guarded thoſe
Bloody Shambles where Virtue and Majeſty ſtood like
Lambs before the Butcher; and now having brought the
Ship of our King's Life, toſt upon the Tumultuous Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
of ſo many uncertain Fortunes, almoſt into the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
of their Malice, he bids Rebellion caſt an Anchor
on the dangerous Sands of the <hi>Good Old Cauſe.</hi> Thus
when all good Chriſtians Hearts were melted in the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150026:21"/>
of Affliction, to ſee Majeſty lye a Bleeding, and
Pleading for Life in every Honeſt Heart, before ſo ſad a
Tribunal. This Gentleman ſpent his Time in raiſing his
Soldiers Spirits to a Pitch of Mirth, laughing at their
Squibs, extreamly pleaſed that Majeſty riſe offended
with ſuch ſad Perfumes from the Seat where he ſate,
which was ſuddenly to ſtumble at a Block, and paſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regarded
to a cold Grave.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:150026:22"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
