<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A copy of the summons from Sir William Brereton, Col. Morgan, and Col. Birch, sent in for the surrender of the city of VVorcester to the Parliament: with their answer and our reply. Also the taking of High-Arkall, the Lord Newports house, by the Shropshire forces on Fryday last, and therein 250 armes, divers long gunnes, 20 halberts and other short weapons, all their horse except 40. with the garrison and forts, powder, match, and all their ammunition and provisions, and all their bag and baggage. Printed by the originall papers, and published according to order of Parliament.</title>
            <author>Brereton, William, Sir, 1604-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4367</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E330_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200715</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861383</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159624</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A77319)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159624)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 54:E330[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A copy of the summons from Sir William Brereton, Col. Morgan, and Col. Birch, sent in for the surrender of the city of VVorcester to the Parliament: with their answer and our reply. Also the taking of High-Arkall, the Lord Newports house, by the Shropshire forces on Fryday last, and therein 250 armes, divers long gunnes, 20 halberts and other short weapons, all their horse except 40. with the garrison and forts, powder, match, and all their ammunition and provisions, and all their bag and baggage. Printed by the originall papers, and published according to order of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Brereton, William, Sir, 1604-1661.</author>
                  <author>Morgan, Thomas, Sir, d. 1679?</author>
                  <author>Birch, John, 1615-1691.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Matthew Walbancke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>31 March, 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Worcester (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159624:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Copy of the
SUMMONS
FROM
Sir <hi>William Brereton,</hi> Col. <hi>Morgan,</hi>
and Col. <hi>Birch,</hi> ſent in for the ſurrender
of the City of
VVorceſter
To the Parliament: With their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
and our Reply.</p>
            <p>Alſo the taking of <hi>High-Arkall,</hi> the Lord
<hi>Newports</hi> houſe, by the Shropſhire Forces on Fryday
laſt, and therein 250 Armes, Divers long Gunnes,
20 Halberts and other ſhort Weapons, all their
horſe except 40. with the Garriſon and
Forts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Powder, Match, and all their
Ammunition and proviſions,
and all their bag and baggage.</p>
            <p>Printed by the Originall Papers, and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
according to Order of Parliament.</p>
            <p>LONDON,
Printed for <hi>Matthew Walbancke,</hi> 31 March, 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:159624:2"/>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:159624:2"/>
            <head>The Copy of a Letter of the taking of
High-Archall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat I told you in my laſt we hoped
to effect, God hath made us able
(by his bleſſing on our endeavours)
to accompliſh; we have played on
<hi>High-Arkall</hi> with our Gunnes, and
made ſome batteries, which we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
ſo cloſe that we brake one of our pieces, and
crackt two more; we ſhot in divers Granadoes, and
ſo g<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uled the enemy that they were eaſily perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
to capitulate: The Governour himſelfe, as I
forme<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly told you, was out, but the reſt of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers
and Gentlemen in the Caſtle treated with us,
and have agreed to ſurrender the Garriſon, with all
the Works, Arms, and Ammunition therein to us
for the uſe of the Parliament, onely the Gentlemen
and Officers (not exceeding the number of forty) are
to march away with horſe and armes; ſo that all
the foot Armes are to be delivered to us, and they
to have a convoy with them to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve
they were ignorant that that City is beſieged;
it will (I doubt not) further Sir <hi>William Brereton,</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell
<hi>Morgan,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Birch</hi> their deſigne
againſt that place, if they continue before it. There
were in <hi>High-Arkall</hi> above 200. all which are draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
out to march according to the Articles; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee
have deported themſelves very bravely in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159624:3"/>
this buſineſſe, and ſo have all our Officers and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,
and it is of exceeding great conſequence to
theſe long ſuffering parts of this County. There are
about 250 Armes in the Garriſon, divers long fowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
pieces that will kill a great way, which have done
them great ſervice: Some horſe they have alſo left
for us in the Garriſon, and all their Bag and Baggage;
Powder they had not much, but proviſions no lack,
onely they had no freſh meat, but powdred Beefe,
Bacon, and Corne a reaſonable quantity. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee
are now conſidering of an other Deſigne
which is of very great concernment, and I beleeve
they will goe on in it; but of that I ſhall certifie you
further hereafter.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Archall</hi> 
                  <date>27 March 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Yeſterday they agreed for the ſurrender of High-Archall,
and this day they march away to <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_confiscated_goods">
            <head>A Liſt of what was taken in High-Arkall,
the Lord Newports Houſe, in Shropſhire by the
Shropſhire Committee, and the Forces of
Shropſhire, <date>27 March 1646.</date>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>225 Armes.</item>
               <item>Divers long Gunnes.</item>
               <item>20 Halberts and other ſhort weapons.</item>
               <item>All their Horſes, except 40.</item>
               <item>Powder and Match but little.</item>
               <item>Much Bacon, powdred Beefe and Corne.</item>
               <item>All their Ammunition, Bag and Baggage.</item>
            </list>
            <p>40 Marched away with Horſe and Armes.</p>
            <p>200 Marched away without Armes.</p>
            <p>The Gariſon and Forts, and all therein was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
to the Committee, 27 March 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:159624:3"/>
            <head>The Copy of a Letter from Sir Will.
Brereton to certaine Members of the
Houſe of Commons, read before the
Committee of both Kingdomes.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVE find here every day more of Gods goodneſſe
unto us in the iſſue of the laſt Victory, which was
as compleat and cleare a Victory as was yet in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;
I doe beleeve not above 200. of their whole Army
eſcaping, and there being (as it is thought) neere 500.
Horſe taken, beſides what was ſlaine and wounded, and
many more Officers taken then are in any of your Liſts;
Sir <hi>Jacob Aſhley</hi> being taken by one of my Brigade, and Col.
<hi>Egerton,</hi> who are now both in Warwick Caſtle; ſo alſo Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<hi>Sidney,</hi> and ſeverall others taken. Upon the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
we received from the Committee at Eveſham, and
many others, it was thought fit to ſend in a friendly Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
to Worceſter, the Copy whereof is incloſed, as alſo
their Anſwer, &amp; our reply. And hereof I can aſſure you, that
if I had ſome addition to this Army, I had not doubted but
to have given a very good account of Worceſter in a ſhort
time; but we have now received Commands from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee
of both Kingdomes which we muſt obſerve. But if
theſe Forces might have continued here, and that there
might have been ſome further aſſiſtance applyed, I beleeve
very good ſervice might have been performed. The Lord
proſper and direct you in all your Counſells, and ſend an
happy and ſpeedy end of theſe unnaturall warres, which is
by no man deſired more, then by him who will alwaies
profeſſe himſelfe to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>your moſt thankfull and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
friend to ſerve you. William Brereton.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March the 27.
1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="summons">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:159624:4"/>
            <head>This Summons (following) was ſent into
Worceſter, upon the blocking up of that City by
Sir William Brereton, Colonell Morgan, and
Colonell Birch, <date>March 25. 1646.</date>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>OUr tender and neighbourly affection to your
welfare, and care to prevent that ruine which
hath fallen upon other places which have obſtinately
refuſed good Conditions, and have had farre greater
hopes of reliefe then your ſelves, there being now
not any appearance of an army in the Weſt, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where
within this Kingdom, but what have ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to the Parllament or are already their priſoners,
hath moved us to ſend you this Summons, to let you
know, that you may prevent your houſes from <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>poile
your Eſtates from ruine, your perſons from reſtraint,
and effuſion of blood, and ſuch other miſeries as will
inevitably fall upon your ſelves, your wives and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
(if the Lord have ſo great a mercy for you and
your City) by timely ſubmitting to the two Houſes of
Parliament, in whoſe name we now require this from
you, and that you deliver the City and Forts into our
hands, for the uſe of the King and Parliament, the
which if you ſhall do, we ſhall willingly ſecure unto
you any of your reaſonable deſires; but in caſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
and that miſery follow, the cauſe of it may not
be imputed unto thoſe who deſire your preſervation,
not your deſtruction, and (expecting your ſpeedy
anſwer) reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March 25. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>For the Major, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
Aldermen, and
Citizens of Worceſter
theſe
Your Servants
<list>
                     <item>Will. Brereton,</item>
                     <item>Tho. Morgan,</item>
                     <item>John Birch.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:159624:4"/>
               <p>To this Summons an Anſwer was returned from
the City (the next day) a Copy of which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth:</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF the Arguments you give for the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of this City and Forts were true, in all
likelihood we ſhould (before this time)
have received his Majeſties further plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
and untill we doe we ſhall take no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
of any Summons; but according to
our Duties, and the truſt repoſed in us, we
ſhall (God willing) keep this Town.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Worceſter <date>March
26. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
               <hi>For Sir</hi> Wil. Brereton,
Col. <hi>Morgan,</hi> and
Col <hi>Birch</hi>
               <signed>Your Servants-
<list>
                     <item>Hen. Waſhington.</item>
                     <item>Will. Gleſcet <hi>Mayor.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ma. Sandys.</item>
                     <item>Iehn Knotisford.</item>
                     <item>Thomas Hacket.</item>
                     <item>Rich. Henge.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <p>This Anſwer being received, a Reply
was returned from Sir <hi>William Brereton,</hi> Col.
<hi>Morgan,</hi> and Col. <hi>Birch,</hi> the 27. of March,
1646. a Copy of which followes.</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:159624:5"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE know no cauſe why you ſhould
queſtion the truth of our intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,
which we aſſure you is in every part
thereof moſt true, and therefore to the end
you may more fully informe your ſelves
therein, we will draw our Forces to ſuch a
convenient diſtance as that you may gaine
more certaine intelligence, and then we
cannot doubt but you will better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
your ſelves; which if it be done,
within a few daies you may expect the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
of what was tendred; if otherwiſe,
what ever miſery befall your City muſt be
imputed to your ſelves, and not to</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March 26.
1646.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Servants.
<list>
                     <item>William Brereton.</item>
                     <item>Tho. Morgan.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Birch.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
