<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King. A proclamation for the better government of His Majesties army and for the preventing the plundring, spoyling, and robbing of His Majesties subjects, under any pretense whatsoever, upon pain of the punishments herein declared.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.5[109]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R211465</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870189</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870189</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160821</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A79003)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160821)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 245:669f5[109])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King. A proclamation for the better government of His Majesties army and for the preventing the plundring, spoyling, and robbing of His Majesties subjects, under any pretense whatsoever, upon pain of the punishments herein declared.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In this edition the 7th line of text begins with: "that".</note>
                  <note>At foot of page: "Given at Our court at Reading, the 25 day of November, in the eighteenth yeer of Our raign. God save the King."</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>With engraving including royal seal at head of document.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Militia --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Confiscations and contributions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:160821:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <p>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</p>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Proclamation for the better Government of His Majeſties Army, and for the preventing the Plundring, Spoyling, and Robbing of His Majeſties ſubjects, under any Pretence whatſoever, upon pain of the Puniſhments herein declared.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E having taken into Our Princely and ſerious Conſideration the great miſery and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine falling, and likely to fall upon Our good Subjects (if not timely prevented) by the Plundring, Robbing, and Spoyling of their houſes, and taking from them their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Plate, Houſhold-ſtuff Cattle, and other goods, under pretence of their being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to Us and Our Service; And theſe unjuſt and unlawfull Actions done by divers Souldiers of Our Army, and others ſheltring themſelves in the ſame, under that Title; Have, of Our tender commiſeration of ſuch their ſufferings, as deteſting all ſuch horrid and barbarous proceedings, and for their future defence and preſervation, thought fit to publiſh and declare Our Royall Pleaſure to be; That from henceforth no Officer, Souldier, of Horſe or Foot, or Party ſent from Our Army, preſume to ſearch for, or ſeize upon any Money, Plate, Goods, or Houſhold-ſtuff belonging to any of Our Subjects, of what Condition ſoever, without Our expreſſe Warrant for the ſame, under Our Sign Manuall, declaring the cauſe of ſuch ſeizure: And if any, either Officer or Souldier of Our Army of Horſe or Foot, preſume from henceforth, to Plunder, Spoyl, or Rob any of Our People, or take from them any their Money, Plate, Houſhold-ſtuff, or any Oxen, Sheep or other Cattle, or any Victualls, Corn, Hay, or other Commodities or Proviſions going to, or from any Our Markets or otherwiſe, Being in the Grounds, Houſes, or Poſſeſſion of any Our Subjects, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving full ſatisfaction for the ſame: Upon complaint made thereof, We will and command the Officer in chief of the Quarter within which ſuch fact ſhall be committed, to proceed againſt ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor or Offendors by the Law Martiall, without Favour or Connivence, and cauſe him or them to be executed accordingly without mercy. And if any Officer in chief of ſuch Quarter, ſhall either neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or refuſe to do Juſtice upon any perſon whatſoever, offending againſt any particular herein mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Our Will is, and We do require the party grieved to repair unto Us, whereſoever We ſhall remain, and appeal to Our Juſtice, which We ſhall be ever moſt ready to afford any of Our Subjects for redreſſe of their ſuffering, in any the leaſt kinde whatſoever. Likewiſe for the better Order in Our Army and for the preſervation of the due Government thereof, We do farther ſtrictly Charge and Command all Officers and Souldiers, both of Horſe and Foot of the ſame, as alſo all Parties ſent out, That they, nor any of them, preſume to depart or be abſent from their Quarter, without a Paſſe or Licenſe under the Hand of the Officer commanding in chief in ſuch Quarter of Our Army, upon pain of death; nor that any other, but ſuch Our Officer in chief, preſume to give any Paſſe or other Licenſe to any Officer or Souldier to be abſent, upon pain of caſhiering. And that Our Pleaſure herein declared, may be fully obſerved, and produce the effects We intend, for the good and ſecuritie of Our Subjects, We do hereby further require all the Officers commanding in chief, in any the Quarters of Our Army, to cauſe this Our Proclamation to be publiſhed and made known to all the officers and ſouldiers under their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and to ſee that ſevere and due puniſhment be inflicted upon ſuch as ſhall henceforth offend againſt any the leaſt Particulars herein before mentioned, as they and every of them expect to avoid our high diſpleaſure for the neglect thereof.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at Our Court at <hi>Reading,</hi> 
                  <date>the 25 day of <hi>November,</hi> in the eighteenth Year of Our Raign.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſave the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
