<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Maiesties declaration to all his subiects of the kingdome of England.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79205</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3003A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.14[91]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R211324</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870054</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870054</idno>
            <idno type="VID">163078</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A79205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 163078)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 246:669f14[91])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Maiesties declaration to all his subiects of the kingdome of England.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With engraving of royal seal at head of document.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Given at Our Court at Castle-Elizabeth in Our Isle of Jersey the twenty third day of October, 1649. In the First Yeare of Our Reigne.</note>
                  <note>Vowing revenge for his father and asserting his right to the crown.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 26" [barely legible].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:163078:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <p>C R</p>
                  <p>DIEV ET MON DROIT</p>
                  <p>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</p>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>HIS MAIESTIES DECLARATION To all His SUBIECTS <hi>OF</hi> The KINGDOME of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>CHARLES R.</signed>
               <lb/>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES</hi> The Second of that Name, by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defendor of the Faith &amp;c. <salute>To all Perſons within Our Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> to whom theſe preſents ſhall come, Greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Wee cannot without unſpeakeable grief and ſorrow call to mind, nor without horror expreſſe, That Our deare and Royall Father King <hi>CHARLES</hi> of ever bleſſed memory, hath beene moſt barbarouſly and moſt cruelly Murthered, by the hands of bloody Traytours and Rebels within Our Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> with proceedings and circumſtances ſo prodigious, that the particulars induce rather amazement than expreſſion. And although We have hitherto ſeemed ſilent in a matter ſo highly concerning Us, as not publickly to expreſſe to the People of <hi>England</hi> Our grief of heart and high deteſtation of that heynous fact : Yet being now ſafely arrived in a ſmall part of Our owne Dominions, at the Iſland of <hi>Jerſey,</hi> We have thought fit rather from hence, where Our Kingly Authority takes place, than from any forraigne Countrey, where We have been hitherto neceſſitated to reſide, publickly to Declare, That out of a bitter ſenſe and indignation of thoſe horrid proceedings againſt Our deare Father, We are according to the Lawes of Nature and Juſtice, firmly reſolved, by the aſſiſtance of Almighty God though We periſh alone in the enterprize, to be a ſevere Avenger of His Innocent blood, which was ſo barbarouſly ſpilt, and which calls ſo lowd to Heaven for Vengeance. And We ſhall therein by all waies and meanes poſſible, endeavour to purſue and bring to their due puniſhment thoſe bloody Traytours who were either Actors or Contrivers of that unparalell'd and inhumane Murther. And ſince it hath pleaſed God ſo to diſpoſe, as by ſuch an untimely Martyrdome, to deprive Us of ſo good a Father, and <hi>England</hi> of ſo gracious a King; We doe further Declare, That by His Death the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> with all Priviledges, Rights, and Preheminences, belonging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, is by a cleare and undoubted Right of Succeſſion juſtly and lineally deſcended upon Us, as next &amp; immediate Heyre &amp; Succeſſor thereunto, without any Condition or Limitation, without any Intermiſſion or Claime, without any Ceremony or Solemnity whatſoever; And that by vertue thereof We are now in Right lawfully ſeized of the ſaid Crowne; and ought by the Lawes of God and of that Nation to enjoy a Royall power there, as well in Church as Common-wealth, to Governe the People of that Kingdome, according to the antient and knowne Lawes, to maintaine them in Peace and Juſtice, and to protect and defend them from the oppreſſion of any uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Power whatſoever. And the People of that Nation by the like Lawes owe unto Us, and ought reciprocally to pay duty and obedience unto Us, as unto their Liege Lord and Soveraigne. This Royall Right of Ours is grounded upon ſo cleare a Title, is ſetled by ſuch fundamentall Lawes, confirmed by ſo many Oathes of Allegiance in all Ages, is ſupported by ſuch a long continued Succeſſion in Our Royall Progenitours, and by ſuch a Conſtant ſubmiſſion of all the People, that the ſame can admit of no Diſpute, no act of Our Predeceſſours can debarre Us of it, no Power on Earth can juſtly take it from Us; and by the undoubted Lawes of that Nation, to oppoſe Us either in the Claim or Exerciſe thereof, is a Treaſon of the higheſt degree. And although the bloody Contrivers of our Fathers Murther (out of a pernitious hatred to all Monarchies) have by force, as much as in them lies, Diſ-inherited Us of Our Princely Right thereunto, Baniſhed and proſcribed Us, ſeized all Our Revenues, prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all entercourſe and ſupplies to be ſent to Us, and have by violence impoſed upon the People of <hi>England</hi> a new Yoake of popular Tyranny, to the utter s;ubverſion, not onely of Our Juſt Rights, but of their Lawes and Liberties. Yet We doe profeſſe that We cannot perſwade Our ſelfe, that the Body of the <hi>English</hi> Nation hath ſo farre degenerated from their antient Loyalty and Vertue, as to conſent to theſe horrid proceedings againſt Us, or to approve the caſting off that Kingly Government, under which they and their Forefathers have happily flouriſhed ſo many Ages paſt, to the envy of all their Neighbour Nations. How can that once-happy Nation of <hi>England</hi> deſpaire of bleſſed daies under a Royall Scepter, and vainly hope for them under the Iron Rod of an inſolent Multitude? No, We cannot look upon theſe ſad and diſmall Changes, as the Deſires or Intentions of the better part of Our Subjects of that Kingdome, but rather as the Deſignes and Contrivances of thoſe Wicked Murtherers of Our Father, whoſe Ambitions are endleſſe, whoſe Avarice is unſatiable, and whoſe Guilt hath made them deſperate. And therefore out of a Confidence We have of the Loyalty and good Affections of many of Our Subjects of that Nation; And as well for their encouragement who ſtill perſiſt in their Naturall Allegiance and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Us, as for the ſecurity of ſuch as ſhall yet returne to their Duties and Loyalties; We have thought fit hereby further to Declare, That We are graciouſly pleaſed to receive all Perſons of Our Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales</hi> (other then ſuch who Voted or Acted in that bloody Murther of Our deare Father) into Our Royall Grace, Mercy and Protection, owning and eſteeming them all as our good and loving Subjects, whom upon Acceſſe to Our Kingly Authority, We ſhall hold Our ſelf bound according to the Law of God, the knowne Lawes of that Nation, and the Duty of Our Kingly Office, to protect, maintaine, and preſerve in wealth, peace and happineſſe. And for a cleare evidence of Our good intentions towards them, We ſhall be contented freely to Pardon or otherwiſe by Act to Declare, or hold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnifyed, all Perſons within Our ſaid Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales</hi> (except before excepted) for any matter whatſoever relating to the late unhappy Warres and Diſtractions. And We ſhall (according to the example of Our deare Father) be ready upon the eſtabliſhment of Our Royall Throne, to make ſuch further Conceſſions, for the ſatisfaction and ſecurity of Our good Subjects in generall, and of all intereſts in particular, as ſhall be adjudged moſt to conduce to the Peace and Happineſſe of that Kingdome. And We doe further Declare, that We ſhall give Our utmoſt aſſiſtance to reſtore Parliaments to their antient Dignity and Honour, and ſhall preſerve their juſt Priviledges, and joyne to repaire all thoſe Injuries and Affronts, which have been done to the Members of that High Court. And becauſe all waies of gaining a mutuall confidence, betwixt Us and Our good Subjects, are at preſent obſtructed, by the uſurped Force and Power now prevalent in that Kingdome, We are therefore reſolved to make uſe of ſuch expedients as ſhall be neceſſary for the ſuppreſſion of that Tyrannicall and unjuſt Power now exerciſed over them; And for bringing to their due puniſhment, thoſe bloody Murtherers of Our deare Father; For shaking off the heavy Burthens and Taxes they now groane under; And for reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Our juſt Rights, and the antient Liberties and Freedome of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; Not doubting but We ſhall find all Our good Subjects ready to concurre, and to aſſiſt Us in Our juſt and pious Undertakings for thoſe ends. And in the meane time, We require and command all Our ſaid Subjects, according to their duty to God their Allegiance to Us, their ſeverall Oathes and Proteſtations, and the love and affection they bear to the Peace of their Native Country, that they doe not betray their Lawfull King, nor the glorious Liberties and Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> into a perpetuall ſlavery, by Acknowledgement or voluntary ſubmiſſion to any new formes or models of Government, under the name or mask of a <hi>Free State,</hi> nor under any other title or pretence whatſoever.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>¶ Given at Our Court at <hi> Caſtle-Elizabeth</hi> in our Iſle of <hi>Jerſey</hi> 
                  <date>the Twenty third Day of <hi>October, 1649.</hi> In the Firſt Yeare of Our Reigne.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
¶ GOD SAVE THE <hi>KING.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
