<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A collection of such of the orders heretofore used in Chauncery, with such alterations &amp; additions thereunto, as the Right Honorable the Lords Commissioners for the Great Seal of England, by and with the advice and assistance of the Honorable the Master of the Rolls, have thought fit at present (in order to a further reformation now under their Lordships consideration) to ordain and publish, for reforming of several abuses in the said court, preventing multiplicity of suits, motions, and unnecessary charge to the suitors, and for their more expeditious and certain course for relief.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Court of Chancery.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80116</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5195</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1377_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209283</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858765</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858765</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110823</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A80116)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110823)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 180:E1377[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A collection of such of the orders heretofore used in Chauncery, with such alterations &amp; additions thereunto, as the Right Honorable the Lords Commissioners for the Great Seal of England, by and with the advice and assistance of the Honorable the Master of the Rolls, have thought fit at present (in order to a further reformation now under their Lordships consideration) to ordain and publish, for reforming of several abuses in the said court, preventing multiplicity of suits, motions, and unnecessary charge to the suitors, and for their more expeditious and certain course for relief.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Court of Chancery.</author>
                  <author>Lenthall, William, 1591-1662.</author>
                  <author>Keble, Richard, fl. 1650.</author>
                  <author>Whitlocke, Bulstrode, 1605-1675 or 6.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>92, [10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Macock for Francis Tyton, and are to be sold at his shop at the three Daggers neer the Inner-Temple, Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an initial imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Signed on p. [93]: B. Whitelock C.S.[,] Rich. Keble C.S.[,] W. Lenthall Master of the Roles.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Court of Chancery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Equity pleading and procedure --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Law reform --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110823:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A COLLECTION Of ſuch of the ORDERS Heretofore uſed in <hi>CHA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCERY,</hi> With Such Alterations &amp; Additions thereunto, as the Right Honorable the Lords Commiſſioners for the <hi>GREAT SEAL</hi> of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> By and with the advice and aſſiſtance of the Honorable the Maſter of the <hi>Rolls,</hi> Have thought fit at preſent (in Order to a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reformation now under their Lordſhips Conſideration) to Ordain and Publiſh, FOR Reforming of ſeveral Abuſes in the ſaid Court, preventing Multiplicity of Suits, Motions, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary Charge to the Suitors, and for their more expeditious and certain courſe for Relief.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Macock</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the three Daggers neer the <hi>Inner-Temple, Fleet ſtreet.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:110823:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliament.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110823:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:110823:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:110823:3"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pleadings.</head>
               <p>THat no Councellor<note place="margin">1. Suecinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Bills and Pleadings</note> do put his hand to any Bill, Anſwer, or other Pleading, unleſs it be drawn, or at leaſt peruſed by himſelf in the paper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draught, before it be engroſſed, (which they ſhall do well, for their own diſcharge, to ſign al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo after peruſal.) And Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell are to take care that the ſame be not ſtuft with repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Deeds, Writings, or Records in <hi>Haec Verba;</hi> but the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110823:4"/>
effect and ſubſtance of ſo much of them only, as is pertinent and material to be ſet down, and that in brief terms, without long and needleſs traverſes of points not traverſable, tauto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies, multiplication of words, or other impertinencies, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioning needleſs prolixity, to the end the ancient brevity, and ſuccinctneſs in Bills, and other pleadings, may be reſtored and obſerved. Much leſs may Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel incert therein any matter meerly criminous or ſcandal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous under the penalty of good coſts to be laid on ſuch Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and payd to the party grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before ſuch Councel be heard in Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:110823:4"/>
               <head>Pleas &amp; Demurrers.</head>
               <p>FOraſmuch as the Defendant<note place="margin">2. What Pleas or Demurers may be put in without perſonal attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or charge of Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> being ſerved with proceſs to anſwer, may by advice of Councel, upon ſight of the Bill only, be enabled to demur there unto, if there be cauſe; or may by like advice be enabled to put in any juſt Plea, which he hath in diſability of the perſon of the Plaintiff, or to the Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Court: It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Ordered, That ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murrer, or ſuch Plea in diſabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or to the Juriſdiction of the Court under the hand of Councel learned, ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and filed, although the Defendant do not deliver the ſame in perſon, or by Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; And therefore if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110823:5"/>
ſhall pray a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thereby return a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murrer only, or only ſuch Plea which ſhall be afterwards over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled, the Defendant ſhall pay five Marks coſts; and although it be allowed, the Defendant ſhall have no coſts in reſpect of the Plaintiffs needleſs trouble, occaſioned by ſuch Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>No Demurrer ſhall be ſaid<note place="margin">3. No Plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to be of effect till filed.</note> to be received, or to be of effect in Court, until the ſame be filed to the Bill in the cuſtody of the ſix Clerk, being the Plaintiffs Attorney. No more ſhall any Bill, Anſwer, or other Pleading, be ſaid to be of record, or to be of any effect in Court, until the ſame be filed with ſuch of the ſix Clerks, with whom it ought properly to remain.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:110823:5"/>Every Demurrer ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs<note place="margin">4. Demurers and Pleas on the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Matter, or to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction.</note> the ſeveral Cauſes of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murrer, and ſhall be determined in open Court. And ſuch Pleas alſo as are grounded upon the ſubſtance and body of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or extend to the Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Court, ſhall be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in open Court: And for that purpoſe the Defendant is to enter the ſame with the Regiſter, within eight days after the filing thereof; or in default of ſuch entry made, the ſame ſhall be diſallowed of courſe, as put in for delay, &amp; the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff may then take out Proces to enforce the Defendant to make a better anſwer, and pay forty ſhillings coſts, and the ſame ſhall not afterwards be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to be ſet down or deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, unleſs (upon ſpecial reaſon ſhewed to the Court before
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110823:6"/>
ſuch Proces to make better an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer be taken out) it ſhall be otherwiſe ordered by the Court. And if any cauſe of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murrer ſhall ariſe, and be inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt on at the debate of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murrer (more then is particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly alledged) yet the Defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant ſhall pay the ordinary coſts of over ruling a Demurrer, (which is hereby ordered to be five Marks) if thoſe cauſes which are particularly alledged be diſallowed, although the Bill, in reſpect of that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, ſo newly alledged, ſhall be diſmiſſed by the Court.</p>
               <p>A Plea of Outlary, if it be in<note place="margin">5. Plea of Outlary.</note> any Suit for that duty, touching which, relief is ſought by the Bill, is inſufficient according to the Rule of Law, and ſhall be diſallowed of courſe, as put
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110823:6"/>
in for delay, and the Plaintiff may (notwithſtanding ſuch Plea) take our Proces to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the Defendant to make a better anſwer, and pay five Marks coſts; Otherwiſe a Plea of Outlary is always a good Plea, ſo long as the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary remaineth in force, and therefore the Defendant ſhall not be put to ſet it down with the Regiſter: And after the ſaid Outlary reverſed, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant upon a new Subpena ſerved on him, and payment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him of twenty ſhillings coſts, ſhall anſwer the ſame Bill, as if ſuch Outlary had not been: But if the Plaintiff conceive ſuch Plea of Outlary through miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleading, or otherwiſe, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, he may, upon notice given to the Clerk, on the other ſide ſet it down with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110823:7"/>
to be Debated with the reſt of the <hi>Pleas</hi> and <hi>Demur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers</hi> in Courſe; but if the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe ſhall not in ſuch caſe enter it with the Regiſter, within eight days after the ſame ſhall be filed, the Defendant may take out Proces againſt the Plaintiff for his Ordinary Coſts of five marks, as if the ſame had been heard.</p>
               <p>The Dependancy of a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer<note place="margin">6. Plea of a former ſuit depending</note> ſuit for the ſame matter, is alſo a good Plea, and therefore the Defendant ſhall not be put to ſet it down with the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. But if the Plaintiffe be not ſatisfied therewith, the ſame ſhall be referred to one of the Meſters of the Court to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the truth thereof: and if it ſhall be determined againſt the Plaintiff, he ſhall pay to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110823:7"/>
Defendant, five pounds Coſts. But ſuch Reference ſhall be procured by the Plaintiff, and a Report thereupon within one Moneth after the filing of ſuch Plea, otherwiſe the Bill to ſtand diſmiſſed of courſe, with the ordinary Coſts of ſeven no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</p>
               <p>If after a Suit Commenced<note place="margin">7. Plea of a Suit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending in another Court.</note> at the Common-Law, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inferiour Court, a Bill ſhall be exhibited in this Court to be relieved for the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Dependancy of the former Suit ſhall be admitted as a good Plea, and the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant not be put to motions for an Election, or Diſmiſſion: and that Plea ſhall be proceeded in, as in Caſe of a Plea of a former Suit Depending in this Court for the ſame matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:110823:8"/>If the <hi>Demurrer</hi> be grounded<note place="margin">8. Demurrer upon a flip or miſtake</note> only upon ſome Error, ſlip, or miſtake in the Bill, the Plaintiff without Motion ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of Courſe to amend the ſame, paying to the Defendant, or his Attorney to his uſe, twenty ſhillings Coſts. But if the Plaintiff ſhall not within eight days after ſuch <hi>Demurrer</hi> put in, amend, or alter it, and pay the Coſts, then the <hi>Demurrer</hi> ſhall ſtand to be determined in <hi>Court,</hi> and if the ſame be ruled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Plaintiff, he ſhall pay the Ordinary Coſts for over-ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a <hi>Demurrer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Plaintiffe or his Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney<note place="margin">9. Demurrer being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Bill to be diſmiſſed of Courſe.</note> in Court ſhall, within eight days after a <hi>Demurrer</hi> filed, give notice to the Defendant, or his Attorney in Court, under either of their hands, that the Plaintiff
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110823:8"/>
doth admit the <hi>Demurrer</hi> to be good, and ſhall pay the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants Attorney, or his Clerk in <hi>Court,</hi> fourty ſhillings Coſts; then the Defendant ſhall not need to attend his <hi>Demurrer:</hi> but the Bill ſhall ſtand diſmiſt of Courſe without Motion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Parties, or their Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys on both ſides ſhall agree to an amendment of the ſame, but ſuch diſmiſsion is to be no Bar to a new Bill to be exhibited by the Plaintiff.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwers.</head>
               <p>AN anſwer to a matter char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged<note place="margin">10. Anſwer to matter of Fact.</note> as the Defendants own fact, muſt regularly be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſaying to his <hi>Remembrance,</hi> or as he <hi>Believeth,</hi> if it be laid to be done within ſeven years
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110823:9"/>
before, unleſſe the <hi>Court</hi> upon exception taken, ſhall finde ſpecial cauſe to diſpence with ſo poſitive an Anſwer. And if the Defendant deny the Fact, he muſt traverſe or deny it (as the cauſe requires) directly, and not by way of Negative preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. As, if he be charged with the receipt of a ſumme of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; he muſt deny, or traverſe that he hath not received that ſumme, or any part thereof, or elſe ſet forth what part he hath received. And if a Fact be laid to be done with divers circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanees, the Defendant muſt not deny or traverſe it literal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as it is laid in the Bill, but muſt Anſwer the point of ſubſtance poſitively and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:110823:9"/>VVhen the Defendent hath<note place="margin">11. Hearing on Bill &amp; Anſwer with cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> anſwered, the Plaintiff is to be well adviſed upon the anſwer; and if he ſhall find that upon the anſwer alone without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proofe, there be ſufficient ground for a finall Order or Decree, the Plaintiff may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his Attorney to preſent the ſame in courſe to be ſet down, to be heard upon Bill and Anſwer, without further lengthning of the cauſe; but in caſe the Court ſhall not find grounds to make a Decree or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Order thereupon, the Bill ſhall be diſmiſſed with coſts, or the Plaintiff admitted to reply if he deſire it, firſt paying down 5. l. coſts to the Defendent or his Clark, which if he ſhall not do in foure daies after ſuch hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, then the diſmiſſion to ſtand, and the concluſion of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110823:10"/>
Order upon hearing, is to be pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Regiſter according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the ſaid Bill ſtand diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed without any further or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or direction, and then ſuch diſmiſſion ſhall be a good plea in Barre of any new Bill for the ſame matter.</p>
               <p>If a hearing be prayed upon<note place="margin">12. At hearing on Bill and Anſwer, what evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> a Bill and Anſwer, the anſwer muſt be admitted to be true in all points, and no other evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to be admitted, unleſſe it be matter of record, to which the anſwer refers and is prove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by the record. The Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff is therefore to be well advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therein, that the Court be not put to an unneceſſary trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and himſelfe to a certaine charge, in bringing his cauſe to hearing, which will not beare a Decree.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:110823:10"/>VVhereas the Defendent<note place="margin">13. Plaintiff to reply, if the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer good to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</note> hath put in an anſwer, if the Plaintiff hath proofs for the matters denied, he is not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon the inſufficiency of the anſwer, if the ſame be good to a common intent, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to replication and proofe, to avoid charge and expence of time in cavilling with anſwers.</p>
               <p>If exceptions be put in to an<note place="margin">14. Time to anſwer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions.</note> Anſwer after the Terme, the Defendent ſhall not be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ſtay in Towne, to attend the Plaintiffs exceptions, but ſhall have time to anſwer untill the fourth day of the next Terme, unleſſe the Court ſhall<note place="margin">15. Time for exceptions to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and coſts for inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers.</note> find ſpeciall cauſe to haſten it, and ſhall ſee Order in open Court.</p>
               <p>When a Plaintiff excepteth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110823:11"/>
to a Defendents Anſwer, he ſhall ſet downe his exceptions in writing, and the ſame Terme the anſwer is filed, or within eight daies after that Terme, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the ſame exceptions to the Councell, whoſe hand is to the Anſwer, or to the Defendents Attorney in Court, and if the Defendent ſhall within the times before limited reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfie the Plaintiff of the invalidity of thoſe exceptions, or put in a perfect or better Anſwer, and pay xx s. coſts, then the Plaintiff may reply thereunto. But if the Defendent ſhall faile to do the ſame, or put in a ſecond inſufficient anſwer, then the Plaintiff may get the ſaid anſwer, or anſwers refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and if the ſame ſhall be ruled inſufficient, the Defendent ſhall pay forty ſhillings coſts;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110823:11"/>
and in caſe the Plaintiff ſhall procure a reference of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and the ſame be ruled good, the Plaintiff ſhall pay the Defendent forty ſhillings coſts.</p>
               <p>If the firſt Anſwer be certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note place="margin">16. Further inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, and the coſts for them.</note> inſufficient, as aforeſaid, the Defendent ſhall pay forty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings coſts, if the Anſwer were put in perſon; but if the ſame came in by Commiſſion, the Defendent ſhall pay fifty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings coſts, and no new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſhall be awarded for taking any ſecond Anſwer, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be by Order made in Court, and <hi>Affidavit</hi> made of the parties inabilitie to travell, or other good matter to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Court touching that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, and firſt paying the coſts of ſuch inſufficient Anſwer, or by the Plaintiffs own aſſent for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110823:12"/>
the expediting of his Cauſe. If the ſecond anſwer be reported inſufficient unto any of the points formerly certified, (which are only to be inſiſted upon without any new excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) the Defendent ſhall pay three pounds coſts; and upon the third anſwer foure pounds coſts; and upon a fourth anſwer certified inſufficient, he ſhall pay five pounds coſts, and be examined upon Interrogatories to the points reported inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and ſhall be committed till he hath perfectly anſwered thoſe Interrogatories, and pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the coſts, in reſpect of the great vexation and delay which in ſuch caſe will happen to the Plaintiff.<note place="margin">17. Proofs to be only of matters neceſſary.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If upon peruſall of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, the Plaintiff ſhall find it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110823:12"/>
will be neceſſary to make proof of one, or few particulars, then the Plaintiff is to reply to thoſe particulars only, and not draw into pleadings and proofs any more, then the points neceſſary to be proved: And in caſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hearing it ſhall appeare that the Plaintiff might have had as full relief on Bill and Anſwer, the Plaintiff ſhall not only go without coſts, but ſhall pay the Defendent good coſts, to be aſſeſſed by the Court, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit he be relieved upon the merit of his cauſe, in reſpect of the Defendents needleſſe vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.<note place="margin">18. Bill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed for want of proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not to be retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed till the coſts paid.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If a Bill be regularly and juſtly diſmiſt of courſe, or by order for want of proſecution, no motion ſhall be admitted for the retainer thereof without a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110823:13"/>
Certificate from the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents Atturney in Court, that the coſts of the diſmiſſion are paid, to the end unneceſſary charge to the parties by ſeverall motions for one and the ſame matter may henceforth be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Examination of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</head>
               <p>IN caſe the parties proceed to<note place="margin">19. Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories to be perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</note> examine Witneſſes, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories are to be penned with care, that the ſame be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, and onely to the points neceſſary to be examined un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: and the Witneſſes are to be ſorted &amp; examined on thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories only that their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony doth extend unto, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the needleſſe interrogatories
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110823:13"/>
of matters unneceſſary and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>materiall, as well to avoid the charge of both parties, Plaintiff and Defendent, in ſuperfluous examinations, as that apt Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories (which are the life of the Cauſe) may be exhibited.</p>
               <p>The Examiners (in whom<note place="margin">20. Examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers duty.</note> the Court repoſeth much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence) are themſelves in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be diligent in examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Witneſſes, and not intruſt the ſame to meane and inferior Clarks; and are to take care to hold the Witneſſe to the point interrogated, and not to run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to extravagances and matters not pertinent to the queſtion,<note place="margin">21. To have care of their Clarks and be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable for them.</note> thereby waſting paper for their own profit, of which the Court will expect a ſtrict accompt.</p>
               <p>The Examiners are to take
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110823:14"/>
care that they imploy under them in their Office, none but perſons of known integrity and ability, who ſhall take an oath not to deliver or make knowne directly or indirectly to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe party, or any other ſave the Deponent, who coms to be examined, any of the Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories delivered to be examined upon, any examination by him taken or remaining in the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miners Office, or extract, copy, or breviate thereof, before pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication be thereof paſſed, and copies thereof taken. And if any ſuch Deputy, Clerk or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo imployed, ſhall be found faulty in the premiſes, he ſhall be expulſed the Office, and the Examiner who ſo imployed him, ſhall be alſo anſwerable to the Court for ſuch miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and to the party grieved
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110823:14"/>
for his coſts and damages ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained thereby: and ſuch Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citor or other perſon, who ſhall be diſcovered to have had a hand therein, ſhall be liable to ſuch cenſure for the offence, as the Court ſhall find juſt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict upon him.</p>
               <p>No Witneſſe ſhall be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined<note place="margin">22. Notice of a Witneſſe to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined.</note> in Court by the Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, without the privity of the adverſe party, or of his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney or his Attorneys Clerk, who deales for the adverſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to whom the perſon to be examined ſhall be ſhowed, and a note of his name and place of dwelling delivered in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, by ſuch as ſhall produce him, and the Examiner is to take care, and be well ſatisfied that ſuch notice be given, and then ſhall add to the title of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110823:15"/>
the Witneſſes examination, the time of ſuch notice given, and the name of the perſon to whom it is given, and by whom, that at the hearing of the cauſe, the Suitor be not delayed, upon pretence of want of notice.</p>
               <p>For prevention of perjury and<note place="margin">23. Witneſſes to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined to Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atim.</note> other miſchiefs often appearing to the Court, the Examiner is to examine the deponent to the Interrogatories directed <hi>ſeria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim,</hi> and not to permit him to read over, or heare read any other of Interrogatories, untill that in hand be fully finiſhed, much leſſe is he to ſuffer the Deponent to have the Interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatories, and pen his owne De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, or to depart after he hath heard an Interrogatory read over, untill he hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected his examination there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110823:15"/>
and if any Witneſſe ſhall refuſe ſo to conform himſelfe, the Examiner is thereof to give notice to the Attorney, or Clark of the other ſide, and to proceed no further in his exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, without the conſent of the ſaid Attorney or Clark, or Order made in Court to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant his ſo doing.</p>
               <p>In examining of Witneſſes,<note place="margin">24. Examiner to avoid imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies.</note> the Examiner ſhall not uſe any idle repetitions, or needleſſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, nor ſet downe any anſwer to the queſtions, to which the Examinant cannot depoſe other then thus, To ſuch an Interrogatory this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminant cannot depoſe. And in caſe ſuch impertinencies be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Court, the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner is to recompence the charge thereof to the party grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110823:16"/>
as the Court ſhall award.</p>
               <p>The Examiner ſhall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine<note place="margin">25. Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the credit of a Witneſſe, and how.</note> any Witneſſe, to invalid the credit of any other Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but by ſpeciall Order of the Court, which is ſparingly to be granted: and upon excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons firſt put into writing, and filed with the Examiner with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fee, and notice thereof gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the adverſe party or his Attorney, together with a true copy of the ſaid exceptions, at the charge of the party ſo exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining.</p>
               <p>From henceforth the Fee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken<note place="margin">26. Fee for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining a Witneſſe to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted.</note> by the Examiner, upon the producing of a Witneſſe to be examined by him, ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted to the party Plaintiff or Defendent, who paid the ſame, when the Copies of ſuch Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110823:16"/>
Depoſitions are taken out by him, and ſuch Exhibitions whereupon any Witneſſe is examined, ſhall be alwaies <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſed and certified by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminer, at the ſame time that the Witneſſe is thereupon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, and his examination perfected and ſubſcribed.</p>
               <p>When Witneſſes are exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note place="margin">27. No new Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories for the ſame Witneſſe, nor exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination after Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication.</note> in Court upon a Schedule of Interrogatories, there ſhall be no new Interrogatories put in to examine the ſame Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; nor ſhall any Witneſſes be examined in Court after the day of publication, though they were ſworne before; ſo as a copy of the Rule or Order whereby publication paſſed, be delivered to the Examiner, that he may take notice thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:110823:17"/>If the Defendent being ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved<note place="margin">28. Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parte</hi> when.</note> with a <hi>Subpoena</hi> to rejoyne and joyne in Commiſſion, ſhall not upon requeſt by the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffs Clark, made to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendents Clark, deliver Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners names, by the end of that terme, wherein the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poena ad rejungend.</hi> is returna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; The Plaintiff may without motion or Petition take the Commiſſion <hi>ex parte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Plaintiff ought regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly<note place="margin">29. Carriage of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</note> to have the carriage of the Commiſſion for examination of Witneſſes, as often as any is ſued forth: but if through the default of him or his Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, the ſame be not executed, he ſhall pay unto the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſuch reaſonable coſts, as the Defendent ſhall by oath make appeare, he was put unto
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110823:17"/>
by ſuch failer, and ſhall renew the Commiſſion at his owne charge, but the other ſide ſhall have the carriage of ſuch new Commiſſion. And the like ſhall be done to the Plaintiff, where the Defendent for juſt reaſon hath obtained the carriage of the Commiſſion; and if through any errour of the Clark in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out the ſaid Commiſſion, or miſnaming the Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or parties, or the like, the execution of a Commiſſion ſhall be put off, the party put to charge in attendance of ſuch Commiſſion, ſhall receive his coſts to be aſcertained by his oath as aforeſaid, from him that obtained ſuch Commiſſion, and the Clark that made out the ſame, or his Superiour the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney in Court, (who is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable for him) ſhall make
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110823:18"/>
reſtitution thereof to the Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and Suitor.</p>
               <p>If both ſides joyne in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Commiſſion, and the<note place="margin">30. New Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and how.</note> one ſide produceth and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all his Witneſſes, and the other ſide doth not, but prayeth a new Commiſſion, the ſame ſhal not be granted (unleſs it be by conſent of the parties, or their Attornies in Court,) but upon oath of good cauſe, why he could not then examine all his Witneſſes. And in caſe the ſame be granted, the party praying the ſame ſhall bear the reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able charge of the other ſide, both of renewing &amp; executing the Commiſſion, to be aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Oath, and the other ſide ſhall be at liberty, to croſſe examine the Witneſſes produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by him that reneweth the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110823:18"/>
Commiſſion. But if he ſhall not onely croſſe examine the Witneſſes of the adverſe party, but examine new Witneſſes, he ſhall beare his part of the charge.</p>
               <p>If at the inſtance of a Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,<note place="margin">31. New Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion through Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault.</note> a Commiſſion to examine Witneſſes be renewed, either for a default by him or his Commiſsioners, or becauſe he did not examine all his Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes by the firſt Commiſſion, he ſhall at his perill examine all his Witneſſes by ſuch renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Commiſſion, or in Court by the returne of ſuch Commiſſion without more or further delay, and no more Commiſſions to iſſue, except for examination beyond the ſeas, by Order in Court, or by conſent of the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:110823:19"/>Upon the returne of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,<note place="margin">32. One rule on a joynt Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion.</note> if the ſame be executed by both parties, one rule onely ſhall be given for Publication, and if the ſaid Commiſſion be not renewed, or another obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Plantiff or Defendent within that time, then Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall paſſe, and no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſhall be afterwards granted or renewed, without ſpeciall Order in Court.</p>
               <p>Upon the taking out of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies<note place="margin">33. No Fees for the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of the parties own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſave for wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> of Depoſitions examined in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by Commiſſion ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Plaintiff or Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, no Fee ſhall be taken by the Six Clarks or the Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for the copies, either of the Plaintiffs or Defendents re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Interrogatories, ſave onely the Clarks uſuall Fee for the writing thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:110823:19"/>Depoſitions of Witneſſes in<note place="margin">34. Depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in croſſe Cauſes.</note> ſeverall cauſes, which are meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly croſſe cauſes, (<hi>viz.</hi>) between the ſame parties, and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame matter, may be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at the hearing of both cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (coming to hearing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) without any motion or order in that behalf.</p>
               <p>VVhere either party Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff<note place="margin">Depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Cauſe.</note> or Defendent obtaineth an order to uſe Depoſitions of VVitneſſes taken in another cauſe, the adverſe party may likewiſe uſe the ſame without motion, unleſſe he be upon ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall reaſon ſhewed to the Court, by that party firſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame, inhibited by the ſame order ſo to do.</p>
               <p>No motion ſhall be made in<note place="margin">36. Depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be ſuppreſſed and how.</note> Court or by Petition, for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110823:20"/>
of Depoſitions as irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly taken, untill the ſix Clerks not toward the cauſe have been firſt attended with the complaint of the party grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and ſhall certifie the true ſtate of the Fact to the Court with their opinion: if the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tornies or Clerks on either ſide ſhall not for the eaſe of their Clients agree before them, for which purpoſe a rule for atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the ſix Clerks in ſuch caſe ſhall be entred of courſe with the Regiſter, at the deſire of the party complaining, which ſhall warrant their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings and certificate to the Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:110823:20"/>
               <head>Proces.</head>
               <p>EVery <hi>Subpoena</hi> to anſwer<note place="margin">37. Service of a <hi>Subpoena ad reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend.</hi>
                  </note> ſhall be ſerved perſonally, or left at the Defendents dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſe, or place of reſidence with one of that family, and no Clerk of this Court ſhall iſſue any attachment for not appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, but on <hi>Affidavit</hi> firſt made, poſitive and certaine, of the day and place of ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the <hi>Subpoena,</hi> and the time of the returne thereof, whereby it ſhall appeare that ſuch ſervice was made (if in London, or within twentie miles, foure dayes at the leaſt excluding the day of ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and if above twentie miles, then to have been) eight daies before ſuch attachment
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110823:21"/>
entred; and that ſuch attach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall not be diſcharged, but on payment of twenty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings coſts if the ſervice be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall, and ten ſhillings if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, and ſo the ſucceeding Proces to be double.</p>
               <p>Every <hi>Subpoena</hi> to make a<note place="margin">38. <hi>Subpoena</hi> for better Anſwer and coſts in one.</note> better anſwer, ſhall alſo contain a clauſe for payment of the coſts ordinary in that behalfe, and the Suitor not be put to take out ſeverall Writs, nor proſecute ſeverall contempts, as in that caſe hath been uſed; and if upon the ſervice of ſuch <hi>Subpoena,</hi> the coſts be not paid, the anſwer of ſuch Defendent ſhall not be received or filed, unleſſe the ſaid coſts be alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered and payed to the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffs Clark, together with the ſaid anſwer, but Proces of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110823:21"/>
contempt ſhall iſſue in that caſe, as for want of an anſwer, at the returne of the ſaid <hi>Subpoena.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Subpoena ducens tecum</hi> (when<note place="margin">39. <hi>Subpoena duc. tec.</hi> to be ſued out of courſe.</note> the Defendent confeſſeth in his anſwer, the having of any writings materiall to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined upon, or confeſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Plaintiff) may be taken out by the Plaintiff of courſe without motion, for the Defendent to bring them into Court, or ſhew cauſe, &amp;c. But if the Defendent either confeſſe not the having them in his hands, or makes his title by them, or to them by his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, he ſhall be excuſed from any contempt, although he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bring them into Court, nor ſhew cauſe, and if the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff ſhall notwithſtanding pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute a contempt in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110823:22"/>
(and the caſe upon the Defendent his anſwer appear to be ſuch) he ſhall be thereof diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, and have his coſts.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Subpoena ad audiendum Judicium</hi> ſhall be ſerved either<note place="margin">40. Service of a <hi>Subpoena ad audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end. Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium.</hi>
                  </note> on the perſon of the Defendent, or left at his dwelling houſe, where his family then reſides: or in caſe oath be made that he cannot be found to be ſerved perſonally, and that he hath no certaine dwelling, or is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, the Court will Order the leaving of a <hi>Subpoena</hi> with his Attorney in this Court to be a ſufficient ſervice.</p>
               <p>All Proces of contempt ſhall<note place="margin">41. Proces of contempt into the proper County.</note> be made out into the County, where the party proſecuted is reſident, unleſſe he ſhall be then in or about London; in which
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110823:22"/>
caſe it may be made into the County, where the party then is. And if any perſon ſhall be taken upon Proces otherwiſe or irregularly iſſued, the party ſo taken firſt appearing unto, and ſatisfying the Proces which did regularly iſſue againſt him, ſhall be diſcharged of his contempt, and have his full coſts to be tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Courſe by the ſix Clerks not towards the Cauſe for ſuch undue or irregular proſecution, from the time that the error firſt grew without motion or other order.</p>
               <p>Every ſuitor who proſecuteth<note place="margin">42. Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be uſed in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it.</note> a contempt ſhall do his beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to procure each ſeverall Proces to be duly ſerved and executed upon the party proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and his wilfull default therein appearing to the Court,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110823:23"/>
ſuch perſon offending ſhall pay unto the party grieved good coſts, and loſe the benefit of the Proces returned without ſuch endeavour.</p>
               <p>That all Attachments in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces<note place="margin">43. To be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged on pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the coſts, or upon tender and refuſall.</note> ſhall be diſcharged upon the Defendents payment, or tender to the Plaintiffs Clerk &amp; refuſall of the ordinary coſts of the Court, &amp; filing his Plea, Anſwer or D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rer (as the caſe regularly requires) without any motion in Court in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. And if after ſuch confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and payment of the coſts, (or tender and refuſall thereof) any further proſecution ſhall be had of the ſaid contempt, the party proſecuted ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with his coſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:110823:23"/>
               <head>Commiſsions to anſwer.</head>
               <p>AFter a contempt duly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted<note place="margin">44. After <hi>Att. cum Procl.</hi> no Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, nor Plea, or Demur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer.</note> to an Attachment with Proclamation returned, no Commiſſion ſhall b<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> made to Anſwer, nor Plea or Demur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer admitted, but upon motion in Court, and <hi>Affidavit</hi> made of the parties inability to travail, or other good <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atter to ſatisfie the Court touching that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay.</p>
               <p>The Defendent who is ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved<note place="margin">45. Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Anſwer gives li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to plead and d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>murre alſo.</note> with a <hi>Subpoena ad reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend.</hi> and obtaineth a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to anſwer in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſhall without more words have the ſame liberty there by to Anſwer, Plead, and Demur, as he had by the originall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110823:24"/>
if he could have appeared in perſon.</p>
               <p>After a Commiſſion once<note place="margin">46. In what caſe a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Com. to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</note> obtained to anſwer, no ſecond Commiſſion ſhall be granted without ſpeciall Order of Court; or the Plaintiffs owne aſſent under his hand. And if the time for the Defendents an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering be inlarged upon <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidavit,</hi> that he or they cannot anſwer without fight of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings in the Country, or in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the length of the Bill or the like, which ſhal not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeciall Order in Court, no Commiſſion ſhall be afterwards granted without like ſpeciall Order of Court, upon good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhewed to induce the ſame, or the like aſſent of the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:110823:24"/>In caſe where the Defendent<note place="margin">47. Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon <hi>non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</hi> or reſcue.</note> ſits all Process of contempt and cannot be found by the Serje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant at Armes, or makes a reſcue, a Sequeſtration ſhall be granted of the land in queſtion. And if the Defendent render not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf within a yeare, then an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction for the poſſeſſion, and the profits ſo ſequeſtred to be delivered over to the Plaintiff.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:110823:25"/>
               <head>Injunctions.</head>
               <p>FOr that it is agreeable to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,<note place="margin">48. Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to anſwer to contain an Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and the conſtant pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of this Court, that a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendent obtaining a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to take his Anſwer in the Country, ſhould not by that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay or favour of the Court, get an advantage againſt the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff, by proceeding at Law in the meane time, It is Ordered, that from henceforth every Commiſſion to take an Anſwer in the Countrey ſhall containe in it a clauſe of Injunction to ſtay the Defendents ſuit at Law (if any be) touching the matter complained of in the Bill untill he hath anſwered the Bill, and the Court given other Order, ſo as iſſue were not joyned at
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110823:25"/>
Law, before the returne of the <hi>Subpoena</hi> ſerved upon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendent, and in that caſe to ſtay judgement for the like time, ſo that the taking of ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion under ſeale, ſhall be a ſufficient notice and ſervice of the ſaid Injunction, without motion or other trouble to the Plaintiff, whereupon for breach to ground an Attachment, upon <hi>Affidavit</hi> of a proceeding at Law after the Commiſſion prayed.</p>
               <p>No Injunction to ſtay Suits<note place="margin">49. Grounds for Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to ſtay ſuits.</note> at Law ſhall be granted upon priority of ſuit onely, nor up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bare ſurmiſe of the Bill; but upon the Defendents de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay or wilfull contempt in not Anſwering, or upon matter confeſſed in the Anſwer, or matter of Record, or writing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110823:26"/>
plainly appearing, or the duty demanded appearing to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ancient.</p>
               <p>Where a Bill comes in after<note place="margin">50. Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on Bills after Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict.</note> a Verdict a Law for a debt, an Injunction is not to be granted, without depoſiting the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall money, except there ſhall, upon hearing both ſides, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to the Court in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendents Anſwer, or by deed under hand and ſeale, or other good matter for relief in equity. And an Injunction granted in ſuch caſe, or otherwiſe upon the merit of the cauſe or equity appearing to the Court, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly to ſtand, untill the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the cauſe, unleſſe the Plaintiff delay the cauſe, in which caſe he may beſt be quickned, by diſſolving the Injunction.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:110823:26"/>For avoiding multiplicity of<note place="margin">51. Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the matter without reference.</note> references heretofore uſed, and charged to the ſuitor, It is Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that where a motion is made for an Injunction to ſtay a ſuit at Law upon allegation of matter of equity confeſt in the anſwer, the Councell moving the ſame, ſhall have that ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion fair written in his hand, and read or truely open the ſame to the Court: and if the Court hold that matter of ſufficient weight, will thereupon grant an Injunction as is deſired, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reference, report or further motion, and then the Regiſter is in Court to receive the ſaid ſuggeſtion ſo fairly written, and inſert the ſame <hi>verbatim</hi> in the Order for granting the Injunction. But if the ſaid ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion be untrue in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thereof, upon conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:110823:27"/>
of the whole Anſwer, and the Defendent be proſecuted by the Plaintiff for breach of the Injunction granted thereupon, he ſhall be cleare from any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in that behalfe and have his coſts, and ſuch Councell ſhall juſtly incurre the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Court.</p>
               <p>Where an Injunction to ſtay<note place="margin">52. Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> ſuits is obtained upon a miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation made to the Court, (as of matter confeſſed in the Defendents Anſwer which in truth is not ſo confeſſed, or if confeſſed in one place, is avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in another part of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, or upon other ſuch like plaine abuſe to the Court, in that caſe the party proſecuted with contempt for breach of ſuch Injunction ſhall upon his examination (the matter appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:110823:27"/>
as aſoreſaid) be diſcharged of any contempt, although he hath proceeded at Law after ſuch Injunction granted, and alſo have his coſts taxed for his wrongfull vexation, by the ſame Maſter to whom the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſhall be referred without other motion in Court, which alſo ſhall be done in like caſes, where a contempt ſtands refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a Maſter of the Court, he ſhall tax coſts, and certifie the ſame in his report to the Court, together with his opinion tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the contempt, as well for the proſecutor in caſe the contempt be confeſſed or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as for the party examined if he be cleared thereof.<note place="margin">53. Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be diſſolved without motion and in what caſes.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For avoiding the many mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions heretofore frequently made, touching diſſolving and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:110823:28"/>
continuing Injunctions, it is Ordered, That when an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction is granted till Anſwer and further Order, if no Order be made within fourteen daies, (after the Anſwer duly filed in Court) for continuance of the Injunction, the ſame ſhall ſtand diſſolved without further moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon Certificate only of the Regiſter.</p>
               <p>Injunctions to quiet poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">54. Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> (uſually granted for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the publike peace, and prevention of force) ſhall not be granted before hearing, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on oath that the Plaintiff was in actuall poſſeſſion at the time of the Bill exhibited, (and not of Rents or other things which lie not in manuall occupation:) and for ſuch poſſeſſion as the Plaintiff himſelf had at the time
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:110823:28"/>
of the Bill exhibited and three yeares before, but not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended further to the poſſeſſion of ſuch from whom he claimes, or of him and his Tenants, much leſſe him and his Aſſignes or the like. Which Injunction ſhall not be extended to give the Plaintiff any other poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then he had at the time when the motion was made. And ſuch Injunction in caſe the Plaintiff delay to bring his cauſe to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is alſo to be diſſolved.</p>
               <p>No Injunction to quiet ſuch<note place="margin">55. Not to hinder ſuits, leaſe, entry or diſtreſſe.</note> poſſeſſion ſhall extend to hinder the Defendents proceedings at Law to evict the Plaintiff, or from making any leaſe, or peaceable entry, or ſingle di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe for that end.<note place="margin">56. Not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to take away a poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>
               </p>
               <p>No poſſeſſion ſhall be taken
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:110823:29"/>
from any perſon by colour of any ſuch Injunction before the cauſe be heard. And if any be, the Court will reſtore poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and award coſts.</p>
               <p>Injunctions againſt felling of<note place="margin">57. Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for Timber, ploughing. &amp;c.</note> timber, ploughing up of Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow or ancient paſtures not ploughed in twenty yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or for maintainance of Incloſures that have continued for the better part of twenty yeares ſhall be granted as uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they have been, but no De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendent who by Anſwer claims an eſtate of Inheritance, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eſtate diſpuniſhable of waſt, ſhall be thereby reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unleſſe it be particularly ſo Ordered and mentioned in the ſaid Injunction. And upon mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made for ſuch Injunction, the caſe is to be truly opened
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:110823:29"/>
as it ſtands in Court, and the Defendents Glaime by his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer if he have anſwered.</p>
               <p>When the day is appointed<note place="margin">58. Cauſes to be ſet down ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Priority of Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> for ſetting downe Cauſes for the follovving Terme, the fix Clerks ſhall preſent the Cauſes according to their priority in Publication, to be ſet downe in their Order, ſo as the old Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes may be firſt heard and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched. And for that purpoſe with the names of each Cauſe they ſhall preſent the time when Publication paſſed, with a ſhort note of the nature of every ſuch cauſe preſented. And according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Court will give Order for ſetting them downe, ſo that puyne Cauſes ſhall not thruſt out thoſe that were ready for hearing before them. Provided that no Cauſe be preſented the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:110823:30"/>
ſame Terme in which Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall paſſe.</p>
               <p>Where no Councell appears<note place="margin">59. Default at hearing.</note> for the Defendent at the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and Proces appears to have been duely ſerved, the Anſwer of ſuch Defendent ſhall be read, and if the Court upon ſuch hearing ſhall find cauſe to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree for the Plaintiff, yet a day ſhall regularly be given to the Defendent to ſhew cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame, but before he be admitted thereunto, he ſhall pay downe to the Plaintiff or his Attorney in Court ſuch coſts as the Court upon that hearing ſhall aſſeſſe, and the Order is to be penned by the Regiſter accordingly, (<hi>viz.</hi>) it is decreed ſo and ſo, &amp;c. unleſſe the Defendent ſhall by ſuch a day pay to the Plaintiff or his
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:110823:30"/>
Attorney in Court coſts, and ſhew good cauſe to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſuch Defendent upon his ſhewing cauſe ſhall firſt produce a Certificate from the Plaintiffs Attorney in Court, that he hath paid the coſts or <hi>Affidavit</hi> of tender and refuſall thereof.</p>
               <p>The reaſons of the judgement<note place="margin">60. Reaſons to be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Order.</note> of the Court are in ſuch caſe where the Defendent makes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault to be by the Regiſter ſhortly inſerted in the Order, that the Defendent may know how to apply his cauſe without a new hearing, but if the Court ſhall not receive ſatisfaction thereupon to alter or conforme the decretall Order, but that a new hearing ſhall be requiſite, the Defendent (if the Court ſhall confirme their firſt Order upon the ſecond hearing, ſhall
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:110823:31"/>
alſo pay the Plaintiff his full coſts expended in the ſuit.</p>
               <p>If the Court upon the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring<note place="margin">61. Coſts to be given on hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</note> of a Cauſe ſhall give no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe to the Plaintiff, the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſhall have coſts awarded him in reſpect of his cauſleſſe vexation. And where a Decree is made againſt a Defendent the Court will likewiſe give coſts to the Plaintiff as there ſhall be cauſe.</p>
               <p>Where coſts are awarded by<note place="margin">62. Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to pay the coſts double.</note> the Court and the party ſhall refuſe to pay them and be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards proſecuted and found in contempt for not paying of them, he ſhall not be diſcharged of ſuch his contempt, untill he ſhall pay the ſaid coſts double, over and beſides the coſts tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:110823:31"/>
for the proſecution of the ſaid contempt.</p>
               <p>Where Cauſes are removed<note place="margin">63. <hi>Certiorari</hi> Bill.</note> by ſpeciall <hi>Certiorari</hi> upon a Bill containing matter of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; the Plaintiff is before he have the <hi>Certiorari</hi> granted, to put in bond to be taken by the Regiſter, to prove his ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons within fourteen daies after the receipt of his Writ, which if he ſhall faile to do, upon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate from the Examiners that no Witneſſes are examined, or upon a report that the ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are not proved, the Court wil diſmiſſe the Bill with coſts, and award a <hi>Procedendo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:110823:32"/>
               <head>Decrees.</head>
               <p>NO Decree bindeth any<note place="margin">64. Who is bound and who not.</note> man that cometh in <hi>bona fide</hi> by conveyance before the Bill exhibited, and is made no Pertie either by Bill or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. But where he claimes in truſt for ſuch perſon againſt whom the Decree is made or comes <hi>in dependente lite</hi> without allowance or privity of the Court it is otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>No Decree ſhall recite the<note place="margin">65. To be drawne briefly.</note> Bill, Anſwer, pleadings or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions or any of them <hi>verba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim,</hi> but onely the ſhort ſtate of the matter and the Decretall Order, and the opinion and judgement of the Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:110823:32"/>No Decree being once under<note place="margin">66. Not to be altered but by Bill of review.</note> the Great Seale ſhall be reverſed or altered at the ſuit of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt whom the Decree is made, or any man claiming in privity, by, from or under him, but by Bill of review onely.</p>
               <p>But in caſe of miſtaking in a<note place="margin">67. Save in miſtakes demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative.</note> Decree which is demonſtrative, <hi>viz.</hi> an errour in auditing or numbring, miſtaking the date or the like, by the leave of the Court the ſame may be certified without a Bill.</p>
               <p>That all Decrees and diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions<note place="margin">68. When to be enrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note> pronounced upon hearing the cauſe in this Court be drawne up, ſigned and enrolled before the firſt day after the next Michaelmas or Eaſter Term after the ſame ſhall be ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced reſpectively, and not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110823:33"/>
at any time after, without ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall leave of the Court.</p>
               <p>That a ſhort entry and <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet</hi>
                  <note place="margin">69. An entry to be made of the Lands &amp;c.</note> be made in a Regiſter book kept by the Regiſter of this Court, or ſuch Clerk as he ſhall appoint for that purpoſe of all Decrees that are drawne up and enrolled, whereby any Lands or Leaſe is decreed or charged with any ſum of money, annui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c. &amp; of the Lands in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and the Pariſh, or Town and County where the ſame lie, to the end that any perſon that hath occaſion may reſort to that Regiſter Book, to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any Decree be made tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſuch Lands, houſes, &amp;c. and in caſe no ſuch entry be made within ſix moneths after ſuch Decree ſhall be ſigned by the Lords Commiſſioners for
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:110823:33"/>
the great Seal and enrolled, the ſame ſhall not prejudice any Purchaſer, who ſhall <hi>bona fide</hi> purchaſe any eſtate in ſuch lands, houſes, &amp;c. after the time limited for ſuch entry to be made.</p>
               <p>That the ſix Clerks, and all<note place="margin">70. Clerks to take care it be done.</note> other Clerks of this Court doe therefore take care for their Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, that ſuch entry be made of all Decrees by them drawn up and inrolled by the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore limited, that the Client do not ſuffer through their neglect: And that the Regiſter ſhall take onely the Fee of twelve pence for ſuch entry, twelve pence for a Certificate, and four pence for a ſearch where no Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate<note place="margin">71. Proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Decree for lands.</note> is made.</p>
               <p>In caſe of a Decree for lands
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:110823:34"/>
upon Oath made, that the ſame hath been perſonally ſerved, and is not obeyed, and an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment is iſſued under Seale for ſuch contempt, the Court doth uſually grant an Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the poſſeſſion, and upon Oath made of the ſerving there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of upon the party, and that the ſame is not obeyed, a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is to be awarded to ſome of the Juſtices of the Peace of that County, to put and keep the Plaintiff and his Aſſignes in poſſeſſion, and in caſe of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, a Writ of aſſiſtance is to be awarded to the Sheriffe for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Where the party is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">72. Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner when to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged.</note> or brought in by a Serjeant at Arms for breach of a Decree, he is not to be inlarged untill he hath performed the Decree in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:110823:34"/>
all things that are to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently done, and given ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by Recognizance with Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as the Court ſhall order, to performe the other parts of the Decree (if any be to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) at future dayes and times appointed by the Decree.</p>
               <p>Where the party is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<note place="margin">73. When re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained.</note> for breach of a Decree, or Order of Court, he ought to be reſtrained within the Fleet, and not permitted to go abroad without ſpeciall licenſe of the Court.</p>
               <p>Where a Decree is made for<note place="margin">74. Decree for money out of land.</note> Rent to be paid out of the land, or a ſum of money to be levied out of the profits of lands, there a Sequeſtration of the ſame lands being in the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents hands, or of any rent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:110823:35"/>
to the Defendent out of the ſame lands may be granted.</p>
               <p>Where cauſes are diſmiſſed<note place="margin">75. Diſmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</note> upon full hearing, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſigned and inrolled, ſuch cauſes are not againe to be retained, nor any new Bill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, except it be a Bill of Review, or upon matter of like nature, as in caſe where a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree is ſought to be avoided, and upon like ſecurity and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of the Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:110823:35"/>
               <head>Bills of Review.</head>
               <p>TO the end that after a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree<note place="margin">76. Grounds of Bill of Review.</note> made the party may be at peace, and multiplicity of ſuits be avoided, no Bill of Review ſhall be admitted, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it containe either error in Law appearing in the body of the Decree, without either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment, or further examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of matters in fact, or upon new matter diſcovered in time after the Decree made, and whereof the party could not have had advantage before; and upon ſuch Bill of Review no Witneſſes ſhall be examined to any matters which were or might have been examined un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to upon the former Bill; but upon Oath made of ſuch new
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:110823:36"/>
matter diſcovered as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, a Bill of Review may be exhibited by leave of the Court and not otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>No Bill of Review ſhall be<note place="margin">77. Not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted till obedience, except in particular caſes.</note> admitted, nor any other Bill to change matters decreed, except the Decree be firſt obeyed and performed: But if any Act be decreed to be done, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſheth the parties right at Common Law, as making of aſſurance or releaſe, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging ſatisfaction, cancelling Bonds or Evidences, and the like, or where the error is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in the body of the Decree, as aforeſaid, the Court upon motion may diſpenſe with the actuall performance of that part of the Decree till the Bill of Review be determined.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:110823:36"/>No Bill of Review ſhall be<note place="margin">78. And upon Security.</note> allowed, except the party that prefers it (giving notice to the Defendent therein) do firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a Recognizance with Sureties before ſome Maſter of the Court in ordinary, of a fit penalty in relation to the matter decreed for the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the coſts and damages if the Bill of Review be diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:110823:37"/>
               <head>Contempts.</head>
               <p>VVHere a contempt is<note place="margin">79. Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts.</note> proſecuted againſt any man he ſhall not be put to move the Court as formerly hath been uſed, either for Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories to be exhibited, or for reference of his examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and diſcharge being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined. But where any perſon ſhall be brought in by Proces or ſhall appeare <hi>gratis</hi> to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined upon a contempt, he ſhall give notice of ſuch his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance to the Attorney or Clerk of the other ſide: And if within eight daies after ſuch ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance and notice given In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories ſhall not be exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited whereon to examine him; or if being examined, no refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:110823:37"/>
ſhall be procured of his examination, nor Commiſſion taken out by the other ſide, nor Witneſſes examined in Court to prove the contempt within one moneth after ſuch examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then the party ſo examined ſhall be diſcharged of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt without further motion, and may attend any one of the Maſters of the Court for the taxing of his coſts, which the Maſter is to tax without further Order, and that taxation being entred in the Regiſter the party may proceed for the ſame of courſe, as in like caſes of coſts taxed.</p>
               <p>If after appearance and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories<note place="margin">80. Departure without being exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</note> exhibited as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, the party appearing ſhall depart before he be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined (without leave of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:110823:38"/>
Court) he is upon motion and Certificate from the Regiſter, and of ſuch his departing and not being examined, and of the Interrogatories exhibited from the Examiner, to ſtand commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without further day given unto him, and is not to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from ſuch his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt untill he hath been exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and been cleared of his contempt. And if he ſhall upon his Examinations or by proofs be found in contempt, he ſhall cleare ſuch his contempt and pay the proſecutor his coſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be diſcharged of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment. And although he be cleared of his ſaid contempt yet he ſhall have no coſts, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his diſobedience in not being examined without the proſecutors trouble and charges in moving the Court as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:110823:38"/>In caſe of proſecution of a<note place="margin">81. Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories not to exceed the <hi>Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit.</hi>
                  </note> contempt for breach of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derof the Court or otherwiſe grounded upon an <hi>Affidavit,</hi> the Interrogatories ſhall not be extended to any other matter then what is comprehended in the ſaid <hi>Affidavit</hi> or Order. And if any other ſhall be exhibited, the party examined may for that reaſon demurre unto them, or refuſe to Anſwer them.</p>
               <p>Where the party proſecuted<note place="margin">82. Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to prove it of courſe.</note> upon a contempt hath denied it, or the ſame doth not clearly appeare by his Examinations, the proſecutor may take out a Commiſſion of Courſe to prove the contempt, and in ſuch caſe the party proſecuted may name one Commiſſioner to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:110823:39"/>
at the execution of the Commiſſion, and may hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth (notwithſtanding the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer uſage to the contrary) croſſe examine the Witneſſes produced againſt him, to prove the contempt, but is not to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine any Witneſſes on his part, unleſſe he ſhall ſatisfie the Court touching ſome matter of Fact neceſſary to be proved for clearing the truth. In which caſe the Court if there be cauſe will give leave to him to examine Witneſſes to ſuch particular points ſet down, and the other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide may croſſe examine ſuch Witneſſes. But the Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories on both ſides are to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the Commiſſion.<note place="margin">83. In what caſes a Com. ſhall be to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Where a contempt is proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted againſt one who by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of age, ſickneſſe or other
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:110823:39"/>
cauſe is not able to travaile, or in caſe the ſame be againſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons who are ſervants or workmen and live far off: the Court will upon motion and <hi>Affidavit</hi> thereof, grant a Commiſſion to examine them in the Countrey<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſhall be ſued out and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted at the charge of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons deſiring it, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to ſuch indifferent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners as the proſecutor of the contempt ſhall name (as in other caſes) and one Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner onely at the nomination of the party proſecuted as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. Which Commiſſion ſhall be executed at ſuch convenient time and place, as the ſix Clerks not towards the cauſe upon hearing the Clerks on both ſides ſhall ſet downe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:110823:40"/>Upon every examination or<note place="margin">84. Maſter to tax coſts of courſe.</note> proof of a contempt referred to any of the Maſters of the Court, to certifie whether the contempt be confeſſed or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or not: the Maſter in his Certificate thereof made to the Court ſhall likewiſe aſſeſſe and certifie the coſts to either party, as there ſhall be cauſe without other Order or motion made for that purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Commitment.</head>
               <p>THe Court being tender of<note place="margin">85. On miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour on ſervice.</note> the liberty of mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and to avoid their impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment upon malicious <hi>Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davits,</hi> which are often made by one mean and ignorant perſon, and which hath heretofore by the courſe of the Court drawn
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:110823:40"/>
on a Commitment, doth Order, That from henceforth where oath ſhall be made of miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour in beating or abuſing the party upon ſerving of the Proces or Orders of the Court, the party offending is to ſtand committed upon motion, and no examination is in that caſe to be admitted.</p>
               <p>And where <hi>Affidavit</hi> ſhall<note place="margin">86. For ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Court.</note> be made by two perſons, of ſcandalous or contemptuous words againſt the Court or the Proces thereof, the party offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhall likewiſe ſtand com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon motion without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further examination. And a ſingle <hi>Affidavit</hi> in ſuch caſe ſhall be ſufficient to ground an Attachment, whereupon ſuch perſon ſhall be brought in to be examined. And if the miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour ſhall be confeſſed, or
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:110823:41"/>
proved againſt him, he ſhall ſtand committed until he ſatisfie the Court touching his ſaid miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanour, &amp; pay the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor his coſts: and if he ſhall not be thereof found guilty, ſave by the oath of the party who made ſuch <hi>Affidavit,</hi> he ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, but without any coſts, in reſpect of the oath made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>That no Order whatſoever,<note place="margin">87. Orders to be entred in eight daies.</note> except decretal or final Orders upon hearing be received to be entred after the ſpace of eight days, to be reckoned from the day of the Order pronounced <hi>excluſivè:</hi> And if the party on whoſe behalf the motion is made do not proſecute the drawing up of the Order within 4. days, the Regiſter is to do the ſame according to his notes at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the adverſe party.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:110823:41"/>
               <head>Maſters.</head>
               <p>THE Maſters are not<note place="margin">88. Reports not to be ſpecial without Order.</note> upon the importunity of Councel (how eminent ſoever) or their Clyents, to return ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial certificates to the Court, unleſs they are required by the Court ſo to do, or that their own judgment in reſpect of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty leadeth them unto it. Such kinde of certificates for the moſt part occaſioning a needleſs trouble, rather then eaſe to the Court, and certain expence to the Suitor.</p>
               <p>Their Certificates and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports<note place="margin">89. Nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix.</note> are to be drawn as ſuccin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly as may be (preſerving the matter clearly for the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Court) and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:110823:42"/>
recital of the ſeveral points of the Orders of Reference (which do ſufficiently appear by the Orders themſelves) or the ſeveral debates of Councel before them; unleſs that in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes where they are doubtfull, they ſhortly repreſent to the <hi>Court,</hi> the reaſons which induce them ſo to be.</p>
               <p>The Maſters of the Court<note place="margin">90. To be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</note> are to take notice, That when the Court requires to be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from them touching any matter alledged to be confeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or ſet forth in the Defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants Anſwer; it is intended that without further Order they ſhould take conſideration of the whole Anſwer or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers of the Defendant, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie not only whether the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be ſo confeſſed or ſet forth,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:110823:42"/>
but alſo any other matter, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding that confeſſion, or bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancing the ſame, that the <hi>Court</hi> may receive a clear and true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
               <p>The Maſters in taking Affida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vits,<note place="margin">91. Oaths re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertndly to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred. and taken</note> and adminiſtring of Oaths in caſes duly preſented unto them, are to be circumſpect and wary that the ſame be reverend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and knowingly given and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and are therefore to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the ſame themſelves to the party, and where they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern him raſh, or ignorant, to give him ſome conſcionable admonition of his Duty, and be ſure he underſtand the matter contained in his Affidavit, and read the ſame over, or hear it read in his preſence, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe his name or mark there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto before the ſame be certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:110823:43"/>
by the Maſter, who is not to receive or certifie any Affida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, unleſs the ſame be fairly and legibly written without blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or interlineation of any word of ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>In all matters referred to the<note place="margin">92. Reports poſitive.</note> Maſters of the Court, their Certificate (not being to ground a Decree) if it be poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive is to ſtand, and Proces may be taken out to enforce per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther motion, unleſs the adverſe party upon notice given (to his Attorney or Clerk in Court) that ſuch report is filed againſt him, ſhall within eight days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch notice (if it be given in Term, or whiles the General Seals for motions are held, or within four days in the next Term, if it be given after) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:110823:43"/>
ſome Order in Court to controle or ſuſpend the ſame. And in caſe of an inſufficient Anſwer certified by the Maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the Plaintiff may imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately take out Proces againſt the Defendant for his Coſts, and to make a better Anſwer as hath been formerly uſed.</p>
               <p>Where after Certificate or<note place="margin">93. Appeals from them</note> Report made by the Maſters of the Court, either Party ſhall appeal from the ſame, to the judgement of the Court, he ſhall firſt file his exceptions thereunto briefly, with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter and depoſite with him, Fourty ſhillings to be paid to the other Party for his Coſts, if he prevail not in ſuch Appeal. And then the Regiſter ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch Cauſes of Appeal in a paper in order as they are
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:110823:44"/>
brought unto him to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the Court in courſe upon days of motions, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof to be given by the party appealing, to the Clerk of the other ſide. And alſo the Regiſters Paper to be ſet up in the Office two days before. And if the Court ſhall not alter the Maſters Report, then the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhillings depoſited to be paid to the Party defending the ſame, with ſuch increaſe as the Court ſhall finde cauſe to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, otherwiſe to be reſtored to the party appealing, and both without charge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Petitions.</head>
               <p>NO Injunction for ſtay of<note place="margin">94. No injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to be granted on Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Suit at Law ſhall be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, revived, diſſolved, or ſtaid
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:110823:44"/>
upon Petition. Nor any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of any other nature ſhall paſs by Order upon Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without notice and a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of the Petition firſt given to the other ſide, and the Petition filed with the Regiſter, and the Order entered.</p>
               <p>No Sequeſtration, Diſmiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">95. Nor Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, Retainer, nor final Order.</note> Retainers upon diſmiſsions or final Orders, are to be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon Petition.</p>
               <p>No former Order made in<note place="margin">96. Nor Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> Court is to be altered, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained upon a Petition; no Commitment of any perſon taken upon Proces of contempt to be diſcharged by Order made upon Petition, unleſs in the Vacation, and upon hearing the adverſe Party his Attorney or Clerk in Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:110823:45"/>No Commiſsions for exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations<note place="margin">97. No Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions to examine witneſſes to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, or diſcharged nor exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations ſuppreſſed by Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> of witneſſes, ſhall be awarded or diſcharged, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations ſuppreſſed upon Petition, except it be upon point of the Courſe of the Court firſt referred to the ſix Clerks not towards the Cauſe and certificate thereupon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Paupers.</head>
               <p>After an admittance <hi>In forma</hi>
                  <note place="margin">98. Not to pay Fees.</note> 
                  <hi>Pauperis,</hi> no Fee, Profit, or Reward ſhall be taken of ſuch Party admitted, by any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor or Attorney for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of the <hi>Paupers</hi> buſineſs, during the time it ſhall depend in Court, and he continued <hi>In forma pauperis;</hi> nor any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, nor agreement be made for any Recompence, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:110823:45"/>
afterwards. And if any Perſon offending herein ſhall be diſcovered to the Court, he ſhall undergo the diſpleaſure of the Court, and ſuch further puniſhment as the Court ſhall think fit to inflict upon him, and the party admitted, who ſhall give any ſuch Fee or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or make any ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, or agreement, ſhall be from thenceforth <hi>Diſpaupered,</hi> and not be afterwards admitted again in that Suit to proſecute <hi>in forma pauperis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it ſhall be made appear to<note place="margin">99. No<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to contract for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Suit.</note> the Court, That any Perſon proſecuting <hi>in forma pauperis,</hi> hath ſold or contracted for the benefit of the ſuit, or any part thereof whiles the ſame depends, ſuch cauſe ſhall be from thenceforth totally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:110823:46"/>
the Court, and never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain Retained.</p>
               <p>Such Councel, or Attorney<note place="margin">100. Councel and Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to do their duty.</note> as ſhall be aſsigned by the <hi>Court</hi> to aſsiſt the Perſon admitted <hi>in forma pauperis,</hi> either to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute or defend, may not refuſe ſo to do, unleſs they ſatisfie the Lords Commiſsioners, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Rolles who granted the admittance, with ſome good reaſon of their forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
               <p>That Councellor who ſhall<note place="margin">101. Motions for them to be firſt made.</note> move any thing to the Court, on the behalf of a Perſon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <hi>in forma pauperis,</hi> ought to have the Order of admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him, and firſt to move the ſame, before any other motion. And if the Regiſter ſhall finde that ſuch perſon was
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:110823:46"/>
not admitted <hi>in forma pauperis,</hi> he ſhall not draw up any Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon the ſecond motion made by any ſuch Councel, but he ſhall loſe the fruit of ſuch ſecond motion in reſpect of his abuſe to the Court.</p>
               <p>No Proces of Contempt<note place="margin">102. Proces of Contempt for them to be firſt ſigned by the ſix Clerk.</note> ſhall be made forth and ſent to the Great Seal at the ſuit of any Perſon proſecuting as Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff <hi>in forma pauperis,</hi> untill it be ſigned by the ſix Clerk who deals for him, and the ſix Clerks are to take care, that the ſuch Proces be not taken out need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly, or for vexation, but upon juſt and good cauſe, as they will anſwer it to the Court, if the contrary ſhall appear.</p>
               <p>And laſtly; it is Ordered,<note place="margin">103.</note> That all Maſters of the Court
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:110823:47"/>
of Chancery, Councellors, and all Officers, Miniſters, Clerks, and Solicitors in the ſaid Court, do obſerve theſe Orders, which are to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue until upon further Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and experience, any Alterations ſhall be thought fit to be made therein.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:110823:47"/>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>B. Whitelocke <hi>C. S.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Rich. Keble <hi>C. S.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>W. Lenthall</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the <hi>Roles.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:110823:48"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110823:48"/>
            <head>An Alphabetical Table.</head>
            <div type="index">
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>A</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ANſwer to matter of Fact.</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Time to anſwer exceptions.</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Time to deliver Exceptions to an Anſwer.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Further inſufficient Anſwers, and Costs for them.</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Appeals from Masters Reports.</cell>
                        <cell>85</cell>
                        <cell>93</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>B</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ccinctneſs in Bills.</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Certiorari Bill.</cell>
                        <cell>61</cell>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Bills of Review.</cell>
                        <cell>69</cell>
                        <cell>76</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Not to be admitted till obedience, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in particular caſes,</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>77</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:110823:49"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>And upon ſecurity.</cell>
                        <cell>71</cell>
                        <cell>78</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>C</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>CAuſes to be ſet down according to priority of Publication.</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Commiſſion to Anſwer gives liberty to Plead and Demur alſo.</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Commiſſion to Anſwer to contain an Injunction.</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Not to be granted after Attach <hi>cum procl.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>In what caſe a ſecond Commiſſion to Anſwer.</cell>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Carriage of a Commiſſion to Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Commiſſion <hi>ex parte</hi> when</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>New Commiſſions, and how</cell>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>New Commiſſion through the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants default.</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Commitment for Miſdemeanors on Service.</cell>
                        <cell>78</cell>
                        <cell>85</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For Scandalous, and Contemptuous words againſt the Court.</cell>
                        <cell>79</cell>
                        <cell>86</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:110823:49"/>
                  <table>
                     <head>Contempts.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Proces of Contempt into the proper County.</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Endeavour to be uſed in ſerving it.</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To be diſcharged on payment of the Coſts, or on Tender and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall.</cell>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Appearance on Contempts.</cell>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                        <cell>79</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Departure without b<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ing Examined.</cell>
                        <cell>73</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>In what caſe a Commiſſion ſhall be to Examine Contemners.</cell>
                        <cell>76</cell>
                        <cell>83</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Commiſſion to prove a Contempt of courſe.</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>81</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Contemners, when to be diſcharged.</cell>
                        <cell>66</cell>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>When reſtrained.</cell>
                        <cell>67</cell>
                        <cell>73</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Coſts for inſufficient Anſwer.</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For further inſufficient Anſwer.</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Maſters to tax Coſts on Contempts of Courſe.</cell>
                        <cell>78</cell>
                        <cell>84</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Coſts to be given on hearing</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>61</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Contemner to pay the Costs double.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>D</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>DEcrees, who is bound by them, and who not.</cell>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To be drawn briefly.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <pb facs="tcp:110823:50"/>Not to be altered but by Bill of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view,</cell>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                        <cell>66</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Save in miſtakes demonſtrative.</cell>
                        <cell>ib,</cell>
                        <cell>67</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>When to be enrolled.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>68</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>An entry to be made of the lands &amp;c.</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                        <cell>69</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Clarks to take care it be done.</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Proſecution of Decrees for Lands.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>71</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For money out of Lands.</cell>
                        <cell>67</cell>
                        <cell>74</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Default at hearing.</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>59</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Demurrer to put in without perſonal attendance or charge of Commiſſion.</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Demurrers to expreſs the cauſes.</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Demurrer upon a ſlip or miſtake.</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>No demurrer after Attach <hi>cum proc.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Demurrer being admitted the Bill to be diſmiſſed of Courſe.</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Depoſitions in Croſs cauſes.</cell>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Depoſitions in another cauſe.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Depoſitions to be ſuppreſsed, and how.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Diſmiſſion for non-proſecution not to be retained till coſts paid.</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Diſmiſſions on hearing.</cell>
                        <cell>68</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>E</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>TIme to anſwer Exceptions.</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Time for Exceptions to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <pb facs="tcp:110823:50"/>Examiners Duty.</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To have care of their Clerks, and be anſwerable for them.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Examiner to avoid impertinences.</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>No Examination after publication.</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>H</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>HEaring on Bill and Anſwer.</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>What evidence admitted.</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Default at hearings.</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>59</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Reaſons to be expreſſed in the Order.</cell>
                        <cell>59</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Coſts to be given on hearing,</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>61</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>I</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>INterrogatories to be pertinent.</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>No new Interrogatories for the ſame witneſſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>No Fees for the Copies of the parties own Interrogatories, ſave for writing.</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Interrogatories not to exceed the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidavit.</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>81</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Injunction contained in a Commiſſion to Anſwer</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <pb facs="tcp:110823:51"/>Grounds for Injunctions to ſtay ſuits.</cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Injunction on Bills after verdict,</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Injunctions on the matter without Reference.</cell>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Injunctions on miſ-information.</cell>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Injunctions to be diſſolved without motion, and in what caſes.</cell>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Injunctions to quiet Poſſeſſion.</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Not to hinder Suits, Leaſe, Entry, or Distreſs.</cell>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Not to extend to take away Poſſeſſion</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Injunct. for Timber, Ploughing</hi> &amp;c.</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>O</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>OAths reverendly to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred and taken.</cell>
                        <cell>83</cell>
                        <cell>91</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Orders to be entered in eight days.</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>87</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>P</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>PAupers not to pay Fees,</cell>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                        <cell>98</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Nor to contract for the benefit of his Suit.</cell>
                        <cell>89</cell>
                        <cell>99</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Councel and Attorney aſſigned to do their duty.</cell>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Motions for them to be first made.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>101</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <pb facs="tcp:110823:51"/>Proces of Contempt for them to be firſt ſigned by the ſix Clerk.</cell>
                        <cell>91</cell>
                        <cell>102</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>No Pleadings to be of effect till filed.</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Pleadings to be ſuccinct.</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Pleas to be put in without perſonal attendance or Commiſſion.</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Pleas on the matter, or to the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Plea of Outlawry.</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Plea of a former Suit depending.</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Plea of a Suit depending in another Court.</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Petitions. No Injunction to be granted by Petition.</cell>
                        <cell>86</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Nor Sequeſtration, Diſmiſſion, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers upon Diſmiſſions, or final Orders.</cell>
                        <cell>87</cell>
                        <cell>95</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Nor Order altered or explained, nor Commitment diſcharged.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>96</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>No Commiſſions for Examination of Witneſſes to be awarded or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, nor Examinations ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by Petition.</cell>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                        <cell>97</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Proofs to be only of matters neceſſary.</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>One rule for Publication on a joynt Commiſſion.</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:110823:52"/>
                  <table>
                     <head>R</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Plaintiff to Reply, if Anſwer good to common intent.</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Reports of Maſters not to be ſpecial without Order.</cell>
                        <cell>81</cell>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Nor prolix.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>89</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To be upon the whole Anſwer.</cell>
                        <cell>82</cell>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Reports that are poſitive.</cell>
                        <cell>84</cell>
                        <cell>92</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>S</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>SErvice of a <hi>Subpoena</hi> to anſwer.</cell>
                        <cell>39</cell>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Subpoena</hi> for better Anſwer and Coſts in one.</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>38</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Subpoena ducens tecum</hi> to be ſued out of courſe.</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>39</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Service of a <hi>Subpoena ad audiend. Judicium.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sequeſtration on <hi>non eſt invent.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>W</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Reg.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>NO Witneſs to be exaamined without notice, &amp;c.</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Witneſſes to be examined to <hi>Interr. ſeriatim.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Examination to the credit of a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and how.</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Fee for examining a Witneſs to be deducted.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
