<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>At Edinburgh, the 9th day of July, 1696 Whereas the books of subscription to the Company of Scotland trading to Africa and the Indies, have continued open at Edinburgh for the twenty sixth day of February last, to this instant; ...</title>
            <author>Company of Scotland Trading to Africa and the Indies.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5593</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231864</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900074</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900074</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137261</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A80264)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137261)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2510:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>At Edinburgh, the 9th day of July, 1696 Whereas the books of subscription to the Company of Scotland trading to Africa and the Indies, have continued open at Edinburgh for the twenty sixth day of February last, to this instant; ...</title>
                  <author>Company of Scotland Trading to Africa and the Indies.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from caption and opening lines of text.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the John Carter Brown Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:137261:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <opener>
               <dateline>AT EDINBURGH, <date>
                     <hi>The</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>Day of</hi> July, 1696.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>WHEREAS the Books of Subſcription to the COMPANY <hi>of SCOTLAND Trading to AFRICA and the INDIES,</hi> have continued open at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> from the Twenty Sixth Day of <hi>February</hi> laſt, to this Inſtant; And altho' continuing the Subſcriptions in <hi>SCOTLAND</hi> ſo long, hath been very prejudicial to the Affairs of the COMPANY at Home and Abroad; Yet in regard that all Doubts and Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties may be fully Obviated, and no reaſonable Means or Opportunity omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to make this the moſt Diffuſive and National <hi>Joynt-Stock</hi> in the World: The COURT <hi>of</hi> DIRECTORS <hi>of the ſaid COMPANY,</hi> Do hereby Agree and Declare, that the ſaid Books of Subſcriptions ſhall continue open until <hi>Saturday</hi> the firſt Day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> next, at Six a Clock in the Afternoon: And the ſaid COURT of DIRECTORS do further Reſolve, Publiſh and Declare, that if any of the Subſcribers of the ſaid COMPANY ſhall neglect to pay the firſt Quarter-part of their Subſcriptions until the Tenth Day of the ſaid Month of <hi>August;</hi> That then, and from thence-forward, the Share of Stock belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuch Perſon or Perſons, ſhall either be Purſued for according to Law, or Transferr'd and Diſpos'd of by the ſaid COURT, to ſuch as will Adventure and pay the Sum or Sums required, at the Pleaſure of the ſaid COURT of DIRECTORS.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Publiſhed by Order of CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RT,
ROD. MACKENZIE, <hi>Sec:<hi rend="sup">ry</hi>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <opener>
               <dateline>EDINBURGH, <date>the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of<hi>Auguſt</hi> 1696.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THE above-written ACT of the ſaid CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RT of DIRECTORS was Read, Conſidered and Approved of by the CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCIL-GENERAL of the ſaid COMPANY: And the ſaid CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCIL-GENERAL, Doth hereby further Enact and Declare, That the ſaid CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RT of DIRECTORS may, at any time after the ſaid Tenth Day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> inſtant, Inveſt in themſelves, for the COMPANY'S <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, the reſpective Shares and Intereſts of ſuch Subſcribers or Proprietors in the <hi>Joynt-Stock</hi> of the ſaid COMPANY, as ſhall either neglect or refuſe to Pay or Cauſe Pay the firſt Fourth-Payment of the reſpective Sums Subſcribed by them as aforeſaid, before the ſaid Tenth Day of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> And that upon ſuch Inveſtment, the ſaid CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RT of DIRECTORS, or any appointed by them for that intent, may thereafter Transferr the ſeveral Shares and Intereſts, not paid as aforeſaid, to ſuch as, by advancing the ſeveral Sums required, ſhall become Proprietors thereof.</p>
            <p>Then a Report being made to the ſaid CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCIL-GENERAL, by the COMPANY'S <hi>Chief-Accomptant,</hi> that the compleat Sum of Four Hundred Thouſand Pounds <hi>Sterling</hi> was Subſcribed in the Books of the ſaid COMPANY, by Perſons reſiding in <hi>SCOTLAND;</hi> The ſaid CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCIL-GENERAL have Ordered the ſaid Books of Subſcription to be cloſed, and that the ſame be hereby Publiſhed and Declared accordingly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>DAVID HOME P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
