<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lady Pecunia's journey unto hell with her speech to Pluto, maintaining that she sends more soules to hell then all his fiends: with Pluto's answer and applause.</title>
            <author>Crouch, Humphrey, fl. 1635-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81066</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.17[75]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R211785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870484</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870484</idno>
            <idno type="VID">163323</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A81066)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 163323)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 246:669f17[75])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Lady Pecunia's journey unto hell with her speech to Pluto, maintaining that she sends more soules to hell then all his fiends: with Pluto's answer and applause.</title>
                  <author>Crouch, Humphrey, fl. 1635-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Clarke, at the signe of the Flowre-de-luce, neare the Hospitall Gate in Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse - "Great Pluto, Prince of hell, I come to thee,".</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "January 30"; the '4' in the imprint has been crossed out and replaced with a "3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hell --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Greed --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:163323:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
            <head>The Lady PECUNIA'S Journey unto Hell, with her ſpeech to <hi>Pluto,</hi> maintaining that ſhe ſends more Soules to Hell then all his Fiends: With <hi>Pluto's</hi> anſwer and applauſe.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I Lady</hi> Pecunia, <hi>Miſtreſs of the Mint,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Am riding unto hell all in a Print.</hi>
                  </l>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Fiends dance for joy <hi>Pecunia</hi>'s baniſht.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <l>GReat Pluto, Prince of hell, I come to thee,</l>
               <l>To give account what hath been done by mee:</l>
               <l>When all your Fiends (great Pluto) did ſmall good</l>
               <l>In bringing ſoules to Hell, I underſtood,</l>
               <l>I ſent you thouſands, who my wayes then trod,</l>
               <l>That honour'd me, as I had been their God;</l>
               <l>Forgot their prayers, neglected their owne ſoules,</l>
               <l>And all for love of me, poore ſimple fooles!</l>
               <l>And many of them too (ſuch is their caſe)</l>
               <l>They cannot reſt untill they ſee my face;</l>
               <l>Nay, when they are in bed, ſo kinde they bee,</l>
               <l>They cannot ſl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ep for thinking then of me,</l>
               <l>The Clergy mourns, my abſence oft doth grieve 'em,</l>
               <l>Till I come double handed to relieve 'em.</l>
               <l>Which of your Feends can do more feats than I?</l>
               <l>I can foole Conſcience, make the guiltleſs die,</l>
               <l>Pull Juſtice from her ſeat, and free the guilty,</l>
               <l>Make the impure ſeem pure, though ne're ſo filthy.</l>
               <l>The Lawyer will not plead the Subjects caſe,</l>
               <l>Without he ſees Lady PECUNIA'S face:</l>
               <l>Such is their love to me, and ſuch my might,</l>
               <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t when a cauſe is bad, I make it right.</l>
               <l>The Judge himſelfe doth know I ſpeak but truth;</l>
               <l>For I have made them Knaves, even from their youth:</l>
               <l>Nay, many mortals are ſuch ſimple Elves,</l>
               <l>That for my ſake they will forſwear themſelves,</l>
               <l>D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mn their owne ſoules, and all for love of me,</l>
               <l>So over loving, and ſo kinde they be,</l>
               <l>The great Church of S. Pauls, Ile have it down,</l>
               <l>Though it were once a place of great renown,</l>
               <l>The wood, the ſead, the ſtones, which ſome count traſh,</l>
               <l>In time may yield the Common-wealth ſome caſh:</l>
               <l>Kings cannot war, nor make their foes afraid,</l>
               <l>Nor make their ſwords drink bloud without my aid.</l>
               <l>I can bewitch the Prudent, ſpoyle Devotion,</l>
               <l>With promiſe of ſome wealth, and high promotion.</l>
               <l>I ruine Towns, and make the ſlave rebell,</l>
               <l>And after ſend the Rebels ſouls to hell.</l>
               <l>Some think the Poet for applauſe doth ſing,</l>
               <l>When for my ſake he undertakes this thing;</l>
               <l>A Cup of Sack doth make his ſpirits glad,</l>
               <l>But without me there's no Sack to be had:</l>
               <l>Of all men living he cares leaſt for mee,</l>
               <l>For a rich Poet who did ever ſee?</l>
               <l>My Slver-hooke can never bring him in,</l>
               <l>Though many years about it I have bin:</l>
               <l>I have lookt here about me pritty well.</l>
               <l>Yet I can ſee no Poets here in hell.</l>
               <l>And ſo great Lord I have no more to ſay,</l>
               <l>All living men but Poets me obey.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pluto's Anſwer.</head>
               <l>Lady<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quoth Pluto, I do honour thee,</l>
               <l>For ſending of ſo many ſouls to mee;</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt be call'd the Lady of the Earth,</l>
               <l>As I was Prince of th'Aire before thy birth:</l>
               <l>Though thou canſt do but little good in hell,</l>
               <l>Send ſouls to me, and that ſhall do as well,</l>
               <l>With that there was a fearfull noyſe in hell,</l>
               <l>The helliſh fiends began for to rebell,</l>
               <l>'Cauſe Pluto took Lady PECUNIA'S part,</l>
               <l>His ſubjects from their loyalty did ſtart,</l>
               <l>The helliſh fiends at him exceptions took;</l>
               <l>Murther ſpoke firſt with fearfull angry look:</l>
               <l>Shall I (quoth Murther) ſlighted be, great Lord,</l>
               <l>Who have deſtroyd ſo many by the ſword?</l>
               <l>How many men have I made, for your good,</l>
               <l>Moſt barbarouſly to ſhed each others bloud?</l>
               <l>Have I not made the brother kill the <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>other,</l>
               <l>The little infant murther'd by the mother?</l>
               <l>Have I not made the man to kill the wife,</l>
               <l>And made the woman end the husbands life?</l>
               <l>What miſchiefe have I left undone in Towns?</l>
               <l>With bloudy hands and feet trampled on Crowns.</l>
               <l>Tell me what miſchiefe I have left undone</l>
               <l>To advance you: and will you dote upon,</l>
               <l>And honour this great Lady 'bove us all,</l>
               <l>Who to raiſe you do make ſo many fall?</l>
               <l>Brother Revenge, now ſpeak, is this not true?</l>
               <l>How many men have faln by me and you?</l>
               <l>Then came Revenge with hands all dipt in bloud,</l>
               <l>And ſaid, great Prince, if it be underſtood,</l>
               <l>Murther and I have done beſt ſervice now,</l>
               <l>To inlarge hell under command of you:</l>
               <l>How many duels h ve I made men fight,</l>
               <l>And kill each other in revenge and ſpite?</l>
               <l>How many women have I Witches made,</l>
               <l>And to revenge their cauſe lent them my aid?</l>
               <l>What is't but I can doe? you know it well,</l>
               <l>I have brought thouſands to the pit of hell.</l>
               <l>Nay then quoth Luſt, I pray Iet me come in,</l>
               <l>For I have made more men and women ſin</l>
               <l>Then either of you both: you kill and ſlay;</l>
               <l>But I bring ſouls to hell an eaſie way:</l>
               <l>I tempt men from the Dunghill to the Crown,</l>
               <l>And bring them unto hell in beds of down;</l>
               <l>I Iull them ſo aſleep with pleaſures rate,</l>
               <l>Till they'r in hell they know not where they are:</l>
               <l>I tempt the wanton woman day by day;</l>
               <l>The idle man can hardly ſay me nay:</l>
               <l>I with provoking meats can pleaſe their pallats,</l>
               <l>And ſtrengthen nature with voluptuous ſallats:</l>
               <l>My name is Luſt; 'cis I can doe theſe things,</l>
               <l>And with faire Maids deceive the greateſt Kings.</l>
               <l>You ſee (great Prince) by what is here expreſt,</l>
               <l>I have done more for Hell then all the reſt.</l>
               <l>Thou vaporing fool, quoth Pride, 'tis I muſt raigne,</l>
               <l>Thou waitſt on every Pander, Whore, and Queane;</l>
               <l>I rule in Princes Courts, 'tis I alone</l>
               <l>That can advance the Peaſant to the throne,</l>
               <l>And if Ambition render him a Crowne,</l>
               <l>We finde a way to pull the Peaſant down:</l>
               <l>New faſhions day by day I doe invent,</l>
               <l>To pleaſe the humoriſt and male content.</l>
               <l>I into Barbers ſhops do creep, and there</l>
               <l>Invent white powder to perfume the haire;</l>
               <l>And ſo with that, and ſuch like ſimple toyes,</l>
               <l>I make them looke juſt like Millers boyes:</l>
               <l>I make the Oyſter woman leave her bawling,</l>
               <l>And weare gold lace, a thing beyond her calling.</l>
               <l>Not without me quoth Money, by your leave,</l>
               <l>For without me none can go fine and brave.</l>
               <l>With that the Fiends on Lady PECUNIA fell,</l>
               <l>And caſt her in great fury out of Hell:</l>
               <l>And ſince ſhe's come againe, thus ſtands the caſe,</l>
               <l>She makes diviſion ſtill in every place.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l>O love not Money then ſo well,</l>
                  <l>That ſends ſo many ſouls to Hell.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>HUMPHREY CROVVCH.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Clarke,</hi> at the ſigne of the Flowre-de-luce, neare the Hoſpitall Gate in Smithfield, 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
