<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of a strange and wonderfull monster: born in Kirkham parish in Lancashire (the childe of Mrs. Haughton, a Popish gentlewoman) the face of it upon the breast, and without a head (after the mother had wished rather to bear a childe without a head then a Roundhead) and had curst the Parliamnet [sic]. Attested by Mr. Fleetwood, minister of the same parish, under his own hand; and Mrs. Gattaker the mid-wife, and divers other eye-witnesses: whose testimony was brought up by a member of the House of Commons. Appointed to be printed according to order: and desired to be published in all the counties, cities, townes, and parishes in England: being the same copies that were presented to the Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82095</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E325_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200628</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861326</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861326</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113459</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A82095)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113459)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E325[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of a strange and wonderfull monster: born in Kirkham parish in Lancashire (the childe of Mrs. Haughton, a Popish gentlewoman) the face of it upon the breast, and without a head (after the mother had wished rather to bear a childe without a head then a Roundhead) and had curst the Parliamnet [sic]. Attested by Mr. Fleetwood, minister of the same parish, under his own hand; and Mrs. Gattaker the mid-wife, and divers other eye-witnesses: whose testimony was brought up by a member of the House of Commons. Appointed to be printed according to order: and desired to be published in all the counties, cities, townes, and parishes in England: being the same copies that were presented to the Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Jane Coe.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 3 1645"; the second 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monsters --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Abnormalities, Human --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Roundheads --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113459:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION,
<hi>Of a ſtrange and Wonderfull</hi> MONSTER:
Born in KIRKHAM Pariſh in LANCASHIRE (the Childe
of Mrs. <hi>Haughton,</hi> a Popiſh Gentlewoman) the face of it upon the breaſt,
and without a head (after the mother had wiſhed rather to bear a
Childe without a head then a Round head) and had curſt the
PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>Atteſted by Mr. FLEETWOOD, Miniſter of the ſame Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,
under his own hand; and Mrs. <hi>Gattaker</hi> the Mid-wife, and divers
other eye-witneſſes: Whoſe teſtimony was brought up by a <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>Appointed to be printed according to Order: And deſired to be publiſhed in all the
Counties, Cities, Townes, and Pariſhes in <hi>England:</hi> Being the ſame
Copies that were preſented to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
London, Printed by <hi>Jane Coe.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:113459:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113459:2"/>
            <head>A
DECLARATION OF A
Strange and Wonderfull
MONSTER:
born in Kirkham Pariſh, in
Lancaſhire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His wonderfull manifeſtation of Gods
anger, againſt wicked and prophane peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;
we ſhall lay open thus.</p>
            <p>1. In declaring where it was done.</p>
            <p>2. Upon whom.</p>
            <p>3. What is ſuppoſed might be the
cauſe.</p>
            <p>4. What proofs there are to make it
appear to be a truth.</p>
            <p>In the firſt, we have diſcovered the County, Pariſh, and the
Houſe.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond; the woman her parentage, her husband, and
religion.</p>
            <p>In the third, her courſe of life, and her ſpeeches.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113459:3"/>
In the fourth, that it is confirmed, both by relation and teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials
under their own hands, who were eye witneſſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Dukedome of <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> is the County where this
Monſter was brought forth; the County it ſelf lyes North, borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
upon the Weſt of York-ſhire, and Derby-ſhire, and by the
Iriſh Sea. The people that live there, are a mixt Number; ſome
precious godly people; but for the moſt part very bad: No parts
in <hi>England</hi> hath had ſo many Witches, none fuller of Papiſts, and
they were the chiefe Inſtruments in ſeeking to have that wicked
Book of Allowance for Sports on the Lords Day to be publiſhed,
and it was ſet forth by their procurements, and the godly people
amongſt them have ſuffered very much under their reproaches and
wicked malice.</p>
            <p>This Monſter was born in the Town and Pariſh of <hi>Kirkeham</hi>
in that County, which is in <hi>Amounderneſſe</hi> Hundred, between <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston</hi>
and little <hi>Morton,</hi> within three miles of <hi>Clifton,</hi> on the Weſt
ſide of <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> within ſome three miles of one point of the Sea,
and ſome ſix or ſeven miles of the main; a Pariſh which God hath
bleſſed with good Miniſters, and ſome godly people (though but
few) in it; who by the malice of wicked and prophane Wretches,
have been much abuſed heretofore.</p>
            <p>This Gentlewoman (for ſo ſhe is both by Birth and Mariage)
was delivered of this Monſter at her Husbands houſe in <hi>Kirkeham</hi>
Pariſh aforeſaid, and about a mile from <hi>Kirkeham</hi> Town, where
the Midwife being ſent for came to her, and delivered her in that
houſe, the Child (or rather Monſter) was born, but dead, and there
it was ſhewed, and from thence caryed into the Church-yard a
day or two after, and there buried: after which, ſome (in Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens
habit) were ſeen to go in; ſuppoſed to be Popiſh Prieſts and
Fryars: and thus you have the place where this Monſter was
brought forth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the woman that bore it, ſhe is a good hanſome,
proportionable, comely Gentlewoman, young, and of a good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion,
of a merry diſpoſition, and an healthfull Nature, well perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
had her conditions been ſuitable.</p>
            <p>For her Parents they were of a very bitter diſpoſition againſt
godly people; Papiſts they were both, and divertive againſt honeſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113459:3"/>
proteſtants, For her mother ſhe would uſually call honeſt men
Roundheads and Puritans, and Hereticks, many gentlemen did
much uſe her houſe, which were ſuſpected to be popiſh prieſts
her husband (which was this womans father) was called Mr.
<hi>Browne,</hi> who lived in the pariſh of <hi>Kirkham</hi> alſo: And amongſt
other reproaches and ſcornes which her mother caſt upon religious
people ſhe took her Cat; and ſaid that it muſt be made a Round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head
like <hi>Burton, Prinne,</hi> and <hi>Baſtwicke,</hi> and cauſing the eares to
be cut off; called her cat Prynnn (inſtead of Puſſe) both then
and after ſhe hath often ſaid, that ſhe hoped to ſee the Church flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
againe (meaning the Popiſh Church) and all Roundheads
ſubdued; and ſhe hath done much for the releife of poore Papiſts
in thoſe parts.</p>
            <p>The young woman, viz: Miſtris <hi>Brownes</hi> daughter, who
bore this monſter, was married by one Maſter <hi>Haughton</hi> a papiſt
alſo; for none elſe were admitted to come ſuiters to her, This
Maſter <hi>Haugh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> then lived at <hi>Grimſhall</hi> in the ſame Countie, but
after they were married dwelt ſometimes in a village neere <hi>Kerk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>
in the ſame pariſh where her mother lived, Mr. <hi>Haughton</hi> is a
gentlema<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſcended of an ancient family, wel known in thoſe parts
and not altogether of ſuch a bitter ſpirit as thoſe he matched with,
he hath been a gentleman wel bred, only in a popiſh way educated.</p>
            <p>The woman he married was a notorious papiſt, and would ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
times hold a notable diſcourſe with her neighbours about her
religion, ſhe was not onely borne of popiſh parents, but bred, and
brought up with them, and educated in the popiſh Religion ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
many popiſh pictures, and Crucifixes, and other popiſh trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery
wherein ſhe much delighted; and i<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhe were at any time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
for the ſuperſtitious fooleries ſhe ſo affected, ſhe would
ſpeak much in defence thereof, and was alwayes very obſtinate,
and would expreſſe much invection againſt thoſe godly proteſtants
and others that reproved her.</p>
            <p>3 Now for the courſe of life which the woman lived, who
bare this monſter, it hath been much ſpent in popiſh devotion;
and ſome<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imes in company with her neighbours the gentlewomen
and Fa<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ers wives that lived about her, ſhe was one v<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
amongſt papiſts, and fri<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndly amongſt neighbours, onely
when her Religion was touched, ſhe expreſſed much paſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113459:4"/>
She hath been often heard to curſe againſt Mr. <hi>Prinn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi>
and Doctor <hi>Baſtwick,</hi> and the Roundheads. Alſo to revile
the Parliament, and ſay that ſhee thought that the King
and the Biſhops were the righter part of us; ſhe hath
been heard to wiſh, that ſhe and hers might never live to be <hi>Round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads,</hi>
nor <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> and that ſhe hath praid to God, that ſhe
might never live to ſee any of hers ſuch; and that the <hi>Puritans</hi>
and <hi>Independents</hi> deſerve all to be hanged: and many ſuch like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
would often fall from her.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the reſt, one ſpeech of hers was moſt notorious, and
hath reſted in the memory of ſome Gentlewomen, and others that
heard her when ſhe ſpake it; that being in company with her,
they fell to diſcourſe of the preſent miſeries of the Kingdome, by
theſe warres; and ſome ſpoke againſt the <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> and the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi>
in the Kings Army; Whereupon this Mrs. <hi>Haugton</hi> ſaid lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
leſſe againſt the <hi>Roundheads</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> and ſhe ſaid the
King was in the right againſt them; ſhe was replyed to, that thoſe
called <hi>Roundheads</hi> were honeſt men, and in the rght way of walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
and living like the people of Ged, and ſutable to the profeſſion
of Chriſtians: And withall wiſhing, if it pleaſed God, that ſhe
had her eyes opened, and was ſuch a Roundhead. No ſaith ſhe, I
had rather have no head, nor life: I nor any of mine, I hope will
ever be ſuch. Anſwer was made her, that her children if ſhe had
any, might (if God ſo pleaſe) have their eyes opened; and ſee that
good which ſhe is ignorant of. Mrs. <hi>Haughton</hi> made anſwer again
in theſe words: <hi>I pray God, that rather than I ſhall be a Roundhead,
or bear a Roundhead, I may bring forth a Childe without a head.</hi>
This was a fearfull ſaying, and taken notice of by divers of her
neighbours that heard her ſpeak it. And this many who know it,
do apprehend, might be a great meanes to provoke God to ſhew
ſuch a teſtimony of his diſpleaſure againſt her, by cauſing her to
bring forth this Monſter, whoſe Picture is in the Title-page of
this Book.</p>
            <p>4. Now for teſtimony of the truth of this, we ſhall give it
you in Order thus:</p>
            <p>Her Neighbours who heard her ſpeak the aforeſaid words, have
been with Mr. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> the Miniſter of the Pariſh of <hi>Kirkham,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113459:4"/>
where ſhe was brought to bed of this Monſter, and where it was
buried alſo, and it was told to ſome of the Committee of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
what had happened and that ſhe had ſpoke thoſe words. And
after that ſhe was with childe, and delivered of the Monſter, one
Widdow <hi>Gattaker</hi> the Midwife, formerly wife to Mr. <hi>Gattaker,</hi>
ſometimes Vicat of the ſaid Pariſh; ſhe being a godly woman,
could not be eaſed in her minde, untill ſhe had diſcharged her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
in making it known to Mr. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> the Miniſter afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid;
That ſhe had brought the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Haughton</hi> to bed of a
Monſter, which had no head; declaring her opinion, that ſhe veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
believed that it was the hand of God upon her, for thoſe impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations
ſhe wiſhed upon her ſelf, as is before expreſt: The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
he ſpoke of it to others, and ſo did the Midwife alſo, which
made it to be ſpread up and down the Country, ſo that it came to
the eares of ſome of the Committee; And for the further ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
of the truth thereof, Collonel <hi>More</hi> an honeſt godly
Gentleman, a Member of the Houſe of Commons, and one of the
Committee being there, it was deſired he ſhould ſend a Letter to
Mr. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> the Miniſter of the Pariſh, to know the certainty of
it, whether it was truth or not; which Letter was writ, and by
him ſent accordingly. And Mr. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> receiving the ſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
ſent for the Midwife about it, and ſhe ſtill confirmed what ſhe
ſaid before, yet for better ſatisfaction, Mr. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> cauſed the
grave to be opened, and the childe to be taken up, and laid to view,
and found there a body without an head, as the Midwife had ſaid;
onely the childe had a face upon the breaſt of it, as you may ſee in
the portraicture.</p>
            <p>The Certificate was ſhewed before divers of the Committee,
and by Collonel <hi>More</hi> a Member of the Houſe of Commons,
brought up to <hi>London,</hi> and ſhewed to divers of the Houſe; who
have commanded it to be printed, that ſo all the Kingdome might
ſee the hand of God herein; to the comfort of his people, and the
terrour of the wicked that deride and ſcorn them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:113459:5"/>
            <head>A Copie of a Certificate under the hand
of Mr. Edward Fleetwood Miniſter of Kirkham
Pariſh in Lancaſhire, concerning the
Monſter brought forth by Mrs. Haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton
a Papiſt, living in that
Pariſh.</head>
            <p>AS we muſt tell no lye, ſo we ſhould not conceal any truth; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
when it tends to Gods glory: There was a great Papist
and of great Parentage, within the Pariſh of <hi>Kirkham,</hi> and his wives
mother being of the ſame Religion, did uſually ſcoffe and mocke the
Roundheads, and in deriſion of Mr. <hi>Prinne,</hi> and others, cut off th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
the Cats eares, and called it by his name. But behold an example of
the juſtice and equity of God in his judgements: As <hi>Adonibezeck</hi>
was repaid in his own kinde: <hi>Haman</hi> hanged upon the ſame Gallowes
he had prepared for <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his Hoſte drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
in the Sea into which he had thought to have driven the Iſraelites,
And likewiſe one of the Popiſh Prelates, who ſaid he would not dine
before <hi>Ridley</hi> and <hi>Latimore</hi> were burnt, was burned in his own ent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails.
So (much what) alike, it fell out with this mans wiſe, a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh
creature, who being great with childe, when the time of her deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
came, ſhe brought forth a Monſtrous childe without an head<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
ugly and deformed, the portraicture whereof (as near as we could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineate)
is here deſcribed, and my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>EDWARD FLEETWOOD, Paſtor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
With the Midwife, and others who ſaw the
Childe taken out of its grave;
Witneſſes hereof.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
