<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, concerning diverse well affected persons and citizens of the City of London who are willing and ready to undertake and advance a considerable number of souldiers, and them to arme, maintaine, and pay for severall months ensuing, or during these times of danger, upon the publike faith. Die lunæ. 14. Novemb. 1642</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82636</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1364</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.5[104]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R211422</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870149</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160817</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A82636)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160817)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 245:669f5[104])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, concerning diverse well affected persons and citizens of the City of London who are willing and ready to undertake and advance a considerable number of souldiers, and them to arme, maintaine, and pay for severall months ensuing, or during these times of danger, upon the publike faith. Die lunæ. 14. Novemb. 1642</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Declaration signed: John Brown, Cler. Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Signed at bottom of text: Isacke Pennington, Major. John Langham, Thomas Andrews, Shreiffes [sic].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>London (England) --  Defenses --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="Parliamentary_declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:160817:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <head>A Declaration of the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning diverſe well affected perſons and Citizens of the City of London, who are willing and ready to undertake and advance a conſiderable number of Souldiers, and them to Arme, maintaine, and pay for ſeverall months enſuing, or du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring theſe times of danger, upon the publike Faith.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die Lunae.</hi> 14. <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas divers well-affected Perſons, Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and others, have advanced ſeverall great ſummes of money, and other ſupplies for the ſafety of the King, Parliament, and Kingdome, and alſo have ſet forth many Souldiers under the ſeverall Commands of their Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies the Earles of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Warwicke:</hi> Notwithſtanding all which ſaid former Advances, and for the better ſupply of the ſaid Forces, as alſo for the more ſure preſervation and ſafety of the King, Parliament, and City, which ſo much concernes the Publique. And no way to hinder or backward the ſaid former undertakings or intentions; divers of the ſaid well-affected Perſons, are and do declare themſelves yet willing and ready, further to undertake and advance a conſiderable number of Souldiers, and them to Arme, maintaine and pay for ſeverall moneths enſuing, or during theſe times of dangers and Diſtractions, for the purpoſes aforeſaid. Provided they may have the Publique Faith of the Kingdome for repayment of all ſuch ſummes of money, which they ſhall ſo advance by way of Loane. All which is Declared by the Lords and Commons in Parliament, to be an acceptable Service to the King, Parliament, and Kingdome, and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily tending to the preſervation of them. And doe therefore Order that all ſuch as ſhall fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Men, Money, Horſe or Armes for this Service, ſhall have the ſame fully Repayed againe, with intereſt for the forbearance thereof from the times disburſed: And for the true pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, doe hereby engage to all and every ſuch perſon and perſons the Publique Faith of the Kingdome. And doe further Order, that the Lord Major, and Sheriffes of <hi>London</hi> for the time being, ſhall by themſelves, and ſuch Sub-Committee as they ſhall appoint to take the ſaid Subſcriptions, who are to order the performance of this Service for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Brown, Cler. Parliament.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to an ordinance of Parliament bearing date the fourteenth day of this preſent Moneth of <hi>November</hi> 1642 concerning the advancing of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of Souldiers, by contribution of Money; and Armes, to be raiſed within this City, and liberties by the ſubſcriptions of perſons to be called upon in the ſeverall Wards and Pariſhes, for the perfecting of this neceſſary worke, and the furtherance of the ſame, being directed by the ſaid ordinance unto us the Major and Sheriffs of this City, and to ſuch ſubcommittee, as by us ſhall be thought fit, for the execution of the contents of the ſaid ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, we doe therefore hereby ordaine and appoint the ſeverall perſons here under men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned that is to ſay <hi>(Robert Sweet</hi> for <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gborne</hi> Ward. <hi>John Bellamie</hi> for <hi>Cornehill</hi> Ward. <hi>Hugh Smithſon</hi> for <hi>Cheap</hi> Ward. <hi>Richard Willet</hi> for <hi>Cordwinders</hi> Ward. <hi>Wylliam Walwin</hi> for <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey</hi> Ward. <hi>Haugan Hovell</hi> for <hi>Broadſtreete</hi> Ward. <hi>Chriſtopher Nicholſon</hi> for <hi>Caſtle-Bennets</hi> Ward. <hi>Miguel Styles</hi> for <hi>Candleweak</hi> Ward. <hi>John Hilliard</hi> for <hi>Dowgate</hi> Ward. <hi>Rich. Cotes</hi> for <hi>Alderſgate</hi> without. and <hi>John Leigh</hi> for <hi>Alderſgate</hi> within. <hi>Walter Boothby</hi> for <hi>Cripplegate</hi> Ward. <hi>Nicholas Gerrard</hi> for <hi>Breadſtreete</hi> Ward. <hi>Will.</hi> and <hi>Matthew Fox</hi> for <hi>Farington</hi> without. <hi>Tho. Lentall</hi> for <hi>Billingſgate</hi> Ward. <hi>Tho. Hutchins</hi> for <hi>B<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhopſgate</hi> Ward. <hi>Richard Finch</hi> for <hi>Queene-hithe</hi> Ward. <hi>Robert Meade</hi> for <hi>Walbrooke</hi> Ward. <hi>Will. Farrington</hi> for <hi>Port-Sokin</hi> Ward without. <hi>Marke Hilſley</hi> for <hi>Colemanſtreete</hi> Ward. <hi>John Dethick,</hi> for <hi>Limeſtr.</hi> Ward. <hi>John Kenricke</hi> for <hi>Tower</hi> Ward. <hi>Tho. Foote,</hi> for <hi>Bridge</hi> Ward. <hi>Francis Greeneway</hi> for <hi>Baſinghall</hi> Ward. <hi>Edward Vaughan</hi> for <hi>Farring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> within. <hi>Solomon Vandebrooke</hi> for the <hi>Dukes place,)</hi> and to any other Committes, that have not yet brought in their names unto you to be a generall Committee for the mannaging of this buſineſſe, and for the ſame to aſſemble themſelves together from time to time, keeping their Court at <hi>Weavers Hall,</hi> or where-elſe your ſelves ſhall finde moſt convenient, to conſider and conclude of thoſe things which may promote the expedition of this ſervice, to which purpoſe we give you by theſe preſents full power and authority together with the other treaſurers of ſeverall pariſhes to collect and receive all ſuch ſubſcriptions as ſhall be advanced for money and armes as aforeſaid, and that by monethly payments to begin from the firſt day of this preſent Moneth, and to deale with the Deputies, Common-councell men, Church-wardens and all others of the ſeverall Wards and Pariſhes within and about this City of <hi>London,</hi> and particularly with thoſe who have not yet promoted the ſubſcriptions in their Wards or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, nor have hitherto choſen any Treaſurers nor Committes for the furtherance of this worke; to call before you all ſuch perſons, and to preſſe them thereunto, by vertue of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Parliament, and of this our authority given unto you in this behalfe, for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, it will be convenient that the greateſt number of you ſhould be preſent at your Courts, however when there ſhall be a defect of the greater number, then whatſoever ſix per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of you at the leaſt ſhall debate and reſolve upon, ſhall paſſe for good, and be entred for an order, and for your eaſe and more free attendance upon the Committee Court. We give you power in your ſeuerall Pariſhes to chuſe and appoint ſuch perſon or perſons as you think meet together in the ſubſcriptions, and to bring in the ſame to you that are Treaſurers, as well as Committees.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>Iſacke Pennington, Major.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Shreiffes.</head>
                        <item>John Langham,</item>
                        <item>Thomas Andrews,</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
