<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties whole army in the west conquered. And all Sir Ralph Hoptons horse and armes delivered to Sir Thomas Fairfax: with the copies of the severall letters that passed between them. The articles tendred by the Generall, Sir Ralph Hoptons answer, with the conclusions and agreements of the commissioners. Upon what termes all their horse, in number 2000. and more, and all their armes, are surrendred to Sir Thomas Fairfax, besides 120. come in from Pendennis Castle, and the last news from Prince Charles. The taking of Truro, and the whole proceedings of the affairs in those parts. These letters are commanded to be printed, and are published according to order.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E328_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200671</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861351</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861351</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113484</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A84736)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113484)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E328[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties whole army in the west conquered. And all Sir Ralph Hoptons horse and armes delivered to Sir Thomas Fairfax: with the copies of the severall letters that passed between them. The articles tendred by the Generall, Sir Ralph Hoptons answer, with the conclusions and agreements of the commissioners. Upon what termes all their horse, in number 2000. and more, and all their armes, are surrendred to Sir Thomas Fairfax, besides 120. come in from Pendennis Castle, and the last news from Prince Charles. The taking of Truro, and the whole proceedings of the affairs in those parts. These letters are commanded to be printed, and are published according to order.</title>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
                  <author>Hopton, Ralph Hopton, Baron, 1598-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 15 [i.e. 13], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Matthew Walbancke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>16 March 1645 [i.e. 1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing has publication year 1645[6]; Thomason catalogue lists under 1646.</note>
                  <note>Page number 13 is misnumbered 15.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hopton, Ralph Hopton, --  Baron, 1598-1652 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113484:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>His Majeſties
Whole ARMY in the Weſt
Conquered. 
And all Sir <hi>Ralph Hoptons</hi> Horſe and
Armes delivered to
Sir THOMAS FAIRFAX:
With the Copies of the ſeverall Letters that
paſſed between them.
The Articles tendred by the Generall, Sir
<hi>Ralph Hoptons</hi> anſwer, with the Concluſions and
agreements of the Commiſſioners.
Upon what termes all their Horſe, in number
2000. and more, and all their Armes, are ſurrendred
to Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> beſides 120. come in
from Pendennis Caſtle, and the laſt news
from Prince CHARLES.
The taking of <hi>Truro,</hi> and the whole proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
of the affairs in thoſe parts.</p>
            <p>Theſe Letters are commanded to be printed, and are
publiſhed according to Order.</p>
            <p>LONDON,
Printed for <hi>Matthew Walbancke,</hi> 16 March 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:113484:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113484:2"/>
            <head>A Copy of a Letter ſent from Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas
Fairfax</hi> to the Lord <hi>Hopton.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="body_of_letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hrough the goodneſſe of God to his
people, and his juſt hand againſt
their Enemies, your forces being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
to ſuch condition, as (to my
ſence the ſame good hand of God, continuing
with us, wherin alone we truſt) they are not like
neither to have ſubſiſtence or ſhelter long where
they are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or to eſcape thence; nor (if they could)
have they whither to go for better. I have
thought good (for prevention of more blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,
or of further hardſhip or extremity to any,
but ſuch whoſe hearts God ſhall harden to their
own deſtruction, to ſend you theſe Summons;
For your ſelf and them to lay down Arms, and
withall a tender of ſuch conditions, upon a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
ſurrender and ingagement, never more to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113484:3"/>
bear Arms againſt the Parliament, as may be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
then any thing they can rationally expect
by ſtanding out.</p>
               <p>1 Therefore, to the Souldiery in generally
Engliſh and Forraigners, I ſhall grant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
to go beyond ſea, or to their homes in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
as they pleaſe; and to ſuch Engliſh as ſhall
chuſe to live at home, my Protection for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
of their perſons, and for the immunity of
their eſtates, from all plunder or violence of
Souldiers, and all to go their waies with what
they have, ſaving Horſes and Arms<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2 But for
Officers in Commiſſion, and Gentlemen of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
I ſhall allow them to go with Horſes for
themſelves and one ſervant or more, ſuitable to
their quality, and with Arms befitting Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
in a condition of peace, and ſuch Officers
as would go beyond the Sea for other ſervice,
to take with them their Arms and full number
of Horſes anſwerable to their Offices<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3 To all
Troopers, and the inferiour ſort of Horſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,
bringing in and delivering up their Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
and Arms, twenty ſhillings a man, in lieu of
their Horſes, to carry them home. 4 To Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
Gentlemen of conſiderable Eſtates, my Paſſe
and Recommendation to the Parliament for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113484:3"/>
their moderate compoſition. 5 Laſtly, for your
ſelf, beſides what is meerly implyed to you in
common with others, you may be aſſured of
ſuch mediation to the Parliament, in your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half,
both from my ſelf and others, as for one,
whom for perſonall worth and many vertues,
but eſpecially for your care of, and moderation
towards the Countrie, we honour and eſteem
above any other of your party, whoſe Errour,
ſuppoſing you more ſwayed with Principles of
honour and conſcience then others, we moſt
pitty, and whoſe happineſſe, ſo far as conſiſtent
with the publike welfare, we ſhould delight in,
more then in your leaſt ſuffering. Theſe things,
not from any need or other ends then humane
and chriſtian, having offered, I leave to your
conſideration and theirs whom it may concern<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
deſiring your and their ſpeedy reſolving which
I pray may be ſuch, as ſhall be moſt for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
of God, the peace and welfare of this poor
Kingdom, and for your and their good, ſo far
as may ſtand therewith; and having herein diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged,
as I conceive, the duty of an honeſt
man, a Souldier, and a Chriſtian, if God ſhall ſee
it good to let your hearts be hardened againſt
your own peace, I ſhall, though with ſome regret
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113484:4"/>
to that ill, which ſhall inſue to any, yet with
cheerfulnes and rejoycing at the righteous judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of God, purſue my charge and truſt for
the publike in another way, not doubting of
the ſame preſence and bleſſing which God hath
hitherto vouchſafed in the ſame Cauſe, to the
weak endeavours of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Tho. Fairfax.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>5. March 1645.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="summary_of_battle">
               <head>A Liſt of the particulars of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> his Victory
at Caſtle, Dennis, March 8.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Major Generall <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Dutton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Shore.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Farmer.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>29 of the Princes Life-guard,
whoſe names are</head>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Iohn Wood.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>An. Dickſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>George Carey.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Rich. Creſwell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Tho. Pearce.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Richard Rich.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Rich Sargeant.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Simon Wilmot.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Tho. Maddock.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Philip Morris.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Iohn Stephens.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Iohn Taylor.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Iemery Boughs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Walt. Weyfield.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Charles Bryre.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Rob. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>il.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Mark Shaw.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Iohn Thomas.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Henry Pecket.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Iohn Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>t.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Iohn Richard.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Iohn Iohnſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Wil. Welch.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Laurence Dutton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Edw. Reynolds.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Iohn Clark.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M. <hi>Tho. Pearce.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Tho. Sands.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Richard Trew.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Five of the Lord Clevelands
Life-guard,</head>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Iames Sout.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Rich. Wilkinſon,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Hen. Timpſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Philip Spene.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Rich. Oliver.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>Lieutenant <hi>Linhouſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Coronet <hi>Ellis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>14 Officers more.</item>
                  <item>180 Horſe</item>
                  <item>100 Priſoners.</item>
                  <item>40 Slain.</item>
                  <item>The Major-Generall mortally
wounded.</item>
                  <item>800 Routed.</item>
                  <item>4 Of our men ſlain.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113484:4"/>
            <head>A Letter from the Generalls head
Quarters, to a Member of the
Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <div type="body_of_letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall continue the Intelligence of
the proceedings of this Army ſince
my laſt from Bodman of the 8.
inſtant, wherein you had the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
of the taking above two
hundred of the Enemies Horſe
neere Caſtle-Dennis, on Munday
March 9. the whole Army of Horſe and Foot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced
from Bodman, and the Townes adjacent
to Tregny and Probus, within three or foure miles
of Truro; the march being not aboue fourteene
miles. Upon the comming of our forlorne hope
neere Probus, the Enemies forlorne ſtood in a
peaceable poſture, not offering to charge; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
whereof being demanded; they ſaid, There was
a Ceſſation of Armes on both Parties, and they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
there would be a Peace; Comiſſary Generall
<hi>Ireton</hi> and other Officers there had much adoe to
perſwade them out of their miſtake; yet told them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113484:5"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey were ſo poſſeſſed, they would not take
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vantage if they made haſt away; they retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rankes for that civility and retreated. This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
was firſt raiſed amongſt them out of a Politick
reſpect, that if our men had taken advantage, they
might have a plea that we kept no faith or ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and ſo make them the more deſperate, but
it wrought a contrary effect; for that night, and
every day ſince, many of the Enemy come in with
their Horſes and Armes unto the Generall. About
twelve of the Clocke that night, a Trumpeter
came from the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> to deſire a Parley, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying
his great inclination to make a ſpeedy end:
On Tueſday March the tenth, about three of the
Clock in the morning the Trumpeter was ſent back
with our Commiſſioners names. <hi>viz.</hi> Commiſſary
Generall <hi>Ireton,</hi> Colonell <hi>Lambert,</hi> controuler of
the Ordnance, Commiſſary <hi>Staines,</hi> and Colonell
St. <hi>Aubine;</hi> the place for Treaty was at Treſtlea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
Bridges neere Truro, at a Conſtables houſe, and
to begin at nine of the Clocke this morning, to
continue three houres; but the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> ſent
not the names of his Commiſſioners till after nine
a Clock, but our Army, Horſe and Foot (having
a Rende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vouz in Serue Fields on the Eaſt of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,
at ſeven this morning were by ten of the Clock
marched within two miles of Truro: by this the
Lord <hi>Hoptons</hi> Trumpeter came with their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners
names, <hi>viz.</hi> Col. <hi>Goring,</hi> Col. <hi>Pont,</hi> Col.
<hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> Col. <hi>Trever,</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Prideaux,</hi> the
Kings high Sheriffe of this County, to countervaile
Col. St. <hi>Aubine,</hi> the Enemy further deſigned that
<pb facs="tcp:113484:5"/>
Col. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> a French man might be added, which
was granted, &amp; a Capt. <hi>Herne</hi> ppoynted on our ſide,
and the ſafe convoyes from both Generals, ſent to
each other about 11 clocke, with a Letter from the
General to the Lord <hi>Hopton,</hi> to ſignifie to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
that he intended to quarter that night with his
army at <hi>Truro,</hi> and therefore deſired, that his forces
might draw out, and that in regard it would be late
before the buſineſſe be ended, the bounds ſet for the
quarters of both Armies, there might be a Ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of armes, till to morrow morning at ſix of the
clock, before which time I doubt not but the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
will be determined, and a good end made of
the troubles in theſe parts, by an aſſent to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions
which I ſent to you, which will not only
conduce much to the ſetling of the Peace of the
Kingdome, but afford a good number of horſes and
recruits for the publique ſervice, the enemies field<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forces
ſcattered, and the joyning of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> if they
ſhould land, with ſo conſiderable a body of Horſe
wil be prevented. We are this Evening entred <hi>Truro,</hi>
where we found many of the enemies forces drunk,
which we were contented to drive to their quarters,
though many were unwilling to leave their good
Liquor: about halfe a mile before we came to this
Towne, we had a ſight of <hi>Pendenis</hi> caſtle 8 miles off.
Sir, within few dayes after this, I ſhall acquaint you
with the iſſue of this Treaty: till when, I always reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant,
W. C.</signed>
                  <dateline>Truro, <date>March, the 10. 1645.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>I have ſent you incloſed, the Lord Hoptons Anſwers to
to the Generals Propoſitions, I had not time to Coppy out
the Reply, and other Letters of Intercourſe, which you ſhall
have ſo ſoone as I can have leiſure.</p>
               </postscript>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113484:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:113484:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:113484:7"/>
               <head>A Copy of Sir <hi>Ralph Hoptons</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
to Sir THOMAS FAIRFAX'S
LETTER.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours, bearing date the fifth of this
moneth, wherein I muſt acknowledge much
kindneſſe from you, and a very Chriſtian conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
of ſparing of blood: But one thing
there is, I am confident, you have too much honour
to expect from me, which is, that to avoyd any
danger, or to enjoy any worldly advantage; I will
renounce my Maſters Service, to whom, I am both
a ſworne Subject, and a ſworne Servant, that I muſt
profeſſe; I am reſolved, to undergoe all fortunes
with him, and if there ſhall be cauſe, to ſuffer any
thing, rather then in the leaſt poynt to taint my
honour in that particular, and I hope, there is not
a man of any conſideration in that Army, under
my command, that is not ſo reſolved; yet in all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
and honourable wayes, to procure the Peace of
this Kingdome, and the ſhedding of Chriſtian
blood, and take God to witneſſe, I am, and ſtill
have beene moſt deſirous: And I heare, from good
hands, our Gracious Soveraigne, is at preſent ſo
farre adviſed in a Treatie with the Parliament, as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113484:7"/>
that he hath promiſed to paſſe 14 of the principall
of their Bils propoſed, whereof the intruſting the
<hi>Militia</hi> for ſeven yeares, in hands agreed betweene
them is one. I deſire you to deale freely with me in
that particular, for if that be ſo, it will ſhew the
labour of further Treatie; being, for my part, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
to obey whatſoever his Majeſtie ſhall agree un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to:
God indeed hath of late humbled us with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
ill ſucceſſes, which I acknowledge as a very cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
evidence of his juſt judgement againſt us for
our perſonall crimes. Yet, give me leave to ſay,
your preſent proſperitie cannot be ſo certaine an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
of his being altogether pleaſed with you.
It is true, we are reduced to a lower condition then
we have beene, yet have we a gallant body of Horſe,
that being preſerved to a generall accord, may be
for good uſe againſt our common Enemies, and
being otherwiſe preſt, I may ſay it without vanity,
want not a reſolution, at leaſt to ſell our ſelves at a
deare rate againſt any odds: Your Propoſitions,
though they be not wholly to be conſented unto,
yet if a generall accord, much more deſirable, be
not in a likely forwardneſſe to prevent them, I ſhall
b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> willing, that eight Commanders of ours, with
three Countery Gentlemen, give a meeting as ſoon
as you pleaſe, to an equall number of yours at any
indifferent place, to conſult of that great buſineſſe,
and to conclude of ſome Propoſitions that
may be Reaſonable and Honourable for both
p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rts, wherein, I hope, God will ſo bleſſe our
cleare intentions, as may procure a probable
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113484:8"/>
inducement to a generall Peace, according to the
unfained deſire of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Servant
RALPH HOPTON.</signed>
                  <date>March 8.
1645.</date>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>A parte of yours falling upon a guard of ours
yeſterday, it is likely they have taken ſome priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners;
I deſire the favour from you, to receive a liſt
of them by this Trumpeter, till I receive a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
Anſwer to the contents of this Letter, I ſhall
not permit any offence to attempt any thing upon
any of your Forces.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Servant
RALPH HOPTON.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113484:8"/>
            <head>A Letter from the Generals head
Quarters, to a Member of the Houſe of
COMMONS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis laſt Night there came a Letter from the
Lord <hi>Hopton,</hi> ſignifying, that when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
the place of Treaty, he hoped it ſhould
have beene at a reaſonable diſtance betweene both
Quarters: but in regard our Army was advanced to
<hi>Truro,</hi> it would be inconvenient to have the Treaty
three Miles within our Quarters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereupon <hi>Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi>
was appointed to be the place, and our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners
wee removed laſt night from <hi>Treſillian</hi> to
St. Clemence, a mile and a halfe hence, and both
Commiſſioners are to meete this day at <hi>Truro.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. C.</signed>
               <dateline>Truro, <date>March, 11. 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:113484:9"/>
            <head>A Letter from the Scout-Maſter
Generals Quarters.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>OUr Commiſſioners and the Lord <hi>Hoptons</hi> have
now agreed, and all Colonels, Lieutenant
Colonels, Serjeant Majors, and Captaines, are to
March away with every field Officer two Horſes,
and every Captaine one, and ſo alſo late the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
of the Army to march away with every one
a Horſe, but all others without Horſe and Armes,
and thoſe who will to goe home, and others are to
goe beyond the Seas, and all their Ammunition
is ours, beſides <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Men and Armes, came into
us laſt Night from <hi>Peudennis,</hi> where they are in as
reall a feare, and much diſtracted, as theſe in the
Field were, where they are like men agaz'd, and
halfe frighred out of their wits: the Generall
Quartred in <hi>Truro,</hi> the head Quarters this light
Nights where was quartred alſo Colonel <hi>Porteſcue,</hi>
Colonel <hi>Hammond,</hi> and Colonel <hi>ingleſby,</hi> with their
Regiments; the Prince is ſtill in the Iſly of <hi>Sylly,</hi>
from whence divers have come away from him,
making ſome excuſes to get away, and glad if they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113484:9"/>
can procure any way; the Generall is much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
with many Tickets hourely comming to him,
for Perſons of ſeverall degrees to come in: In the
Articles it is agreed, to permit Forty Horſe to
goe to <hi>Oxford,</hi> the Army would have had 500. but
that would not be granted; at laſt they accepted
of 40. and truely I believe the buſineſſe of the Weſt
will be now but ſhort, ſo as that wee may have it
in a good poſture, that the Country may ſecure
themſelues. This day we are drawing to a Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz,
where I believe divers of our men will be
mounted on the Enemies Horſe: wee ſhall have
compleat 2000. of the Enemies, and thoſe very
good ones to mount our men on, that is the leaſt,
befides thoſe allowed to the Field Officers, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,
and Miniſters, which doth ſo trouble the
Enemies Officers (eſpecially the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi>
and ſuch who thought to have advanced themſelves
by the ruins of this Kingdome) that now they did
(ſome of them) cry like Children that have bin
whipped, and wring their hands and vex extreamely,
wiſhing they had never come into <hi>England;</hi> wee
ſhall now conſider whether it be thought fit to
goe againſt <hi>Pendennis,</hi> or leave it to the Country
and returne.</p>
            <closer>So I reſt, <signed>yours to command, J. S,</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Truro,</hi> 
                  <date>the 12. of
<hi>March,</hi> 1645. 10 a Clock.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
