<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sir Thomas Fairfax letter to the Honoble William Lenthal Esq; Speaker of the Honorable House of Commons. Concerning all the passages of his army since his advance from Exeter, and the manner of routing the Princes and the Lord Hoptons forces at Torrington, together with all the particulars in that expedition. Also another letter from a gentleman of quality, of the whole passages of this great victory. Both which were read in the House of Commons. Ordered by the Commons assembled in Parliament, that these letters be forthwith printed and published: H: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
            <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84825</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F195</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E324_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200618</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861319</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861319</idno>
            <idno type="VID">163958</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A84825)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 163958)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E324[15] or 247:E324[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sir Thomas Fairfax letter to the Honoble William Lenthal Esq; Speaker of the Honorable House of Commons. Concerning all the passages of his army since his advance from Exeter, and the manner of routing the Princes and the Lord Hoptons forces at Torrington, together with all the particulars in that expedition. Also another letter from a gentleman of quality, of the whole passages of this great victory. Both which were read in the House of Commons. Ordered by the Commons assembled in Parliament, that these letters be forthwith printed and published: H: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
                  <author>Rushworth, John, 1612?-1690.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edw. Husband, Printer to the Honorable House of Commons, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Golden Dragon in Fleetstreet, neer the Inner-Temple,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Feb. 24. 1645. [i.e. 1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The letter from the "Gentleman of quality" is dated and signed at end: Torrington, Feb. 19. twelve at night. J.R. [i.e. John Rushworth].</note>
                  <note>Wing has publication year 1645[6]; Thomason catalogue lists under 1646.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Torrington (England), Battle of, 1646 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:163958:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> LETTER To the Hono<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> 
               <hi>William Lenthal</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Speaker of the Honorable Houſe of Commons. CONCERNING All the Paſſages of his Army ſince his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance from <hi>Exeter,</hi> and the manner of Routing the Princes and the Lord <hi>Hoptons</hi> Forces at Torrington, Together with all the particulars in that Expedition. ALSO Another LETTER from a Gentleman of quality, of the whole paſſages of this great Victory. Both which were read in the Houſe of COMMONS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, That theſe</hi> Letters <hi>be forthwith printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed:</hi> H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edw. Husband,</hi> Printer to the Honorable Houſe of Commons, and are to be ſold at his Shop at the ſigne of the Golden Dragon in Fleetſtreet, neer the Inner-Temple. <hi>Feb.</hi> 24. 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:163958:2"/>
            <head>To the Honorable <hi>William Lenthal</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Speaker of the Honorable Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. Speaker,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lymouth being ſet free, and Da|
rtmouth taken, I ſent Col. <hi>Hamond</hi> with part of the foot to poſſeſs certain houſes near <hi>Exeter</hi> for the blocking of it upon the Weſt ſide of the River (as formerly I had done on the Eaſt) and lay with the reſt of the Army, ſo as to countenance both that work, and the raiſing of ſome Forces in the Southams to lie about Totneſs for the ſecuring of that Countrey, and to keep the Enemy from coming of that ſide of Devonſhire again, when the Army ſhould remove to the other. Theſe two things, with the continual foul weather at that time, and the abſence of Col. <hi>Cook</hi> with ſo many of the Horſe, ocacſioned my ſtay thereabouts above a Fortnight, in which time the Houſes being competently Fortified, and the Forces raiſing in the Southams in good forwardneſſe, I drew the Army up towards Crediton, with purpoſe to advance into the North of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhire to diſlodge the Enemies Horſe from their Quarters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, and force them into Cornwal, and to endeavour the further clearing of that part of Devonſhire alſo, either by the taking of Barnſtable, or by blocking of it up, and raiſing a Force in that well-affected Corner to keep it in, ſo as (having all clear or made faſt behinde me) I might the better follow the remaining Field forces of the Enemy into Cornwal: And to continue the blocking up of <hi>Exeter</hi> on the Eaſt ſide, I left Sir <hi>Hardres Waller</hi> with three Regiments of Foot, and a Regiment of Horſe of this Army, and advanced with ſeven Regiments of Foot, five Regiments of Horſe, and five Troops of Dragoons, (the reſt of the Horſe and Dragoons being abſent with Col: <hi>Cook</hi> in Dorſetſhire, but then ſent for to come up) when I was reſolved upon my advance this way, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy at the ſame time advanced out of Cornwal with all the Foot they could make to Torrington, about which their Horſe did lie before, and began to fortifie the Town. Their intentions therein (as we conceived, and do ſince further finde) were by the advantage of this place, and their Garriſon of Barnſtaple ſo near it,
<pb facs="tcp:163958:2"/>
to make this part of <hi>Devonſhire</hi> more ſurely theirs, &amp; more difficult for us to come into, and lying ſo much the nearer to <hi>Exeter</hi> (againſt which they ſuppoſed this Army wholly ingaged) to take their beſt advantages: From hence, and from Chimleigh, which they meant alſo to have poſſeſſed, to relieve Exeter on the North ſide, or diſturb us in the Siege; and 'tis probable, they might have a further pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in their poſture here to ſecure the Landing of Iriſh or Welch Supplies ſo much the forwarder towards the Eaſt.</p>
            <p>On Saturday laſt, I advanced from <hi>Crediton</hi> to <hi>Chimleigh,</hi> where by many Priſoners taken I was Informed, That the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> had hereabouts Four thouſand Horſe, and Three thouſand Foot; we believed them to be about Two thouſand Foot or upwards, and Three thouſand Horſe. The extreme foulneſſe of weather that day and next, occaſioned me not to advance from about <hi>Chimleigh</hi> for the next night, ſave only one Foot quarter, and an Horſe Guard advanced to <hi>Ring-aſh,</hi> three miles towards the Enemy, to ſecure a Rendezvouz ſo much the nearer to them for the day following: I underſtood by the beſt Intelligence, That the Enemy was reſolved to make good their ſtation, and ſet their reſt upon it to fight us there, if we would come up to them: And truly, men in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition could not hope (all things conſidered) to have more for it. Their Horſe in number ſuperior to what I brought up with me, their Foot (as I finde ſince) not much inferior; and if they could with all their force make good this Town, and put us to lie in the field, (there being no Villages near it that could ſhelter the Army; the wet weather continuing which was then moſt likely) would have forc'd us to draw back, and make our Fire-arms little uſeful, either for aſſault or defence; and beſides, we were like for matter of Proviſions to be forced to draw off firſt, they having both by their poſture (with the plentiful Countrey of Cornwal behinde them, and a River at their backs ſecuring alſo a good part of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhire unto them) and by their ſtrength of Horſe much advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for longer ſubſiſtence then we; and we (by the barrenneſſe of the place where we muſt have lien before them, eſpecially for Horſe-meat, their Garriſon of <hi>Barnſtaple</hi> lying partly behinde us, their Horſe more numerous then ours. which might with ſtronger parties cut off our ſupplies) had had little poſſibility to ſubſiſt long before them. Theſe conſiderations we had in our eye to diſcourage us from going on (as I believe they had to incourage them to ſtand) yet on the other ſide finding, That by reaſon of the barrenneſs and long exhauſting of our Quarters behinde us, we could neither keep
<pb facs="tcp:163958:3"/>
our Horie ſo cloſe together as to lie ſafe ſo near the Enemy, nor indeed finde ſubſiſtence for the Army, either where we were, or in any other Quarters more backward, (where we could lye, ſo as to ſecure the Siege of <hi>Exeter</hi> from relief) and upon all conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, conceiving the Affairs of the Kingdom did require us, and God by all did call us to make a preſent attempt upon the Enemy, we reſolved to go on to try what God would do for us, and truſt him for weather, ſubſiſtence, and all things. Accordingly on Monday morning I drew out the Army to an early Rendezvouz at <hi>Ring-aſh</hi> (within ſix miles of the Enemy) the weather ſtill continued very wet, and ſo by all ſignes, was like to hold, till we were advanced from the Rendezvouz; but ſuddenly when we were upon march, it beyond all expectation grew fair and dry, and ſo continued, whereas we had ſcarce ſeen one fair blaſt for many dayes before. The Enemy (as we underſtood by the way) had all their Horſe drawn together about <hi>Torrington,</hi> and with their Foot prepared to defend the Town, which they had fortified with good Barra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadoes of Earth, caſt up at every Avenue, and a competent Line patcht up round about it, their Horſe ſtanding by to flanck the ſame, and ſome within to ſcowre the ſtreets. Our Forlorn hope had Order to advance to <hi>Stephenſon</hi> Park (about a mile from the Town) and there to ſtay for the drawing up of the Army, there being no other place fit for that purpoſe nearer to the Town on that ſide we came on: But when we came near, we underſtood the Enemy had with Two hundred Dragoons poſſeſt the Houſe in the Park, and were Fortifying of it, being of it ſelf very ſtrong: But upon our nearer approach, their Dragoons quitted the Houſe, and our Forlorn hope falling on them, took many Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and purſuing them near the Town, were ingaged ſo far as they could not well draw back to the Park, which occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſending up of ſtronger parties to make them good where they were, or bring them off; and at laſt (there being ſome fear the Enemy would draw about them, and hem them in, Col: <hi>Hamond</hi> was ſent up with three Regiments of Foot (being his own, Col: <hi>Harlows,</hi> and mine) and ſome more horſe to lye for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves unto them, by which time the night was grown on, ſo as it was not thought fit, unleſſe the Enemy appeared to be drawing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to attempt any thing further upon the town till morning, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard none of us knew the ground nor th'advantages or diſadvanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of it; But about 9. of the clock, there being ſome apprehenſion of the Enemies drawing away, by reaſon of their drawing back
<pb facs="tcp:163958:3"/>
ſome out-guards, ſmall parties were ſent out towards the towns end, to make a certain diſcovery, which going very neer their works before the Enemy made any firing, but being at laſt entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a great volley of ſhot, and thereupon ſuppoſed to be inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; ſtronger parties were ſent up to relieve them, and after them the three Regiments went up for Reſerves, till at laſt they fell on in earneſt; after very hot firings, our men coming up to the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racadoes and Line, the diſpute continued long at puſh of Pike, and with But-ends of Muskets, until at laſt it pleaſed God to make the Enemy flye from their works, and give our men the entrance. After which, our men were twice repulſed by their horſe, and almoſt all driven out again, but col: <hi>Hamond</hi> (with ſome other officers &amp; a few Souldiers) made a ſtop at the Barracadoes, and ſo making good their Reentrance, rallyed their men, and went on again (Major <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phens</hi> with their Forlorn of horſe coming ſeaſonably up to ſecond them) The Enemies foot ran ſeveral wayes, moſt of them leaving their Arms, but moſt of their Officers, with aſſiſtance of horſe, made good their own Retreat out of the Town towards the Bridge, and taking advantage of ſtrait paſſages to make often ſtands againſt our men, gave time for many of their foot to get away over the Bridge. Their horſe without the Town (after ſome attempts at other Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues to have broke in again upon us being repulſed, at laſt went all away over another Bridge, and at ſeveral other paſſes of the River, and all fell Weſtward; the ground, where their horſe had ſtood, and the Bridge they went over lying ſo beyond the Town, as our horſe could not come at them, but through the Town, which (by reaſon of ſtrait paſſage through ſeveral Barracadoes was very tedious, by means whereof, and of the continued ſtrait Lanes the Enemy had to Retreat by after they were over the River (as alſo by th'advantage of the night, and by their perfect knowledge of the country, and of eſcape, and our utter ignorance therein) our horſe could do little execution upon the purſuit, but parties being ſent out ſeveral wayes to follow them (as thoſe diſadvantages would admit) did the beſt they could, and brought back many priſoners and horſes; we took many priſoners in the Town, who being put into the Church, where the Enemies Magazine lay (of above Eighty barrels of powder, as is reported, beſides other Ammunition) either purpoſely by ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate priſoner, or caſually by ſome Souldier, the powder was fired, whereby the Church was quite blown up, the priſoners and moſt of our men that guarded them were killed, and overwhelmed in the ruines, the houſes of the Town ſhaken and ſhattered, and our men
<pb facs="tcp:163958:4"/>
all the Town over much indangered by the ſtones, Timber and Lead, which with the blaſt were carryed up very high, and ſcatter'd in great abundance all the Town over, and beyond, yet it pleaſed God that very few of our men were ſlain or hurt thereby (ſave thoſe in the Church only) our loſſe of men otherwiſe in this ſervice was ſmall, though many wounded, it being an hotter ſervice then any ſtorm this Army hath before been upon, wherein God gave our men great reſolution, and Col: <hi>Hamond</hi> eſpecially, with other Officers engaged with him, behaved themſelves with much cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and diligence recovering the ground after their men were twice repulſed; of priſoners taken in this ſervice, about two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred were blown up, two hundred have taken up Arms with us, and above 200 more common Souldiers remain priſoners, beſides many Officers, Gentlemen and Servants, not many ſlain, but their foot ſo diſperſed, as that of about Three thouſand, (which the moſt credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſons do affirm they had here, and we finde by a Liſt taken among the Lo: <hi>Hoptons</hi> papers themſelves did accompt them more) we cannot hear of above four hundred that they carried off with them into Cornwal, whither their horſe alſo are gone, being much broken and diſperſed as well as their foot. By the conſiderations and circumſtances in this buſineſſe which I have here touch'd upon, you will perceive whoſe hand it was that lead us to it, and gave ſuch ſucceſſe in it. And truly there were many more evident appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the good hand of God therein then I can ſet forth, let all the honour be to him alone for ever, being deſirous (as God ſhall ſee it good, and further enable me) to improve th'advantage of this ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to the utmoſt. The next day having ſent ſome Regiments of horſe and foot to advance unto quarters up towards Holſworthy to ſet the Enemy more home into Cornwal, and with more terrour upon them: I ſent alſo one Regiment of foot with ſome horſe back towards Barnſtable, to poſſeſſe the Earl of Bathes houſe at N. Tave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock, about a mile from Barnſtable on this ſide the River, whereby that Garriſon will be eaſily kept in on this ſide, and I ſhall further try what may be done upon it other wayes, while the Army takes a little reſt hereabouts, which the unſeaſonable marches, miſerable quarters, and hard duty both horſe and foot for many dayes have been put unto do neceſſarily require: But I conceive, that ſo ſoon as the Army can be fitted for the purpoſe, it would be beſt to follow the Enemy home, and throughly into Cornwal, the breaking of that body of horſe that's left there being the likelyeſt means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent or diſcourage the landing of any Forreign forces in theſe
<pb facs="tcp:163958:4"/>
parts, or the raiſing of any more out of Cornwal. In order to which, I muſt earneſtly recommend to your care two things eſpecially, the one, To provide by the diſpoſal of your Forces in the Midland parts, that by Excurſions from <hi>Oxford</hi> hitherward I may not be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from proſecution of the work in Cornwal, to ſend again that way; nor the ſieges of Exeter and Barnſtable diſturbed when I am ingaged further Weſt: The other, that Money may be ſpeeded (if any wayes poſſible, but for one moneth or ſix weeks) to enable the horſe as well as foot, to pay quarters in Cornwal, whereby th'oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions that people might make would in all likelyhood be taken off, and their affections or good opinions gained, to make them helpful to us againſt their preſent oppreſſors.</p>
            <p>There came unto me this day a yong man from about Truro, who certifieth me, That Sir <hi>Walter Dudley</hi> came very lately from France, to let thoſe about the Prince know, That if there were an abſolute neceſſity, they could bring over their men from France with a fair wind, to be here by the middle of the next moneth; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing, That they had neer Eight thouſand foot, and a thouſand horſe in readineſſe, and three moneths pay provided for them, beſides Ten thouſand pounds in Bullion daily expected, a Mint being ready to coyn the ſame: But yet intimated a conveniency in the giving a little more time for their coming over; whereupon Sir <hi>Iohn Culpeper</hi> was to go in all haſte for France upon Friday laſt and is ſuppoſed on purpoſe, either to haſten all or a good part of thoſe Forces over. I think it will be very good, that as much ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping as may be obtained be haſtened to thoſe parts; I ſhall upon this Information, and the good ſucceſſe God hath been pleaſed to give us, ſo to diſpoſe of the Army, as may moſt effectually conduce to a ſpeedy and thorough ſettlement of theſe Weſtern parts of the Kingdom. Therefore I deſire you again to have a ſpecial care, that the Forces about Oxford be not permitted to range into theſe parts, when the Army is like to be ingaged ſo far Weſt, leſt it occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the diverſion of our Forces, and hinder the accompliſhment of that we deſire to effect. I remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant,
T: FAIRFAX.</signed>
               <dateline>Great Torrington, <date>Feb. 19. 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:163958:5"/>
            <head>To the Honorable <hi>William Lenthal</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Speaker of the Honorable Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Suppoſe before the Date of this Letter, you have received my former Letter of the Engagement of this Army and <hi>Hoptons</hi> at <hi>Torrington</hi> on Monday night laſt, where we took Six hundred Priſoners, beſides Officers, near Two hundred Priſoners blown up with <hi>Haptons</hi> Magazine, ſet on fire by one <hi>Wate</hi> a Northern man, for thirty pounds promiſed him by Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> as he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a little before his death: He died this day of the wounds he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Timber that fell upon him: The reſt of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners caſt him out for a Monſter, that would have deſtroyed all them his Friends. All the houſes in the Town are almoſt ſhattered in pieces with the blaſt. <hi>Hopton</hi> had his Horſe kill'd under in the ſtreet; and as we underſtand by thoſe that come to day from Cornwal, he is deſperately wounded; All his force are All-ago in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Cornwall, there they are in great Confuſion for fear of our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies advance, and an Army out of <hi>France:</hi> we had been there before now, but for ſetling the buſineſſe of <hi>Barnſtaple,</hi> by blocking it up cloſe: One Regiment is at the E: of <hi>Bathes</hi> houſe at <hi>Taveſtock</hi> within a mile of <hi>Barnſtaple;</hi> other Forces at <hi>Biddiford</hi> and other places. On Saturday or Sunday we are for Cornwal, Godwilling. By <hi>Hoptons</hi> Papers we perceive the Relief of <hi>Exeter</hi> was the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal end of his Motion to <hi>Torrington.</hi> The quantities of Powder and Salt to be left in <hi>Exeter,</hi> we finde in writings. We took eight Colours, one <hi>Hoptons</hi> own Colours with this Motto, <hi>I will ſtrive to help my Soveraign King.</hi> His Commiſſion from the King and Prince to be General, and <hi>Digbies</hi> to be Colonel General of the Forces before <hi>Plymouth,</hi> were alſo taken. Two Ships are come into <hi>Biddiford</hi> yeſterday; the one will prove Prize.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. R.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Torrington,</hi> 
                  <date>Feb. 19. twelve at night.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
