<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A faithfull and impartiall relation of what passed betweene His Majesty, and the commissioners from the two houses, both at the delivery of their votes for a personall treaty, and at their receiving His Majesties most gracious answer. By an eye and eare-witness, who not trusting to his memory, made use of his Pen: and for the truth of this relation, the relator appeales to the Commissioners themselves, or to any there present, who had the happinesse with him, to heare the most pious, most Christian expressions, of a most religious King.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.13[3]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202016</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862457</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862457</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162898</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A85065)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162898)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 246:669f13[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A faithfull and impartiall relation of what passed betweene His Majesty, and the commissioners from the two houses, both at the delivery of their votes for a personall treaty, and at their receiving His Majesties most gracious answer. By an eye and eare-witness, who not trusting to his memory, made use of his Pen: and for the truth of this relation, the relator appeales to the Commissioners themselves, or to any there present, who had the happinesse with him, to heare the most pious, most Christian expressions, of a most religious King.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August ye 22th 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Treaties --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:162898:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <head>A Faithfull and Impartiall Relation of what paſſed betweene His MAjESTY, And the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners from the two Houſes, both at the delivery of their Votes for a <hi>Perſonall Treaty,</hi> and at their receiving His MAjESTIES moſt Gracious Anſwer.</head>
            <byline>By an Eye and Eare-witneſſe, who not truſting to his Memory, made uſe of his Pen: And for the truth of this Relation, the Relator appeales to the Commiſsioners themſelves, or to any there preſent, who had the happineſſe with him, to heare the moſt pious, moſt Chriſtian Expreſsions, of a moſt Religious KING.</byline>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N <hi>Munday, Aug.</hi> 7. 1648. The Commiſsioners having admittance into the KING's preſence, the Votes were firſt read, and then preſented to the KING by the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> who deſired His MAJESTIES ſpeedy Anſwer: Telling Him, that their Returne was limited to <hi>ten dayes:</hi> The KING then askt, <hi>Whether the ten dayes were not to be counted from that of the delivery of the Meſſage?</hi> My Lord of <hi>Middleſex</hi> anſwered, <hi>No, Sir, they are to be counted from the day of our ſetting forth.</hi> The KING replyed, <hi>I have not then five dayes allowed me to conſider of my Anſwer, which I preſume you expect in writing; And I have none to help me, no not ſo much as a Clarke to tranſcribe; however I will really contribute my beſt endeavours to a happy Peace.—</hi>After a ſhort pauze, the KING ſaid, <hi>I would have ſent to the Parliament, but I deſire them to take notice, that my long ſilence proceeded not from a dull, ſtupid lazineſſe, or my being inſenſible of my owne or the Kingdomes condition; but from the</hi> Incapacity <hi>that lay on me by reaſon of former Votes: but now a way is opened to a Treaty, which I ever apprehended, as the onely meanes to a durable Peace: I ſhall cheerfully embrace it, and none ſhall more ſpeedily run to it, then my ſelfe: And for my part, as being more concerned then any one in this Kingdome, nay ſhould I ſay more then all, I ſpeake it without vanity, I hope it will be thought no Hyperbolicall Expreſsion, for I am aſſured, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever gaines, I ſhall be a loſer.—</hi>His MAJESTY then read the Votes to Himſelfe, and having read them, ſaid, <hi>I like them well, my deſires being included in theſe Votes: for what can I deſire more, then to Treat with</hi> Honour, Freedome, <hi>and</hi> Safety, <hi>upon the Propoſitions, and ſuch other things as either I or the Houſes ſhall offer?—</hi>His MAjESTY then askt, <hi>Whether the Commiſsioners to Treat were yet nominated?</hi> My Lord of <hi>Middleſex</hi> Anſwered, <hi>No, Sir.</hi> Then the KING ſaid, <hi>In a Treaty, two ſorts of things are conſiderable; ſome</hi> Neceſſary, <hi>others</hi> Convenient.—Then the KING ſaid to them, <hi>I will goe and apply my ſelfe to my Anſwer, that</hi> I <hi>may not delay a minute to promote ſo good a worke:</hi> And then withdrew, and for that time diſmiſſed the Commiſsioners.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Thurſday, Aug.</hi> 10. the Commiſsioners waited on His MAjESTY to receive His Anſwer; and upon their entrance into the Preſence, the KING ſaid, <hi>He was ſorry that He was limited to ſo ſhort a time, and had ſo little helps for diſpatch, yet notwithſtanding he had prepared his Anſwer:</hi> And immediately before the reading thereof, uſed theſe words, <hi>That the laſt Meſſage he ſent to the Houſes, was delivered to the Commiſsioners Sealed: And had it been ſo preſented, it would have been better for him, but now he thought it fit to ſend this open, becauſe he could not be in a worſe</hi> Condition; <hi>being under ſo</hi> cloſe a Reſtraint, <hi>none being ſuffered to ſpeak a word to him, without ſuſpition.—</hi>He then produced his Anſwer, and read it aloud in the Preſence Chamber, being full of company: And after he had read it, His MAjESTY ſaid, <hi>That he hoped he had therein indeavoured to give ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to his Parliament: There being nothing in it but what he conceived implyed in their Votes.</hi> And farther added, <hi>That there might be ſome that would oppoſe this Treaty, as being gainers by theſe Wars, and therefore deſired the continuance of it. Others might think him revengefull, but he ſaid he was ſo far from ſeeking revenge, That if a Straw lay in the way to hurt them, He would ſtoope and take it up to prevent it:</hi> And ſaid, <hi>God forgive them, for I do:</hi> Then the Commiſſioners comming to take their leaves of him, He called them to him, and asked them, <hi>how they liked his Anſwer?</hi> They told him, <hi>They thought and hoped, it would produce a ſudden and happy well-grounded Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <add>Auguſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 22<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1648</add>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
