<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good news from Somerset-shire: of the taking of Captaine Digby son to the Earle of Bristow, who had raised a troupe of horse to come against the Parliament. : With the manner of his apprehending, and the staying of his horse by the town of Sherburne, and himself staid, to be sent up to the House of Parliament for his censure. : Also an instruction from both houses of Parliament to all iustices of the peace. / Joh. Brown cler. Parl.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85360</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1067</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213113</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097802</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097802</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171387</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A85360)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171387)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2572:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good news from Somerset-shire: of the taking of Captaine Digby son to the Earle of Bristow, who had raised a troupe of horse to come against the Parliament. : With the manner of his apprehending, and the staying of his horse by the town of Sherburne, and himself staid, to be sent up to the House of Parliament for his censure. : Also an instruction from both houses of Parliament to all iustices of the peace. / Joh. Brown cler. Parl.</title>
                  <author>Browne, John, ca. 1608-1691.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Thomson.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642. August 12.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bristol, George Digby, --  Earl of, 1612-1677.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171387:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
            <p>Good News
FROM
SOMERSET-SHIRE:
Of the taking of Captaine <hi>Digby</hi> ſon to the Earle of
<hi>Briſtow,</hi> who had raiſed a troupe of horſe to come
againſt the Parliament.
<hi>WITH</hi>
The manner of his apprehending, and the ſtaying of his
horſe by the town of <hi>Sherburne,</hi> and himſelf ſtaid,
to be ſent up to the Houſe of Parliament
for his Cenſure.
<hi>ALSO</hi>
An Inſtruction from both Houſes of Parliament to
all Iuſtices of the Peace.
Joh. Brown Cler. Parl.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for</hi> Richard Thomſon. 1642. Auguſt 12.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account_of_battle">
            <pb facs="tcp:171387:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171387:2"/>
            <head>GOOD
NEVVES
FROM
SOMERSET-SHIRE.
ALSO
AN INSTRUCTION
from both Houſes of Parliament
to all Iuſtices of the Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O hath it pleaſed
the omnipotent &amp;
wiſe providence of
God, that hitherto
the evill-affected
diſturbers of this
our Sion have been
way-layed and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
in their owne
devices, yet hath
the devill ſo far prevailed with his deare chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
the Popes Brats, that they have ſought
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171387:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
the utter ruining of three flouriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,
and have left no plot unattempted
for the diſſolution and very eſſence of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and have wrought both beyond ſea and
in <hi>England,</hi> to ſet His Majeſty againſt this
higheſt Court of Iudicature, the Court of
Parliament, as may appeare by the Lord <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies</hi>
and the reſt of the Fugitives eſcape, and
deſiring His Maieſty to retire to ſome place
of ſtrength, where he might attend His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty
with His ſervice, and now in defiance of
iuſtice made His Maieſties Court a Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
for all his deſignes and practiſes formerly
by him practiſed, in his appearance in a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
manner at <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Thames,</hi> to the
afrightment of the whole towne, and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
ſadles and other engines of warre, which
now his brother Captain <hi>Digby</hi> thought to
have imployed: and having prepared a troup
of horſe ready to have gone for <hi>Yorke,</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
great rewards to all that would attend him
in his iourney to <hi>York.</hi> But having raiſed his
troupe ready to ſet forward, he was taken in
<hi>Sherburne,</hi> the whole town having intelligence
of his coming that way, where himſelfe and
his followers are in hold, till the cenſure of
the high Court of Parliament.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account_of_plot">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171387:3"/>
            <head>A TRUE RELATION OF THE
Plot intended againſt HVLL.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Cavaliers now about <hi>Hull</hi>
make their approaches near the
wals in the night, but in the day
time dare not come neare for
feare of pellets, not within two
miles of the town: they burnt two of the mills
near the town, and in attempting to burn the
reſt, were violently oppoſed by the ſhot of
the Canon from the town; inſomuch as they
returned ſwiftly. It is not certainly knowne
how many of the Cavaliers were kild; and the
Earle of <hi>Newport</hi> was by the force of a Canon
ſhot diſmounted and throwne into a ditch of
water of a great depth, where (after he had
once ſunk) he was catcht hold on by the haire
of his head, and his life ſaved, which cauſed
the Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> to give him his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
ſaying, If he had been a Roundhead he
he had been drowned, for there was no hold
on his head, and that the long-hair'd Cavaliers
were the onely ſaints. But after their retreat
the high wayes were much beſprinkled with
blood. On tueſday night laſt the plot was laid,
and perſons appointed to doe the worke, for
firing of the Towne in foure ſeverall places,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171387:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
the deſigne for the doing it was when they did
diſcern a fire on <hi>Beverley</hi> Minſter, it ſhould be
an aſſurance unto them, that at the ſame time
two thouſand men ſhould aſſault the wals
whileſt the ſouldiers were a quenching the
fire. But this plot was diſcovered a few
houres before, the plotters being of the alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
of <hi>Beck,</hi> with the Papiſt who ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
have betrayed the towne, and is now the
onely favourite at Court. It is certainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,
that the King adhereth to the advice
of the Cavaliers, and totally deſerts the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
of his Lords, which makes them ready
to returne to <hi>London,</hi> ſeeing themſelves in a
manner not worthy to be hearkened unto, but
rather the advice of ſuch as ſeek and thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
nothing but blood, and the utter deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the three Kingdomes: which if it pleaſe
not God to prevent, we are like by their evill
ſuggeſtions to undergo the miſeries of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi>
and other neighbouring countreyes, who
have their hands died in the ſcarlet blood of
the ſaints, and nothing more ſought after then
the deſtruction one of another. Therefore let
us remember that <hi>a kingdome divided againſt it
ſelfe cannot ſtand,</hi> and ſeek, as farre as in us lies,
with tears and ſupplications to the Almighty
for the prevention thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instruction_to_justices_of_the_peace">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:171387:4"/>
            <head>Die Mercurii.</head>
            <p>VVHereas ſeverall Commiſsions of
Array have lately iſſued out under
the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> into the ſeverall
Counties of <hi>Leiceſter, Worceſter,</hi> and other
Counties of this Realme, tending to the great
danger of His Majeſty, and the diſturbance of
the peace of the Kingdome: For the prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
thereof, and of the execution and iſſuing
out ſuch Commiſsions for the time to come,
It is Ordered by the Lords and commons aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled
in Parliament, That the Iudges and
Iuſtices of Aſsize, of the ſeverall Counties of
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> be required in their ſeveral
Circuits, at the Aſsizes and great Seſsions to
be next held for each County, within this
Realme, and the Dominion of <hi>Wales</hi> reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively,
in open Court, and in their ſeverall
Charges to be delivered to the Grand-Iuries
at the ſaid Aſsizes, and great Seſsions, openly
to declare and publiſh, That the ſaid Lords
&amp; Commons aſſembled in Parliament have,
upon mature deliberation, Reſolved upon the
Queſtion, That the ſaid Commiſsions of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray
are againſt Law, and againſt the Liberty
and Property of the Subiect: And that all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171387:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
thoſe that are Actors in putting the ſame in
execution, ſhalbe eſteemed diſturbers of the
Peace of the Kingdome, and Betrayers of the
Liberty of the Subject.</p>
            <p>Ordered by the Lords and Commons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
in Parliament, That this ſhalbe forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
printed and publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ioh. Brown Cleric. Parliament.</signed> 
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
