<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Philadelphia: or, XL. queries peaceably and inoffensively propounded for the discovery of truth in this question, or case of conscience; whether persons baptized (as themselves call baptism) after a profession of faith, may, or may not, lawfully, and with good conscience, hold communion with such churches, who judg themselves truly baptized, though in infancy, and before such a profession? Together with some few brief touches about infant, and after-baptism. By J.G. a minister of the gospel of Jesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1189</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E702_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207109</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866180</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866180</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118444</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A85408)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118444)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 108:E702[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Philadelphia: or, XL. queries peaceably and inoffensively propounded for the discovery of truth in this question, or case of conscience; whether persons baptized (as themselves call baptism) after a profession of faith, may, or may not, lawfully, and with good conscience, hold communion with such churches, who judg themselves truly baptized, though in infancy, and before such a profession? Together with some few brief touches about infant, and after-baptism. By J.G. a minister of the gospel of Jesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for Henry Cripps, and Lodowick Lloyd, and are to be sold at their shop in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.G. = John Goodwin.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 22.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118444:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>PHILADELPHIA:</hi> OR, XL.
QUERIES Peaceably and inoffenſively propounded For the Diſcovery of Truth in this Queſtion, or Caſe of Conſcience; <hi>Whether Perſons Baptized (as themſelves call Baptiſm) after a profeſsion of Faith, may, or may not, lawfully, and with a good Conſcience, hold Communion with ſuch Churches, who judg themſelves truly Baptized, though in Infancy, and before ſuch a Profeſsion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with ſome few brief Touches about Infant, and after-Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. G.</hi> a Miniſter of the Goſpel of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I thank God that I baptized none of you, but</hi> Criſpus <hi>and</hi> Gaius.<hi>—And I baptized alſo the bouſhold of</hi> Stephanas: <hi>beſides, I know not whether I baptized any other. For</hi> Chriſt <hi>ſent me not to baptize, but to preach the Goſpel.</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 14, 16, 17.</p>
            <q>For ye are all the children of God by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus.</q>
            <bibl>Gal. 4. 26.</bibl>
            <q>For in Jeſus Chriſt, neither circumciſion availeth any thing, nor uncircumciſion, but Faith which worketh by love.</q>
            <bibl>Gal. 5. 6.</bibl>
            <q>Circumciſion is nothing, nor uncircumciſion is nothing; but the keeping of the Commandments of God.</q>
            <bibl>1 Cor. 7. 19.</bibl>
            <q>Deus nobis imperavit congregationem: ſibi ſervavit ſeparationem.</q>
            <bibl>August. in Mat. 13. 47.</bibl>
            <q>Infantibus minime negandus Baptiſmus, quos Deus adoptat, &amp; filii ſui ſanguine abluit.</q>
            <bibl>Calvin. Harm. p. 253.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>Henry Cripps,</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Lloyd,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shop in <hi>Popes-head</hi> Alley. 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:118444:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118444:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>QUERIES ABOUT Lawfulneſs of Communion, with Churches deemed unbaptized; As alſo about <hi>Infant and after-Baptiſm.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>WHether is there any Precept, or Example in the Goſp<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, of any perſon, how duly ſoever bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, who diſclaimed <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Communion, either in Church fellowſhip, or in any the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the Goſpel, with thoſe, whom he judged true Beleevers, upon an account only of their not having been baptized, eſpecially af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch a manner, as he judged neceſſary for them to have been? Or in caſe there be neither precept, nor example found in the Scriptures to warrant ſuch a practiſe, upon what ground are the Conſciences of ſuch men, who practiſe it, ſatisfied or emboldened, in their way? Or if it be replyed, that there were no Beleevers in the Apoſtles days, who were not baptized, and that truly, and conſequently, that there was no occaſion of ſcrupuling communion with any Beleever in theſe days; 1. How can this ever be proved, <hi>(viz.</hi> that there were no Beleevers unbaptized in the Apoſtles days,) the contrary being apparant (as may be touched hereafter?) 2. Be it granted, that there were no Beleevers unbaptized, or unduly baptized, in the Apoſtles days, upon what ground notwithſtanding can the practiſe now queried, be juſtified, or maintained, unleſs the Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers certainly know, and can ſatisfie themſelves, that in caſe there had been ſuch Beleevers in theſe times (I mean, who had been un-baptized, or unduly baptized) thoſe duly Baptized would have declined ſuch communion with them, as that ſpecified; eſpecially
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118444:3"/>
conſidering that poſitive actions (ſuch is a declining, or withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from, communion with the Saints in Church-fellowſhip) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be juſtified upon negative grounds, at leaſt not further then in point of meer lawfulneſs, or indifferency, no nor thus far, in caſe of ſcandal; which is the caſe of thoſe, who withdraw from Church-communion to the offence, both of that Church from which they withdraw, and of many others?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>Whether can it be proved from the Scriptures, or by any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, like, or meet, to ſatisfie the Conſcience of any tender and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that the Apoſtles or other <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in their days, would have declined Church-communion with, or denyed Church-communion unto, ſuch perſons, whom they judged true Beleevers in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and Partakers of like precious Faith with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, only becauſe they had not been Baptized or dipped in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, after a profeſſion of their beleeving; eſpecially in caſe they had been baptized, and ſolemnly conſecrated by waſhing with water, unto the ſervice of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> before, conſidering that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly ſaith, that <hi>in Jeſus Chriſt [i. e.</hi> under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, or profeſſion of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the world] <hi>neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion,</hi> BUT FAITH <hi>which worketh by love</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Gal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. 6.</note>: And again; That <hi>Circumciſion is nothing, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion is nothing, but the keeping of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 19.</note>? meaning, that under the Goſpel, and profeſſion thereof, neither did the obſervation of any external Rite or Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony [Circumciſion, by a <hi>ſynecdoche ſpeciei,</hi> being put for all kind of external Rites, or Ceremonies] avail or contribute any thing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the commending of any perſon unto God; nor yet the want of any ſuch obſervation, diſcommend any man unto God, or prejudice his acceptation with him: but that which was all in all unto men, and which availed any thing, in, and under the Goſpel, that which being ſound in men, rendered them accepted and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of God, and the want of it, diſapproved, was ſuch a kind of Faith [not ſuch, or ſuch, a kind of Ceremony, or ſuch or ſuch a kind of <hi>Baptiſm]</hi> which by the mediation or interveening of that heavenly affection of love, uttereth and expreſſeth it ſelf in <hi>keeping the Commandments of God, [viz.</hi> ſo far as they are made known unto them, and as humane infirmity will well bear and admit.] Or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118444:3"/>
is it to be beleeved, that either the Apoſtles, or other <hi>Chriſtians</hi> taught by them, would have rejected thoſe from their communion, who were weak in the Faith, and were not convinced of every thing that was in any degree neceſſary for them to know, and to do, only for want of ſuch an external obſervance, of the lawfulneſs whereof they were unconvinced, and which, had they ſubmitted unto it, would have <hi>availed</hi> them little or nothing?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>Whether can it be proved by any text, or paſſage of Scripture, either directly, or by any tolerable conſequence, that Chriſtian Churches were (in the Apoſtles days) conſtituted by Baptiſm, or that none were reputed members of Churches, or admitted into <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Communion with thoſe who were Baptized, but only ſuch who were Baptized likewiſe; conſidering that that text <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 41. [commonly, and only, as far as I know, pretended for proof of ſuch a thing] doth not ſo much as colour, much leſs cotton, with ſuch a ſuppoſal, or concluſion; the tenor of the place being only this, <hi>Then they that gladly received his word, were baptized: and the ſame day there were added unto</hi> [them] <hi>about three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Souls?</hi> For, 1. It is not here ſaid, that all they that gladly received the Word, were baptized; but indefinitely only, <hi>They that gladly received, &amp;c.</hi> Now indefinite expreſſions in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are not always equipollent to univerſals, but ſometimes to partitives, or particulars. When the Apoſtle, ſpeaking of Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers under the Old Teſtament, ſaith, that THEY <hi>ſtopped the mouths of Lions, quenched the violence of fire, &amp;c. [Hebr.</hi> 11. 33, 34.] he doth not mean, that they all did either of theſe; nor indeed that many of them did either. See <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 34. compared with <hi>verſ.</hi> 48. (to omit an hundred inſtances more of like import.) Yea many times univerſal expreſſions themſelves are to be underſtood with limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reſtraine. Theſe things are ſufficiently known to perſons any thing converſant in the Scriptures. 2. Neither is it here ſaid, nor is it a thing in it ſelf much probable, that ONLY they who were baptized, were added unto them, <hi>[i. e.</hi> to the pre-ex<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtent number of Diſciples,] but only and ſimply that there were the number of three thouſand added the ſame day. Within which number it is the probable opinion of ſome, that the children, and families, of thoſe, who are ſaid to have gladly received the Word,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118444:4"/>
are comprehended; it being no ways likely, ſcarce poſſible, that 3000 men ſhould diſtinctly hear the voyce of a man ſpeaking: eſpecially unleſs we ſhall ſuppoſe, that theſe 3000 ſtood neareſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that ſpake, and with the beſt advantage to hear, there being many thouſands more preſent; which can hardly be the ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any conſidering man in the caſe in hand. Nor, 3. Is it ſaid, or ſo much as intimated or hinted in the leaſt, that any of the whole number of the three thouſand who were added unto them, were added by means, or upon the account, of their being baptized, although this addition be not mentioned till after their baptizing. It is ten degrees more probable, that their beleeving, or diſciple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which according to the principles of thoſe Brethren them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with whom we now argue, were precedent to their bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, and not their being baptized, were the reaſon and ground of <hi>Luke</hi>'s ſaying, they <hi>were added unto the Church,</hi> or former number of Diſciples; conſidering, 1. That the original, main and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal foundation of the holy brotherhood amongſt the Saints, and that which makes them fellow-members, or members one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is, not the Ceremony of their external Baptiſm, but their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and communion in the divine Nature, and inward relation unto the ſame <hi>Chriſt</hi> by one and the ſame precious Faith. 2. That it cannot be demonſtratively proved from the Scriptures, that thoſe hundred and twenty Diſciples <hi>[Act.</hi> 1. 15.] unto which it is here ſaid that three thouſand were added, were, or had been, all of them baptized, in as much as (as will preſently appear) there were divers members of Churches in the Apoſtles days, who were unbaptized; no, nor can it any whit more be proved from Scripture, that the Apoſtles themſelves mentioned <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 13. had been baptized, then that <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> was baptized. 3. (And laſtly,) That had the Church, or perſons, unto whom theſe three thouſand are ſaid to have been added, been eſtimated by their having been baptized, (which muſt be ſuppoſed, if thoſe who are added to them, are ſaid to have been added upon the account of their being baptized,) their number muſt needs have far exceeded <hi>an hundred and twenty,</hi> conſidering the great numbers and vaſt multitudes of perſons, that had been baptized by <hi>John, Mat.</hi> 3. 5, 6. compared with <hi>Mark 1. 5. Luk.</hi> 3. 7, 21. as alſo by Chriſt himſelf and his Diſciples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 22 26. Yea had the Church been eſtimated, or conſtituted, by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118444:4"/>
the Evangeliſt <hi>Luke,</hi> intending (queſtionleſs, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 4.) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the increaſe of the Church and progreſs of the Goſpel, with as much advantage as truth would afford, had prevaricated with the cauſe, which he intended to promote, in reporting their number to have been <hi>about five thouſand</hi> only; when as, upon the ſaid ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and the tenor of the late premiſſes, he might with as much Truth have reported them about forty thouſand, yea and many more. <hi>Howbeit many of them which heard the Word,</hi> BELEE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VED: <hi>and the number of the men were about five thouſand.</hi> In which paſſage, the increaſe of the Church, or addition unto the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Saints, is with much more pregnancy of intimation aſcribed unto their <hi>beleeving,</hi> then in the other place it is unto their being <hi>baptized.</hi> Therefore both men and women, who are indeed ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Conſcience in things appertaining unto God, had need have a better foundation to bear them out in their practiſe of rending and tearing Churches [or, if this name will not paſs, of rending and tearing holy Societies and fellowſhips of Saints] then any thing that can be ſo much as tolerably inferred from the Text now ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 41.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>Whether did not the Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> in the Apoſtles days, and ſo alſo the Churches in <hi>Galatia,</hi> hold Church-communion with ſome, who were not baptized, conſidering, 1. That the Apoſtle to the former writeth thus: <hi>Know ye not, that</hi> SO MANY OF US <hi>as were baptized into Jeſus Chriſt, were baptized into his death? Rom.</hi> 6. 3. and to the latter (after the ſame manner) thus: <hi>For</hi> AS MANY OF YOU <hi>as have been baptized into Chriſt. Gal.</hi> 3. 27. 2. That this particle, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>as many as</hi> (uſed in both places) is, in ſuch conſtructions as theſe, always partitive, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing or dividing the entire number of perſons ſpoken of, ſome from others, by the character or property ſpecified, or at leaſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth a poſſibility of ſuch a diſtinction. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>as many as touched</hi> [the hem of his garment] <hi>were made whole, (Mat.</hi> 14. 36.) This clearly ſuppoſeth, either that there were ſome, or at leaſt that there might be ſome, who did not thus touch. So again: <hi>They brought in all</hi> AS MANY AS <hi>they found,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 10. So, AS MANY <hi>[i. e.</hi> as many men and women] <hi>as are of the works of the Law, are under the curſe. Gal.</hi> 3. 10. See alſo <hi>Mark 3. 10. &amp;</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118444:5"/>
6. 11, 56. <hi>Luk. 4 40. Ioh. 1. 12. Act.</hi> 3. 24 (with others more of like tenor and import, almoſt without number.) Therefore is it not without controverſie and diſpute, that the Apoſtle ſaying to the Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> and to thoſe in <hi>Galatia,</hi> As MANY OF You <hi>as have been baptized, &amp;c.</hi> ſuppoſeth, either that there actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally were, or at leaſt that (for ought he knew to the contrary) there might be, ſundry of their members, who had not been bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized? And if he had either known, or ſo much as by conjecture ſuppoſed, that all the members of theſe Churches had without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception been baptized, is it credible that he would have expreſſed himſelf thus unto them (reſpectively,) As MANY OF You As <hi>have been baptized,</hi> and not rather, <hi>You having all been baptized,</hi> or the like?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>Whether did not the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> (in the Apoſtles days) entertain members, and hold communion with thoſe, who had not been baptized; conſidering that he demandeth thus of this Church: <hi>Elſe what ſhall</hi> [or, what will] <hi>they do, which are baptized for the dead, if the dead riſe not at all? why are they then baptized for the dead</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 29. <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Cameron. Myroth.</hi> p. 229. <hi>&amp; Ambroſs<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m in locum.</hi> I know the place is much vexed with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters and interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain I am that the ſence here ſuppoſed and argued upon, is the m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt grammatical, and beſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting with the propriety of he words and phraſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>? Or doth not this imply, that there was a corrupt and ſuperſtitious practiſe on foot in this Church, to baptize one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſurviving kindred, or Friends, in the name of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (reſpectively) who dyed unbaptized, and that this Church thought and ſuppoſed, that ſuch Baptiſm was available for good unto the deceaſed in ſuch a caſe; which practiſe and opinion of theirs the Apoſtle here inſiſteth on as inconſiſtent with that moſt dangerous and pernicious Error of denying the Reſurrection of the dead, which had now gotten head amongſt them? And if there were ſuch a practiſe as this in this Church, I mean to baptize ſome of the living members, in the name and ſtead of ſome that were dead, is it not a plain caſe that there were ſome of theſe members, who lived and dyed unbaptized?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>Whether, when <hi>Paul,</hi> ſoon after his converſion, aſſayed to joyn himſelf to the Church and Diſciples at <hi>Jeruſalem (Act.</hi> 9. 26.) did this Church make any enquiry after his Baptiſm, as whether he had been baptized, or no, in order to his reception amongſt them; or did they know that he had been baptized? Or did <hi>Barnabas,</hi> in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118444:5"/>
giving ſatisfaction to the Apoſtles and Church concerning his meetneſs to be admitted into communion with them, ſo much as mention his being Baptized, but only <hi>declared unto them how he had ſeen the Lord in the way, and that he had ſpoken to him, and how he had preached boldly at Damaſcus in the Name of Jeſus? Acts</hi> 9. 27.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>Whether, upon a ſuppoſal, that it cannot be proved from the Scriptures, that any unbaptized, or unduly baptized perſon, was ever admitted into Church-communion by <hi>Christians</hi> in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles days, or that any duly baptized perſon held communion with a Church, the greateſt part of whoſe members he deemed either unbaptized, or unduly Baptized, is ſuch a defect of proof ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to juſtifie a withdrawing of communion by a perſon, who conceiveth himſelf duly baptized, from ſuch a Church, the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of whoſe members he ſuppoſeth are either not baptized, or unduly Baptized; conſidering that very many things may be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of duty, and neceſſary to be done, which are not warranted for ſo much as lawful, by any example in the Scriptures of like action in all circumſtances? It is the duty of Churches, and of every member reſpectively, to admit their women-members to the Lords Table; yet cannot this practice be warranted by any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample recorded in the Scriptures. Yea in caſe at the time of this Sacramental Adminiſtration in a Church, all the men-members ſhould occaſionally be abſent, except only the Adminiſtrator, and (it may be) a Deacon or two, and only the women-members pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, there is little queſtion to be made, but that the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ought to proceed notwithſtanding, and the elements be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto this female Congregation, though there be no example of ſuch an Adminiſtration as this in the Scriptures. There is no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in Scripture of any perſon worſhiping the Holy Ghoſt: yet it is a great duty lying upon <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to worſhip him. When <hi>David,</hi> and the men with him, entred into the Houſe of God, and did eat the ſhew-bread <note n="a" place="margin">1 Sam. 21. 6</note>, he had no Scripture-example to juſtifie his action; no more had the Diſciples to juſtifie theirs, when they plucked the ears of Corn as they paſſed through the Fields on a Sabbath day: yet were both theſe actions lawful, and (to a degree) neceſſary. The reading of the Scriptures tranſlated out of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118444:6"/>
Original Languages into <hi>Engliſh, Welch, Dutch, French, &amp;c.</hi> is not only lawful, but neceſſary, in the Chriſtian Churches in theſe Nations; yet is there no example extant in Scripture of any ſuch practice in the primitive Times, no nor ſo much as of any Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Scriptures at all. It were eaſie to add more inſtances of like conſideration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>Whether is an action or practice, ſuppoſe in matters relating to the ſervice or worſhip of God, upon this account evicted to be unlawful, becauſe it hath neither precept [I mean, no particular or expreſs precept, and wherein the action or practice it ſelf, with all the circumſtances under which it becomes lawful, is named,] nor example, to warrant the lawfulneſs of it? Or hath the practice of admitting women to the Lords Table, any ſuch, either precept, or example, to juſtifie it? Or in caſe a Miniſter ſhall preach to a Congregation conſiſting of young men only, and from <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 3, or 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. would ſuch an act as this be unlawful? or is there any ſuch precept, as that mentioned, or example in Scripture, for the warrant of it? Or when <hi>David,</hi> and thoſe that were with him, went into the Houſe of God, and, contrary to the letter of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, <hi>eat the ſhew-bread,</hi> had they either ſuch a precept, as that mentioned, or any example, to bear them out in ſuch a practiſe? Or doth not our Saviour in the Goſpel juſtifie that action of theirs notwithſtanding? Or if the caſe, or law of neceſſity, or of peril, either of health, or life, be pleadable for the juſtification thereof; is not the ſame Law altogether as, yea &amp; much more, pleadable, on the behalf of ſuch perſons, who being of tender, weak, and ſickly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, dare not tempt God, or expoſe themſelves to the immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent hazard of health or life, by being douſed in their apparel over head and ears in the water; eſpecially conſidering that God hath teſtified from Heaven his diſ-approbation of the practice, by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering ſome to be grievouſly afflicted in their bodies, and ſome alſo to miſcarry in life it ſelf, by means (in all likelyhood) of the temptation? Or hath not God ſufficiently and plainly enough de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his mind and pleaſure in all ſuch caſes as this, in ſaying, <hi>I will have mercy, and not ſacrifice</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Matt. 12. 7</note>? Or if it be pleaded, that all danger of miſcarrying in either kind, may be prevented, by chuſing a warm room, and warm water, for the tranſacting of the Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118444:6"/>
Dipping, is it not queryable hereupon, whether this be not to alter and change, to new-mold, ſhape, and transform the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, as men pleaſe, and this under a pretext of obſerving it? Or is there not as much difference between hot water, and cold, as is between a child, and a man?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>Whether, when God hath by Faith purified the hearts of a people walking in a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Brotherhood and Fellowſhip toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hath he not ſanctified them? And in caſe any perſon ſhall now deſpiſe, or decline their fellowſhip, as unholy, doth he not ſin againſt that heavenly Admonition delivered by ſpecial Revelation unto <hi>Peter; What God hath cleanſed</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, or purified] <hi>call not thou</hi> [or, make not thou] <hi>common</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Acts 10. 15</note>? Or can a man (lightly) call, or make, that <hi>common,</hi> which God hath <hi>ſanctified,</hi> in a more opprobrious and contumelious way, then by fleeing from it, as polluted or unholy?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>Whether doth, or needs, a man contract any guilt of ſin before God, by walking in ſuch a ſociety of men, who being otherwiſe confeſſedly <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and holy, have only ſome practice amongſt them in the judgment and conſcience of this man not approvable, in caſe, 1. he ſhall at any time openly declare his diſlike of this practice; and, 2. Be no ways conſtrained, or ſolicited to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate in this practice? Or, when men may ſeparate that which is precious from that which is vile, and enjoy it thus ſeparated, and apart, without ſuffering any inconvenience by that which is vile, is it a point of wiſdom in them to deprive themſelves of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of what is precious, becauſe there is ſomewhat, which they ſuppoſe to be vile, near to it?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p>Whether may perſons, who are weak in the Faith, be rejected by a Church from communion with them, in caſe they deſire it, only becauſe they queſtion, or diſſent from, the ſence of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of this Church, in ſome one point <hi>of doubtful disputation?</hi> Or is not the practice of a man, who pretends to be ſtrong in the Faith, in renouncing communion with a Church (or, which is the ſame, in rejecting a Church from his communion) which he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth weak in the Faith, only becauſe they more generally diſſent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118444:7"/>
from him in a matter of doubtful diſputation, a practice much more unchriſtian and unwarrantable, then the former? Or is not the practice, eſpecially the neceſſity, of dipping, after Infant-ablu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Infant-Baptiſm, a matter <hi>of doubtful disputation;</hi> unleſs (haply) by matters <hi>of doubtful disputation,</hi> we mean, not what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is queſtioned, oppoſed, or denyed by any man, or any ſort of men, being aſſerted and held by others; but only ſuch things, which are controverted and diſputed with good probability on either ſide, by men of gravity, worth, ſoberneſs of judgment, throughly verſed and expert in the Scriptures? &amp;c. And whether, in this ſence or notion of matters <hi>of doubtful disputation,</hi> is the neceſſity of the ſaid practice of after-Baptiſm ſo much as matter <hi>of doubtful disputation,</hi> the generality of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſo qualified, as hath been expreſſed, unanimouſly agreeing in the non-neceſſity, yea and (which is ſomewhat more) in the irregularity of it?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>Whether did the Lord <hi>Chriſt,</hi> pointing to any river, or water, ſay, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon</hi> this water <hi>will I build my Church?</hi> Or did he not, ſpeaking either of himſelf, or of that great Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> that He was <hi>the Son of the living God,</hi> which <hi>Peter</hi> had confeſſed, ſay, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock will I build my Church</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Matt. 16. 18</note>? Or is there the ſofteſt whiſper, or gentleſt breathing in the Scripture, of any ſuch noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or opinion, as this, that a true Church of Chriſt cannot be conſtituted, or made, no not of the trueſt and ſoundeſt Believers in the world, unleſs they have been baptized after their believing, how, or after what manner ſoever, they have been baptized be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>Whether is an error, or miſtake, about the adequate or appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate ſubject of Baptiſm, of any worſe conſequence, or greater danger, then an error or miſtake about <hi>Melchiſedec's</hi> Father, as <hi>viz.</hi> in caſe a man ſhould ſuppoſe him to have been <hi>Noah</hi> (which he muſt be, in caſe <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> were the ſame Perſon with <hi>Sem)</hi> when as he was ſome other man? If ſo, how, or wherein doth the exceſs of the danger, or evil of the conſequence appear? If not, whether is it <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or any ways becoming the Spirit of the Goſpel, to abandon communion with ſuch Churches, which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing interpreted) is to proclaim them polluted, hated and abhorred
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118444:7"/>
by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> only becauſe a man ſuppoſeth them to lie under the guilt of ſuch an error, or miſtake?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <p>Whether may not the importune conteſt, or queſtion, about the appropriate ſubject of Baptiſm, as it is ſtated by the Brethren of New Baptiſm, in oppoſition to the judgment and practice (almoſt) of the whole Chriſtian World, juſtly be numbered amongſt thoſe queſtions, which the Apoſtle calls <hi>fooliſh,</hi> and <hi>unlearned,</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth both <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> to <hi>avoyd,</hi> as being queſtions which <hi>ingender ſtrife</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 23</note>, <hi>and are unprofitable and vain</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Tit. 3. 9.</note>; conſidering, 1. That the experience of many years in the Reformed Churches abroad, and of ſome years amongſt our ſelves at home, hath abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly taught and informed us, that the ſaid queſtion hath yielded little other fruit unto thoſe that have ſet their hearts to it, yea and unto others alſo, but contention, ſtrife, emulations, evil ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zings, diſtractions, confuſions, alienations of mind and affections amongſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Brethren, evil ſpeakings, vilifyings, revilings, needleſs and waſtful expence of time, loſs of many precious op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities for matters of greateſt conſequence, unprofitable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbings and turmoylings of weak Conſciences, ſhatterings, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terings, rendings, and teerings of ſuch Churches, and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Societies, who, till this root of bitterneſs ſprang up amongſt them, walked in love, and with the light of Gods countenance ſhining on them, holding the unity of the Spirit in the band of peace, edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying one another in their moſt holy Faith, &amp;c. 2. That the ſaid Queſtion, in the nature and direct tendency of it, leadeth unto very little that is conſiderable, or of much conſequence for <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> to know; and that what is brought to light (of moment and conſequence) by occaſion of the ventilation of it, is nothing but what might arrive at the knowledg of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> in a more peaceable, and leſs troubleſom way: And, 3. (and laſtly) That thoſe who are moſt confident that they have found the treaſure of Truth, which the Queſtion we ſpeak of, ſeeketh after, are no ways, as far as any ways appeareth, or can be diſcerned, ſpiritually enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it, but rather impoveriſhed (at leaſt the generality of them) loſing by degrees, that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſweetneſs, meekneſs, humility, love, patience, ſoberneſs of mind, fruitfulneſs of converſation, &amp;c. which were obſervable in them before; as if their new Baptiſm
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118444:8"/>
had been into a new, or another <hi>Jeſus,</hi> altogether unlike unto him, whom <hi>Paul</hi> preached?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p>Whether is any Member of a Chriſtian Church, or Society, at any more liberty, or under any greater neceſſity, to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, cut off, or ſeparate this Church, or all the members of it, from his communion, only upon his private conceit or perſwaſion, ſuppoſe according to truth, that they walk not in all things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Goſpel-rule, then this Church is to excommunicate him, upon a true and certain perſwaſion, that he walketh not in every thing according to the rule of the Goſpel? Or if Churches either be at liberty, or under an obligation by way of duty, to excommunicate every of their members (reſpectively) becauſe they judg them not to walk in all things according to the Goſpel, are they not at liberty, or bound in duty and conſcience, thus to caſt out all their members one after another; conſidering, that not in ſome things only, but even <hi>in many things</hi> (as the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>we offend all?</hi> Or hath any ſingle member of a Church any more liberty, or authority, to adjudg and determine without the Scriptures, upon what grounds or occaſions, his departure from a Church is juſtifiable, then a Church hath to make Laws and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of her own for the ejecting of her members? Or is it any where a caſe adjudged in the Scriptures, that if a Church in any part of the world, ſuppoſe under the frozen Zone, ſhall not practice dipping after ſprinkling, or other waſhing, in the Name of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> every member thereof ſtands bound in conſcience, yea or is ſo much as at liberty, to reverſe, or diſoblige himſelf from, his ſolemn and ſacred engagements to it?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <p>Whether did not <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> hold Chriſtian Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with thoſe <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Converts which they made at <hi>Antioch, Acts</hi> 13. 43, 48, 52. and with thoſe alſo, which they made ſoon after in great numbers at <hi>Iconium, Acts</hi> 14. 1, 4? Or doth it any ways appear from the Scripture, that theſe Converts, during the continuance of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> with them, yea or at any time after, were baptized? If not, is it any ways neceſſary that we ſhould believe, or ought it to be any Article of our Faith to believe, that they were baptized? If it be not neceſſary, then we are at
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118444:8"/>
liberty to believe, that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> did hold <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Communion with unbaptized <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> eſpecially conſidering, that the tenor of the Hiſtory diligently conſulted, eſpecially concerning thoſe, who were converted to the Faith at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and the ſhort abode of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> with them after their Converſion, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the troubleſom oppoſitions which the <hi>Jews</hi> of the place made all the while againſt them, makes it probable in the higheſt, that they were not baptized, at leaſt whileſt theſe men continued with them?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <p>Whether, in caſe any member, one or more, of any <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, or Society, which he judgeth faithful in the main, and willing and ready to walk up to their light, ſhall verily think and be perſwaded, that he hath diſcovered ſome defect, or error in this Church, may ſuch an one lawfully and with a good conſcience give himſelf a diſcharge from all care &amp; ſervice otherwiſe due from him unto it, by renouncing the communion thereof upon ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or occaſion; eſpecially before, or until, he hath with all long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering and meekneſs, and with the beſt of his underſtanding, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored the information of this Church in the Truth, and the rectify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the judgments of the members thereof; conſidering, that as in the natural body, ſo in the ſpiritual or Church-body, <hi>the members ought to have the ſame care one for another,</hi> and if one <hi>member ſuffereth, all the members to ſuffer with it</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 25</note>, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh,) and conſequently no one member, being healthful and ſound, ought to deſert its fellow-members being ſickly and weak, eſpecially whileſt there is yet any hope of their cure and heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <p>Whether ought a company of true Believers, concerning whoſe lawful Church conſtitution there can no other thing with reaſon and truth be objected, to be vilified, or ſeparated from, as a falſe Church, or no Church of Chriſt at all, only becauſe, either, 1. They do not practice contrary to their judgment and conſcience, ſuch things, one, or more, which ſome men conceive it meet they ſhould practice; Or, 2. becauſe, either God hath not enlightened them to ſee every thing, which ſome other men ſee; or elſe becauſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan hath not blinded them, ſo as to make them ignorant of ſuch
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118444:9"/>
Truths, one, or more, whereof ſome others are ignorant, judging them to be Errors?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <p>Whether is it reaſonable or <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that a company of true Believers, who have met together in the ſimplicity of their hearts in the fear of God, in the Name of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> mutually en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging themſelves, as in the preſence of God, to walk together in all the Ordinances of the Goſpel, as far as they ſhall from time to time be revealed unto them, and walking accordingly, ſhould be infamouſly ſtigmatized as no Church, no true Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and conſequently be eſteemed but as a rabble rout of the world only pretending Churchſhip, and this by ſome one, or a few per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, only becauſe they cannot ſee with their eyes, or practice that as neceſſary, the neceſſity whereof, after much and earneſt prayer unto God, after much enquiry and ſearch, and this with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and impartialneſs, in order to their conviction and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doth no ways to them appear?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <p>Whether is it <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or meet, for any one perſon, man, or woman, to bid defiance unto an whole Church or fellowſhip of Saints being many, and who are otherwiſe ſober, grave, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly faithful in all their walking, onely becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with a good Conſcience ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to every notion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, which theſe perſons themſelves judg worthy of reverence and honour, and particularly, becauſe they cannot, againſt the ſence, Judgment and practiſe, as well of all Chriſtian Antiquity, as of all the Reformed Churches (very few, if any, excepted) in the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> world, thus ſpiritually court their private apprehenſions about the time and manner of an external Adminiſtration; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conſidering, that they neither have, nor can, either ſhew pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, example, or any competent ground otherwiſe, from the Scriptures, to commend theſe their apprehenſions unto the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of any man? Or is there any precept, which injoyns baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or dipping, in the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> after a baptizing in infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy into this name? Or is there any example in Scripture of any baptized after profeſſion of Faith, who had been baptized, or who judged themſelves, and were generally ſo judged by others, to have been baptized, before? If neither, is it not a clear caſe, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118444:9"/>
here is neither precept, nor example in Scripture, which reacheth home to the caſe, or which warranteth the practice, of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of after-Baptiſm amongſt us? And as for any competent ground otherwiſe to juſtifie the practice, hath ſuch a thing ever ſeen the light of the Sun hitherto?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <head>XXI</head>
               <p>Whether do not they, who magnifie the ceremony or external rite of Baptiſm to ſuch an height, as to eſtimate <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> by it, or to judg them no true or ſound <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who are without it, ſtumble at the ſame ſtone of danger and peril of Soul, at which the Jews ſtumbled, when they practiced and urged Circumciſion as neceſſary for Juſtification; to whom, upon this account, <hi>Paul</hi> teſtified; <hi>Behold, I Paul ſay unto you, that if ye be circumciſed,</hi> [meaning, with an opinion of a neceſſity of your being circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed for your Juſtification before God,] <hi>Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 5. 2.</note>? conſidering, 1. That Circumciſion was an Ordinance of God, yea as great and ſolemn an Ordinance, as Baptiſm; and 2. That when <hi>Paul</hi> threatened thoſe who ſo magnified it (as was ſaid) with lofing their part and portion in Chriſt, it was as Lawful, though (haply) not ſo neceſſary (and yet in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it was neceſſary too) as Baptiſm it ſelf; yea and the Apoſtle himſelf adminiſtred it, as well as he did Baptiſm, yea and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced it <hi>profitable,</hi> (rightly underſtood and practiced?) <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 1. 2. Or might not the ſame threatening (I mean, of loſing the great bleſſing of Juſtification and Salvation by <hi>Chriſt)</hi> have been with altogether as much truth and neceſſity, adminiſtred upon a like occaſion and account, unto perſons ſo opinionated of circumciſion, as the <hi>Galathians</hi> were, even when, and whilſt, the uſe and practice of it was every whit as neceſſary (or rather more neceſſary) as the uſe of Baptiſm now is?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <head>XXII.</head>
               <p>Whether is there any precept, or example in the Scriptures, of any perſon Baptized after many years profeſſion of the Goſpel, or after any conſiderable meaſure of aſſurance of the pardon of ſin obtained, or at any other time, ſave at, or about, their firſt entrance upon a profeſſion of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Or is there any competent ground, either in Reaſon, or Religion, why either ſuch a thing ſhould have been practiſed by <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the Apoſtles days, or why it ought
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118444:10"/>
to be practiſed by any in theſe days; conſidering, 1. That it is uncomely, and contrary to the Law, which God hath eſtabliſhed, both in Nature, and in Grace, to return or fall back from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to imperfection, from that which is more ſpiritual, to that which is more carnal; And, 2. That types and figures, which are not rememorative (as the Paſſover was, and the Lords Table now is) but either only ſignificative, or obſignative (as Baptiſm is) ſhould be uſed, after the ſubſtance of the things typified and figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them, have been of a long time exhibited unto, received, and enjoyed by thoſe, who uſe them; 3. That a profeſſion of the Name and Faith of <hi>Chriſt</hi> by an holy and blameleſs converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for many years together in the world, by a long continued courſe of mortification, ſelf-denyal, fruitfulneſs in well doing, &amp;c. is the truth and ſubſtance, the heart, life, and ſoul of that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is made by being externally Baptized; 4. (And laſtly) That that which is a duty at one time, in reſpect of ſuch and ſuch circumſtances, may ceaſe to be, or may not be, a duty at another time, when circumſtances are changed, many inſtances whereof might be readily given?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <head>XXIII.</head>
               <p>Whether ought not the Law of Edification [1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 26.] to over-rule all Laws and Precepts concerning ſpiritual and Church-adminiſtrations, as the Law of <hi>Salus Populi</hi> ought to umpire and over-rule all politique Laws and Conſtitutions, in their reſpective Executions? If ſo, ought not the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm to be rather appropriated unto Infants, then unto others, conſidering, 1. That God himſelf adjudged the Adminiſtration of the Ordinance of Circumciſion (an Ordinance the ſame with Baptiſm, though not in the ſhape and form of the letter, yet in ſtrength and ſubſtance of the Spirit, as evidently appeareth from <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11. well underſtood, and diligently compared with <hi>Mark 1. 4. Luk.</hi> 3. 3, &amp;c.) unto Infants, to be moſt edifying in the Church of the <hi>Jews;</hi> otherwiſe it muſt be ſaid that he ordered the Adminiſtration of it to the ſpiritual detriment and loſs of thoſe, to whom he gave it; And, 2. That there can no reaſon, nor colour of reaſon be given, why, or how, the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm unto Infants in <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Churches, ſhould not as well be more edifying unto theſe, then an after-Adminiſtration of it would be,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118444:10"/>
as the like Adminiſtration of Circumciſion was unto the <hi>Jews;</hi> 3. (And laſtly) That whatſoever the wiſdom of men may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <note place="margin">u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de multi poſt Baptiſmum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficientes, &amp; maxime qui In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes vel pueri baptizati ſunt, &amp;c. <hi>Aug. de Baptiſmo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Donatiſtas</hi> lib. 4. c. 14.</note> and plead colourably and plauſibly to the contrary, ought to give place to the determination and reſolution of God himſelf? <hi>Be ſilent, O all fleſh, before the Lord, Zech. 2. 13. The Lord is in his holy Temple; let all the Earth keep ſilence before him, Habak.</hi> 2. 20. although it be demonſtrable enough, even by clear grounds and principles in reaſon, that to Baptize in Infancy, muſt needs be more edifying to the Church, then to transfer the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration to maturity of years.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <head>XXIV.</head>
               <p>Whether is not the Baptizing of Children, by the Apoſtles and other Baptiſts appointed by them in their days, ſufficiently ſignified and implyed in thoſe paſſages (eſpecially in conjunction with the known Law and Cuſtom of circumciſing children amongſt the <hi>Jews)</hi> where they are recorded to have baptized houſholds, or families, without exception of any perſon in any one of them? as <hi>Act. 16. 33. 1 Cor. 1. 16. Act. 16. 15. &amp;c.</hi> Or can there any arguments or conjectures be levyed from the Scriptures to prove the contrary, which will balance or hold weight againſt theſe; conſidering, 1. That it is at no hand probable, that God, who had made a Law againſt him, that ſhould <hi>open or dig a pit in his field, and not cover it</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 21. 33 34</note>, would, not only have left the precept and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual example of circumciſing Infants by the <hi>Jews,</hi> as a pit uncovered for Believers, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> under the Goſpel, to fall into, by baptizing their Children, without giving the leaſt notice of the alteration of his mind in this behalf, but alſo have digged this pit yet broader, deeper, and wider, by cauſing the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of ſeveral families to be recorded in the New Teſtament, without the leaſt mention or intimation of the paſſing by children in the Adminiſtration; 2. That that which is commonly replyed to diſable theſe paſſages as to the proof of Infant-Baptiſm, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly weak, and no ways ſatisfactory; <hi>viz.</hi> that it is elſewhere ſaid of whole houſholds and families that they believed, which (ſay the Replyers) doth not imply, that children are here included, or that they believed, this (I ſay) is unſatisfactory; in as much as, 1. Children may in a ſence (and this very frequent in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) be ſaid to believe, <hi>i. e.</hi> to be in the ſtate and condition of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118444:11"/>
Believers, in reſpect of the love and favor of God, in title to the <note place="margin">Similia ſimili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>um occupait nomina. <hi>Hur. Grot.</hi> in <hi>Act.</hi> 13 33. Multa offi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantur ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer &amp; forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter, quae per equivalentiam ſeu comparatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem tantum ſunt intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da: Vid. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ai, 66. 3. 1 Tim. 5. 8 Matt. 19. 12 Rom. 11, 15, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Kingdom of Heaven, &amp;c. yea and are by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf (in theſe reſpects) expreſly ſaid to believe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 6. And, 2. Were it granted, that children are in no ſence capable of believing, and in this reſpect cannot be included, when it is ſaid of whole houſes, that they believed; yet are they as capable of being Baptized, or (as our Brethren will needs have it) of being dipped (yea in ſome reſpect more capable hereof) as men; and conſequently can upon no tolerable account be thought to be excluded, when it is ſaid of whole houſes or families that they were dipped; as (for inſtance) becauſe, when <hi>Johns</hi> Diſciples ſaid, <hi>And all men come unto him, [Joh.</hi> 3. 26.] Children muſt needs be excluded, and not contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the word, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>all men,</hi> in as much as they were in no capacity of <hi>coming;</hi> it doth not follow from hence, that therefore when the Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>Chriſt by the grace of God taſted Death for all men, [Heb.</hi> 2. 9.] and ſo again, that <hi>it is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for men</hi> (meaning, all men) <hi>once to dye, [Heb.</hi> 9. 27.] Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren muſt be here excluded alſo, and not be comprehended in the general term, <hi>all men;</hi> in as much as they are as well capable as men, of ſuch a grace, as <hi>Chriſts dying for them</hi> imports, and ſo of dying themſelves, though they are not capable of coming unto any man to be baptized: 3. Conſidering, that men ought not to contend with God, or to reject any part of his Counſel or Will, becauſe it is only ſomewhat ſparingly, and with ſome ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of evidence, diſcovered in his Word, but to reſt ſatisfied with that meaſure or degree of revelation of things, which he judgeth meet to vouchſafe unto them, until further light ſhall ſhine: 4. That they who are diſſatisfied with that diſcovery, which learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Paedobaptiſts make unto them from the Scriptures, of the will and mind of God for the Baptizing of Infants, do readily embrace and entertain many other notions and opinions upon far weaker, and leſs lightſom grounds of conviction, as <hi>viz.</hi> the common Doctrines or Tenents concerning Original Sin, admiſſion of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to the Lords Table, the obſervation of the Sabbath on the firſt day of the week (yea ſome of them on the laſt day,) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the Soul into Heaven, and happineſs, immediately up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on death, (with many other things, which we ſhall not now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,) not that I mention theſe with diſlike of the common opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118444:11"/>
about them all, but only to ſhew, that as the generality of the <hi>Jews</hi> rejected the true <hi>Meſſiah</hi> notwithſtanding all the true and real Miracles which he wrought amongſt them, and yet entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed falſe Meſſiahs one after another, with their counterfeit and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miracles; ſo do the generality of Anti-Paedobaptiſts reject In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm, notwithſtanding the many real and ſubſtantial proofs, by which it is commended and confirmed unto them, in the mean time bowing down their Judgments and Conſciences to ſuch Doctrines, which have little but hay and ſtubble to ſupport them. 5. (And laſtly) That God doth expect, that men ſhould dig for the treaſure of Truth, and of his Counſel, even where it lies much deeper under-ground, then Infant-Baptiſm doth in ſeveral of thoſe Texts of Scripture, which have been argued by learned men of that Judgment, in proof thereof; yea and hath reproved men for their unmanlike oſcitancy, and neglect in this behalf? Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe and conſider diligently theſe Texts and Paſſages at your leaſure (becauſe it would be too long to argue them,) <hi>Mat. 12 3, 4, 5, 7. Mat. 23. 16, 17, 18, 19, &amp;c. Mat. 22. 29, 31, 32, &amp;c. Luk 24. 25, 26. Acts</hi> 7. 25, 26. (to omit others.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <head>XXV.</head>
               <p>Whether is the practiſe of demanding, or ſubmitting unto, a Baptiſmal dipping, after a ſolemn dedication unto the ſervice of Jeſus <hi>Chriſt</hi> by a baptiſmal ſprinkling, or ablution, any where countenanced in the Scriptures, or enjoyned, either by particularity, or expreſſneſs of precept or example? If not, is not the practiſe of it traditional, and the product of humane diſcourſe, as well, and as much, as the Baptizing of Infants? And do not they who practiſe it, preſume every whit as much, or rather far more, upon their own judgments and underſtandings, in making Infant-Baptiſm to be a meer nullity or nothing, the Scripture no where giving any ſuch ſentence, nor any ſyllable, letter, or tittle of any ſuch ſentence, againſt it, as they who make it an Ordinance of God, or rather (to ſpeak more properly) a meet and neceſſary adminiſtration of an Ordinance of God? conſidering, 1. That Baptiſm it ſelf, <hi>i. e.</hi> the external act of Baptiſm, rightly ſo called, (whether it be dipping, waſhing, or ſprinkling, is not material to the caſe now in hand, Infants being alike capable of them all) is by expreſſneſs of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, an Ordinance, or appointment of God; And 2. That Infants
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118444:12"/>
(at leaſt, of Beleevers) not onely, are no where excluded by God from part and fellowſhip in the Adminiſtration, but are in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places and paſſages more then overtured as the moſt proper and meet Subjects of it?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <head>XXVI.</head>
               <p>Whether, was not a <hi>dying the death of the uncircumciſed</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ezek. 28. 10. 31, 18. 32. 19. 21.</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, and ſo a being puniſhed with <hi>the uncircumciſed</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Jer. 9. 25. Ezek. 32 19. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1 Sam. 17. 26, 36.</note>, matter of threatning, and an intimation of anger and diſpleaſure in God; importing, that the lives of uncircumciſed perſons in the world, were nothing ſo precious in his ſighte, nor ſo tenderly watched over, nor ſo carefully protected and preſerved by him, as the lives of thoſe who were circumciſed? yea did not the threatning of the <hi>uncircumciſed man-child, that his ſoul ſhould be cut off from his people, becauſe he had broken Gods Covenant,</hi> (Gen. 17. 4.) plainly ſignifie, that children uncircumciſed, were much more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious unto the ſtroke of death from the hand of God, then they would have been, or need to have been, if circumciſed? If then it be ſuppoſed, that Baptiſm is altogether as neceſſary, or of as high eſteem with God, under the Goſpel, as Circumciſion was under the Law, can it reaſonably be judged, or thought, that he is as ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and providentially watchful, over the lives of children or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, unbaptized, as he is over the lives of thoſe who are baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? And if ſo, do not they who neglect or refuſe, the baptizing of their children, reject the counſel of God againſt their lives and preſervations, depriving them of that Intereſt in the ſpeciall Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God for their peace and ſafety, which they might, and ought to, intitle them unto by Baptizing them? And when chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren unbaptized are taken away by any ſudden or ſtrange hand of death, have not the Parents juſt cauſe to queſtion, whether they were not acceſſary to their death, by leaving them amongſt the unbaptized ones of the world?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <head>XXVII.</head>
               <p>Whether were not the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> notwithſtanding the expreſs and ſtrict Inſtitution and command of God for the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſing of the Males amongſt them on the eight day, blameleſs under their non-Circumciſion for forty yeers together, upon the account of that bodily inconvenience and danger, whereunto Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, during their journying and travel through the wilderneſs, would in the eye of Reaſon have expoſed them? Or had they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118444:12"/>
not ſinned, by tempting the Providence of God, if under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or plea, of the commandment of God for their circumciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they had cauſed either themſelves, or their children, to be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, during ſuch their travel, how long ſoever it had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued? If ſo, do not they ſin by tempting the Providence of God who are Authors, either to themſelves or others, of being dipped over head and eares in water, where, and when, and whilſt, ſuch dipping cannot, both according to the principles of Reaſon, the natural courſe and operation of ſecond cauſes, yea, and frequent experience it ſelf, but endanger either their healths, or lives, or both; yea though this be upon a pretext, or plea, that ſuch dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping is the Inſtitution, or command of God?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <head>XXVIII.</head>
               <p>Whether doth the requiring of Faith, or a profeſſion of Faith to be made by men and women in order to their being Baptized, by any better conſequence prove, that Infants without ſuch Faith, or Profeſſion of Faith, ought not to be baptized, then <hi>Pauls</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, which he commended to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> viz. <hi>That if any would not work, neither ſhould he eat</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">2 Theſ. 3. 10.</note>, proveth, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought children to eat, unleſs they work too, as well as men or women, who are healthfull and ſtrong, and ſo capable of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? Or then this prohibition of God of old concerning the eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Paſchal Lamb, <hi>No uncircumciſed perſon ſhall eat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 12. 48.</note>, proveth, that his intent was, that no perſon of woman kind, whether yong, or old, though daughters of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſanctified, ſhould eat thereof?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <head>XXIX.</head>
               <p>Whether, if dipping, or a diſpoſing, or conveying of the whole body under water, be of the eſſence and neceſſity of Baptiſm, are not they rather Se-Baptiſts, or Self-Baptiſers, then Baptiſed (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of Chriſt) by others, who themſelves convey or dip under water their whole bodies, leaving onely their heads above the water to be bowed down, forced, or thruſt under wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by the Baptizer? Or is there either <hi>vola</hi> or <hi>veſtigium,</hi> little or much of ſuch a practiſe as this to be found in the Scriptures, where they ſpeak of Baptiſm? Or can he in any tolerable ſence or conſtruction be ſaid to be the Architect, or builder of a Turret, or Steeple, who onely ſetteth the Weather-cock on the top of it,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118444:13"/>
and not rather he, who buildeth the reſt of the body and Fabrick hereof?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <head>XXX.</head>
               <p>Whether, is there any particular or expreſs Inſtitution of Baptiſm to be found in the Scriptures; I mean, any ſuch Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as there is of Circumciſion, and the Paſſover in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, or of the Lords Supper in the New; or which preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth and determineth all circumſtances eſſentiall unto Baptiſm, as all the other do preſcribe and determine all circumſtances eſſentially requiſite to their adminiſtrations reſpectively? If not, do not they <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, make themſelves wiſe above that which is written, &amp; (conſtructively) obtrude upon the conſciences of men an Inſtitution of their own, in the Name of the Ordinance and Inſtitution of God, who undertake to preſcribe and determine, either particularity of ſubject, or manner of Adminiſtration, in Baptiſm?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <head>XXXI.</head>
               <p>Whether did not they amongſt us, (or at leaſt the generality, and far greater part of them) who have accepted and entred into the way of new-Baptiſm, and at preſent walk in it, receive that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Faith from God, together with all thoſe Graces or fruits of the Spirit, whereby they are, whatſoever they are in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and towards God; did they not (I ſay) receive all this bleſſedneſs from God, under the diſpenſation of their Infant-Baptiſm? Or is there one of a thouſand of thoſe ingaged in this new way, who have added ſo much as the breadth of the leaſt hair of their heads un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their former growth and ſtature in Chriſt, I do not ſay, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or means of this their new Ingagement, but ſince, or after it? Or is there not a viſible and manifeſt change for the worſe in very many of them, and this (in all probability) occaſioned by an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verweening conceit, that by means of their new baptizing, they are more excellent then their Neighbours, and too holy and near unto God to ſuffer themſelves to be numbred amongſt the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of other Churches? Or do ſuch things as theſe any way fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour or ſtrengthen the claim, which their way of Baptizing makes of being a Divine Ordinance, yea the onely true Baptiſm of God?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118444:13"/>
               <head>XXXII.</head>
               <p>Whether, amongſt men and women, whoſe conſciences have at any time been ſurprized with a Religious conceit of a neceſſity of new Baptiſm, and have accordingly ſubmitted to it, have not the moſt Chriſtianly-meek and humble on the one hand, and the moſt Judicious and Learned on the other hand, upon a little experience of this way, grown cool, and very indifferent in their thoughts about it? yea and many of them repented of their ſurprizal and <note place="margin">Vide Scultet. Annal. Anno 1521, &amp; 1525, &amp;c.</note> weakneſs in this kind, as <hi>Johannes O<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>colampadius, Johannes Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kius, Johannes Gaſter,</hi> men of great learning, worth, and humility, (with ſeveral others) about <hi>Luthers</hi> dayes; yea and ſome of like Character, of late amongſt our ſelves, who might be named, if it were neceſſary or meet?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <head>XXXIII.</head>
               <p>Whether, becauſe Baptiſm is termed the <hi>Baptiſm of Repentance</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e. for,</hi> or towards, <hi>the remiſſion of ſins, (Mar,</hi> 1. 4.) doth it a whit more follow that children ought not to be Baptized, either becauſe they cannot repent, or becauſe they have no ſins to be remitted unto them, then it doth, that children ought not to have been circumciſed; conſidering that <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> the nature of it, and counſell of God in it, conſidered, may as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be called, the Circumciſion of Repentance, for the remiſſion of ſins, as Baptiſm, The Baptiſm of Repentance for the Remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſins; yea, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf giveth a definition of Circumciſion, for ſubſtance and import of matter, the ſame with that of Baptiſm, when he calleth it, <hi>the ſeal of the righteouſneſs of Faith, (Rom.</hi> 4. 11.) and however, Children are altogether as uncapable of Faith, as they are of Repentance; and have no more need of the righteouſneſs of Faith, then they have of remiſſion of ſins, theſe being but one and the ſame thing?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <head>XXXIV.</head>
               <p>Whether, when the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh thus to his new Converts, <hi>Acts 2. 38, 39. Repent, and be baptized every one of you in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt for the remiſsion of ſins, and ye ſhall receive the gift of the Holy Ghoſt: For the promiſe is to you, and to your children, &amp;c.</hi> Doth he ſo much enjoyn or exhort them to Repent in order to their being baptized, as encourage them both unto the one duty, and the other, upon the account of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118444:14"/>
the Promiſe relating both to them, and their children, and the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of its being fulfilled and made good unto them both, upon their Repentance, and ſubmiſſion unto Baptiſm, reſpectively? And if their title unto, and intereſt in, the Promiſe, be a ground or motive unto them [the Parents] to be baptized; is not the like title and intereſt, in the children, a ground and motive alſo why they ſhould be baptized?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <head>XXXV.</head>
               <p>Whether doth God ſmell the aſſemblies [or, in the aſſemblies] of thoſe, who judg themſelves the onely Baptized perſons under Heaven, with any ſuch pleaſure or delight, as he <hi>ſmelleth</hi> many the aſſemblies of thoſe, who are called Unbaptized, by the other? Or are the Church-meetings of the former filled with the glory and preſence of God at any ſuch rate, or to any ſuch degree, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the holy aſſemblies of the latter are? Or are there any ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations of the Spirit, either in gifts, or in graces, in the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of the Baptized, as there are amongſt thoſe, who bear the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbaptized?</hi> Or are <hi>the powers of the world to come</hi> any wayes ſo buſie, active and ſtirring in the Churches, which call themſelves Baptized, as they are in many the congregations, which are caſt out to the Gentiles, as unclean and Un-baptized? Or is not that good word of God, (the Scriptures,) as a ſealed book in many the aſſemblies of the former, whereas even the deep things of God contained in it, are by the Holy Ghoſt revealed in many Churches of the latter? Or are ſuch differences as theſe, of no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, intereſt, or import, to umpire or decide the controverſie depending between the two Baptiſms?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <head>XXXVI.</head>
               <p>Whether are not children oft-times in Scripture comprehended under, or with, their Parents, men and women, &amp;c. where they are not expreſly mentioned, or named; and particularly <hi>Joſ. 25. 26. 1 Cor.</hi> 10. 1, 2 <note n="*" place="margin">See alſo Mat: 4: 4: &amp; 12: 12: (beſides many others.)</note> even as Subjects are under the names of their Kings, and Families and Deſcents, under the names of their Heads? &amp;c. Yea, are not both women and children to be underſtood, where men only are named? (See <hi>Mark 6. 44. Joh.</hi> 6. 10. compared with <hi>Mat.</hi> 14. 21.) If ſo, doth not this argument or plea againſt Infant-Baptiſm, halt right-down; In the Scriptures we find no mention of the Baptizing of Children, either by Chriſt, or his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118444:14"/>
or any others: therefore no children were Baptized by them? Indeed if we could here find no mention of the Baptizing either men, or women, then the non-finding any mention neither of children baptized, were an argument of ſome authority and credit to prove, that there was none of this capacity, or age, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <head>XXXVII.</head>
               <p>Whether, in caſe it could be proved (which yet hath not been proved, nor, I am full of belief, ever will be, the proofs lying much more ſtrong and pregnant for it, then againſt it) that there were no children baptized during the Apoſtles days, doth it by any whit better conſequence follow from hence, that therefore chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ought not now to be (or might not then, as to point of ſimple lawfulneſs, have been) baptized, then from the non-circumciſing of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> children for forty years together <hi>(Joſ. 5. 5.) viz,</hi> during the whole time of their journeying through the wilderneſs, it follows, that neither ought they to have been circumciſed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, eſpecially conſidering, 1. That there may be many more, and more weighty, reaſons (though poſſibly unknown unto us) why neither <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor his Apoſtles, ſhould baptize children in their days, though the lawfulneſs, yea and neceſſity of their bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, at other times, and in ſome caſes, be ſuppoſed, then there was why the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhould omit the circumciſing of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for thoſe forty years together, which were ſpecified; And, 2. That the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that he <hi>was not ſent to baptize, but to preach the Gospel;</hi> [meaning, that baptizing, whether perſonally, or by commiſſioning or delegating others hereunto, was not only not the principal, but not any conſiderable end of his ſending, but the publiſhing and preaching of the Goſpel,] for if he was not ſent to <hi>baptize</hi> [meaning, neither one age, nor one ſex, or other,] neither could he be ſent to baptize children; and if he was not ſent to baptize, either one, or other, [in the ſence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared,] neither was the Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, nor the reſt of the Apoſtles ſent about this work (in ſuch a ſence,) What marvel then is it, that Perſons ſent about matters incomparably greater and more weighty, ſhould not be ſo throughly intent upon things of a ſecondary and lighter conſequence, as to proſecute them to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of what they lawfully might, yea and in caſe of a lighter
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118444:15"/>
burthen upon their ſhoulder in thoſe more important affairs, had been bound to do? Or are there not many caſes, wherein a man may <hi>break a Law, [i. e.</hi> a ſtanding Law, or a Law provided for ordinary caſes] <hi>and yet be blameleſs?</hi> yea and ſome caſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he may do it with commendation? See <hi>Mat. 12. 3, 4, 5. 2 Cor. 11. 17, 18, 21. 1 Joh.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <head>XXXVIII.</head>
               <p>Whether is not that principle, or humor, in the children of new Baptiſm, of making ſuch ſacred treaſure hereof as generally they do, eſtimating <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelf, and acceptance with God, by it, counting all perſons unclean and unholy, and not meet for Church-communion, who ſubmit not unto it &amp;c. thus making Gods <hi>Nothing,</hi> their <hi>All things;</hi> is not this humor (I ſay) the expreſs character of ſuch perſons in all ages, who have unduly, and without cauſe, broken the bands of unity, love, and peace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they had been ſometimes bound up in a ſweet bundle of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity with other Churches, to walk in ſome crooked and by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of particular choyce by themſelves, to the offence, grief, and reproach of thoſe Churches, from which, upon ſuch an account, they rent themſelves? Or did not <hi>Eunomius</hi> the Heretique, who maintained this Doctrine (by way of diſſent from the Churches of <hi>Chriſt) That the Son of God is altogether unlike the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt unlike the Son,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the groundleſſneſs and errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of it, yet attribute this high and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred priviledg unto it, that whoſoever belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it could not poſſibly periſh, how wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoever he lived <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eunomius</hi>—defendit hanc haereſin, diſſimilem per omnia Pa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aſſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ens Filium, &amp; Filio Spiritum ſanctum. Fertur etiam uſque adeo fuiſſe bonis moribus inimicus, ut aſſeveraret, quod nihil cuique obeſſet quorumlibet perpetratio ac perſeverantia peccator rum, ſi hujus, quae ab il o docebatur, fidei particeps effet. <hi>Aug.</hi> de Haereſ. c. 54</note>? Or did not the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> aſcribe all <hi>Chriſtian</hi> worth and excellency to their Sect and Opinions, <hi>denying that there was any true Church of Chriſt in all the World, but only amongst them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing all other Chriſtians, but themſelves,</hi> and yet giving entertainment to <hi>moſt vile and wicked men in their Communion</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Nam illi [Donatiſtae] dicebant univerſum orbem Chriſtianum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam non habere—Deinde, qui prae le omnes alios Chriſtianos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnabant, ſeveritatem cenſurae in ſuos relaxaverant, &amp; in ſuis coetibus homines impuriſſimos, ut Optato<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Gildoniano<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Primianoſque patie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur. <hi>P. Mar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> Loc. Claſſ. 4. c. 5. ſect. 15.</note>, as if the giving of the right hand of fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip unto them in their way, rendered men religious and holy, in the midſt of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118444:15"/>
practice of all wickedneſs? Or did not <hi>Theophanes</hi> attribute ſo much to the uſe of Images in Religious Worſhip, that he cenſured <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperor (by-named, <hi>Copronymus)</hi> as an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate from God, for oppoſing Images, and Idol-worſhip <note n="c" place="margin">Theophanes Miſcel. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>c.</hi> ult, <hi>&amp;</hi> Joſeph Mede, <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of latter times.</hi> p. 131</note>? Or did not ſome <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Teachers labor to poſſeſs men with ſuch an high opinion of their Tradition and practice of waſhing hands before meat, as that they ought to look upon him, who ſhould neglect or not obſerve it, <hi>as one that lieth with an Harlot</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ainſworth</hi> in Levit. 15. 12</note>? Or did not the Author and Abettors of that hideous Doctrine, That God ſeeth no ſin in perſons juſtified, pronounce all thoſe <hi>Traytors to the Blood of Chriſt,</hi> that held the contrary <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>P. Gunter,</hi> Sermon of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, printed <hi>anno</hi> 1615. Preface to the Reader, p. 3.</note>? Or did not the Monks, who (generally) were the compilers of the Hiſtories of this Nation in former times, place ſo much of the very eſſence (as it were) of Religion, in reverencing Biſhops and Monks of theſe times, that (as <hi>Daniel,</hi> a late <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtorian obſerveth) <hi>they perſonated all their Princes, either Religious, or irreligious, as they humored, or offended, the Biſhops rochet, and the Monks bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Smectymnuus</hi> Vindicat. p 8.</note>? Or did not <hi>Theodore</hi> the Abbot, give this advice to a Monk, who (as himſelf informed the ſaid Abbot) was threatened by the Devil, that he would never ceaſe vexing and moleſting him by temptations unto fornication, until he left worſhiping the Image of the bleſſed Virgin; did not (I ſay) this Abbot give this advice to the Monk in his caſe, that <hi>it were better that he frequented all the ſtews in the City, then not to worſhip Chriſt and his Mother in an Image</hi> 
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mede,</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy of latter times, p. 140</note>? Or do not all theſe inſtances (with many more that might be added unto them, of like conſideration) plainly ſhew and prove, that to conceit and ſpeak glorious things, of any private opinion, or by-practice, is an argument of very great probability (at leaſt) that this, both opinion, and practice, are mens own, or from themſelves, and not from God, or agreeable unto his Word? Or are there not ſeveral grounds, and theſe near at hand, very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial and weighty, to ſtrengthen this conjecture? yea and when the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, that <hi>thoſe that are unlearned and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, pervert,</hi> or <hi>wreſt, the Scriptures, to their own deſtruction,</hi> doth not this great danger or miſery ariſe from hence, that they who do wreſt the Scriptures, are inordinately conceited of, and confidently reſt and build upon, ſuch notions, ſences, and opinions,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118444:16"/>
which are engendered and begotten in their minds or conſciences, by this <hi>Scripture-wreſting?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <head>XXXIX.</head>
               <p>Whether, is not the Teſtimony of that worthy, zealous, and learned Martyr M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>John Philpot</hi> (recorded in a letter written by him to a freind of his, a priſoner in Newgate at the ſame time) wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy credit and beliefe, wherein he affirms, that <hi>Auxentius,</hi> an <hi>Arrian heretique, (with his adherents) was</hi> one <hi>of the firſt that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the Baptiſm of children, and next after him, Pelagius the heretique?</hi> Or can Auguſtin be ſuſpected, at leaſt by thoſe who have any Competent knowledg of his unparallel'd candor and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, to ſpeake any thing but the truth, when he ſaith that the Baptizing of Infants was a cuſtom of the Chriſtian Church in his days, <hi>Salubriter firmata, wholſomely</hi> ratified and confirmed <note n="a" place="margin">De peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num meritis &amp;c. <hi>lib. 3. c.</hi> 13.</note>: in another place, That <hi>the univerſal Church of Chriſt always held, or retained the cuſtom of Baptizing</hi> children <hi>even from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and that it was not inſtituted by any Council; and that no Chriſtian would ſay that children were impertinently, or in vain baptized</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Quod tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum cenet uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitas Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. Cum par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vuli infantes baptizantur, nullus Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anorum dixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit eos inaniter baptizari. Et ſi quiſquam in hac re authoritatem divinam quaerat, quanquam quod univerſa tenet Eccleſia, nec conciliis inſtitutum, ſed ſemper retentum eſt, non niſi authoritate Apoſtolica traditum rectiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me creditur, tamen veraciter continere poſſumus quid valeat in parvulis baptiſmi ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ex circumciſione carnis, quam prior populus accepit, &amp;c. <hi>Aug. de Baptiſmo</hi> contra <hi>Donat. l. 4. c.</hi> 23.</note> (with much more to like purpoſe.) Or is not the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Ierome</hi> worthy to be received, who affirmeth, that he (with the Orthodox <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in his days) <hi>held one Baptiſm, which they affirmed ought to be adminiſtred in the ſame Sacramental words unto Infants,</hi> and thoſe of riper years. <note n="c" place="margin">Baptiſma unum tenemus, quod iiſdem ſacramenti verbis in inſantibus, quibus etiam in majoribus, aſſerimus eſſe celebrandum. <hi>Hieron.</hi> t. 4. Symboli explan. ad <hi>Dama<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="part">
               <head>XL.</head>
               <p>Whether can it proved from the Scriptures, or by any argument whatſoever, that either Faith, or a profeſſion, of Faith, is either the only, or the beſt ground, either <hi>diviſim</hi> or <hi>conjunctim,</hi> whereon to build a Baptiſmal adminiſtration? Or whether did not the Apoſtles and thoſe who baptized by their direction and order in their days, inſiſt upon believing, and profeſſion of believing, with men and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118444:16"/>
women, who were willing, or deſirous, to be baptized, onely for want of better, and of better aſſured grounds, whereon to proceed to the baptizing of ſuch perſons? Or did they inſiſt upon either of theſe qualifications, in reference to the ſaid Adminiſtration, ſimply and meerly, as, or becauſe, they were ſuch, or in reſpect of their poſitive and abſolute nature, and not rather, in reſpect of their relative natures, or properties, <hi>viz.</hi> as they were ſignificative, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarative unto them [the Baptizers] and unto others, of the happy eſtate of thoſe in whome they were found, as being perſons in Grace and favour with God? Otherwiſe, how could the Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, having no ſuch Faith, as that which the Apoſtles and their Baptiſts required (together with the profeſſion of it) in thoſe, whom they Baptized, be a meet or duly qualified ſubject of this Adminiſtration? Or will any man preſume to ſay, that he was Baptized, either contrary unto, or beſides, the rule, or mind of God, touching perſons meet to be Baptized, eſpecially when as himſelf renders this account why he ſubmitted himſelf unto, and deſired, Biptiſm, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>it became him to fulfil all RIGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SNES</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 3. 15</note>? And beſides, is it not altogether irrational to imagine or think, that Faith ſhould be required in order unto Baptiſm, ſimply for Faiths ſake? or profeſſion of Faith, meerly for this Profeſſions ſake? Or that God, or <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhould enjoyn a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirement of them upon ſuch a ſlender account as this? Or that they would ever have been nominated by them for qualifications unto Baptiſm in men and women, unleſs they had been ſo ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative or declarative, as hath been ſaid, I mean, of the gracious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of ſuch perſons, in whom they are, with God? Yea or unleſs they had been declarative in this kind, upon the beſt terms, whereof perſons newly converted from ways of ſin unto God, are capable, there being no other way, or means, more effectual or proper for ſuch perſons to make known their ſtanding, or being, in the favor of God, unto others, then by a profeſſion of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> how ever it be moſt true, that even ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations as theſe, many times deceive thoſe, who accept of them, and truſt to them, though without ſin in thoſe, who are ſo decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? Now then, if Faith, and profeſſion of Faith, qualifie for Baptiſm, meerly in reſpect of their relation, and as they report
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118444:17"/>
(with ſuch credit as appertains to them, and is meet to be given them by men) the perſons in whom they are, and from whom they proceed, to be in an eſtate of Grace and Favor with God, is it not as evident as the Sun at noon day, that all perſons of mankind, who are, or may be known by more aſſured teſtimonies and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, then any mans own profeſſion of his own Faith amounts unto, to be in the ſame, or like grace and favor with God, to be every whit as regularly, and as compleatly qualified for Baptiſm, as the greateſt and loudeſt Profeſſors of their Faith under Heaven? If ſo, are not Infants and Children before the commiſsion of actual <note place="margin">That Children are in favor with God, and ſo declared, ſee briefly <hi>Redemp. Redeemed,</hi> p. 330, 516, 517.</note> ſin, to whom God himſelf hath given a loud and expreſs teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from Heaven, that they are in grace and favor with him, and that <hi>to them,</hi> and ſuch as they are, <hi>belongeth the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, &amp;c.</hi> are they not (I ſay) upon this account fully declared to be, not only or ſimply, regular and meet ſubjects of Baptiſm, but ſubjects in this kind of the higheſt, and moſt unqueſtionable qualifications?</p>
               <q>For by one Spirit <hi>[not by one, or the ſame, water, or dipping]</hi> we are all baptized into one Body.</q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 12. 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>What therefore God hath joyned together, let no man put aſunder.</q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 19. 6.</bibl>
               <q>Baptiſmus ſine impietatis ſcelere conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mni nequit: &amp; graviſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam reprehenſionem coràm Deo &amp; hominibus merentur, qui tantum beneficium differunt, vel ſibi, vel ſuis liberis accipere.</q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>za Opuſc. p. 334.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Tingimus pueros, tingimus provectioris aetatis:—Nullam aeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem praecepit Baptiſmo Chriſtus, ſed neque ullam vetuit, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Norlingenſis Paſtores.</q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Scultet. Annal. Anno 1525.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
