<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter written by Sir Richard Grenvile (under his own hand) to an honorable person in the city of London, concerning the affairs of the west. Published by authority.</title>
            <author>Grenville, Richard, Sir, 1600-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E333_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200757</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861416</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861416</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113550</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A85684)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113550)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 54:E333[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter written by Sir Richard Grenvile (under his own hand) to an honorable person in the city of London, concerning the affairs of the west. Published by authority.</title>
                  <author>Grenville, Richard, Sir, 1600-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Husband, printer to the Honorable House of Commons.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>April 17. 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The letter is dated at end: 9. April, 1646.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Personal narratives --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113550:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:113550:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <p>A LETTER Written by Sir Richard Grenvile <hi>(under his own hand)</hi> To an Honorable Perſon in the City OF LONDON, Concerning the Affairs of the WEST.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for <hi>Edward Husband,</hi> Printer to the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe of Commons. <hi>April</hi> 17. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:113550:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113550:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <head>A LETTER Written By Sir <hi>Richard Greenvile,</hi> under his own hand, to an Honorable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the City of <hi>London, Concerning the Affairs of the</hi> WEST.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>FOrmer obligations have moved me to repreſent unto you my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate ſervice: I am now at <hi>Nantes</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and about to depart hence toward <hi>Italy</hi> for the war againſt the Turk (not much unlike the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py war of <hi>England.)</hi> My Lord, I truly value you in the number of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113550:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
my beſt and honorable Friends, and therefore have preſumed to ſend you herewith a narrative truth concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the former proceedings of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the VVeſt of <hi>England,</hi> though not ſo particular, as the evil managing thereof deſerved: ſince which, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Ieaſt chanced at <hi>Peurin</hi> (a town nigh <hi>Pendennis</hi> caſtle in <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wal)</hi> for <hi>Hopton</hi> with his new forces (lately before) taking a ſtrange af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright at a party of the Parliaments forces at <hi>Torrington</hi> in <hi>Devon,</hi> and flying into <hi>Cornwal</hi> with his men di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed ſeveral wayes, like a wilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gooſe chace; the ſad News thereof made the Prince command the Earl of <hi>Branford</hi> and Lord <hi>Culpepper</hi> with all ſpeed to meet the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> and Lord <hi>Capel</hi> at <hi>Wadebridge,</hi> nigh
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113550:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
the heart of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> to adviſe on af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs for the ſafety of the VVeſt (I think to ſhut the ſtable door when the horſe was gone) but <hi>Culpepper</hi> in his haſte and way, finding ſome Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men merry and drinking in <hi>Peurin</hi> town, he would needs make one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and ſo did, till night came, and then <hi>Bacchus</hi> prevailing, <hi>Culpeppers</hi> Eloquence diſpleaſed Mr. <hi>Slingsby,</hi> by which grew a quarrel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them two onely, and at bare fiſtycuffs they were a good ſpace, till the company parted them, and then <hi>Culpepper</hi> and <hi>Slingsby,</hi> in the Moon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine, got them into the garden, and like two Cocks at the end of a Battel, not able to ſtand wel, offer'd &amp; peck'd at one another, till the weight of <hi>Slingsbies</hi> head drew him to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113550:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
ground, which advantage <hi>Culpepper</hi> took hold of, and by it got <hi>Slingsbies</hi> ſword, and then like St. <hi>George,</hi> made more ſuch triumphant flouriſhes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Slingsby,</hi> then a German Fencer at the begining of a Prize; but by good fortune, the reſt of the aſſociates came in, and eaſily perſwaded the Duelliſts to end the quarrel by the cup again, which ſervice continued till the next day, with divers and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral bouts at fiſtycuffs: the next day (about ten of the clock) they having red Herrings and muſtard for Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, <hi>Culpepper</hi> again gave <hi>Slingsby</hi> diſtaſte, whereon he threw a diſh of muſtard in <hi>Culpeppers</hi> face (taking his Noſe for a red Herring) which procur'd another grievous incounter, in ſuch ſort, that the Market people
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113550:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
(to part the fray) thronged the houſe full, whereby that alſo was taken up, and the ſaucy Lord fain to get his muſtard-Face, Eyes, Beard, Band, and Coat waſh'd; and about four of the next evening, <hi>Culpepper</hi> rid on in his haſty journey to overtake the Lord of <hi>Branford,</hi> who rid chafing &amp; ſtaying for him above twenty four hours in his way. Such a Privie-Councellor will ſoon finiſh his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters buſineſſe one way, preferring his own delights before the important buſineſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that concerns the ſafety of the Prince, &amp;c. This ſtory is indeed very true in every particular, and ſo I leave it with you, and depart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humble Servant, R: GRENVILE.</signed>
               <dateline>Nantes in France, <date>9. <hi>April,</hi> 1646. new ſtile.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
