<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An inquisition after blood. To the Parliament in statu quo nunc, and to the Army regnant; or any other whether Royallist, Presbyterian, Independent or Leveller, whom it may concern.</title>
            <author>Howell, James, 1594?-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3080</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E531_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15284</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859832</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859832</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111931</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A86624)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111931)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 82:E531[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An inquisition after blood. To the Parliament in statu quo nunc, and to the Army regnant; or any other whether Royallist, Presbyterian, Independent or Leveller, whom it may concern.</title>
                  <author>Howell, James, 1594?-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeer, 1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to James Howell.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 17th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Angela Berkley</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Angela Berkley</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111931:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN
INQUISITION
AFTER
BLOOD.</p>
            <p>To the PARLIAMENT <hi>in ſtatu quo nunc,</hi>
AND
To the ARMY Regnant;
Or any other whether Royalliſt, Presbyterian, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent
or Leveller, whom it may concern.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Blood</hi> is a crying ſin, but that of Kings</l>
                  <l>Cryes loudeſt for revenge, and ruine brings.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeer, 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:111931:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111931:2"/>
            <head>AN
INQUISITION
AFTER
BLOOD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſcope of this ſhort diſcourſe is to
make ſome reſearches after Truth,
and to rectifie the world according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in point of opinion, ſpecially
touching the firſt <hi>Author</hi> and Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor
of the late ugly war in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
which brought with it ſuch an
inundation of blood, and ſo let in
ſo huge a torrent of miſchiefs to ruſh upon us. There
be many, and they not only Presbyterians and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,
but <hi>Cavaliers</hi> alſo, who think that the King had
taken the guilt of all this blood upon himſelfe, in regard
of that Conceſſion he paſſed in the preamble of the
late Treaty at the <hi>Iſle of Wight;</hi> The aime of this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
is to cleere that point, but in ſo temperate a way, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111931:3"/>
I hope 'twill give no cauſe of exception, much leſſe of
offence to any: the blood that's ſought after here, ſhall
not be mingled with <hi>gaule,</hi> much leſſe with anie ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome
at all.</p>
            <p>We know there is no Principle either in <hi>Divinity, Law,</hi>
or <hi>Phyloſophie,</hi> but may be wreſted to a wrong ſenſe;
there is no truth ſo demonſtrative and cleere, but may
be ſubject to cavillations; no Tenet ſo plaine, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe
inferences may be drawne out of it; ſuch a fate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell
that preambular Conceſſion His Majeſty paſſed at
the Tranſactions of the late Treaty, in that <hi>he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd
therein that the two Houſes of Parliament were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated
to undertake a war in their owne juſt and lawfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
&amp;c. and that therefore all Oaths, Declarations, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
public Inſtruments againſt the Houſes of Parliament,
or any for adhering to them, &amp;c. be declared null, ſuppreſſed,
and forbidden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, His Majeſty paſſed this grant, but with
this weighty conſideration, as it had reference to two
ends.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to ſmoothen and facilitate things thereby to
ope a paſſage, and pave the way to a happy peace, which
this poor Iland did ſo thirſt after, having been ſo long
glutted with civill blood.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that it might conduce to the further ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
and the indemnifying of the two Houſes of Parle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
with all their inſtruments, aſſiſtants, and adherents,
and ſo rid them of all jealouſies, and fear (of future dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers)
which ſtill lodg'd within them. Now touching
the expreſſions and words of this Grant, they were not
his owne, nor did he give order for the dictating or
penning thereof; the King was not the <hi>Author</hi> of them,
but an <hi>Aſſenter</hi> only unto them: nor was He or his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
accus'd, or as much as mentioned in any of them, to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111931:3"/>
draw the leaſt guilt upon themſelves. Beſides, He paſs'd
them as he doth all Lawes aud Acts of Parlement, which
in caſe of abſence another may do for him in his <hi>politic</hi>
capacity, therefore they cannot prejudice his <hi>perſon</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
way. I am loth to ſay that he condeſcended to this
Grant,
<q>—Cùm ſtrict a novacula ſupra,</q>
When the razor was as it were at his throat, when ther
was an Army of about thirty thouſand effect if Horſe and
Foot that were in motion againſt him, when his Perſon
had continued under a black long lingring reſtraint, and
dangerous menacing Petitions and Papers daily obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
againſt him. Moreover, His Majeſty paſs'd this
Conceſſion with theſe two proviſos and reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</p>
            <p>Firſt, that it ſhould be of no vertu or validity at all,
till the whole Treaty were intirely conſummated.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that he might when he pleas'd inlarge and
cleer the truth with the reſervedneſs of his meaning here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
by public Declaration: Now the Treaty being confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly
huddled up, without diſcuſſing, or as much as recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
any Propoſition from himſelf as was capitulated,
(and reciprocal Propoſals are of the eſſence of all Treaties)
it could neither bind him, or turne any way to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage:
Therfore under favour, ther was too much
haſt us'd by the Parlement, to draw that hipothetick
or proviſional Conceſſion to the form of an Act ſo
ſuddenly after in the very heat of the Treaty, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
His Majeſties knowledge, or the leaſt intimation of
his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Add hereunto, that this <hi>Grant</hi> was but a meer pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bular
Propoſition, 'twas not of the eſſence of the Treaty
it ſelf: And as the Philoſophers and Schoolemen tell
us, there is <hi>no valid proof can be drawn out of Proemes, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troductions</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:111931:4"/>
or <hi>Corallaries</hi> in any ſcience, but out of the
poſitive aſſertions and body of the Text, which is only
argument-proof; ſo in the Conſtitutions and Lawes of
England, as alſo in all accuſations and charges, forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
prefaces and preambles (which commonly <hi>weak</hi>
cauſes want moſt) are not pleadable: and though they
uſe to be firſt in place, like gentlemen-Uſhers, yet are they
laſt in dignity, as alſo in framing, nor had they ever the
force of Lawes, but may be term'd their attendants to
make way for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beſides, ther's not a ſyllable in this preface which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales
or connives at any former Law of the Land, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
thoſe Lawes</hi> that ſo ſtrictly inhibit Engliſh Subjects to
raiſe armes againſt their liege Lord the King, <hi>and thoſe
Lawes</hi> è contrario, <hi>which</hi> exempt from all dangers, penalties
or moleſtation any Subject that adheres to the perſon of the
King in any cauſe or quarrell whatſoever, <hi>are ſtill in force.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, this <hi>introductory</hi> Conceſſion of the Kings,
wherein he is contented to declare, That the two Houſes
were neceſſitated to take Armes for their defence, may be
ſaid to have relation to the <hi>neceſsity, à parte pòſt,</hi> not <hi>à par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
antè: ſelf-defence</hi> is the univerſall Law of Nature, and
it extends to all other creatures, as well as the rationall:
As the ſluent Roman Orator in that ſentence of his,
which is accounted among the Critiques the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenteſt
that ever drop'd from him; <hi>Eſt enim haec non ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,
ſed nata Lex, quam non didicimus, accepimus, legimus,
verùm ex natura ipſa arripuimus, hauſimus, expreſsimus,
ad quam non docti, ſed facti, non inſtituti, ſed imbuti ſumus,
ut ſi vita noſtra in</hi> &amp;c. For this (meaning ſelf-defence)
is not a written, but a Law born with us; A Law which
we have not learnt, receiv'd or read, but that which we
have ſuck'd, drawn forth, and wrung out of Nature her
ſelf; A Law to which we are not taught, but made unto,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111931:4"/>
wherewith we are not inſtructed, but indued withall,
that if our lifes be in jeopardy, &amp;c. we may repell force
by force. Therefore when the Houſe of Parliament had
drawn upon them a neceſſity of ſelf-defence (and I could
have wiſh'd it had been againſt any other but their own
Soveraign Prince) his Majeſty was contented to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
that neceſſity. As for example: A man of war
meets with a Marchant man at Sea, he makes towards
him, and aſſaults him; The Marchant man having a good
ſtout veſſell under him, and reſolute generous Seamen,
bears up againſt him, gives him a whole broad ſide, and
ſhoots him 'twixt wind and water; ſo there happens a
furious fight betwixt them, which being ended, the
Marchant cannot deny but that the man of war, though
the firſt Aſſailant, was neceſſitated to fight, and that juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in his own defence, which neceſſity he drew upon
himſelf, and ſo was excuſable, <hi>à poſteriori,</hi> not <hi>à priori;</hi>
As the Civilians ſpeak of a clandeſtine marriage, <hi>Fieri
non debuit, ſed factum valet;</hi> It ought not to have been,
but being done 'tis valid: whereunto relates another
ſaying, <hi>Multa ſunt quae non niſi peracta approbantur.</hi> There
are many things which are not allowable till they are
paſſ'd.</p>
            <p>The Kings of <hi>France</hi> have had ſundry civill warrs, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
bloudy encounters and claſhes with their Subjects,
ſpecially the laſt King <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenth, which turn'd
all at laſt to his advantage; among other Treaties upon
that of <hi>Loudu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he was by force of Article to publiſh an
Edict, <hi>Dons lequel le Roy approuvoit tout le paſſé comme ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant
eſté fait pour ſon ſervice,</hi> &amp;c. Whrein the King approv'd
of all that was paſſ'd, as done for his ſervice, &amp;c. and
theſe conceſſions and extenuations are uſuall at the cloſe
of moſt civill warrs; but there was never any further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
made of them, then to make the adverſe party
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111931:5"/>
more capable of grace and pardon, to enable them to
bear up againſt the brunt of Lawes, and ſecure them more
firmly from all afterclaps; They were paſſ'd in order to
an <hi>Act of Abolition,</hi> to a generall pardon, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to a reeſtabliſhment of Peace; now, <hi>Peace and VVarr</hi>
(we know) <hi>are like VVater and Ice, they engender one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi>
But I do not remember to have read either in the
French ſtory, or any other, that ſuch Royall Conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
at the period of any inteſtin war were ever wrung ſo
hard, as to draw any inference from them, to caſt therby
the guilt of blood or indeed the leaſt ſtain of diſhonor
upon the King; For Royall Indulgences and grants of
this nature are like nurſes breaſts, if you preſſe them
gently there will <hi>milk</hi> come forth, if you wring them
too hard you will draw forth <hi>blood</hi> in lieu of milk: And
I have obſerved, that upon the concluſion of ſuch Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
in France, both parties wold hugg and mutually em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
one another in a gallant way of national humanity;
all rancor, all plundrings, ſequeſtration, and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
wold ceaſe, nor wold any be proſecuted, much leſſe
made away afterwards in cold bloud.</p>
            <p>Touching the Comencer of this monſtrous war of
ours, the world knows too well, that the firſt man of
bloud was <hi>Blewcap,</hi> who ſhew'd Subjects the way, how
to preſent their King with Petitions upon the pikes
point, and what viſible judgements have fallen upon him
ſince by ſuch confuſions of diſcord and peſtilence at
home, and irreparable diſhonour abroad, let the world
judge. The Iriſh took his riſe from him: and whereas
it hath been often ſuggeſted, that his Majeſty had fore-knowledge
thereof, among a world of convincing argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
which may cleer him in this particular, the Lord
<hi>Maguair</hi> upon the ladder, and another upon the Scaffold,
when they were ready to breath their laſt, and to appear
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111931:5"/>
before the Tribunall of heaven, did abſolutely acquit
him, and that <hi>ſpontaneouſly</hi> of their own accord, being
unſought unto, but only out of a love to <hi>truth,</hi> and the
diſcharge of a good conſcience: But touching thoſe c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entous
Iriſh warrs, in regard there was nothing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
more advantage was made againſt His late Majeſty,
to imbitter and poiſon the hearts of his Subjects againſt
him then that Rebellion, I will take leave to wind up the
main cauſes of them upon a ſmall bottome.</p>
            <p>1. They who kept intelligence and complied with
the <hi>Scot,</hi> in his firſt and ſecond inſurrection.</p>
            <p>2. They who diſmiſs'd the firſt Iriſh Commiſſioners
(who came of purpoſe to attend our Parlement with
ſome grievances) with ſuch a ſhort unpolitic harſh an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <p>3. They who took off <hi>Straffords</hi> head, (which had it
ſtood on, that Rebellion had never been) and afterwards
retarded the diſpatch of the Earl of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> from going
over to be Lord-Lievtenant.</p>
            <p>4. Laſtly, they who hindred part of that disbanded
Army of 8000. men rais'd there by the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi>
which His Majeſty, in regard they were ſouldiers of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,
and looſe caſheer'd men, to prevent the miſchiefs
that might befall that Kingdome by their inſolencies,
had promiſed the two Spaniſh Ambaſſadors, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſes
of <hi>Velada</hi> and <hi>Malvezzi,</hi> then reſident in this
Court: which ſouldiers riſe up firſt of any, and put fire
to the tumult to find ſomething to do.</p>
            <p>They, I ſay, who did all this, may be juſtly ſaid to
have been the true cauſes of that horrid Inſurrection in
Ireland; and conſequently 'tis eaſie to judge upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
of whoſe ſouls muſt be laid the blood of thoſe
hundred and odd thouſand poor Chriſtians who periſhed
in that war: and had it been poſſible to have brought o're
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111931:6"/>
their bodies unputrified to England, and to have caſt
them at the lower Houſe door, and in the preſence of
ſome Members, which are now either ſecluded, or gone
to give account in another world, I believe their noſes
would have guſh'd out with blood for diſcovery of the
true murtherers.</p>
            <p>Touching this laſt fire-brand of war, which was thrown
into <hi>England,</hi> who they were that kindled it firſt, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
of thoſe indifferent &amp; unblaſſed men are fitteſt to
be judges, who have been curious to obſerve with impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
eyes, the carriage of things from the beginning.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe 'twas a fatall infortunate thing, that the King
ſhould put ſuch a diſtance 'twixt his Perſon and his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
but a more fatall and barbarous thing it was,
that he ſhould be <hi>driven</hi> away from it, that there ſhould
be a deſperate deſigne to ſurprize his Perſon, that <hi>Ven</hi>
with his <hi>Myrmidons,</hi> and <hi>Bourges</hi> with his Bandogs, (for
ſo they call'd the riffraff of the City they brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
with them) ſhould rabble him away, with above
four parts in five of the Lords, and neere upon two parts
in three of the Commons: Yet 'tis fit it ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred,
what reiterated Meſſages his Majeſty ſent
from time to time afterward, that he was alwaies ready
to return, provided there might be a courſe taken to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
his Perſon, with thoſe Peers &amp; others who were riot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
away from the Houſes; 'tis fit it ſhold be remembred,
that there was not the leaſt motion of war at all, till
<hi>Hotham</hi> kept his Majeſty out of his own Town <hi>Kingſton</hi>
upon Hul, where being attended by a few of his meniall
Servants, he came only to viſit her, which act of <hi>Hotham's</hi>
by ſhutting the gates againſt him was voted warrantable
by the Houſe of Commons, and it may be call'd the firſt
thunderbolt of war: 'Tis fit it ſhould be remembred,
that a while after there was a compleat Army of 10000.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111931:6"/>
effect if Horſe and Foot inrolled in and about London to
fetch him to his Parliament by force, and remove ill <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors</hi>
from about him, (long before he put up his Royall
Standard) and the Generall nam'd to live and die with
them: and very obſervable it is, how that Generalls Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
was executed for a Traytor, for but attempting ſuch
a thing upon Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> I meane to remove ill
Counſellors from about her by force. 'Tis alſo to be
obſerved, that the ſame Army which was rais'd to bring
him to his Parliament, was continued to a clean contrary
end two yeers afterwards to keep him from his Parle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
'Tis fit it ſhould be remembred, who <hi>interdicted
Trade</hi> firſt, and brought in <hi>Forraigners</hi> to help them, and
whoſe Commiſsions of Warre were neere upon two
moneths date before the Kings. 'Tis fit it ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mebred
how his Majeſty in all his Declarations and
public Inſtruments made alwaies deep Proteſtations, that
'twas not <hi>against his Parliament</hi> he raiſed Armes, but
againſt ſome ſeditious <hi>Members,</hi> againſt whom he had
onely deſired the common benefit of the Law, but
could not obtaine it. 'Tis fit to remember, that after any
good ſucceſſes or advantage of his, he ſtill Courted
both Parlement and City to an Accommodation;
how upon the Treaty at <hi>Uxbridge,</hi> with much importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
for the generall advantage and comfort of his people
and to prepare matters more fitly for a peace, he deſired
there might be freedom of trade from Town to Town,
and a Ceſſation of all Acts of Hoſtility for the time, that
the inflamation being allayd, the wound might be cur'd
the ſooner: all which was denied him. 'Tis fit to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
how a Noble Lord at that time told the Parlements
Commiſſioners in his Majeſties Name, at the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy
rupture of the ſaid Treaty, <hi>that when he was at the
higheſt he wold be ready to treat with them, and fight with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111931:7"/>
them when he was at the loweſt:</hi> 'Tis fit the preſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Army
ſhold remember how often both in their Propoſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, and
public Declarations they have inform'd the world, and
deeply proteſted that their principall aime was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore
his Majeſtie to honor, freedom and ſafety, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
they were formerly bound, both by their own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation
and Covenant, that the <hi>two Commanders</hi> in
chief pawn'd unto him their ſoules thereupon. Let them
remember, that ſince he was firſt ſnatch't away to their
cuſtody, he never diſpleas'd them in the leaſt particular,
but in all his Overtures for Peace, and all his Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
he had regard ſtill <hi>that the Army ſhold be ſatisfied:</hi> let
it be remembred, that to ſettle a bleſſed Peace to preſerve
his Subjects from rapine and ruine, and to give content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to his Parlement, he did in effect freely part with
his Sword, Scepter, and Crown, and ev'ry thing that
was perſonall to him: Let it be remembred with what an
admired temper, with what prudence and conſtancie
with what moderation and manſuetude hee compor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
himſelfe ſince his deep afflictions, inſomuch that thoſe
Commiſſioners and others who reſorted unto him, and
had had their hearts ſo averſe unto him before, return'd
his Converts, crying him up to be one of the ſanctifiedſt
perſons upon earth: and will not the blood of ſuch a
Prince cry aloud for vengeance?</p>
            <p>Let it be remembred, that though there be ſome Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents
of depoſing Kings in this Kingdome, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where,
when there was a competition for the right Title
to the Crown by ſome other of the <hi>blood Royall,</hi> yet 'tis a
thing not only unſampled, but unheard of in any age,
that a King of England whoſe Title was without the leaſt
ſcruple, ſhold be ſummon'd and arraign'd, tryed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd,
and executed in his own Kingdom, by his own
Subjects, and by the name of their own King, to whom
they had ſworn Alleagiance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:111931:7"/>
The meaneſt Bariſter that hath but taſted the Laws of
the Land can tell you, that it is an unqueſtionable funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall
Maxime, <hi>The King can do no wrong,</hi> becauſe he
acts by the mediation of his Agents and Miniſters, he
heares with other mens eares, he ſees with other mens
eyes, he conſults with other mens braines, he executes
with other mens hands, and judges with other mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences;
therefore his Officers Counſellors or favorits
are puniſhable, not <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and I know not one yet whom he
hath ſpar'd, but ſacrificed to Juſtice. The Crown of
England is of ſo coruſcant and pure a mettall, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
receive the leaſt taint or blemiſh; and if there were
any before in the perſon of the Prince, it takes them all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
and makes him to be <hi>Rectus in C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a.</hi> This as in many
others may be exemplified in <hi>Henry the Seventh,</hi> and the
late <hi>Queen Elizabeth:</hi> when the firſt came to the Crown
'twas mention'd in Parlement, that the <hi>attainder</hi> might
be taken off him, under which he lay all the time he liv'd
an Exile in France; it was then by the whole Houſe of
Parlement reſolv'd upon the queſtion, that it was unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary,
becauſe the Crown purg'd all. So likewiſe when
<hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> was brought as it were from the <hi>Scaffold</hi>
to the <hi>Throne;</hi> though ſhe was under a former attainder,
yet 'twas thought ſuperflous to take it off, for the Crown
waſ lieth away al ſpots, and darteth ſuch a brightneſſe, ſuch
reſplendent beams of Majeſty, that quite diſpel al former
clouds: ſo that put caſe King <hi>Iames</hi> died a violent death,
and his Son had been acceſſary to it (which is as baſe a lie
as ever the devil belch'd out) yet his acceſſe to the Crown
had purg'd all. This buſineſſe about the playſter which
was applied to King <hi>Iames,</hi> was ſifted &amp; winnow'd as nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly
as poſſibly a thing could be in former Parlements,
yet when it was exhibited as an Article againſt the Duke
of Buckingham, 'twas term'd but a <hi>preſumption</hi> or <hi>miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanure</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:111931:8"/>
of a high nature: And 'tis ſtrange that theſe new
accuſers ſhold make that a <hi>parricide</hi> in the King, which
was found but a preſumption in the Duke, who in caſe it
had been ſo, muſt needs have been the chiefeſt Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
            <p>And as the antient Crown and Royall Diadem of
England is made of ſuch pure allay, and caſt in ſo dainty
a mould, that it can receive no taint, or contract the leaſt
ſpeck of enormity and fouleneſſe in it ſelf, ſo it doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
the perſon of the Prince that weares it with ſuch
high Prerogatives, that it exempts him from all ſorts of
publique blemiſhes, from all Attainders, Empeachments,
Summons, Arraignments and Tryalls; nor is there or
ever was any Law or Precedent in this Land, to lay any
Crime or capitall charge againſt him, though touching
civill matters, touching propertie of <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum,</hi> he
may be impleaded by the meaneſt vaſſall that hath ſworn
fealty to him; as the Subjects of France, and Spain may
againſt their Kings, though never ſo abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs.</p>
            <p>In the Conſtitutions of England, there are two incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulable
Maximes, whereof the meaneſt mootman that
hath but ſaluted <hi>Littleton</hi> cannot be ignorant: the firſt is,
<hi>Rex in ſuis Dominiis ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> habet Parem, nec Superiorem.</hi> The
King in his own Dominions hath neither Peer, or Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior.
The other is <hi>Satis habet Rex ad poenam quod Deum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectet
ultorem:</hi> 'tis puniſhment enough for a King that God
will take revenge of him. Therefore if it be the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall
Conſtitution of the Land, that all juſt Tryalls
muſt be by <hi>Peers,</hi> and the Law proclaimes the King to
have none in his own Dominions, I leave the world to
judge, what capacity or power thoſe men had to arraigne
the late King, to be in effect his Accuſers and Judges; and
that an exorbitant unſampled Tribunall ſhold be erected,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111931:8"/>
with power and purpoſe to <hi>condemn</hi> all that came before
it, to cleer none, and that ſentence of death ſhold paſſe
without conviction or Law upon Him that was the head
and protector of all the Lawes. Laſtly, that they who by
their own confeſſion repreſent but the Common <hi>people,</hi>
ſhould aſſume power to cut off Him who immediately
repreſented God,
<q>
                  <l>—Cui dabit partes ſcelus expiandi</l>
                  <l>Iupiter?—</l>
               </q>
Well, we have ſeen ſuch portentous things, that former
Ages never beheld, nor will future Ages ever be witneſſe
of the like: Nay, poſterity, after a Century or two will
hold what is now really acted to be but <hi>Romances:</hi> And
now with thoughts full of conſternation and horror;
with a heartfull of amazement and trembling for the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant
and crying ſins of this forlorn Nation, which hath
drawn ſuch an endleſſe warr, and an unheard of ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
upon it ſelf, I will conclude with this ſhort prayer,
which carrieth with it as much of univerſall charity, as
of particular: <hi>God amend all, and me firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
