<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The common salvation contended for, and the faith which was once delivered to the saints· Or, An answer to a book called a plain answer to eighteen queries of Iohn Whitehead, put forth by William Kays, who calls himself minister of the Gospel at Stokesly; wherein he hath perverted the faith once delivered to the saints, and pleads for those things which the Scripture declares against, and so he is made manifest, not to be a minister of the everlasting Gospel, but preachesanother [sic] Gospel. The queries laid down, and the substance of his answer, with a reply to his answer. / By one who is a friend to all, who wait for the appearance of Iesus Christ without sin to salvation, known to the world by the name. Francis Howgill.</title>
            <author>Howgill, Francis, 1618-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86648</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3155</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E824_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18577</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860428</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860428</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112548</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A86648)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 125:E824[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The common salvation contended for, and the faith which was once delivered to the saints· Or, An answer to a book called a plain answer to eighteen queries of Iohn Whitehead, put forth by William Kays, who calls himself minister of the Gospel at Stokesly; wherein he hath perverted the faith once delivered to the saints, and pleads for those things which the Scripture declares against, and so he is made manifest, not to be a minister of the everlasting Gospel, but preachesanother [sic] Gospel. The queries laid down, and the substance of his answer, with a reply to his answer. / By one who is a friend to all, who wait for the appearance of Iesus Christ without sin to salvation, known to the world by the name. Francis Howgill.</title>
                  <author>Howgill, Francis, 1618-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold, at the Black-spread-Eagle, at the west-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Kaye, William.  A plain answer to the eighteen quæries of John Whitehead, commonly called Quaker.</note>
                  <note>Thomason received his copy 14 January 1654 [i.e. 1655].</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan. 14 1654".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kaye, William. --  Plain answer to the eighteen quæries of John Whitehead, commonly called Quaker --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Whitehead, John, 1630-1696.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112548:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112548:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The common SALVATION CONTENDED FOR, And the Faith which was once delivered TO THE SAINTS. OR, An Anſwer to a Book called a plain anſwer to eighteen Queries of <hi>Iohn Whitehead,</hi> put forth by <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Kays,</hi> who calls himſelf Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Stokeſly;</hi> Wherein he hath perverted the faith once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints, and pleads for thoſe things which the Scripture declares againſt, and ſo he is made manifeſt, not to be a Miniſter of the everlaſting Goſpel, but prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches another Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The Queries laid down, and the ſubſtance of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, with a Reply to his Anſwer.</p>
            <p>By one who is a friend to all, who wait for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Ieſus Chriſt without ſin to ſalvation, known to the world by the name. FRANCIS HOWOILL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold, at the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread-Eagle, at the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:112548:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112548:2"/>
            <head>The common SALVATION CONTENDED FOR, And the faith which was once delivered TO THE SAINTS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, as to the Title of thy Book, thy plain anſwer as thou calſt it; thou art plainly made manifeſt to be among the falſe Prophets, and the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes, and the falſe Brethren, which the Lord ſent his true Prophets to bear witneſs againſt, and which Chriſt cryed wo againſt, and the Apoſtles exhorted them who were in the faith, to turn away from: and art one that is gone out into the world, ſeparated from the light, from the life, from the practice of all the holy men of God, who ſpoke forth the Scripture, as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt; had they declared againſt all theſe things that thou art pleading for, like <hi>Demetrius,</hi> and yet thou wilt tell of the Scripture being thy rule, thy rule ſhall try thee, and thou ſhalt be laid to it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and it will condemn thee, and the life of all the Saints, and the practice of them who dwelt in the light, will bear witneſs againſt thee: thy hidden myſteries which thou ſpeakſt, are ſeen by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible eye of God, and thy deceit, and thy adding to the Scriptures, and thy perverting of Chriſts words and thy imaginations upon their words, who dwelt in the light, and one day thou ſhalt witneſs the Lord who is juſt, will plead with thee for it, when by thy ſerpents wiſdom, which is in the curſe, and in the diſobedience, and thou pleadſt expreſly againſt Chriſts own words, and holdſt up the types which was in the firſt Covenant, and yet wilt not act according to the firſt Covenant, and ſo art one that denyes Chriſt the ſubſtance, the everlaſting Covenant the oath of God; and yet calls thy ſelf a Miniſter of the Goſpel, thy Goſpel he and all that knows his voice will deny thee, and it who teaches for doctrine, the traditions of men, and ſets up an image of many mixtures, that all may fall down and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112548:3"/>
worſhip, which thou haſt built and ſet up in thy ſenſual carnal wiſdom, and would have all to worſhip the image of the beaſt, that ſits upon many wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers; but the Lord i<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> riſen to cut it down, and ſtamp upon it, and grind it to duſt, and the whirlwind of the Lord ſhall blow it away, and thou and all who hath worſhipped the Beaſt ſhall be broken by him who is ſet for the riſe and fall of many in Iſrael, and all thoſe things that thou haſt ſet up in thy carnal mind, and calls them the Ordinances of God; ſhall become as the broth of abominable things, and as the ſlaying of a man, and all who worſhip their own imaginations, both the circumciſed, and the uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed will the Lord cut off together, for the Lord is ariſen to plead with all the enemies of <hi>Zion,</hi> and his ſword ſhall be fatted with the blood of the ſlain; for prophaneſs is gone forth from the Teachers of this Nation, who abide not in the doctrine of Chriſt to the ends and coſts thereof, and the Lord is grieved, and the earth ſhall diſcloſe her blood, and the ſlain ſhall no longer be covered, but the deceiver of the Nations ſhall be caſt forth, and great ſhall be the lamentation of the Merchants of <hi>Babylon</hi> and <hi>Ieſabel</hi> that hath ſlain Prophets, now is ſuffered to propheſie, and many are deceived by her witchcrafts, but ſhe ſhall be caſt into a bed of ſorrow, and ſhe ſhall be daſhed in pieces; and the dogs ſhall lick her blood, for behold he is riſen who is King of Kings, and he makes war in righteouſneſs, and his name is called the Word of God; and out of his mouth proceeds fire that ſhall conſume the men of the earth, and all who have not the Image of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther written in their foreheads. The fire is kindled already in the earth, and the ſlain is great, and many ſhall gnaw their tongues for pain, and ſhall be conſumed to aſhes; and he will plead with all the falſe Prophets and Merchants in <hi>Babylou</hi> as in the valey of <hi>Iehoſaphet</hi> and his wrath is kindled as in the days of <hi>Gibin,</hi> and the Heathen ſhall all periſh by the edge of the ſword, lamentation and howling, and wo and ſorrow, and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs ſhall come upon all who have profeſſed his name and his words, and yet put him to open ſhame, and denies the end of his coming, which is to redeem his people from their ſins, and to preſent them unto God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot or wrinkle, which many in this generation, teachers and people are pleading for ſin, and yet ſay Chriſt is made manifeſt, but this anſwer all ſuch ſhall have, depart workers of iniquity.</p>
            <p>I. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether thou have the ſame eternal infallible ſpirit that gave forth the Scripture, yea or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſaith thou dareſt not conceal to bear witneſs with thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that thou haſt in ſome ſmall meaſure the ſame ſpirit which was in the Saints, yet an infallible ſpirit thou canſt not own, and calſt it a Popiſh te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and thou ſaith Chriſt had ſuch a ſpirit that did not erre; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thou ſaith if any Miniſter as <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Revelation ſhall wander, yet the Lord can is he hath a mercy unto his people, make the people to receive nothing but wholſome doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Here thou haſt made thy ſelf manifeſt unto all that thou haſt no meaſure of the ſpirit, neither great nor ſmall, not of the ſame ſpirit which was in the Saints, for the ſpirit which the Saints had, was the ſpirit of Chriſt, which is the ſpirit of truth, and infallible, and led them into all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112548:3"/>
truth, and this Spirit thou blaſphemer calls a Popiſh tenent, and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes Chriſt and the Saints: Was it one ſpirit which dwelt in the Saints, and another ſpirit that Chriſt had? and here thou ſpeakſt contrary to the Scripture, as many as are the Sons of God, are led by the Spirit of God, and they that have not the Spirit of Chriſt, are none of his; and all who walked in the ſpirit, and were led by the ſpirit, were led out of pollution, and the luſt of the fleſh, and out of error, and out of all deceit; and they had received the anointing, which was truth, and no lie, and it guided them into all truth: and here thou wouldſt divide the Spirit of Chriſt from the Saints; and here thy ſpirit is made manifeſt not to be that ſpirit which was in the Saints, and which was in Chriſt; but thy ſpirit is fallible, that ſaith, that infallible ſpirit diſgraces the Miniſtery; ſuch a Miniſter thou art, that a fallible ſpirit, and a ſpirit of error is thy glory: and therefore I ſay that ſpirit is not diſtinct from the Saints, which was in Chriſt, but one; there is one ſpirit by which all the Miniſters of Chriſt were guided, and they were Miniſters of the Spirit which was infallible, and true, and eternal, and bore witneſs of him who was true and eternal; and thou calſt this a Popiſh tenent, art raiſed out, and judged by the Scripture not to have the ſame, and ſo art no Miniſter, nor witneſs of the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eternal ſpirit, but ſpeaks in thy own name: And thou art accuſing <hi>Iohn,</hi> that he did wander, (as <hi>Iohn</hi> did in the Revelation thou ſaith) and ſo would make <hi>Iohn</hi> a wandering ſtar like thy ſelf, which <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeaks of, who art fallen into the earth out of the firmament, and ſo would bring reproach upon him, who witneſſed the Spirit, and was in the ſpirit, and dwelt in it; but thy ſhame is made manifeſt, and now the eternal ſpirit is witneſſed, which is infallible, and they will receive thy doctrine no longer, for it is not wholſome, but contrary to the Scripture.</p>
            <p>II. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether thou know the rules of Chriſt, and whether thou wert immediately called by him, to be a Miniſter or Paſtor of the Goſpel, yea or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſaith ſo often as thou haſt the word rightly divided in opening of the ſame in any Chapter or verſe, ſo often thou haſt heard the the voice of Chriſt, and thou ſayeſt thou doſt not deny the reaching of the ſpirit to be an extraordinary voice of Chriſt, and that thou haſt heard, and ſo thou witneſſes an immediate call, and yet thou ſayeſt our imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect actions being made perfect by Chriſt, thou witneſſes an immediate call.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thou that tells of opening Chapters or Verſes by meanings, thou never heard the word of Chriſt; and I ſay unto thee, as Chriſt ſaid to the Phariſees, which had <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, they had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heard his voice, nor ſeen his ſhape, and they which have not the word abiding in them, never heard his word; and therefore if thou never hear of God or from Chriſt, but what is written without thee, thou never yet heard his Word, the Word of God endures for ever, Chapters and Verſes endures not for ever; but thou art made manifeſt when thou canſt not hear what is already writ, nor receive it, nor underſtand it without meanings; and therefore brings their words down to thy reaſon, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112548:4"/>
cals that the Word of God; and thou calſt the teachings of the ſpirit the extraordinary voice of Chriſt: where reads thou in the Scripture, of an ordinary and extraordinary voice of the ſpirit? and here be a witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy ſelf, in thy anſwer to the fourth Query, the fourth page of thy book, to ſay thou had not known the ſpirit, nor the anointing but by the Scripture, and the Scripture is not the ſpirit; and here thy immediate call is the like, that which is viſible and without thee, is not immediate; and here thou art tryed, that thou knoweſt nothing at all but by hearſay, and ſo thou art a falle witneſs, and thou ſaith our imperfect actions are made perfect by Chriſt, when that which is perfect is come, imperfection is done away, but that which thou calls thy imperfect actions he comes not to be perfect, but to deſtroy, but to thee is a myſtery.</p>
            <p>III. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether the Word thou preacheſt, is the ſame from the beginning which thou haſt heard and ſeen, and haſt been taught immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately by the Revelation of Ieſus Chriſt, yea or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Word that thou preaches is ſo muth the ſame thou ſaith from the beginning, as a River is the ſame that runs continually from the fountain; and as God is pleaſed to appear in his outward adminiſtrators.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> He who is the fountain is eternal, which was in the beginning, and before all things, and endures for ever, and they who witneſs him &amp; preach him, and have ſeen him, and taſted of the water of life, which they were witneſs of, <hi>Iohn</hi> the firſt, but the River which thou drinkeſt, is as the brooks of <hi>Teman,</hi> ſpoken of in <hi>Iob,</hi> and ſhall be dried up, and as <hi>Euphrates</hi> that ſhall be dried up, and the Kings of the Eaſt ſhall paſs over it, and the time is come already, bleſſed be the Lord for ever, but thy fountain at the beſt is but the letter without thee, that was ſince the beginning, and thy old Authors, and thy carnal wiſdom, which is in the curſe, and this is thy higheſt attainments, and thy adminiſtrations; if thou hadſt not had the letter without thee, thou hadſt not known ſuch a thing, and then where had all thy preaching been, as in the fourth page of thy book, thou mayeſt remember that thou ſaidſt thou hadſt not known God, but by that others have left upon record; and therefore ceaſe from thy divining, for thou canſt not witneſs what thou ſpeakeſt, but as thou ſtealeſt others words</p>
            <p>IV. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether ever any ſhall grow up under thy Miniſtery, that they ſhall that no man teach them; and whether thou own the anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or had known there had been ſuch a thing, if the Scripture had not ſpoken of it, yea or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Concerning thy Miniſtery, there is no ſuch promiſe thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt made to any mans Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Here thou haſt manifeſted thy Ignorance of the Miniſtery of Chriſt, for they turned many from darkneſs to light, and from Satan unto God, and it was and is the very end wherefore the Miniſters was ſent forth, for the perfecting of the Saints, and to lead them from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection to perſection, and a perſect man in Chriſt Ieſus; and they were ſent out for this end, and are now ſent out to direct all minds, and the Apoſtle laboured and travelled, that he might preſent them without
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112548:4"/>
ſpot or wrinkle unto God, and in that thou ſaith, there is no promiſe to the Miniſtry of man, in that thou ſayeſt truly, but they which were Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, they neither were learned of man, nor had it from man, and ſo thou acknowledgeſt thy Miniſtry to be of man, and ſo art not a Miniſter of Chriſt, but of Anti-chriſt; and thou ſaith if the anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſhould onely teach, there would be no flock, here thou art blind and knows nothing; is not Chriſt the anointing, and Chriſts ſheep hear his voice, and he putteth them forth, and goeth before them, and he leadeth his flock like a ſhepheard; but thou that preaches: for hire, and divineſt for money, and they that follow thee are not of this flock: and as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thy knowledge of the anointing, thou ſaith thou mayeſt ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of ſin, he had not known ſin but by the Law, ſo thou hadſt not known the anointing, had not he Scriptures declared it, and thou ſayeſt without it there is nothing to be known, here thou blind guide, thou puts the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures in the room of God, and wouldſt exalt it above God, and haſt made thy folly manifeſt that thou never knew the anointing but by hearſay, and if thou haſt not had their words, who witneſſed the anointing in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, thou hadſt not known whether there had been ſuch a thing, and thou that knows nothing but without thee, knows nothing at all, and yet the Scripture is able to make wiſe unto ſalvation, and perfect the man of God through faith in Chriſt Ieſus, but of the man of Gods eſtate thou knoweſt nothing of, who art pleading and holding up thoſe things which the men of God witneſſed againſt.</p>
            <p>V. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether thou own Chriſt to be the light of the world, and hath enlightned every one, yea or no?</p>
            <p>VI. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether thou own the word of <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 9. where he wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed Chriſt to be the true light which enlightneth every one that cometh into the world?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſaith thou thinkſt its not amiſs to declare that Chriſt is not onely the light of the world through Revelation but in works of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and meritorious ſufferings, and as he gives to all creatures the light in their Creation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thy thoughts are vain and not as Gods thoughts, he is but one, who is the light of the world, and in him is no darkneſs at all, the light is but one and the ſame light in which he lives, the ſame light the Saints lives in, who are guided by him who is the light, and the light is but one in him that loves it, and in him that hates it; the one he loves it, and the other he hates it: and thou that art making diſtinctions of the light, art divided from the light, and ſo makes many lights by thy imaginations, and ſo perverts the Scripture. And where readſt thou of meritorious ſuffering of Chriſt in the Scripture; nay, thou art ſo ignorant of him who is the true light, and hath not ſo much as a form of ſound words: and where reads thou of ſuch a diſtinction of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and ſpiritual light in Chriſt, thy rule ſhall try thee, and thou ſhalt be judged by it, for in thy ſerpents wiſdome thou wouldſt darken the counſel of God, and rent the Scripture in pieces by thy imaginations, and thou never knewſt what the light of Chriſt was, and never ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112548:5"/>
it with all thy diſtinctions, and though the world is in darkneſs, yet the light ſhines in darkneſs, but this is a myſtery, and ſealed to thee, and therefore thou wouldſt give thy meanings upon their words who were in the light.</p>
            <p>VII. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether it is not blaſphemy to call the true light of Chriſt which enlightneth every one that cometh into the world a natural light, and whether they do not deny the Scriptures, that ſay that every one is not enlightned with the true light, yea or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Is light by juſt conſequence and not otherwiſe called naturall, ſo the light may be called ſupernatural, which is properly called Chriſts light, and thou tells of ordinary lights.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thy conſequences are denyed, thou art in the Philoſophy and vain deceits: where reads thou in Scripture of a natural and ſupernatural light? and where reads thou that the light which is in every creature is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary light, and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thou goe<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t on to prove that there is two lights in Chriſt; and that the light of Chriſt is natural and ſpiritual, and ſo would make two Chriſts: is Chriſt ſpiritual? and is that which is his light na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural? a natural man underſtands not the things of God, but the light which comes from Chriſt which is but one, not divided, but is ſpiritual, it leads to an underſtanding of the things of God, and that which may be known of God is revealed in man, but thou art ignorant and blind, and cannot comprehend it, that which is natural is carnal, and ſo thou wouldſt make a carnal Chriſt, as one like thy ſelf affirmed, who called himſelf a Miniſter of Chriſt, but he that loves the light is led up out of darkneſs, to the light of life, and he that hates the light, its his condemnation, and he is but one that judges and ſaves his people from their ſin: and in the laſt part of thy anſwer, thou ſayeſt thou acknowledgeſt the light of the Law of Chriſt to be more or leſs in the light of nature; here again thy ignorance is made manifeſt, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, the Law was ſpiritual, and the Law of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of life in Ieſus, had freed him from the Law of ſin and death; was that natural? is Chriſt ſpiritual, and his Law natural? for ſhame be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and ſpeak not of the Law, it is holy; is that natural? and thou ſpeaks of putting the light of Chriſt under a buſhel, and ſome that deſtroy Chriſts light; thou blind Phariſee, thou art he that puts the light of Chriſt under a buſhel, that walks in thoſe things, and pleads for thoſe things which they declared againſt: and thou art he that goes about to deſtroy Chriſts light which is pure and eternal, and calſt it natural and ſupernatural, when the light is but one, and thou that wouldſt divide the light, art divided from it, and walks not by it, and ſo art in darkneſs till now: and thou ſaith fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that as Chriſt is pleaſed, he can by the preaching of the Goſpel o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen thine eyes, and turn them from darkneſs to light: here again thy ſhame and thy nakedneſs appears: haſt thou profeſſed thy ſelf a Miniſter of the Goſpel, and a teacher, and are thy eyes unopened? yetart thou yet unturned from darkneſs unto light? then darkneſs ſpeaks and wrote the book, and darkneſs cannot comprehend the light, and wouldſt thou be judging of the light, and of Chriſt, that is yet in darkneſs? for ſhame own thy condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for what thou haſt done in ſpeaking in the name of the Lord, he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112548:5"/>
no ſuch teſtimony, nor the teſtimony of them that walk in darkneſs, and not in the light; and he will judge thee, who is the light, for perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the truth in thy dark mind; and thou confeſſeth that thou art blind, and thine eyes are not yet opened; then how canſt thou declare of him, whom thou haſt neither ſeen nor heard, and here be a witneſs againſt thy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf?</p>
            <p>VIII. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether the true light of Chriſt, which enlightneth every one that cometh into the world, which diſcovereth all the deeds of darkneſs, is not ſufficient to lead all thoſe that love and follow him into holineſs and all truth, ſeeing Chriſt who is the light ſaith that thoſe that follow him ſhall not abide in darkneſs, but have the light of life?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this thou anſwers, Yea, it is when it is revealed; and in thy anſwer to the third Query, thou ſaith there is nothing that can be known but by the Scriptures, and ſo here thou lyes in confuſion and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, and puts the letter for the light of Chriſt, and ſo art blind indeed, as thou confeſſed thy eyes were not opened, and thou was not turned from darkneſs, and thou ſaith Chriſts light when it is revealed is ſufficient, the light which Chriſt Ieſus hath enlightned every one withal, is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and convinceth of all ungodlyneſs and worldly luſt; yea, he which is the Comforter convinceth the world of ſin, as the Scripture witneſſeth; neither is their any other light in the world that convinceth the lyer, the ſwearer, the drunkard, but that light that comes from Chriſt, and this is the condemnation of them that hate it, and that which declares againſt unrighteouſneſs is righteous, and that which ſhews ſin is holy, and thou that calls this natural, thy eye is blind, and thy underſtanding is darkned, and thy ear heavy, and ſo can neither hear, ſee, not underſtand it; now the natural man underſtands not the things of God, but the light of Chriſt in every mans conſcience underſtands by it what is not of God, and by it he comes to ſee ſin, that it is againſt God, and therefore I am a witneſs againſt thee, and againſt all the hirelings in the world, that by the light, which a meaſure is given to every one, that he that loves it, It leads to the the light of life, and though the light ſhine in a naturall man, yet it is not natural, but ſeven ſeals, and upon this, to the ſerpents ſeed, and he that hates it, and diſputes againſt it, ſhall never know it, and thou ſaith, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever hath this light of Chriſt, may ſee to obey Magiſtrates and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Lords day, worſhip, faſting, praying, ſinging, as well as to avoid blaſphemy and profanneſs, Magiſtrates we obey in the Lord, and all their juſt commands, but we deny flattery and deceit, and reſpecting perſons, but honours the power that is of God, and that which is acted by them which is not of God, we ſuffer for conſcience ſake, and reſiſts not, but all that thou obeys is without, in ſlattery and deceit, and hath mens perſons in admiration, becauſe of advantage; and Miniſters of Chriſt we own, who are ſent of God, and honours ſuch, but thee and all the hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and imitaters, <hi>Ianes</hi> and <hi>Iambres</hi> like, we deny, and are bold to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt you all, who walk contrary to the Saints, and that which you call your rule, and are a generation of hypocrites, and your rule ſhall judge you all, and thou art tried by it, when all along thy anſwers, thou
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112548:6"/>
pleads againſt the Scripture, and adds thy meanings, and God will judge thee for it, and thy ſhame ſhall be made manifeſt to all; the day of the Lord we own, bleſſed be that day; but it ſhall burn as an oven, againſt all deceivers and hypocrites; and falſe Prophets, and this thou ſhalt know and witneſs; and baptiſm, and watching, and faſting, and praying, and ſinging, this is witneſſed, the ſame that ever was, and the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, but we deny thee, and all ſuch as go and baptize, and then preach repentance to them fourty years after; and faſting; thou might have been ſparing in this, pull out the beam, I ſpeak to thy conſcience: how often haſt thou faſted, and croſſed thy luſt, nay all is too little, hay and corn, Calves, Lambs, Eggs and Swines fleſh and all is to little for you, but you are ſtill at a want, and removing from one place to another, for filthy lukre, and makes merchandiſe of ſouls for diſhoneſt gain, and ſues men at the Law, as many can witneſs in the North of England, and caſts thoſe in priſon that they call their flock, and ſo you are as ravening wolves, greedy of your prey, and as foxes in the deſert, that devours all that reſiſt you; and then cries they are not ſubject to the Magiſtrates nor Miniſters; and then ſaith the labourer is worthy of his hire, and brings this for a cloak, when as they never hired you, and yet you ſeek wages of them, you do not work for, to maintain your luks: Howl ye Caterpillers and Canker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worms, that devours the earth, and ſpends your time in the luſts of the fleſh, and yet accuſes others, and as for thy prayers they ſtink. God hears not ſinners, and while thou lives in this nature, pleading for thoſe things which the Scripture declare againſt, and thy ſongs ſhall be turned into la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation and howling, the dead cannot praiſe, nor the blind, and thou ſaith thou art blind and deaf; what haſt thou to preach, or pray, or ſing; and ſo ceaſe thy gainſaying, the hand of the Lord is againſt thee, and the Scripture was not given out for thee to prattle on, and for thoſe things thou cals ordinances, thou had not known ſuch a thing, as in the anſwer to the fourth Query thou confeſſeſt, and ſo let ſhame cover thy face, and let thy mouth be ſtopped, and all fleſh keep ſilence, for what is known without, leads no<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o God, but that which may be known of God is revealed in man, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. and the time is come, <hi>Ieſable</hi> that hath ſlain the Prophets, ſhall be caſt into torment, and ſhe ſhall propheſie no more, and by the light which thou ſets all nought, ſhall thou and all the inchanters and diviners be confounded, to it ſhall all Nations how, for he from whom it come, is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, who makes war in righteouſneſs, and is now coming to cut off all by the edge of the ſword, who hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phefied lies in his name, and cauſed men to abhor the ſervice of the living God.</p>
            <p>IX. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether the end of begiſting and ſending forth Miniſters; is for the perfecting of the Saints, and for bringing them up to his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or fulneſs, yea or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Here thou thy ſelf, ſhall be a witneſs againſt all the Miniſtery which long hath been in this Nation, for verily it is ſo far from perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Saints, that openly the Miniſtry pleadeth againſt it, and cryeth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112548:6"/>
out of thoſe that witneſs it to be in error; and here thou ſhalt ſtand as a witneſs for the truth, againſt thy ſelf, and againſt all thy Brethren.</p>
            <p>X. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether any ſhall grow up under thy Miniſtery, to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man, to the meaſure of fulneſs, and ſtature of Chriſt, yea or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſayeſt, ſpeaking of thy own hearers, they are at age, ask them, and try them whether there be not ſome that will not avoid to anſwer thee; to which I do Reply, It may be ſome of thy hearers might be as impudent in ſpeaking lies againſt their own conſcience, as thou art in writing againſt the Commands of Chriſt; but that in their conſcience, to which I deſire to be known, and to the upright principle in them, to which I deſire to ſpeak, will not witneſs that under thy Miniſtery, they have attained to perfection, but are yet learning under thee, and never able by thee to come to the knowledge of the truth; and that which is of God in them, ſhall witneſs againſt thy Miniſtery, that it perfects none into holineſs, and into the Image of God; and thou ſayeſt thou hopes we may ſee in the <hi>Epbeſ.</hi> 4. 13. Concerning the fulneſs of the ſtature of Chriſt; and further, by faith, then all our defects, imperfections and ſins are not imputed, as therby God may apply the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, whereby we may ſee no tranſgreſſion in <hi>Jacob;</hi> we are, and all Believers muſt come to the meaſure of the perfection of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> What <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> we know is true, but what is this to thee, and thoſe who are out of <hi>Pauls</hi> way and life; in the way of the falſe Prophets, and of the Scribes and Phariſees, and the defects and imperfections, and ſins, muſt lie upon your own head, for Chriſt will be no cloak unto you in your iniquities, to cloak your hypocriſie and deceit; if you had faith, then ſhould you be purified from Imperfection; for faith is perfect, and ſo are all that live by it: and for thy word apply the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt, it is not the language of the ſpirit of God, which gave forth the Scripture; for the righteouſneſs of Chriſt is not to be applied to the head of the wicked, nor to cover wickedneſs, but to deſtroy it; but where ſin ſtands, it will be imputed: for God cannot acquit the wicked, and he that ſins is not of <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſeed, but of <hi>Eſaus,</hi> and the righteouſneſs of Chriſt is not unto that birth, and thou and all thy Believers, who art in defects and imperfections, and in your ſins, art in the ſtature and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and not of the ſtature of the ſame God; who art free from all unrighteouſneſs, and defects, and imperfections.</p>
            <p>XI. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether they be not Miniſters of Antichriſt, and never were ſent of Chriſt, that deny perfection which they are ſent of Chriſt, to bring unto, yea or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Nay, they are not. Reply, here thou haſt manifeſted the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and confuſion, who in thy anſwer to the nineth Query, ſaid it yea, it was the end of ſending faith, the Miniſters for the perfecting of the Saints; and now then ſayeſt, they are not Miniſters of Antichriſt, which denyes perfection, and ſo ſpeaks a plain contradiction, and ſo out of thy own mouth ſhalt thou be condemned; and let all whoſe eye is open, ſee and behold thy deceit and blindneſs, and ſo alſo manifeſt thy ſelt, that thou was never ſent of Chriſt, who hath brought up none to perfection,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112548:7"/>
But ſayeſt they are not Miniſters of Antichriſt, that denies perfection, and yet ſayes the Miniſters of Chriſt was ſent to that end, to bring up unto perfection; and further thou ſayeſt, that exhorting the world to look to the light that is within them, they ſhall never come to perfection, none muſt think or imagine</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Here thou haſt uttered Blaſphemy, and quite contrary to Chriſts own words, who ſaith I am the light of the world, he that follows me ſhall have the light of life, and this is perfection; and be it known unto thee, and unto all, that no other light we direct or exhorts unto, but the light of Chriſt within, which is ſufficient to lead to perfection as Chriſt himſelf ſaith his light leads to the light of life all that walk in it, and thou ſaith contrary and ſo ſpeaks-againſt Chriſt, and would make his light imperfect, and not able to lead to perfection, and part found an enemy to him, and mayeſt ſtop thy mouth for ſhame, who art ignorant of the Scripture; and whilſt thou profeſſes it, art found both walking and ſpeaking contrary to it.</p>
            <p>XII. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether he that is born of God, do commit ſin, yea or no? and whether he that committeth ſin is of the Devil, yea or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> He that is born of God is exhorted to repent; and may be delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and thou affirmatively ſays that thoſe that are born of God may ſin, as all the Saints have experienced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Here thou more plainly haſt ſhewed thy ſelf to be a perverter of the Scripture, and one that ſpeaks contrary to it; for he who is born of God, is the Image of God, and needs no repentance, he which was born of God was commended by God, and not exhorted to repent, as that Scripture which thou haſt named, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. ſhall witneſs: but he which was fallen from the birth-born of God, was exhorted to repent; and thou ſayeſt he that is born of God may be deluded, and the Scripture ſaith it is not poſſible that the elect ſhould be deceived: and here again thou ſpeaks contrary to the Scripture, and thou ſayeſt affirmatively, that thoſe that are born of God may ſin: and here again thou ſpeaks contrary to the Scripture, which ſaith, he that is born of God cannot ſin: Now let ſhame cover thy face, and let thy own conſcience convince thee, that thou art a perverter of the Scripture to thy own deſtruction, and ſo art unlearned, and without true experience, for that experience, and thoſe Saints which thou ſpeaks of, which experiences that which is contrary to the plain words of Scripture, which was the experiences of true Saints, is damnable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences, and ſervants of the Devil, and cannot be believed by them who are true Saints, and have true experiences, according to the working of the holy Ghoſt in them: and further thou ſayeſt that Scripture, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 8, 9. may be hard to be underſtood, yet taking good notice, the truth is eaſily reconci<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, and thou ſayeſt, this is his meaning, that the child of God ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not after the ſimilitude, manner, or meaſure, or nature that the devil &amp; his reprobates ſins, &amp; ſo to make good what thou ſayeſt thou haſt added to <hi>Iohns</hi> words, his ſeed remains in him (whereby he ſhall repent him of his ſin, this laſt thou haſt deceitfully added, as alſo haſt added after the ſimilitude, manner, or meaſure, or nature, that the Devil and his repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112548:7"/>
ſins, let all ſeareh the Scripture, and ſee if <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeak any ſuch thing, and ſo gives thy ſenſual meaning of <hi>Iohns</hi> words, quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what he ſpoke: for further, he ſaid he that ſins is of the devil, and never knew God; and thou affirms, he that is born of God, which know God may ſin, and ſo divides the Scripture, and adds thy own imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions unto it; and ſo thou mayeſt read thy portion in it, God will add all his plagues unto thee, and truth needs no reconciling, for it is in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and cannot be underſtood by thee, who art unlearned, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou wreſts it: and further, thou ſayeſt a child of God being renewed through Goſpel-repentance, ſins not devil like unto death or damnation.</p>
            <p>Reply, O thou blind Phariſce, a child of God needs no repentance and all ſin is of and like the Devil his image, the Scripture ſaith he that ſins is of the Devil; thou ſayeſt contrary, and ſpeaks of ſin not to be like the Devil: and here again art ſpeaking contrary to the Scripture. And further, thou ſayeſt thou doſt ſay that the child of God as he ſins, is of the Devil, not that the Devil can claim him for his, or that he is in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Devil, for your gift is of <hi>Balaams</hi> nature, and not of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Pauls,</hi> and ſo your reward will be as <hi>Balaams,</hi> and not as <hi>Pauls,</hi> who inherits the everlaſting treaſure for ever. And further, thou ſayeſt, but as to the point of taking Tythes, which in reſpect of darkneſs and prejudice, ſome Saints are herein unſatisfied: and thou ſayeſt we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not our ſelves in judging from the Apoſtles example, except we could prove by Scripture, that the Apoſtles might have had Tythes, or thoſe Miniſters which were like <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> ſettled in a parochial way in their quarters, might have had Tythes given them, and yet refuſed them.</p>
            <p>Reply. They which are ſatisfied that they are Miniſters of Chriſt which takes Tythes, are indeed in darkneſs as thou ſpeaks, and unto all that fear God, taking of <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ythes whether in paying or receiving, will be preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice: and be it known unto thee, and unto all ſuch that we do under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand our ſelves in judging thee and all ſuch; to be Antichriſts, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers and falſe Prophets, who acts and upholds thoſe things which the deceivers and falſe Prophets acted in former generations; and in ſeeking for your gain from your Quarter and in making merchandiſe of people through covetouſneſs, you make it manifeſt that you are ſuch, and ſo in the light which was in the Prophets, and in the Apoſtles, we ſee you, and by it we judge you, and by the example of the Apoſtles you may all be condemned; who never took Tythes, nor ſought for their gain from their Quarter, nor made merchandiſe of any through covetouſneſs, as you do: and we tell thee plainly, it is as true as the Scripture, for by the ſame Spirit we ſpeak, that none of the Miniſters of Chriſt nor his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, did take Tythes or wages of the world for preaching, and this we can prove by the Scripture, that the Apoſtles refuſed to take that which they might have had, which was offered unto them, and herein they ſhall judge you, who not onely takes what men give you willing, but compels ſome to pay againſt their will: and that <hi>Timothy</hi> or <hi>Titus,</hi> or any of the miniſters of Ieſus Chriſt, was never ſettled in a parochial way in Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112548:8"/>
we do deny it, and doth charge it upon thee, to be a falſe accuſer, and a ſlanderer, and a lyar, upon <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> and would make them as bad as thy ſelf, and the reſt of the falſe Prophets, and here let thy own conſcience condemn thee, for believing the holy men of God, and ſpeaking that of them which they were not to cloak and uphold thy own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits &amp; abominations: &amp; further, thou ſayeſt till then the light of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles that took whatſoever was given them, ſatisfies thy conſcience to praiſe God for the Magiſtrate that doth freely give it unto thee, and then brings the Apoſtles words, they that preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</p>
            <p>Reply. The light in which the Apoſtles lived, by which they were act<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, will for ever condemn thee except thou repent; for by their example thou art judged already as it is manifeſted, thy conſcience is blinded by the god of the world, and not ſatisfied by the light of Chriſt which was in the Apoſtles, for if the light of the Apoſtles acted thee, then would thou be found in their ſteps, but be witneſs againſt thy ſelf, that thou art acted by that ſpirit which acted the falſe Prophets, and falſe Apoſtles, being thou art found in the ſame ſteps, making merchandiſe of people, and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for hire as they did; which of the Apoſtles had any Law from any Magiſtrate, to compel men to pay Tythes to them, ſhew this by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture if thou canſt, or elſe be a witneſs againſt thy ſelf, that thou lives not upon the Goſpel? For I know if you had not a Law to compel men to maintain you, the Goſpel which you preach, and the people to whom you preach, would ſtarve you for maintenance; this Scripture we own, and do witneſs, they that preach the Goſpel ſhall live of the Goſpel, and doth, without running to Magiſtrates to receive order from them, to compel men to pay them.</p>
            <p>XVI. <hi>Query.</hi> Shew me by the Scripture where ever any of the Miniſters of Chriſt did give <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms to be ſung of the people in a rime; and if not, thou acknowledgeſt that thou art in the inventions and traditions of men, raiſed out from them all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In thy anſwer unto this Query, thou brings many Scriptures to prove ſinging, ſome of which doth not at all prove any ſinging, and none of them will prove the ſinging which thou pleads for; which is a great company of proud and covetous, and earthly minded perſons, to ſing <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> words which they cannot witneſs, but are enemies to the life of what he ſpoke; for the world cannot ſing praiſes unto God, but you by your traditions cauſe men to ſing lies, that they are not puft in mind, and that the Law of God is dear unto them, and that every night water they their bed with tears, when as they never witneſſed theſe things, though all this was true in <hi>David;</hi> and as for that Scripture 2 <hi>Chron,</hi> 29. where it was commanded of the Prieſts to ſing the words of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Aſaph;</hi> this was under the Law, a figure, as the Prieſts was a figure: and from that Scripture you may as well prove the offering of ſacrifice, as ſinging; but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112548:8"/>
thou makes manifeſt thy ignorance and blindneſs hereby unto all the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and many other Scriptures thou brings, and the example of Chriſt and his Diſciples, and the example of the Churches, which will not at all prove the ſinging of your aſſemblies, which is onely by tradition and invention we do deny, and bear teſtimony againſt it, that it is not the ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the praiſe of God, but God is diſhonoured by it, and it ſhall all be turned into howling and bitterneſs, and the time is at hand wherein the Iudgements of God ſhall be revealed againſt it, for in the eternal light it is diſcovered to be abomination unto God, and inſtead of ſinging you ſhall howle and lament, the Lord hath ſaid it; and a great deal more rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſtuff thou haſt written to prove thy deceitful practice, which I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to anſwer, as not worth naming.</p>
            <p>XVII. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether that wo which Chriſt pronounced againſt the Phariſees, who were called of men Maſters, had the ceief place in the Aſſemblies, and ſtood praying in the Synagogues, do not abide upon thee, who art called of men Maſters, haſt the chief ſeat in the Aſſemblies, ſtands praying in the Synagogue? or how wilt thou juſtifie thy ſelf in theſe prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices, ſeeing Chriſt is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever, who cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed woe againſt them that lived in them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſayeſt thou doth not feare the woes pronounced againſt the Pharilees.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> It is becauſe thy heart is hardened, and thy mind is ſtiffnecked and rebellious, for as ſure as Chriſt is the ſame for ever, the ſame woe will be thy portion as was theirs, which acts thoſe things which they acted, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the command of Chriſt: and further, thou ſayeſt Chriſt, his Prophets and Apoſtles and as well as thy ſelf, were called Maſters, and Sirs.</p>
            <p>Reply. Chriſt was called Maſter, and here he approved it, and ſo he was, and is, even the one Maſter of all the Saints; and their being called Maſter will not juſtifie thee in thy Phariſees ſteps: for he ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. Be not ye called Maſter, and thou mani<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſts thy ſelf to be an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Chriſt, who brings Scripture againſt his commands, and this I ask thee, or any, whether you dare juſtifie that to be of God, which Chriſt expreſly commands contrary either in your ſelves or others? and though ſome have erred herein, yet this will not juſtifie thee in thy Phariſee ſteps; for Chriſt did plainly deſcribe the Phariſees to the Deſciples, by their walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and we find thee, and the reſt of thy Brethren, compleat in their ſteps, by the ſame ſpirit as Chriſt did we cry woe againſt you; and as ſure as Chriſt is the ſame for ever, it will come upon you: and further thou anſwers, as concerning thy preaching and praying in a pulpit of wood in the Synagogue, thou art no more then Chriſt, his Prophets and Apoſtles; who did preach in the Synagogues to be condemned:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:112548:9"/>
Reply. Yea, thou art in the Phariſees ſteps, having the chief ſeat in the Aſſembly, and art to be condemned by the ſame which condemned the Phariſees.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou haſt brought many Scriptures to vindicate thy Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee like action, none or them will juſtifie thee nor thy action; and thou haſt belyed the Prophets, and Chriſt and his Apoſtles, for they had not the chief place in the Aſſemblies, which thou would go about to make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear they had, and ſo would make them as bad as thy ſelf, and the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, but let all ſearch the Scriptures which thou haſt named; and as for that where <hi>Ezra</hi> the Scribe read the Law in a Pulpit of wood in the ſtreet, will not juſtifie thee except thou will own thy ſelf to be a Scribe and Prieſt of the Law as he was, and ſo deny thy ſelf to be a Miniſter of the Goſpel: this was not in a formal cuſtomary way, but at a particular time, and to a particular people, and he is not an example to the Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, for they went up and down in Towns, and Markets, and Vilages, preaching to every creature, which is our example, and not <hi>Ezra:</hi> and as for the other Scriptures, they will bear witneſs againſt thy action, for not one of them doth prove that either-Chriſt or his Apoſtles had the chief ſeat in the Synagogues, but ſometimes they went and declared againſt them, and ſometime they were hailed out and perſecuted in them, as we are: and thy manner or action in the Aſſemblies, is according to the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, and not according to the Apoſtles, thou makes a trade to get mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by thy action, and they did not ſo, but freely what they had received from God they declared, but thou ſels thine for money, and upholds an Idols Temple which they bore witneſs againſt, as the Scripture bears wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and here thou haſt wreſted the Scripture being unlearned, to thy own deſtruction, and where is thou ſpeaks of feeding the flock of Chriſt, I anſwer, they who are the ſheep of Chriſt knows thy voice to be the ſtranger, and will deny thee and thy food which feeds dead minds with the dead let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and then make a prey upon the people, as the falſe Prophets did, and thou art raiſed out from all the holy Prophets and Apoſtles, art in the ſteps of the falſe Prophets, and Scribes and Phariſees, and falſe Brethren, thou ſpeaks of our profaning the Temples, and baſely contemning it: to which I anſwer, we bear witneſs againſt the Idols Temples of the world, which God is diſhonoured in, and <hi>Baal</hi> worſhiped, and do ſay God dwels not in Temples made with hands, &amp; no other ways we profane it nor contemn it, but as the Apoſtles did, in witneſſing forth the Subſtance, and denying the figure: and further, thou ſayeſt that as Chriſt did, ſo thou doeſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to be called Maſter, Miniſter, or Paſtor, and do likewiſe Chriſt like, own in ſincerity and humility, to ſtand praying in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouge.</p>
            <p>Reply. Here thou art impudent and ſhameleſs, who acknowledges thy ſelf to be called Maſters, abſolute contrary to the command of Chriſt, and ſo art to be condemned with the Phariſees, and as for Miniſters of the Goſpel, and Paſtor of the flock of Chriſt, thou art none: for thy fruits
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112548:9"/>
doth make thee manifeſt, and being found out of the doctrine of Chriſt, and of his Apoſtles, art to be Iudged by their life and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and that Chriſt ſtood praying in the Synagogue, which thou ſayeſt, I declare againſt thee here to be a lyar, for in the Scripture thou canſt not prove that Chriſt ſtood praying in the Synagogue, and ſo haſt belyed him; and haſt added in this anſwer to the Scripture, as thou haſt done in the twelfth Query; and ſo thou mayeſt read thy portion, plagues will God adde unto thee, and as for ſincerity and humility, thou who pleads for that which the holy men of God wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed againſt, mayeſt be aſhamed to profeſs ſincerity and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and thus thy anſwers are replied unto, and thy ſhame laid open, and thy portion read, even the breath of the Lord will kindle thy torment, who hath ſlandered Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, and would make them as bad as thy ſelf, and the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars portion muſt thou have, the mouth of the Lord hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it.</p>
            <p>XVIII. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether they be not Miniſters of Antichriſt that do practice thoſe things that Chriſt cryed woe againſt? and whether they be Miniſters of Chriſt, that though their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty go about to juſtifie thoſe practices that Chriſt forbad and cryed woe againſt, yea or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſayeſt if thou know any goes about ſubtilly to juſtifie theſe practices, it were well it were put out of a query.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> For the Information of the ſimple it was put forth, and that thou might be made manifeſt, and I put it out of all queſtion, and ſay that they are the Miniſters of Antichriſt that practiſe thoſe things that Chriſt cryed woe againſt; and thou art ſeen to be one of them, that hath declared thy ſelf openly to all that ſhall read thy anſwers, that all thou hath written was in ſubtilty, and thou goes about to juſtifie that which Chriſt cryed woe againſt, as is manifeſt pleading for Tythes, and denying Chriſt come in the fleſh, and pleads againſt the words and commands of Chriſt, and to be called of men Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and for ſtanding praying in the Synagogue, and calls it Chriſt like, let ſhame ſtrike thee in thee face, and I chalenge thee to prove where Chriſt ſtood praying in the Synagogue; did he act thoſe things that he cryed woe againſt, and ſo thou would make him like thy ſelf a diſſembler and an hypocrite; but thou judges out of thy corrupt imaginations, and he will judge thee for it: and thou ſaith thou in charity ought to judge me to contend for the faith; and in thy anſwer to <hi>Iohn Whites</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:112548:10"/>
concluſion, thou ſays he Pope like commands thee to anſwer; and further, thou ſaith he required thee in his one name, what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion thou lies in, and forgets what thou ſpeaks thy heart is ſo full of deceit: and thou further ſaith, he ought to abound in charity, to think no evil, and to die to all cauſleſs jealouſies and contempt againſt profeſſors, thou would not have deceit judged nei<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her in thy ſelf nor others, but would build up, and be daubed with untempered morter, and it is beyond jealouſies that we have of thee, and all profeſſion that ſtands in that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, when your profeſſion is contrary to the doctrine of Chriſt, and now poſſeſs not what you ſpeak, and therefore makes hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites by your preaching, and to profeſs that which they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs not.</p>
            <p>And in thy concluſion, thou ſaith <hi>Iohn Whitehead,</hi> let me tell thee plainly, that thy words being far from the meek ſpirit of the Apoſtles, I beſeech you brethren.</p>
            <p>Reply. The Apoſtle never ſaid I beſeech you brethren to ſuch as thou art, who acts thoſe things that he declared againſt, and ſuffered by thy generation, as we do now, hailing, mocking, buffeting: and thou that art joyned to a harlot, would thou be called a Brother, and thou ſaith thou ſhould not have anſwered theſe Queris, if it had not been to anſwer the command of God, and the teaching of the Spirit; the command of God thou never knew, who art pleading againſt Chriſts commands and the Spirit thou knows nothing of, who confeſſed in the fourth page of thy book, who confeſſed thou knew nothing but by the Scripture, and the Scripture is not the Spirit; and here let all judge of thy blindneſs, and thou ſaith thou haſt anſwered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out adding or diminiſhing the Scripture, let all thy writing be a witneſs againſt thee, in thy anſwer to the twelfth Query, and in thy concluſion thou ſayes thou would not draw arguments from, and fetch guns out of a caſtle, to turn them againſt the ſame place; this ſhall ſtand for thy ſelf, and let all judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou have not fetched arguments and Scriptures to uphold thy trade of divination, and hath pleaded againſt Chriſts own com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and ſets one Scripture againſt another; and thou would have diſtinctions to ſtand, becauſe the holy Ghoſt ſaith, this he ſpoke concerning the Temple of his body; but where is that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that ſaith this was ſaid not of the material Temple? that is thy own word, and ſo thou cannot but twine, and wreſt, and pervert, for if thou did not, the whole Scripture would bear witneſs againſt thee; and thou art accuſing that thou heard him preſs, caſting off ordinances, we know what thou calls ordinances, even beggerly ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments, ſprinkling Infants, ſinging others condition, and when
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112548:10"/>
you read puts them on, and when you ſing puts them off, and ſtanding praying in the Synagogue, and would accuſe Chriſt as thou haſt done, in thy anſwer to the ſeventeenth Query, and coming to an Idols Temple; and hear thee ſpeak an hour or two, what thou haſt raiſed up by thy imagination from the Scripture all the week, and then cry hear the Word of the Lord, and theſe and ſuch like are your ordinances, but God will plead with thee, and all that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſtrange fire, and all your ſacrifice God is weary of, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ceaſe to pervert the way of the Lord, leſt thou be cut off within thy gainſaying, and periſh with the uncircumciſed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
