<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter sent from Sr. Simon Harcourt, to a worthy member of the House of Commons. VVith a true relation of the proceedings of the English army, under his command, to this present March. Whereunto is added the many miraculous deliverances, in the relieving and defending of the city of Tredagh, by the providence of God. Exactly related, by the minister of the same town, who was an eye witnesse thereof, and is still resident there.</title>
            <author>Harcourt, Simon, Sir, 1603?-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E140_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212747</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871323</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871323</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156533</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A87085)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156533)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 25:E140[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter sent from Sr. Simon Harcourt, to a worthy member of the House of Commons. VVith a true relation of the proceedings of the English army, under his command, to this present March. Whereunto is added the many miraculous deliverances, in the relieving and defending of the city of Tredagh, by the providence of God. Exactly related, by the minister of the same town, who was an eye witnesse thereof, and is still resident there.</title>
                  <author>Harcourt, Simon, Sir, 1603?-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Hunscott,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>At head of title: March 18.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156533:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <date>March <hi>18.</hi>
               </date> A LETTER <hi>SENT FROM</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Simon Harcourt, To a worthy Member of the Houſe of <hi>COMMONS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a true Relation of the proceedings of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, under his command, to this preſent <hi>March.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is added the many miraculous delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, in the Relieving and Defending the City of <hi>Tredagh,</hi> by the providence of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Exactly Related, by the Miniſter of the ſame Town, who was an eye witneſſe thereof, and is ſtill reſident there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Hunſcott.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:156533:2"/>
            <head>A Letter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Hope by this time, you are fully ſatſfied by the receipt of my Letters, that I have made it my care to uphold my ſelfe in your good opinion, which I ſhall ever value at a high rate: Therfore I will never prove ſo great an enemy unto my ſelfe, as to looſe by the neglect and omiſsion of the tender of my due reſpects, which ſhall on all oppertunities attend you in a moſt affectionate manner. And now give me leave to give you a briefe accompt of a piece of ſervice which hath lately bin acted on the Rebels, at a place called <hi>Killſhaughall,</hi> ſome ſeven or eight miles from <hi>Dublin,</hi> where lodged neere upon <hi>2000.</hi> as we had intelligence. The ſcituation of the place as naturally ſtrong as I have ſeen any Caſtle in <hi>Ireland,</hi> having mooriſh an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> boggy ground on the one ſide, the other invironed with thick Woods, quick-ſet heages, high bancks, and deep Ditches (inacceſſible) but as we forced our way by Pyoners (under the favour of our Muſquetiers) in the middle of which Woods ſtood the Caſtle, which had but one Aveneu unto it; on that ſide we approached it, on wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch they had <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a reverſe or Barricadoe, which we beate them from. That done, I ſent Capta<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne <hi>Congrave</hi> with <hi>100.</hi> Muſquetiers, to fall on them in the, Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard in which they were <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſtood oppoſite unto the Caſtle gate, he found the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> all reſc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce; and then in great diſorder fledde, taking their way (<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>) unto the bogge ground; Thoſe which betooke themſelves unto the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Borlaſles</hi> Troop in chaſe of them, who had the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſome 60 or 70; of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and about as many more were killed in the in the W<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> by the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Caſtle was maintained againſt us (ſome of their beſt men have <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fer Sanctuary.) And we having no pieces of Battery, were forced to leave it. In this expedition was my Lord of <hi>Ormond,</hi> the Lord <hi>Lambert,</hi> in <hi>Charles Coote,</hi> and my ſelfe having with us <hi>500.</hi> foote, and 300 Horſe, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> leſt one Captaine <hi>Rochford,</hi> who led the forlorne hope, being of Sir <hi>Charles Coote</hi> his Regiment, with ſome five or ſix of my Rigiment, and as many bu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And this is all that for the preſent I can acquint you with, only that to morrow we make a viſit unto the Lords and Gentry of the Pale with <hi>3000.</hi> Foot, and between, <hi>5.</hi> and <hi>600</hi> Horſe, and this we are forced to doe for the relieſe of our Souldiers who have bin kept this tenne weekes upon a meane allowance of ſalt Beef, and Herring, which had cauſed great ſickneſſe and mortality amongſt them; But I hope that your care of this poore Army here, wilbe ſuch, that the may be ſpeeddy ſupplyed with M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ney Clothes and Victuals for them. I ſpeake of their miſery as briefly as I can, but the Lord Iuſtices better will more <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> informe you. I am confident you will doe all the friendly offices (in your power, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Souldiers here, whereby you ſhall ing<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em and me, moſt faithfully and affectionately to remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Dubl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <hi>6.</hi> Martii. <hi>1641.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>your humble Servant,
<hi>HARCOURT.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156533:2"/>
            <head>An Abſtract of <hi>Newes</hi> Since our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe <hi>Ianuary.</hi> 11. to the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>February.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter much miſery we were relieved by the Pinnace with ſome Biſquet and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, extremity of want drawing on of both, that it was not unobſerved, that where we had bin ſolemly praying for it. The Rebells had ſunck a Barque in the Channell, but two or three daies before the winde and tide had driven her out to Sea, they had hoyſted an iron chaine, but that hindred not her paſſage over it 1000 ſhot were ſent from either ſide the River, and had double returnes from ours, yet not one of our men loſt, with what joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acclamations the Pinace and her Shallope were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived within the Bay, what mutuall ſalutations of ſhot were given and anſwered; how the Streets rang againe with thanks and Prayers to God from all ſorts, thoſe who were eye and eare witneſſes can never forget, at this reliefe the countenances of the Towneſmen told aſmuch, upon ſecond thoughts towards night, they ſeemed to be very glad, and for an expreſſion were very kinde to the Souldiers, offering them drinke upon every guard on free coſt; the poore men not uſing to receive ſo liberally without their Officers knowledge, two parts of the Watch were drunke, about mid-night, (moſt being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe) a breach was made in the wall, in an our orchard betwixt St. James gate, and the water, in which, as was confeſſed by one hanged the next day, an Officer had a chiefe hand in; about 3 of the clock 500 entred and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued an houre or two undiſcovered, till being marched upon the key they ſhouted, which was either for aſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of victory, or to invite the Towne to their promiſed aſſiſtance, ſome of them had adventured up to the Mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount,
<pb facs="tcp:156533:3"/>
and killed the firſt Centinell, others had entred the Bridge. This ſhout being our firſt Allarum, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour ran out unarmed, and was the firſt that cauſed a Drum to beat, and in that haſt, was compelled to take the maine guard, who were his owne company, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded men from by-guards, theſe were his preſent ſtrength, firſt poſted downe ſome Pikes commanded by his Enſigne, to make good the Bridge, untill the Muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teeres could make ready; we met the enemy upon the firſt entry, and finding them reſiſted by a guatd of ours charged home, and ſoone compelled them to retreate, the Governor immediatly relieved his Enſigne with Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queteeres, who met not farre from the Bridge, another company of the Rebells, but being in the darke, tooke them by their an ſwere to be friends, untill hee found the contrary by a ſhot made at him, which went throw the brims of anothers hat next him. As ſoon as we gave fire it proved ſo effectuall, that they inſtantly ſcattered &amp; were chaſed through the ſtrees, leaving their dead bodies as ſtumbling blocks in our way. And now my Lord <hi>Moore</hi> with what Horſe he could make ready, came to his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, who chaſed the reſidue of them up the Hill, where they dropped a paſe, but where the breach was, could not yet be found, till they directed us by their flight, through which 100 eſcaped: and now each Captaine had got together Forces, and environ'd them in each quarter and with eaſe layd them on heapes in every corner, ſo that the ſlain within the walls and priſoners taken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, were 200. This deliverance the worſt of men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlege to be the hand of God, for had they marched towards the next Port, and cut the guard off there, who were moſt ſleeping: one thouſand of their owne men were there ready to enter, and we had bin loſt. 'Twas Gods hand that their ſhouts gave us the firſt Allarum to our ſafety and their deſtruction. In this hot skirmiſh we loſt but few, the moſt being butcher'd by them at their
<pb facs="tcp:156533:3"/>
firſt entrance unarm'd to prevent their giving <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ice, only three were loſt in fight. This was the only night (of any neglected) which the joy of the preſent reliefe occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned, but for the future doubled our Watches, forty Horſe in ſeverall Diviſlons ſtill riding the Rounds, and by their often viſits, a Sentinel hath ſcarce time to wink. My Lord Moore one night, and the Governor another (as ſuperviſors of the whole) have not failed ſince, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to watch in their owne perſons. The enemy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, on the South-ſide of the Towne, ſeemed to be about 3000 who in ſeverall bodies ſtayd one houre or two after day, believing the Towne to be taken, expecting the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of a Port, which we perceiving, and having taken, a Piper of theirs, cauſed him to play very merily on one of the Plat-formes, and to call out in Iriſh, that the Towne was theirs. It was good ſport to ſee them ſhorten the way by leaping ditches, and runing themſelves out of breath, who ſhould be firſt taken, and ſo were brought in by tens. This extraordinary bleſſing, I conceive, deſerv'd a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſolemne thankes-giving, which wee performed two daies after. A faire winde inviting the Pinnace next day to returne, paſt with as many praiers for ſafety by the Soldiers on the walls, as ſhe had bin received with prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. But a ſmall Fiſher-boate, as a full judgement of God for the former nights worke, by the unskillfulneſſe of the Pilate, ranne aground, and that nigh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was taken by the enemy, with foureteene Priſoners: alſo about three miles off, at Alermine Towne, the Pinnace fell into the like hazard, being moſt falſely left by the Shallopes, to the mercy of the enemy, who played upon her on both ſides, 100 of the Rebells, under the ſhelter of Carre-loads of Furs, deſperatly approached ſo neere, that they got under the Sterne, and with Crowes and Pike-axes began to bulge her, neither Pike nor Muſquet could offend them: in this ſtreight Captaine <hi>Stutvile</hi> (who hath much
<pb facs="tcp:156533:4"/>
deſerv'd) in the adventure of relieving us twice, threw ſome Granadoes amongſt them; they indured the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſix, but when the ſeventh was throwne, they ranne away and never attempted their deſigne after.</p>
            <p>The number of the ſlaine is uncertaine, but by the mighty ſtreame of blood it is conjectured 60. Whilſt we ſaw this danger we ceaſed not in publique to pray for her ſafety, whoſe loſſe was likely to be our ruine: That night ſhee was freed into the Poole, and one the Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day with a faire wind bid us farewell; We had another friggat which aſiſting the Pinnace in burning ſome Barques ranne the ſame caſualitie and lay under the ſame advantage to the Enemie. Who having made a breſt worke played on her all night, but returned with our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny harme ſave the loſſe of one man.</p>
            <p>Many Drums were ſent by the Rebels for exchange of Priſoners, till theirs here being ſpent, they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſend for more to <hi>Amagh,</hi> who have beene cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Towneſ-men. as if they had beene Martyrs. they giving them good Victuals Caddoes and Capps, ſoe that they make no ſute to be realeaſed. In 14. <hi>dayes</hi> our former ſupplies were waſted and a great Scarcitie began to grow among us: The whole deſigne of the Rebels we ſaw was to ſtarve us, by burning all the Corne and Hay within two Miles of us, they drew often nigh us, in the darke Nights, and in mockerie aſked our Sentinall, if we had yet eaten up our Cabidge ſtalks, and Horſe hides, and indeed the Famine was ſuch at length with the common Souldiers that Horſes, Catts and Dogs were good meat. Some proviſions by ſearching were found hid in Cellors this ſufficed not but we were forced to Sallie out which was alwaies bleſt with ſome releife and without the loſſe of any Souldiers <hi>February</hi> the 7th. we ſallied out 40. muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queteers and 25. Horſe to ſecure others, appointed to bring in proviſion, who were unexpectedly ſet upon by 400. newly come out of the North; we inſtantly charged
<pb facs="tcp:156533:4"/>
them, kild 80. tooke two of their Cullors kil'd a Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and on enſigne and took another, and 9. Priſoners, one dyed as ſoone as he came to Towne, and being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buttoned he was begirt with a Saint. <hi>Francis Girdle</hi> next his skin, not one of our men being hurt: Another time we marched out 100. Foot and a Troope of Horſe, we were ſet upon by 500. but we having notice by ſome of their owne Partie, of their intention, we made a faire retreate through them and killed many of them, of ours not one hurt, one was ſhot through the Dublet and Shirt and had his skin raſed: At length our ſtore failed us, ſo that from the hartieſt nothing could be heard but inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of deſperate courſes, our <hi>Friggatts</hi> and our <hi>Agents</hi> had beene long in <hi>Dublin</hi> but heard nothing of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and by the continuance of contrary winds our hopes wee ſaw were daſhed from thence, alſo in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity (beſides our ordinary meeting on <hi>Wenſday</hi>) wee appointed the next <hi>Friday</hi> as a day extraordinary onely to begg our bread of God for my Subject I tooke the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>Petition</hi> of the Lords Prayer, That day we continued in the Church from morning till evening, which was bleſt with much affection and teares, wherein ſome confident paſſages fell in aſſuring ſome preſent extraordinary an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, it might have ſeemed to have bin without warrant, but ſee the event: That very night, the winde inclined, and the next morning ſuddenly changed to as fair a wind and weather as we could wiſh and ſo continued, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning we received notice that our Supplie aproached on Sunday morning we met at church earlier then we uſed in the continuance of the ſame Subject, aad Petition and at the coucluſion of the Sermon, a meſſenger came into the Church with the glad tidings of our releif within the barre; it being ſo received in Gods houſe we tooke it as from God himſelfe: And ſo with thankes given to him from whom every good gift deſcendeth, we went and ſaw the ſalvation of God, I muſt not forget another delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb facs="tcp:156533:5"/>
the ſame Sunday morning, the Enemy about foure a clock with their whole ſtrength made a bold atempt with ſcaling Ladders to the wals, 2 or 3 were fixed in one place and ſome were gotten up the ſentinall miſſing fire at one, knockt him downe with the butt end of his Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, and crying out to the Guard who was nigh my cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber window I was the firſt that heard him, and the clat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of the Ladders, we inſtantly gave them their fill of Shot, and they left their ladders with ſome of their blood, the number of the ſlaine is uncertain they having drawn them away, but an Engliſh boy taking this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity eſcaped from them: ſaid he ſaw 3 lying in one ditch, by which may be conjectured, what was ſlaine of them, on our ſide not one hurt, ſo that in the word of Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſalmes.</hi> 136. <hi>verſe</hi> 24. Wee may praiſe God for that one day, who gives food to all fleſh, and who delivers us from our enemies, for his mercy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for ever. And get a farther deliverance, we are now quitting the Towne of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who have bin the cauſe of all this evill, ſome of the Aldermen are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſome have offered to go to Church, but it is thought with the ſame affection as the <hi>Capernaites</hi> (for the <hi>Loaues</hi>) An <hi>Inventory</hi> of all their goods are taken and ſuch of men and women as have bin ſuſpected to ſide with the <hi>Rebells,</hi> have their dayly paſſes to them, ſome ſober ſoules, and of good faſhion have deſir'd to be inform'd, in which worke ſhall be glad to be employed all day, and eyery day. A prize was alſo taken by the <hi>Pinnace</hi> laden with herring, Biſquets, and other proviſions, which hath added ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to our ſtore, we have 4. companies more ſo that we have in all 2000. Foote and 200. Horſe more I could have writ but the unexpected haſte of your Pinnaces returne, who is now ready to weigh Anchor cauſes me to breake off.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
