<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Poems. By W.H.</title>
            <author>Hammond, William, b. 1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87057</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1604_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208440</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867394</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867394</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119704</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A87057)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119704)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 203:E1604[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Poems. By W.H.</title>
                  <author>Hammond, William, b. 1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Dring at the George in Fleetstreet, neer Cliffords Inne Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.H. = William Hammond.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber [i.e. September] 13".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English poetry --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119704:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>POEMS.
<hi>By</hi> W. H.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—cineri gloria ſera venit.</l>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for <hi>Thomas Dring</hi> at the George
in Fleetſtreet, neer <hi>Cliffords</hi> Inne
Gate, 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:119704:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119704:2"/>
            <head>POEMS.</head>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Commanded to write VERSES.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince your Command inſpires</l>
               <l>My willing heart with Lyrick fires,</l>
               <l>Though my Compoſure owe its Birth,</l>
               <l>Or to cold Water, or dull Earth,</l>
               <l>Wanting the active qualities</l>
               <l>That ſprightly Fire and Aire compriſe;</l>
               <l>Yet guided by that Influence,</l>
               <l>I may with thoſe Defects diſpence:</l>
               <l>And Raptures no leſs winning vent</l>
               <l>Then the fam'd Thracian Inſtrument.</l>
               <l>What though old ſullen <hi>Saturn</hi> lye</l>
               <l>Brooding on my Nativity,</l>
               <l>So your bright eyes the Clouds diſpell,</l>
               <l>Which on my drooping Fancy dwell?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119704:3"/>
But ſtay, what Glaſſe have we ſo bright,</l>
               <l>To do your matchleſſe beauty right?</l>
               <l>Nature but from her owne diſgrace</l>
               <l>Can add no luſtre to that face;</l>
               <l>Nor from her patterns can we finde,</l>
               <l>A Form to repreſent your minde.</l>
               <l>The figures which this World inveſt</l>
               <l>Are Images in which expreſt</l>
               <l>Some truer Eſſences appear,</l>
               <l>Which not to ſight ſubjected are.</l>
               <l>So you fair <hi>Celia</hi> inwardly</l>
               <l>Diſſemble well the Deity,</l>
               <l>And counterfeit in fleſh and skin</l>
               <l>The fineneſſe of a <hi>Cherubin:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But fair one, if you muſt put on</l>
               <l>This Orders Inſtitution,</l>
               <l>Admitted to this Hierarchie,</l>
               <l>A Guardian Angell be to me.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119704:3"/>
               <head>The Walke.</head>
               <l>BLeſt Walke, that with your leavy armes imbrace</l>
               <l>In ſmall, what beauty the dilated face</l>
               <l>Of the whole World containes! The Violet,</l>
               <l>Bowing its humble head down at her feet,</l>
               <l>Payes homage for the livery of her vaines:</l>
               <l>Roſes and Lillies, and what beautuous ſtaines</l>
               <l>Nature adornes the Sping with, are but all</l>
               <l>Faint Copies of this fair Originall.</l>
               <l>She is a moving Paradiſe, doth view</l>
               <l>Your greens, not to refreſh her ſelfe, but you.</l>
               <l>This path's th' Ecliptick, heat prolifick hence</l>
               <l>Is ſhed on you by her kind influence;</l>
               <l>She is (alaſſe) too like the Sun, who grants</l>
               <l>That warmth to all, which in himſelfe he wants.</l>
               <l>You thus oblig'd, this benefit return,</l>
               <l>Teach her by Lectures viſible to burn;</l>
               <l>That She, when <hi>Zephyre</hi> moves each whiſpring bough</l>
               <l>To kiſſe his neighbour, thence may learn t' allow</l>
               <l>The reall ſeals of kindneſſe, and be taught</l>
               <l>By twining Woodbines what ſweet joyes are caught</l>
               <l>In ſuch imbraces: Thus and thouſand wayes</l>
               <l>Told you by amorous Fairies, and the layes</l>
               <l>Of your fond Guardian, waken her deſires,</l>
               <l>Requiting your own warmth with equall fires.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119704:4"/>
               <head>Husbandry.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen I began my Love to ſow,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe with <hi>Venus</hi> Doves I plow'd,</l>
                  <l>Fool that I was, I did not know</l>
                  <l>That frowns for furrows were allow'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The broken heart to make Clods torn</l>
                  <l>By the ſharp Harrows of diſdain,</l>
                  <l>Crumbled by preſſing rolls of ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>Gives iſſue to the ſpringing grain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Coyneſs ſhuts Love into a Stove,</l>
                  <l>So froſt-bound lands their own heat feed:</l>
                  <l>Neglect ſits brooding upon Love</l>
                  <l>As pregnant Snow on Winter-ſeed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Harveſt is not till we two</l>
                  <l>Shall into one contracted be;</l>
                  <l>Loves crop alone doth richer grow</l>
                  <l>Decreaſing to Identity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All other things not nouriſh'd are</l>
                  <l>But by Aſſimilation:</l>
                  <l>Love, in himſelf and Dyet ſpare,</l>
                  <l>Grows fat by Contradiction.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119704:4"/>
               <head>Mutuall Love.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FRom our loves, Heat and light are taught to twine,</l>
                  <l>In their bright nuptiall bed of ſolar beams.</l>
                  <l>From our loves <hi>Thame</hi> and <hi>Iſis</hi> learn to joyn,</l>
                  <l>Looſing themſelves in one anothers ſtreams.</l>
                  <l>And if Fate ſmile, the Fire loves emblem bears,</l>
                  <l>If not, the Water repreſents our tears.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From our Loves all magnetick virtue grows,</l>
                  <l>Steel to th' obdurate Loadſtone is inclind.</l>
                  <l>From our Loves all the power of Chymiſts flows,</l>
                  <l>Earth by the Sun is into Gold refind.</l>
                  <l>And if Fate ſmile, this ſhall Loves Arrows head,</l>
                  <l>If not, in thoſe is our hard fortune read.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From our ſtill ſpringing loves the youthfull Bayes,</l>
                  <l>Is in a robe of laſting verdure dreſt,</l>
                  <l>From our firm loves the Cypreſs learns to raiſe,</l>
                  <l>Green in deſpight of ſtorms, her deathleſs creſt.</l>
                  <l>And if Fate ſmile, with that our Temples bound,</l>
                  <l>If not, with this our Hearſes ſhall be crownd.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119704:5"/>
               <head>The forſaken Maid.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>GO fickle Man and teach the Moon to change,</l>
                  <l>The Winds to vary, the coy Bee to range:</l>
                  <l>You that deſpiſe the conqueſt of a Town</l>
                  <l>Renderd without reſiſtance of one frown.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Is this of eaſie faith the recompence?</l>
                  <l>Is my prone loves too prodigall expence,</l>
                  <l>Rewarded with diſdain? did ever dart,</l>
                  <l>Rebound from ſuch a penetrable heart?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diana,</hi> in the ſervice of whoſe Shrine,</l>
                  <l>My ſelfe to ſingle life I will confine,</l>
                  <l>Revenge thy Votareſſe; for unto thee</l>
                  <l>The reeling Ocean bends his a zure knee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſince he loves upon rough Seas to ride,</l>
                  <l>Grant ſuch an <hi>Adria,</hi> whoſe ſwelling Tide,</l>
                  <l>And ſtormy tongue may his falſe Veſſell wrack,</l>
                  <l>And make the Cordage of his heart to crack.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119704:5"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>KNow falſeſt Man, as my love was</l>
                  <l>Greater then thine, or thy deſert,</l>
                  <l>My ſcorne ſhall likewiſe thine ſurpaſſe,</l>
                  <l>And thus I tear thee from my heart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art ſo farr my love below,</l>
                  <l>That then my anger thou art leſſe;</l>
                  <l>I neither love nor quarrell now,</l>
                  <l>But pity thy unworthineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go joyn, before thou think to wed,</l>
                  <l>Thy heart and tongue in Wedlocks knot:</l>
                  <l>Can peace be reaped from his bed,</l>
                  <l>Who with himſelfe accordeth not?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go learn to weigh thy words upon</l>
                  <l>The ballance of reality,</l>
                  <l>And having that perfection</l>
                  <l>Attaind, come then, and Ile ſcorn thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119704:6"/>
               <head>J. C.</head>
               <head type="sub">Anagr. <hi>I can be any Lover.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>SEE how the letters of thy Name impart</l>
               <l>The very whiſpers of thy heart.</l>
               <l>This name came ſurely out of <hi>Adams</hi> mint,</l>
               <l>It bears ſo well thy Natures print.</l>
               <l>Woman, <hi>materia prima,</hi> doth preſent,</l>
               <l>Is to all <hi>Formes</hi> indifferent,</l>
               <l>As Pictures do at once with various eyes,</l>
               <l>Diſtinctly view all companies,</l>
               <l>With ſuch a ſtedfaſt look, that each man would</l>
               <l>Swear they did only him behold.</l>
               <l>Thus run we in a Wheel, where ſtedfaſt ground</l>
               <l>To fix our footing is not found,</l>
               <l>Whilſt Womans heart incliningly doth move</l>
               <l>Like twigs to every ſigh of Love.</l>
               <l>She who imparts her ſmiles to more then one,</l>
               <l>May many like, but can love none.</l>
               <l>The force of all things in contraction lies,</l>
               <l>And love thrives by Monopolies.</l>
               <l>Thoſe Glaſſes that collect the ſcatterd rayes</l>
               <l>Into one point, a flame can raiſe:</l>
               <l>Straiten the object, you increaſe loves ſtore;</l>
               <l>So loving leſſe, you love the more.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119704:6"/>
               <head>De Melidoria.</head>
               <head type="sub">è Joh. Barclaij, Poem. lib, 2.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHy languiſh I ye Gods alone?</l>
                  <l>Why onely I? when not one groan</l>
                  <l>Afflicteth her for whom I dye:</l>
                  <l>You mighty powers of Love, oh why</l>
                  <l>Doth <hi>Meledore</hi> deſpiſe your darts,</l>
                  <l>And their effects too, bleeding hearts?</l>
                  <l>If thus (oh Gods) ye ſuffer her</l>
                  <l>Unpuniſhed, none will prefer</l>
                  <l>Your Altars; ſuch examples may</l>
                  <l>Become the ruine of your ſway.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With <hi>Venus</hi> and her mighty Son</l>
                  <l>Expoſtulating thus, I won</l>
                  <l>This anſwer: Alaſſe (<hi>Cupid</hi> cryes)</l>
                  <l>I hood-winkt am; my cloſed eyes</l>
                  <l>Bound with a Fillet, that my Bow</l>
                  <l>Can none but roving Shafts let go;</l>
                  <l>Hence 'tis that Troops of violent</l>
                  <l>Youth, their miſplaced loves reſent;</l>
                  <l>That ſome love raſhly; ſome again</l>
                  <l>Congealed are with cold diſdain:</l>
                  <l>Wouldſt thou thy Miſtreſſe, I inſpire,</l>
                  <l>And in her breaſt convey that fire</l>
                  <l>Which nature ſuffers not to find</l>
                  <l>Birth from thy tears? Do but unbind</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119704:7"/>
My eyes, and I will take ſuch aime,</l>
                  <l>As ſhe ſhall not eſcape my flame:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus ſpake the Boy, my ready hand</l>
                  <l>Prepared was to looſe the band</l>
                  <l>From his faire eye-lids, that his ſight</l>
                  <l>Might to his Dart give ſteady flight;</l>
                  <l>When my good Genius prudent eare,</l>
                  <l>Whiſperd to my raſh ſoule, Beware:</l>
                  <l>Ah ſhameleſſe Boy, deceitfull Love,</l>
                  <l>I ſee thy plot, ſhould I remove</l>
                  <l>Thoſe chaines of darkneſſe from thy eyes,</l>
                  <l>Thou <hi>Melidore</hi> ſo much wouldſt prize,</l>
                  <l>That ſtrait my rivall thou wouldſt be,</l>
                  <l>And warme her for thy ſelfe, not me.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119704:7"/>
               <head>Delay.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon advice to deferr Loves Conſummation.</head>
               <l>DElay, whoſe Parents Phlegme and Slumber are,</l>
               <l>Thinkſt thou two Snailes drawing thy leaden Car,</l>
               <l>Can keep pace with the fiery wheels of loves</l>
               <l>Chariot, that receives motion from ſwift Doves?</l>
               <l>Go viſit Feavours, ſuch as conſcience wrack</l>
               <l>With fear of puniſhment in death, there ſlack</l>
               <l>The pulſe, or dwell upon the fatall tongues</l>
               <l>Of Judges, ſhut up their contagious lungs:</l>
               <l>Thou mayſt a Goale rejoyce, but not decree</l>
               <l>To Loves glad Priſoners a Jubilee.</l>
               <l>How canſt thou think thy Froſt with Icy Laws</l>
               <l>Can bind my tears, when Love thy cold chain thaws?</l>
               <l>He more intenſe for fighting Ice will be,</l>
               <l>And raiſe his heat unto the eighth degree.</l>
               <l>Thus through thy coldneſſe I ſhall feircer burn,</l>
               <l>And by thy Winter into Cinders turn.</l>
               <l>But ſince from Ignorance fears oft ariſe,</l>
               <l>And thence are ſtoln unequall Victories,</l>
               <l>Let us deſcribe this Foe, muſter his force:</l>
               <l>A handleſſe thing it is, and chills the ſourſe</l>
               <l>Of brave attempts. Eyes he pretends to much,</l>
               <l>Yet our experience often ſhews that ſuch</l>
               <l>Exactneſſe in Surveying, opes a gate</l>
               <l>To be ſurprizd by <hi>Semele's</hi> ſad Fate.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119704:8"/>
Tis a meer trunk, hath not for progre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s feet,</l>
               <l>Coward that fears his own deſires to meet.</l>
               <l>His Friends are ſcarſe; the Heavens, whoſe flight debates</l>
               <l>The race with thought, are no confederates:</l>
               <l>The World is love in act; ſuſpend this fire,</l>
               <l>The Globe to its old <hi>Chaos</hi> will retire:</l>
               <l>Infernall ſoules, but for his loathed ſtay</l>
               <l>Might hope their Night would open into Day.</l>
               <l>How can this Cripple then, not with one Band</l>
               <l>Aided by Earth, Heaven, Hell, his power withſtand,</l>
               <l>Who hath of Earth, Heaven, Hell, the forces broke,</l>
               <l>Impos'd on <hi>Neptunes</hi> ſelfe his ſcorching yoak?</l>
               <l>But if thou needſt will haunt me, let thy Mace</l>
               <l>Arreſt delight when I my Love imbrace.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119704:8"/>
               <head>Upon Cloris her viſit
after Marriage,</head>
               <head type="sub">A paſtorall Dialogue betwixt Codrus and Damon
forſaken rivalls.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Codrus.</speaker>
                  <l>WHy (<hi>Damon</hi>) did <hi>Arcadian</hi> Pan ordain</l>
                  <l>To drive our Flocks from that Meridian plain</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Cloris</hi> perpendicular ſhot beames</l>
                  <l>Scorch'd up our lawnes but that cool <hi>Charwells</hi> ſtreams</l>
                  <l>Might here abate thoſe flames which higher were</l>
                  <l>Then the faint moiſture of our Flocks could bear?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Damon.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Codrus,</hi> I wot the dog that tended there</l>
                  <l>Our Flocks was he which in the heavenly ſphear</l>
                  <l>So hotly hunts the <hi>Lyon</hi> that the trace</l>
                  <l>of <hi>Virgo</hi> ſcarſe his fiery ſteps allaies;</l>
                  <l>Into our vaines a feavour he convey'd,</l>
                  <l>And on our vitall Spirits fiercely prey'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119704:9"/>
                  <speaker>Codrus.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh why then brought ſhe back her torred Zone?</l>
                  <l>Conquer'd her Trophyes? Let us not alone</l>
                  <l>After ſo many deaths? renew'd our flame</l>
                  <l>When twas impoſſible to quench the ſame?</l>
                  <l>It is the puniſhment of Hell to ſhow</l>
                  <l>The torturd ſoules thoſe joyes they muſt not know?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Damon.</speaker>
                  <l>Though my Flock languiſh under her aſpect;</l>
                  <l>My panting Dog his office too neglect;</l>
                  <l>Though I refuſe repaſt, and by her eyes</l>
                  <l>Inflam'd, proſtrate my ſelfe her ſacrifice,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall yet covet ſtill her dubious rayes,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe light revives as much as her heat ſlayes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Codrus.</speaker>
                  <l>If <hi>Thyrcis</hi> ſlept not in her ſhady haire,</l>
                  <l>If in his armes her ſnow not melted were,</l>
                  <l>We might expect a more ſucceſsfull day,</l>
                  <l>And to ſome hopes our willing hearts betray,</l>
                  <l>Which now live deſperate without joy of light;</l>
                  <l>Her black eyes ſhed on us perpetuall night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Damon.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Codrus</hi> becauſe his ragged flock was thin,</l>
                  <l>His Sheep walk bare, and his Ewes did not yene,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119704:9"/>
His noble Love (hear this O Swaines) reſignd</l>
                  <l>His eyes delight a wealthier mate to find;</l>
                  <l>But ſhe (raſh in her choice) gave her embrace</l>
                  <l>To one whoſe bread courſer then <hi>Codrus</hi> was.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Codrus.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Damon</hi> (then whom none e're did longer burne;</l>
                  <l>Nor at his rate, upon ſo ſmall returne)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Damon</hi> (the pride and glory of the mead</l>
                  <l>When Nymphs and Swaines their tuned meaſures tread)</l>
                  <l>Begg'd of her that a better choice might prove</l>
                  <l>She lov'd her ſelfe, ſince him ſhe could not love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Damon.</speaker>
                  <l>Had <hi>Thyrſis</hi> flocks in milke abounded more,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould not with ſuch grief my loſſe deplore.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Codrus.</speaker>
                  <l>Could <hi>Thyrſis</hi> pipe more worthily reſound</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cloris,</hi> oh <hi>Cloris,</hi> I had comfort found.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Both.</speaker>
                  <l>That our heart-wracking ſighs no gaine bequeath</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Cloris,</hi> is a dying after death.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119704:10"/>
               <head>On the infrequency of
Celias Letters.</head>
               <l>DId not true love diſdaine to owne</l>
               <l>His ſpirit all duration</l>
               <l>From paper-fuell, I might gueſſe</l>
               <l>Thy love and writing both ſurceaſe</l>
               <l>Together; But I cannot think</l>
               <l>The life and Bloud of love is Ink;</l>
               <l>Yet as when <hi>Phaebus</hi> leaves our coaſt</l>
               <l>(The ſurface bound with chaines of froſt)</l>
               <l>Life is ſuſtained by courſe repaſt,</l>
               <l>Such as in Spring nauſeates the taſt,</l>
               <l>So in my winter whilſt you ſhine</l>
               <l>In the remoteſt Tropick ſigne</l>
               <l>Stramineous food paper and quill</l>
               <l>May fodder hungry love untill</l>
               <l>He reobtaine ſolſtitiall hours</l>
               <l>To feaſt upon thy beauties flowers.</l>
               <l>The wonders then of Nature we</l>
               <l>Within out ſelves will juſtifie:</l>
               <l>Or what monumentall boaſt</l>
               <l>The firſt world made, the latter loſt:</l>
               <l>Thy pointed flame ſhall conſtant 'bide</l>
               <l>As an eternall Pyramid;</l>
               <l>The never dying Lamp of Urnes</l>
               <l>Revivid in my boſome burnes:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119704:10"/>
Th' attractive virtue of the North</l>
               <l>Reſembleth thy magnetick worth;</l>
               <l>And from my ſcorcht heart through mine eyes</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aetnean</hi> flaſhes ſhall ariſe:</l>
               <l>we ſhall make good when more unite</l>
               <l>The fable of Hermaphrodite:</l>
               <l>The Spring and Harveſt of our bliſſe</l>
               <l>The ripe and budding Orange is;</l>
               <l>We little worlds ſhall thus rehearſe</l>
               <l>The wond<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs of the Univerſe</l>
               <l>As a ſmall watch keeps equall pace</l>
               <l>With the vaſt Sun's impetnous race</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119704:11"/>
               <head>To her queſtioning his Eſtate.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>PRethee no more, how can Love ſaile?</l>
                  <l>Thy providence becalmes our Seas:</l>
                  <l>Suſpenſive care binds up each gale;</l>
                  <l>Fear doth the lazy current freize.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Forecaſt and Love, the Lover ſweares,</l>
                  <l>Remov'd as the two Poles ſhould be:</l>
                  <l>But if on them muſt roll the ſpheares</l>
                  <l>Of our well tun'd felicity:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If Summes and Terrars I muſt bring,</l>
                  <l>Nor may my Inventory hide,</l>
                  <l>Know I am richer then the King</l>
                  <l>Who guilt Pactolus yellow Fide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For Love is our Philoſophers ſtone;</l>
                  <l>And whatſoever doth pleaſe thy ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>My priſing eſtimation</l>
                  <l>Shall elevate to quinteſſence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy lips each cup to wine ſhall charme,</l>
                  <l>As the Suns kiſſes do the Vine;</l>
                  <l>Naked embraces keep us warme;</l>
                  <l>And ſtript, then <hi>May</hi> thou art more fine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119704:11"/>
                  <l>And when thou haſt me in thy armes,</l>
                  <l>(The power of Fancie's then moſt high)</l>
                  <l>Inſtate me by thoſe mighty charmes</l>
                  <l>In ſome imperiall monarchy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus I am thy wealth, thou art mine:</l>
                  <l>And what to each other we appear,</l>
                  <l>If Love us two in one combine</l>
                  <l>The ſame then in our ſelves we are,</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119704:12"/>
               <head>The Spring.</head>
               <l>SEE how the Spring courts thee, <hi>Emaphilis;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The painted Meadowes to invite thy eyes</l>
               <l>But on their rich embroydery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſhade</l>
               <l>Of every grove is now an harbour made</l>
               <l>Where devout birds (to celebrate thy praiſe)</l>
               <l>Each morn and evening offer up their laies,</l>
               <l>Now the ſoft wind his winter-rage depoſes</l>
               <l>Sollicites Gardens for the breath of Roſſes.</l>
               <l>To pay as homage to thy ſweeter lips,</l>
               <l>Where ſuch Nectarean fragrancy he ſips</l>
               <l>That richly laden to the Eaſt he roues</l>
               <l>And with thy breath perfumes thoſe ſpicy groves:</l>
               <l>Their native fount and ſacred Naiades</l>
               <l>Theſe Iſſuing ſtreames renouncing to the preſſe;</l>
               <l>whom finding they with purling murmurs chide:</l>
               <l>That Natures Law Commands away their tide:</l>
               <l>wiſhing that winter would confine their race</l>
               <l>In Icy chaines, that they might ſtand and gaze;</l>
               <l>If thou canſt thus enflame Natures cold rheume</l>
               <l>What wonder that my youthfull floud conſume?</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119704:12"/>
               <head>The cruell Miſtreſſe.</head>
               <l>TELL me O love why <hi>Celia,</hi> ſmooth</l>
               <l>As Seas when winds forbear to ſooth</l>
               <l>Their waves to wanton curles, then down</l>
               <l>More ſoft which doth the Thiſtle Crown,</l>
               <l>Whither then is the milky road</l>
               <l>That leades to Joves ſupreme aboad,</l>
               <l>Should harder far and rougher be</l>
               <l>Then moſt obdurate rocks to me;</l>
               <l>Sheds on my hopes as little day</l>
               <l>As the pale Moon's aclipſed ray?</l>
               <l>My heart would break, but that I hear</l>
               <l>Love gently whiſper in my ear,</l>
               <l>Actions of women by affection lead</l>
               <l>Muſt backward like the ſacred tongue, be read</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:119704:13"/>
               <head>To his Miſtreſſe,
Deſiring him to abſent himſelfe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SEE how this river's liquid glaſſe</l>
                  <l>Can never ceaſe its motion,</l>
                  <l>Untill he hide his Chriſtall face</l>
                  <l>Ith' boſome of the Ocean.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The amorous Nymphs who cloſely guide</l>
                  <l>His purling Chariots reines,</l>
                  <l>Declare that loves impetuous tide</l>
                  <l>To be repreſt diſdaines.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Charm <hi>Zephyr</hi> that his gentle wing</l>
                  <l>Not with <hi>Narciſſus</hi> play;</l>
                  <l>The Sun in his diurnall ring</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Thetis</hi> lap delay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Stop the departed ſoules career</l>
                  <l>To its appointed bliſſes;</l>
                  <l>All thi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> effected, you may ſteer</l>
                  <l>Me to abſtaine your kiſſes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:119704:13"/>
               <head>To his ſcornfull Miſtreſſe.</head>
               <l>LOve in's firſt infant dayes had 's Wardrobe full;</l>
               <l>Sometimes we found him courting in a Bull.</l>
               <l>Then, dreſt in ſnowy plumes, his long neck is</l>
               <l>Made pliable and fit to reach a kiſſe:</l>
               <l>When apteſt for imbraces he became</l>
               <l>Either a winding Snake, or curling Flame:</l>
               <l>And cunningly a preſſing kiſſe to gaine,</l>
               <l>The Virgins honour in a Grape would ſtaine:</l>
               <l>When he conſulted Lawns for privacies,</l>
               <l>The Shepheard, or his Ram was his diſguiſe:</l>
               <l>But the blood raging to a rape, put on</l>
               <l>A Satyre, or a wilder Stallion;</l>
               <l>And for variety, in <hi>Thetis</hi> Court</l>
               <l>Did like a Dolphin with the Sea-Nymph ſport:</l>
               <l>But ſince the ſad Barbarian yoak hath bowd</l>
               <l>The Grecian neck, Love hath leſſe change allowd,</l>
               <l>Contracted lives in eyes; no flaming robes</l>
               <l>Wears, but are lent him in your Chriſtall Globes:</l>
               <l>Not worth a waterd Garment; when he wears</l>
               <l>That Element he ſteals it from my tears.</l>
               <l>A Snake he is (alaſſe) when folded in</l>
               <l>Your frowns, where too much ſting guards the fair skin</l>
               <l>A Shepheard unto cares, and onely ſips</l>
               <l>The bluſhing Grape of your Nectarean lips:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119704:14"/>
The Ram Bull ſtallion Satyrs onely fight</l>
               <l>Loves battels now in my wild appetite.</l>
               <l>He in his Swan too ſuffers a reſtraint,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cygnaean</hi> onely in my dying plaint.</l>
               <l>Since all his actions love to moralls turnes,</l>
               <l>And faintly now in things leſſe reall burnes,</l>
               <l>In ſuch a weakneſſe contraries deſtroy,</l>
               <l>And ſhe his murdreſſe is, who now is coy.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119704:14"/>
               <head>To M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> J. L.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon his Treatiſe of Dialling.</head>
               <l>OLd time but for thy art, alone would paſſe,</l>
               <l>And idly bear his ſolitary glaſſe:</l>
               <l>Though he fly faſt, thy judgment mounted on</l>
               <l>The wings of fancy, yoakes his motion:</l>
               <l>Each little ſand falls not unqueſtioned by</l>
               <l>The due obſervance of thy piercing eye;</l>
               <l>Each moment you converſe with ſo, that thus</l>
               <l>Diſcourſing his ſtage ſeemes not tedious:</l>
               <l>others perhaps by their mechanick art</l>
               <l>May ask him what's a clock, then let him part:</l>
               <l>Thou in thy circles conjur'ſt him to ſtay</l>
               <l>Till he relate to thee the month and day;</l>
               <l>All propoſitions of the Globe doſt bring</l>
               <l>To be confeſt as well in dialling:</l>
               <l>What lucky ſignes ſucceſſively do run,</l>
               <l>By the reclining chariot of the Sun;</l>
               <l>And in a various dialect of Schemes</l>
               <l>Interprets't all the motions of his beames</l>
               <l>How many houres each day he travells in</l>
               <l>When he arrives diogonall Inne.</l>
               <l>Other bookes ſhow the trade of dialling,</l>
               <l>But thine the art and reaſon of the thing:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119704:15"/>
Thou knowſt the ſpring and cauſe that makes it go;</l>
               <l>Addeſt new wheeles; demonſtrated all ſo</l>
               <l>That weake eyes now may ſee what was before</l>
               <l>Defective in the fam'd <hi>Oſorius</hi> ſtore:</l>
               <l>A lim at leaſt of this celeſtiall trade</l>
               <l>Aſleep till now lay in the Gnomons ſhade;</l>
               <l>Nor teacheſt thou as thoſe who firſt did find</l>
               <l>With much circumference the Indian mine;</l>
               <l>Thy needle points the neareſt way, and hath</l>
               <l>Made ſtreight th' obliquity of the old path;</l>
               <l>Thou nor thine art our praiſes need, yet I</l>
               <l>Will for this miracle both deify.</l>
               <l>Thine art enlightens by a ſhade, of that</l>
               <l>Nothing a reall Science you create.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119704:15"/>
               <head>Epithalamium,</head>
               <head type="sub">To the L. T. marryed in the North.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WElcome faireſt, Thee our rime</l>
                  <l>Congratulates rather then him</l>
                  <l>Who ſhines obliquely on our Clime.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy beams directly pointed fall,</l>
                  <l>That we our Bear the Cancer call,</l>
                  <l>This Zone ſtile Equinoctiall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The miſts our Germane Seas create</l>
                  <l>Thy eyes (though <hi>Phaebus</hi> mediate)</l>
                  <l>Originally diſſipate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caſſiope,</hi> though heavenly faire,</l>
                  <l>Hides her new face and burniſht Chaire,</l>
                  <l>When you enlighten the dayes aire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They onely rule materiall ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>Your loves example may diſpence</l>
                  <l>To inflam'd ſoules chaſt influence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119704:16"/>
                  <l>Unto that flame which doubly warmes</l>
                  <l>(Thy beauty's Summer, and loves charmes)</l>
                  <l>May time nor ſickneſs threaten harmes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Hymens torch on northen ſhore</l>
                  <l>Dilate into a Pharos; For</l>
                  <l>Beſieg'd by cold fire burnes the more</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119704:16"/>
               <head>To Eugenio,</head>
               <head type="sub">A diſcription of the love of
true Friendſhip.</head>
               <l>MAN, of a troubled Spirit, prone to fight,</l>
               <l>In fortitude placing too much delight,</l>
               <l>Unjuſtly Friendſhip diſinherited,</l>
               <l>No dowry to her hath proportioned</l>
               <l>Amongſt the morall Siſters of the will;</l>
               <l>Goddeſſe of youth though ſhe, yet ſhould not fill</l>
               <l>Their cups, be ſhe none of the wheeles, her right</l>
               <l>Is in the treaſure, drawes the appetite</l>
               <l>To amiable good; But if the raine</l>
               <l>Be held by Prudence (for ſhe guides the wain)</l>
               <l>This virtue next inheritrix is ſhe,</l>
               <l>Fitted to turne upon that axletree;</l>
               <l>For lamely would the wills bright chariot move</l>
               <l>If not inform'd by friendly heat of Love,</l>
               <l>Whoſe lightning ſhoots directly, never bends</l>
               <l>Reflecting glances upon private ends.</l>
               <l>Indeed her ſiſter (of a baſtard race)</l>
               <l>Squints on her good, like <hi>Venus</hi> in her glaſſe;</l>
               <l>Mechanick love, deſire with uſury,</l>
               <l>Which nere is lent but for utility,</l>
               <l>Or ſome returne of pleaſure to the ſenſe;</l>
               <l>A thrifty worldling hight Concupiſcence.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119704:17"/>
The firſt a wealthy Queen of generous ſtrain;</l>
               <l>The latter indigent, and works for gaine;</l>
               <l>That, from the boſome of the deitie;</l>
               <l>Derives the luſtre of her pedigree;</l>
               <l>Who of this wonder truely is poſſeſt</l>
               <l>Hath heavens Epitome lodg'd in his breaſt;</l>
               <l>This Children to their Parents give; by this</l>
               <l>Perfumd with Frankincenſe the alter is;</l>
               <l>That's Gold refined, whoſe ſolidity</l>
               <l>(The perfect emblem of true conſtancy)</l>
               <l>Being ductile, will conſume it ſelfe and pine</l>
               <l>Even to ſmall threads, to make another fine:</l>
               <l>Self-loving this as ſubtle Mercury,</l>
               <l>Which parted, to it ſelf again doth fly</l>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119704:17"/>
               <head>Ad amicum &amp; cognatum T. S.</head>
               <l>AETernae, primo repetam de fonte Sobrine</l>
               <l>A nobis initum foedus amicitiae;</l>
               <l>Non erat in cauſis probitas promiſcua morum,</l>
               <l>Quodque iiſdem tecum ritibus oro deum,</l>
               <l>Nec ſimul edocti quod avenam in flavimus unam,</l>
               <l>Nec Quod de noſtra ſtripe racemus eras?</l>
               <l>Hae modo conciliatrices ſi mentibus eſſent</l>
               <l>Convictus, virtus, ſtrips eademque fides</l>
               <l>Debueram plures arſiſſe hac lege, merentes</l>
               <l>Aeque de noſtra forſan amicitia.</l>
               <l>Cauſa ſubeſt ex Naturae penetralibus hauſta,</l>
               <l>Eſſe meae paritas indolis atque tuae:</l>
               <l>Si flammam admoveas flammae, ſi fluctibus undas,</l>
               <l>Res in idem, fuerat quae modo bina, redit.</l>
               <l>Confuſi pariter genio coaleſcimus uno,</l>
               <l>Compageſque tuae mentis ubique mea eſt:</l>
               <l>Cumque meum tecum ſimilaribus undique conſtet</l>
               <l>Partibus ingenium, prona ſynaxis erat:</l>
               <l>Virtutis ſeges ampla tuae ſit mater amoris,</l>
               <l>Mater amicitiae non critilla meae:</l>
               <l>Plures inter amor diffunditur; ipſo duorum</l>
               <l>Tantum, qui fiunt unus, amicitia eſt,</l>
               <l>Quicquid id eſt quod nos a nobis cogit amari</l>
               <l>Nos eadem ratio temet amare facit.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119704:18"/>
               <head>To the ſame being ſicke of a feavour.
Horat: od: 2. 17.</head>
               <l>AM not I in thy feavour ſacrifiz'd?</l>
               <l>That you alone by Fate ſhould beſurpriz'd,</l>
               <l>(You my ſole Sun-ſhine, my Soules wealth and pride)</l>
               <l>Is both by me and by the Gods denide:</l>
               <l>If haſty death take thee (my ſoule) away,</l>
               <l>Can I, a loath'd imperfect carkaſſe ſtay?</l>
               <l>No no; Our twiſted lives muſt be cut both</l>
               <l>Together; This I dare confirm by oath,</l>
               <l>When e're thou leapſt into the fatall boat</l>
               <l>Ile leap in, glad with thee in death to float:</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall that dubious monſter, breathing fire,</l>
               <l>Nor Gyges hundred hands did he reſpire,</l>
               <l>Pluck me from this reſolve approved ſo</l>
               <l>By Fate and Juſtice: whither <hi>Scorpio</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fierce in my Horoſcope, or Capricorne</l>
               <l>Oppreſſing Latium with his watry horne,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Libra</hi> brooded my nativity,</l>
               <l>'Tis ſure our mutuall Stars ſtrangley agree.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119704:18"/>
               <head>To the ſame,</head>
               <head type="sub">Recovered of the ſmall Pox.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NAture foreſeeing that if thou wert gone,</l>
                  <l>And we her younger Children left alone,</l>
                  <l>None could with Virtue feed this beggerd age</l>
                  <l>(For with thee Heir is gone, and Heritage)</l>
                  <l>In pitty longer lent us Thee, that ſo</l>
                  <l>Thou mightſt lead mankind, and teach how to go,</l>
                  <l>How to ſpeak Languages, to diſcourſe how,</l>
                  <l>How the created book of things to know,</l>
                  <l>How with ſmooth cadence harſher verſe to file,</l>
                  <l>Within ſoft numbers to confine a ſtile,</l>
                  <l>And laſtly how to love a freind, for this</l>
                  <l>Leſſon the Crown of humane actions is.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor was't in pitty to our ſtate alone.</l>
                  <l>She, as all do, reflected on her owne,</l>
                  <l>And gave thee longer breath, that our deſire</l>
                  <l>Might learne of thine her beauty to admire</l>
                  <l>Nor out of pitty to thy youth, whoſe hearſe</l>
                  <l>Not to thy ſelfe, but to the Univerſe</l>
                  <l>Had Ship-wrack been; For thou hadſt ſtood being dead</l>
                  <l>Above the ſphear of being pittied.</l>
                  <l>Let then this thy redintegrated wrack</l>
                  <l>Not Irkſome be if onely for our ſake,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:119704:19"/>
(For friendſhip is the greateſt argument</l>
                  <l>Moves us to be from Angels here content)</l>
                  <l>Yet one inducement more thy ſtay may plead,</l>
                  <l>That nature hath ſo clean thy priſon made;</l>
                  <l>What though ſhe pit thy skin? She onely can</l>
                  <l>Deface the woman in thee, not thee Man.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119704:19"/>
               <head>To the ſame.</head>
               <l>LEt me not live if I not wonder why</l>
               <l>In night of rurall contemplation I,</l>
               <l>So long have dream't, when from thy lips I might</l>
               <l>As inſtantly gain intellectuall light</l>
               <l>As by this Amphitheater of aire</l>
               <l>The Suddain beames of Sol imbibed are;</l>
               <l>Why then by reflex Letters like the Moon</l>
               <l>Shine I, when thou invit'ſt me to thy Noon?</l>
               <l>Why do I vainly ſweat here to controule</l>
               <l>Th' aſſertours of the periſhable Soule,</l>
               <l>Where all the reaſon I encounter, can</l>
               <l>Scarſe win beliefe a tuſtick is a man.</l>
               <l>To reconcile the contradiction</l>
               <l>Of Freedome with Predeſtination,</l>
               <l>To be reſolv'd the Earth doth roſt upon</l>
               <l>Her Ax is as a ſpit againſt the Sun,</l>
               <l>Or what bold Argive fleet durſt to tranſlate</l>
               <l>Of thoſe beaſts that firſt ſtraid from <hi>Ararat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Onely the noxious to <hi>America,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And how theſe puny Pilots found the way,</l>
               <l>Or whether from the habitable Moon,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Saturn,</hi> they, and <hi>Vulcan,</hi> tumbled down,</l>
               <l>Whether abroad Imaginations work,</l>
               <l>Whether in numbers potency doth lurk,</l>
               <l>Whether all Earth intended was for gold,</l>
               <l>And thouſands more we doubtfully do hold?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119704:20"/>
Thus we poor Scepticks in the region</l>
               <l>Of Fancy float, foes to aſſertion,</l>
               <l>But I will pearch on thee, and make my ſtand</l>
               <l>Of ſetled knowledge on thy ſteady hand.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:119704:20"/>
               <head>To the ſame,
On my Library,
A SATYRE.</head>
               <l>A Hundred here together buriedly,</l>
               <l>Still jangling with eternall enmity,</l>
               <l>Conteſting after death; The ſtagirite</l>
               <l>Advanceth there with his truſt band, to fight</l>
               <l>Againſt Ideas: Th' Epicurean Band</l>
               <l>In Armes which pleaſure guilt, here ready ſtand</l>
               <l>To charge the ruſty Sword of the ſevere</l>
               <l>Stoick. Phlebotomizing <hi>Galen</hi> there</l>
               <l>Triumphs in bloud, and not the bad alone</l>
               <l>Exterminates his corporation,</l>
               <l>But makes joynt Oſtraciſmes for the good;</l>
               <l>Till later wits reſenting Natures food</l>
               <l>In greateſt need Promiſcuouſly had been</l>
               <l>Diſgariſond, invent new diſcipline,</l>
               <l>Strengthening the vitalls with ſome cordiall doſe,</l>
               <l>Which Nature might which unbroke files oppoſe.</l>
               <l>But upon freſh ſupplies let her caſhire,</l>
               <l>If not reducible, each mutineer.</l>
               <l>On yonder ſhelfe we may the heritage</l>
               <l>Find of this heathen ſword fal'n to our age:</l>
               <l>A doubtfull blade whoſe fore-edge guards the ſenſe</l>
               <l>Of Stoicks Fate; The ſharp back is the fence</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:119704:21"/>
Of Lernean Predeſtination,</l>
               <l>The bane of Crownes and true devotion.</l>
               <l>The wills ability <hi>Pelagius</hi> calls</l>
               <l>What Peripateticks ſtile <hi>Pure Naturalls.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The point by which Philoſophy did uſe</l>
               <l>To prove Ideas, you'l confeſſe obtuſe</l>
               <l>To that by which Religion now maintaines</l>
               <l>Uncouth Chimaeras of exorbitant braines.</l>
               <l>As the worlds noble Soule, the generous Sun</l>
               <l>By an equivocall conjunction</l>
               <l>Begets the baſeſt creeping progeny,</l>
               <l>So when the princely Sire Phyloſophy</l>
               <l>Adulterates faith, the monſters that ariſe</l>
               <l>Degenerate to baſtard Hereſies.</l>
               <l>Thus have I made a ſhort narration</l>
               <l>Here of a poſthumus contention:</l>
               <l>They to thy Judgement all ſubmit their hate,</l>
               <l>Hoping thy preſence ſoon will moderate</l>
               <l>Their vaſt diſſent, as element all ſtrife</l>
               <l>Is <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inder far when actuated by life.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:119704:21"/>
               <head>To the ſame, on his Poems and
Tranſlations.</head>
               <l>IF what we know be made our ſelves, (for by</l>
               <l>Dev<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſting all materiality,</l>
               <l>And melting the bare ſpecies into</l>
               <l>Our intellect; Our ſelves are what we know)</l>
               <l>Thou art in largeneſſe of thy knowing mind</l>
               <l>As a Seraphick eſſence unconfind,</l>
               <l>Content within thoſe narrow walls to dwell,</l>
               <l>Yet canſt ſo far that point of fleſh outſwell</l>
               <l>That thine intelligence extends through all</l>
               <l>Languages which we Europaean call.</l>
               <l>What Coloſſaean ſtrides doſt thou enlarge!</l>
               <l>Fixing one foot in <hi>Sequan's</hi> watry barge</l>
               <l>Doſt in <hi>Po</hi> t'other lave, teaching each Swan</l>
               <l>A note more dying then their Idiom can:</l>
               <l>Vext <hi>Tagus</hi> Nympths receive of thee new dreſſes,</l>
               <l>Compoſing in <hi>Thame's</hi> glaſſe their golden treſſes:</l>
               <l>Yea more I've ſeen thy young Muſe bath her wing</l>
               <l>In the deep waters of <hi>Stagira's</hi> Spring.</l>
               <l>Nor do thy beames warm by reflex alone;</l>
               <l>Thoſe that emerge directly from the Sun</l>
               <l>Of thy rich Fancy, warm our loves, as well</l>
               <l>As thoſe whom other Languages repell;</l>
               <l>Thou the divine acts thus doſt imitate,</l>
               <l>As well conſerve an Author, as create.</l>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119704:22"/>
                  <l>On then brave youth, Learnings full Syſteme; Go</l>
                  <l>Enlarge thy ſelfe to a vaſt Folio;</l>
                  <l>That the world in ſuſpence where to beſtow</l>
                  <l>That admiration which it late did ow</l>
                  <l>To the large knowing Belgick Magazine [<hi>H. Grot</hi>]</l>
                  <l>May juſtly pay it thee as his aſſigne:</l>
                  <l>If future houres with laden thighes ſhall ſtrive</l>
                  <l>To fill as well thine intellectuall hive</l>
                  <l>As thoſe are paſt, the Court of Honour muſt</l>
                  <l>To Crown thee, raviſh Garlands from his duſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:119704:22"/>
               <head>To the ſame on his Poems,</head>
               <head type="sub">That he would likewiſe manifeſt his more
Serious labours.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THou Natures ſtep here treadeſt in,</l>
                  <l>Doſt ſhow us but thy Soules fair skin,</l>
                  <l>What Phancy more then Intellect did ſpin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus Nature ſhowes the roſes paint,</l>
                  <l>Us with the outſide doth acquaint,</l>
                  <l>But keeps reſerv'd the ſoule of the fair plant.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy ſailes all ſee ſwelling with haſt;</l>
                  <l>Yet the hid ballaſt ſteeres as faſt</l>
                  <l>His ſteady courſe as the apparant maſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For though carv'd workes onely appeare</l>
                  <l>We know there is a Baſis here</l>
                  <l>Doth them together with the Fabrick bear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And that thy lightning Intellect,</l>
                  <l>Though in the cloudes yet undetect</l>
                  <l>Can Natures bowells pierce with its aſpect.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:119704:23"/>
                  <l>Melting through ſtubborn doubts his way,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt Fancy guilds things with her ray,</l>
                  <l>And but oth' ſurface doth of Nature play.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But whilſt thy Intellect doth wear</l>
                  <l>Thy Phancies dreſſe, his motions are</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Epicides</hi> not his proper ſphear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Breake forth and let his double ſigne</l>
                  <l>In their own orbes diſtinctly ſhine;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caſtor</hi> alone bodes danger to the Pine.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:119704:23"/>
               <head>To the ſame</head>
               <head type="sub">On His Tranſlation of two Spaniſh Novells.</head>
               <l>THis Tranſplantation of Sicilian Loves</l>
               <l>To the more pleaſing ſhades of <hi>Albion's</hi> groves</l>
               <l>Though I admire, yet not the thing betrayes</l>
               <l>My ſoule to ſo much wonder, as the wayes</l>
               <l>And manner of effecting; That thy youth</l>
               <l>Untravail'd there, ſhould with ſuch happy truth</l>
               <l>Unlock us this Iberian Cabinet,</l>
               <l>Whoſe diamonds you in poliſht Engliſh ſet,</l>
               <l>Such as may teach the eyes of any dame</l>
               <l>Ith' Brittiſh Court to give and take a flame;</l>
               <l>Herein the greateſt miracle we ſee,</l>
               <l>That Spain for this hath traveld unto thee.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:119704:24"/>
               <head>To the ſame.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>DAmon,</hi> thrice happy are thy layes</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Amarillis</hi> deignes to praiſe,</l>
                  <l>And teacheſt them no reſtleſſe flame,</l>
                  <l>But Centers thy love there whence firſt it came!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her Soul ſhe, and her wealthy flocks</l>
                  <l>Mingles with thine; Braids her bright locks</l>
                  <l>Becomingly with thy brown ſhade,</l>
                  <l>Whence the Morn is ſo ſweetly doubtfull made.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh may that twiſted twilights power</l>
                  <l>Infuſe in each ſucceſſive houre</l>
                  <l>Eternall calmes, untainted raies!</l>
                  <l>Your treſſes rule her nights, and hers your dayes!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whilſt <hi>Thyrſis</hi> his ſad reed inſpires</l>
                  <l>With nought but ſighs and hopeleſſe fires;</l>
                  <l>Yet glad to ſpy from his dark Cell</l>
                  <l>The dawn of Joy from others night expell.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119704:24"/>
               <head>On the Marriage of my deare
Kinſman T. S. <abbr>Eſq</abbr> and
Mrs. D. E.</head>
               <l>WHilſt the yong world was in minority</l>
               <l>Much was indulged; no proximity</l>
               <l>Of equall bloud could then ſtile marriage</l>
               <l>Inceſtuous: But in her riper age</l>
               <l>Nature a polititian grew, and laid</l>
               <l>A ſin on wedlock that at home was made:</l>
               <l>That Families being mixt, the world might ſo</l>
               <l>Both Iſſue propogate and Friendſhip too,</l>
               <l>How will you two then Natures frown abide,</l>
               <l>Who are in worthineſſe ſo neer allide?</l>
               <l>(For ſure ſhe meant that other vertues be</l>
               <l>Enlarged thus, as well as Amitie.)</l>
               <l>Civility you might have taught the North,</l>
               <l>She the South Chaſtity: But now this worth</l>
               <l>Is wanting unto both, 'cauſe you engroſſe</l>
               <l>And to your ſelves communicate this loſſe.</l>
               <l>But ſince beſt tempers vertae ſoon admit,</l>
               <l>Your two well-tun'd complections may ſo fit</l>
               <l>A <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cond race, and naturall goodneſſe lend,</l>
               <l>That nature ſhall not thus miſſe of her end.</l>
               <l>On matchleſſe couple then, Hymen ſmiles, on,</l>
               <l>And by a perfect generation</l>
               <l>Such living Statues of your ſelves erect,</l>
               <l>That they thoſe vertues which this age reject</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:119704:25"/>
May teach the future, and to act reſtore,</l>
               <l>All Honour, living onely now in power.</l>
               <l>Be thou the <hi>Adam,</hi> ſhe the <hi>Eve</hi> that may</l>
               <l>Pople a true reall <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119704:25"/>
               <head>To M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> D. S. on the birth of
Sidney, her ſecond Son.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Neice.</salute>
               </opener>
               <l>MAY reſt drown all thy paines: But never ſleep</l>
               <l>Thy painfull merits whilſt feet Verſes keep,</l>
               <l>And Muſes wings they ſhall along, and blow</l>
               <l>Thy Fame abroad, whilſt time ſhall circuits go</l>
               <l>To judge ſtrifes elementall, and arowſe</l>
               <l>The drouſy world to mind this noble ſpouſe.</l>
               <l>How opportunely her Heroick fruit</l>
               <l>Waving her own, doth our torn ſex recruit</l>
               <l>Two Boyes have ſprung from her wombs lively mold,</l>
               <l>'Ere both the Parents fourty Summers told.</l>
               <l>She might ſuch humane Goddeſſes produce</l>
               <l>As might the relapſ'd world again amuſe</l>
               <l>Into Idolatry, and juſtify</l>
               <l>Bright <hi>Cyprias</hi> fable, each poetick ly</l>
               <l>Old Greece or any modern lover made</l>
               <l>To deify the beauty of a Maid.</l>
               <l>But The prizing her mate 'bove her own eyes</l>
               <l>Him rather with his likeneſſe gratifies;</l>
               <l>The reaſon, if a Poet may divine,</l>
               <l>Why all her Bloſſomes quicken maſculine</l>
               <l>Is, that her Brethren (never extant ſeen,</l>
               <l>But poſſible) by Fate have kindred been</l>
               <l>Into her fleſh, which flowers in Virgin Snow</l>
               <l>Benum'd, ſlept in their winter cauſe, till now</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:119704:26"/>
That Nuptiall Sun approacht, whoſe piercing ray</l>
               <l>Op'ning their Urn, recall'd them into day.</l>
               <l>On this trade Angells wait, and on their wing</l>
               <l>Created Soules into new Bodies bring:</l>
               <l>What power hath Love, that can ſet Heaven a task</l>
               <l>To make a Gem, when he prepares the Cask?</l>
               <l>And if well ſet, or void of heynous flaw,</l>
               <l>Ordained by the Creatures gracious Law</l>
               <l>For his own weating, which himſelfe will own</l>
               <l>An Ornament even to his burniſht Crown.</l>
               <l>On then fair ſpouſe, and eaſe the pangs of Birth</l>
               <l>By thinking you enrich both Heaven and Earth.</l>
               <l>Think you may live till they in honours ſphear</l>
               <l>Brighter then the <hi>Tindaridae</hi> appear;</l>
               <l>And then you cannot dy? the lives you gave,</l>
               <l>They amply will repay, deſpoile the grave</l>
               <l>Of your Immortall name: may you behold</l>
               <l>Them fully act the praiſe I faintly told.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119704:26"/>
               <head>Horat: Od. 3. 3.</head>
               <head type="sub">A Man endeed uwith Virtue feares nothing.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe preſence of a Tyrant, nor the zeale</l>
                  <l>Of Citizens forcing rebellions,</l>
                  <l>Can ſhake a ſquarely ſolid ſoule, the ſeale</l>
                  <l>Infringe of honeſt reſolutions:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Untroubled He on ſtormy <hi>Adria</hi> Sailes;</l>
                  <l>At Thunder is undaunted as the oak:</l>
                  <l>If nature in a generall ruine failes</l>
                  <l>He with contented mind ſuſtaines the ſtroak.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:119704:27"/>
               <head>To Sr. J. G. wiſhing me to regain
my fortunes by complyance
with the Parliament.</head>
               <l>THE reſignation of my ſelfe and mine</l>
               <l>I proſtrate at the footſtep of his Shrine,</l>
               <l>Who for the mighty love he bore to me</l>
               <l>Laid out himſelfe in each capacity,</l>
               <l>Unasked pawnes his deity, and ſhrouds</l>
               <l>All mighty feebleneſſe in humane clouds,</l>
               <l>And even that Cottage did to death engage</l>
               <l>For three dayes, to redeem our Heritage;</l>
               <l>For no leſſe price then his humanity</l>
               <l>Could ranſome us, ſtampt with divinity.</l>
               <l>The ſtory of this noble Surety (friend)</l>
               <l>Should to ſuch extaſy our zeales extend,</l>
               <l>That our Eſtates or ſelves we ne're ſhould deeme</l>
               <l>So free, as when they morgag'd are for him:</l>
               <l>I therefore can with a contented mind</l>
               <l>Shake hands with all the wealth of either Inde;</l>
               <l>In a clear conſcience finding riches more</l>
               <l>Then there the Sun bequeaths unto his Ore;</l>
               <l>Who drinks with ſacred Druids at the brook,</l>
               <l>(Whoſe unjuſt ſufferings are for guilt miſtook,)</l>
               <l>And from their mouth (now the forbidden tree</l>
               <l>Alaſſe, of knowledge) ſucks divinity,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119704:27"/>
With Angels on an honeſt bed of leaves</l>
               <l>Redintegrated Paradiſe conceaves;</l>
               <l>For Heaven is onely Gods revealed face;</l>
               <l>So theſe make Paradiſe, and not the place.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:119704:28"/>
               <head>The World.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>JS this that goodly Edifice</l>
                  <l>So gaz' d upon by greedy eyes?</l>
                  <l>A ſceane where cruelty's expreſt,</l>
                  <l>Or Stage of folly es at the beſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who can the Muſick underſtand</l>
                  <l>From the ſoft touch of Natures hand,</l>
                  <l>When man her chiefeſt Inſtrument</l>
                  <l>So harſhly jarres without conſent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Do not her naturall agents too</l>
                  <l>Faile in their operations, ſo</l>
                  <l>That he to whom they beſt appeare</l>
                  <l>Sees but the Tombes of what they were?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her chiefeſt Actions then are ſuch</l>
                  <l>That no externall ſenſe may touch;</l>
                  <l>Shown doubtfully to the minds ſight</l>
                  <l>By the dark Phancy's glimmering light.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Night indeed which hideth all</l>
                  <l>Things elſe diſcloſeth the Stars pale</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119704:28"/>
And ſickly faces; but our ſenſe</l>
                  <l>Cannot perceive their Influence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They are the hidden books of Fate,</l>
                  <l>Where what with paines we calculate</l>
                  <l>And doubt, is onely plainly known</l>
                  <l>To thoſe aſſiſt their motion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The cloſe conveyances that move</l>
                  <l>With ſilent vertue from above</l>
                  <l>Inceſſantly on things below,</l>
                  <l>Our duller eyes can never know.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nothing but colour, ſhape and light</l>
                  <l>Create their ſpecies in our ſight:</l>
                  <l>All ſubſtances avoyd the ſenſe</l>
                  <l>Cloſe couched under accidents,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In which attir'd by nature, we</l>
                  <l>Their looſe apparell onely ſee;</l>
                  <l>Spirits alone Intuitive,</l>
                  <l>Can to the heart of eſſence dive.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why then ſhould we deſire to ſleep</l>
                  <l>Groveling like ſwine in mire, ſo deep,</l>
                  <l>The mind for breath can find no way,</l>
                  <l>Choak'd up, and crowded into clay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:119704:29"/>
                  <l>Stript of the fleſh, in the clear ſpring</l>
                  <l>Of Truth ſhe bathes her ſoring wing</l>
                  <l>On whom do all Ideas ſhine</l>
                  <l>Reflected from the Glaſſe divine.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119704:29"/>
               <head>Gray Haires.</head>
               <l>WElcome gray haires, whoſe light I gladly truſt</l>
               <l>To guide me to my peacefull bed of duſt:</l>
               <l>My lifes bright Stars, whoſe wakefull eyes ſhut mine;</l>
               <l>Stand on my head as Tapers on my ſhrine,</l>
               <l>The worlds grand noiſe of nothing (which invades</l>
               <l>My ſoule) exclude from deaths approaching ſhades;</l>
               <l>But as the day is usher'd in by one</l>
               <l>And the ſame Star that ſhewes the day is done,</l>
               <l>This twilight of my head, this doubtfull ſphear,</l>
               <l>My Bodys Evening, my ſoules Morning Star,</l>
               <l>Th' allay of white amongſt the browner haires</l>
               <l>As well the birth as death of day declares;</l>
               <l>As he whom from the Hill ſaw the moiſt Tomb,</l>
               <l>Of earth, together with her pregnant womb,</l>
               <l>This mingled colour with ambiguous ſtrife</l>
               <l>Demonſtrates my decaying into life.</l>
               <l>Thus life and death compound the world; Each weed</l>
               <l>That fades revives by ſowing its own ſeed:</l>
               <l>Matter ſuppos'd the whole Creation</l>
               <l>Is nothing but form and privation:</l>
               <l>No borrow'd treſſes then no cheating dy</l>
               <l>Shall to falſe life my dying locks bely;</l>
               <l>I ſhall a perfect Microcoſme grow</l>
               <l>When as the Alpes, I crowned am with ſnow.</l>
               <l>I will beleive this white the milky way</l>
               <l>Which leads unto the Court of endleſſe day.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:119704:30"/>
Then let my life's flame ſo intenſely burn</l>
               <l>That all my haires may into aſhes turn,</l>
               <l>Whence may ariſe a <hi>Phoenix</hi> to repay</l>
               <l>With Hallelujahs this Eygnean lay.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:119704:30"/>
               <head>A Dialogue upon
death.</head>
               <stage>Phillis. Damon.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>DAmon</hi> amidſt the bliſſes we</l>
                  <l>In joynt affections fully prove,</l>
                  <l>Doth it not ſometimes trouble thee,</l>
                  <l>To think that death muſt part our love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dam:</speaker>
                  <l>Though ſweets concentrate in thy armes,</l>
                  <l>And that alone I revell there,</l>
                  <l>A willing priſoner to thoſe charmes,</l>
                  <l>Love cannot teach me death to fear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil:</speaker>
                  <l>Say of theſe ſweets I ſhould beguile</l>
                  <l>Thy taſt by my inconſtancie,</l>
                  <l>And on thy rivall <hi>Thyrſis</hi> ſmile,</l>
                  <l>Would not that loſſe work grief in thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:119704:31"/>
                  <speaker>Dam:</speaker>
                  <l>Oh nothing more; For here to be</l>
                  <l>Is Hell and thy embraces lack;</l>
                  <l>Yet is it Heaven even without thee</l>
                  <l>To dye; Then onely art thou black.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil:</speaker>
                  <l>Then onely art thou black my dear;</l>
                  <l>When death ſhall blaſt thy vitall light;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt I in lifes bright day appear,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſleepſt forgot in deaths ſad Night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dam:</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art thick-ſighted; couldſt thou ſee</l>
                  <l>Farre off, the other ſide of death</l>
                  <l>Would ſuch a proſpect open thee</l>
                  <l>As thou muſt needs be ſick of breath.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil:</speaker>
                  <l>How can that be, when ſenſe doth keep</l>
                  <l>The dore of pleaſure? That deſtroyed,</l>
                  <l>The ſoule if it ſurvive, muſt ſleep,</l>
                  <l>Senſeleſſe of delectation voyd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:119704:31"/>
                  <speaker>Dam</speaker>
                  <l>Senſe is the doore of ſuch delight</l>
                  <l>As beaſts receive; through which alas</l>
                  <l>(Since Nature's nothing but a fight,)</l>
                  <l>More enemies then friends do paſſe:</l>
                  <l>Nor is the ſoule leſſe capable,</l>
                  <l>But naked doth her object prove</l>
                  <l>More truely; as more ſenſible</l>
                  <l>Is this fair hand ſtript of its glove.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil:</speaker>
                  <l>My <hi>Damon</hi> ſure hath ſufeirted</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Phillis,</hi> and would fain get hence;</l>
                  <l>Yet mannerly he vailes his dead</l>
                  <l>Love under a divine pretence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dam:</speaker>
                  <l>Whilſt I am fleſh thou needſt not fear</l>
                  <l>Of love in my warm breath a dearth;</l>
                  <l>For ſince affections earthly are</l>
                  <l>They muſt love thee the faireſt Earth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil:</speaker>
                  <l>If thou receive a certain good</l>
                  <l>Of pleaſure in enjoying me,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:119704:32"/>
'Tis wiſedome then to period</l>
                  <l>Thy wiſhes in a certainty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dam:</speaker>
                  <l>Joyes reap'd on earth like graſped aire</l>
                  <l>Away even in enjoyment fly;</l>
                  <l>Certain are onely ſuch as bear</l>
                  <l>The ſtampt of immortality.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil:</speaker>
                  <l>Shall we for hope of future bliſſe</l>
                  <l>The good of preſent Love neglect?</l>
                  <l>Who will a Wren poſſeſt diſmiſſe,</l>
                  <l>A flying Eagle to expect?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dam:</speaker>
                  <l>Who uſe not here the Heavenly way,</l>
                  <l>And in deſire of thither go,</l>
                  <l>Will at their death uncertain ſtray</l>
                  <l>Loſing themſelves in endleſſe wo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil:</speaker>
                  <l>Since death ſuch hazards wait upon</l>
                  <l>Ile unfrequent love's vain delight,</l>
                  <l>And wing my contemplation</l>
                  <l>For prea-equaintance with that height.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:119704:32"/>
                  <speaker>Dam:</speaker>
                  <l>Come then, let's feed our flocks above</l>
                  <l>On Sions hill; ſo will delights</l>
                  <l>Grow freſher in the vale of Love:</l>
                  <l>Change thus may whet chafte appetites.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:119704:33"/>
               <head>Death.</head>
               <l>SUnk eyes, cold lips, chaps faln, cheeks pale and wan</l>
               <l>Are onely bugbeares falſely frighting man;</l>
               <l>This is the vizard, not deaths proper face,</l>
               <l>For who looks through it with the eye of Grace</l>
               <l>Shall find death deckt in ſo divine a ray</l>
               <l>That none would be ſuch a ſelf-foe to ſtay</l>
               <l>In mortall Clouds, did not the wiſer hand</l>
               <l>Of ſupreme power joyn with his ſtrict command,</l>
               <l>Pangs in our diſſolution, which all ſhun,</l>
               <l>But would wiſh, if they knew life then begun.</l>
               <l>Man is a Creature mixt of Heaven and Earth;</l>
               <l>Of beaſt and Angell; when he leaves this breath</l>
               <l>He is all Angell; The Soules future eye</l>
               <l>Is by the proſpect of Etern<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty</l>
               <l>Determin'd onely; who content doth reſt</l>
               <l>With preſent good no better is then Beaſt.</l>
               <l>The heathens prov'd ſince the ſoule cannot find</l>
               <l>In Natures ſtore to ſatisfie the mind,</l>
               <l>Her eſſence Supernat'rall, and ſhall have</l>
               <l>Her trueſt object not before the Grave.</l>
               <l>Could I ſurmiſe the Immateriall mate</l>
               <l>Of this dull fleſh ſhould languiſh after fate</l>
               <l>Like widdowed Turtles; or the glimmering light</l>
               <l>Bereav'd of her dark lanthorn ſhould be quite</l>
               <l>Blown out by death; or dwell on faithleſſe mire,</l>
               <l>Inhopitable fens, like fooliſh fire</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:119704:33"/>
Wandring through diſmal vales of horrid night</l>
               <l>Th' approach of death deſervedly might fright.</l>
               <l>But faiths clear eye more certainely ſurveyes</l>
               <l>Then any optick Organ, for the rayes</l>
               <l>That ſhew her object to us are divine</l>
               <l>Reflected by Th' omniſcient Chriſtalline.</l>
               <l>They then who ſurely know death leade<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h right</l>
               <l>To a vaſt Sea of raviſhing delight</l>
               <l>Cannot, when he knocks at their earthen Gate,</l>
               <l>Suffer him ſtorm his entrance, but dilate</l>
               <l>Their ready hearts as to a friend, for now</l>
               <l>He beares no ſting, no horror in his brow;</l>
               <l>The Chriſtiall-Ruby ſtreame which did purſue</l>
               <l>The ſpear that ſluc't Chriſts ſide dyde his grim hue</l>
               <l>To white and red, beautys complection:</l>
               <l>He comes no more to ſpoile thy manſion,</l>
               <l>But to afford thee that Inheritance</l>
               <l>Which cannot be conceiv'd without a Trance;</l>
               <l>To be tranſlated to the fellowſhip</l>
               <l>Of Angells, there with an immortall lip</l>
               <l>To drink Nectarean bowles of endleſſe good,</l>
               <l>Where the Creators face is the Soules food.</l>
               <l>The beſt condition here is but to be</l>
               <l>An elect ſpouſe to that great deitie,</l>
               <l>But death the Bride-maid leads us to the bed</l>
               <l>Where youth and pleaſures are eterniſed:</l>
               <l>When I conſider the whole world obeys</l>
               <l>Creations law, onely untame man ſtrayes,</l>
               <l>I cannot think this is his proper ſphear</l>
               <l>Where all his actions move irregular</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall my wiſhes ever ſo exclude</l>
               <l>The decent orderly viciſſitude</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:119704:34"/>
Of Natures conſtant Harmony, to pray</l>
               <l>For a harſh jarring by unruly ſtay.</l>
               <l>Theſe with the p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ines and ſhame of doting age</l>
               <l>Wit cauſe the mind betimes to loath her Cage.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119704:34"/>
               <head>On the death of my dear brother
Mr. H. S. drown'd.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Tomb.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHy weeps this Marble? can his frigid power</l>
                  <l>Thicken the ambient air into a ſhower?</l>
                  <l>Ah no; theſe teares have ſure an other cauſe</l>
                  <l>Then the neceſſity of Natures Lawes;</l>
                  <l>Theſe teares their ſpring have from within; there lies</l>
                  <l>The ſpoile of Nature, crime of deſtinies:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How well this ſilent ſadneſſe doth become</l>
                  <l>His awfull ſhade; the horrour of the Tomb</l>
                  <l>Strikes paleneſſe through my ſoule; yet I muſt on</l>
                  <l>And pay the rights of my devotion.</l>
                  <l>Pardon you guardian Angells (who attend</l>
                  <l>And keep his bones ſafe from the ſtygian fiend)</l>
                  <l>That I diſturb your watch with untun'd layes</l>
                  <l>I come to mourne and not to ſing, his praiſe.</l>
                  <l>A Sun that ſat in flouds, but, oh ſad haſt,</l>
                  <l>Ere the Meridian of his age was paſt,</l>
                  <l>A purer day the <hi>Eaſt</hi> did nere diſcloſe;</l>
                  <l>Then in his clear affections orient roſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:119704:35"/>
Tempeſtuous paſſion did in him appear</l>
                  <l>But Phyſick, as the lightnings purge the aire:</l>
                  <l>Martiall his temper was, yet overcame</l>
                  <l>Others by ſmiles, himſelfe by force did tame;</l>
                  <l>Here lies the beſt of man: nature with thee</l>
                  <l>Loſt her perfection and integritie.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:119704:35"/>
               <head>On the ſame.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Boaſt.</head>
               <l>HOW well this brittle Boat doth perſonate</l>
               <l>Mans fraile eſtate?</l>
               <l>Whoſe concave fill'd with lightſome aire did ſcorn</l>
               <l>The proudeſt ſtorm:</l>
               <l>Mans fleſhy boat beares up, whilſt breath doth laſt</l>
               <l>He feares no blaſt:</l>
               <l>Poor floating Bark, whilſt on yon mount you ſtood</l>
               <l>Rain was your food.</l>
               <l>Now the ſame moiſture which once made thee grow</l>
               <l>Doth thee oreflow.</l>
               <l>Raſh youth hath too much ſaile, his giddy path</l>
               <l>No ballaſt hath;</l>
               <l>He thinks his Keel of wit can cut all waves,</l>
               <l>And paſſe thoſe Graves,</l>
               <l>Can ſhoot all Cataracts and ſafely ſteer</l>
               <l>The fourſcorth year.</l>
               <l>But ſtoop thine eare ill-councelld youth, and hark,</l>
               <l>Look on this Bark,</l>
               <l>His Emblem whom it carried, both defi'd</l>
               <l>Stormes, yet ſoon dyed;</l>
               <l>Onely this difference, that ſunk downward, this</l>
               <l>Waighd up to bl<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:119704:36"/>
               <head>On the ſame.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Tempers.</head>
               <l>THe Elements that do mans houſe compoſe</l>
               <l>Are all his chiefeſt foes;</l>
               <l>Fire, Aire, Earth, Water, all are at debate,</l>
               <l>Which ſhall predominate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Sometimes the Tyrant fire in feavours raves,</l>
               <l>And brings us to our graves,</l>
               <l>Sometimes the Aire in whirling of our braines</l>
               <l>And windy Colicks raignes;</l>
               <l>Now Earth with melancoly man invades,</l>
               <l>Making us walking ſhades;</l>
               <l>Now water in ſalt Rheumes works our decay</l>
               <l>And dropſeys quench our day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>But this war equall was in him; the fight:</l>
               <l>Harmony and delight,</l>
               <l>Till Treacherous <hi>Thames</hi> taking the waters part</l>
               <l>Surpriz'd his open heart.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:119704:36"/>
               <head>To my dear Sister Mrs. S.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Chamber.</head>
               <l>ENtring your doore Iſtarted back, ſure this</l>
               <l>(Said I) deaths ſhady houſe and houſehold is,</l>
               <l>And yonder ſhines a beauty (as of old</l>
               <l>Magnificent Tombs eternall Lamps did hold,</l>
               <l>In lieu of lifes light) a fair Taper hid</l>
               <l>In a dark lanthorn; an eye ſhut in's lid;</l>
               <l>A flower in ſhade; a ſtar in nights dark womb;</l>
               <l>An alablaſter Columne to a Tomb.</l>
               <l>But why this night in day can thy fair eye</l>
               <l>Delight in ſuch an Aethiops company?</l>
               <l>Man hath too many naturall clouds; his bloud</l>
               <l>And fleſh ſo blind his hood wink'd ſoule that good</l>
               <l>Is ſcarce diſcern'd from bad; why ſhould we then</l>
               <l>Seek out an artificiall darkeſome den?</l>
               <l>The better part of nature hidden lies;</l>
               <l>The ſtars indeed we may behold, and Skies,</l>
               <l>But not their Influence; we ſee the fire</l>
               <l>But not then heat; why then ſhould we deſire</l>
               <l>More night, when darkneſſe ſo ore Nature lies</l>
               <l>That all things mask their better qualities:</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:119704:37"/>
               <head>To the ſame.</head>
               <head type="sub">Thurſday:</head>
               <l>NOw Ime reſolv'd the craſy Univerſe</l>
               <l>Growes old, the Sun himſelfe is nigh his hearſe;</l>
               <l>Seven Daughters in one week his youthfull rayes</l>
               <l>Were wont to get; but ſince his ſtrength decays</l>
               <l>Six are the moſt: Thurſday is loſt; for we</l>
               <l>Who boaſt our ſelves ſkill'd in th' Aſtronomy</l>
               <l>Of your day-ſhedding eyes, by that light ſwear</l>
               <l>That day is loſt in which you not appear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>That thy dark phancy might a giant-woe</l>
               <l>Beget, thou makſt a night <hi>Herculean</hi> too;</l>
               <l>The late Aſtronomers have found it true,</l>
               <l>We have loſt many dayes, but 'tis by you</l>
               <l>Our calculation erres; and we ſhall rage</l>
               <l>If you go on to cheat us of our age;</l>
               <l>One day in Seaven is loſt; and in threeſcore</l>
               <l>We are bereaved of nine yeares, and more:</l>
               <l>So will your grief dilate it ſelfe like day,</l>
               <l>And all as you, become untimely gray.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:119704:37"/>
               <head>To the ſame.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Roſe.</head>
               <l>AFter the honey drops of pearly ſhowers</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> walk'd to gather flowers:</l>
               <l>Sweet Roſe (I heard her ſay) why are theſe feares?</l>
               <l>Are theſe drops on thy cheek thy teares?</l>
               <l>By thoſe thy beauty freſher is, thy ſmell</l>
               <l>Arabian ſpices doth excell.</l>
               <l>This rain (the Roſe replied) feeds and betrays</l>
               <l>My odours; adds and cuts off dayes:</l>
               <l>Had not I ſpread my leaves to catch this dew</l>
               <l>My ſcent had not invited you,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> ſigh'd and ſoftly ſaid, 'tis ſo,</l>
               <l>Showers blow the roſe and ripen woe:</l>
               <l>For mine (a laſſe) when waſht in flouds ſweet clean,</l>
               <l>Heaven put his hand forth and did glean.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:119704:38"/>
               <head>To the ſame.</head>
               <head type="sub">Mans Life.</head>
               <l>MAn's life was once a ſpan; now one of thoſe</l>
               <l>Atoms of which old Sophies did compoſe</l>
               <l>The world; a thing ſo ſmall, no emptineſſe</l>
               <l>Nature can find at all by his deceaſe;</l>
               <l>Nor need ſhe to attenuate the aire,</l>
               <l>And ſpreading it, his vacancy repaire,</l>
               <l>The ſwellings that in hearts and eyes ariſe</l>
               <l>Repay with ample bulk deaths robberies.</l>
               <l>Why ſhould we then weep for a thing ſo ſlight</l>
               <l>Converting lifes ſhort day to a long night?</l>
               <l>For ſorrowes make one Moneth ſeem many yeares,</l>
               <l>Times multiplying glaſſe is made of teares.</l>
               <l>Our life is but a painted perſpective;</l>
               <l>Greif the falſe light that doth the diſtance give;</l>
               <l>Nor doth it with delight (as ſhaddowing)</l>
               <l>Set off, but as a ſtaffe fixt in a ſpring</l>
               <l>Seem crookt and larger; then dry up thy teares,</l>
               <l>Since through a double mean nought right appeares.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:119704:38"/>
               <head>To the ſame.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Excuſe.</head>
               <l>NOr can your ſexes eaſineſſe excuſe</l>
               <l>Or countenance your teares to be profuſe.</l>
               <l>Some ſhe's there are, whoſe breath is onely ſighes:</l>
               <l>Who weep their own, in others obſequies:</l>
               <l>But in the reaſon, like the Sun at noon,</l>
               <l>Diſpells uſurping clouds of Paſſion;</l>
               <l>Where feminine defects are wanting, there</l>
               <l>All Femininee xcuſes wanting are;</l>
               <l>Think not, ſince vertue then above them reares<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>A womans name can priviledge thy teares:</l>
               <l>Fortune materiall things onely controwles</l>
               <l>But doth her ſelfe pay homage unto ſoules:</l>
               <l>There hath no power, can do no injurie,</l>
               <l>The Pavement where the ſtars their dances form</l>
               <l>By their own Muſick, is above all ſtorme:</l>
               <l>For Meteors but imperfect mixtures are</l>
               <l>In the raw boſome of diſtemperd aire:</l>
               <l>Then let thy ſoule ſhine in her Chriſtall ſpheare,</l>
               <l>They're Comets in the troubled air appear.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:119704:39"/>
               <head>To the ſame.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Reaſons.</head>
               <l>IS it becauſe he died, or that his yeares</l>
               <l>Not many were, that cauſeth all theſe teares?</l>
               <l>If for the firſt, you ſhould have alwayes wept,</l>
               <l>Even in his life from firſt acquaintance kept</l>
               <l>Sorrow awake, for that you know his Fate</l>
               <l>Prefixed had a neceſſary date;</l>
               <l>How unadviſedly do you lament</l>
               <l>Becauſe things mortall are not permanent?</l>
               <l>Or is 't becauſe he ere his aged Snow,</l>
               <l>Or Autume came, was raviſhd from the bough?</l>
               <l>Ask but the ſacred Oracle, you there</l>
               <l>Shall find, untimely deaths no windfall are.</l>
               <l>The grand example, Miracle of good,</l>
               <l>(In vertue onely old) ſlain in the bud</l>
               <l>Newly diſcloſing man. It were a ſhame</l>
               <l>To wiſh then that of his, a longer flame.</l>
               <l>Who would not dy before ſubdued by age?</l>
               <l>That Conqueſt oft Fortune purſues with rage;</l>
               <l>Or ſin in that advantage wounds him worſe:</l>
               <l>To wiſh him long life then, had been a curſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:119704:39"/>
               <head>To the ſame.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Teares.</head>
               <l>YOu moderne wits who call this world a ſtar,</l>
               <l>Who ſay, the other planets too worlds are,</l>
               <l>And that the ſpots that in the midſtar found</l>
               <l>Are to the people there Ilands and ground;</l>
               <l>And that the water which ſurrounds the Earth</l>
               <l>Reflects to each, and gives their ſhining birth;</l>
               <l>The brightneſſe of theſe teares had you but ſeen</l>
               <l>Faln from her eyes, no argument had been</l>
               <l>To contradict that water here diſplayes</l>
               <l>To them as they to us ſiderious rayes.</l>
               <l>Her Teares have then the ſtars a better right</l>
               <l>And a more clear propriety to light.</l>
               <l>For ſtars receive their borrowd beames from far,</l>
               <l>Theſe bring their own along with them, and are</l>
               <l>Born in the ſphear of light; Others may blind</l>
               <l>Themſelves with weeping much, becauſe they ſpend</l>
               <l>The brightneſſe of their eyes upon their teares,</l>
               <l>But hers are inexhauſtible; ſhe ſpares</l>
               <l>Beames to her teares as Tapers lend their light</l>
               <l>And ſhould exceſſe of teares rob her of ſight,</l>
               <l>Two of theſe moiſt ſparks might reſtore't: our eyes</l>
               <l>An humour watry chryſtalline compriſe,</l>
               <l>Why may not then two chriſtall drops reſtore</l>
               <l>That ſight a Chriſtall humour gave before.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:119704:40"/>
Love dewes his locks here, woes each drop to fall</l>
               <l>A pupill in his eye and ſight recall:</l>
               <l>And I hope fortune paſſing through this rain</l>
               <l>Will at laſt ſee to recompence her pain.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:119704:40"/>
               <head>On the death of my much honourd
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle Mr. G. Sandys.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>PArdon (great Soul) if duty grounded on</l>
                  <l>Bloud and affections firm devotion</l>
                  <l>Force my weak muſe to ſacriledge, and by</l>
                  <l>Short-payment rob thy ſacred memory.</l>
                  <l>To be thy wits Executor, though I</l>
                  <l>No title have, yet a ſmall Legacy</l>
                  <l>Fitting my ſmall reception didſt thou leave,</l>
                  <l>Which from thy learned works I did receive;</l>
                  <l>I ſhould then prove unthankfull to deny</l>
                  <l>Some ſpices to embalm that memory,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Soul and better part thy lines alone</l>
                  <l>Eſtabliſh in Eternity's bright throne:</l>
                  <l>Our humble art the body of thy fame</l>
                  <l>Onely to Memphian mummie tries to frame;</l>
                  <l>Which though a ſwarthy dryneſſe it puts on</l>
                  <l>Is raiſed yet above corruption.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A Tomb of rareſt art, Magnificent</l>
                  <l>As 'ere the <hi>Eaſt</hi> did to thy eyes preſent,</l>
                  <l>Erected by great <hi>Falklands</hi> learned hands</l>
                  <l>To thee alive, in his eloqiums ſtands.</l>
                  <l>Thy body we are onely then t' interre,</l>
                  <l>And to thoſe matchleſſe Epitaphs refer</l>
                  <l>The haſty paſſenger that cannot ſtay</l>
                  <l>To heare thy larger Muſe her worth diſplay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:119704:41"/>
                  <l>Unleſſe unto the Croud about the Hearſe</l>
                  <l>(Thoſe buſy Sons of ſenſe) I ſhall rehearſe</l>
                  <l>What worth in thy material part did dwell,</l>
                  <l>And at the funerall thy Scutcheons ſpell;</l>
                  <l>Declare the extraction of thy noble line,</l>
                  <l>What graces from all parts of thee did ſhine,</l>
                  <l>That age thy ſenſe did not at ſeventy cloud,</l>
                  <l>And thee a youth all then but death allow'd:</l>
                  <l>As for thy Soul, if any do enquire,</l>
                  <l>Tis making Anthems in the heavenly Quire.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:119704:41"/>
               <head>Epitaph on Sir R. D.</head>
               <l>HEre lies the pattern of good men;</l>
               <l>Heaven and Earths lov'd Citizen.</l>
               <l>The Worlds faint wiſhes ſcarſe can reach</l>
               <l>The good he did by action teach:</l>
               <l>So hating ſemblence, that his mind</l>
               <l>Left her deportment ſtill behind,</l>
               <l>That he far better was then ere</l>
               <l>Unto the worlds eye did appeare,</l>
               <l>The poor can witneſſe this, who cry</l>
               <l>Aloud their loſſe, his Charity;</l>
               <l>The ſame and feeble now muſt creep</l>
               <l>To ſhew their crutch is laid aſleep.</l>
               <l>His Houſhold Servants, Tenants, all</l>
               <l>Weep here their Fathers Funeral:</l>
               <l>The war that gorg'd on his Eſtate</l>
               <l>His Table never could abate;</l>
               <l>If ever he unjuſt was known,</l>
               <l>'Twas in receding from his own;</l>
               <l>Exchanging what with trouble he</l>
               <l>Might ſave, to keep tranquilitie.</l>
               <l>His hoſt of vertues ſtruck ſuch feare</l>
               <l>Into his foes, they did not dare</l>
               <l>To lay on his, that penalty</l>
               <l>They did on others Loyalty;</l>
               <l>Which bore with him as high a rate</l>
               <l>As thoſe who bought it with their 'ſtate.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:119704:42"/>
Prudence and Innocence had made</l>
               <l>A league no harm ſhould him invade,</l>
               <l>Peacefull amidſt the wars his life,</l>
               <l>As in the Elementall ſtrife.</l>
               <l>Of bodys that are temperd well</l>
               <l>Harmonious Soules at quiet dwell,</l>
               <l>When the worſt humour had prevaild</l>
               <l>Upon the State, his vita<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls faild<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>To ſhew, this feeling members health</l>
               <l>Was wrapt up in the Common-wealth.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:119704:42"/>
               <head>Grace Compar'd to the Sun.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>GRace as the Sun, inceſſantly its light</l>
                  <l>Dilates upon the Vniverſall face.</l>
                  <l>Pagans that ſit in Antipodian night</l>
                  <l>Taſt, by reflex of reaſon, beames of grace.</l>
                  <l>Their ſickly planet (Queen of night not ſleep)</l>
                  <l>Her wakefull eye in the Suns beames may ſteep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Grace is the Soules Soul; the informing part</l>
                  <l>Reaſon (like <hi>Phoſphere</hi>) uſhers in the day;</l>
                  <l>But the terene affections of the heart</l>
                  <l>Repell which Pharean clouds this ſacred ray.</l>
                  <l>Internall, as externall night alone</l>
                  <l>Springs from the Earths interpoſition.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Goodneſſe is priz'd by her own latitude;</l>
                  <l>The Perſian (wiſeſt of Idolaters)</l>
                  <l>Adores the Sun as the moſt common good,</l>
                  <l>From whoſe balm Natures hand nothing interrs.</l>
                  <l>Worſe then the Caliph is that votary</l>
                  <l>Who worſhips a leſſe loving deity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:119704:43"/>
                  <l>The Sun would raiſe this Globe to nobler birth,</l>
                  <l>Transforming into Gold each minerall;</l>
                  <l>But in diſpoſure of the Stubbourn Earth</l>
                  <l>Renders his vertue ineffectuall?</l>
                  <l>Thus grace endeavours all to ſublimate:</l>
                  <l>Then blame thy ſelfe if not regenerate.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:119704:43"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Nativity of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
and Sacrament then
received.</head>
               <l>SEe from his watry Tropick how the Sun</l>
               <l>Approacheth by a double motion!</l>
               <l>The ſame flight tending to the weſtern ſeas</l>
               <l>Wheeles Northward by inſenſible degrees;</l>
               <l>So this bleſt day beares to our Intellect</l>
               <l>(As its bright fire) a duplycate reſpect:</l>
               <l>None but a two-fac'd <hi>Janus</hi> can be gueſt</l>
               <l>And fit himſelfe unto this double feaſt.</l>
               <l>That muſt before joyntly the Manger ſee,</l>
               <l>And view behind the execrable Tree.</l>
               <l>Here the bleſt Virgins living milk, and there</l>
               <l>The fatall ſtreames of the Sons bloud appear;</l>
               <l>Crowns at his tender feet in <hi>Bethlem</hi> ly;</l>
               <l>Thorns bind his manly browes in <hi>Calvary;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Th' aſhamed Sun from this his light withdrew;</l>
               <l>A new born ſtar the other joy'd to ſhew:</l>
               <l>To furniſh out this feaſt, lo, in the pot</l>
               <l>Death here conſults the ſalting Antidot:</l>
               <l>But leaſt the ſad allay ſhould interfer,</l>
               <l>And corrupt this days ſmile into a tear,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:119704:44"/>
This very death makes up a fuller mirth</l>
               <l>Bequeathing to the worthy Gueſt new birth;</l>
               <l>As to the myſtick head, beſeemingly,</l>
               <l>So to each member gives Nativity:</l>
               <l>The difference onely this, the deitie</l>
               <l>Born to our fleſh, into his Spirit we.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:119704:44"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
