<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from the head-qvarters, at St. Albanes, communicating the proceedings of the generall councell of the Army the weeke past: setting downe such queries by the officers and souldiers, as were presented to the generall and councell. Written to a friend in London, November, 10.</title>
            <author>Johnson, Richard, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E470_34</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205691</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864995</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117228</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A87606)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117228)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E470[34])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from the head-qvarters, at St. Albanes, communicating the proceedings of the generall councell of the Army the weeke past: setting downe such queries by the officers and souldiers, as were presented to the generall and councell. Written to a friend in London, November, 10.</title>
                  <author>Johnson, Richard, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed in the yeare,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>A list following Johnson's letter describes the army's grievances with the proposed peace treaty with King Charles.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Novemb: 14".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Peace --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117228:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117228:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM THE HEAD-QVARTERS, At St. Albanes, Communicating, the Proceedings of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell of the Army the weeke paſt: Setting downe ſuch Queries by the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Souldiers, as were preſented to the Generall and Councell.</p>
            <p>Written to a Friend in London, <hi>November,</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:117228:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117228:2"/>
            <head>A Letter from the Head Quarters.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is fit my ſervice ſhould laſt as long as your commands; and ſince your deſires are but the diſcharge of my ingagements to you, it being my poſitive promiſe to communicate to you the Debates, Reſults, and deſires of the Counſell, and private Souldiery, and Officers of the Army; I heere ſend you what hath beene tranſacted ſince Saturday, which tranſactions are very high, and may doe much good for this Kingdome, if God be but pleaſed <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o owne us in Counſell as he hath owned us in the Field: the Regiments have delivered in their deſires, and ſome Queries to the Counſell, and wee doe dayly expect ſome more from the Liefte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Generalls Army, which wee conceive will be as high as our Armies; the Souldiers are growne to a great diſlike of the Parliament, and much
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117228:3"/>
doubt their owne ſafety under the hands of them, and conceive they have great reaſon, conſidering the mutabillity and unconſtancy of their <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and are ready to ſay, that the Majo<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part of the now ſitting Commons, and the whole Houſe of Peeres are as changeable as the Camelion; vote an affirmative, and as contrary with the ſame breath, which wee believe is very dangerous to both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Army, and much tends to the ruine and deſtruction of both; knowing very well that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabillity and changing is bid to be ware of by the wiſeſt of men; <hi>Medle not with them that are given to change, for their calamities ſhall be great, and who ſhal know the ruines of them?</hi> but you ſhall receive the Queries and deſires heere incloſed, which wee conceive to be both reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and honeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and much tending to the happineſſe of both Kingdome and Army: I am ſomething in haſte, and cannot inlarge my ſelfe at preſent, but in my next you ſhall receive a full account of all the pr<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceedings of the Counſell and Army; from him who is, Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend to ſerve you,
R. Johnſon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Let my ſervice I pray ſalute all our friends in Holburne, Queen-ſtreet, and Savoy.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:117228:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>VVEE ſhou'd, and are worſe be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched then the Galatians, if wee ſhould believe that this Treaty were any thing other then a ſnare to enſlave and ruine, and truely wee cannot but thinke a ſpirit of mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath poſſeſſed the hearts of all thoſe who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this Treaty, or a Treaty with thoſe wee have conquered twice, can any way prove propitious to us, or this Kingdome, there is none ſo blinde as thoſe which doe not ſee ſlavery and bondage coming upon us, and our Poſterity, as travell upon a woman with childe, which wee cannot eſcape if this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty take effect; therefore wee preſent our ſence of it, with all humbleneſſe to this Honourable Counſ<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll in a few Queries, deſiring that they may be ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken into conſideration, as things that are the ſole good, and in which all our happineſſe is wrapt up in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, VVhether an Ordinance made by Parliament in a time (unqueſtionable) of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and liberties, and in a full Houſe upon mature deliberation, and after many dayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117228:4"/>
and after all objections made againſt no Addreſſes to the King, and a full Vote paſſed in the Houſe to governe without Him: Let it be judged whether the ſafety of a Kingdome can be free in the hands of ſuch, when they vote the contrary upon a tumultuous Petition, and treat with, and court our conquered Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
            <p n="2">2. VVhat is an Ordinance of Parliament worth, or will be accounted of by any, if as ſoone as its granted, or upon any Rebellion or Inſurrection, though at a hundred miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance it may be recalled? what a ſlender ground and foundation, nay upon what a broken reed, doe, and will men ſay they have built on all this while, in venturing their lives, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding all that is deare unto them, or in act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Parliament, or by an Ordinance? therefore we cannot thinke our ſelves in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo long as things are thus carried.</p>
            <p>Whether or no in the judgement of any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different men it can ſtand with the honour, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, authority, and gravity of the ſupreame Court of judicature, and the great Counſell of a Kingdome, when upon mature deliberation,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117228:4"/>
and waighty reaſons in the moſt legall way, when noe addreſſes have beene voted in a full Houſe to the King, and now addreſſes made, &amp; he courted as one that hath not had the leaſt finger in all <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat innocent blou<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that hath been ſhed, when he himſelfe hath confeſſed to be the Author of all, and guilty of that bloud that hath been ſpilt in theſe 3 Kingdomes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether the Army can be in ſafety when thoſe their knowne Enemies have the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of this Treaty, and are moſt forward to ſupport that which will ruine us and our poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether the Army can bee in ſafety, when the Counſell of the Citizens are the ſole guide of the Parliaments tranſactions, and the abſolute influence into the Councells of the ſame, and thoſe of the Citizens too, which are our profeſt enemies.</p>
            <p n="5">5. VVhether the Army and Kingdome can be in ſafety, when the deſires and requeſts of the Malignants are ſo frequently granted, and the onely men put in places of truſt.</p>
            <p n="6">6. VVhether the Kingdome and Army can be in ſafety, or we ever expect a bleſſing from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117228:5"/>
heaven, ſo long as the chiefe abetter, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of theſe wars live without puniſhment, and be not brought to juſtice.</p>
            <p n="7">7. VVhether there can bee ſafety for the Kingdome and Army, ſo long as the Kings friends go abroad, and are ſuffred to weare armes, and piſtols, and murder our friends, and are not put to death, and brought to condigne puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now we conceiue that it is the ſence of your Excellency and this Councell, that the Kingdome is in danger, if theſe things be not tak<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious conſideration, and by your wiſedome and care prevented: &amp; we preſent unto you our humbledeſire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that thoſe which have beene the princip<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l of the firſt and ſecond war, may be tryed by a Coun<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cil of war, as priſoners at war.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all thoſe of both Houſes, who v<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted with thoſe that would have further addreſſes may bee <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred the Houſe, as well thoſe of the Peeres as th<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of Commons.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That thoſe Citizens which indeavoured the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of an Army, when we were at Colcheſt<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r may be forthwith apprehended, and brought to ex<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mpla<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being they indeavoured to rai<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e without any Authority or Ordinance of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Treaty may not go on any further, but may be ſpeedily broke off, and a courſe taken that no tearmes may be h<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>kened to, or offred to that Party but that ſpeedy juſtice may be done upon Him and His ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:117228:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
