<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Look abovt yov or, A groatsworth of good councel for a peny : being variety of councels, cautions, caveats, and directions : which, as they are necessary for young-men; so they are not to be rejected by old-men.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88521</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.17[76]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R211786</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870485</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870485</idno>
            <idno type="VID">163324</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A88521)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 163324)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 246:669f17[76])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Look abovt yov or, A groatsworth of good councel for a peny : being variety of councels, cautions, caveats, and directions : which, as they are necessary for young-men; so they are not to be rejected by old-men.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G. Horton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "ffebr. 16 1653"; the '4' in the imprint has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Young men --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Maxims --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:163324:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>LOOK ABOVT YOV:
OR,
A Groatſworth of good Councel for a Peny:
BEING
Variety of Councels, Cautions, Caveats, and Directions: Which, as they are neceſſary for Young-men;
ſo they are not to be rejected by Old-men.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>He that refuſeth now to buy good Councel at a cheap rate,</l>
                  <l>Shal not fail to purchaſe Repentance deer either ſoon or late.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <figure>
               <p>V<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="7 letters">
                     <desc>〈7 letters left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap> VVLNERE VERITAS</p>
               <figDesc>depiction of Truth</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>FIrſt, Make not an envious man
a drunkard, a woman, nor a
man in ſubjection to a woman
of thy councel: for it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
for them to keep cloſe thy ſecrets.</p>
            <p>2 Be not over-prodigal in gifts, or
chargable courteſies, for thanks wax
old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſoon as ever gifts are in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>3 Begin no great Enterpriſe before
thou know how to accompliſh it.</p>
            <p>4 Mock no man in his miſery, but
rather by him take heed how to avoid
the like misfortune.</p>
            <p>5 Labour not to inform him that is
without Reaſon, for ſo ſhalt thou not
only loſe thy labor, but alſo make him
thine enemy.</p>
            <p>6 Deſire not that of another, that
thou thy ſelf being asked wouldſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
for therein it is ridiculous.</p>
            <p>7 Attempt not two things at one
time, but accompliſh one firſt, ſo ſhall
not the one hinder the other.</p>
            <p>8 Chuſe rarher to live ſolitary, for it
is better to live alone in the corner of
an houſe top, then in a ſpacious Palace
w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th a brawling and contentious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            <p>9 Let not thy liberality exceed thine
ability, nor thy hand go beyond thy
purſe.</p>
            <p>10 Bewars of pride in proſperity, for
it wil make thee impatient in adverſity</p>
            <p>11 Speak no more to a ſtranger in
private, then thou wouldſt have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely
known.</p>
            <p>12 If thou doubt in any thing, ask
councel of wiſe men, and be not angry
if they reprove thee.</p>
            <p>13 Do to all men as thou wouldeſt
be done unto.</p>
            <p>14 Boaſt not of thy good deeds, leſt
alſo the bad be laid to thy charge:
however do good to all men, although
in doing good to an ill diſpoſed perſon
it happen to thee as to thoſe that feed
other mens Dogs, which bark at their
feeder as well as at any other ſtranger.</p>
            <p>15 If thou giveſt ought give it at the
firſt asking: for that is not freely given
which is craved with importunity.</p>
            <p>16 When thou giveſt a gift to thy
friend, let it be of the beſt: yet be not
like a Boulter, that in bolting the meal
caſteth out the fine flower, and retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
onely the bran.</p>
            <p>17 Be courteous, and ſhew a good
countenance to all: yet enter not into
familiarity with any, but onely ſuch
whoſe Converſations are honeſt, and
whoſe truth by tryal is made truſty.</p>
            <p>18 Inſtruct Youth in good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable
qualities: for as a Veſſel ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth
alwayes of the ſame liquor
wherewith it was firſt ſeaſoned, ſo the
mind doth retain thoſe qualities in age
in which it was trained up in youth.</p>
            <p>19 Be not over profuſe either in gifts
or expences: for it is better to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied
for thy provident ſparing, then pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied
for thy prodigal ſpending.</p>
            <p>20 Beware of Envie, the moſt anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
pride the moſt great: and women
the moſt dangerous <hi>&amp;</hi> exceſs the moſt
foul evil,</p>
            <p>21 Women in their Wils are perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptory,
and in their anſwers ſharp: yet
like Faulcons they wil ſtoop to a gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
lure, and as they are apt to weep, ſo
are rhey to deceive: for thou knoweſt
whether her teares be of ſorrow, or of
diſſimulation, for ſhe can ſhed both:
and indeed womens ſorrows are either
too extream, not to be relieved; or elſe
picled up with diſſimulation, not to be
believed: it is natural for a woman to
deſpiſe the thing that is offered her, and
yet it is death to be denyed the thing
ſhe demands. Womens hearts are ſaid
to be full of holes, apt to receive, but
not to retain: ſo that if love creeps in
at one hole, it ſteps out at 3 or 4. The
Cloſets of womens thoughts are ever
open, and the depth of their hearts hath
a ſtring that ſtretcheth to their tongues.
Women are like to the pictures of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
ſtanding upon a Globe winged
with the feathers of fickleneſs: and as
for little goodneſs they look for great
praiſe; ſo for much evil they look for
no chaſtiſement: and as there ir no
Creature that more deſires honour, ſo
there is no Creature that worſe keepes
it then a woman. And finally, he that
can abide a curſt wife and her conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
need not care what company he
keeps.</p>
            <p>22 Nevertheleſs, if thou be'ſt wed to
a curſe wife, refrain both thy tongue
and hands, and make a Vertue of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,
placing that with patience thou
canſt not remove with eaſe: and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
that it is thou that deferveſt to be
beaten either for making choice of at
all, or at beſt for making thy choice no
better.</p>
            <p>23 Wine and ſtrong Beer are crafty
Wreſtlers, and overthroweth the Wit,
weakneth the feet, and overcometh the
vital Spirits: and therefore it may be
truly ſaid, that Drunkenneſs doth me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphiſe
a man into a beaſt, a ſtrong
man into a weak, and a wiſe man into
a fool: A drunken man like an old
man is twice a child. Drunkenneſs is a
Monſter with many heads; as abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
diſcourſe, fornication, wrath, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
ſwearing, curſing: and Wine is
ſaid to have deſtroyed more men then
the Sea hath drowned: and to ſay no
more, Drunkenneſs is a voluntary
Madneſs.</p>
            <p>24 Pride eateth Gold, and drinketh
blood, and climeth ſo high by other
mens heads, that it often breaks its
own neck: it chanceth often to proud
men, that in their greateſt jollity, and
when they think their Honour to be
ſpun and weaved, that then the Web
of their lives in a moment are cut and
broken. Pride cauſeth that Work to
become wicked, which in it ſelf would
be good: ſo that humble ſubmiſſion is
beter then proud boaſting of our deeds,
which often cauſe a proud man to fall
into more deteſtable vices then before.
A proud heart in a poor man, is like a
great fire in a ſmall Cottage, which
not onely warmeth the houſe, but bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
all that is in it. Advance one of
low eſtate to high degree, and none
alive aan reap more pride then he: and
when ambition and pride is in the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,
then miſchief and ſhame is on the
Crupper.</p>
            <p>25 Envy is the Daughter of Pride,
the Author of Murther and Revenge,
the beginner of ſecret Seditions, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
waits at Vertues Elbow. Envy is
the ſlime and impoſtume of the ſoul, a
perpetual torment to him in whom it
abideth, as wel as to vertuous perſons,
and actions; a venome, a poyſon, or
quick-ſilver, which conſumeth the
fleſh, and dryeth the very marrow of
the bones. An envious man waxeth
lean at the fatneſs of his Neighbor, and
ever accounteth his Neighbors loſſes
his gains, and his Neighbours gains his
loſſes. Envy is ſaid of the Poets to
dwell in a dark Cave, being pale and
lean, looking a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quint, abounding with
gall, her teeth black, never rejoycing
but at other mens harmes ever unquiet
and alwayes careful of doing miſchief.
And in this, one onely point may be
diſtinguiſhed from Hatred: the one is
ſecret: the other open: And in this
alone is the envious mans meat above
others (to him) he continually gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
upon his own heart.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>GEntle Reader, Be pleaſed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
of this as an Introduction to
ſome other things to follow, wherein
he that collected theſe Sentences, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
variety of Councels, Caveats,
Cautions, and Directions, which as
they be hurtful to none, ſo if they may
be uſeful to any, he ſhall thinke his
time and pains well beſtowed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON:
Printed for G. HORTON,
1654.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
