<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short supply or amendment to the propositions for the new representative, for the perpetual peace and quiet of this nation, and other parts (which be or shall be incorporated with the same) in the enjoyment of their just rights and liberties. Which were lately published by Will: Leach of the middle Temple, Gent. And now published at the request of divers well-affected and eminent Christians of the congregated churches of this nation. / Written and proposed by Edmund Leach of New England, Merchant.</title>
            <author>Leach, Edmund, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88848</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L769</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E644_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208742</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867664</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867664</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119985</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A88848)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119985)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 99:E644[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short supply or amendment to the propositions for the new representative, for the perpetual peace and quiet of this nation, and other parts (which be or shall be incorporated with the same) in the enjoyment of their just rights and liberties. Which were lately published by Will: Leach of the middle Temple, Gent. And now published at the request of divers well-affected and eminent Christians of the congregated churches of this nation. / Written and proposed by Edmund Leach of New England, Merchant.</title>
                  <author>Leach, Edmund, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Macock, and are to be sold by Lodowick Lloyd in Popes-head Alley neer Lumbard-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "No: 2d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119985:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT
Supply or Amendment
TO THE
PROPOSITIONS
FOR THE
New Repreſentative,
FOR THE
Perpetual Peace and Quiet of this
Nation, and other parts (which be or ſhall be
incorporated with the ſame) in the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of their juſt Rights and Liberties.</p>
            <p>Which were lately publiſhed by WILL: LEACH
of the middle Temple, Gent.</p>
            <p>AND
Now publiſhed at the requeſt of divers well-affected
and eminent Chriſtians of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregated
Churches of this Nation.</p>
            <p>Written and Propoſed by EDMUND LEACH
of <hi>New England,</hi> Merchant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Macock,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Lodowick
Lloyd</hi> in Popes-head Alley neer <hi>Lumbard-ſtreet.</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:119985:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119985:2"/>
            <head>A
Short Supply or Amendment
TO THE
PROPOSITIONS
FOR THE
New Repreſentative.</head>
            <p>FOr as much as the Members of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
Parliament of England have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone
great danger of their lives and
Eſtates, and many of them taken exceſſive
pains and care, and divers of their Fellow-Members
loſt their lives for the Preſervation
of the honeſt People of this Nation from utter
ruine and deſtruction, and gaining their juſt
Rights and Liberties, and ſetling the People
of this Nation in a Government of a Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique,
for the enjoyment of the ſame for ever,
for the quiet not only of thoſe who may fear,
but which ſhall hope of much more blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119985:3"/>
Combuſtions, or Alterations, but that
all parties may acquieſce in this peaceable Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
in all future times, without doubting,
or expectance of any other by any Monarch
whatſoever; but that all Tyranny ſhall be for
ever hereafter turned and kept out of doors, and
that all parties may praiſe our great God for
this our Miraculous Deliverance from Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
and Oppreſſion, and pray for the proſperity
of thoſe by whom he out of his good will and
pleaſure hath wrought this our great and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
Freedom.</p>
            <p>And for that, upon or by a New Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,
if the moſt juſt Members (which have
brought to paſs this moſt peaceable Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
which is moſt eaſie to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued,
for the keeping of the People from
Tyranny &amp; Oppreſſion) ſhould be neglected,
(though ſome of the Plebeans may think amiſs
of divers of them for concealing ſeveral things
from them, which they have thought to be for
their weal, the ſudden revealing of which
might have been to their woe) danger might
happen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119985:3"/>
            <head>For Remedy in this behalf, theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions
following be propoſed and
tendered, to the ſame Conſideration
and intent as the ſaid recited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions
are.</head>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>THat every Member of this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
now ſitting or acting for the
benefit and ſupport of this Common-wealth
of England (other then ſuch who by this
preſent Parliament ſhall not be thought fit to
continue without a new Election) may ſit, vote
and act for and in the next Parliament or
Repreſentative.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>And that (for every County, City, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,
Town Corporate, or other place, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,
or which ſhall have, Power or Authority
of electing Members of Parliament or Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters,
and no Member or Repreſenter being
now ſo ſitting, or in action for the ſame)
this now preſent Parliament may ſend to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119985:4"/>
Sheriffs, Bayliffs, Barons, or other head Officers
of the ſame reſpectively, the names of four
perſons for every ſuch place which have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
ſo to elect or chooſe two ſuch Members or
Repreſenters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>And that every ſuch Sheriff and Officer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
mentioned reſpectively ſhall or may pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
the ſame openly in his County, or other
ſuch place, whereof ſuch reſpective Sheriff, or
other ſuch Officer, be or ſhall be chief head
officer or officers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposition">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>And that the Inhabitants of every ſuch
County, City, Burrough, or other place before
mentioned, ſhall or may ſo write or print one
of ſuch four for one, and that he with another
of ſuch Member or Repreſenter as ſuch Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants
ſhall in like manner chooſe, write or
print, as is mentioned in the Propoſitions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
recited, ſhall and may be Members of the
next Parliament or Repreſentative.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="proposition">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>And that ſome of the chief Commanders
of this preſent Army of this Nation may no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119985:4"/>
eight ſuch perſons by the Parliament,
ſo to be ſent, out of which the ſame may ſo
ſend the names of the before mentioned four
perſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="proposition">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>And that according to the ſame number and
proportion for every reſpective County, City,
or other place before mentioned (which have
or ſhall have power or authority to elect or
chooſe more or leſs for ſuch Members or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenters)
the ſame courſe may be taken, as
before is mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="proposition">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>And that in all Parliaments or Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives
hereafter, the fourth or fifth part, or ſome
other number by this Parliament to be thought
convenient, ſhall and may remain and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
as Members or Repreſenters for the then
next Parliament or Repreſentative, unleſs they
be or ſhall be voted out by any Parliament or
Repreſentative ſitting, or to be ſitting, and that
then the Inhabitants of ſuch place for which
they were or ſhall be choſen, may (as is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
in the ſaid recited Propoſals) new elect
and chooſe, and ſend in ſuch manner and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119985:5"/>
form as is mentioned in thoſe Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>In the Propoſitions before recited, in pag. 6.
l. 9. is the word [<hi>after</hi>] where the word [<hi>before</hi>]
ſhould be; and in pag 10. li. 30. is omitted
the word [<hi>not,</hi>] and in pag. 13. li. 14. is alſo
omitted the word [<hi>be,</hi>] and divers other litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
faults, which is eaſily imagined what they
ſhould be; all which are the neglect of the
Printer, and therefore its not neceſſary to write
further againſt or concerning the ſame.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Edmund Leach.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Theſe preſent <hi>Propoſals</hi> are to be ſold by <hi>Lodowick Lloyd,</hi> and
the before-recited <hi>Propoſals</hi> by him, <hi>William Lee, Lawrence
Blaiklock,</hi> and <hi>Gabriel Bedel</hi> in Fleet-ſtreet, and <hi>Lawrence
Chapman</hi> near the Savoy.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
