<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The humble answer of the Divines attending the Honorable Commissioners of Parliament, at the treaty at Newport in the Isle of Wight. To the second paper delivered to them by his Majesty, Octob. 6. 1648. about episcopall government. Delivered to his Majesty, October 17. I appoint Abel Roper to print this copie, entituled The humble answer of the Divines, &amp;c. Richard Vines,</title>
            <author>Westminster Assembly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M757</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E468_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204007</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863746</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863746</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115960</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A89568)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115960)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E468[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The humble answer of the Divines attending the Honorable Commissioners of Parliament, at the treaty at Newport in the Isle of Wight. To the second paper delivered to them by his Majesty, Octob. 6. 1648. about episcopall government. Delivered to his Majesty, October 17. I appoint Abel Roper to print this copie, entituled The humble answer of the Divines, &amp;c. Richard Vines,</title>
                  <author>Westminster Assembly</author>
                  <author>Marshall, Stephen, 1594?-1655, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Abel Roper, at the signe of the Sunne over against S. Dunstans Church in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Stephen Marshall, who was one of the Newport divines.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] ye 20th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Puritan Revolution, 1642-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115960:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115960:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Humble ANSWER Of the DIVINES Attending the Honorable <hi>COMMISSIONERS</hi> OF Parliament, At the TREATY at <hi>Newport</hi> in the Iſle of WIGHT.
To the ſecond Paper delivered to them by his MAJESTY, <hi>Octob.</hi> 6. 1648.
About <hi>Epiſcopall Government.</hi>
Delivered to his Majeſty, <hi>October</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>I appoint <hi>Abel Roper</hi> to Print this Copie, entituled <hi>The Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Anſwer of the Divines,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Richard Vines,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Abel Roper,</hi> at the Signe of the Sunne over againſt S. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in Fleet-ſtreet. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:115960:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115960:2"/>
            <head>The humble ANSWER of the <hi>Divines</hi> attending the Honorable <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners</hi> of PARLIAMENT at the <hi>Treaty</hi> at <hi>Newport</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> To the ſecond Paper delivered to them by his MAIESTY, <hi>Octob.</hi> 6. 1648.
Delivered to his MAIESTY, <hi>Octob.</hi> 17.</head>
            <opener>May it pleaſe your Majeſtly,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in our Paper of <hi>October</hi> the third, in Anſwer to your Majeſties of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> the ſecond We did, ſo now againe we do acknowledge, that the Scriptures cited in the Margin of your Majeſties Paper do prove, that the Apoſtles in their own perſons; That <hi>Timothy,</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> and the Angels of the Churches, had power re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, to do thoſe things, which are in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture ſpecified; But as then, ſo now alſo we humbly do deny, that any of the perſons or Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers fore-mentioned were Biſhops, as diſtrict from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115960:3"/>
Presbyters, or did exerciſe Epiſcopall Government in that ſence; Or that this was in the leaſt meaſure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the alleadged Scriptures, and therefore our <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative</hi> not being to the ſame point, or ſtate of the Queſtion which was <hi>affirmed;</hi> We humby conceive that we ſhould not be interpreted, to have in effect, denyed the very ſame thing, which we had before granted, or to have acknowledged that the ſeverall Scriptures do prove the thing, for which they are ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by your Majeſty; And, if that, which we grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed were all, that, by the Scriptures cited in your Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, your Majeſty intended to prove; It will follow, That nothing hath yet beene proved on your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties part, to make up that concluſion which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
            <p>As then we ſtood upon the Negative to that aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo we now crave leave to repreſent to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that your reply doth not infirme the Evidence given in maintenance thereof. The Reaſon given by your Majeſty in this Paper, to ſupport your aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: That the perſons that exerciſed the power afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid were Biſhops in diſtinct ſence, is taken from a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Epiſcopall Government; <q>which is (as your Majeſty ſaith) nothing elſe, but the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Churches within a certaine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct (commonly called a Dioceſſe) committed to one ſingle perſon, with ſufficient authority over the Presbyters, and people of thoſe Churches for that end; which Government ſo deſcribed, being for ſubſtance of the thing it ſelfe in all the three forementioned particulars, (Ordaining, giving rules of Diſcipline, and Cenſures) found in Scriptures,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115960:3"/>
except we will contend about names &amp; words, muſt be acknowledged in the ſenſe aforeſaid to be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proved from Scriptures: and your Majeſty ſaith further, that the Biſhops do not challeng more, or other power to belong to them, in reſpect of their Epiſcopal office, as it is diſtinct from that of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, then what properly fals under one of thoſe three.</q>
            </p>
            <p>We deſire to ſpeak both to the Biſhops <hi>challenge,</hi> and to your Majeſties <hi>deſcription</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopal govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And firſt to their Challenge; becauſe it is firſt expreſt in your Majeſties reply.</p>
            <p>The Challenge we undertake in two reſpects: 1. In reſpect of the <hi>Power</hi> challenged, 2. In reſpect of that ground, or <hi>Tenure</hi> upon which the claim is laid. The Power challenged conſiſts of three particulars; <hi>Ordaining, giving Rules</hi> of Diſcipline, and <hi>Cenſures.</hi> No more, no other, in reſpect of their Epiſcopal office. We ſee not, by what warrant this Writ of partition is taken forth, by which the Apoſtolical office is thus ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed or divided; The <hi>Governing</hi> part into the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops hands; the <hi>Teaching,</hi> and <hi>adminiſtring</hi> Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, into the Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>byters. For beſides that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture makes no ſuch incloſure, or partition wall; it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, the challenge is grown to more then was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended unto in the times of growne Epiſcopacie. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> do both acknowledge for their time, that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> and Presbyter differed only in the matter of Ordination: and learned Doctor <hi>Bilſon</hi> makes ſome abatement in the claim of <hi>three,</hi> ſaying, the things proper to Biſhops, which might not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to Presbyters, are ſingularly of Succeeding, and ſuperiority in Ordaining.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115960:4"/>
The <hi>tenure</hi> or ground upon which the claim is made is Apoſtolical, which with us is all one with <hi>Divine Inſtitution.</hi> And this, as far as we have learned, hath not been <hi>anciently, openly,</hi> or <hi>generally</hi> avowed in this Church of <hi>England,</hi> either in time of Popery, or of the firſt Reformation; and whenſoever the pretenſion hath been made, it was not without the contradiction of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and godly men. The abettors of the challenge, that they might reſolve it at laſt into the Scripture, did chuſe the moſt plauſible way of aſcending by the ſcale of <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion;</hi> going up the River to find the Head: but when they came to Scriptures, &amp; found it like the head of <hi>Nile</hi> (which cannot be found) they ſhrowded it under the name and countenance of the <hi>Angels of the Churches,</hi> and of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus.</hi> Thoſe that would carry it higher, endeavoured to impe it into the <hi>Apoſtolical office,</hi> and ſo at laſt called it a <hi>Divine Inſtitution,</hi> not in force of any <hi>expreſſe precept,</hi> but <hi>implicite practiſe</hi> of the Apoſtles; and ſo the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> office (except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the gifts, or enablements confeſt only extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary) is brought down to be <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> and the <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal</hi> raiſed up to be <hi>Apoſtolical.</hi> Whereupon it follows, that the <hi>higheſt</hi> Officers in the Church are put into a <hi>lower</hi> orb; an <hi>extraordinary</hi> office turn'd into an <hi>ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſtinct</hi> office, confounded with that which in the Scripture is <hi>not found;</hi> a <hi>temporary,</hi> and an <hi>extinct</hi> office revived. And indeed if the definitions of both be rightly made, they are ſo <hi>incompatible</hi> to the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that he that will take both muſt loſe the one: <hi>aut Apoſtolus Epiſcopatum, aut Apoſtolatum Epiſcopus.</hi> For the Apoſtles, though they did not in many things <hi>ut aliud,</hi> yet they acted <hi>alio nomine &amp; alio munere,</hi> then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115960:4"/>
Presbyters, or Biſhops can do: and if they were indeed Biſhops, and their government properly Epiſcopal in diſtinct ſenſe, then it is not needfull to go ſo far about to prove Epiſcopal government of Divine inſtitution, becauſe they practiſed it; but to aſſert expreſſely, that Chriſt inſtituted it immediately in them.</p>
            <p>For your Majeſties <hi>definition</hi> of Epiſcopal govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is extracted out of the Biſhops of later date, then Scripture times, and doth not ſute to that Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, under which there were more Biſhops then one in a Precinct, or Church; and it is as fully competent to Archiepiſcopal, and Patriarchal government, as Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal. The parts of this definition, <hi>materially,</hi> and <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractly</hi> conſidered, may be found in Scripture. The Apoſtles, <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> were ſingle perſons, but not limited to a Precinct: The government of the <hi>Angels</hi> was limited to a Precinct, but not in ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. In ſeveral offices, not to be confounded, the parts of this definition may be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound; but the aggregation of them altogether into one ordinary Officer cannot be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound. And if that word, <hi>ordinary, and ſtanding Government,</hi> had been made the <hi>genus</hi> in your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties definition (as it ought to be) We ſhould crave leave to ſay it would be <hi>gratis dictum,</hi> if not <hi>petitio principii:</hi> for the Scripture doth not put all theſe parts together in a Biſhop, who never borrowed of <hi>Apoſtles, Evangeliſts</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> the matter of Governing and Ordaining, and left the other of Teaching, diſpenſing Sacraments and dealing onely <hi>in foro interno,</hi> to Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, untill after times. By this that hath been ſaid, it is manifeſt enough, that we contend not <hi>firſt de nomine:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the name of Epiſcopall Government: which yet
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115960:5"/>
(though <hi>names</hi> ſerve for <hi>diſtinction)</hi> is not called or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by that name in Scripture. Nor <hi>ſecondly de opere</hi> about the worke, whether the worke of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ordering, preaching &amp;c. be of continuance in the Church, Which we cleerely acknowledge; But <hi>third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly de munere,</hi> about the Office, it being a greatfallacy to argue, That the Apoſtles did the ſame work which Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops or Presbyters are to do in ordinary. Therefore they were of the ſame Office: for as it is ſaid of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall, and learned Arts one and the ſame thing may be handled in divers of them, and yet theſe Arts are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht by the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> of handling of them, ſo we ſay of Offices, they are diſtinguiſht by their callings and Commiſſions, though not by the worke, as all thoſe that are named, (Eph. 4. 11.) <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts, Paſtors and Teachers,</hi> are deſigned to one and the ſame generall and common worke: <hi>The worke of the Miniſtry,</hi> ver. 12. And yet they are not therefore all one, for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts ſaid, <hi>ſome</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>ſome</hi> Prophets, <hi>ſome</hi> Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and <hi>ſome</hi> Paſtors and Teachers; A <hi>Dictator</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> and an ordinary <hi>Tribune. Moſes</hi> and the ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate governours of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The Court of <hi>Parliament</hi> and of the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> and a <hi>Presbyter</hi> or <hi>Deacon</hi> may agree in ſome common worke, and yet no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of Offices followes thereupon.</p>
            <p>To that which your Majeſty conceives, that the moſt that can be proved from all, or any of thoſe places, by us alleadged (to prove that the Name, Office, and work of Biſhops and Presbyters is one and the ſame in all things, and not in the leaſt diſtinguiſht) <q>Is that the word Biſhop is uſed in them to ſignifie a Presbyter, and that conſequently the Offi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, and work mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115960:5"/>
in theſe places as the Office and worke of a Biſhop are the Office of a Presbyter, which is confeſſed on all ſides.</q> We make this humble returne, that though there be no ſuppoſition, ſo much as implyed, that the Office of a Biſhop and a Presbyter, are diſtinct in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing (for the names are mutually reciprocall,) yet we take your Majeſties conceſſion, that in theſe times of the Church, and places of Scripture, there was no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Office of Biſhops and Presbyters; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the identity of the Office muſt ſtand, untill there can be found a cleere diſtinction or diviſion in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; And if we had argued the identity of Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the <hi>Community</hi> of names, <hi>and ſome part</hi> of the work, the Argument might have been juſtly termed a <hi>fallacy,</hi> but we proved them the ſame Office from the fame worke, <hi>per omnia,</hi> being allowed ſo to do by the fulneſſe of thoſe two words uſed in the <hi>Acts</hi> and St. <hi>Peter his Epiſtle</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> under the force of which words the Biſhops claime their whole power of Government and Juriſdiction, and we found no little weight added to our Argument from that in the <hi>Acts,</hi> where the Apoſtle departing from the <hi>Epheſian Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or Biſhops,</hi> as <hi>never to ſee their faces more,</hi> commits (as by a finall charge) the Government of that Church, both over particular Presbyters and people; not to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> who then ſtood at his elbow, but to the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters under the name of Biſhops, <hi>made by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> whom we read to have ſet many Biſhops over one Church, not one over either one or many, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles arguing from the ſame qualification of a Presbyter
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115960:6"/>
and of a Biſhop in order to ordination or putting him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Office, fully proves them to be two names of the ſame order or function: the <hi>diverſe Orders</hi> of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter and Deacon, being diverſly characteriſed, upon theſe grounds (we hope without fallacie) we conceive it juſtly proved, that a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and a <hi>Presbyter</hi> are wholly the ſame. That <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle perſons, having authority of Government, we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge; but deny, that from thence any argument can be made unto either <hi>ſingle Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Presbyter:</hi> for though a ſingle Presbyter by the power of his Order (as they call it) may preach the Word and diſpenſe the Sacraments; yet by that example of the <hi>Presbyterie,</hi> their <hi>Laying on of hands,</hi> and that Rule of <hi>Telling the Church</hi> in matter of ſcandal, it ſeems manifeſt, that Ordination and Cenſures are not to be exerciſed by a <hi>ſingle Presbyter;</hi> neither hath your Majeſty hitherto proved, either the names of Biſhops and Presbyters, or the function, to be in other places of Scripture at all diſtinguiſhed; You having wholly waved the notice or anſwer of that we did aſſert (and do yet deſire ſome demonſtration of the contrary) <hi>viz.</hi> That the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth not afford us the leaſt notice of <hi>any qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> any <hi>ordination,</hi> any <hi>work</hi> or duty, any <hi>honour</hi> peculiarly belonging to a Biſhop diſtinct from a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter; the aſſignment of which, or any of them unto a Biſhop, by the Scripture, would put this queſtion neer to an iſſue. That GOD ſhould intend a diſtinct and higheſt kind of Officer for Government in the Church, and yet not expreſſe any qualification, work,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115960:6"/>
or way of conſtituting and ordaining of him, ſeemes unto us improbable. Concerning the ſignification of the word <hi>Epiſcopus,</hi> importing an Overſeer, or one that hath a charge committed to him, for inſtance of watching a Beacon, or <hi>keeping ſheep,</hi> and the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the name to ſuch perſons as have inſpection of the Churches of Chriſt committed to them <hi>in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualibus:</hi> We alſo give our ſuffrage, but not to that diſtinction of <hi>Epiſcopus gregis,</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopus paſtorum &amp; gregis;</hi> both becauſe it is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or point in queſtion; and alſo becauſe your Majeſty having ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified that <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> imports a <hi>keeper of ſheep,</hi> yet you have not ſaid that it ſignifies alſo a <hi>keeper of ſhepheards.</hi> As to that which is affirmed by your Majeſty, that the <q>peculiar of the function of Biſhops is Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and that the reaſon why the word <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus</hi> is uſually applied to Presbyterie, was becauſe Church Governours had then another title of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eminencie, to wit, that of <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> until the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church came into the hands of their ſucceſſors; &amp; then the names were by common uſage very ſoon appropriated; That of <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> to Eccleſiaſtical Governours, That of <hi>Presbyter</hi> to the ordinary Miniſters. This aſſer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion your Majeſty is pleaſed to make without any demonſtration;</q> for whom the Scripture cals Presbyters, Rulers, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Teachers, it calls Governors; and commits to them the charge of feeding and inſpection as we have proved, and that without any mention of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment peculiar to a Biſhop; we deny not, but ſome of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115960:7"/>
the Fathers have conceived the notion that Biſhops were called Apoſtles, till the names of <hi>Presbyter</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus</hi> became appropriate, which is either an alluſion or conceipt, without Evidence of Scripture; for, while the Function was one, the names were not divided; when the Function was divided, the name was divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alſo, and indeed impropriate; but we that look for the ſame warrant, for the diviſion of an Office, as for the Conſtitution, cannot find that this appropriation of names, was made till afterwards, or in proceſſe of time, as <hi>Theodoret</hi> (one of the Fathers of this conceit) affirms, whoſe ſaying, when it is run out of the pale of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture time, we can no further follow; from which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes laid altogether, we did conclude the cleernes of our aſſertion, that in the <hi>Scriptures of the New Teſtament,</hi> a Biſhop diſtinct from a Presbyter in <hi>Qualification, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Office or dignity</hi> is not found, the contrary wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, though your Majeſty ſaith, that you have ſeene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by great variety of credible Teſtimony, yet we believe thoſe teſtimonies are rather ſtrong in aſſerting, then in demonſtrating the Scriptures Originall of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, which is declared againſt by a cloud of witneſſes, named in the latter end of our former Anſwer, unto which we ſhould refer if matter of right were not proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tryable by Scripture, as matter of Fact is by Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
            <p>Wee ſaid <hi>that</hi> the Apoſtles were the higheſt order of Officers of the Church, <hi>that</hi> they were extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, <hi>that</hi> they were diſtinguiſht from all other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and <hi>that</hi> their Government was not <hi>Epiſcopall,</hi> but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115960:7"/>
               <hi>Apoſtolicall;</hi> to which Anſwer, your Majeſty being not ſatisfyed, doth oppoſe certaine aſſertions, <q>That Chriſt himſelfe and the Apoſtles received their Authority by Miſſion, their Ability by Unction; That the Miſſion of the Apoſtles was ordinary, and to continue to the end of the world; but the Uncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherby they were enabled to both Offices &amp; Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Teaching and Governing was indeed extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, That in their Unction they were not neceſſarily to have ſucceſſours, but neceſſarily in their Miſſion or Office of Teaching and Governing, That in theſe two ordinary Offices, their ordinary ſucceſſours are Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters &amp; Biſhops, That Presbyters <hi>qua</hi> Presbyters do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſucceed them in the Office of Teaching, and Biſhops <hi>qua</hi> Biſhops immediately in the Office of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning;</q> The demonſtration of which laſt alone, would have carryed in it more conviction then all theſe Aſſertions put together; Officers are diſtinguiſhed by that whereby they are conſtituted, their Commiſſion, which being produced, Signed by one place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, gives ſurer evidence, then a Pedigree drawne forth by ſuch a <hi>ſeries of diſtinctions as do not diſtinguiſh him</hi> into another Officer from a Presbyter; whether this chaine of diſtinction be ſtrong, and the links of it ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently tackt together, we crave leave to examine, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, your Majeſty, was the <hi>Apoſtle and Biſhop</hi> of our ſoules, and he made the Apoſtles both Apoſtles and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; we do not conceive that your Majeſty meanes that the Apoſtles ſucceeded Chriſt as the chief Apoſtle, and that as Biſhops, they ſucceed Chriſt as a Biſhop, leaſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115960:8"/>
thereby Chriſt his <hi>Miſſion</hi> as an <hi>Apoſtle and Biſhop</hi> might be conceived as ordinary as their <hi>Miſſion</hi> is ſaid to be; But we apprehend your Majeſty to mean, that the Office of Apoſtle and Biſhop, was <hi>eminently</hi> contained in Chriſts office, as the office of a Biſhop was <hi>eminently</hi> contained in that of Apoſtleſhip; but thence it will not follow that <hi>inferior</hi> offices being contained in the <hi>ſuperior eminently,</hi> are therefore exiſtent in it <hi>formally;</hi> For becauſe all <hi>honours and dignities</hi> are <hi>eminently</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> would it therefore follow that your <hi>Majeſty</hi> is <hi>formally</hi> and <hi>diſtinctly</hi> a <hi>Baron</hi> of the Realm, as it is aſſerted the Apoſtles to have been Biſhops in diſtinct ſenſe; That <hi>Miſſion</hi> refers to Office and authority, and <hi>Vnction</hi> only to Ability, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſent: for beſides that the breathing of Chriſt upon his Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>Receive ye the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> doth refer to <hi>miſſion</hi> as well as <hi>unction;</hi> we conceive that in the proper <hi>anointing</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> or other Officers, the naturall uſe and effect of the oyle upon the body, was not ſo much intended, as the <hi>ſolemn</hi> and <hi>cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious</hi> uſe of it in the inauguration of them; ſo there is relation to Office in unction, as well as to conferring of abilities; elſe how are Kings or Prieſts or Prophets ſaid to be anointed? And what good ſenſe could be made of that expreſſion in Scripture, of anointing one in <hi>anothers</hi> room: to omit, that Chriſt by this conſtruction ſhould be called the <hi>Meſsias</hi> in reſpect of abilities only. And although we ſhould grant your Majeſties explication of <hi>Miſsion</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> yet it will not follow that the <hi>miſsion</hi> of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115960:8"/>
was ordinary, and their <hi>unction</hi> only extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary: That into which there is ſucceſſion, was ordinary; That into which there is no ſucceſſion, (for ſucceſſion is not unto abilities or gifts) extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary; and ſo the Apoſtles were ordinary officers in all whereunto there is properly any ſucceſſion, and that is <hi>office.</hi> They differed from Biſhops in that wherein one Apoſtle or Officer of the ſame order might differ from another, to wit, in abilities and meaſure of Spirit, but not in that wherein one order of officers is above another by their office; To which we cannot give conſent, for ſince no man is denominated an officer from his meer abilities or gifts, ſo neither can the Apoſtles be called extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry officers, becauſe of extraordinary gifts, but that the Apoſtles miſſion and office (as well as their abilities) was extraordinary and temporay, doth appeare in that it was by immediate Commiſſion from Chriſt without any intervention, of men, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Election or Ordination, for planting an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritative governing of all Churches through the World, comprehending in it all other Officers of the Church whatſoever, and therefore it ſeemes to us very unreaſonable that the Office and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Apoſtles ſhould be drawn down to an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, thereby to make it, as it were, a fit <hi>ſtock,</hi> into which the ordinary Office of a Biſhop may be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted,</hi> nor doth the continuance of Teaching and Governing in the Church more render the office of teaching and governing in the Apoſtles an ordinary office, then the office of teaching, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115960:9"/>
governing in Chriſt himſelfe, render his Office therefore Ordinary. The reaſon given, That the Office of Teaching and Governing, was ordinary in the Apoſtles, becauſe of the continuance of them in the Church (wee crave leave to ſay) is that great miſtake which runnes through the whole file of your Majeſties diſcourſe, for though there be a Succeſſion in the <hi>worke</hi> of Teaching and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet there is no Succeſſion in the <hi>Commiſſion or Office</hi> by which the Apoſtles performed them; for the Office of <hi>Christ,</hi> of <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> of <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> of <hi>Prophets,</hi> is thence alſo concluded Ordinary, as to <hi>Teaching and Governing,</hi> and the diſtinction of Offices Extraordinary and Ordinary <hi>eatenus</hi> deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; The Succeſſion may be into the ſame <hi>worke,</hi> not into the ſame <hi>Commiſſion and Office,</hi> the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Officers, which are to manage the work of Teaching and Governement, are conſtituted, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and limited by warrant of Scripture, as by another Commiſſion then that which the Apoſtles had; And if your Majeſty had ſhewn us ſome Record out of Scripture, warranting the diviſion of the office of teaching and governing into two hands, and the appropriation of teaching to Presbyters, of governing to Biſhops, the queſtion had been determined, otherwiſe we muſt look upon the diſſolving of the Apoſtolicall Office, and diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it into theſe two hands, as the dictate of men who have a minde, by ſuch a precarious Argument, to challenge to themſelves the <hi>Keyes of Authority,</hi> and leave the <hi>Word</hi> to the Presbyters.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115960:9"/>
In our anſwer to the inſtances of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> (which Doctor <hi>Bilſon</hi> acknowledgeth to be the maine erection of Epiſcopall power, if the proofes of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Biſhops, doe ſtand, or ſubverſion, if the anſwer that they were Evangeliſts be good) Your Majeſty finds ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little ſatisfaction though all that is ſaid therein could be proved.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe the Scriptures no where implyeth any ſuch things at all, that <hi>Titus</hi> was an <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> neither doth the text cleerly prove, that <hi>Timothy</hi> was ſo.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <q>1. The name of <hi>Biſhop, the Scripture neither expreſly nor by implication gives to either,</hi> the work which they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to do is common to Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, Paſtors &amp; Teachers, and cannot of it ſelf make a character of one diſtinct and proper office;</q> But that there was ſuch an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Officers</hi> in the Church as <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>extraordinary</hi> and temporary Offices and that <hi>Timothy</hi> was one of that Order, and that both <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>methy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were not ordained to one particular Church, but were companions and fellow Labourers with the Apoſtles, ſent abroad to ſeverall Churches as occaſion did require, it is as we (humbly conceive) clear enough in Scripture, and not denyed by the learned de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of Epiſcopall Government nor (as we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) by <hi>Scultetus</hi> himſelfe during the time of their travailes.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <q>2. To that which Your Majeſty ſecondly ſaith, That we cannot make it appeare by any Text of Scripture that the Office of Evangeliſt is ſuch as we have diſcribed, his worke ſeeming, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 4, 5. to be nothing elſe but diligence in preaching the word, notwithſtanding all impediments and oppoſitions,</q> We humbly Anſwer, That <hi>exact definitions</hi> of theſe or other Church Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers are hard to bee found in any Text of Scripture,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115960:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115960:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115960:11"/>
but by comparing one place of Scripture with another, it may bee proved aſwell that they were, as what the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> were, the deſcription by us given being a Character made up by <hi>collation</hi> of Scriptures, from which Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> doth not much vary, ſaying that <hi>Evangeliſts were Presbyters of Principall ſufficiency whom</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle. Pol l. b.</hi> 5</note> 
               <hi>the Apoſtles ſent abroad &amp; uſed as Agents in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Affaires, whereſoever they ſaw need.</hi> And that <hi>Paſtors</hi> &amp; <hi>Teachers,</hi> were ſettled in ſome certain charge and <hi>therby</hi> differed from <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> whoſe work that it ſhould be nothing but diligence in preaching, &amp;c, which is common to Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, Paſtors and Teachers, and ſo not diſtinctive of this particular Office, argueth to us, that as the Apoſtles Office was divided into Epiſcopall and Apoſtolicall, ſo this alſo is to be divided in Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and Evangeliſtical, Ordination and Cenſures belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Timothy</hi> as a Biſhop, and diligence in Preaching only being left to the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> which diviſion (as we humbly conceive) is not warranted by the Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Thirdly, Your Majeſty ſaith that that which we ſo confidently affirme of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> their acting as Evangeliſts is by ſome <hi>denyed</hi> and <hi>refuted,</hi> yea even with ſcorne <hi>rejected</hi> by ſome rigid Presbyterians, and that which we ſo confidently deny, that they were Biſhops, is <hi>conſirmed</hi> by the conſentient teſtimony of all antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>recorded</hi> by <hi>Ierome</hi> himſelfe that they were Biſhops of <hi>Pauls</hi> ordination, <hi>acknowledged</hi> by very many late Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, and that a Catalogue of 27 <hi>Biſhops of Epheſus</hi> lineally ſucceeding from <hi>Timothy</hi> out of good Record is vouched by Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> and other Writers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Our confidence (as Your Majeſty is pleaſed to call it) was in our Anſwer expreſt in theſe words, <hi>wee cannot ſay</hi> that <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were Biſhops in the ſenſe of Your Majeſty, but <hi>extraordinary officers or Evangeliſts,</hi> in which opinion we were then clear, not out of a totall ignorance
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115960:11"/>
of thoſe Teſtimonies which might be alledged againſt it, but from intrinſick arguments out of Scripture, from which Your Majeſty hath not produced any one to the contrary, nor is our confidence weakned by ſuch replys as theſe, the <hi>Scripture</hi> never cals them Biſhops, but the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> do, the <hi>Scripture</hi> calls <hi>Timothy</hi> an <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> ſome of late have refuted it, and rejected it with ſcorn, the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> relates their motions from Church to Church, but <hi>ſome affirme</hi> them to be fixed at <hi>Epheſus</hi> and in <hi>Creet,</hi> the <hi>Scripture</hi> makes diſtinction of Evangeliſts and Paſtors, but <hi>ſome</hi> ſay that <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were both, we cannot give Your Majeſty a preſent account of <hi>Scultetus</hi> and <hi>Gherards</hi> Arguments, but do believe that M. <hi>Gilleſpi</hi> and <hi>Rutherford</hi> are able with greater ſtrength to refute that opinion of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> their being <hi>Biſhops,</hi> then they do (if they do) with ſcorne reject this of their being <hi>Evangeliſts;</hi> As for <hi>teſtimonies and catalogues</hi> though we undervalue them not, yet Your Majeſty will be pleaſed to allow us the uſe of our Reaſon, ſo far as not to erect an office in the Church, which is not found in Scripture, upon <hi>generall appellations</hi> or <hi>titles</hi> and <hi>alluſions</hi> frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly found in the Fathers, eſpecially when they ſpeake <hi>vulgarly,</hi> and not as to a point in debate, for even <hi>Ierome</hi> who as Your Majeſty ſaith doth Record that <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were made <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and that of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, doth when he ſpeaks to the poynt between Your Majeſty and us, give the Biſhops to underſtand that they are ſuperior to Presbyters <hi>conſueitudine magis quam Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicae veritatis diſpoſitione;</hi> for <hi>catalogues</hi> their creditreſts upon the firſt witneſſes from whom they are reported by <hi>tradition</hi> from hand to hand, whoſe writings are many times <hi>ſuppoſitions, dubius</hi> or not <hi>extant,</hi> beſides that theſe <hi>catalogues</hi> do reſolve themſelves into ſome <hi>Apoſtle</hi> or <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt</hi> as the firſt <hi>Biſhop,</hi> as the catalogue of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115960:12"/>
into the <hi>Apoſtle Iames,</hi> that of <hi>Antioch</hi> into <hi>Peter,</hi> that of <hi>Rome</hi> into <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> that of <hi>Alexandria</hi> into <hi>Marke,</hi> that of <hi>Epheſus</hi> into <hi>Timothy,</hi> which Apoſtles and Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts can neither themſelves be degraded by being made Biſhops, nor be ſucceeded in their proper calling or office, and it is eaſy for us to proceed the ſame way and to finde many antient rites and cuſtoms generally received in the Church (counted by the antients <hi>Apoſtolicall traditions)</hi> as neer the Apoſtles times as Biſhops, which yet are, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly, not of <hi>Divine inſtitution;</hi> and further, if <hi>Timothy</hi> and the reſt that are <hi>firſt</hi> in the <hi>catalogue</hi> were Biſhops with ſuch ſole Power of Ordination and Cenſures, as is aſſerted, how came their pretended ſucceſſors, who were but <hi>Primi Presbyterorum</hi> (as the Fathers themſelves call them) to loſe ſo much Epiſcopall power as was in their Predeceſſors, and as was not recovered in 300 years? and therefore we cannot upon any thing yet ſaid, recide from that of our Saviour, <hi>ab initio non fuit ſic,</hi> from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is was not ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Your Majeſty ſaith, that wee affirme but upon ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weak proofes, that they were from <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Crete</hi> removed to other places, the contrary where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto hath been demonſtrated by ſome, who have exactly out of Scripture, compared the times, and order of the ſeverall journeyes, and ſtations of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>It is confeſſed that our aſſertion, that <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> lies with ſome ſtreſſe upon this, that they <hi>removed from place to place,</hi> as they were <hi>ſent by</hi> or <hi>accompanied</hi> the Apoſtles, the proofe whereof appeares to us, to bee of greaten ſtrength then can bee taken off by the compariſon which your Majeſty makes of the <hi>Divines of the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly at Weſtminſter.</hi> Wee begin with the <hi>Travailes</hi> of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115960:12"/>
               <hi>Timothy,</hi> as we finde them in order recorded in the Scripture-places cited in the Margin, and we <hi>ſet forth</hi> from <note n="a" place="margin">Acts 17. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Berea,</hi> where we finde <hi>Timothy,</hi> then next at <note n="b" place="margin">15.</note> 
               <hi>Athens,</hi> fromwhence <hi>Paul</hi> ſends him to <note n="c" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 3. 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica,</hi> afteward having been in <hi>Macedonia,</hi> he came to <hi>Paul</hi> at <note n="d" place="margin">Acts 18. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Corinth,</hi> and after that, he is with <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> and thence ſent by him into <note n="e" place="margin">Acts 19. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Macedonia,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Paul</hi> went after him, and was by <hi>Timothy</hi> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied into <note n="f" place="margin">Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. 4</note> 
               <hi>Aſia,</hi> who was with him at <note n="g" place="margin">5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Troas</hi> and <note n="h" place="margin">17.</note> 
               <hi>Miletus,</hi> to which place Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſent for the <hi>Presbyters</hi> of the Church in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and gave them that ſolemne charge to take heede unto <hi>themſelves,</hi> and to all the <hi>flock,</hi> over which the holy Ghoſt hath made them <hi>Biſhops,</hi> not ſpeaking a word of recommendation of that Church to <hi>Timothy,</hi> or of him to the Elders. And if <hi>Timothy</hi> was <hi>Biſhop of Epheſus,</hi> he muſt bee ſo when the <hi>firſt Epiſtle</hi> was ſent to him, in which he is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to receive the charge of exerciſing his <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> power in Ordination and government; but it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that after this Epiſtle ſent to him, he was in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall journeyes, or abſent from <hi>Epheſus.</hi> For <hi>Paul</hi> left him at <hi>Epheſus</hi> when he went into <note n="i" place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Macedonia,</hi> and he left him there to exerciſe his Office, in regulating and ordering that Church and in ordaining; but it was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this time that <hi>Timothy</hi> is found with <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Miletus,</hi> for aftur <hi>Paul</hi> had been at <hi>Miletus,</hi> he went to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> whence he was ſent priſoner to <hi>Rome,</hi> and never came more into <hi>Macedonia,</hi> and at <note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 13. 23. Phil. 1. 1. Philem. ver. 1. Col. 1. 1. Heb. 13. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Rome</hi> we find <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy a priſoner</hi> with him, and theſe Epiſtles which <hi>Paul</hi> wrote while he was priſoner at <hi>Rome,</hi> namely the Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> to <hi>Philemon,</hi> to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> doe make mention of <hi>Timothy</hi> as his companion at theſe times, nor doe we ever finde him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> for we finde that <hi>after all this,</hi> towards the end of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> life, after his firſt anſwering before
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115960:13"/>
               <hi>Nero,</hi> and when he ſaid his departing was at hand, hee ſent for <hi>Timothy</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> not from <hi>Epheſus;</hi> for it ſeemes that <hi>Timothy</hi> was not there, becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> giving <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 6. 10. 11. 12. 16.</note> an account of the abſence of moſt of his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſent into divers parts, he ſaith, <hi>Tychicus</hi> have I ſent to <hi>Epheſus.</hi> Now if your Majeſty ſhall bee pleaſed, to caſt up into one totall that which is ſaid; the ſeverall journeyes and ſtations of <hi>Timothy,</hi> the order of them, the time ſpent in them, the nature of his imployment, to <hi>negotiate the affaires of Chriſt in ſeverall Churches and places,</hi> the ſilence of the Scriptures, as touching his being Biſhop of any one Church, you will acknowledge that ſuch a man was not a Biſhop fixed to one Church or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct, and then by aſſuming that <hi>Timothy</hi> was ſuch a man, you wil conclude that he was not Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like concluſion may be inforced from the like pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, from the inſtance of <hi>Titus,</hi> whom we finde at <note n="a" place="margin">Galat. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> before he came to <hi>Crete,</hi> from whence hee is ſent for to <note n="b" place="margin">Titus 3. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Nicopolis,</hi> &amp; after that he is ſent to <hi>Corinth,</hi> from whence he is expected at <note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Troas,</hi> and met with <hi>Paul</hi> in <note n="d" place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Macedonia,</hi> whence he is ſent againe to <note n="e" place="margin">2 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> and after all this is neere the time of <hi>Pauls</hi> death at <hi>Rome,</hi> from whence he went not into <hi>Crete,</hi> but unto <note n="f" place="margin">2 Tim 4. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> and after this is not heard on in the Scripture; and ſo we hope your Majeſty doth conceive, that we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme not upon very <hi>weak proofes,</hi> that <hi>Tymothy</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> were from <hi>Epheſus</hi> &amp; <hi>Crete</hi> removed to other places.</p>
            <p>In the fifth exception your Majeſty takes notice of two places of Scripture cited by us, to prove that they were called away from thoſe places of <hi>Epheſus</hi> &amp; <hi>Crete,</hi> which if they doe not conclude much of themſelves, yet being accompanied <hi>by two other places</hi> which your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty takes no notice of, may ſeeme to conclude more, and theſe are 1 <hi>Tim. v.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Titus</hi> 1. 5. As <hi>I be ſought thee to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide ſtill at Epheſus,</hi> for <hi>this cauſe</hi> left I thee <hi>in Creete,</hi> in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115960:13"/>
both which is ſpecifed the <hi>occaſionall imployment,</hi> for which they made ſtay in thoſe places: and the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons uſed, <hi>I beſought</hi> thee to <hi>abide ſtill</hi> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> I <hi>left thee</hi> in <hi>Crete,</hi> doe not ſound like words of <hi>inſtallment</hi> of a man into a Biſhoprick, but of an <hi>intendment</hi> to call them away again, and if the firſt and laſt be put together, his <hi>actuall revocation</hi> of them both, the <hi>intimation</hi> of his intention, that they ſhould not ſtay there for continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and the <hi>reaſon</hi> of his beſeeching the one to ſtay, &amp; of his leaving the other behind him, which was ſome preſent defects and diſtempers in thoſe Churches, they will put faire to prove that the Apoſtle <hi>intended not</hi> to eſtabliſh them Biſhops of thoſe places, and therefore <hi>did not;</hi> For the <hi>Poſtſcripts,</hi> becauſe your Majeſty layes no great weight upon them, We ſhall not be ſolicitous in producing evidence againſt them, though they doe bear witneſſe in a matter of fact, which in our opinion <hi>never was,</hi> and in your Majeſties Judgement <hi>was long before they were borne,</hi> and ſo we conclude this diſcourſe about <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> with this obſervation, that in the ſame very Epiſtle of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> out of which your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty hath endeavoured to prove that he was a Biſhop, and did exerciſe Epiſcopall Government, there is cleare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence both for Presbyters <hi>impoſing hands,</hi> in ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for their <hi>Ruling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next point concerning the Angels of the Churches, though your Majeſty ſaith, <q>that you lay no weight upon the <hi>Allegory</hi> or <hi>Myſtery</hi> of the denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet you aſſert, that the perſons bearing that name were <hi>perſonae ſingulares,</hi> &amp; in a word <hi>Biſhops,</hi>
               </q>  who yet are never ſo called in Scripture, &amp; the allegorical denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Angels or Stars, which in the Judgement of anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and moderne Writers doth belong to the faithfull Miniſters and Preachers of the word in generall, is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115960:14"/>
(as we may ſo ſay) to the <hi>Myter</hi> and <hi>Croſier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaffe,</hi> and ſo oppoſed to many expreſſe teſtimonies of Scripture;And if your Majeſty had been particular in that, wherein you ſay the ſtrength of your inſtance lies, <hi>viz.</hi> the Judgement of all ancient, &amp; of the beſt moderne Writers, and many probabilities in the text it ſelfe, we hope to have made it apparent, that many ancient &amp; emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Writers, many probabilities out of the text it ſelf do give evidence to the contrary. To that which is aſſerted, That theſe ſingular perſons were Biſhops in diſtinct ſence, whether we brought any thing of moment to infirm this we humbly ſubmit to Your Majeſties judgement, and ſhall only repreſent to you that in Your Reply you have not taken notice of that which in our anſwer ſeems to us of moment, which is this, that in <hi>Myſterious</hi> &amp; <hi>prophetick writings</hi> or <hi>viſionall repreſentations</hi> (ſuch as this of the ſtars and golden Candleſticks is) a <hi>number</hi> of <hi>things</hi> or <hi>perſons</hi> is uſually expreſt <hi>in ſingulars,</hi> and this in viſions is the uſuall way of Repreſentation of things, <hi>a thouſand perſons</hi> making up one Church, is repreſented by one <hi>Candleſtick; Many Miniſters</hi> making up one <hi>Presbytery</hi> by one Angell. And becauſe Your Majeſty ſeemes to call upon us to be particular, though we cannot name the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> nor are ſatisfied in our judgement, that thoſe whom ſome do undertake to name were intended by the name of Angells in thoſe Epiſtles; yet we ſay, <hi>Firſt,</hi> that theſe Epiſtles were ſent unto the Churches, and that under the expreſſion of <hi>this thou doſt,</hi> or <hi>this thou haſt,</hi> and <hi>the like,</hi> the <hi>Churches</hi> are reſpectively intended, for the <hi>ſin repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> the <hi>Repentance commanded,</hi> the <hi>puniſhments threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> are to be referred to the Churches and not to the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Angells onely, and yet wee do not thinke that <hi>Salmatius</hi> did intend, nor doe wee, that in formall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination the <hi>Angells</hi> and <hi>Candleſticks</hi> are the ſame;</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115960:14"/>
Secondly; The <hi>Angels</hi> of theſe Churches or <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> were a <hi>Collective body,</hi> which wee endeavoured to prove by ſuch Probabilities as your Majeſty takes no notice of, namely the inſtance of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> where there were many <hi>Biſhops,</hi> to whom the charg of that Church was by <hi>Saint Paul</hi> at his <hi>finall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture</hi> from them committed; as alſo by that expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. 24. <hi>To you,</hi> and to the <hi>reſt in Thiatyra;</hi> Which diſtinction makes it very probable, that the <hi>Angel</hi> is explained under that <hi>Plurality to you;</hi> the like to which <hi>many</hi> expreſſions may be found in theſe <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> which to interpret according to the Conſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Evidence of other Scriptures of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is not Safe only, but Solid and Evidentiall.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, theſe Writings are directed as Epiſtolary, Letters, to <hi>Collective Bodyes,</hi> uſually are (that is) to <hi>One,</hi> but intended <hi>to the Body;</hi> which your Majeſty illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrateth by your ſending a Meſſage to your. Two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and directing it to the <hi>Speaker of the Houſe of Peers;</hi> which as it doth not hinder (we confeſſe) but that the <hi>Speaker is one ſingle Perſon;</hi> ſo it doth not prove at all, that the Speaker is <hi>alwayes the ſame Perſon;</hi> or if he were, that the refore becauſe your Meſſage is directed to him he is the <hi>Governour</hi> or <hi>Ruler</hi> of the Two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the leaſt, and ſo your Majeſty hath given cleare inſtance, that though theſe Letters be directed to the <hi>Angels,</hi> yet that notwithſtanding they might neither be Biſhops, not yet <hi>perpetuall Moderators.</hi> For the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall opinions ſpecified in your Majeſties Paper, <hi>three</hi> of them, by eaſie and faire accommodati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n (as wee declared before) are ſoon reduced and united a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, and may be holden wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hout <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115960:15"/>
from the received Iudgement of the Chriſtian Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by ſuch as are far from m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iting that Aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is caſt upon the <hi>Reformed Divines,</hi> by Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Writers, that they have divided themſelves from the Common and received Iudgment of the <hi>Chriſtian Church;</hi> which Imputation, wee hope, was not in your Majeſties intention to lay upon us, <hi>untill</hi> it bee made cleare that it is the common and received Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Christian Church</hi> that <hi>now is,</hi> or of that in <hi>former Ages,</hi> that the Angels of the Churches were Biſhops having Prelacy as well over Paſtors as Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple within their Churches.</p>
            <p>In the following Diſcourſe we did deny, that the Apoſtles were to have any Succeſſors in their Office, and affirmed onely <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Orders</hi> of <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>Standing Officers</hi> in the Church, <hi>vizt. Presbiters</hi> and <hi>Deacons.</hi> Concerning the former of which your Majeſty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to what you had in part already declared: <q>That in thoſe things which were extraordinary in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, as namely, the Meaſure of their Gifts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They had no Suceſſors in <hi>cundem graedum;</hi> but in thoſe things which were not extraordinary, as the Office of Teaching and Power of Governing (which are neceſſary for the Service of the Church in all times) they were to have and had no Succeſſours:</q> Where your Majeſty deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s a Doctrine <hi>new</hi> to us. Namely, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es had Succeſſors into their <hi>Offices,</hi> not into their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> For (beſides that, <hi>Succeſsion</hi> is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> into <hi>Abiliti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> but into <hi>Offic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> We cannot ſay, that one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> another in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115960:15"/>
or Patts, but into his Roome and Function, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that the Office Apoſtolicall was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in whole,</hi> becauſe their <hi>Miſsion</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o, and the ſervice or work of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Teaching and Governing being to continue in all times doth not render their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice <hi>Ordinary;</hi> as the Office of <hi>Moſes</hi> was not rendred Ordinary, becauſe many workes of Government ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed by him, were re-committed to the <hi>standing El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And if they have Succeſſors, it muſt be, either into their <hi>whole Office,</hi> or into ſome <hi>parts:</hi> Their Succeſſors into the <hi>whole</hi> (however differing from them in meaſure of Gifts and peculiar Qualifications) muſt be called <hi>Apostles,</hi> the <hi>ſame Office</hi> gives the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Denomination,</hi> and then we ſhal confeſſe that Biſhops, if they be their Succeſſors in Office, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> becauſe the Apoſtolicall Office <hi>him ſo;</hi> if their Succeſſors come into part of their Office only, the <hi>Presbiters</hi> may as well bee called their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Biſhops, and ſo indeed they are called by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the ancient Fathers, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Origen, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: Whereas in much the Apoſtle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Succeſſors into Office, but the ordin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry Power of Teaching and Governing (which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Church for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the hands of ordinary Officers by a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and Commiſſion according to the rules of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and calling in the word, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Biſhop hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yet produced for himſelfe, and without which he cannot challenge it upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And whereas your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of their work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Apoſtles, we could wiſh that you had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115960:16"/>
whether it belong to their <hi>Miſſion</hi> or <hi>Unction;</hi> for we humbly conceive, that their Authorative Power to do their Work in <hi>all places</hi> of the world did proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belong to their <hi>Miſſion,</hi> and conſequently that their <hi>Office,</hi> as wel as their <hi>Abilities</hi> was extraordinary and ſo by your <hi>Majesties own conceſsion</hi> not to be ſucceded in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by the Biſhops.</p>
            <p>As to the Orders of ſtanding Officers of the Church your Majeſty doth reply, <q>That although in the places cited, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 8. there be no mention but of the <hi>two Orders only of Biſhops or Preſbiters, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,</hi>
               </q> Yet it is not thereby proved that there is no other ſtanding Office in the Church beſides, which we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive is juſtly proved, not only becauſe there are no other named, but becauſe there is no rule of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyning any <hi>third,</hi> no Warrant or <hi>way of Miſſion,</hi> and ſo the Argument is as good, as can be made, <hi>a non cauſe ad non effectum;</hi> ſor we do not yet apprehend that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops pretending to the Apoſtolick Office do alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the ſame manner of <hi>Miſsion,</hi> nor do we know hat thoſe very many Divines that have afferted <hi>two or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders onely,</hi> have concluded it from any other grounds then the Scriptures cited.</p>
            <p>There appears (as your Majeſty ſaith) two other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt reaſons why the Office of Biſhops might not bee ſo proper to be mentioned in thoſe places. And wee humbly conceive there is a third more manifeſt then thoſe two, <hi>vizt,</hi> becauſe, <hi>It was not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The one reaſun given by your Majeſty, is becauſe in the Churches which the Appoſtles themſelves planted; they placed <hi>Presbiters</hi> under them for the Office of <hi>Teaching,</hi> but reſerved in their <hi>own hands</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115960:16"/>
the Power of <hi>Governing</hi> thoſe Churches for a <hi>longer,</hi> or <hi>ſhorter</hi> time before they ſet Biſhops over them.</q> Which under your Majeſties favour is not ſo much a reaſon why <hi>Biſhops are not mentiioned</hi> to bee in thoſe places as that they indeed were not; the variety of reaſons (may we ſay or conjectures) rendred why Biſhops were not ſet up <hi>at firſt,</hi> as namely becauſe <hi>fit men</hi> could not be ſo ſoon found out, which is <hi>Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> his reaſon, or for remedy of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> which is <hi>Jeromes</hi> reaſon, or becauſe the Apoſtles ſaw it not <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient,</hi> which is your Majeſties reaſon doth ſhew that this cauſe labours under a manifeſt weakneſſe; for the Apoſtles reſerving in their own hands the power of Governing, we grant it, they could no more deveſt themſelves of power of Governing, then (as Dr. <hi>Bilſon</hi> ſaith) they could looſe their Apoſtleſhip: had they ſet up Biſhops in all Churches, they had no more pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted with their power of Governing, then they did in ſeting up the Presbyters, for we have proved that Presbyters, being called <hi>Rulers, Governours, Biſhops,</hi> had the power of Governing in <hi>Ordinary,</hi> committed to them, as well as the Office of <hi>Teaching,</hi> and that <hi>both the Keys</hi> (as they are called) being by our Saviour comitted into <hi>one hand,</hi> were not by the Apoſtles divided <hi>into two:</hi> Nor do we ſee, how the Apoſtles could, reaſonably commit the Government of the Church to the <hi>Presbyters of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus, Act.</hi> 20, and yet reſerve the power of Governing <hi>(viz.</hi> in Ordinary) in his own hands, who took <hi>his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn leave of them, as never to ſee their faces more.</hi> As that part of the power of Government, which for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e may be called <hi>Legis-Lative,</hi> and which is one of the three fore-mentioned things challenged by the Biſhops, <hi>viz giving Rules,</hi> the reſerving of it in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115960:17"/>
Apoſtles hands hindred not, but that in your Majeſties Iudgment <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were Biſhops of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Creete,</hi> to whom the Apoſtles gives <hi>Rules</hi> for <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> and <hi>Governing</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> Nor is there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y more reaſon, that the Apoſtles reſerving that part of the Power of Governing which is called <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cuti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in ſuch caſes, and upon ſuch occaſions as they thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould hinder the ſetting up of Biſhops, if they had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it; and therefore the reſerving of Power in their <hi>hands</hi> can be no greater reaſon why they did not ſet up Biſhops <hi>at the firſt,</hi> then that <hi>they never did.</hi> And ſince (by your Majeſties Conceſſion) the Presbiters were placed by the Apoſtles <hi>first,</hi> in the Churches by them planted, and that with Power of Governi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, as wee prove by Scripture, you muſt prove the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of a Biſhop over the Presbyters by the Apoſtles in ſome after times, or elſe we muſt conclude that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop got both his Name and Power of Government out of the Presbyters hand, as the <hi>Tree in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns out the ſtones by little and little as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> grows<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>As touching <hi>Phillippi,</hi> where you Majeſty ſaith, it may be probable there was <hi>yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Biſhop,</hi> it is certaine there <hi>were many,</hi> like them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> at <hi>Epheful,</hi> to whom if only the Office of Teaching did belong they had the moſt <hi>labori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> and <hi>honorable</hi> part that which was leſs honorable being reſerved in the Apoſtles hands and the Churches left in the mean time without ordinary Government.</p>
            <p>The other reaſon given why two Orders only a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mentioned in thoſe places is, becauſe he wrot in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> to them that were Biſhops, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> there was no need to writ any thing concerning the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Qualification of any other ſort of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115960:17"/>
then ſuch, as belonged to their Ordination, or inſpection, which were <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> only, and no Biſhops. The former reaſon why two only Orders are mentioned in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Philip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ans,</hi> was, becauſe <hi>there was yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Biſhop<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> this latter reaſon why the ſame two onely are mentioned in theſe Epiſtles, is becauſe there was <hi>no Biſhop i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Ordained</hi> we might own the reaſon for good, if there may bee found any rule for the Ordination of the other order of Biſhops in ſome other place of Scripture, but if the <hi>Ordination cannot be found,</hi> how ſhould we <hi>find the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</hi> and it is reaſonable to think, that the Apoſtle in the Chapter formerly alleadged, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. where he paſſes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly from the Biſh to the De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on, would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> expreſt, or at leaſt hinted what ſort of Biſhop he meant whither the <hi>Biſhop <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver Presbyters,</hi> or the <hi>Presbiter Biſhop,</hi> to have avoyded the confuſion of the name, and to have ſet as it were ſome mark of difference in the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the Presbiter-Biſh. if there had bin ſome other Biſhop <hi>of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And wheras your Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. ſaith there was no need to writ to them about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in a diſtinct ſence, who belonged not to their Ordination and inſpection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We conceive that in your Majeſties judgment, Biſhops might then have Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined Biſhops like themſelves; for there was then no <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> forbiding one ſingle Biſh to ordain another of his own rank, and ther being <hi>many Cities</hi> in <hi>Creete, Titus</hi> might have found it expedient (as thoſe ancient Fathers that call him Arch-Biſhop think he did) to have ſet up Biſhops in ſome of thoſe Cities<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that this reaſoning his againſt the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, of thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to have been Biſhops, for our part we beleeve that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>Word-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> belonged unto <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Churches where they might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> any time
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115960:18"/>
have the Office of Ordeyning and Governing, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the ſame Chapter, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 14, 15. <hi>Thoſe things I have written unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. that thou mayeſt know how to be have thy ſelfe in the Houſe of God,</hi> which is the <hi>Church;</hi> and therefore if there had been any proper Character or Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of a Biſhop diſtinct from a Presbyter, if any <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination or Office,</hi> we think the Apoſtle would have ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied it, but becauſe he did not, we conclude (and the more ſtrongly from the inſufficiency of your Majeſties two reaſons) that there are <hi>onely two Orders of Officers,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently that a Biſhop is not ſuperiour to a Presbyter, for we find not (as we ſaid in our Anſwer) that one Officer is ſuperiour to another, who is of the ſame Order.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Ages ſucceeding the Apoſtles.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>Your Majeſty having in your firſt Paper ſaid, that you could not in Conſcience conſent to Aboliſh Epiſcopall Government, becauſe you did conceive it to be of <hi>Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Inſtitution, Practiſed</hi> by the Apoſtles themſelves, and by them <hi>comitted</hi> and <hi>derived</hi> to particular perſons as their <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> and have ever ſince til theſe laſt times bin <hi>exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> by Biſhops in al the Churchs of Chriſt:</q> We thought it neceſſary in our Anſwer, to ſubjoyne to that we had ſaid out of the Scriptures, the Iudgment of divers ancient <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> and <hi>Fathers,</hi> by whom Biſhops were not acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged as a <hi>Divine,</hi> but as an <hi>Eccleſiaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ticall Inſtitution,</hi> as that which might very much conduce both to the eaſing of your Majeſties ſcruple, to conſider that howſoever Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Government was generally currant, yet the ſuperſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was not jugded Divine, by ſome of thoſe that either were themſelves Biſhops, or lived under that Government, &amp; to the vindication of the opinion which we hold, from the prejudice of <hi>Novelliſme,</hi> or of <hi>receſſe</hi> from the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all Antiquity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115960:18"/>
We doe as firmely beleeve (as to matter of fact) that <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi> were <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was a <hi>Philoſopher, Cicer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> an <hi>Orator;</hi> though wee ſhould rather call out Faith and beliefe thereof <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rtaine</hi> in matter of fact, upon humane Teſtimonies uncontrouled, then <hi>infallible,</hi> in reſpect of the Teſtimonies themſelves. But where is your Majeſtie ſaith, <q>That the darkneſſe of the Hiſtorie of the Church, in the time ſucceeding the Apoſtles, is a ſtrong Argument for <hi>Epiſcopacie,</hi> which notwithſtanding that darkneſſe hath found ſo full proofe by <hi>unquestioned Catalogues,</hi> as ſcarce any other matter of fact hath found the like:</q> Wee humbly conceive, that thoſe fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned times were darke to the <hi>Catalogue-makers,</hi> who muſt derive the <hi>ſeries</hi> of <hi>Succeſsion</hi> from, and through thoſe Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoricall darkneſſes, and ſo make up their <hi>Catalogues</hi> very much from <hi>Tradition</hi> and <hi>Reports,</hi> which can give no great Evidence, becauſe they agree not amongſt themſelves: and that which is the great blemiſh of their Evidence is, that the <hi>neerer</hi> they come to the Apoſtles times (wherein they ſhould be moſt of all clear, to eſtabliſh the ſucceſſion firm and cleare <hi>at firſt)</hi> the more <hi>doubtfull,</hi> uncertaine, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>contradictorie</hi> to one another; are the Teſtimonies. Some ſay, that <hi>Clemens</hi> was <hi>firſt Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> after <hi>Peter;</hi> ſome ſay, the <hi>third:</hi> and the intricacies about the Order of Succeſſion, in <hi>Lin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, Anacletus, Clemens,</hi> and another called <hi>Cletus</hi> (as ſome affirme) are inextricable. Some ſay, that <hi>Titus</hi> was <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Crate;</hi> ſome ſay, <hi>Arch-biſhop;</hi> and ſome, <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Dalmatia.</hi> Some ſay, that <hi>Timothy</hi> was <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Epheſus;</hi> and ſome ſay, that <hi>Iohn</hi> was <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Epheſus</hi> at the ſame time. Some ſay, that <hi>Polycarpus</hi> was firſt <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Smyrna:</hi> another ſaith, that he ſucceeded one <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>colus;</hi> and another, that <hi>Ariſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was firſt. Some ſay, that <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> had but <hi>one Biſhop,</hi> and other Cities <hi>two;</hi> and others, that there was but <hi>one Biſhop</hi> of <hi>one Citie</hi> at the ſame time. And how ſhould thoſe <hi>Catalogues</hi> be unqueſtionable,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115960:19"/>
which muſt be made up out of Teſtimonies that fight one with another? Wee confeſſe, that the Ancient Fathers, <hi>Tertulltan, Irenaus,</hi> &amp;c. made uſe of Succeſſion, as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt <hi>Heretikes,</hi> or Innovators, to prove that they had the <hi>traduces Apoſtoliei ſeminis,</hi> and that the Godly and Orthodox Fathers were on their ſide. But that which we now have in hand, is <hi>Succeſsion in Office;</hi> which, according to the <hi>Catalogues,</hi> reſolves it ſelfe into ſome <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> or <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> as the firſt <hi>Biſhop</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Citie,</hi> or <hi>Place,</hi> who (as we conceive) could not be <hi>Biſhops</hi> of thoſe <hi>places,</hi> being of an higher <hi>Office;</hi> though, according to the language of after-times, they might by them that drew up the <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues,</hi> be ſo called, becauſe they <hi>planted and founded, or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered</hi> thoſe Churches to which they are entituled, and had their <hi>greateſt reſidence</hi> in them; or elſe the <hi>Catalogues</hi> are drawne from ſome eminent men that were of great <hi>vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> and <hi>reverence</hi> in the times and places where they lived, and <hi>Preſidents</hi> or <hi>Moderators</hi> of the <hi>Presbyteries,</hi> whereof themſelves were Members: from whom, to pretend the Succeſſion of after<hi>-Biſhops,</hi> is as if it ſhould be ſaid, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> was <hi>Succeſſor</hi> to the <hi>Roman Conſuls.</hi> And we humbly conceive, that there are ſome <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> uſed continually in the Church of old, which are aſſerted to be found in the Apoſtolicall and Primitive times, and yet have no colour of Divine Inſtitution; and, which is Argument above all other, <hi>the Fathers,</hi> whoſe Names wee exhibited to your Majeſtie in our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, were doubtleſſe acquainted with the <hi>Catalogues</hi> of <hi>Biſhops</hi> who had beene before them, and yet did hold them to be of <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Inſtitution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And leſt your Majeſtie might reply, That however the Teſtimonies and Catalogues may varie, or be miſtaken, in the order, or times, or names of thoſe perſons that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Apoſtles, yet all agree, that there was a Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>ſome</hi> perſons; and ſo, though the credit of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115960:19"/>
Catalogues be <hi>infirmed,</hi> yet the thing intended is <hi>confirmed</hi> thereby: We grant, that <hi>Succeſsion</hi> of men to feed and governe thoſe Churches, while they continued Churches, cannot be denyed, and that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> that planted and watered thoſe Churches (though extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie and temporarie Officers) were by Eccleſiaſticall Writers, in <hi>complyance with the Language and uſage of their owne times,</hi> called <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and ſo were other eminent men, of <hi>chiefe</hi> note, <hi>preſiding</hi> in the <hi>Presbyteries</hi> of the Cities or Churches, called by ſuch Writers as wrote after the <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> or <hi>diſtinction</hi> of the names of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops:</hi> But that thoſe <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ancienteſt Presbyters</hi> were <hi>Biſhops</hi> in proper ſence, according to your Majeſties deſcription, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with <hi>power</hi> over <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>people,</hi> to whom (as diſtinct from <hi>Presbyters)</hi> did belong the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, giving Rules</hi> and <hi>Cenſures;</hi> wee humbly conceive can never be proved by authentike or competent Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. And granting, that your Majeſtie ſhould prove the Succeſſion of Biſhops from the Primitive times <hi>ſeriatim;</hi> yet if theſe from whom you draw, and through whom you derive it, be found either <hi>more then</hi> Biſhops, as Apoſtles, and extraordinarie perſons, or <hi>leſſe then</hi> Biſhops, as meerly <hi>firſt Presbyters,</hi> having not one of the <hi>three eſſentials to Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall Government</hi> (mentioned by your Majeſtie) in their owne hand; it will follow, that all that your Majeſtie hath proved by this Succeſſion, is the <hi>Homonymy</hi> and equivocall acceptation of the word <hi>Epiſcopus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Clemens</hi> his Teſtimonie, which your Majeſtie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth to be made uſe of, as our old fallacie, from the <hi>promiſcuous</hi> uſe of the words to inferre the indiſtinction of the things; wee referre our ſelves to <hi>himſelfe</hi> in his <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi> now in all mens hands, whoſe Teſtimonie wee thinke cannot be eluded, but by the old Artifice, of <hi>hiding the Biſhop under the Presbyters name:</hi> for they that have read his whole Epiſtle, and have conſidered, that himſelfe is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115960:20"/>
called a Biſhop, <hi>may doubt of Clemens</hi> opinion, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the diſtinct offices of <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>not doubt</hi> of it, if onely his one Epiſtle, may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paneld upon the Inqueſt. Concerning <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, your Majeſty is pleaſed to uſe ſome <hi>earneſtneſſe</hi> of <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,</hi> charging ſome of late, without any regard of <hi>ingenuity</hi> or <hi>truth,</hi> out of their partiall diſaffection to Biſhops, to have endeavoured to diſcredit his writings. One of thoſe cited by us, cannot (as we conceive) be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected of <hi>diſaffection</hi> to <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and there are great Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments drawn out of thoſe Epiſtles <hi>themſelves, betraying</hi> their <hi>inſincerity,</hi> adulterate mixtures, and <hi>interpolations;</hi> So that <hi>Ignatius</hi> cannot be diſtinctly known in <hi>Ignatius.</hi> And if we take him <hi>in groſſe,</hi> we make him the <hi>Patron</hi> (as <hi>Baronious,</hi> and the reſt of the Popiſh writers do) of ſuch rites and obſervations, as the Church in his time cannot be thought to have <hi>owned.</hi> He doth indeed give te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>timonie to the <hi>Prelacy</hi> of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> above a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> that which may juſtly render him ſuſpected, is that he <hi>gives too much. Honour</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Biſhop</hi> as Gods high Prieſt, and <hi>after him</hi> you muſt honour the <hi>King.</hi> He was indeed a holy <hi>Martyr,</hi> and his writings have ſuffered <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> aſwell as he; <hi>Corruptions could not go currant, but under the credit of worthy Names.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which your Majeſty ſaith in Your fourth Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, That we might have added, (if we had pleaſed) That <hi>Iames, Timothy, Titus, &amp;c.</hi> were conſtituted and ordained Biſhops, of the forementioned places reſpectively, and that all the Biſhops of thoſe times, were <hi>reputed</hi> ſucceſſors to the <hi>Apoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les in their Epiſcopall office:</hi> We could not have added it without prejudice (as we humbly conceive) to the truth; for the Apoſtles did not ordein <hi>any of themſelves Biſhops,</hi> nor could they do it, for even by your Majeſties conceſſion, they were Biſhops <hi>before, viz.</hi> as they were <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> nor could any Apoſtle his choyce of <hi>a certain</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115960:20"/>
                  <hi>Region</hi> or Place to exerciſe his function in, whileſt he pleaſed, render him a Biſhop, any more then <hi>Paul</hi> was Biſhop of the <hi>Gentiles, Peter</hi> of the <hi>Circumciſion.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ordein the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> Biſhops of thoſe Places unto which they ſent them; Nor were the Biſhops of thoſe times any more then as your Majeſty ſaith, <hi>reputed ſucceſſours</hi> to the Apoſtles in their Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall office, they <hi>came after</hi> the Apoſtles in the Churches by them planted, ſo might <hi>Presbyters do;</hi> but thats not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>ſucceſſion,</hi> at leaſt not ſucceſſion <hi>into office;</hi> and this we ſay with <hi>a Salv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to our aſſertion, that in thoſe times there were no ſuch Biſhops diſtinct from Presbyters: Neither do we underſtand, whether the <hi>words Epiſcopall office,</hi> in this Section, refer to the <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> for in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> it inſinuates a diſtinction of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles office, into <hi>Apostolicall</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopall,</hi> or that the office Apoſtolicall, was <hi>wholly</hi> Epiſcopall, unto neither of which we can give our conſent for reaſons forementioned. To the teſtimonies by us recited in proof of <hi>two onely Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> Your Majeſty anſwers firſt, that the <hi>promiſcuous uſe</hi> of the <hi>names of Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> is imported; That which your Majeſty not long ago called <hi>our old fallacy,</hi> is now Your anſwer, onely with this <hi>difference,</hi> We under <hi>promiſcuous names</hi> hold the <hi>ſame office:</hi> Your Majeſty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>promiſcuous names</hi> ſuppoſes <hi>two,</hi> which if as it is often <hi>aſſerted,</hi> was but once <hi>proved<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> We ſhould take it for a <hi>determination</hi> of this controverſie. Secondly, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late <q>to a School-point, or a nicety, <hi>utrum Epiſcopat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſit ordo vel gradus,</hi> both ſides of the queſtioniſts or diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in the mean time acknowledging the right of Church-government in the Biſhops alone;</q> It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by us, that that queſtion as it is ſtated by <hi>Popiſh Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,</hi> is a <hi>curious nicety,</hi> to which we have no eye or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference; for though the ſame officers may <hi>differ</hi> fromand <hi>excell</hi> others of the <hi>ſame order</hi> in <hi>gifts</hi> or qualifications,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115960:21"/>
Yet the <hi>office it ſelf,</hi> is <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame,</hi> without <hi>difference</hi> or <hi>degrees,</hi> as one Apoſtle or Presbyter, is not ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to another in degree of office; they that are of the ſame order are of the ſame <hi>degree,</hi> in reſpect <hi>of office,</hi> as having Power and Authority to the ſame Acts. Nor doth the Scripture warrant or allow, any ſuperiority of <hi>one over another</hi> of the <hi>ſame order;</hi> and therefore the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>of two orders onely</hi> in the Church, is a <hi>demonſtration,</hi> that Presbyters and Biſhops are the ſame. In which point, the Scripture will counter-ballance the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of thoſe that aſſert <hi>three degrees or orders,</hi> though <hi>ten</hi> for <hi>one.</hi> But for eaſing of your Majeſty of the trouble of producing teſtimonies againſt thoſe cited by us, We make this <hi>humble motion,</hi> that the <hi>Regiments</hi> on both ſides may be diſcharged out of the <hi>field,</hi> and the point diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Dint of holy Scripture, id verum quod primum.</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving paſſed through the Argumentative parts of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Reply, wherein we ſhould account it a great happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to have given your Majeſty <hi>any ſatisfaction,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whereunto You pleaſed to honour us with this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, We ſhall contract our ſelves in the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, craving your Majeſties pardon, if You ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us to have been <hi>too much</hi> in the former, <hi>and too little</hi> in that which follows. We honour the Pious intentions and munificence of Your Royall Progenitors, and do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that <hi>ornamentall</hi> acceſſions granted to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, do not make any ſubſtantiall change in the <hi>office;</hi> the reall difference between that Epiſcopall Government, which firſt obtained in the Church, and the <hi>preſent Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy,</hi> conſiſts <hi>in ipſo regimine &amp; modo regiminis,</hi> which cannot be clearly demonſtrated in particulars, untill it be agreed on both ſides, what that Epiſcopacy <hi>was then,</hi> and what the Hierarchy <hi>is now,</hi> and then it would appear, whether theſe three forementioned <hi>eſſentialls</hi> of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Government, were the ſame in both: For the <hi>power</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115960:21"/>
under <hi>Christian</hi> Princes, and under <hi>Pagan,</hi> is one and the ſame, though the <hi>exerciſe be not.</hi> And we humbly receive your Majeſties Pious advertiſement, (not unlike that of <hi>Constantines)</hi> ſtirring us up as men unbyaſſed with pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſts, to ſtudy the neereſt <hi>accommodation</hi> and <hi>beſt reſemblance</hi> to the <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> and <hi>Primitive times.</hi> But for your Majeſties <hi>Salve</hi> to the Biſhops <hi>ſole Power,</hi> of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> and <hi>Iuriſdiction,</hi> and that <hi>diſtinction</hi> of <hi>Ordination, Authoritative</hi> in the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>Concomitant</hi> in the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, which You ſeem to <hi>found</hi> upon theſe two Texts, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 14. and which is uſed by D. <hi>Bilſon,</hi> and other defenders of Epiſcopacy, in explication of that Cannon of the fourth <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Carthage, which enjoyns the joyns impoſition</hi> of the Biſhops and Presbyters hands, We ſhall give your Majeſty an accompt, when we ſhall be called to the diſquiſition thereof; Albeit that we do not for the preſent ſee, but that this <hi>Proviſo of your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty,</hi> renders our accommodation to the Apoſtolicall and Primitive times (where unto You did exhort us) unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable. We not withſtanding, do fully profeſſe our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of <hi>ſubordination</hi> of the <hi>outward exerciſe</hi> of <hi>Iuriſdiction,</hi> to the Soveraign <hi>Power,</hi> and our accompta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe to the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land. As for your Majeſties <hi>three queſtions</hi> of great importance, <hi>Whether</hi> there be a certain form of Government left by Chriſt or his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, to be obſerved by all Chriſtian Churches; <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> it binde perpetually, or be upon occaſion <hi>alterable</hi> in whole, or in part; <hi>Whether</hi> that certain form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, be the <hi>Epiſcopall, Presbyterian,</hi> or ſome <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> differing from them both: The whole <hi>volume</hi> of Eccleſiaſticall <hi>Policy,</hi> is contained in them; and we hope that neither your Majeſty expected of us a particular an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to them at this time, nor will take offence at us, if we hold onely to that which is the queſtion, in order to the Bill of <hi>Abolition;</hi> for we humbly profeſſe our readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115960:22"/>
to ſerve your Majeſty, anſwering theſe or any other queſtions, within our proper <hi>Cognizance,</hi> according to the proportion of our mean abilities.</p>
               <p>For your Majeſties condeſcenſion, in vouchſafing us the liberty and honour of examining Your <hi>learned</hi> Reply, <hi>clothed</hi> in ſuch <hi>excellency</hi> of <hi>stile,</hi> and for Your exceeding <hi>candour,</hi> ſhewed to ſuch men as we are; and for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of our humble duty, we render to your Majeſty moſt <hi>humble thanks,</hi> and ſhall <hi>pray,</hi> That ſuch a <hi>pen</hi> in the hand of ſuch <hi>abilities,</hi> may ever be imployed in a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject worthy of it.</p>
               <p>That your Majeſty would pleaſe to conſider, that in this point under debate, <hi>ſucceſsion</hi> is not the beſt <hi>clew,</hi> and moſt <hi>certain,</hi> and <hi>ready</hi> way to finde out the <hi>Originall;</hi> for to go that way, is to go the furtheſt way about, yea, <hi>to go backward;</hi> and when You are at the <hi>ſpring, viz.</hi> the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> it ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> You go to the <hi>rivers end,</hi> that You may ſeek the <hi>ſpring.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that the Lord would guide your Majeſty, and the two Houſes of Parliament, by the <hi>right hand</hi> of his Councell, and ſhew You a happy way of healing our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy differences, and of ſettling the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, which is the <hi>Church;</hi> ſo as all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, may live under You in all Godlineſſe, Peace, and Honeſty.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi> Ia. Cranford.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octob.</hi> 19. 1648.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115960:22"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
