<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the Lord Broghil, and the officers of the army of Ireland in the province of Munster</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90192</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O475</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.24[26]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R211713</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870419</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870419</idno>
            <idno type="VID">163757</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A90192)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 163757)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 247:669f24[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the Lord Broghil, and the officers of the army of Ireland in the province of Munster</title>
                  <author>Orrery, Roger Boyle, Earl of, 1621-1679.</author>
                  <author>Ireland. Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Bladen, by special order ;</publisher>
                  <publisher>and re-printed at London by John Macock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659 [i.e. 1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: "Broghill." i.e., Roger Boyle, Earl of Orrery [and 42 others].</note>
                  <note>A request for the restoration of the secluded members of Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 20".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:163757:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Declaration of the Lord BROGHIL, and the Officers of the Army of <hi>Ireland</hi> in the Province of <hi>Munſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS the Freedom of Parliaments is their undoubted Right: ſo are our utmoſt endeavours for reſtoring them unto, and preſerving them in their Freedom, our undoubted Duty. Our Intereſt alſo is involved in our Duty; and if we truly love that, we cannot decline this; ſince whoſoever enquires into the Foundations of his own Freedom, his Poſterities and his Countries: in a Free and Full Parliament, as in a common Center, will find them all to meet. And therefore he that is not free in his Repreſentative, hath little reaſon to hope he ſhall be ſo in his Perſon or Property. The Theory of this truth hath not been more believed by other Nations, than the Practick of it hath been ſadly felt by Ours. For, ever ſince the firſt violence which was put upon the Authority of Parliament in 1648 we have been without Foundation; it having coſt us more Bloud and Treaſure to maintain confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, than ever it did coſt any former Age to free it ſelf out of them. For whilſt we were fighting for our Properties and Liberties, we have even almoſt in our ſucceſſes loſt both; and whilſt we contended for Reformation in Religion, we have almoſt loſt the very Being and Life of it. More Hereſies and Schiſms being introduced whilſt the higheſt Light was pretended to, than ever the darkeſt times were involved in; and whilſt we ſeemingly aſpired to Perfectneſs, we actually loſt that Charity which is the Bond of it; becoming thereby a reproach to our ſelves, and a deriſion to that Proteſtant part of the World, unto which, whilſt our Supreme Authority was inviolated, we were a Bulwark: the Univerſities and Schools of Learning in our Nations ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been looked more after to poyſon them, than to keep them ſound; that not only our Streams might be impure, but even our Fountains; many have been employed to teach, who ſtood in need to be taught; and the Legal Maintenance of the Miniſtery of the Goſpel conferred on Men unable, unwilling or unfit to diſpenſe it, who had leſs ill deſerved a Maintenance for their Silence, than their Speaking. Never greater Taxes raiſed for Armies and Fleets, and never Fleets and Armies more in Arrear. Taxes and Impoſitions laid, which paſt Ages never knew, and many thouſand Families of the preſent have been beggered by. Powers have made Laws, and ſubſequent Powers diſown'd and null'd what the preceding Powers had Acted: that now the Queſtions are not ſo many, What is the meaning of the Law, as, What is a Law: whereby that is become a Subject of Debate, which formerly was a Rule for ending of it. All which are yet inſeparable Effects of ſuch a Cauſe: for whilſt an Authority it ſelf is diſputed, their Acts will always be the like; and whilſt many are unrepreſented in making of Laws, few will be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be obliged by them: And what is Enacted by any but a Full and Free Parliament, will always be Queſtioned, if not Repealed, when ſuch an One doth ſit: nor can it be believed that the Laws of a Parliament, the very much greater part of whoſe Members are kept out without Impeachment or Tryal, will ever paſs the Teſt of a Free Parliament; leſt thereby they ſhould encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage others to ſerve them in like kind.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſad Miſeries, and theſe certain Truths, made us believe we hazarded more in ſubmitting to that Force that was ſo lately over us, than in taking up Arms to oppoſe it; and thereby endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the Reſtauration of the Parliaments Authority: in which God was pleaſed ſo to own the duty of our endeavours, that in a few days we were not only at unity among our ſelves, but even able and willing to offer our aſſiſtance to our Brethren in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> which had it been needed, it had been as readily ſent as offered. But we muſt confeſs, we could hardly ſo much as imagine that thoſe Members which had ſo recently felt, and juſtly exclaimed againſt a Force upon themſelves, would when it was taken off, have deny'd their Brethren to participate in that right they ſaw the three Nations had engaged their All to reſtore them unto.</p>
            <p>If it be a juſtice to declare for the reſtoring of ſome Parliament Members under a Force, 'tis a greater juſtice to appear for the reſtoring of all that are under it: yea, as much as the whole is preferrable to a part; ſo much greater is the duty of this declaring, than of that.</p>
            <p>We were more than hopeful, that when the Cauſe ceaſed, the Effect would do the like; and when the Rebellious part of the Army was broken, thoſe Members would have been re-admitted, which hitherto, we were made believe, were kept out only by it. The happineſs of the now-Members Reſtauration, and of the ſuppreſſing of thoſe Forces which lately had interrupted them, could not have been greater than the Honour they would have acquired, in making thoſe other Members, which had participated with them in their Sufferings, to have alſo participated in their Reſtitution. We were loath by an Addreſs of that nature to have leſſened the beauty of their expected performance, and had rather have enjoyed the Right and happineſs of having this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Full and Free, as the Product of the Juſtice of this preſent Houſe, than as any Effect of Our Sollicitations.</p>
            <p>When the violence was put upon the Parliament in 1648, we did with much contentment obſerve how ſollicitous thoſe that ſate were to have it taken off, thereby aſſerting their Rights, though they were denied the actual enjoyment of them; which made us the more chearfully engage our ſelves to reſtore thoſe to the Power of doing Juſtice, who then manifeſted they wanted not the Will: It being a crime too great to enter into our beliefs, That they asked, becauſe they were ſure to be deny'd; and would approve when they had the power, what they condemned when they had not the power: which, though then objected againſt them by many, we did not then credit, and we wiſh we never ſince had cauſe to believe. Nor was it unobſervable, that though ſuch Members of theirs as have been lately put out of the Houſe by them, as Sir <hi>Hen. Vane</hi> and others, were known to be guilty of joyning with that Rebellious part of the Army: yet they admitted them to ſit in the Houſe, till particular Charges were brought in againſt every one of them; they heard, and judged by the Houſe. If ſuch be not the true and antient manner of proceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Members of Parliament, why was it practiſed to thoſe ſo deeply guilty? and if it be, why is it deny'd to others, who have not hitherto appeared to be ſo? Doubtleſs ſuch as were kept out of the Houſe by a Rebellious part of the Army, merited at leaſt as much favour and juſtice, as thoſe who joyned with it. We do the more deplore ſuch a Procedure, becauſe from it Pleas have been raiſed for the like violence acted on the Members now ſitting: and happy are thoſe who condemn not themſelves in the things which they allow.</p>
            <p>What more pregnant proof need there be of the want of thoſe worthy Patriots, ſo long excluded, who with the earlieſt ſtood in the gap for our Liberties and Properties, than, that Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the Parliament is now puniſhed as a high Crime in the People, which at the Parliaments firſt meeting was declared to be their undoubted Right? And though a conſtant experience hath taught us, that the People may lawfully Petition for Repealing an Act of Parliament which is grievous to them, and therefore much more againſt a Vote which is ſo: yet to our Trouble and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement we underſtand thoſe worthy and eminent perſons, who in obedience to their Countries deſires, preſented Petitions for the Reſtauration of the Excluded Members, an impriſonment in the Tower was their Anſwer: That, we again ſay, which was declared the Right of the People, being now become their tranſgreſſion, Is it not high time to declare for that Juſtice, which when Petition'd for, is puniſhed?</p>
            <p>And becauſe we know the common aſperſion to ſuch a Declaration is, That it ſavors of a Deſign of introducing the Common Enemy; We ſhall here ſet down ſome of thoſe many Grounds which makes us experience, That in the Duty we now ingage in, we are not to be frighted by ſuch words: it may indeed terrifie and dare others; but ſuch who mean what they ſay, and are ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in what they do, will only pity thoſe who therein believe what they ſpeak, &amp; contemn thoſe who therein ſpeak what they do not believe. We rather doubt, that if the Houſe be kept ſo empty as it is, it will admit the Common Enemy, than the Houſe ſo filled: for whilſt eight parts of ten of the People are unrepreſented, and two Nations of the three intirely; may not it too probably pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke thoſe People to joyn with whoever will promiſe them their Right, than lie under that power which hath hitherto deny'd it to them? To keep out moſt of the Members, that a few may keep him out; is to do evil that good may come thereof. We love to do Lawful things, Lawfully.</p>
            <p>That the Houſe ought to be fuller than now it is, ſeems of late to be the granted Opinion of the Members that now ſit in it; and that we conceive can no way ſo probably with ſafety be effected, as by admitting all thoſe who in the year 1648. and ſince, were excluded; thoſe being likelyeſt to take care of our Safeties and Settlement, by whoſe Authority our Actings were influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced during the greateſt heat of our Wars; and therefore in Intereſt as well as Juſtice will be moſt concerned for us. And when ſuch are admitted, there will be no fear that the neceſſary Qualifications for thoſe Additional Members to be futurely elected, to ſupply the vacancies of delinquent and dead Members, will be diſobey'd, being enacted by ſo unqueſtionable an Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; nor that thoſe then choſen can be able to over-vote ſo full a Houſe, were that as much their deſign, as 'tis far from our thoughts to have ſo unworthy a belief of them.</p>
            <p>We believe, under ſubmiſſion, that we have acted and fought againſt the pretended King, as long as any others; and therefore ought to apprehend his coming in, as much as any others: but, through the mercy of God, our Principle is not to act an Evil our ſelves, to ſecure the doubts of ſome, that our Supreme Authority elſe would commit one. We are not to ſpeak nor think evil of the Rulers of our People; nor out of the fear of an uncertain Ill, to decline a certain Duty.</p>
            <p>If the ſaid Excluded Members be re-admitted, they muſt be either the Greater or the Leſſer Number in the Houſe: If the Leſſer, where is the Danger of their Admiſſion? If the Greater, where is the Juſtice of their Excluſion? for then it will appear, that the Minor Number keeps out the Major. And if in the apprehenſion, that a Parliament when Full and Free, will abuſe their Authority, it be a received Maxime to keep them from the Exerciſe of it; a certain Foundation is laid for all that have the greateſt Force, to have alſo the greateſt Authority; and whoever hath ſtrength and this Tenent together, may too eaſily be perſwaded to believe, that he hath as much Right over the Minor part of a Parliament, as the Minor part has over the Major. Neither can any Act of a Supreme Authority be ſo evil, as is the admitting that any but the Supreme Authority ought practically to judge what is beſt for the Nations: the One can be but an ill Act in Governours, but the Other is a deſtroying of Government. VVe do not deſire that any of the Secluded Members, if they have offended, may not be tryed: but we humbly deſire that they may have a Parliamentary Tryal. And though we much value their Perſons, yet we can with as much truth aver, VVe ask this for their Cauſe, not for Them. And had thoſe Members who now ſit, been in the Condition of the Excluded Members, and the Excluded Members in their Condition, we had as cheerfully appeared for Theſe, as now we do for Thoſe.</p>
            <p>And conſidering that in paſt Ages, and more particularly ſince the beginning of the late horrid Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> our Brethren in <hi>England</hi> have abundantly manifeſted a tender and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate ſence of the Condition of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and were careful to relieve us in our loweſt Eſtate, as bone of their bone, and fleſh of their fleſh: which we do and ſhall ever acknowledge with humble thankfulneſs; and (as a debt which we well know to be due from us to them above all people in the world) ſhall be for ever as tender of their happineſs and welfare, as of our own, which indeed is involved in theirs, and without whom <hi>Ireland</hi> cannot be happy: VVe therefore remaining conſtant in the Reaſons of our Brethrens Declaration of the 14 of <hi>December</hi> 1659. for adhering to the Parliament in defence of its Priviledges, and the juſt Rights and Liberties of theſe Nations; all which we ſee now are apparently more and more violated by the not-admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſaid Excluded Members, and by not filling the vacant places, whereby the Houſe might be full; and being freed from force, might uninterruptedly act according to their Judgements and Conſciences towards re-ſettling theſe Nations, which otherwiſe in all humane probability can never be reſtored to Peace and Tranquillity.</p>
            <p>VVe do therefore declare for a full and free Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> conſiſting not onely of thoſe that ſate on the 11 of <hi>October</hi> 1659. but alſo of all ſuch of the Members of Parliament, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, excluded or withdrawn in <hi>December</hi> 1648. as are yet living; whom we deſire may be reſtored to the freedom and liberty of their ſitting and acting, according to the Truſts committed to them by the ſeveral Counties and Places which did chuſe them; that ſo they may be no longer debarred from diſcharging their ſaid Truſts; and that vacant places may be ſpeedily ſupplyed by free and due Elections of the People: yet ſo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s none of the Perſons to be admitted or elected, be any of thoſe who have been in Arms, or otherwiſe aiding, abetting or aſſiſting the late King or his Son in the late VVar againſt the Parliament; or that have put rebellious Violence upon the Parliament: and that the Houſe ſo filled, may proceed unanimouſly to conſult the beſt means for re-ſetling the peace of the Nations, the re-eſtabliſhment of true Religion, (the ſureſt Foundation as of all Government, ſo of all the happineſs of a Nation) the Fundamental Laws of the Land, (whereby all mens Rights and Liberties are preſerved) and the Liberties and Freedom of the People, which are ſupported by thoſe Laws.</p>
            <p>And for theſe Ends, and in diſcharge of our duty to God and our Country, we do reſolve (by the bleſſing of Almighty God) to joyn with all our Brethren in <hi>England, Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> who have or ſhall joyn with us for the ends aforeſaid; and do reſolve for the maintenance and preſervation thereof, to hazard our Lives and Eſtates, and all that is dear to us: and we doubt not but all our Brethren in the ſaid Nations, who diſdain to be made Slaves, will joyn with us herein, as being with wiſdome and reaſon deſirous to deliver over to their Poſterity that Liberty and Freedom which was conveyed to them at ſo dear a rate by our Anceſtors. And then we truſt, that by the great mercy of God, will ſpeedily follow a happy Settlement of theſe yet-miſerable and diſtracted Nations; and conſequently, that the true Proteſtant Religion in the power and purity thereof, may be eſtabliſhed; the Godly, Learned and Orthodox Miniſters of the Goſpel main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by their Tythes, and other their accuſtomed Rights; their perſons ſupported and countenanced; the Univerſities, and all other Seminaries of Learning, cheriſhed; Hereſies and Schiſms ſuppreſſed; needleſs Impoſitions and Taxes on the people, removed; and no charge to be laid on any of the Nations without their own free conſents, given by their Repreſentatives in their ſeveral and reſpective Parliaments: Manufactures and publick Trade and Commerce at home and abroad, advanced; Juſtice in its due and wonted courſe, adminiſtred; the juſt debts of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſatisfied; the Treaſure and Revenues thereof preſerved, and returned to their right and proper Chanels; the Arrears of the Army, and other publick debts, duly ſatisfied; the Armies and Forces continued in due obedience to the Supreme Authority, and not preſume, as ſome have done, to give Laws thereunto, which hath been the root of a great part of our miſeries; the Nations enriched, united and ſtrenthned; the reformed Proteſtant Churches abroad ſupported and countenanced; the Honour of the Engliſh Nations reſtored, to the comfort of Friends, and terrour of Enemies; the Plantation of <hi>Ireland</hi> in the hands of Adventurers and Souldiers, and other Engliſh and Proteſtants advanced, as a further acceſſion of honour and greatneſs to the Engliſh Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n: And ſo by the bleſſing of God, all will ſhortly terminate in the Glory of God, the Peace and Tranquillity of theſe Nations, the ſtrengthning of them againſt forreign Invaſion, and inteſtine Rebellion, and the comfort, contentment and ſatisfaction of all the good people in theſe Nations.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>BROGHILL.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>p. Sir <hi>Mau. Fenton</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Col. <hi>Ralph Wilſon</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lt. Col. <hi>J. Widenham</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lt. Col. <hi>Ben. Lucas</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lt. Col. <hi>A. Barrington</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lt. Col. <hi>Fr. Foulk</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Major <hi>Will. Wade</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Major <hi>Will. King</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Major <hi>N. Purdon</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Major <hi>R. Goodwyn</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>And. Ruddock</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>J. Wakeham</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>Ge. Dillon</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>Ja. Manſerghe</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>Ro. Ruſſel</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>Jo. Nicholls</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>Sampſ. Towgood</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>Thomas Cullen</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>D. Coghlan</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>Hum. Hartwell</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>Tho. Lucas</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>Will. Pope</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>Will. Hartwell</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. <hi>John Frend </hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chriſtop. Perkins</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lt. <hi>Hum. Ray</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lt. <hi>Jo. Zan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lt. <hi>Rich. Wakeham</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lt. <hi>Rich. Aſhwood</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lt. <hi>Pat. Dowdal</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lt. <hi>Zac. Holland</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lt. <hi>Hen. Haward</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cornet <hi>H. Fagetter</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cor. <hi>Mat. Pennefether</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cor. <hi>Dane Rono</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Enſign <hi>Bar. Foulk</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Enſ. <hi>John Brown</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Enſ. <hi>Ant. Shackleton</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Enſ. <hi>Iohn Sloughter</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Enſ. <hi>James Banting</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Enſ. <hi>Hen. Bindon</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Qu. Mr. <hi>Jaſon Whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rob. Fletcher,</hi> Com.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Dublin,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Bladen,</hi> by ſpecial Order, and Re-printed at <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>John Macock.</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
