<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The duty of pastors and people distingushed [sic]. Or A briefe discourse, touching the administration of things commanded in religion. Especially concerning the means to be used by the people of God (distinct from church-officers) for the increasing of divine knowledge in themselves and others. Wherein bounds are prescribed to their peformances, their liberty is enlarged to the utmost extent of the dictates of nature and rules of charity: their duty laid downe in directions, drawn from Scripture-precepts, and the practise of Gods people in all ages. Together with the severall wayes of extraordinary calling to the office of publike teaching, with what assurance such teachers may have of their calling, and what evidence they can give of it, unto others. / By John Ovven, M.A. of Q. Col. O.</title>
            <author>Owen, John, 1616-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O741</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E49_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2375</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872039</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872039</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155115</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A90265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155115)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 9:E49[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The duty of pastors and people distingushed [sic]. Or A briefe discourse, touching the administration of things commanded in religion. Especially concerning the means to be used by the people of God (distinct from church-officers) for the increasing of divine knowledge in themselves and others. Wherein bounds are prescribed to their peformances, their liberty is enlarged to the utmost extent of the dictates of nature and rules of charity: their duty laid downe in directions, drawn from Scripture-precepts, and the practise of Gods people in all ages. Together with the severall wayes of extraordinary calling to the office of publike teaching, with what assurance such teachers may have of their calling, and what evidence they can give of it, unto others. / By John Ovven, M.A. of Q. Col. O.</title>
                  <author>Owen, John, 1616-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] 54, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L. N. for Philemon Stephens, at the gilded Lion in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 21".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clergy --  Office --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155115:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The duty of Paſtors and People diſtinguſhed.
OR A BRIEFE
DISCOVRSE,
Touching the
ADMINISTRATION
OF THINGS COMMANDED
IN RELIGION.
ESPECIALLY CONCERNING
the means to be uſed by the people of God
(diſtinct from Church-Officers) for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing
of divine knowledge in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
and others.
WHEREIN
BOUNDS ARE PRESCRIBED TO
their <hi>performances,</hi> their <hi>liberty</hi> is enlarged to the utmoſt <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi>
of the <hi>dictates</hi> of Nature and <hi>rules</hi> of charity: their
<hi>duty</hi> laid downe in <hi>directions,</hi> drawn from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-precepts,
and the practiſe of Gods
people in all ages.
Together with
THE SEVERALL WAYES OF EXTRAORDINARY
<hi>calling</hi> to the office of publike <hi>Teaching,</hi> with what <hi>aſſurance</hi>
ſuch teachers may have of their <hi>calling,</hi> and what <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi>
they can give of it, unto others.</p>
            <p>By JOHN OVVEN, <hi>M. A.</hi> of <hi>Q. Col. O.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON,
Printed by <hi>L. N.</hi> for <hi>Philemon Stephens,</hi> at the gilded
Lion in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:155115:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155115:2"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVLY NOBLE,
and my ever honoured friend, Sir EDWARD SCOT,
of Scots-Hall in Kent, Knight of the honourable Order
of the BATH.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving of late been deprived of the happineſſe to ſee you,
I make bold to ſend to viſite you; and becauſe that the
times are troubleſome, I have made choiſe of this meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger:
who having obtained a licenſe <hi>to paſſe,</hi> feares no
ſearching: he brings no <hi>newes</hi> (at leaſt) to you, but that which was
from the <hi>beginning,</hi> and muſt continue unto the <hi>end,</hi> which you
have heard, and which (for ſome part thereof) you have practiſed
out of the word of God. He hath no ſecret meſſages prejudiciall to
the ſtate of Church or Common-wealth; neither I hope, will he
entertain any ſuch comments by the way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> conſidering from <hi>whom</hi> he
comes, and to <hi>whom</hi> he goes; of whom, the one would <hi>diſclaime</hi> him,
and the other <hi>puniſh</hi> him. Ambitious I am not of any entertainment
for theſe few ſheetes, neither care much what ſucceſſe they find in
their travel; ſetting them out meerly in my own defence, to be freed
from the continued ſolicitations of ſome honeſt judicious men, who
were acquainted with their contents: being nothing, but an houres
<hi>Country-diſcourſe,</hi> reſolved, from the ordinary pulpit method, into its
own principles: when I firſt thought of ſending it to you, I made ful
account to uſe the benefit of the advantage, in <hi>recounting</hi> of, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning
thanks <hi>for</hi> ſome of thoſe many undeſerved favours which I
have received from you. But addreſſing my ſelf to the performance,
I fainted in the very entrance; finding their <hi>ſcore</hi> ſo large, that I
<hi>know</hi> not where to <hi>begin,</hi> neither ſhould I <hi>know</hi> how to <hi>end:</hi> only <hi>one</hi>
I cannot ſuffer to lye hid in the <hi>croud,</hi> though other engagements
hindred me from embracing it, <hi>viz.</hi> your free <hi>proffer</hi> of an Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical
<hi>preferment,</hi> then vacant, and in your donation. Yet truly all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
courteſies, have <hi>no</hi> power to oblige me unto you, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:155115:3"/>
of that abundant worth, which by experience I have found to be
dwelling in you. <hi>Twiſe</hi> by Gods providence, have I been with you,
when your County hath been in great danger to be ruined, once by
the horrid <hi>inſurrection</hi> of a rude godleſſe multitude; and againe, by
the <hi>invaſion</hi> of a potent enemy, prevailing in the neighbor County;
at both which times, beſides the generall calamity juſtly feared, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
threatnings were daily brought unto you: under which ſad
diſpenſations, I muſt crave leave to ſay (only to put you in mind of
your ſelfe, if it ſhould pleaſe God againe to reduce you to the like
ſtraights) that I never ſaw more reſolved <hi>conſtancy,</hi> more cheerfull
unmoved Chriſtian courage in any man. Such a valiant heart in a
weak body, ſuch a directing head, where the hand was but feeble,
ſuch unwearied endevours, under the preſſures of a painful infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
ſo well adviſed reſolves in the midſt of imminent danger, did I
then behold, as I know not where to parallel. Neither can I ſay leſſe
in her kind of your vertuous <hi>Lady,</hi> whoſe <hi>known</hi> goodneſſe to al, and
particular <hi>indulgences</hi> to me, make her (as ſhe is in her ſelf) very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
in my thoughts and remembrance: whom having named, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
to take the advantage thankfully to mention her worthy ſon, my
noble and very deare friend <hi>C. Weſtrow,</hi> whoſe judgement to diſcerne
the differences of theſe times, and his valour in proſecuting what he
is reſolved to be juſt and lawfull, places him among the number of
thoſe very few, to whom it is given to know aright the cauſes of
things, and vigorouſly to execute holy and laudible <hi>deſignes.</hi> But fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of him I chooſe to ſay nothing, becauſe if I would, I cannot but
ſay too little. Neither will longer detain <hi>you</hi> from the enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
which I deſire to commend to your favourable acceptance,
and with my hearty prayers, that the Lord would meet you and
yours in all thoſe wayes of mercy and grace, which are neceſſary to
carry you along through all your engagements, untill you arrive at
the haven of everlaſting glory, where you would be: <hi>I reſt</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt obliged Servaent in Ieſus Chriſt
our common Maſter:
JOHN OVVEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155115:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO
the enſuing Diſcourſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE glaſſe of our <hi>lives,</hi> ſeemes to runne and
keep <hi>pace</hi> with the <hi>extremity</hi> of time: the <hi>end</hi>
of thoſe <hi>ends of the world</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 11 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Revel. 10. 6. 1 Epiſt. Joh. 2. 18.</note> which <hi>began</hi> with
the Goſpell, is doubtleſſe <hi>comming</hi> upon us,
hee that was <hi>inſtructed</hi> what ſhould <hi>bee,</hi> till
time ſhould <hi>be</hi> no <hi>more,</hi> ſaid, it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
the <hi>laſt</hi> houre in his <hi>time:</hi> much <hi>ſand</hi> cannot be
behind, and Chriſt <hi>ſhakes</hi> the glaſſe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth. 24. 23. 1 Cor.</hi> 15. 52. Zanch. de fine ſec. Mol. acc. proph.</note> many <hi>minutes</hi> of that <hi>houre</hi>
cannot remaine; the next <hi>meaſure</hi> we are to evpect, is but a <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
the <hi>twinkling of an eye,</hi> wherein we ſhall all be <hi>changed;</hi>
now as if the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> of the decaying <hi>age,</hi> had ſome ſecret <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence</hi>
into the wils of men, to comply with the <hi>decrepit world,</hi>
they generally <hi>delight</hi> to run into <hi>extreames:</hi> not that I would
have the <hi>fate of the times</hi> to beare the <hi>faults</hi> of men, like him who
cried,<note place="margin">Rom. 9. 19.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to free <hi>himſelf, intitling</hi> God
and <hi>fate</hi> to his ſins; but only to ſhew how the All-diſpoſing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
of the moſt Hign, works ſuch a complyance of <hi>times</hi> and
<hi>perſons,</hi> as may joyntly <hi>drive</hi> at his glorious aymes, cauſing men
to <hi>ſet out</hi> in ſuch <hi>ſeaſons</hi> as are <hi>fittest</hi> for their <hi>travell.</hi> This <hi>Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall</hi>
diſeaſe of the <hi>aged world,</hi> is the cauſe, why in that great <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity</hi>
of contrary opinions, wherewith mens <hi>heads</hi> and hearts
are now <hi>repleniſhed:</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> pretended to be ſought with ſo
much <hi>earneſtneſſe,</hi> may be often <hi>gathered</hi> up, quite neglected, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the <hi>parties</hi> litigant; <hi>medio tuliſſimus,</hi> is a ſure rule, but that
<hi>fiery</hi> ſpirits, <hi>pyrout Eocus &amp; Aethon quartuſque Phlegon,</hi> will be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155115:4"/>
               <hi>mounting.</hi> In the matter concerning which, I propoſe my weake
<hi>Eſſay,</hi> ſome would have all <hi>Christians</hi> to be <hi>almoſt Ministers,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<hi>none</hi> but <hi>Ministers,</hi> to be Gods <hi>Clergie: thoſe</hi> would give
the <hi>people</hi> the <hi>keys, theſe</hi> uſe them, to <hi>lock</hi> them out of the <hi>Church,</hi>
the one aſcribing to them <hi>primarily</hi> al <hi>Eccleſiaſticall power</hi> for the
ruling of the <hi>Congregation;</hi> the other <hi>abridging</hi> them of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
of <hi>ſpirituall duties,</hi> for the building of their <hi>own ſoules:</hi>
as though there were no <hi>habitable earth</hi> betweene the valley (I
had almoſt ſaid the pit) of <hi>Democraticall confuſion,</hi> and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitious
rock of <hi>Hierarchicall tyranny:</hi> when unskilfull <hi>Archers</hi>
ſhoot, the ſafeſt <hi>place</hi> to avoid the arrow, is the <hi>white:</hi> going, as
neare as God ſhall direct me, to the <hi>truth</hi> of this matter, I hope
to avoid the <hi>ſtrokes</hi> of the combatants on every <hi>ſide.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
wil not handle it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with oppoſition to any <hi>man,</hi> or <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi>
but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> briefly propoſing mine owne <hi>required</hi> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
the ſummary reſult whereof, is, that <hi>the ſacred calling may
retaine its ancint dignity, though the people of God be not deprived
of their Chriſtian liberty;</hi> to cleare which propoſall, ſomethings
I ſhall briefly premiſe,</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the Adminiſtration of holy things among the Patriarks
before the Law.</head>
               <p>1. COncerning the ancient <hi>Patriachs;</hi> from <hi>theſe,</hi> ſome who
would have <hi>Judaiſme,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euſeb. Eccleſ. Hiſt. lib. 1. cap. Ambr. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra. lib. 4. <hi>Epheſ</hi> 2. 35.</note> to be but an interciſion of <hi>chriſtiauity</hi>
derive the <hi>pedigree</hi> of chriſtians, affirming the diference between
<hi>us</hi> &amp; <hi>them,</hi> to be ſolely in the <hi>name</hi> &amp; not the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelf: Of <hi>this</hi>
thus much at leaſt is <hi>true, that the Law of Commandements,
contained in Ordinances</hi> did much more diverſifie the <hi>Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi>
of the Covenant, before, and after Chriſt, then thoſe
plaine <hi>moralities,</hi> wherewith in their dayes it was <hi>cloathed:</hi>
where the aſſertion is <hi>dificient, Antiquity</hi> hath given its authors
<hi>ſanctuary</hi> from farther purſuit. their <hi>practice</hi> then, were it <hi>cleer,</hi>
can be no <hi>preſident</hi> for Chriſtians; All <hi>light</hi> brought to the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi>
in compariſon of thoſe <hi>full and glorious beames,</hi> that ſhine
in it <hi>ſelfe,</hi> is but a <hi>Candle</hi> ſet up in the <hi>ſunne:</hi> Yet for <hi>their ſakes,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:155115:4"/>
who <hi>found out</hi> the former Unity, I will, (not following the
<hi>conceit of any,</hi> nor the <hi>comments of many</hi>) give you ſuch a <hi>bare</hi>
naration, as the <hi>ſcripture</hi> will ſupply me <hi>withall,</hi> of their <hi>admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration</hi>
of the <hi>holy things</hi> and practiſe of their Religion: (as it
ſeemes Chriſtianity, though not ſo called) and doubt you not of
divine <hi>approbation,</hi> and <hi>inſtitution:</hi> For all <hi>prelacy,</hi> at leaſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<hi>Nimrod hunted for preferment,</hi> was <hi>dejure divino:</hi> I finde
then, that before the giving of the <hi>Law,</hi> the <hi>chief men</hi> among
the ſervants of the <hi>true God,</hi> did every one in their owne <hi>fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi>
with their <hi>neighbors adjoyning,</hi> of the ſame perſwaſion, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
thoſe things which they knew to be required, <hi>by the Law
of nature, tradition,</hi> or ſpeciall revelation (the unwritten word
of thoſe times) in the ſervice of God, <hi>inſtructing</hi> their childeren
and ſervants in the <hi>knowledge</hi> of their <hi>creed</hi> concerning the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
and goodneſſe of God, the fall and ſin of man,</hi> the <hi>uſe of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,</hi>
and the <hi>promiſed ſeede,</hi> (the ſumme of their religion) and
moreover performing <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> things appertaining unto
God.<note place="margin">Gen. 4. 26. cap. 5. 22. cap. 6. 8, 9. &amp;c. 8. 20. cap. 9. 25, 26, 27. cap. 18 18, 19 cap. 19 9. cap. 28. 1, 2. cap. 34. 26. cap. 35. 3, 4, 5. Exo. cap. 3. 1. Job cap. 1. 5. cap. 42. 8, 9, 10. <hi>Tho: 22. ae q. 87. ad</hi> 3.</note> This we have delivered concerning <hi>Seth, Enoch, Noah,
Abraham, Lot, Iſaack, Iacob, Iethro, Iob,</hi> others: Now
whither they did this, as any way peculiarly <hi>deſigned unto it as an
Office,</hi> or rather <hi>in obedient duty to the prime Law of Nature,</hi> in
which, and to whoſe performance, many of them were inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
and incouraged, <hi>by divine revelation,</hi> (as ſeemes moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable)
is not neceſſary to be inſiſted on: To me truely it ſeemes
evident, <hi>that thert were no determiuate Miniſters of Divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
before the Law,</hi> For, where finde we any ſuch <hi>Office</hi> inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
where the duties of thoſe <hi>Officers</hi> preſcribed? or were they
of <hi>human</hi> invention? God would never <hi>allow,</hi> that in any regard,
the <hi>wil of the creature</hi> ſhould be <hi>the meaſure of his honour &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi>
but the <hi>right</hi> and exerciſe of the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> ſay ſome was
in the <hi>firſt borne;</hi> but a <hi>proofe</hi> of this will be for ever wanting.
<hi>Abel</hi> was not <hi>Adams eldeſt ſonne,</hi> yet if any thing were peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar
to ſuch an <hi>Office,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jacob Armin. de ſacerd. Ch. orat.</note> it was by him performed, that both the <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi>
carried their <hi>ſacrifices</hi> to their <hi>father,</hi> is a vaine ſurmize:
Who was <hi>Prieſt</hi> then, when <hi>Adam</hi> dyed? neither can any <hi>order
of deſcent</hi> be handſomely <hi>contrived: Noah</hi> had three ſonnes, grant
the <hi>eldeſt</hi> onely a Prieſt; Were the <hi>eldeſt</hi> ſonnes of his other <hi>ſons</hi>
Prieſts or no? If not, how many <hi>men, feareing</hi> God, were ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155115:5"/>
over the face of the <hi>earth,</hi> utterly deprived of the means of
right worſhip; if ſo, there muſt be a new <hi>rule</hi> produced, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
the preſcript of <hi>nature,</hi> whereby a man may be enabled
by <hi>generation</hi> to convey that to <hi>others,</hi> which he hath not in <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:</hi>
I ſpeake not of <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> and his <hi>extraordinary
Prieſthood;</hi> why ſhould any <hi>ſpeak</hi> where the holy ghoſt is <hi>ſilent?</hi>
if we <hi>pretend</hi> to know him, we overthrow the whole <hi>myſtery,</hi>
and run croſſe to the apoſtle, afirming him to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
without father, mother, or genealogie; for ſo <hi>long time</hi> then, as
the greateſt <hi>combination</hi> of men, was in diſtinct <hi>families</hi> (which
ſometimes were very great)<note place="margin">Gen. 14. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Politickes</hi> and <hi>Oeconomicks</hi> being
of the <hi>ſame extent,</hi> all the way of <hi>inſtruction</hi> in the ſervice and
knowledge of God, was by the way of <hi>paternall admonition:</hi>
For the diſcharge of <hi>which duty, Abraham</hi> is commended <hi>Gen.</hi>
18. 19. whereunto the <hi>inſtructers</hi> had no particular <hi>ingagement,</hi>
but only the generall <hi>obligation</hi> of the law of nature; what <hi>rule</hi>
they had, for their <hi>performances</hi> towards God, doth not appeare;
all <hi>poſitive</hi> law, in every <hi>kinde</hi> is ordained for the good of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity:</hi>
that <hi>then being not,</hi> no ſuch <hi>rule</hi> was aſſigned, untill God
gathered a <hi>people,</hi> and lifted up the ſtandard of <hi>circumciſion</hi>
for his ſubjects to repaire unto: the world in the dayes of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
beginning generally to incline to <hi>Idolatry and polutheiſme,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantum. Auguſt. con. Fauſt. lib. 19. cap. 11.</note>
the firſt evident inreconcileable <hi>diviſion</hi> was made betweene <hi>his
people</hi> and the <hi>malignants,</hi> which before lay hid in his <hi>decree, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi>
ſignes and preſcript <hi>rules,</hi> were neceſſary for ſuch a <hi>gathered</hi>
Church: This before I conceive to have been ſupplyed <hi>by ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>law</hi> of <hi>nature</hi> a long time <hi>prevailed</hi> for the worſhip of the
one true <hi>God.</hi> The <hi>manner</hi> of this worſhip, the <hi>generalty</hi> had at
firſt (as may be conceived) from the <hi>vocall inſtruction</hi> of <hi>Adam,</hi> ful
of the <hi>knowledge</hi> of divine things; <hi>this</hi> afterwards their <hi>children</hi>
had from them by <hi>tradition;</hi> helped forward by <hi>ſuch</hi> who recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
particular <hi>revelations</hi> in their generation;<note place="margin">Per incremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta temporum crevit divinae cognitionis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crementum Eſ. Regno. Hom. 16. in Ezek. a med.</note> ſuch as <hi>Noah,</hi> thence
called a <hi>preacher</hi> of <hi>righteouſneſſe:</hi> ſo <hi>knowledge</hi> of Gods will <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed,</hi>
untill <hi>ſinne</hi> quite prevailed, and all <hi>fleſh</hi> corrupted their
wayes; all <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> for the moſt part beginnes in the <hi>will,</hi> which
is more <hi>bruiſed</hi> by the fall, then the <hi>underſtanding. Nature</hi> is
more <hi>corrupted,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>deſire</hi> of good, then the <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:155115:5"/>
of truth; the <hi>knowledge of God</hi> would have flouriſhed longer
in mens <hi>mindes,</hi> had not ſinne baniſhed the <hi>love of God</hi> out of
their hearts. The ſumme is, that before the giving of the Law,
<hi>every one in his owne perſon, ſerved God according to that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
he had of his</hi> Will. <hi>Publike performances were aſſigned to
none, further then the obligation of the law of Nature, to their duty
in their owne familyes.</hi> I have purpoſely omitted to ſpeake of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedocke</hi>
as I ſaid before, having ſpoken all that I <hi>can,</hi> or <hi>dare</hi>
concerning him, on another <hi>occaſion,</hi> Onely this I will <hi>adde,</hi> they
who ſo confidently affirme him to be <hi>Shem,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Noah,</hi>
and to have his Prieſthood in an <hi>ordinary way,</hi> by vertue of his
<hi>Primogeniture,</hi> might have done well to aske leave of the <hi>Holy
Ghoſt,</hi> for the <hi>revealing</hi> of that which he purpoſely concealed, to
ſetforth no ſmall <hi>myſtery,</hi> by them quite overthrowne. And he
who of late makes him <hi>looke</hi> upon <hi>Abraham</hi> and the four <hi>Kings,</hi>
all of his <hi>Poſterity,</hi> fighting for the <hi>Inheritance</hi> of <hi>Canaan;</hi> (of
which cauſe of their quarrell the Scripture is ſilent) robs him at
leaſt of <hi>one</hi> of his <hi>titles, a King of peace;</hi> making him neither,
<hi>King</hi> nor peaceable, but a <hi>bloody Grandſire,</hi> that either <hi>could</hi> not,
or <hi>would</hi> not part his fighting <hi>children,</hi> contending for that
whoſe <hi>right</hi> was in him, to beſtow on whom he would. And
thus was it with them in the adminiſtration of ſacred things:
<hi>There was no divine determination of the Prieſtly office on any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
of men: when things appertaining unto God, were to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in the name of a whole family (as afterwards</hi> 1 Sam. 20. 6.)
<hi>Perhaps the honour of the performance was by conſent given to the
firſt borne: Further, the way of teaching others, was by petarnall
admonition: (ſo</hi> Gen. 18. 19) <hi>motives thereunto, and rules of
their proceeding therein, being the law of nature, and ſpeciall reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.
Preſcription of poſitive law, ordained for the good of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity,
could have no place,, when all ſociety was domeſticall. To
inſtruct others (upon occaſion) wanting inſtruction for their good,
is an undeniable dictate of the firſt principles of nature; obedience
to which, was all the ordinary warrant they had, for preaching to
any beyond their owne families, obſerved by</hi> Lot Gen. 19. 7. <hi>though
his ſermon contained a little falſe doctrine,</hi> ver. 81. <hi>Againe, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
revelation leaves as a great impreſſion on the minde of him to
whom it is made, ſo an effectuall obligation for the performance of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155115:6"/>
what it directeth unto, the Lyon hath roared, who will not fear; the</hi>
Lord God <hi>hath ſpoken who can but propheſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> Amos 3. 8. <hi>And
this was</hi> Noahs <hi>warrant for thoſe performances, from whence he
was called a preacher of righteouſnes,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 5. Thus although
I doe not finde any determinate order of Prieſthood by divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,
yet do I not thence conclude with <hi>Aquin. 12. ae queſt.</hi> 3.
<hi>a</hi> 1 (if I noted right at the reading of it) that all the worſhip of
God, I meane for the manner of it was of humane invention, yea
ſacrifices themſelves: for this Will worſhip as I ſhewed before
God alwayes rejected, no doubt but ſacrifices and the manner of
them were of divine inſtitution, albeit their particular originall,
in regard of precept though not of practice be to us unknowne;
for what in all this concernes us, we may obſerve that <hi>a ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution
of a new ordinance, doth not overthrow</hi> any thing that
went before in the ſame kinde, univerſally <hi>morrall,</hi> or <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary;</hi>
nor at all <hi>change</hi> it, unleſſe by expreſſe <hi>exception,</hi> as by the
introduction of the <hi>ceremoniall law,</hi> the offering of ſacrafices,
which before was <hi>common to all,</hi> was reſtrained to the <hi>poſterity</hi>
of <hi>Levi:</hi> looke then what <hi>performances</hi> in the ſervice of God,
that <hi>primitive houſhold of faith</hi> was in the generall <hi>directed</hi> unto,
by the law of nature, the <hi>ſame</hi> regulated by Goſpel <hi>light</hi> (not
particularly excepted) ought the <hi>generallity</hi> of chriſtians to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme,
which what they were may be collected from what was
fore ſpoken.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the ſame among the Jewes, and of the duty of that people di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct
from their church officers.</head>
               <p>2. COncerning the <hi>Jews</hi> after the giving of <hi>Moſes</hi> law, the <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi>
of God were then <hi>gathered</hi> in <hi>one,</hi> and a <hi>ſtandard</hi> was
ſet up for all his to repaire <hi>unto,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
like a <hi>City</hi> upon a <hi>hill,</hi> conſpicuous to all; and a certaine
<hi>rule</hi> ſet downe for every one to <hi>obſerve</hi> that would approach un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
him: as then before the law we ſought for the manner of Gods
worſhip from the practiſe of men, ſo now ſince the change of the
externall adminiſtration of the covenant, from <hi>the preſcription
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155115:6"/>
of God;</hi> then we <hi>gheſſed</hi> at <hi>what</hi> was <hi>commanded,</hi> by what was
<hi>done; now</hi> at what was <hi>done,</hi> by what was <hi>commanded;</hi> and this
is all the <hi>certainety</hi> we can have in either kinde, though the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
from the <hi>precept,</hi> to the <hi>performance;</hi> and on the <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi>
in this corrupted ſtate of nature, be not of abſolute neceſſity;
onely the difference is, where things are obſcured, it is a ſafer
way to prove the practiſe of men by Gods precept, charitably
ſuppoſing them to have been obedient, then to wreſt the divine
rule to their obſervation; knowing how prone men are to deifie
themſelves, by mixing their inventions with the worſhip of
God: The Adminiſtration of Gods <hi>providence</hi> towards his
Church hath been <hi>various</hi> and the communication of <hi>himſelfe</hi>
unto it, at <hi>ſundry times,</hi> hath been in <hi>divers manners;</hi> eſpecially,
it pleaſed him not to bring it to <hi>perfection</hi> but by degrees,<note place="margin">Marke 4 18.</note> 
                  <hi>as the
earth bringeth forth fruit, firſt the blade, then the eare, then the
full corne in the eare:</hi> thus the <hi>Church</hi> before the giving of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
law, ſeems to have had two maine <hi>defects,</hi> which the Lord at
that time ſupplyed; one in <hi>diſcipline,</hi> or <hi>government,</hi> in that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
family exerciſed the publique worſhip of God within it ſelf
or a part. (though ſome do otherwiſe <hi>conclude</hi> from <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 26.)
which was firſt removed, by <hi>eſtabliſhing</hi> a conſiſtory of Elders,
the other, in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> wanting the <hi>rule of the written word</hi>
being directed by tradition, the manifold <hi>defects</hi> whereof, were
made up, by ſpeciall <hi>revelatition:</hi> to neither of theſe defects
was the Church ſince expoſed: whether there was any thing
<hi>written</hi> before the giving of the <hi>law,</hi> is not worth <hi>contending</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout:
<hi>Auſtine</hi> thought <hi>Enochs</hi> propheſie was written by him;<note place="margin">Aug. de civit. dei. lib 15. cap. 23. Joſeph. Antiq. lib. 1. ca. 3. Sixt. ſenenſ. Bib. lib. 2.</note> propheſie was written by him;
and <hi>Joſephus</hi> afirmes, that there were two pillars erected, one of
<hi>ſtone,</hi> the other of <hi>brick</hi> before the ſtoode, wherein divers things
were <hi>ingraven;</hi> and <hi>Sixtus Senenſis,</hi> that the <hi>booke of the wars
of the Lord</hi> was a volume ancienter then the bookes of <hi>Moſes;</hi>
but the contrary opinion is moſt received, ſo <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> Hom. 1.
in <hi>Mali.</hi> after its giving, none ever doubted of the <hi>perfection of
the written word</hi> for the end to which it was ordained, untill the
Jewes had broached their <hi>Talmud,</hi> to oppoſe <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
their <hi>Traditions,</hi> to advance <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> doubtleſſe the ſole
aime of <hi>the work,</hi> what ever, were the intentions of the <hi>workmen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Lights</hi> which God maketh, are ſufficient to rule the <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:155115:7"/>
for which they are ordained; as, in <hi>creating of the world,</hi>
God made two great <hi>lights,</hi> the <hi>greater light</hi> to rule the <hi>day,</hi> and
the leſſer <hi>light</hi> to rule the <hi>night;</hi> ſo in the erection of the <hi>new
world</hi> of his Church, he ſet up two great <hi>lights,</hi> the <hi>leſſer light</hi>
of the old Teſtament, to guide the <hi>night,</hi> the <hi>darke</hi> ſpace of time
under the <hi>law,</hi> and the <hi>greater light</hi> of the new Teſtament, to
rule the <hi>glorious day</hi> of the Goſpel, and theſe two <hi>lights</hi> do ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<hi>enlighten</hi> every man that commeth into this <hi>new world:</hi>
There is no neede of the falſe fire of tradition, where God ſets
up ſuch glorious <hi>lights.</hi> This be <hi>premiſed,</hi> for the pronaſs of men,
to deflect from the golden <hi>rule,</hi> and heavenly <hi>poleſtarre</hi> in the
inveſtigation of the truth; eſpecially in <hi>things</hi> of this nature, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
which we treat, wherein ordinary <hi>indeavours,</hi> are farre
greater in ſearching after what men <hi>have</hi> done, then what they
<hi>ought</hi> to have done; and when the <hi>fact</hi> is once evidenced, from
the pen of a <hi>Rabbi,</hi> or a <hi>Father,</hi> preſently conclude <hi>the right:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
many, we may take a late <hi>treatiſe</hi> for inſtance, intituled,
<hi>of Religious Aſſemblies and the publike ſervice of God,</hi> whoſe <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>
would preſcribe the <hi>manner</hi> of Gods worſhip among <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi>
from the <hi>cuſtome</hi> of the <hi>Jewes;</hi> and their <hi>obſervations,</hi> he
would prove from the <hi>Rabbines;</hi> not at all taking <hi>notice,</hi> that
from ſuch <hi>obſervances,</hi> they were long agon <hi>recalled,</hi> to the <hi>law
and to the teſtamony.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 6.</note> And afterwards for them ſharply rebuked
by <hi>truth</hi> it ſelfe: doubtleſſe it is a worthy <hi>knowledge</hi> to be <hi>able,</hi>
and a commendable <hi>deligence</hi> to ſearch into thoſe coyners of <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſities,</hi>
but to imbrace the <hi>fancy's</hi> of thoſe wild-heads which
have nothing but <hi>noveltie</hi> to commend them, and to ſeeke their
<hi>impoſition</hi> on others, is but an abaſing of their owne ceiſure and
others <hi>induſtry:</hi> The <hi>iſſue</hi> of ſuch a temper, ſeemes to bee
the greateſt part of that <hi>treatiſe,</hi> which becauſe I wait one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
for ſome <hi>ſpare houres</hi> to demonſtrate in a perticular <hi>tract.</hi>
I ſhall for the <hi>preſent,</hi> omit the handling of <hi>divers things</hi> there
<hi>ſpoken</hi> of, though otherwiſe they might very <hi>opportunately</hi> here
be mentioned. As the <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Prophets,</hi> the <hi>manner</hi>
of gods worſhip in their <hi>Synagogues,</hi> the <hi>originall</hi> and inſtitution
of their latter <hi>teachers,</hi> Scribes and Phariſes, &amp;. And briefly
onely <hi>obſerve</hi> thoſe things, which are moſt immediatly conduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to my <hi>propoſed</hi> ſubject. The <hi>worſhip</hi> of God among them,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155115:7"/>
was either <hi>Morall,</hi> or <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> and <hi>Typicall,</hi> the <hi>perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances</hi>
belonging unto the <hi>latter,</hi> with all things thereunto <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing,</hi>
were appropriated to <hi>them,</hi> whom God had peculiarly
ſet a part for that <hi>purpoſe:</hi> By <hi>Ceromoniall</hi> worſhip, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
all <hi>Sacrifices</hi> and Offerings, the whole ſervice of the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi>
and afterwards of the <hi>Temple:</hi> all which, were <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picall,</hi>
and eſtabliſhed merely for the preſent <hi>diſpenſation,</hi> not
without purpoſe of their <hi>Abrogation,</hi> when that which was to
be more <hi>perfect,</hi> ſhould appear. Now the ſeverall <hi>Officers</hi> with
their diſtinct <hi>employments,</hi> in and about this <hi>Service,</hi> were ſo
punctually <hi>preſcribed,</hi> and limited by Almighty God, that as
<hi>none</hi> of them might <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> without preſumptious impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety,
intrude into the <hi>function</hi> of others, not allotted to them, as
<hi>Numb.</hi> 16. 7, 8, 9, 10. So none of their <hi>Bretheren</hi> might <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume</hi>
to <hi>intrude</hi> into the leaſt part of their <hi>Office,</hi> without mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<hi>ſacriledge. Joſh.</hi> 22. 11, 12. True it is, that there is <hi>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
of divers in the <hi>Scripture</hi> that offered <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> or vowed
ſo to do, who were <hi>Strangers</hi> from the Prieſts <hi>Office,</hi> yea from
the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> as <hi>Jepha. Judges, 11. Manoah, Jud.</hi> 13.
<hi>David, 2. Sam.</hi> 6. And again, 2. <hi>Sam. 24. Solomon, Kings</hi> 3.
and again, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 9. But following our former <hi>rule</hi> of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting,
the <hi>practiſe,</hi> by the <hi>precept,</hi> we may <hi>finde,</hi> (and that true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly)
that all the <hi>expreſions</hi> of their <hi>Offerings</hi> ſignifie no more; but,
they <hi>brought</hi> thoſe things <hi>to be offered,</hi> and <hi>cauſed</hi> the Prieſts to
<hi>do,</hi> what in their owne <hi>perſons</hi> they ought not to <hi>performe.</hi> Now
hence by the way we may <hi>obſerve,</hi> that the <hi>people</hi> of God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the new <hi>Teſtament,</hi> contrary diſtinct from their <hi>Teachers,</hi>
have a greater <hi>intereſt</hi> in the performance of <hi>ſpirituall duties</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
to the worſhip of God, and <hi>more</hi> in that regard is <hi>grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
unto them, and <hi>required</hi> of them, then was of the ancient <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi>
of the Jewes, conſidered as diſtinguiſhed from their <hi>Prieſts,</hi>
becauſe their <hi>duty</hi> is preſcribed unto them under the <hi>notion of
thoſe things</hi> which then, were appropriate onely to the <hi>Prieſts;</hi>
as of <hi>offering incenſe, ſacrifice; oblations,</hi> and the like, which in
their <hi>originall inſtitution</hi> were never <hi>permitted</hi> to the people of
the <hi>Jewes,</hi> but yet tralatitiouſly and by <hi>Analogie</hi> are <hi>injoyned</hi>
to all <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but of theſe afterwards; the main queſtion is,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155115:8"/>
about the <hi>duty</hi> of the people of God, in <hi>performances</hi> for their
owne <hi>edification,</hi> and the extent of their <hi>lawfull undertakings</hi> for
others inſtruction; for the firſt, which is of neareſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
unto themſelves: The ſumme of their duty in this kind
may bee reduced to theſe two heads; Firſt, to <hi>heare the Word
and Law of God read</hi> attentively, eſpecially when it was expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
Secondly, to <hi>meditate</hi> therein themſelves, to ſtudy it day
and night, and to get their ſenſes exerciſed in that rule of their
duty. Concerning each of which, we have both the <hi>precept,</hi> and
the <hi>practiſe,</hi> Gods <hi>command,</hi> and their <hi>performance.</hi> The <hi>one,</hi> in
that injunction given unto the Prieſt, <hi>Daut.</hi> 31. 11, 12, 13.
<hi>When all Iſrael is come to appeare before the Lord thy God, in the
place that hee ſhall chooſe, thou ſhalt reade this Law before all
Iſrael in their hearing: Gather the people together, men, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
and children, and thy ſtranger that is within thy gates, that
they may heare, and that they may learne, and feare the Lord your
God; and that their children which have not knowne may heare
and learne.</hi> All which we find punctually performed on both
ſides, <hi>Nehem. 8. 2, 3, 4, 5. Ezra</hi> the Prieſt ſtanding on a Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit
of wood, read the Law, and gave the meaning of it, and
the <hi>eares of all the people were attentive to the Booke of the Law.</hi>
Which courſe continued untill there was an end put to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances
of that Law; as <hi>Act. 15. 21. Moſes of old time hath
in every Citie them that preach him being read in the Synagogues
every Sabbath day:</hi> On which ground, not receding from their
ancient obſervations, the people aſſembled to heare our Saviour
teaching with authority, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 38. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> divers times
tooke advantage of their <hi>ordinary aſſemblies</hi> to preach the Goſpel
unto them. For the other, which concernes their own ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
into the Law, and ſtudying of the Word wee have a ſtrict
command, <hi>Deut. 6. 6, 7, 8, 9. And theſe words which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
thee this day ſhall bee in thy heart, and thou ſhalt teach them
diligently unto thy children, and ſhalt talke of them when thou ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
in thy houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou
lyeſt down, and when thou riſeſt up, and thou ſhalt bind them for a
ſign upon thy hand, &amp; they ſhal be as front lets between thine eyes, &amp;
thou ſhalt write them upon the poſts of thy houſe &amp; upon thy gates:</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:155115:8"/>
which ſtrict charge is again repeated, <hi>cap.</hi> 11. 18. ſummarily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending
<hi>all wayes whereby they might become exerciſed in the
Law:</hi> Now becauſe this charge is in particular given to the
<hi>King, Chap. 17. verſ.</hi> 18, 19. The <hi>performance</hi> of a <hi>King</hi> in
obedience thereunto, will give us light enough into the <hi>practiſe</hi>
of the people: And this we have in that moſt excellent Pſalme
of <hi>David,</hi> viz. 119. which for the moſt part, is ſpent in petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
for <hi>light, direction,</hi> and <hi>aſſistance</hi> in that <hi>ſtudy,</hi> in expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of the performance of this <hi>duty,</hi> and in ſpirituall glorying of
his ſucceſſe, in his divine <hi>Meditations:</hi> eſpecially <hi>verſ.</hi> 99. hee
aſcribeth his <hi>proficiency in heavenly wiſedome and underſtanding
above his teachers,</hi> not to any ſpeciall revelation, not to that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall
light wherewith he was endued (which indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting
in a tranſient irradiation of the mind, being a ſupernaturall
impulſion commenſurate to ſuch things as are connaturall onely
unto God, doth of it ſelfe give neither wiſedome nor underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing)
but unto his <hi>ſtuddy in the teſtimonies</hi> of God. The <hi>bleſſings</hi>
pronounced upon, and <hi>promiſes</hi> annexed to the performance of
this <hi>duty,</hi> concerne not the matter in hand: only from the words
wherein the former <hi>command</hi> is delivered, two things may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,
1. That the <hi>paternall teaching</hi> and inſtruction of families
in things which appertaine to God, being a <hi>duty</hi> of the Law of
<hi>Nature,</hi> remained in its <hi>full vigor,</hi> and was not at all impaired,
by the <hi>inſtitution</hi> of a new order of <hi>Teachers</hi> for aſſemblies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
domeſticall then eſtabliſhed: Neither without doubt
ought it to <hi>ceaſe</hi> amongſt Chriſtians, there being no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
why <hi>now</hi> it <hi>ſhould,</hi> but that, which <hi>then</hi> was not effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the <hi>people of God,</hi> were not onely <hi>permitted,</hi>
but <hi>enjoyned</hi> alſo, to <hi>reads</hi> the Scriptures, and upon all <hi>occaſions,</hi>
in their owne <hi>houſes,</hi> and elſe-where, to <hi>talke</hi> of them, or <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate</hi>
their knowledge in them, unto <hi>others:</hi> There had
been <hi>then,</hi> no <hi>Councell at Trent</hi> to forbid the one, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
was there any <hi>ſtrict Canon,</hi> to bring the other with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
the compaſſe of a Conventicle: But now for the <hi>ſolemne
publique teaching</hi> and inſtructing of others, it was <hi>otherwiſe</hi>
ordained, for this was committed to <hi>them</hi> in regard of <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:155115:9"/>
performance, who were <hi>ſet apart by</hi> GOD; as for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
before named: ſo alſo for that purpoſe, the <hi>Author</hi> of the
Treatiſe I before <hi>mentioned,</hi> concludeth that the people were not
taught at the <hi>publike aſſemblies</hi> by Prieſts, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> that is, teaching
the people was no part of their <hi>office</hi> or <hi>duty:</hi> but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
that ſeems to be a mans <hi>duty</hi> in the ſervice or worſhip of God,
which God <hi>requires</hi> of him, and that appertain to his <hi>office</hi> whoſe
performance is expreſſely <hi>enjoyned</hi> unto him, as ſuch, And for
whoſe <hi>neglect,</hi> hee is <hi>rebuked</hi> or <hi>puniſhed:</hi> now all this wee find
concerning the Prieſts <hi>publike teaching</hi> of the people: for the <hi>prof</hi>
of which the recitall of a few <hi>pertinent</hi> places ſhal ſuffice, <hi>Levit.</hi>
10. 11. we have an injunction laid upon <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes, <hi>to
teach the children of Iſrael all the ſtatutes that the Lord had ſpoken
to them by the hand of Moſes.</hi> And of the Levites it is affirmed,
<hi>Deut. 33. 10. They ſhall teach Jacob thy ſtatutes, and Iſrael thy
Law.</hi> Now though ſome reſtraine theſe places to the <hi>diſcerning
of leproſies,</hi> and <hi>between holy</hi> and <hi>unholy,</hi> with their <hi>determination
of difficulty emergent</hi> out of the Law, yet this no way impaires
the truth of that I <hi>intend</hi> to prove by them for even, <hi>thoſe things,</hi>
belonged to that kind of publike <hi>teaching,</hi> which was neceſſary
under that adminiſtration of the <hi>Covenant:</hi> but in ſtead of many,
I will name <hi>one</hi> not lyable to exception: <hi>Mil. 2. 7. The Prieſts
lips ſhould preſerve knowledge, and they ſhould ſeeke the Law
at his mouth, for he is the meſſenger of the Lord of Hosts:</hi> where
both a recitall of his own duty, <hi>that</hi> he <hi>ſhould be full of knowledge</hi>
to inſtruct, the intimation of the people, that they <hi>ſhould ſeeke
unto him,</hi> or give heed to his teaching with the <hi>reaſon</hi> of them
both, for he is the Lords meſſenger, (one of the higheſt titles of
the Miniſters of the Goſpell performing the ſame office) doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly
<hi>confirme,</hi> that <hi>inſtructing</hi> of the people in the <hi>morall</hi>
worſhip of God, was a duty of the Prieſtly <hi>office,</hi> or of <hi>the Prieſts
as ſuch.</hi> Eſpecially conſidering the effect of this <hi>teaching</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
<hi>verſ.</hi> 9. the <hi>turning of many from their iniquitie.</hi> The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
end of <hi>teaching in aſſemblies:</hi> all which we find <hi>exactly</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>performed
by an excellent Prieſt, <hi>preaching</hi> to the people on a
<hi>Pulpit</hi> of wood: <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8. 5, 6, 7, 8. Further, for a neglect
of <hi>this,</hi> the Prieſts are <hi>threatned</hi> with rejection from their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155115:9"/>
                  <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4. 6. Now it doth not ſeeme <hi>juſtice,</hi> that a man
ſhould be put out of his <hi>office,</hi> for a <hi>neglect</hi> of that, whoſe <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance</hi>
doth not belong unto <hi>it;</hi> the <hi>fault</hi> of every neglect,
<hi>ariſeth</hi> from the deſcription of a <hi>duty:</hi> untill <hi>ſomething</hi> then of
more <hi>force,</hi> then any thing as yet I have <hi>ſeene,</hi> bee objected to
the <hi>contrary,</hi> we may take it for granted, <hi>That the teaching of
the people under the Law, in publique aſſemblies, was performed
ordinarily by the Prieſts, as belonging to their duty, and office.</hi>
Men indued with <hi>gifts ſupernaturall, extraordinarily</hi> called,
and <hi>immediately</hi> ſent by God himſelfe, for the <hi>inſtruction</hi> of
his people, the <hi>reformation</hi> of his Church, and <hi>fore-telling things</hi>
to come, ſuch as were the <hi>Prophets,</hi> who when ever they met
with <hi>oppoſition,</hi> ſtaid themſelves upon their <hi>extraordinary</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
come not within the <hi>compaſſe</hi> of my diſquiſition. The <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi>
alſo of the Schooles of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> the <hi>employment</hi>
of the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of the Prophets, the <hi>originall</hi> of the <hi>Scribes,</hi> and
thoſe other <hi>poſſeſſours</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> Chaire in our Saviours <hi>time,</hi>
wherein hee <hi>converſed</hi> here below, being neceſſarily to be <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi>
in my <hi>Obſervations</hi> on the fore-named Treatiſe, I ſhall
omit untill more <hi>leiſure,</hi> and an enjoyment of the ſmall <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder</hi>
of my poore <hi>Library,</hi> ſhall better enable me. For the
<hi>preſent,</hi> becauſe treating in <hi>cauſa facili,</hi> although <hi>writing</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<hi>bookes,</hi> I hope I am not beſides the <hi>Truth:</hi> the Booke of
<hi>Truth,</hi> praiſed bee GOD, is eaſie to bee <hi>obtained,</hi> and GOD is
not tyed to <hi>meanes,</hi> in diſcovering the <hi>truth</hi> of that Booke.
Come we then, to the <hi>conſideration</hi> of what <hi>duty</hi> in the <hi>ſervice</hi>
of GOD, beyond thoſe belonging unto ſeverall <hi>families,</hi> were
permitted to any of the <hi>people,</hi> not peculiarly ſet <hi>apart</hi> for ſuch
a purpoſe. The <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> part of Gods worſhip, as we ſaw
before, was ſo <hi>appropriate</hi> to the Prieſts, that God uſually <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged</hi>
the trangreſſion of that <hi>ordinance,</hi> very ſeverely, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples
of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> are dreadfull teſtimonies of his
wrath in that kind:<note place="margin">2 Chr. 26. 19. caſt him out, Joh. 9.</note> It was an unalterable <hi>law,</hi> by vertue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
the <hi>Priests</hi> excommunicated that preſumptuous <hi>King.</hi> For
that whch we chiefly <hi>intend</hi> the publique <hi>teaching</hi> of others, as
to <hi>ſome</hi> it was enjoyned, as an act of their <hi>duty,</hi> ſo it might at
<hi>first</hi> ſeeme, that it was <hi>permitted</hi> to all, who having <hi>ability</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:155115:10"/>
thereunto, were called by <hi>charity</hi> or <hi>neceſſitie;</hi> So the <hi>Princes</hi>
of <hi>Jehoſhaphat taught</hi> the people out of the Law of God, as
well as the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and Levites, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17. 7, 8, 9, 10. ſo alſo
<hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and others of the <hi>chiefe</hi> of the people are reckoned
among them who <hi>taught</hi> the people, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8. and afterwards,
when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> at any time entred into their <hi>Synagogues;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 13. 15.</note>
they never <hi>questioned</hi> any thing but his <hi>abilities,</hi> if he had any
word of <hi>Exhortation</hi> to the people he might <hi>ſay on:</hi> and the
<hi>Scribes</hi> queſtioning the <hi>authoritie</hi> of our Saviour for his <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
were moved to <hi>it,</hi> not becauſe he <hi>taught,</hi> but becauſe he
taught <hi>ſo,</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> things, with authoritie, and againſt their <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,</hi>
otherwiſe they rather troubled <hi>themſelves,</hi> to thinke
how he ſhould become <hi>able to teach: Mark</hi> 6. 2, 3. then <hi>him,</hi>
becauſe he <hi>did:</hi> there are indeed many ſharpe <hi>reproofes</hi> in the old
<hi>Testament</hi> of thoſe who undertooke to be Gods Meſſengers
without his warrant, as <hi>Jerem. 23. 21, 22. I have not ſent theſe
Prophets, yet they ran: I have not ſpoken to them, yet they
propheſied. But if they had ſtood in my counſell,</hi> &amp;c. to <hi>which,</hi> and
the like places it may <hi>ſatisfactorily</hi> be anſwered, that howſoever
by the way of <hi>analogie,</hi> they may be drawn into <hi>rule,</hi> for theſe
<hi>times</hi> of the Goſpel, yet they were ſpoken only in <hi>reference</hi> to
<hi>them</hi> who falſly <hi>pretended</hi> to extraordinary <hi>revelations,</hi> and a
power of <hi>foretelling</hi> things to come: whom the Lord <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned</hi>
his people of, and appointed <hi>puniſhments</hi> for them,
<hi>Deut.</hi> 13. with which ſort of <hi>pretenders</hi> that nation was ever
<hi>repleniſhed,</hi> for <hi>which</hi> the very <hi>heathen</hi> often derided them: <hi>he,</hi>
who makes it his <hi>employment,</hi> to counterfeit Gods <hi>diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
had then no more glorious worke to <hi>imitate</hi> then that of
<hi>propheſie,</hi> wherein he was not <hi>idle:</hi> yet notwithſtanding all
<hi>this,</hi> I doe not conceive the former <hi>diſcourſe</hi> to be punctually
<hi>true</hi> in the <hi>latitude</hi> thereof: as though it were <hi>permitted</hi> to <hi>all</hi>
men, or <hi>any</hi> men, beſides the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and Prophets to teach <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely</hi>
at <hi>all</hi> times, and in <hi>all</hi> eſtates of that Church. Only I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
that the uſuall <hi>anſwers</hi> given to the fore-cited places, when
objected, are not <hi>ſufficient:</hi> take an inſtance in <hi>one, 2 Chro.</hi> 17. of
the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> teaching with the Prieſts: the Author
of the book before <hi>intimated,</hi> conceives that neither <hi>Prieſts</hi> nor
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155115:10"/>
                  <hi>Princes</hi> taught at all in that way we now treat of, but only that
the <hi>Prieſts</hi> rode <hi>circuit</hi> to adminiſter <hi>judgement,</hi> and had the
<hi>Princes</hi> with them to do <hi>execution;</hi> but this interpretation he
borroweth only to confirme his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that <hi>priests</hi> did
not teach as <hi>ſuch,</hi> the very circumſtance of the <hi>place</hi> inforces a
contrary <hi>ſence;</hi> and in the 19. Chap. there is expreſſe <hi>mention</hi> of
appointing <hi>Judges</hi> for the <hi>determination</hi> of civill <hi>cauſes</hi> in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<hi>City,</hi> which evidently was a <hi>diſtinct</hi> work diſtinguiſhed from
that <hi>mentioned</hi> in this place: &amp; upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the like ground I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceive it to
be no <hi>intimation</hi> of a moveable Sanedrim, <hi>which</hi> although of ſuch
a mixt conſtitution, yet was not <hi>itinerant,</hi> and is mentioned in
that other <hi>place:</hi> neither is that other <hi>ordinary gloſſe</hi> more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable,
they were ſent to <hi>teach,</hi> that is to <hi>countenance</hi> the teaching
of the Law; a <hi>duty</hi> which ſeldome implores the <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<hi>countenance,</hi> and if for the preſent it <hi>did,</hi> the Kings <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>
commanding it was of more value then the <hi>preſence</hi> of the
<hi>Princes.</hi> Beſides, there is nothing in the <hi>Text,</hi> nor the <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi>
thereof, which ſhould hold out this <hi>ſence</hi> unto us; neither
do we <hi>find</hi> any other <hi>rule,</hi> precept or practiſe, whoſe <hi>analogie</hi>
might lead us to ſuch an <hi>interpretation:</hi> that, which to me <hi>ſeemes</hi>
to come neereſt the <hi>truth</hi> is that they <hi>taught</hi> alſo, not in a <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall</hi>
way, like the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and Levites, but <hi>imperially,</hi> and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<hi>declaring</hi> the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the Law, the <hi>offences</hi> againſt it, and
the <hi>puniſhments</hi> due to ſuch offences; eſpecially in as much as they
had reference to the peace of the common-wealth: which <hi>differs</hi>
not much from that which I <hi>reſt</hi> upon, to wit, that in a <hi>collapſed</hi>
and corrupted <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> when the <hi>ordinary</hi> teachers
are either utterly <hi>ignorant</hi> and cannot, or <hi>negligent</hi> and will not
performe their <hi>duty, gifts</hi> in any one to be a <hi>teacher,</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi>
in others by him to be <hi>taught,</hi> are a ſufficient <hi>warrant</hi> for the
performance of it: and then this, the <hi>places</hi> cited out of the old
Teſtament <hi>prove</hi> no more. For the <hi>proceedings</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> in the
<hi>Synagogues,</hi> their great <hi>want</hi> of teaching (being a people before
forſaken of the Spirit &amp; then withering) might be a <hi>warrant</hi> for
them to <hi>deſire</hi> it, and his <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> miſſion for him to do it; It
doth not then at <hi>all</hi> from hence <hi>appear,</hi> that there was <hi>then</hi> any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
of teaching in publike <hi>aſſemblies</hi> granted <hi>unto,</hi> or aſſumed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155115:11"/>
                  <hi>by</hi> any in ſuch an <hi>eſtate</hi> of the Church, as wherein it <hi>ought</hi> to be:
when indeed it is <hi>ruinouſly</hi> declining every <hi>one</hi> of Gods ſervants
hath a <hi>ſufficient warrant</hi> to helpe or prevent the <hi>fall:</hi> this <hi>lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
being but a <hi>common</hi> duty of <hi>zeale</hi> and charitie, the former
an <hi>Authoritative</hi> act of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> the Miniſter whereof
is onely an inſtrumentall <hi>agent,</hi> that from whence it hath its <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy,</hi>
reſiding in another, in whoſe <hi>ſtead,</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 19, 20.)
and under whoſe <hi>perſon</hi> it is done. Now who ever <hi>doth</hi> any
thing in anothers <hi>ſtead,</hi> not by expreſſe <hi>patent</hi> from him, is a
plaine <hi>impoſtor;</hi> and a grant of this <hi>nature</hi> made unto <hi>all</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
doth not <hi>appeare.</hi> I am bold to ſpeake of <hi>theſe things</hi> under
the notion of the <hi>keyes,</hi> though in the time of the <hi>Law;</hi> for I
cannot <hi>aſſent</hi> to thoſe <hi>Schoole-men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aquin. Durand.</note> who will not <hi>allow</hi> that the
<hi>keyes</hi> in any ſenſe, were <hi>granted</hi> to the legall <hi>Prieſts;</hi> their <hi>power</hi>
of teaching, <hi>diſcerning, judging,</hi> receiving in, and caſting out,
<hi>import</hi> the <hi>thing,</hi> though the <hi>name</hi> (no more then that of <hi>reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num
coelorum,</hi> as <hi>Hierom</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerve) be not to
bee <hi>found</hi> in the <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament. And doubtleſſe God <hi>ratified</hi>
the execution of his owne <hi>ordinances</hi> in heaven, <hi>then,</hi> as well
as <hi>now: What the immediate effect of their ſervices was,</hi> how
far <hi>by their own force</hi> they reached,<note place="margin">Tractatu de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotio Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, contra Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min Socini: &amp; Papiſtas, non. dum edito.</note> and what they <hi>typified,</hi> how in
<hi>ſignification</hi> onely, and not <hi>immediatly</hi> they extended to an <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi>
into, and <hi>excluſion</hi> from the <hi>heavenly</hi> Tabernacle, and
wherein lyes the <hi>ſecret power</hi> of Goſpell <hi>commiſſions beyond</hi>
theirs to attaine the ultimate end, I have declared elſe-where.</p>
               <p>Thus much of what the ancient <hi>people of God</hi> diſtinguiſhed
from their <hi>Prieſts</hi> might <hi>not doe,</hi> now briefely of what they
<hi>might,</hi> or rather of what they <hi>ought,</hi> and what their obedience
and profeſſion <hi>declared,</hi> that they thought themſelves <hi>obliged</hi>
unto: private exhortations, rebukings, and ſuch <hi>dictates of the
law of Nature</hi> being preſuppoſed; we find them further, <hi>ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
often one to another,</hi> of thoſe things which concerned the
feare, and worſhip of the Lord, <hi>Malac.</hi> 3. 16. by their lips <hi>fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
many with wiſedome,</hi> Prov. 10. 21. <hi>Diſcourſing</hi> of Gods
Lawes upon all occaſions, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 6, 7, 8. By <hi>multitudes encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging
each other</hi> to the ſervice of God, <hi>Zach. 8. 20, 21. Iſa.</hi> 2. 3.
<hi>joyntly praiſing God</hi> with chearefull hearts. <hi>Pſalm. 42. 4. Giving
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155115:11"/>
and receiving</hi> mutuall conſolation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. 14. and all this, with
much more of the ſame nature, at their meetings, either <hi>occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi>
or for that purpoſe <hi>indicted.</hi> Alwayes provided, that they ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained
from <hi>fingring the Arke,</hi> or medling with thoſe things
which were <hi>appropriated</hi> to the office of the <hi>Prieſts:</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
them hitherto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3.</head>
               <head type="sub">Containing a digreſſion concerning the name of Priests, the right
of Chriſtians thereunto by their intereſt in the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
of Chriſt, with the preſumption of any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
appropriating it to themſelves.</head>
               <p>ANd now the <hi>tranſaction</hi> of theſe <hi>things,</hi> in the Chriſtian
<hi>Church,</hi> preſents it ſelfe, to our conſideration; in hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
whereof, I ſhall not at all <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> concerning the <hi>ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
Church Officers</hi> inſtituted by Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
for the <hi>edification</hi> of his <hi>body:</hi> nor concerning the <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi>
between <hi>them,</hi> who were partakers <hi>at first</hi> of an <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary</hi>
vocation, and <hi>thoſe</hi> who ſince have been <hi>called</hi> to the
ſame work in an ordinary <hi>manner,</hi> divinely <hi>appointed</hi> for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
of the Church: neither yet doth that <hi>diverſity</hi> of the
adminiſtration of <hi>government</hi> in the Churches, <hi>then</hi> when they
were under the <hi>plenitude</hi> of Apoſtolicall <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>now</hi> when
they follow <hi>rules</hi> preſcribed for their <hi>reiglement,</hi> come in my
way.</p>
               <p>Further, Who are the <hi>ſubject</hi> of the <hi>keyes</hi> in whom all that
ſecondary <hi>eccleſiaſticall</hi> power, which is committed to <hi>men</hi>
doth <hi>reſide,</hi> after the <hi>determination</hi> of ſo many learned men,
by cleere Scripture <hi>light,</hi> ſhall not by <hi>me</hi> be called in queſtion:
All theſe though conducing to the <hi>buſineſſe</hi> in hand, would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
a large <hi>diſcuſſion,</hi> and ſuch a Scholaſticall <hi>handling,</hi> as
would make it an inconſutilous <hi>piece,</hi> of this popular diſcourſe:
my intent being only to <hi>ſhew, that ſeeing there are, as all acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
ſome under the New Teſtament, as well as the old, pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly
ſet apart by Gods own appointment for the administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of Chriſts ordinances, eſpecially teaching of others by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
of the Goſpell, in the way of office and duty, what remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155115:12"/>
for the reſt of Gods people to doe, for their own and others
edification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here before I enter <hi>directly</hi> upon the matter, I muſt <hi>remove</hi>
one <hi>ſtone</hi> of offence, concerning the common <hi>apellation</hi> of thoſe
who are ſet apart for the <hi>preaching</hi> of the Goſpell: that which is
moſt <hi>frequently</hi> uſed for them in the New Teſtament is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo
1 <hi>Cor. 3. 5. 2 Cor.</hi> 3. 6. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. 4. and 11. 15, 23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi>
4. 6. and in divers other places; to which adde <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
41. a word though of another <hi>originall,</hi> yet of the ſame <hi>ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi>
with the former: &amp; both rightly tranſlated <hi>Miniſters:</hi> the
names of <hi>Ambaſſadours, Stewards</hi> and the like, wherewith they
are often <hi>honoured</hi> are figurative, &amp; <hi>given</hi> unto them, by <hi>alluſion</hi>
only, that the <hi>former</hi> belonged unto them, and were <hi>proper</hi> for
them, none ever <hi>denied</hi> but ſome <hi>Rabſhakes</hi> of Antichriſt; another
<hi>name</hi> there is, which ſome have <hi>aſſumed</hi> unto themſelves, as an
<hi>honour,</hi> and others have <hi>impoſed</hi> the ſame upon them for a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch:</hi>
viz. that of Prieſt, which to the <hi>takers</hi> ſeemed to <hi>import</hi> a
more <hi>myſterious</hi> imployment, a greater <hi>advancement</hi> above
the reſt of their <hi>brethren,</hi> a neerer <hi>approach</hi> unto God, in the
performances of their <hi>office,</hi> then that of <hi>Miniſters:</hi> wherefore
they <hi>embraced</hi> it, either <hi>voluntarily,</hi> alluding to the <hi>ſervice</hi> of
God and the adminiſtration <hi>thereof</hi> amongſt his antient <hi>people</hi>
the <hi>Jewes,</hi> or <hi>thought</hi> that they ought <hi>neceſſarily</hi> to undergoe
it, as <hi>belonging</hi> properly to them, who are to <hi>celebrate</hi> thoſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries,
and offer thoſe <hi>ſacrifices,</hi> which they imagined, were to
them preſcribed: the <hi>impoſers</hi> on the contrary, pretend divers
<hi>reaſons</hi> why now that <hi>name</hi> can ſignifie none but <hi>men rejected</hi>
from Gods work, and given up to <hi>ſuperstitious</hi> vanities; atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
in their <hi>minds,</hi> the old <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>Baal,</hi> and the now <hi>ſhave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi>
of Antichriſt: it was a new <hi>Etimologie</hi> of this name,
which that learned man <hi>cleaved</hi> unto, who unhappily was <hi>inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi>
into the defence of ſuch <hi>errours,</hi> as he could not but <hi>ſee,</hi> and
did often <hi>confeſſe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hook: eccleſ. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit lib 5. Whitgift. anſ. to the Admon.</note> To which alſo he, he had an <hi>entrance</hi> made by
an Arch-biſhop; to wit, that it was but an <hi>abbreviation</hi> of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,
knowing full well, not only that the <hi>ſignification</hi> of theſe
words, is divers amongſt <hi>them,</hi> to whom belongs <hi>jus &amp; norma
loquendi,</hi> but <hi>alſo,</hi> that they are <hi>widely</hi> different in holy <hi>writ.</hi> Yea
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155115:12"/>
farther, that thoſe who firſt <hi>dignified</hi> themſelves with this <hi>title,</hi>
never called themſelves <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> by way of <hi>distinction</hi> from
the people, but only to have a <hi>note</hi> of diſtance among <hi>themſelvs:</hi>
there being <hi>more</hi> then one <hi>ſort</hi> of them that were <hi>ſacrificers,</hi> and
which <hi>eo nomine,</hi> accounted themſelves <hi>Priests:</hi> ſetting aſide
then all ſuch <hi>evaſions</hi> and diſtinctions as the <hi>people</hi> of God are
not bound to take <hi>notice</hi> of, and taking the <hi>word</hi> in its ordinary
<hi>acceptation,</hi> I ſhall briefly declare, what I conceive of the uſe
thereof, in reſpect of <hi>them,</hi> who are <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpell:
which I ſhall labour to <hi>cleare</hi> by theſe following obſervations:</p>
               <p>1. All faithfull <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpell, in as much as they
are <hi>ingrafted</hi> into Chriſt, and are true <hi>believers,</hi> may, as all other
true <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> be called <hi>Prieſts:</hi> but <hi>this</hi> inaſmuch as they are
<hi>members</hi> of Chriſt, not <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpell: it <hi>reſpecteth</hi>
their <hi>perſons,</hi> not their <hi>function,</hi> or not them as <hi>ſuch:</hi> now I
conceive it may give ſome <hi>light</hi> to this <hi>diſcourſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 1. 6. &amp; 5. 10. &amp; 20. 6. 1 Pet. 2. 5. &amp;c.</note> if we conſider
the <hi>grounds</hi> and reaſons of this <hi>metaphoricall</hi> appellation, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
places of the <hi>Gospell,</hi> aſcribed to the <hi>worſhippers</hi> of Chriſt;
and how the <hi>analogie,</hi> which the preſent <hi>dispenſation</hi> holds with
what was <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> under the adminiſtration of the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi>
may take <hi>place:</hi> for there we find the <hi>Lord</hi> thus beſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
his <hi>people,</hi> ye <hi>ſhall be unto me a kingdome of Prieſts, an
holy nation,</hi> Exod. 19. 6. ſo that it ſhould ſeeme that there was
then a twofold <hi>Priesthood:</hi> a <hi>rituall</hi> Prieſthood, conferred
upon the tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> and a <hi>royall</hi> Prieſthood, belonging to the
whole <hi>people:</hi> the <hi>first</hi> is quite <hi>abrogated</hi> and ſwallowed up in
the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> of Chriſt, the <hi>other,</hi> is put over unto us under the
<hi>Goſpell,</hi> being <hi>aſcribed</hi> to <hi>them</hi> and <hi>us,</hi> and every <hi>one</hi> in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
with God, not <hi>directly</hi> and properly, as <hi>denoting</hi> the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<hi>peculiarly</hi> ſo ca<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>led, but <hi>comparatively</hi> with reference had
to <hi>them</hi> that are without; for as thoſe who were <hi>properly</hi> called
Prieſts, had a neerer <hi>acceſſe</hi> unto God, then the reſt of the <hi>people,</hi>
eſpecially in his <hi>ſolemne</hi> worſhip, ſo all the people that are in <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi>
with God, have ſuch an <hi>approximatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> unto him by vertue
thereof, in <hi>compariſon</hi> of them that are <hi>without,</hi> that in <hi>reſpect
thereof,</hi> they are ſaid to be <hi>Priſts:</hi> now the outward <hi>covenant</hi>
made with <hi>them,</hi> who were the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> after the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155115:13"/>
fleſh, was <hi>repreſentative</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> of grace made with the
children of <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and that whole <hi>people</hi> typified the hidden
<hi>elect</hi> people of God; ſo that of both there is the ſame reaſon. Thus
as <hi>the Prieſts the ſons of Levi are ſaid to come neere unto God,
Deut.</hi> 21. 5. and God tels them that <hi>him whom he hath choſen, he
will cauſe to come neere unto him, Numb.</hi> 16. 5. choſen by a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
calling <hi>ad munus</hi> to the office of the <hi>rituall</hi> prieſthood: ſo
in regard of that other kind, <hi>comparatively</hi> ſo called, it is ſaid of
the <hi>whole people, What nation is there ſo great that hath God ſo</hi>
nigh <hi>unto them, as the Lord our God is in all things that we call
upon him for, Deut.</hi> 4. 7. their approaching <hi>nigh</hi> unto God made
them all a nation of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> in <hi>compariſon</hi> of thoſe dogs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean
<hi>Gentiles</hi> that were out of the <hi>Covenant:</hi> now this <hi>Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative</hi>
is often appropriate to the <hi>faithful</hi> in the new Teſtament:
for <hi>through Chriſt we have an</hi> acceſſe <hi>by one ſpirit unto the Lord,
Eph.</hi> 2. 18. &amp; 3. 19. <hi>We have boldneſſe &amp;</hi> acceſſe <hi>with confidence:</hi>
ſo <hi>James 4. 8. Draw</hi> nigh <hi>unto God, and he will draw nigh unto
you:</hi> which acceſſe and <hi>approximation</hi> unto God, ſeemed as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
was ſpoken to be uttered in <hi>alluſion</hi> to the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the old
Law, who had this <hi>Priviledge</hi> above others in the <hi>publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi>
in which reſpect <hi>only</hi> things <hi>then</hi> were typicall. Since be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
we enjoy that prerogative in the <hi>truth</hi> of the thing it ſelfe;
which they had onely in <hi>type,</hi> we alſo are called <hi>Prieſts:</hi> and as
<hi>they</hi> were ſaid to draw <hi>nigh</hi> in reference to the reſt of the <hi>people;</hi>
ſo <hi>we,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>them,</hi> who are ſtrangers to the <hi>Covenant:</hi> that
<hi>now</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>afarre</hi> off, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 17. and <hi>hereafter</hi> ſhall be
<hi>without,</hi> for <hi>without are dogs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 15. thus this <hi>metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall</hi>
appellation of <hi>Prieſts</hi> is in the firſt place an intimation of
that tranſcendent priviledge of grace and favour, which <hi>Jeſus
Chriſt</hi> hath purchaſed for every one that is ſanctified with the
bloud of the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. We have an intereſt in this appellation of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> by vertue of
our <hi>union with Chriſt,</hi> being one with our <hi>high Prieſt,</hi> we alſo are
<hi>Priests:</hi> there is a twofold <hi>union</hi> between Chriſt &amp; us: the <hi>one,</hi> by
<hi>his</hi> taking upon him <hi>our nature,</hi> the <hi>other,</hi> by beſtowing on <hi>us</hi>
his <hi>Spirit:</hi> for as in <hi>his Incarnation</hi> he took upon him <hi>our</hi> fleſh
and bloud by the work of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſo in <hi>our regeneration</hi> he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155115:13"/>
beſtoweth on <hi>us</hi> his fleſh and blood, by the operation of the
ſame <hi>ſpirit:</hi> yea ſo <hi>ſtrict</hi> is this latter <hi>union,</hi> which we have with
Chriſt, that as the <hi>former</hi> is truly ſaid to be a union of two <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi>
into one <hi>perſon,</hi> ſo <hi>this,</hi> of many <hi>perſons</hi> into one <hi>nature;</hi> for
by <hi>it,</hi> we are made <hi>partakers of the divine nature,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 4. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming
<hi>members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bones,</hi> Epheſ. 5. 30.
we are ſo parts of <hi>him,</hi> of his myſticall body, that <hi>we</hi> and <hi>he</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<hi>thereby</hi> as it were <hi>one</hi> Chriſt; <hi>for as the body is one, and hath
many members, and all the members of that one body being many,
are one body, ſo is Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 12. and the ground of this is,
becauſe the ſame <hi>ſpirit</hi> is in <hi>him</hi> and <hi>us;</hi> in <hi>him</hi> indeed dwelleth
the <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of it, when it is beſtowed upon us, onely by <hi>meaſure:</hi>
but yet it is ſtill the <hi>ſame ſpirit;</hi> and ſo makes <hi>us,</hi> according to his
own prayer, <hi>one with him:</hi> as the <hi>ſoul</hi> of man being <hi>one,</hi> makes
the whole <hi>body</hi> with it, to be but <hi>one</hi> man; <hi>two</hi> men cannot be
<hi>one,</hi> becauſe they have <hi>two ſouls;</hi> no more could <hi>we</hi> be <hi>one</hi> with
Chriſt, were it not the <hi>ſame</hi> ſpirit in <hi>him</hi> and <hi>us:</hi> now let a <hi>man</hi>
be never ſo big or <hi>tall,</hi> that his <hi>feet</hi> reſt upon the <hi>earth,</hi> and his
<hi>head</hi> reach to <hi>heaven,</hi> yet having but <hi>one ſoul,</hi> he is ſtill but <hi>one
man:</hi> now though Chriſt for the <hi>preſent,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>
aſſumed, be never ſo far <hi>remote</hi> and <hi>diſtant</hi> from us in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
yet by the effectuall <hi>energie,</hi> and inhabitation of the <hi>ſame
spirit, he</hi> is ſtill the <hi>head</hi> of that one <hi>body,</hi> whereof <hi>we</hi> are <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi>
ſtill but <hi>one</hi> with <hi>us.</hi> Hence ariſeth to us a twofold <hi>right</hi> to
the title of <hi>Prieſts;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. Becauſe being in <hi>him,</hi> and members <hi>of him, we</hi> are account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to have done, <hi>in him,</hi> and <hi>with him,</hi> whatſoever <hi>he</hi> hath done
for <hi>us;</hi> we are <hi>buried</hi> with Chriſt, Rom. 6. 4. <hi>dead</hi> with him, v. 8.
<hi>quickned</hi> together with Chriſt, Epheſ. 2. 5. being raiſed up, we
<hi>ſit together with him in heavenly places,</hi> v. 6. <hi>riſen</hi> with him, Coloſ.
3. 1. now all theſe in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> were in ſome ſence <hi>Sacerdotall;</hi>
wherefore we having an intereſt in <hi>their</hi> performance, by reaſon
of that heavenly <hi>participation,</hi> derived from them unto us, and
being united unto him, that in them was ſo <hi>properly,</hi> are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
called <hi>Prieſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, by vertue of this <hi>union,</hi> there is ſuch an <hi>analogie</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
that which Chriſt hath <hi>done for us</hi> as a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and what
he <hi>worketh in us,</hi> by his holy <hi>spirit,</hi> that thoſe acts of <hi>ours,</hi> come
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155115:14"/>
be called by the ſame <hi>name</hi> with <hi>his,</hi> &amp; <hi>we</hi> for <hi>them,</hi> to be termed
<hi>Prieſts.</hi> Thus becauſe Chriſts <hi>death,</hi> and ſhedding of his blood, ſo
<hi>offering</hi> up himſelf by the eternall ſpirit, was a true, proper <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice</hi>
for ſin, even our <hi>spirituall death</hi> unto ſin, is deſcribed to
be <hi>ſuch,</hi> both in the <hi>nature</hi> of it, to be an <hi>offering</hi> or ſacrifice; for
<hi>I beſeech you Brethren</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) that you offer up your bodies
a living ſacrifice, holy,</hi> &amp;c. Rom. 12. 1. and for the <hi>manner</hi> of it,
our <hi>old man is crucified with him, that the body of ſin might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,</hi>
Rom. 6. 6.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, we are <hi>Prieſts</hi> as we are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or partakers of
an holy <hi>unction,</hi> whereby we are <hi>annointed</hi> to the participation of
all Chriſts glorious <hi>Offices;</hi> we are not called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;
if truly we are <hi>ſo,</hi> then have we an <hi>unction from the holy
one, whereby we know all things,</hi> 1 Ioh. 2. 20. and thus alſo were
all <hi>Gods people</hi> under the old <hi>Covenant,</hi> when God gave that
<hi>caution</hi> concerning them, <hi>Touch not my</hi> CHRISTIANS, <hi>and do
my Prophets no harm,</hi> Pſal. 105. 15. the <hi>unction</hi> then of the holy
<hi>ſpirit,</hi> implies a <hi>participation</hi> of all thoſe <hi>endowments</hi> which were
<hi>typified</hi> by the anointing with <hi>oyl,</hi> in the old Teſtament; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſts
<hi>us</hi> with the priviledges in a <hi>spirituall acceptation,</hi> of all the
<hi>ſorts</hi> of men, which <hi>then</hi> were ſo anointed; to wit, of <hi>Kings,
Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Prophets:</hi> ſo that by being made <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (every
one is not ſo that bears that name) we are ingrafted into Chriſt,
and do attain to a <hi>kinde</hi> of holy and intimate <hi>Communion</hi> with
him, in all his glorious <hi>Offices,</hi> &amp; in that regard are called <hi>Prieſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, the <hi>ſacrifices</hi> we are injoyned to <hi>offer,</hi> give ground to
this appellation; now they are of <hi>divers ſorts,</hi> though all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
<hi>Euchariſticall;</hi> as firſt, of prayers and thankſgivings, Pſa. 116
17. <hi>I will offer unto thee the ſacrifice of thanksgiving, and will call
upon the name of the Lord;</hi> And again, <hi>Let my prayer be ſet before
thee as Incenſe, and the lifting up of my hands be as the evening ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi>
Pſa. 141. 2. ſo, Heb. 13. 14. <hi>Therefore let us offer unto God the
ſacrifice of praiſe,</hi> that is, the fruit of our lips. Secondly, of <hi>good
vvorks,</hi> Heb. 13. 14. <hi>to do good, and to communicate forget not, for
vvith ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi> Thirdly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or
ſelf-ſlaughter, <hi>crucifying</hi> the old man, <hi>killing</hi> ſin, and <hi>offering</hi> up
our ſouls and <hi>bodies,</hi> an acceptable <hi>ſacrifice</hi> unto God, Rom. 12. 1.
Fourthly, the ſweet <hi>Incenſe</hi> of <hi>Martyrdom;</hi> yea, and <hi>if I be offered
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155115:14"/>
up on the ſacrifice and ſervice of your faith,</hi> Philip. 2. 17. Now <hi>theſe</hi>
and ſundry other <hi>ſervices acceptable</hi> to God, receiving this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation
in the Scripture, denominate the <hi>performers</hi> of them
<hi>prieſts.</hi> Now here it muſt be obſerved, that theſe aforenamed <hi>holy
duties,</hi> are called <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> not <hi>properly,</hi> but <hi>metaphorically</hi> onely,
not in regard of the <hi>externall acts,</hi> as were <hi>thoſe</hi> under the <hi>Law,</hi>
but in regard of the <hi>internall</hi> purity of heart, from whence they
proceed. And becauſe <hi>pure Sacrifices</hi> by his own appointment,
where <hi>heretofore</hi> the moſt acceptable <hi>ſervice</hi> to Almighty God;
therefore <hi>now,</hi> when he would declare <hi>himſelf,</hi> to be very much
delighted with the <hi>spirituall</hi> acts of our duty, he calls them, <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,
Incenſe, Sacrifices, Offerings,</hi> &amp;c. to intimate alſo a <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation</hi>
with him in his <hi>Offices,</hi> who <hi>properly</hi> and <hi>directly</hi> is the
onely <hi>Prieſt</hi> of his Church, and by the <hi>communication</hi> of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
of whoſe <hi>ſacrifice</hi> we are made <hi>Prieſts,</hi> not having <hi>authority</hi>
in our <hi>own names,</hi> to go unto God for <hi>others,</hi> but having liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<hi>through him,</hi> and in <hi>his name,</hi> to go unto GOD for <hi>our
ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not to loſe my ſelf and Reader in this <hi>digreſſion,</hi> the ſum is,
the unſpeakable bleſſings which the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> of Chriſt hath
obtained for us, are a ſtrong <hi>obligation</hi> for the duty of <hi>praiſe</hi> and
thankſgiving, of which that in ſome meaſure we may <hi>diſcharge</hi>
our ſelves, he hath furniſhed us with <hi>ſacrifices</hi> of that kinde, to
be offered unto God: for our <hi>own</hi> parts, we are <hi>poor,</hi> and <hi>blinde,</hi>
and <hi>lame,</hi> and <hi>naked,</hi> neither in the <hi>field,</hi> nor in the <hi>fold,</hi> in our
<hi>hearts,</hi> nor among our <hi>actions,</hi> can we finde any thing worth
the <hi>preſenting</hi> unto him; wherefore he himſelf provides <hi>them</hi>
for us, eſpecially for that <hi>purpoſe,</hi> ſanctifying and conſecrating
our <hi>ſouls</hi> and <hi>bodies,</hi> with the ſprinkling of his <hi>blood,</hi> and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
of the holy <hi>ſpirit.</hi> Further, he hath erected an <hi>Altar (to
ſanctifie our gifts</hi>) in <hi>heaven,</hi> before the Throne of <hi>grace,</hi> which
being <hi>spread over</hi> with his <hi>blood,</hi> is conſecrated unto God, that
the <hi>ſacrifices</hi> of his ſervants may for ever appear <hi>thereon:</hi> adde
to this, what he alſo hath added, the eternall and never expiring
<hi>fire,</hi> of the <hi>favour of God,</hi> which <hi>kindleth and conſumes</hi> the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
laid on that <hi>Altar:</hi> and to the end that all this may be <hi>rightly</hi>
accompliſhed, he hath <hi>conſecrated</hi> us with his blood, to be Kings
and <hi>Prieſts to God for evermore.</hi> So that the cloſe of this diſcourſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155115:15"/>
will be, that all true <hi>Beleevers,</hi> by vertue of their intereſt in
Jeſus Chriſt, are in the holy Scripture, by reaſon of divers
<hi>alluſions,</hi> called Prieſts, which name, in the ſenſe before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated,
belonging unto them <hi>as ſuch,</hi> cannot on <hi>this ground,</hi> be
aſcribed to any part of them, diſtinguiſhed any wayes from the
reſt, by vertue of ſuch <hi>diſtinction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the ſecond <hi>thing</hi> I obſerve concerning the <hi>buſineſſe</hi>
in hand, is, that the <hi>offering</hi> up unto God, of ſome <hi>metaphoricall</hi>
ſacrifices, in a peculiar <hi>manner,</hi> is appropriate unto men, ſet a
part for the <hi>work</hi> of the Miniſtery: as the <hi>ſlaying</hi> of mens <hi>luſts,</hi>
and the offering up of <hi>them</hi> being <hi>converted</hi> by the <hi>preaching</hi> of
the Goſpel, unto God: ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> of his <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> Rom.
15. 16. <hi>That I ſhould be the Miniſter of Ieſus Chriſt, unto the
Gentiles, miniſtring the Gospel of God; That the offering up
of the Gentiles might be acceptable,</hi> &amp;c. Miniſters preaching
the <hi>Gospel,</hi> to the converſion of <hi>ſouls,</hi> are ſaid to <hi>kill</hi> mens luſts,
and <hi>offer them</hi> up unto God, as the fruit of their calling; as
<hi>Abel</hi> brought unto him an <hi>acceptable ſacrifice,</hi> of the fruit of
his <hi>flock;</hi> and ſo alſo in reſpect of divers other <hi>acts</hi> of their
<hi>duty,</hi> which they perform in the name of their <hi>Congregations.</hi>
Now theſe <hi>ſacrifices</hi> are <hi>appropriate</hi> to the Miniſters of the
Goſpel, not in regard of the <hi>matter,</hi> for <hi>others</hi> alſo may <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
ſouls</hi> unto God, and <hi>offer</hi> up <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>praiſes,</hi> in the
name of their companions: but in reſpect of the <hi>manner,</hi> they
do it <hi>publikely</hi> and <hi>ordinarily; others</hi> privately, or in <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi>
caſes; now if the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who are thus Gods inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
for the <hi>converſion</hi> of ſouls, be themſelves ingrafted into
CHRIST; all the acts they perform in that great <hi>work,</hi>
are but parts of their own <hi>duty,</hi> of the ſame <hi>nature</hi> in that
regard, with the reſt of our <hi>spirituall ſacrifices:</hi> ſo that they
have not by <hi>them,</hi> any further peculiar intereſt in the <hi>Office</hi>
of the Prieſthood more then others: But if theſe <hi>Preachers</hi>
themſelves do not belong unto the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> (as
God oftentimes out of his care for his flock, beſtows gifts
upon ſome for the good of others, on whom hee will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow
no graces, for the benefit of their own ſouls, men
may adminiſter that conſolation out of the Word unto their
flock, which themſelves never taſted, preach to others,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:155115:15"/>
and bee themſelves caſtawaies. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells us that
ſome Preach Chriſt out of envy and contention, not ſincerely,
but on purpoſe to adde to his affliction; and yet ſaith he whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in pretence or in truth, Chriſt is preached, and therein doe
I. rejoyce, yea, and will rejoyce, Philip. 1. 16, 17, 18. ſurely
had there been no good effected by ſuch Preaching, Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
would not have rejoyced in it; and yet doubtleſſe it was no evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of Sanctification, to Preach Chriſt meerely out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,
(and on purpoſe to adde to the affliction of his ſervants)
but I ſay if the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhall be pleaſed at any time to make uſe of
<hi>ſuch,</hi> as inſtruments; in his glorious worke of converting
ſoules, ſhall we thinke that it is looked upon, as their <hi>ſacrifice</hi>
unto God? No ſurely, the ſoule of the <hi>Lord</hi> is delighted with the
<hi>Repentance of ſinners;</hi> but all the <hi>ſacrifices</hi> of theſe wicked men are
an <hi>abomination</hi> unto him, and therefore they have no intereſt
in it; neither can they from <hi>hence,</hi> be ſaid to be <hi>Prieſts</hi> of God,
ſeeing they continue <hi>dogges</hi> and uncleane beaſts, &amp;c. ſo that all
the right unto this <hi>Prieſtly Office,</hi> ſeemes be reſolved <hi>into,</hi> and
be the ſame <hi>with</hi> the common <hi>intereſt of all beleevers in Chriſt,</hi>
whereby they have a participation of his office: whence I
affirme;</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that the name of <hi>Prieſts</hi> is no where in the <hi>Scripture</hi>
attributed peculiarly, and diſtinctly to the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Goſpel
<hi>as ſuch;</hi> let any produce an <hi>inſtance</hi> to the contrary, and this <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie</hi>
is at an end: yea that which puts a <hi>difference</hi> betweene
<hi>them,</hi> and the <hi>reſt</hi> of the people of Gods Holineſſe, <hi>ſeemes</hi> to be
a more immediate participation of Chriſts <hi>Propheticall</hi> Office, to
<hi>teach, inſtruct,</hi> and <hi>declare the Will of God unto men,</hi> and not of
his <hi>ſacerdotall,</hi> to offer <hi>ſacrifices</hi> for men unto God. Now I could
never obſerve that any of <hi>thoſe,</hi> who wereſo forward of <hi>late</hi> to
ſtile themſelves <hi>Prieſts,</hi> were at all greedy of the apellation of
<hi>Prophets;</hi> no, this they were content to let goe, <hi>name</hi> and thing;
and yet when Chriſt aſcended on high, he gave ſome to be <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi>
for the edification of his body, Epheſ. 4. 11. none as wee
finde to be <hi>Prieſts:</hi> Prieſts then (like Prelats) are a ſort of
<hi>Church Officers,</hi> whom Chriſt never appointed; whence I
conclude;</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that whoſoever maintaineth any <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the New
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:155115:16"/>
                  <hi>ſtament,</hi> as properly ſo called in relation to any <hi>Altar</hi> or <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi>
by them to be <hi>offered,</hi> doth as much as in him lyeth diſanull
the <hi>Covenant</hi> of grace, and is blaſphemouſly injurious to the
Prieſthood of Chriſt; the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> under the new
<hi>Teſtament</hi> are one, and the <hi>ſame:</hi> and therefore they who make
themſelves <hi>Prieſts,</hi> muſt alſo make themſelves <hi>Chriſts,</hi> or get
another <hi>ſacrifice</hi> of their owne. As there is but one God, ſo there
is but <hi>one Mediator of God and man, the man Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Tim.
2. 5. now he became the <hi>Mediator</hi> of the New Teſtament chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
by his <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> becauſe by the eternall ſpirit <hi>he offered up
himſelfe unto God,</hi> Heb. 9. 14. 15. neither is any now called of
God to be a <hi>Prieſt</hi> as was <hi>Aaron,</hi> and without ſuch divine vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
to <hi>this office,</hi> none ought to undertake it, as the Apoſtle
argues, Heb. 5. now, the <hi>end</hi> of any ſuch <hi>vocation,</hi> and <hi>office</hi> is
quite <hi>ceaſed;</hi> being nothing but to offer gifts and <hi>ſacrifices</hi> unto
God, Heb. 8. 3. for <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath <hi>offered</hi> one <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for ſin for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
and is ſate downe at the right hand of God, Heb. 10. 12. yea
by one <hi>offering</hi> he hath perfected them that are ſanctified, <hi>v.</hi> 14.
and if that did procure <hi>remiſſion</hi> of ſins, there muſt be no more
offering for ſin, <hi>v.</hi> 18. and the ſurrogation of another makes the
<hi>bloud of Christ</hi> to be no better <hi>then that</hi> of bulls and goates. Now
one of thoſe they muſt doe, who make themſelves <hi>Prieſts,</hi> (in
that ſence concerning which we now treat) either get them a
<hi>nevv ſacrifice</hi> of their owne,<note place="margin">For offering the Hoſt or their Chriſt they pray: <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra quae, propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ac ſereno vultu reſpirere digneris, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta habere fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus es muno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae pueri tui juſti</hi> Abel, <hi>&amp; ſacrificium Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchae noſtri Abrahae:</hi> with many more to that purpoſe.</note> or pretend <hi>to offer Chriſt againe;</hi> the
firſt ſeemes to have been the <hi>fault,</hi> of thoſe of <hi>ours,</hi> who made a
<hi>ſacrifice</hi> of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> yet pretended not to beleeve the <hi>reall
preſence</hi> of Chriſt in, or under the outward <hi>elements</hi> or <hi>ſpecies</hi> of
them; the other of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> whoſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> in their <hi>Maſſe,</hi>
blaſphemouſly make themſelves <hi>Mediators,</hi> between God and
his <hi>Son,</hi> and <hi>offering up</hi> Chriſt Ieſus for a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> deſire God to
<hi>accept him;</hi> ſo charging that <hi>ſacrifice</hi> with <hi>imperfection,</hi> which he
<hi>offered</hi> on the Altar of the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and making it <hi>neceſſary</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
that he ſhould <hi>annually,</hi> but <hi>daily,</hi> yee <hi>hourely</hi> ſuffer afreſh, ſo
<hi>recrucifying</hi> unto themſelves, the Lord of glory. Further, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<hi>confeſſing,</hi> that to be a true <hi>ſacrifice</hi> it is required, that that
which is <hi>offered</hi> unto God be <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> and ceaſe to be, what it
<hi>vvas,</hi> they doe <hi>confeſſe by</hi> what lyes in <hi>them,</hi> to deſtroy the Son
of God, and by their <hi>Maſſe,</hi> have <hi>tranſubſt anciatd</hi> their <hi>Altars</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:155115:16"/>
into <hi>Croſſes,</hi> their <hi>Temples</hi> into <hi>Golgatha's,</hi> their <hi>Prelates</hi> into
<hi>Pilates,</hi> their <hi>Prieſts</hi> into <hi>Hangmen;</hi> tormentors of Ieſus Chriſt,
Concerning <hi>them</hi> and <hi>ours</hi> we may ſhut up this <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> with
<hi>what</hi> the Apoſtle <hi>intimates</hi> to the Hebrews, viz. that all <hi>Prieſts</hi>
are ceaſed, who were <hi>mortall,</hi> now ſmall cauſe have we to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve
them to be <hi>immateriall ſpirits,</hi> among whom we finde the
<hi>Workes of the fleſh</hi> to have been ſo frequent.</p>
               <p>And this may give us <hi>ſome light,</hi> into the <hi>iniquity</hi> of thoſe <hi>times,</hi>
whereinto we were <hi>lately</hi> fallen; in which <hi>Lord Biſhops</hi> and
<hi>Prieſts,</hi> had almoſt quite oppreſſed the <hi>Biſhops of the Lord,</hi> and
<hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpell; how <hi>unthankefull</hi> men were we, for the
<hi>light</hi> of the Goſpell, men that <hi>loved darkeneſſe</hi> rather then <hi>light.
A wonderfull, and horrible thing vvas wrought in</hi> our <hi>Land, the
Prophets propheſied falſly, the Prieſts bare rule by their meanes,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
the whole <hi>people loved to have it ſo, and what</hi> ſhall we <hi>now
doe in the end thereof,</hi> Ierem. 5. 30. 31. ſuch <hi>a haſty Apoſtacy</hi> was
growing on us, as we might <hi>juſtly wonder</hi> at, becauſe <hi>unparalel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi>
in any <hi>Church,</hi> of any <hi>age:</hi> but our revolters were profound,
<hi>haſty</hi> men and eager in their <hi>maſters ſervice.</hi> So what an height
of <hi>impiety,</hi> and oppoſition to Chriſt, the Roman <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> in a
<hi>thouſand yeeres</hi> attained unto, and yet I dare <hi>aver</hi> that never ſo
many <hi>errors</hi> &amp; ſuſpitions in an 100. <hi>yeeres</hi> crept into that Church,
as did into <hi>ours of England</hi> in 16. and yet I cannot herein give
the commendation of ſo much as <hi>induſtry</hi> to our <hi>Innovators;</hi> (I
accuſe not the whole Church, but particulars in it, and that had
ſeized themſelves of its authority) becauſe they had <hi>a Platforme</hi>
before them, and materialls provided to their hand; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
it was an <hi>eaſie</hi> thing for them to erect a <hi>Babel</hi> of Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
confuſion; when the <hi>Workemen</hi> in the Roman <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> were
forced to <hi>build</hi> in the <hi>plaine of Chriſtianity</hi> without any praeexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent
<hi>materialls,</hi> but were fain to uſe <hi>brick</hi> and <hi>ſlime,</hi> of their own
<hi>proviſion;</hi> beſides they were unacquainted with the maine <hi>deſigne</hi>
of <hi>Satan,</hi> who ſet them on <hi>worke;</hi> and therefore it is no wonder
if thoſe <hi>Nimrods</hi> oftimes <hi>hunted counter,</hi> and diſturbed each other
in their <hi>progreſſe;</hi> yea the firſt <hi>mover in Church Apoſtacy,</hi> knowes,
that <hi>novv</hi> his time is but ſhort, and therefore it <hi>behooves</hi> him to
make ſpeedy worke in <hi>ſeducing,</hi> leſt he be <hi>prevented</hi> by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:155115:17"/>
Then having <hi>himſelfe</hi> a long tract of <hi>time</hi> granted unto him, he
allowed his <hi>agents</hi> to take <hi>leaſure</hi> alſo; but what he doth <hi>novv,</hi>
muſt be done <hi>quickly,</hi> or his whole <hi>deſigne</hi> will be <hi>quaſhed:</hi> and
this made him inſpire the <hi>preſent buſineſſe,</hi> with ſo much <hi>life</hi> and
vigor. Moreover, he was <hi>compelled</hi> then to ſow his <hi>tares</hi> in the
<hi>darke,</hi> while men <hi>ſlept,</hi> taking advantage at the <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broylement</hi>
of the <hi>times;</hi> if any man had <hi>leaſure</hi> enough to <hi>ſearch,</hi>
and <hi>learning</hi> enough to <hi>ſee</hi> and <hi>finde</hi> him at it, he commonly filled
the <hi>world</hi> with <hi>clamors</hi> againſt him, and ſcarſe any but his vowed
<hi>champions</hi> durſt be his <hi>Advocates;</hi> in our <hi>time</hi> he was grown <hi>bold</hi>
and <hi>impudent,</hi> working at noone day; yea, he <hi>openly accuſed</hi> and
condemned, all that durſt <hi>accuſe</hi> him, for <hi>ſowing</hi> any thing but
good <hi>Wheat,</hi> that durſt ſay that the <hi>tares</hi> of his <hi>Arminianiſme and
Popery</hi> was any thing but true <hi>doctrine:</hi> let us give ſo much way
to <hi>indignation,</hi> we know <hi>Satans trade</hi> what it is, <hi>to accuſe the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi>
as <hi>men</hi> are called after their <hi>profesſions,</hi> one a <hi>Lawyer,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
a <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> ſo is he the <hi>accuſer of the brethren;</hi> now ſurely if
ever he ſet up <hi>a ſhop</hi> on earth, to practiſe his <hi>trade</hi> in, it was our
<hi>High Commisſion Court,</hi> as of late imployed, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 4.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the duty of Gods people in caſes extraordinary
concerning his Worſhip.</head>
               <p>THis being thus determined, I returne againe to the maine
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, concerning the duty and priviledge of the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
people of Chriſtianity,</hi> in ſacred things: and firſt in caſes <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary,</hi>
in which <hi>perhaps</hi> it may be <hi>affirmed,</hi> that every one
(of thoſe I meane before named) is ſo farre a <hi>Miniſter</hi> of
the <hi>Goſpell</hi> as to <hi>teach and declare</hi> the faith to others, although he
have no <hi>outward</hi> calling thereunto; and yet in this <hi>caſe</hi> every <hi>one</hi>
for ſuch an <hi>undertaking</hi> muſt have a <hi>Warrant</hi> by an <hi>immediate cal</hi>
from God, and when <hi>God calls</hi> there muſt be no <hi>oppoſition,</hi> the
<hi>thing</hi> it ſelfe he <hi>ſends</hi> us upon, becomes lawfull by his <hi>misſion,
what God hath cleanſed, that call not thou common,</hi> Act. 10. 13.
never feare the <hi>equity</hi> of what Cod <hi>ſets</hi> thee upon; no excuſes of
<hi>diſability</hi> or any other <hi>impediment,</hi> ought to take place, the Lord
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:155115:17"/>
                  <hi>can</hi> and <hi>will</hi> ſupply all ſuch defects: This was <hi>Moſes</hi> caſe, Exod.
10. 14. Oh Lord (ſaith hee) <hi>I am not eloquent, neither hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
nor ſince thou haſt ſpoken to thy ſervant, but of a ſlow ſpeech,
and a ſlow tongue; And the Lord ſaid unto him, who hath made
mans mouth, have not I the Lord?</hi> So alſo was it with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<hi>Jeremy,</hi> when God told him, that hee had <hi>ordained</hi> him a
Prophet unto the Nations, he replyes, <hi>Ah Lord God, behold I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
ſpeake, for I am a Child; But the Lord (ſaith hee) ſaid unto
me, ſay not I am a Child, for thou ſhalt goe to all that I ſhall ſend
thee, and whatſoever I command thee, thou ſhalt ſpeak, Jer.</hi> 1. 6.
Nothing can excuſe <hi>any</hi> from going on his <hi>meſſage,</hi> who can
perfect his praiſe, out of the mouth of <hi>Babes</hi> and Sucklings.
This the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> reſted upon, when he was queſtioned,
although he were <hi>unfit</hi> for that heavenly <hi>employment,</hi> either by
<hi>education</hi> or <hi>courſe</hi> of life: <hi>I was no Prophet, neither was I a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
ſonne; but I was an heardman, and a gatherer of Sycamore
fruit; and the Lord tooke me as I followed the flock, and ſaid unto
me, go Prophecy to my people Iſrael Amos</hi> 7. 14, 15. So on the
<hi>contrary,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> a man of ſtrong <hi>parts,</hi> great learning, and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments,</hi>
of indefatigable <hi>induſtry,</hi> and large <hi>abilities,</hi> yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes
of <hi>himſelfe,</hi> that when God called <hi>him</hi> to preach his word,
he <hi>conferred not with fleſh and bloud,</hi> but went on preſently with
his <hi>work. Gal.</hi> 1. 16, 17.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:155115:18"/>
               <head>CAP. V.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the ſeverall wayes of extraordinary
calling to the teaching of others; the
firſt way.</head>
               <p>NOw <hi>three wayes</hi> may a man <hi>receive,</hi> and be <hi>aſſured</hi> that hee
hath <hi>received</hi> this divine <hi>miſsion,</hi> or know that he is <hi>called
of God,</hi> to the <hi>preaching</hi> of the Word: I meane not that <hi>perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
of divine concurrence,</hi> which is neceſſary alſo for them, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat are
partakers of an <hi>ordinary</hi> vocation, (but which is required in <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi>
caſes to them, in whom all outward calling is
wanting.</p>
               <p>1. By immediate <hi>Revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. By a <hi>concurrence of Scripture rules,</hi> directory for ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.</p>
               <p>3. By ſome <hi>outward acts of providence</hi> neceſſitating him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>firſt,</hi> not to ſpeak of <hi>light Propheticall,</hi> whither it
conſiſts in a <hi>habit,</hi> or rather in a <hi>tranſient</hi> irradiating <hi>motion,</hi> nor
to diſcourſe of the <hi>Species,</hi> whereby <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> things are
conveyed to the <hi>naturall</hi> facultie, with the ſeverall <hi>wayes</hi> of
divine <hi>Revelation,</hi> (for St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirmeth it to have been <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
as well as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) with the ſundry <hi>appellations</hi> it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,
from the <hi>manner</hi> whereby it came; I ſhall onely ſhew,
what <hi>aſſurance</hi> ſuch a one as is thus called may have in himſelfe,
that he is <hi>ſo called,</hi> and how he may <hi>manifeſt</hi> it unto <hi>others.</hi> That
men receiving any <hi>revelation</hi> from God, had alwayes an <hi>aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi>
that <hi>ſuch</hi> it was, to <hi>me</hi> ſeemes moſt <hi>certain:</hi> Neither could
I ever approve the note of <hi>Gregory</hi> on the 1. of <hi>Ezek. viz. That
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:155115:18"/>
Prophets being accuſtomed to Prophecying,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sciendum eſt quod aliquando prophetae ſancti dum conſulun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ex magno u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu prophetandi quaedam ex ſuo ſpiritu pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerunt, et ſe hoc ex pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetiae ſpiritu dicere ſuſpican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Gregor: Hom. 1. in Ezek.</note> 
                  <hi>did oftentimes ſpeake
of their own ſpirit, ſuppoſing that it proceeded from the ſpirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie.</hi>
What is this but to <hi>queſtion</hi> the truth of all <hi>propheticall
revelations,</hi> and to <hi>ſhake</hi> the faith that is built upon it: Surely
the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> had an <hi>infallible aſſurance</hi> of the author of
his <hi>meſſage,</hi> when he pleaded for himſelf before the Princes, <hi>of
a truth the Lord hath ſent me unto you, to ſpeake all theſe words in
your eares. Chap.</hi> 26. 15. And <hi>Abraham</hi> certainly had neede of
a <hi>good aſſurance</hi> whence that motion did <hi>proceed,</hi> which made
him <hi>addreſſe himſelfe,</hi> to the ſacrificing the <hi>ſon of promiſe;</hi> And
that all other Prophets had the like <hi>evidence of knowledge,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the <hi>divine verity</hi> of their revelations <hi>is unqueſtionable;</hi>
hence are thoſe <hi>alluſions</hi> in the Scripture, whereby it is compared
unto things whereof we may be moſt certaine by the <hi>aſſurance
of ſenſe.</hi> So <hi>Amos 3. 8. The Lyon hath roared, who will not
feare? The Lord God hath ſpoken, who can but Prophecy?</hi> And
Jerem. 20. 9. <hi>His word was in my heart as a burning fire ſhut up
in my bones,</hi> things ſenſible enough. Happily <hi>Satan</hi> may ſo far
delude <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> as to make them <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> their <hi>lying vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi>
are from above: whence they are ſaid to be <hi>Prophets of the
deceit of their owne hear,</hi> Jerem. 23. 26. being <hi>deceived,</hi> as well
<hi>deceivers;</hi> thinking in <hi>themſelves,</hi> as well as <hi>ſpeaking</hi> unto <hi>others,
he ſaith,</hi> verſ. 31. but that any <hi>true Prophets</hi> ſhould not know a
<hi>true Revelation,</hi> from a <hi>motion</hi> of their owne <hi>hearts,</hi> wants not
much of blaſphemy. The Lord ſurely <hi>ſuppoſes</hi> that aſſurance of
diſcerning, when he gives that command; <hi>the Prophet that hath
a Dreame, let him tell a Dreame, and he that hath my Word, let
him ſpeake my Word faithfully; what is the chaffe to the wheate?
Ierem.</hi> 23. 28.<note place="margin">Dicebat ſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernere (neſcio quo ſapore quem verbis explicare non poterat) quid intereſſet interdeum reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantem, &amp; ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam ſuam ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niantem. Aug. Confeſſ.</note> He muſt be both <hi>blind</hi> and <hi>mad,</hi> that ſhall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake,
<hi>wheat,</hi> for <hi>chaffe,</hi> and on the contrary, what ſome men
ſpeak of an <hi>hidden inſtinct</hi> from God, moving the <hi>mindes of
men,</hi> yet ſo, as they <hi>know</hi> not wither it be from <hi>him,</hi> or no, may
better ſerve to illuſtrate <hi>Plutarchs</hi> diſcourſe of <hi>Socrates Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
then any <hi>paſſage</hi> in holy Writ. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaies, his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
would affirme, that though ſhe could not expreſſe it, yet
ſhe could diſcern the difference between <hi>Gods Revelation,</hi> and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:155115:19"/>
her own <hi>Dreames:</hi> In which relation, I doubt not but the
<hi>learned Father</hi> tooke <hi>advantage</hi> from the <hi>good old womans</hi> words
of what ſhe <hi>could do,</hi> to <hi>declare</hi> what <hi>might be done,</hi> of every one
that had ſuch immediate revelations. Briefly then, the <hi>ſpirit of
God,</hi> never <hi>ſo</hi> extraordinarily <hi>moveth</hi> the minde of man to <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend</hi>
any <hi>thing of this kinde</hi> whereof we ſpeake, but it alſo <hi>illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrateth</hi>
it with a knowledge, and aſſurance, that it is <hi>divinely mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi>
to this apprehenſion. Now becauſe it is agreed on all ſides,
that <hi>light Propheticall</hi> is no <hi>permanent habit</hi> in the minde of the
Prophets, but a <hi>tranſient impreſſion,</hi> of it ſelfe, not apt to give any
ſuch <hi>aſſurance,</hi> it may be <hi>queſtioned</hi> from what other <hi>principle</hi> it
doth proceed. But not to <hi>pry</hi> into things perhaps not <hi>fully</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed,
and ſeeing St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhewes us that in ſuch heavenly <hi>rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi>
there are ſome things <hi>unutterable</hi> of them, and <hi>incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible</hi>
of us, we may let this reſt, amongſt thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appeareth
then from the preceding diſcourſe, that, a man pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
to <hi>extraordinary vocation,</hi> by <hi>immdiate revelation,</hi> in
reſpect of <hi>ſelfe-perſwaſion,</hi> of the truth of his call, he muſt be, as
<hi>aſcertained</hi> of it, as he could be, of a <hi>burning fire in his bones,</hi> if
there ſhut up.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">What aſſurance men extraordinarily
called, can give to others, that
they are ſo called in the former
way.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>next thing</hi> to be conſidered, is, <hi>what aſſurance</hi> he can give
to <hi>others,</hi> and by <hi>what means,</hi> that he is ſo called. Now the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:155115:19"/>
                  <hi>matter,</hi> or <hi>ſubject</hi> of their imployment may give us ſome <hi>light,</hi> to
this conſideration: and this is either, the <hi>inchoation</hi> of ſome <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
work</hi> to be eſtabliſhed amongſt <hi>men,</hi> by vertue of a <hi>new,</hi> and
before <hi>never heard of Revelation</hi> of Gods will; or a <hi>reſtauration</hi>
of the ſame, when <hi>collapſed</hi> and <hi>corrupted</hi> by the <hi>ſin</hi> of men. To
the <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe, God never ſendeth any, but whom he doth ſo
<hi>extraordinarily and immediately call,</hi> and <hi>ordain</hi> for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
and that this may be <hi>manifeſted</hi> unto others, he alwayes
accompanieth them with his own <hi>almighty power,</hi> in the working
of ſuch <hi>miracles,</hi> as may make them <hi>beleeved,</hi> for the very <hi>works</hi>
ſake which God by them doth effect. This we may ſee in <hi>Moſes,</hi>
and (after Ieſus Chriſt anointed with the oyl of gladneſſe above
his fellows to preach the Goſpel) the Apoſtles: but this
may paſſe; for nothing <hi>in ſuch</hi> a way, ſhall ever again <hi>take place,</hi>
God having <hi>ultimately</hi> revealed his <hi>minde,</hi> concerning his <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi>
and our <hi>ſalvation;</hi> a <hi>curſe</hi> being denounced to <hi>man</hi> or <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,</hi>
that ſhall pretend to <hi>Revelation,</hi> for the altering or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
one jot or title of the Goſpel. For the <hi>other, the work of
Reformation,</hi> there being, ever ſince the <hi>writing</hi> of his Word, an
<hi>Infallible rule,</hi> for the performance of it, making it fall within
the <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>ability</hi> of men, partakers of an <hi>ordinary vocation,</hi>
and inſtructed with <hi>ordinary gifts;</hi> God doth not always <hi>immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately</hi>
call men unto it: but yet becauſe <hi>oftentimes</hi> he hath ſo
done, we may enquire <hi>what aſſurance</hi> they could give, of this
their <hi>calling,</hi> to that imployment. Our Saviour Chriſt informs us,
that a Prophet is often without <hi>honour</hi> in his own <hi>country:</hi> The
<hi>honour</hi> of a Prophet, is to have <hi>credence</hi> given to his <hi>Meſſage;</hi>
of which it ſhould ſeem, <hi>Jonas</hi> was above meaſure <hi>zealous;</hi> yet
ſuch is the <hi>curſed Infidelity</hi> and hardneſſe of mens <hi>hearts,</hi> that
though they <hi>cryed, Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> yet they would reply
<hi>the Lord hath not ſpoken;</hi> hence are thoſe <hi>pleadings</hi> betwixt the
Prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> and his <hi>enemies</hi> the Prophet <hi>averring of a truth,
the Lord hath ſent me unto you,</hi> and they conteſting, <hi>that the
Lord had not ſent him, but that he lyed in the Name of the Lord;</hi>
now to leave them <hi>inexcuſable,</hi> and whether they would <hi>heare</hi>
or whether they would <hi>forbeare,</hi> to convince them, <hi>that there hath
been a Prophet amongſt them,</hi> as alſo to give the greater <hi>credibility</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:155115:20"/>
to their extraordinary <hi>meſſage,</hi> to them that were to beleeve
their <hi>report,</hi> it is neceſſary that <hi>the Arme of the Lord ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed,</hi>
working in and by them, in ſome <hi>extraordinary</hi> manner,
it is certain enough, that God never ſent any one <hi>extraordinarily,</hi>
inſtructed onely with <hi>ordinary gifts,</hi> and for an <hi>ordinary end:</hi>
the ayme of their imployment I ſhewed before was <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,</hi>
even the <hi>reparation</hi> of ſomething <hi>inſtituted</hi> by God, and
<hi>collapſed</hi> by the ſin of man; that it may be credible, or appeare
<hi>of a truth,</hi> that God had ſent them for this <hi>purpoſe,</hi> they were
alwayes <hi>furniſhed,</hi> with ſuch <hi>gifts and abilities,</hi> as the utmoſt
reach of <hi>humane indeavours,</hi> with the aſſiſtance of <hi>common
grace</hi> cannot poſſibly attaine. The generall opinion is, that <hi>God</hi>
alwayes ſupplies ſuch, with the gift of miracles. Take the <hi>Word</hi>
in a large ſence, for every <hi>ſupernaturall product,</hi> beyond the <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
activity</hi> of that ſecondary cauſe <hi>whereby</hi> it is <hi>effected,</hi> and
I eaſily grant it; but in the uſuall reſtrained acceptation of it,
for <hi>outward wonderfull workes,</hi> the power of whoſe <hi>production</hi>
conſiſts in <hi>operation,</hi> I ſomething doubt the univerſall truth of the
aſſertion. We do not read of any ſuch miracles wrought by the
Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> and yet he ſtands upon his <hi>extraordinary imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate</hi>
vocation; <hi>I was neither Prophet nor the ſon of a Prophet, but
the Lord called me, &amp;c.</hi> it ſufficeth then that <hi>they</hi> be <hi>furniſhed</hi> with
a <hi>ſupernaturall power</hi> either in, 1. <hi>Diſcerning, 2. Speaking, 3. Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king:</hi>
the power of <hi>Diſcerning</hi> according to the things by it
<hi>diſcernable,</hi> may be ſaid to be of two ſorts, for it is either of
<hi>things preſent,</hi> beyond the power of <hi>humane</hi> inveſtigation, as
to know the <hi>thoughts of other</hi> mens hearts, or their <hi>words</hi> not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily
to be knowne, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> diſcovered the <hi>bed-chamber-diſcourſe</hi>
of the King of <hi>Syria</hi> (not that by vertue of their calling
they come to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, knowers of the heart, which is
Gods property alone, but that God doth ſometimes reveale ſuch
things unto them, for otherwiſe no ſuch power is included in the
nature of the gift, which is perfective of their knowledge, not
by the way of habit, but actuall motion in reſpect of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,
and when this was abſent, the ſame <hi>Eliſha</hi> affirmeth that
he knew not why the <hi>Shunamitiſh</hi> woman was troubled) or
ſecondly of <hi>things future</hi> and <hi>contingent</hi> in reſpect of their <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundary
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:155115:20"/>
cauſes,</hi> not preciſely <hi>neceſsitated</hi> by their own <hi>internall
principle of operation,</hi> for the effecting of the things ſo fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known:
and therefore the truth of the fore-knowledge, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts
in a <hi>commenſuration</hi> to Gods <hi>purpoſe.</hi> Now effects of
this <hi>power,</hi> are all thoſe <hi>predictions</hi> of ſuch things which wee
finde in the <hi>old</hi> and new Teſtament, and divers alſo ſince:
ſecondly, the ſupernaturall gift in ſpeaking I intimate, is that
of <hi>Tongues,</hi> proper to the <hi>times</hi> of the Goſpel, when the <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi>
of God was no <hi>longer</hi> to be <hi>confined</hi> to the people of one
nation.</p>
               <p>The third in <hi>Working,</hi> is that which <hi>ſtrictly</hi> and <hi>properly,</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
the gift of <hi>Miracles:</hi> which are <hi>hard, rare,</hi> and <hi>ſtrange effects</hi>
exceeding the whole <hi>order</hi> of <hi>created nature:</hi> for whoſe <hi>producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
God ſometimes uſeth his ſervants <hi>inſtrumentally,</hi> moving and
inabling them thereunto, by a <hi>tranſient impreſſion,</hi> of his power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
grace; of which <hi>ſort</hi> the holy Scripture hath innumerable
<hi>relations.</hi> Now with <hi>one</hi> of thoſe <hi>extraordinary</hi> gifts at the leaſt,
ſometimes with <hi>all,</hi> doth the Lord furniſh <hi>thoſe</hi> his <hi>meſſengers</hi> of
whom we treat: which makes their <hi>meſſage</hi> a <hi>ſufficient</hi> revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of Gods Will, and gives it <hi>credibility</hi> enough, to ſtir up <hi>faith</hi>
in <hi>ſome,</hi> and leave others <hi>inexcuſable.</hi> All the <hi>difficulty</hi> is, that
there have been <hi>Simon Maguſſes,</hi> and are <hi>Antichriſts, falſely</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
to have in <hi>themſelves,</hi> this <hi>mighty power of God,</hi> in <hi>one</hi> or
<hi>other</hi> of the forenamed kinds.<note place="margin">The diſcovery of Pretenders.</note> Hence were thoſe many <hi>falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
Dreamers,</hi> and <hi>Wizards</hi> mentioned in the old <hi>Teſtament,</hi>
which the Lord himſelfe <hi>forewarnes</hi> us of, as alſo thoſe
Agents of that man of ſin, whoſe comming is after the working
of Satan with <hi>povver and ſignes,</hi> and <hi>lying vvonders,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. 9.
I meane the jugling <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> pretending <hi>falſely</hi> by
their <hi>impoſtures</hi> to the power of <hi>miracle vvorking;</hi> though their
<hi>imployment</hi> be not to <hi>reforme,</hi> but profeſſedly to <hi>corrupt</hi> the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
of God: now in ſuch a caſe as <hi>this,</hi> we have: 1. The <hi>mercy</hi>
of God to <hi>relye</hi> upon, whereby he will guide <hi>his</hi> into the <hi>vvay</hi> of
<hi>truth,</hi> and the <hi>purpoſe</hi> or decree of God, making it <hi>impoſſible</hi> that
his <hi>elect ſhould be deceived</hi> by them. Secondly, <hi>humane diligence</hi>
accompanied with Gods <hi>bleſſing,</hi> may helpe us wonderfully in
a diſcovery, whither the <hi>pretended miracles</hi> be of God, or no;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:155115:21"/>
for there is nothing more <hi>certaine,</hi> then that <hi>a true and reall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle,</hi>
is beyond the activity of all <hi>created povver,</hi> (for if it be
not, it is not a miracle) ſo that the <hi>Divell</hi> and all his <hi>Emiſſaries</hi>
are not able to effect any one <hi>act truely</hi> miraculous: but in all
their pretences there is a defect diſcernable, either in reſpect of
the <hi>thing it ſelfe</hi> pretended to be done, or of the manner of its
doing, not truely exceeding the power of art or nature, though
the apprehenſion of it, by reaſon of ſome <hi>Hell-conceived</hi> circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,
be above our capacity. Briefely, either the thing is a <hi>lye,</hi>
and ſo it is eaſie to <hi>faigne miracles,</hi> or the <hi>performance</hi> of it, is
pure <hi>jugling,</hi> and ſo it is eaſie to <hi>delude</hi> poore <hi>mortalls.</hi> Innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
of this <hi>ſort</hi> at the <hi>beginning</hi> of the Reformation, were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered
among the <hi>Agents,</hi> of that <hi>Wonder-vvorking</hi> man of ſin,
by the bleſſing of God upon <hi>humane endeavours;</hi> now from ſuch
<hi>diſcoveries,</hi> a good <hi>concluſion</hi> may be drawne, againſt the <hi>doctrine</hi>
they deſire by ſuch meanes to <hi>confirme:</hi> for as <hi>God</hi> never worketh
true <hi>miracles,</hi> but for the confirmation of the <hi>truth,</hi> ſo will not
<hi>men</hi> pretend ſuch as are <hi>falſe,</hi> but to <hi>perſvvade</hi> that to <hi>others</hi> for
a <hi>truth,</hi> which <hi>themſelves</hi> have juſt reaſon to be <hi>perſvvaded</hi> is a
<hi>lye;</hi> now if this <hi>meanes</hi> faile, Thirdly, God himſelfe hath ſet
downe a <hi>rule</hi> of <hi>direction</hi> for us, in the time of ſuch <hi>difficulty,</hi>
Deut. 13. 1, 2, 3. <hi>If there ariſe among you a Prophet or Dreamer
of Dreames, and giveth thee a ſigne or a vvonder, and the ſigne, or
the vvonder come to paſſe, vvherefore he ſpake unto thee, ſaying, let
us goe after other Gods to ſerve them, thou ſhalt not hearken to the
vvords of that Prophet, or dreamer of dreames, for the Lord your
God proveth you, to know whether yee love the Lord your God, with
all your heart, and all your ſoul. Ye ſhall vvalk after the Lord
your God, and fear him, and keep his Commandements, and obey
his voice, and you ſhall ſerve him, and cleave unto him, and that
Prophet or Dreamer of dreams ſhall be put to death.</hi> The ſum is,
that ſeeing ſuch men <hi>pretend</hi> that their <hi>Revelations</hi> and <hi>Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi>
are from <hi>Heaven,</hi> let us ſearch, whither the <hi>Doctrine</hi>
they ſeeke to confirme by <hi>them,</hi> bee from heaven, or no;
if it bee not, let them bee <hi>ſtoned,</hi> or <hi>accurſed,</hi> for they
ſeeke to <hi>dravv</hi> us from our GOD, if it bee, let not the
<hi>curſe</hi> of a <hi>ſtony heart,</hi> to refuſe them, be upon us. Where
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:155115:21"/>
the <hi>miracles</hi> are <hi>true,</hi> the <hi>doctrine</hi> cannot be falſe; and if the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
be true, in all probability the miracles confirming it, are not
falſe; and ſo much of <hi>them,</hi> who are <hi>immediatly</hi> called of God
from heaven, what <hi>aſſurance</hi> they may have in <hi>themſelves,</hi> of ſuch
a <hi>call,</hi> and what <hi>aſſurance</hi> they can make of it to <hi>others;</hi> now
ſuch are not to expect any <hi>ordinary vocation;</hi> from men below,
God calling them <hi>aſide</hi> to <hi>his worke,</hi> from the middeſt of their
Brethren: The <hi>Lord of the harveſt</hi> may ſend <hi>labourers</hi> into his
<hi>field,</hi> without asking his <hi>Stewards</hi> conſent, and they ſhall <hi>ſpeake</hi>
what ever he <hi>ſaith</hi> unto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7.</head>
               <head type="sub">The ſecond way whereby a man may be called extraordinarily.</head>
               <p>SEcondly, a man may be <hi>extraordinarily</hi> called to the <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
and publiſhing of Gods word by a <hi>concurrence of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
rules, directory</hi> for ſuch <hi>occaſions, occurrences,</hi> and <hi>oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities</hi>
of <hi>time, place,</hi> and <hi>perſons,</hi> as he liveth in, and under.
<hi>Rules</hi> in this kinde, may be drawn either from <hi>expreſſe precept,</hi> or
<hi>approved practiſe: Some</hi> of theſe I ſhall <hi>intimate,</hi> and leave it to
the indifferent <hi>Reader,</hi> to judge, whether or no they hold in the
<hi>application;</hi> and all that in this kinde I ſhall <hi>propoſe,</hi> I did with
<hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> to better judgements.</p>
               <p>Conſider then,</p>
               <p>1. That of our Saviour to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> Luke 22. 32. <hi>When thou
art converted, ſtrengthen the Brethren,</hi> which containing nothing
but an application of one of the <hi>prime dictates</hi> of the Law of <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
cannot, ought not to be <hi>reſtrained</hi> unto <hi>men</hi> of any peculiar
<hi>calling</hi> as <hi>ſuch:</hi> not to multiply many of this kinde, (whereof in
the Scripture is plenty) adde only that of Saint <hi>James, Brethren,
if any of you do erre from the truth, and one convert him, let him
know, that he which converteth the ſinner from the error of his way,
ſhall ſave a ſoule from death, &amp;c.</hi> from theſe and the like places
it <hi>appeares</hi> to me, that</p>
               <p>1. There is a generall obligation on all Chriſtians, to promote
the converſion and inſtruction of ſinners, and man erring from the
right way:</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:155115:22"/>
Againe, conſider <hi>that</hi> of our Saviour, <hi>Mat. 5. 15. Men d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
not light a Candle and put it under a Ruſhell, but on a Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke,
and it giveth light unto all that are in the houſe:</hi> to which
adde that of the Apoſtle, <hi>If any thing be revealed to another that
ſitteth by, let the firſt hold his peace, 1 Cor.</hi> 14. 30. which words,
although <hi>primarily</hi> they intend extraordinary <hi>immediate revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
yet I ſee no reaſon why in their <hi>equity</hi> and extent, they may
not be <hi>directory</hi> for the <hi>uſe</hi> of things <hi>revealed</hi> unto us by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
light; at leaſt we may <hi>deduce</hi> from them, by the way of <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi>
that</p>
               <p>2. Whatſoever neceſſary truth is revealed to any out of the word
of God, not before known, he ought to have an uncontradicted
liberty of declaring that truth, provided that he uſe ſuch regulated
wayes for that his declaration, as the Church wherein he liveth
(if a right Church) doth allow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Further ſee</hi> Amos 3. 8. The Lion hath roared, who will not
feare? The Lord God hath ſpoken, who can but propheſie? <hi>And</hi>
Jer. 20. 9. Then ſaid I, I will not make mention of his name, but his
word was in mine heart, as a burning fire ſhut up in my bones, I
was weary with forbearing, and I could not ſtay: <hi>With the anſwer
of</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> John, <hi>to the Rulers of the</hi> Jews, Acts 14. 19, 20.
Whether it be right in the ſight of God to hearken unto you more
then unto God, judge yee, for we cannot but ſpeake the things that
we have ſeen and heard.</p>
               <p>Whence it appeares, that</p>
               <p>3. Truth revealed unto any, carries along with it an unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
perſwaſion of Conſcience (which is powerfully obligatory)
that it ought to be publiſhed and ſpoken to others.</p>
               <p>That none may take <hi>advantage</hi> of this to introduce <hi>confuſion</hi>
into our Congregations, I gave a ſufficient <hi>caution</hi> in the ſecond
Rule.</p>
               <p>Many other <hi>obſervations</hi> giving <hi>light</hi> to the buſineſſe in hand,
might be taken from the common <hi>dictates</hi> of nature, concurring
with the many generall <hi>precepts</hi> we have in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
them, the next thing I <hi>propoſe</hi> is the practiſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>1. Of our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, who did not only <hi>poſe the
Doctors</hi> when he was but twelve years old, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 46. but alſo
afterwards <hi>preached</hi> in the Synagogue of <hi>Nazareth, Luke</hi> 4. 18.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:155115:22"/>
being neither <hi>Doctor,</hi> nor <hi>Scribe,</hi> nor <hi>Levite,</hi> but of the <hi>Tribe</hi> of
<hi>Juda</hi> (concerning which <hi>Tribe</hi> it is evident that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
concerning the prieſthood.)</p>
               <p>2. Againe, in the eight of the <hi>Acts,</hi> great <hi>perſecution</hi> ariſing
againſt the <hi>Church,</hi> after the death of <hi>Stephen,</hi> they were <hi>all</hi> ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
abroad from <hi>Jeruſalem, ver.</hi> 1. that is, <hi>all</hi> the faithfull <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi>
of the Church, who being thus <hi>diſperſed,</hi> went every where,
<hi>preaching the word,</hi> ver. 4. and to this their <hi>publiſhing</hi> of the
Goſpell (having no <hi>warrant,</hi> but the generall <hi>engagement</hi> of all
Chriſtians, to further the <hi>propagation</hi> of Chriſts <hi>Kingdome) occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned</hi>
by their own <hi>perſecution,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> gave ſuch a <hi>bleſſing,</hi> that
they were thereby the firſt <hi>planters</hi> of a ſetled <hi>Congregation</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> they, and their <hi>converts</hi> being the firſt that
were <hi>honoured</hi> by the name of <hi>Chriſtians, Acts</hi> 11. 21. and 26.
Neither 3. is the <hi>example</hi> of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> altogether <hi>impertinent,</hi>
who with his <hi>companions</hi> repaired into the <hi>Synagogues</hi> of the
Jews, taught them <hi>publikely,</hi> yea, upon their own <hi>requeſt, Acts</hi>
13. 15. <hi>Apollos</hi> alſo <hi>ſpake</hi> boldly, and <hi>preached</hi> fervently, when
he knew only the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of <hi>John,</hi> and needed himſelfe further
<hi>inſtruction, Acts</hi> 18. 24. it ſhould ſeeme <hi>then,</hi> in that juncture of
time, he that was inſtructed in any <hi>truth,</hi> not ordinarily known,
might <hi>publikely</hi> acquaint <hi>others</hi> with it, though he himſelfe were
<hi>ignorant</hi> in other points of high <hi>concernment;</hi> yet perhaps now
it is not poſſible that any <hi>occurrences</hi> ſhould require a preciſe <hi>imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi>
of what was not only <hi>lawfull,</hi> but alſo expedient, in that
<hi>dawning</hi> towards the <hi>cleare</hi> day of the laſt <hi>unchangeable</hi> revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of Gods <hi>will.</hi> Now in <hi>theſe</hi> and the <hi>like,</hi> there is ſo much <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety,</hi>
ſuch ſeverall <hi>grounds,</hi> and <hi>circumſtances,</hi> that no direct <hi>rule</hi>
can from them be <hi>drawn,</hi> only they may give <hi>ſtrength</hi> to what
from the <hi>former</hi> ſhall be concluded.</p>
               <p>For a further light to this <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> conſider what <hi>deſolate</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate
the Church of God, <hi>hath been, may be,</hi> and at this <hi>preſent,</hi> in
divers places <hi>is</hi> reduced to: Her <hi>ſilver</hi> may become <hi>droſſe,</hi> and
her <hi>wine</hi> be mixt with <hi>water,</hi> the <hi>faithfull</hi> City becomming an
<hi>Harlot,</hi> her <hi>Shepheards</hi> may be turned into <hi>dumb ſleeping dogs,</hi>
and devouring <hi>wolves,</hi> her <hi>watchmen</hi> may be turned <hi>ſmiters,</hi> her
<hi>prophets</hi> to propheſie <hi>falſely,</hi> and her <hi>prieſts</hi> to beare rule by <hi>lies,</hi>
the <hi>Commandements</hi> of God being made void by the <hi>traditions</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:155115:23"/>
of men, ſuperſtition, humane inventions, <hi>will-worſhip,</hi> may defile
and contaminate the <hi>ſervice</hi> of God;<note place="margin">Ezek. 22. 27, 28. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 8. 13.</note> yea, and greater <hi>abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
may men <hi>poſſeſſing Moſes</hi> Chaire by <hi>ſucceſſion</hi> doe: Now that
the <hi>Temple</hi> of God hath been thus made a <hi>den</hi> of theeves, that the
<hi>abomination</hi> of deſolation hath been ſet up in the holy <hi>place,</hi> is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident
from the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church: for in the <hi>one</hi> it
was clearly <hi>ſo,</hi> when the <hi>government</hi> of it was devolved to the
<hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and in the <hi>other,</hi> when the <hi>man of ſin</hi> had
exalted himſelfe in the midſt thereof. Now ſuppoſe a man, living
in the <hi>midſt</hi> and <hi>height</hi> of ſuch a ſad <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> when an univerſall
<hi>darkneſſe</hi> had ſpread it ſelfe over the face of the <hi>Church,</hi> if the
Lord be pleaſed to <hi>reveale</hi> unto him out of his <hi>word</hi> ſome <hi>points</hi> of
faith, <hi>then</hi> either not at all <hi>known,</hi> or generally <hi>disbelieved,</hi> yet a
right beliefe whereof is neceſſary to ſalvation; and further out of
the ſame <hi>word</hi> ſhall <hi>diſcover</hi> unto him the wickedneſſe of that
<hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> and the <hi>meanes</hi> to remove it, I demand, Whether that
<hi>man</hi> without expecting any <hi>call</hi> from the <hi>fomenters</hi> and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers
of thoſe <hi>errors,</hi> with which the Church at that <hi>time,</hi> is only
not <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> may not <hi>preach, publiſh,</hi> and publikely <hi>declare</hi> the
ſaid truths to <hi>others</hi> (the knowledge of them being ſo neceſſary
for the good of their ſoules) and <hi>conclude</hi> himſelfe thereunto <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi>
of God, by vertue of the <hi>forenamed,</hi> and other the like <hi>Rules?</hi>
Truly for <hi>my part</hi> (under correction) I conceive he may, nay he
ought, neither is any other <hi>outward call</hi> requiſite to <hi>conſtitute</hi> him
a <hi>Preacher</hi> of the Goſpell, then the <hi>conſent</hi> of Gods people to be
<hi>inſtructed</hi> by him; for inſtance, ſuppoſe that God ſhould <hi>reveale</hi>
the <hi>truth</hi> of the Goſpel, to a meere <hi>lay man</hi> (as they ſay) in <hi>Italy,</hi>
ſo that he be fully <hi>convinced</hi> thereof; what ſhall he now do? ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine
from <hi>publiſhing</hi> it, though he be perſwaded in <hi>conſcience,</hi>
that a great doore of <hi>utterance</hi> might be granted unto him, onely
becauſe ſome <hi>hereticall, ſymonaicall, wicked Antichriſtian</hi> Prelate,
hath not <hi>ordained</hi> him Miniſter; who yet would not do <hi>it,</hi> unleſſe
he will <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> to thoſe <hi>errors</hi> and <hi>hereſies</hi> which he is <hi>perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi>
to be ſuch: truly I think by ſo <hi>abſtaining,</hi> he ſhould <hi>ſin</hi> againſt
the <hi>law</hi> of charity, in ſeeing (not the Oxe or Aſſe of his brother
falling into the pit, but) their precious <hi>ſoules,</hi> ſinking to everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<hi>damnation,</hi> and not <hi>preventing</hi> it, when he might? and were
he indeed truly <hi>angry</hi> with his whole <hi>Nation,</hi> he might have the
advantage of an <hi>Italian</hi> revenge.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:155115:23"/>
Moreover, he ſhould <hi>ſin</hi> againſt the <hi>precept</hi> of Chriſt, by hiding
his <hi>light</hi> under a buſhell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>napkining</hi> up his talent, an <hi>increaſe</hi>
whereof will be <hi>required</hi> of him at the laſt day: Now with this I
was alwayes ſo well <hi>ſatisfied,</hi> that I ever <hi>deemed</hi> all curious <hi>diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi>
after the outward vocation of our firſt <hi>reformers, Luther,
Calvin,</hi> &amp;c. altogether <hi>needleſſe;</hi> the caſe in their <hi>dayes</hi> being <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
that,</hi> which I have laid <hi>downe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Come we now to the third and laſt <hi>way,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The third way.</note> whereby men not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers
of any outward <hi>ordinary vocation,</hi> may yet receive a <hi>ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
warrant</hi> for the preaching and publiſhing of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and
that by ſome outward <hi>act of providence</hi> guiding them thereunto;
For example, put caſe a <hi>Chriſtian man,</hi> ſhould by any <hi>chance</hi> of
providence, be caſt by <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> or otherwiſe, upon the Country
of ſome <hi>barbarous</hi> people, that never heard of the name of Chriſt,
and there by hs goodneſſe that brought him thither, be received
amongſt them, into civill <hi>humane ſociety;</hi> may he not, nay, <hi>ought</hi>
he not to preach Chriſt unto <hi>them?</hi> and if God give a <hi>bleſſing</hi> to
his endeavours, may hee not become a Paſtor to the <hi>converted</hi>
ſoules? none I hope makes any <hi>doubt</hi> of it; and in the <hi>Primitive
times,</hi> nothing was more frequent then ſuch examples; thus were
the <hi>Indians</hi> and the <hi>Moores</hi> turned to the <hi>faith,</hi> as you may ſee in
<hi>Euſebius:</hi> yea great was the liberty which in the <hi>firſt Church</hi>
was uſed in this kinde, preſently after the ſupernaturall <hi>gift</hi> of
<hi>tongues</hi> ceaſed amongſt men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the liberty and duty of gifted, uncalled Chriſtians, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerciſe
of divers acts of Gods worſhip.</head>
               <p>ANd thus have I <hi>declared,</hi> what I conceive, concerning extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<hi>calling</hi> to the <hi>publick teaching</hi> of the word; in what
caſes onely it uſeth to take <hi>place,</hi> whence I <hi>conclude,</hi> that
whoſoever <hi>pretends</hi> unto it, not <hi>warranted</hi> by an evidence
of one of thoſe three <hi>wayes,</hi> that God taketh in ſuch <hi>proceedings,</hi>
is but a <hi>pretender,</hi> an <hi>impoſtor,</hi> and ought accordingly to be <hi>reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi>
of all Gods <hi>people</hi> in other <hi>caſes,</hi> not to <hi>diſuſe</hi> what outward
ordinary occaſion from them who are <hi>intruſted</hi> by <hi>commiſſion</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:155115:24"/>
from God, with that <hi>power,</hi> doth conferre upon <hi>perſons</hi> ſo called,
we muſt needs grant it a <hi>negative voyce,</hi> in the <hi>admiſſion</hi> of any
to the <hi>publick Preaching</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> if they <hi>come</hi> not in at that
<hi>doore,</hi> they do <hi>climbe</hi> over the wall, if they make any <hi>entrance</hi> at
all: It remaines then, to ſhut up all, that it be <hi>declared,</hi> What <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
Chriſtians,</hi> living in a pure, <hi>Orthodoxe,</hi> well <hi>ordered Church
may doe,</hi> and how far they may <hi>intereſt</hi> themſelves, in holy <hi>ſoule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerning</hi>
affaires, both in reſpect of their owne <hi>particular,</hi> and
of their <hi>brethren</hi> in the midſt of whom they live: in which <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination,</hi>
becauſe it concerneth men of <hi>low degree,</hi> and thoſe
that <hi>comparatively</hi> may be ſaid to be <hi>unlearned,</hi> I ſhall labour to
expreſſe the <hi>conceivings</hi> of my minde, in as <hi>familiar</hi> plaine obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations
as I can; onely thus much I deſire may be <hi>premiſed,</hi> that
the <hi>principles</hi> and <hi>rules</hi> of that Church <hi>governement,</hi> from which,
in the following <hi>aſſertions</hi> I deſire not to wander, is of <hi>that</hi> (to
which I <hi>doe,</hi> and <hi>alwayes</hi> in my poore judgement have <hi>adhered,</hi>
ſince by Gods <hi>aſſiſtance,</hi> I had <hi>engaged</hi> my ſelfe to the ſtudy of his
<hi>word</hi>) which commonly is called <hi>Presbyteriall,</hi> or <hi>Synodicall,</hi> in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
to <hi>Prelaticall,</hi> or <hi>Dioceſan</hi> on the one ſide; and that which
is commonly called <hi>Independant,</hi> or <hi>Congregationall</hi> on the <hi>other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. Then a diligent <hi>ſearching</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> with fervent
<hi>prayers</hi> to Almighty God, for the taking away that <hi>vaile</hi> of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
which by nature is before their <hi>eyes,</hi> that they may come to
a ſaving <hi>knowledge</hi> in, and a right <hi>underſtanding</hi> of them, is not
only <hi>lawfull</hi> and convenient for all <hi>men</hi> profeſſing the name of
Chriſt, but alſo abſolutly <hi>neceſſary</hi> becauſe <hi>commanded,</hi> yea indeed
<hi>commanded,</hi> becauſe the <hi>end</hi> ſo to be <hi>attained</hi> is abſolutely <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie</hi>
to ſalvation: to confirme <hi>this,</hi> I need not multiply <hi>precepts</hi> out
of the old or new Teſtament, ſuch as that of <hi>Iſa. 8. 20. To the law
and to the teſtimony,</hi> and that of <hi>Joh, 5. 39. Search the Scriptures,</hi>
which are inumerable, nor yet heap up motives unto it, ſuch as are
the diſcription of the <hi>heavenly countrey,</hi> whither we are going,
in them is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained, <hi>Joh. 14. 2. 2 Cor. 5. 1. Revel: 22. 1. &amp;c.</hi> the <hi>way</hi>
by which we are to travaile laid down, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 39. and 14. 5, 6.
<hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> whom we muſt labour to be <hi>like, painted</hi> out, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 1.
and the <hi>back-parts</hi> of God <hi>diſcovered, Deut.</hi> 29. 29. by <hi>them</hi> onely
true ſpirituall <hi>wiſdom</hi> is conveied to our <hi>ſouls, Iere.</hi> 8. 9. whereby
we may become even <hi>wiſer</hi> then our teachers, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119. in <hi>them</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:155115:24"/>
all comfort and <hi>conſolation</hi> is to be had, in the time of danger and
<hi>trouble, Pſa.</hi> 119. 54. and 71, 72. in <hi>briefe</hi> the <hi>knowledge</hi> of Chriſt
which is life eternall <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17. 3. yea, all that can be ſaid in this kinde
comes <hi>infinitely</hi> ſhort, of thoſe treaſures of <hi>wiſdom, riches,</hi> &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
which are <hi>contained</hi> in them; <hi>the law of the Lord is perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting
the ſoule, the teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, making wiſe
the ſimple, Pſa.</hi> 19. 7. but this duty of the people is cleere, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed;
the <hi>objections</hi> of the Papiſts againſt <hi>it,</hi> being for the moſt
part, ſo many <hi>blaſphemies</hi> againſt the holy <hi>word</hi> of God; they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<hi>it</hi> of difficulty, which <hi>God</hi> affirmes to make <hi>wiſe</hi> the <hi>ſimple,</hi>
of <hi>obſcurity,</hi> which <hi>openeth</hi> the eyes of the <hi>blinde;</hi> to be a <hi>dead
letter,</hi> a <hi>noſe</hi> of <hi>wax,</hi> which is <hi>quicke and powerfull pearcing to the
dividing aſunder of the ſoule and ſpirit;</hi> to be weake and <hi>inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,</hi>
which is able to make the <hi>man of God perfect and wiſe unto
ſalvation;</hi> yea that <hi>word</hi> which the Apoſtle affirmeth to be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
for <hi>reproofe,</hi> is not in any thing more full, then in reproving
of this blaſphemy.</p>
               <p>2. They may not onely (as before) ſearch the Scriptures, but
alſo <hi>examine,</hi> and <hi>try by them the doctrine</hi> that publikely is taught
unto them; the people of God, muſt not be like <hi>children toſſed too
and fro, and carried about with every winde of doctrine, by the
ſlight of men, and cunning craftineſſe, whereby they lie in wait to
deceive:</hi> Epheſ. 4. 14. all is not preſently <hi>Goſpell,</hi> that is ſpoken in
the Pulpit, it is not long ſince, that <hi>Altar-worſhip, Arminianiſme,
Popery, Superſtition,</hi> &amp;c. were freely <hi>preached</hi> in this Kingdom;
now what ſhall the <hi>people</hi> of God do in ſuch a <hi>caſe?</hi> yeild to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<hi>breath,</hi> to every <hi>puffe</hi> of falſe doctrine? or rather <hi>try</hi> it by the
<hi>word</hi> of God, and if it be not agreeable thereunto, <hi>caſt</hi> it out like
<hi>ſalt</hi> that hath loſt its ſavour: muſt not the <hi>people</hi> take <hi>care</hi> that they
be not <hi>ſeduced?</hi> muſt they not beware of <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> which
come unto them in <hi>ſheepes cloathing,</hi> but inwardly are ravening
wolves? and how ſhall they do this? what way remaines, but a
<hi>trying</hi> their <hi>doctrine</hi> by the rule? in theſe <hi>evill dayes</hi> wherein we
<hi>live,</hi> I heare many daily <hi>complaining,</hi> That there is ſuch <hi>difference,</hi>
and contrariety among <hi>preachers,</hi> they know not what to <hi>doe,</hi> nor
ſcarce what to believe; my anſwer is, Do but your own <hi>duty,</hi> and
this <hi>trouble</hi> is at an <hi>end;</hi> is there any <hi>contrarity</hi> in the book of <hi>God?</hi>
pin not your <hi>faith</hi> upon mens <hi>opinions,</hi> the <hi>Bible</hi> is the <hi>touchſtone:</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:155115:25"/>
that there is ſuch <hi>diverſity</hi> amongſt <hi>teachers</hi> is their fault, who
ſhould thinke all the ſame <hi>thing;</hi> but that this is ſo <hi>troubleſome</hi>
to you, is your <hi>own</hi> fault, for neglecting your <hi>duty</hi> of <hi>trying</hi> all
things by the <hi>word:</hi> Alas, you are in a miſerable <hi>condition,</hi> if you
have all this while, relied on the <hi>authority</hi> of men, in <hi>heavenly</hi>
things; he that builds his faith upon <hi>preachers,</hi> though they preach
nothing but <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>he</hi> pretend to <hi>believe</hi> it, hath indeed no <hi>faith</hi>
at all, but a wavering <hi>opinion,</hi> built upon a <hi>rotten</hi> foundation:
what ever then is <hi>taught</hi> you, you muſt go with it, <hi>to the law, and
to the teſtimony, if they ſpeake not according to this word, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
there is no light in them,</hi> Iſaiah 8. 20. yea, the <hi>Bereans</hi> are
highly <hi>extolled,</hi> for <hi>ſearching</hi> whether the Doctrine concerning
our <hi>Saviour,</hi> preached by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> were ſo, or <hi>no, Acts</hi> 17. 11.
<hi>agreeably</hi> to the <hi>precept</hi> of the ſame <hi>Preacher, 1 Theſ. 5. 21. Make
triall of all things, and hold faſt that which is good:</hi> as alſo to that
<hi>of</hi> St. <hi>John, 1 Epiſt. 4. 1. Beloved, believe not every ſpirit, but try
the ſpirits whether they be of God, becauſe many falſe ſpirits ar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
gone out into the world; prophets</hi> then muſt be <hi>tried,</hi> before they
be <hi>truſted;</hi> now the <hi>reaſon</hi> of this holds <hi>ſtill:</hi> There are many falſe
<hi>teachers</hi> abroad in the world, wherefore <hi>try</hi> every one, <hi>trie</hi> his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
his ſpirituall <hi>gift</hi> of <hi>teaching,</hi> &amp; that by the word of God. And
here you have a door <hi>rule</hi> laid down, how you may <hi>extricate</hi> your
ſelves from the former perplexity: Nay, St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to <hi>underſtanding</hi> Chriſtians, requires them to <hi>judge</hi> of it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
10. 15. I ſpeake as to <hi>wiſe, judge</hi> ye what I ſay: hence are
thoſe <hi>cautions,</hi> that the people ſhould looke that none do ſeduce
them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 4. to which end, they muſt have their ſouls <hi>exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed,</hi>
in the <hi>word</hi> of God, to diſcerne good and evil, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 14.
thus alſo in one place, Chriſt biddeth his <hi>followers,</hi> heare the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,
and <hi>do</hi> what they ſhould <hi>command,</hi> becauſe they <hi>ſate in
Moſes chaire, Matt.</hi> 23. 2, 3. and yet in <hi>another</hi> place, gives them
a <hi>caution</hi> to beware of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Phariſees, <hi>Matr.</hi> 16.
12. it remaineth then, that the people are <hi>bound</hi> to hear thoſe, who
<hi>poſſeſſe</hi> the place of <hi>teaching</hi> in the Church, but withall they muſt
<hi>beware</hi> that it contain nothing of the old <hi>leaven,</hi> to which end they
muſt <hi>try</hi> it by the <hi>word</hi> of God: when as Saint <hi>Paul prayeth</hi> for
the Philippians, <hi>that their love might abound yet more and more
in knowledge, and all judgement, that they might approve things
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:155115:25"/>
that are Excellent,</hi> Phil. 1. 9, 10. unleſſe <hi>miniſters</hi> will <hi>anſwer</hi> for
all thoſe <hi>ſoules</hi> they ſhall miſlead, and <hi>excuſe</hi> them before God,
at the day of <hi>triall,</hi> they ought not to <hi>debar</hi> them, from <hi>trying</hi>
their Doctrine; now this they cannot do, for if the <hi>blinde,</hi> lead the
<hi>blinde</hi> both ſhall fall into the pit of deſtruction. And here I might
have juſt occaſion of complaint: 1. Of the Superſtitious <hi>pride</hi> of the
late <hi>Clergy</hi> of this land, who could not <hi>endure</hi> to have their <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi>
tried by their <hi>auditors,</hi> crying to <hi>poor men</hi> with the <hi>Phariſes,
John</hi> 9. you were altogether borne in <hi>ſins,</hi> and do you <hi>teach us?</hi> A
<hi>pretty world</hi> it is like to be, when the <hi>ſheepe</hi> will needs teach their
<hi>Paſtors;</hi> nothing would <hi>ſerve</hi> them, but a <hi>blinde</hi> ſubmiſſion, to
the <hi>looſe</hi> dictates of their <hi>cobweb</hi> homilies: he <hi>ſaw</hi> farther ſure, in
the <hi>darkeneſſe</hi> of Popery, who contended that a whole <hi>generall
Councell,</hi> ought to give <hi>place,</hi> to a ſimple <hi>lay man,</hi> urging <hi>Scripture,</hi>
or ſpeaking <hi>reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſurely this is very far from that <hi>gentleneſſe, meekneſſe,</hi> and
aptneſſe to teach, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> requireth in a <hi>man of God,</hi> a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
of the Goſpel: Secondly, the negligence of the <hi>people</hi> alſo,
might here come under a juſt <hi>reproofe,</hi> who have not laboured, to
<hi>diſcerne</hi> the voice of the <hi>hireling,</hi> from that of the true <hi>ſhepheard,</hi>
but have promiſcuouſly <hi>followed,</hi> the <hi>new fangledneſſe,</hi> &amp; hereticall
<hi>errours,</hi> of every <hi>time ſerving</hi> ſtarver of ſouls. Whence proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
all that <hi>miſery,</hi> the land now <hi>groaneth</hi> under, but that we have
had a <hi>people,</hi> willing to be <hi>led</hi> by a corrupted <hi>Clergy,</hi> freely drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in the <hi>poiſon,</hi> wherewith <hi>they</hi> were <hi>tainted:</hi> the <hi>Prophets</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied
<hi>falſely,</hi> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> bare <hi>rule,</hi> by their meanes, the <hi>people</hi>
loved to have it ſo, but what ſhall we <hi>now doe</hi> in the <hi>end</hi> thereof;
<hi>who</hi> could ever have <hi>thought,</hi> that the people of <hi>England,</hi> would
have yeilded a willing <hi>eare,</hi> to ſo many <hi>Popiſh errours,</hi> and an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
<hi>ſhoulder,</hi> to ſuch a heavy <hi>burden</hi> of Superſtitions, as in a few
<hi>years,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vos facite quod Scriptum eſt, ut unodicente, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes examinent, me ergodicente quod ſentio, vos diſcern<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>te &amp; examinate; Orig. in <hi>Joſh. Hom.</hi> 21.</note> were <hi>inſtilled</hi> into them, and laid upon <hi>them:</hi> voluntarily by
their own <hi>ſinfull neglect,</hi> enſnaring their <hi>conſciences,</hi> by the omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
of this <hi>duty</hi> we inſiſt <hi>upon,</hi> of <hi>examining</hi> by the word what
is <hi>taught</hi> unto them; but this is no place for complaints, and this
is a ſecond thing, which the <hi>people</hi> diſtinct from their <hi>Paſtors</hi> may
do for their own <hi>edification.</hi> now whether they do this privately,
every one apart, or by <hi>aſſembling</hi> more <hi>together,</hi> is altogether <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</hi>
And that this was obſerved by <hi>private</hi> Chriſtians, in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:155115:26"/>
the Primitive <hi>times</hi> is very apparent.</p>
               <p>Come we in the third <hi>place,</hi> what either their <hi>duty</hi> bindes them
<hi>to,</hi> or otherwiſe by the <hi>word,</hi> they are <hi>allowed</hi> to doe, in ſacred <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances,</hi>
having reference to <hi>others;</hi> looke then in <hi>generall</hi> upon
thoſe <hi>things</hi> we finde them <hi>tied</hi> unto, by vertue of ſpeciall <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept:
ſuch</hi> as are to <hi>warne the unruly, comfort the feeble minded,</hi>
ſupport the weake, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 14. To <hi>admoniſh and reprove offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
brethren,</hi> Matth. 18. 15. to inſtruct the ignorant. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 29.
<hi>Act.</hi> 18. 26. to <hi>exhort</hi> the negligent, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 15. and 10. 24. 25. to
<hi>comfort</hi> the afflicted, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 11. to <hi>reſtore</hi> him that falleth, <hi>Gal.</hi>
6. 1. to <hi>viſit the ſicke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Matth. 25. 36, 40. to <hi>reconcile</hi> thoſe that are
at variance, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 9. to <hi>contend for the truth, Jude 3. 1 Pet.</hi> 3.
15. to <hi>pray for the ſinner</hi> not unto death, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 16. to <hi>edifie</hi> one
another in their moſt holy <hi>faith, Jude</hi> 20. to ſpeak to <hi>themſelves</hi>
in <hi>Pſalmes</hi> and hymnes, and ſpirituall ſongs, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. 19. to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
to <hi>anſwer</hi> every man, in giving account of their faith, <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 6.
to <hi>marke</hi> them that make diviſions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 17. with <hi>innumerable</hi>
others to the like purpoſe, it remaineth them to conſider: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
in particular, what <hi>courſe</hi> they may take, beyond private <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi>
between man and man, by indiction of <hi>time</hi> or <hi>place,</hi> for
the fulfilling of what by theſe precepts, and the like is of them
required: To which I anſwer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>1. <hi>Lawfull</hi> things muſt be done <hi>lawfully,</hi> if any unlawfull <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance,</hi>
attends the performance of a <hi>lawfull</hi> action, it vitiates
the whole <hi>worke,</hi> for <hi>Bonum oritur ex integris;</hi> for <hi>inſtance,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
an offender, is a Chriſtian <hi>duty,</hi> but for a private man to do
it, in the <hi>publicke</hi> congregation, whileſt the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
were inſtead of a <hi>good act,</hi> a <hi>ſoule</hi> crime, being a notorious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance
of Church <hi>decency</hi> and Order.</p>
               <p>2. That for a <hi>publicke, formall, Miniſteriall</hi> teaching, two
things are required in the Teacher: Firſt, <hi>gifts</hi> from God: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<hi>authority</hi> from the Church (and I ſpeake now of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
caſes) he that wants <hi>either,</hi> is no true <hi>Paſtor:</hi> For the firſt, God
ſends <hi>none</hi> upon an <hi>employment,</hi> but whom he fills with gifts for
it: 1. not one <hi>command</hi> in the Scripture made to <hi>Teachers</hi> 2. Not
one <hi>rule</hi> for their <hi>direction:</hi> 3. Not one <hi>promiſe</hi> to their <hi>endeavours,</hi>
4. Not any <hi>end</hi> of their <hi>unemployment;</hi> 5. not one incouragement to
their <hi>duty,</hi> 6. Not one reproofe for their <hi>negligence,</hi> 7. Not the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:155115:26"/>
leaſt <hi>intimation</hi> of their <hi>reward,</hi> but <hi>cuts</hi> off <hi>ungifted:</hi> Idoll pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors,
from any true <hi>intereſt</hi> in the <hi>calling:</hi> And for the <hi>other,</hi> that
want <hi>authority</hi> from the Church, neither <hi>ought</hi> they to <hi>undertake</hi>
any <hi>formall</hi> act, properly <hi>belonging</hi> to the <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> ſuch as is,
<hi>ſolemne</hi> teaching of the word; For, 1. they are none of Chriſts <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,
Epheſ.</hi> 4. 11. 2. They are expreſly <hi>forbidden</hi> it, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23. 21.
<hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 4. 3. The bleſſing on the word is <hi>promiſed</hi> only to ſent
teachers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 14, 15. 4. If to be <hi>gifted,</hi> be to be <hi>called,</hi> then,
1. Every one might <hi>undertake</hi> ſo much in <hi>ſacred</hi> duties, as he <hi>fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi>
himſelfe to be <hi>able</hi> to performe. 2. <hi>Children</hi> (as they report
of <hi>Athanaſius</hi>) might <hi>baptiſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euſebius Ruſſ.</note> 3. Every<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>common</hi> Chriſtian, might
<hi>adminiſter</hi> the <hi>Communion:</hi> but endleſſe are the <hi>arguments</hi> that
might be multiplied againſt this <hi>fancy;</hi> In a word, if our Saviour
<hi>Chriſt</hi> be the God of <hi>order,</hi> he hath left his <hi>Church</hi> to no ſuch
<hi>confuſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, that to appoint <hi>time</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> for the doing of that
which God hath <hi>appointed</hi> indefinitely to be done, in <hi>time</hi> and
<hi>place,</hi> rather <hi>commends</hi> then <hi>vitiates</hi> the duty; ſo did <hi>Jobs</hi> friends
in the <hi>duty</hi> of comforting the afflicted, they made an <hi>appointment</hi>
together to come and comfort him, <hi>Job</hi> 2. 11. and ſo did <hi>they,
Zech.</hi> 8. 21. and ſo did <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119. 62.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, There is much difference betweene <hi>opening</hi> or <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting</hi>
the word, and <hi>applying</hi> the word upon the <hi>advantage</hi> of
ſuch an approved <hi>interpretation,</hi> as alſo betweene an <hi>authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi>
act, or doing a thing by vertue of <hi>ſpeciall office,</hi> and <hi>a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
act,</hi> or doing a thing out a <hi>motion</hi> of Chriſtian <hi>love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, It may be <hi>obſerved</hi> concerning <hi>gifts;</hi> Firſt, that the <hi>gifts</hi>
and <hi>graces</hi> of Gods <hi>Spirit,</hi> are of two <hi>ſorts,</hi> ſome being beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
for the <hi>ſanctification</hi> of Gods people, ſome for the <hi>edification</hi>
of his Church, ſome of a private <hi>alley,</hi> looking <hi>primarily</hi> inwards,
to the ſaving of his <hi>ſoule,</hi> on <hi>whom</hi> they are <hi>beſtowed,</hi> (though in
their <hi>fruits</hi> alſo, they have a relation, and habitude to others) <hi>other</hi>
ſome, ayming at the <hi>common wealth</hi> or profit of the whole
Church, as <hi>ſuch:</hi> of the firſt <hi>ſort,</hi> are thoſe mentioned, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 22,
23. <hi>The fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, &amp;c.</hi> with all other
<hi>graces</hi> that are neceſſary to make the <hi>man</hi> of God <hi>perfect,</hi> in all
<hi>holineſſe</hi> and the <hi>feare</hi> of the Lord: the other are thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
ſpirituall <hi>gifts</hi> of <hi>teaching<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> praying, prophe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ying,</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:155115:27"/>
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. and in other places.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That all theſe <hi>gifts</hi> comming <hi>down</hi> from the <hi>Father</hi> of
lights, are <hi>given</hi> by the ſame Spirit, <hi>dividing to every one as he
will, 1 Cor.</hi> 12. 11. he is not <hi>tied</hi> in the beſtowing of his <hi>gifts,</hi> to
any <hi>ſort, eſtate, calling</hi> or <hi>condition</hi> of men, but worketh them
<hi>freely,</hi> as it <hi>pleaſeth</hi> him, in whom he will; the <hi>Spirit</hi> there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
is that <hi>God</hi> which worketh all things, according to the
<hi>counſell of his owne will, Epheſ.</hi> 1. 11. they are neither <hi>deſerved</hi> by
our <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> nor <hi>obtained</hi> by our <hi>endeavours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, That the <hi>end</hi> why God <hi>beſtoweth</hi> theſe <hi>gifts</hi> on <hi>any,</hi> is
meerely, that within the <hi>bounds</hi> of their owne <hi>calling</hi> (in which
they are circumſcribed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 24.) they ſhould <hi>uſe</hi> them to his
<hi>glory,</hi> and the <hi>edification</hi> of his Church, <hi>For the manifeſtation of
the Spirit is given to every man to profit withall, 1 Cor.</hi> 12. 7.
<hi>Chriſt</hi> gives none of his <hi>talents</hi> to be <hi>bound</hi> up in <hi>napkins,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 9.</note> but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects
his owne with increaſe: and from theſe <hi>conſiderations</hi> it is
eaſily <hi>diſcernable,</hi> both <hi>what</hi> the people of God diſtinct from their
<hi>Paſtors</hi> in a well ordered <hi>Church,</hi> may do in this <hi>kinde,</hi> whereof
we <hi>treate,</hi> and how: in <hi>generall</hi> then I <hi>aſſert,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That for the <hi>improving</hi> of knowledge, the <hi>increaſing</hi> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<hi>charity,</hi> for the <hi>furtherance</hi> of a ſtrict and holy <hi>communion</hi>
of that ſpirituall <hi>love</hi> and amity which ought to be amongſt the
<hi>brethren,</hi> they may of their owne <hi>accord, aſſemble</hi> together, to
<hi>conſider</hi> one another, to provoke unto <hi>love</hi> and <hi>good works,</hi> to ſtir
up the <hi>gifts</hi> that are in them, yeilding and receiving <hi>mutuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation,</hi>
by the <hi>fruits</hi> of their moſt holy faith. Now becauſe <hi>there</hi>
be many <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzahs</hi> amongſt us, who have an <hi>itching</hi> deſire to be
<hi>fingring</hi> of the <hi>Arke, thinking</hi> more <hi>highly</hi> of themſelves, then
they ought to <hi>thinke,</hi> and like the ambitious ſons of <hi>Levi,</hi> taking
<hi>too much</hi> upon them; it will not be amiſſe, to give two <hi>cautions,</hi>
deducted from the former <hi>rules:</hi> Firſt, that they doe not, under a
<hi>pretence</hi> of Chriſtian <hi>liberty</hi> and freedome of <hi>conſcience,</hi> caſt away
all <hi>brotherly</hi> amity, and cut themſelves off from the <hi>communion</hi> of
the Church; Chriſt hath not <hi>purchaſed</hi> a liberty for <hi>any</hi> to rent
his <hi>body:</hi> they will <hi>prove</hi> at length, to be no duties of <hi>piety,</hi> which
breake the ſacred bonds of <hi>charity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Men ought not under a <hi>pretence,</hi> of <hi>congregating</hi> themſelves to
ſerve <hi>their</hi> God, <hi>ſeparate</hi> from their <hi>brethren,</hi> neglecting the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:155115:27"/>
pnblick <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> as was the <hi>manner</hi> of ſome, rebuked by the
Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 25. there be <hi>peculiar</hi> bleſſings, and <hi>tranſcendent</hi>
priviledges annexed to publick <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> which <hi>accompany</hi> not
private men to their <hi>receſſes;</hi> the <hi>ſharp-edged</hi> ſword becomes more
<hi>keene,</hi> when ſet on by a skilfull <hi>maſter</hi> of the Aſſemblies; and
when the <hi>water</hi> of the word flowes <hi>there,</hi> the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of God <hi>moves</hi>
upon the <hi>face</hi> thereof, to make it <hi>effectuall</hi> in our <hi>hearts:</hi> What,
<hi>deſpiſe</hi> you the Church of God? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 22.</p>
               <p>Secondly, As the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> ſo alſo ought the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> to
have that <hi>regard,</hi> reſpect and <hi>obedience,</hi> which is due to their <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi>
in that ſacred <hi>Calling:</hi> Would we could not too <hi>frequently</hi>
ſee more <hi>puffed</hi> up with the conceit of their owne <hi>gifts,</hi> into a
<hi>contempt</hi> of the moſt <hi>learned</hi> and pious <hi>Paſtors;</hi> theſe are <hi>ſpots</hi> in
your Feaſts of <hi>charity, clouds</hi> without water, carried about of
<hi>winds:</hi> It muſt doubtleſſe be an evill <hi>roote,</hi> that bringeth forth
ſuch <hi>bitter fruit.</hi> Wherefore let not our <hi>brethren</hi> fall into this
<hi>condemnation,</hi> leſt there be an evill <hi>report,</hi> raiſed by them that are
without: <hi>But remember them who have the</hi> rule <hi>over</hi> you, <hi>who
have ſpoken unto you the word of God,</hi> Heb. 13. 7. there is no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<hi>evidence,</hi> of the heavenly <hi>improvement,</hi> you make by your <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes,</hi>
then that <hi>you obey them that are guides unto you,</hi> and <hi>ſubmit
your ſelves, for they watch for you ſoules, as they that muſt give an
account, that they may do it with joy, and not with griefe, for that
is unprofitable for you,</hi> ver. 17. Let not them who <hi>deſpiſe</hi> a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
painfull <hi>Miniſter</hi> in publick, <hi>flatter</hi> themſelves, with hope of
a <hi>bleſſing</hi> on their <hi>endeavours</hi> in private: Let them <hi>pretend</hi> what
they <hi>will,</hi> they have not an equall <hi>reſpect</hi> unto all Gods <hi>ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi>
Wherefore that the <hi>comming</hi> together in this <hi>ſort,</hi> may be
for the <hi>better,</hi> and not for the <hi>worſe,</hi> obſerve theſe things:</p>
               <p>Now for what <hi>gifts,</hi> (that are as before freely beſtowed) whoſe
exerciſe is <hi>permitted,</hi> unto <hi>ſuch</hi> men, <hi>ſo</hi> aſſembled: I meane in a
private <hi>family,</hi> or two or three met <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in one.</p>
               <p>And firſt we may name the gift of <hi>prayer,</hi> whoſe <hi>exerciſe</hi> muſt
not be <hi>exempted,</hi> from ſuch <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> if any be granted: theſe
are the <hi>times,</hi> wherein the Spirit of <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>ſupplications,</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
to be <hi>poured</hi> out upon the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> of God, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12. 10.
Now God having <hi>beſtowed</hi> the gift, and <hi>requiring</hi> the duty, his
<hi>people</hi> ought not to be <hi>hindred</hi> in the <hi>performance</hi> of it: are all
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:155115:28"/>
thoſe <hi>precepts</hi> to pray in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> onely for our <hi>Cloſets?</hi>
when the <hi>Church</hi> was in diſtreſſe for the impriſonment of <hi>Peter,</hi>
there was a <hi>meeting</hi> at the <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>Mary</hi> the mother of <hi>John,
Act. 12. 12. manie</hi> were gathered together <hi>praying,</hi> ſaith the <hi>text:</hi>
A ſufficient <hi>warrant</hi> for the people of God in like <hi>caſes:</hi> the
Churches are in no leſſe diſtreſſe <hi>now,</hi> then at that time, and in ſome
<hi>congregations</hi> the miniſters are ſo <hi>oppreſſed,</hi> that publikely they
dare not, in others ſo <hi>corrupted,</hi> that they will not <hi>pray</hi> for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity
of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> Now truly it were a <hi>diſconſolate</hi> thing, for
any one of <hi>Gods</hi> ſervants to ſay, during all theſe <hi>ſtreights,</hi> I never
<hi>joyned</hi> with any of Gods <hi>children</hi> in the pouring out of my <hi>prayer</hi>
in the behalfe of his <hi>Church:</hi> neither can I ſee how this can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly
be <hi>prevented,</hi> but by the former <hi>meanes;</hi> to which adde the
<hi>councell</hi> of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>themſelves,</hi> in Pſalmes, and
hymnes, and Spirituall <hi>ſongs,</hi> making melody in their hearts unto
the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 19.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they may <hi>exerciſe</hi> the gifts of <hi>wiſdom, knowledge,</hi> and
underſtanding in the <hi>wayes</hi> of the Lord; comforting, ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
and incouraging each other with the ſame conſolations, and
<hi>promiſes,</hi> which by the benefit of the publicke <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> they
have <hi>received</hi> from the word: thus in time of diſtreſſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<hi>Malachi</hi> tels us, that they that feared the Lord, <hi>ſpake</hi> often
one to another, and the Lord hearkned and heard, &amp;c. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. 16.
comforting (as it appeares) one another in the <hi>promiſes</hi> of God,
made unto his Church, againſt the <hi>flouriſhing</hi> of the wicked, and
<hi>overflowing</hi> of ungodlineſſe, the <hi>perſecution</hi> of Tyrants, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity
of tranſgreſſors.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they may make <hi>uſe</hi> of the <hi>tongue</hi> of the learned (if gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
unto them) to ſpeake a <hi>word in ſeaſon to him that is weary,</hi> Iſa.
50. 4. for being <hi>commanded to confeſſe their faults one to another,</hi>
James 5. 16. they have power alſo to <hi>apply</hi> to them that are peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
the promiſes of mercy: We ſhould never be commanded
to open our <hi>wounds,</hi> to them who have no <hi>balme,</hi> to powre into
them: he ſhall have cold <hi>comfort,</hi> who ſeekes for <hi>Councell</hi> from
a <hi>dumbe</hi> man, ſo that in <hi>this,</hi> &amp; the like <hi>caſes,</hi> they may <hi>apply</hi> unto,
and <hi>inſtruct</hi> one another <hi>in</hi> the word of God, doing it as a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
duty, and not as out of <hi>neceſſary function,</hi> even as <hi>Aquila,</hi>
and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> expounded unto <hi>Apollos</hi> the word of God more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155115:28"/>
then he knew it before, <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 23. in ſumme, and not to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large</hi>
this diſcourſe with any more particulars, the people of God
are <hi>allowed</hi> all <hi>quiet,</hi> and <hi>peaceable</hi> meanes, whereby they may <hi>help</hi>
each other <hi>forward,</hi> in the knowledge of <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> and the way
towards heaven; now for the cloſe of this diſcourſe, I will <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move</hi>
ſome <hi>objections,</hi> that I have heard <hi>godly</hi> men, and men not
<hi>unlearned</hi> lay againſt it, out of a <hi>zeale</hi> not unlike that of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> for
<hi>Moſes ſake,</hi> the conſtitute <hi>Paſtors</hi> ſake, to whom, though I might
briefly anſwer, with <hi>Moſes,</hi> I would to God all the <hi>Lords people</hi>
were prophets; I heartily wiſh that every one of <hi>them,</hi> had ſuch
a plentifull <hi>meaſure</hi> of ſpirituall <hi>endowments,</hi> that they might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
wiſe unto <hi>ſalvation,</hi> above many of their <hi>Teachers,</hi> in which
<hi>vote,</hi> I make no doubt but <hi>every one</hi> will concurre with me, who
have the leaſt experimentall <hi>knowledge,</hi> what a <hi>burthen</hi> upon the
<hi>ſhoulders,</hi> what a <hi>griefe</hi> unto the <hi>ſoule</hi> of a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> knowing, and
deſiring to diſcharge his duty, is an ignorant <hi>congregation,</hi> of
<hi>which,</hi> thanks to our <hi>Prelates, Pluraliſts, non-Reſidents, Homilies,</hi>
Service-Book, and Ceremonies, we have too toomany in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
the many alſo of our miniſters in this <hi>Church,</hi> taking for
their <hi>directory,</hi> the <hi>laws</hi> and <hi>penalties</hi> of men, informing what
they <hi>ſhould not do,</hi> if they would avoid their <hi>paniſhment,</hi> and not
the precepts of God, what they <hi>ſhould</hi> as their <hi>duty</hi> do, if they
meant to <hi>pleaſe</hi> him, and knowing there was no <hi>Stature,</hi> whereon
they might be <hi>ſued,</hi> for (pardon the expreſſion) the <hi>dilapidation
of ſoules,</hi> ſo their owne <hi>houſes</hi> were <hi>ceiled,</hi> they cared not at <hi>all</hi>
though the <hi>Church</hi> of God lay waſt: I ſay, though I might thus
<hi>anſwer,</hi> with opening my deſire for the <hi>increaſing</hi> of knowledge
among the <hi>people;</hi> of which, I take this to be an <hi>effectuall</hi> means, yet
I will give briefe <hi>anſwers,</hi> to the ſeverall objections.</p>
               <p>Then this ſeemes to <hi>favour</hi> an allowance of licentious <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Object.</note>
which in all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>laces,</hi> the <hi>Lawes</hi> have condemned, <hi>learned</hi>
men in all <hi>ages</hi> have abhorted, as the <hi>ſeminaries</hi> of faction and
<hi>ſchiſme</hi> in the Church of God.</p>
               <p>That (under correction) I conceive,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> that the <hi>Law</hi> layeth hold
of none, as <hi>peccant</hi> in <hi>ſuch</hi> a kinde, but onely <hi>thoſe,</hi> who have <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>declared</hi>
themſelves to be <hi>oppoſers</hi> of the worſhip of God, in the
<hi>publique Aſſemblies</hi> of that Church wherein they live: Now the
<hi>patronage</hi> of any ſuch, I before <hi>re<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cted;</hi> neither doe I <hi>conceive,</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:155115:29"/>
that they ought at all to be allowed the benefit of <hi>private meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi>
who wilfully <hi>abſtaine</hi> from the publique <hi>Congregations,</hi> ſo
long as the <hi>true</hi> worſhip of <hi>God</hi> is held forth in them: Yea, how
averſe I have <hi>ever</hi> beene, from that kinde of <hi>confuſed</hi> licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
in any Church, I have ſomewhile ſince <hi>declared,</hi> in an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
(drawne up for my owne, and ſome private friends ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions)
to the arguments of the <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> in their <hi>Apologie,</hi>
and replies to <hi>Vedelius,</hi> with other Treatiſes, for ſuch a liberty
of <hi>prophecying,</hi> as they terme it. If then the <hi>Law</hi> account onely
ſuch <hi>aſſemblies</hi> to be <hi>conventicles,</hi> wherein the <hi>aſſemblers</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne
and deſpiſe the <hi>ſervice</hi> of God in <hi>publique,</hi> I have not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
one word in <hi>favour</hi> of them: and for that <hi>Canon</hi> which was
<hi>mounted</hi> againſt them, whether <hi>intentionally,</hi> in the firſt <hi>inſtitution</hi>
of it, it was <hi>moulded,</hi> and framed againſt <hi>Anapabtiſts,</hi> or no, I
cannot <hi>tell?</hi> but this I am <hi>ſure,</hi> that in the <hi>diſcharge</hi> of it, it did
<hi>execution</hi> oftentimes, upon ſuch as had Chriſts <hi>precept</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi>
to warrant their <hi>aſſembling, Mat.</hi> 18. 19, 20. Not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
about <hi>words,</hi> would to God that which is <hi>good,</hi> might not
be perſecuted into odious <hi>appellations,</hi> and called <hi>evill,</hi> when it is
otherwiſe; ſo to oppoſe it to the tyrannicall <hi>oppreſſion,</hi> of the <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi>
of the Goſpell: The <hi>thing</hi> it ſelfe, rightly <hi>underſtood,</hi> can
ſcarce be condemned of any, who <hi>envies</hi> not the <hi>ſalvation</hi> of
ſoules. They that would <hi>baniſh</hi> the Goſpell from our <hi>houſes,</hi>
would not much <hi>care,</hi> if it were gone from our <hi>hearts;</hi> from our
<hi>houſes</hi> I ſay, for it is all one whether theſe <hi>duties</hi> be performed in
one <hi>family,</hi> or a collection of <hi>more;</hi> ſome one is bigger then <hi>ten</hi>
other; ſhall their <hi>aſſembling</hi> to performe what is <hi>lawfull</hi> for that
one, be condemned for a Conventicle? Where is the <hi>law</hi> for that?
or what is there in all <hi>this</hi> more then God <hi>required</hi> of his ancient
people, as I ſhewed before?</p>
               <p>Or muſt a <hi>maſter</hi> of a <hi>family,</hi> ceaſe <hi>praying</hi> in his family, and
<hi>inſtructing</hi> his <hi>children,</hi> and <hi>ſervants</hi> in the <hi>wayes</hi> of the Lord, for
feare of being <hi>counted</hi> a Preacher in a <hi>Tub?</hi> things were ſcarcely
<hi>carried</hi> with an equall <hi>hand,</hi> for the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt, when <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi>
came forth on the one ſide, to give <hi>liberty</hi> to the profane <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi>
to <hi>aſſemble</hi> themſelves at heatheniſh <hi>ſports,</hi> with beſtiall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations,
on the <hi>Lords</hi> own <hi>day,</hi> and on the other, to <hi>puniſh</hi>
them, who durſt gather <hi>themſelves</hi> together for <hi>prayer,</hi> or the ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:155115:29"/>
of <hi>Pſalmes;</hi> but I hope, through Gods <hi>bleſſing,</hi> we ſhall be
for ever quit of all ſuch <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> diſcipline, as muſt be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed</hi>
according to the <hi>intereſt</hi> of idle <hi>drones,</hi> whom it <hi>concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi>
to ſee that there be none to <hi>try</hi> or <hi>examine</hi> their doctrine, or of
ſuperſtitious <hi>innovators,</hi> who deſire to obtrude their <hi>fancies,</hi> upon
the unwary people; whence comes it that we have ſuch an innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable
<hi>multitude</hi> of <hi>ignorant</hi> ſtupid ſoules, unacquainted with
the very <hi>principles</hi> of Religion? but from the diſcountenancing
of theſe <hi>means</hi> of increaſing <hi>knowledge;</hi> by men who would not
labour todo it themſelves; oh that we could ſee the many <hi>ſwearers,</hi>
and <hi>drunkards,</hi> &amp; Sabbath-breakers, &amp;c. in this nation, guilty one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
of this crime; would the <hi>Kingdom</hi> were ſo <hi>happy,</hi> the Church
ſo holy!</p>
               <p>Men are apt,<note place="margin">2. Object.</note> to <hi>pride</hi> themſelves in their <hi>gifts,</hi> and flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
in their <hi>performances,</hi> ſo that let them approch as nigh as the
<hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and you ſhall quickly have them <hi>encroaching</hi> upon the
Prieſts <hi>office</hi> alſo, and by an over-weening of their own <hi>indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours,</hi>
create themſelues Paſtors in <hi>ſeperate</hi> congregations.</p>
               <p>It cannot be,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> but <hi>offences</hi> will come, ſo long as there is <hi>malice</hi>
in Satan, and <hi>corruption</hi> in men, there is no doubt, but there is
<hi>danger</hi> of ſome ſuch thing: but hereof the liberty mentioned is
not the <hi>cauſe,</hi> but an accidentall <hi>occaſion</hi> onely, no way blameable,
<hi>gifts</hi> muſt not be <hi>condemned,</hi> becauſe they may be <hi>abuſed,</hi> God-fearing-men
will remember <hi>Korah,</hi> knowing (as one ſayes well)
that <hi>Vzzah</hi> had better <hi>ventured</hi> the falling then the <hi>fingring</hi> of the
Arke, they that truely love their <hi>ſoules,</hi> will not ſuffer <hi>themſelves</hi>
to be carried away by <hi>ſelfe-conceit,</hi> ſo farre as to help overthrow
the very <hi>conſtitution</hi> of any Church by <hi>confuſion,</hi> or the flouriſhing
of it by <hi>ignorance,</hi> both which, would <hi>certainly</hi> follow ſuch
courſes; knowledge if <hi>alone</hi> puffeth up, but joyned to <hi>charity</hi>
it <hi>edifieth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But may not this be a <hi>meanes</hi> for men to vent and <hi>broach</hi> their
owne <hi>private</hi> fancies unto <hi>others?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. Object.</note> to foment and cheriſh <hi>errors</hi>
in one <hi>another?</hi> to give falſe <hi>interpretations</hi> of the word, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
no way to <hi>prevent</hi> it?</p>
               <p>For <hi>interpreting</hi> of the word,<note place="margin">Anſwer</note> I ſpeake not, but <hi>applying</hi> of it
being rightly interpreted; and for the reſt, would to God the
<hi>complaints</hi> were not true, of thoſe <hi>things</hi> that have for divers
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:155115:30"/>
                  <hi>yeares</hi> in this Church beene done <hi>publickly,</hi> and outwardly accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to <hi>order:</hi> but that no <hi>inconvenience</hi> ariſe from hence, the
care reſts on <hi>them,</hi> to whom the <hi>diſpenſation</hi> of the word is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,
whoſe ſedulous <hi>indeavour,</hi> to reprove and <hi>convince</hi> all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound
<hi>doctrine,</hi> not agreeing to the <hi>forme</hi> of wholeſome words,
is the ſoveraigne and onely <hi>remedy</hi> to <hi>cure,</hi> or meanes to <hi>prevent</hi>
this evill. For the cloſe of <hi>all,</hi> we may <hi>obſerve,</hi> that <hi>thoſe</hi> who are
moſt offended, and afraid, leſt others ſhould encroach upon their
<hi>callings,</hi> are for the moſt part <hi>ſuch,</hi> as have almoſt <hi>deſerted</hi> it
themſelves, neglecting their owne <hi>imployment,</hi> when they are the
<hi>buſieſt</hi> of mortals, in things of this world. To <hi>conclude</hi> then, for
what I have delivered in this <hi>particular,</hi> I conceive that I have the
<hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>practiſe</hi> of the whole <hi>Church</hi> of Scotland, (agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
to the word of God) for my warrant; witneſſe that Act of
their Aſſembly at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> An. 1641. wherewith the learned
<hi>Rutherſurd</hi> concludes his Defence of their <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> with whoſe
words I will ſhut up this Diſcourſe; <hi>Our Aſſembly alſo, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
goldy</hi> conference <hi>at all occaſionall meetings, or as Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
ſhall diſpoſe, as the word of God commandeth, providing
none invade the Paſtors office, to preach the word, who are not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
thereunto by God and his Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:155115:30"/>
            <p>I Have peruſed this Diſcourſe touching <hi>The
adminiſtration of things commanded in Religion,</hi>
and conceive it written with much cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
of judgement, and moderation of ſpirit,
and therefore do approve of it to be publiſhed
in Print.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>May 11.
1644.</date>
               <signed>JOSEPH CARYL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
