<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triumphs of love: chastitie: death: translated out of Petrarch by Mris Anna Hume.</title>
            <title>Trionfi. Selections. English</title>
            <author>Petrarca, Francesco, 1304-1374.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1873</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1164_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208709</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867636</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867636</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119955</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A90620)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119955)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 166:E1164[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triumphs of love: chastitie: death: translated out of Petrarch by Mris Anna Hume.</title>
                  <title>Trionfi. Selections. English</title>
                  <author>Petrarca, Francesco, 1304-1374.</author>
                  <author>Hume, Anna.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 58, [2], 59-98 [i.e. 96], [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler, printer to the Kings most excellent Majestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 96 misnumbered 98.</note>
                  <note>With separate dated title pages for "The triumph of chastitie" and "The triumph of death"; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill: 11".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119955:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
TRIUMPHS
Of
<list>
                  <item>LOVE:</item>
                  <item>CHASTITIE:</item>
                  <item>DEATH:</item>
               </list>
TRANSLATED
OUT OF
PETRARCH
BY
M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> ANNA HUME.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi>
Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to
the Kings moſt Excellent
Majeſtie. 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedicatory_poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:119955:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119955:2"/>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the moſt excellent Princeſſe,
her Highneſſe, the Princeſſe
ELISABETH,
Eldeſt daughter to the King of
BOHEMIA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat my rude lines durſt meet the dazeling rayes</l>
                  <l>Of Majeſty, which from your Princely eyes</l>
                  <l>Would beat the owner back, blame them not, they</l>
                  <l>Want ſenſe, nor had they wit to bid me ſay</l>
                  <l>Thus much in their behalfe: elſe having heard</l>
                  <l>Y' are mercifull, they could not be affeard:</l>
                  <l>Or doubting ſome arreſt of ſudden death</l>
                  <l>Made haſte to be reprived by your breath!</l>
                  <l>True glory of your ſex, whoſe ſingle name</l>
                  <l>Protecteth vertue, and commandeth fame.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119955:3"/>
Now you have ſav'd them with a looke, the reſt</l>
                  <l>Aſſume like boldneſſe, and deſire to taſte</l>
                  <l>Like honour, ſince they justly think their claim</l>
                  <l>Better, by vertue of great <hi>Petrarchs</hi> name:</l>
                  <l>Whom if they lamely follow tis more grace,</l>
                  <l>Then t' have outgone a meaner Poets pace.</l>
                  <l>Your milder judgement muſt the ſentence give,</l>
                  <l>For which they humbly wait to make them live.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>The humbleſt of your
Highneſſe ſervants
ANNA HUME.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="dedication">
               <pb facs="tcp:119955:3"/>
               <head>ANOTHER TO HER
HIGHNESSE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> Doe not dedicate theſe to delight</l>
                  <l>Or profit you, both are the Authors right:</l>
                  <l>Nor is it that your Highneſſe may protect</l>
                  <l>My part, it merits not ſo much reſpect;</l>
                  <l>Nor that you may examine and compare,</l>
                  <l>It leſſe deſerves ſuch ſerious Princely care:</l>
                  <l>Nor is it gratitude, becauſe y' have been</l>
                  <l>Pleas'd to approve ſome others you have ſeen:</l>
                  <l>Since retribution ſo farre below</l>
                  <l>Proportion, would be worſe then ſtill to owe:</l>
                  <l>Nor vanity, that thus I may have leave</l>
                  <l>To tell the world the honour I receive,</l>
                  <l>In that my name hath reacht your ſacred eare:</l>
                  <l>I hate that emptie vice; yet need not feare</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119955:4"/>
The cenſure, were it juſt ſince 't would make proud</l>
                  <l>The ſtaideſt thoughts to be by you allow'd.</l>
                  <l>If any aske me, What is then my end?</l>
                  <l>'Tis to approve my ſelfe a reall friend</l>
                  <l>To chaſte <hi>Lauretta,</hi> whom ſince I have tane</l>
                  <l>From the dark Cloyſter, where ſhe did remain</l>
                  <l>Unmarkt, becauſe unknown, my aime is now</l>
                  <l>To make her happy, by attending you:</l>
                  <l>Where ſhe may ſee her trueſt worth outgone,</l>
                  <l>And learn more vertue then ſhe yet hath known</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>The humbleſt of your
Highneſſe ſervants
ANNA HUME.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119955:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>REader, I have oft been told,</l>
               <l>Verſe that ſpeake not Love, are cold.</l>
               <l>I would gladly pleaſe thine eare,</l>
               <l>But am loth to buy 't too deare.</l>
               <l>And 'tis eaſier farre to borrow</l>
               <l>Lovers tears, then feel their ſorrow.</l>
               <l>Therefore he hath furniſh't me,</l>
               <l>Who had enough to ſerve all three.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119955:5"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119955:5"/>
                  <head>The Triumph of LOVE,
Tranſlated out of Petrarch.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <head>The Argument.</head>
                        <l>A viſion ſhews the captived</l>
                        <l>By mighty Love in triumph led.</l>
                     </argument>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the time, when I doe ſadly pay</l>
                     <l>My ſighs, in tribute to that ſweet-ſowre-day,</l>
                     <l>Which firſt gave being to my tedious woes:</l>
                     <l>The Sunne, now o're the Bulls horns proudly goes,</l>
                     <l n="5">And <hi>Phaëton</hi> had renew'd his wonted race:</l>
                     <l>When Love, the Seaſon, and my owne ill caſe,</l>
                     <l>Drew me that ſolitary place to finde,</l>
                     <l>In which I oft unload my charged minde:</l>
                     <l>There tir'd with raving thoughts and helpleſſe moan<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l n="10">Sleep ſeal'd my eyes up, and my ſenſes gone,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119955:6"/>
My waking fancie ſpied a ſhining light,</l>
                     <l>In which appear'd long pain, and ſhort delight.</l>
                     <l>A mighty Generall, I then did ſee,</l>
                     <l>Like one, who (for ſome glorious victory)</l>
                     <l n="15">Should to the Capitol in triumph go:</l>
                     <l>I (who had not been us'd to ſuch a ſhow</l>
                     <l>In this ſoft age, where we no valour have</l>
                     <l>But pride) admir'd his habit, ſtrange and brave,</l>
                     <l>And having rais'd mine eyes, which wearied were,</l>
                     <l n="20">To underſtand this ſight was all my care.</l>
                     <l>Foure ſnowie ſteeds a fiery Chariot drew;</l>
                     <l>There ſat the cruel boy; a threatning ewe</l>
                     <l>His right hand bore, his Quiver arrowes held,</l>
                     <l>Againſt whoſe force, no helme or ſhield prevail'd.</l>
                     <l n="25">Two party-coloured wings his ſhoulders ware;</l>
                     <l>All naked elſe; and round about his chaire</l>
                     <l>Were thouſand mortals: ſome in battell tain,</l>
                     <l>Many were hurt with darts, and many ſlain.</l>
                     <l>Glad to learn newes I roſe, and forward preſt</l>
                     <l n="30">So farre, that I was one amongſt the reſt;</l>
                     <l>As if I had been kill'd with loving pain</l>
                     <l>Before my time; and looking through the train</l>
                     <l>Of this teare-thirſty King, I would have ſpi'd</l>
                     <l>Some of my old acquaintance, but deſcri'd</l>
                     <l n="35">
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119955:6"/>
No face I knew: If any ſuch there were,</l>
                     <l>They were transform'd with priſon, death and care.</l>
                     <l>At laſt one Ghoſt, leſſe ſad than th' others, came,</l>
                     <l>Who neare approaching, call'd me by my name,</l>
                     <l>And ſaid: This comes of Love: What may you be,</l>
                     <l n="40">(I anſwer'd, wondring much) that thus know me?</l>
                     <l>For I remember not t' have ſeen your face.</l>
                     <l>He thus reply'd: It is the duskie place</l>
                     <l>That dull's thy ſight, and this hard yoake I beare:</l>
                     <l>Elſe I a Thuſcan am; thy friend, and deare</l>
                     <l n="45">To thy remembrance: his wonted phraſe</l>
                     <l>And voyce did then diſcover what he was.</l>
                     <l>So we retir'd aſide, and left the throng,</l>
                     <l>When thus he ſpake; I have expected long</l>
                     <l>To ſee you here with us; your face did ſeem</l>
                     <l n="50">To threaten you no leſſe. I doe eſteem</l>
                     <l>Your propheſies; but I have ſeen what care</l>
                     <l>Attends a Lovers life; and muſt beware.</l>
                     <l>Yet have I oft been beaten in the field,</l>
                     <l>And ſometimes hurt, ſaid I, but ſcorn'd to yeeld.</l>
                     <l n="55">He ſmil'd and ſaid: Alas! thou doſt not ſee,</l>
                     <l>(My ſonne) how great a flame's prepar'd for thee.</l>
                     <l>I knew not then what by his words he meant;</l>
                     <l>But ſince I finde it by the dire event:</l>
                     <l n="60">
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119955:7"/>
And in my memory 'tis fixt ſo faſt,</l>
                     <l>That marble gravings cannot firmer laſt.</l>
                     <l>Mean while my forward youth did thus enquire:</l>
                     <l>What may theſe people be? I much deſire</l>
                     <l>To know their names, pray, give me leave to aske.</l>
                     <l n="65">I thinke ere long, 'twill be a needleſſe taske</l>
                     <l>(Replied my friend) thou ſhalt be of the train,</l>
                     <l>And know them all; this captivating chain</l>
                     <l>Thy neck muſt beare, (though thou doſt little feare)</l>
                     <l>And ſooner change thy comely forme and haire,</l>
                     <l n="70">Then be unfettered from the cruell tie,</l>
                     <l>How ere thou ſtruggle for thy liberty;</l>
                     <l>Yet to fulfill thy wiſh, I wil relate</l>
                     <l>What I have learn'd. The firſt that keeps ſuch ſtate,</l>
                     <l>By whom, our lives and freedomes we forgoe,</l>
                     <l>The world hath call'd him Love; and he (you know</l>
                     <l n="75">But ſhal know better when he comes to be</l>
                     <l>A Lord to you, as now he is to me)</l>
                     <l>Is in his child-hood milde, fierce in his age;</l>
                     <l>'Tis beſt beleev'd of thoſe that feel his rage.</l>
                     <l n="80">The truth of this thou in thy ſelfe ſhalt finde,</l>
                     <l>I warn thee now, pray keep it in thy mind.</l>
                     <l>Of idle looſeneſſe, he is oft the childe;</l>
                     <l>With pleaſant fancies nouriſht, and is ſtil'd</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119955:7"/>
Or made a God by vain and fooliſh men:</l>
                     <l>And for a recompenſe, ſome meet their bane:</l>
                     <l n="85">Others, a harder ſlavery muſt endure,</l>
                     <l>Than many thouſand chains and bolts procure.</l>
                     <l>That other gallant Lord, is conquerour</l>
                     <l>Of conquering Rome, led captive by the faire</l>
                     <l>Egyptian Queen, with her perſwaſive Art,</l>
                     <l n="90">Who in his honours claimes the greateſt part:</l>
                     <l>For binding the worlds victor with her charmes,</l>
                     <l>His Trophees are all hers by right of armes.</l>
                     <l>The next is his adoptive ſonne, whoſe love</l>
                     <l>May ſeem more juſt, but doth no better prove:</l>
                     <l n="95">For though he did his loved <hi>Livia</hi> wed,</l>
                     <l>She was ſeduced from her husbands bed.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nero</hi> is third, diſdainfull, wicked, fierce<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>And yet a woman found a way to pierce</l>
                     <l>His angry ſoul. Behold <hi>Marcus</hi> the grave</l>
                     <l n="100">Wiſe Emperour is faire <hi>Fauſtina's</hi> ſlave:</l>
                     <l>Theſe two are tyrants: <hi>Dionyſius,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Alexander,</hi> both ſuſpicious,</l>
                     <l>And yet both loved: the laſt a juſt reward</l>
                     <l>Found of his cauſeleſſe feare. <hi>I</hi> know y' have heard</l>
                     <l n="105">Of him, who for <hi>Creuſa</hi> on the rock</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Antandrus</hi> mourn'd ſo long; whoſe-warlike ſtroke</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119955:8"/>
At once, reveng'd his friend, and wonne his love:</l>
                     <l>And of the youth whom <hi>Phedra</hi> could not move</l>
                     <l>T' abuſe his fathers bed; he left the place,</l>
                     <l n="110">And by his vertue loſt his life (for baſe</l>
                     <l>Unworthy loves to rage doe quickly change)</l>
                     <l>It kill'd her too; perhaps in juſt revenge</l>
                     <l>Of wronged <hi>Theſeus,</hi> ſlain <hi>Hyppolito,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And poore forſaken <hi>Ariadne:</hi> ſo</l>
                     <l n="115">It often proves that they who falſely blame</l>
                     <l>Another, in one breath themſelves condemne:</l>
                     <l>And who have guilty been of treachery,</l>
                     <l>Need not complain, if they deceived be.</l>
                     <l>Behold the brave <hi>Heros</hi> a captive made</l>
                     <l n="120">With all his fame, and twixt theſe ſiſters led:</l>
                     <l>Who, as he joy'd the death of th' one to ſee,</l>
                     <l>His death did eaſe the others miſery.</l>
                     <l>The next that followeth, though the world admire</l>
                     <l>His ſtrength, love bound him. Th' other full of ire</l>
                     <l n="125">Is great <hi>Achilles,</hi> he whoſe pittied fate</l>
                     <l>Was caus'd by love, <hi>Demophoon</hi> did not hate</l>
                     <l>Impatient <hi>Phyllis,</hi> yet procur'd her death.</l>
                     <l>This <hi>Jaſon</hi> is, he whom <hi>Medea</hi> hath</l>
                     <l>Oblig'd by miſchief; ſhe to her father prov'd</l>
                     <l n="130">Falſe, to her brother cruel; t' him ſhe lov'd</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119955:8"/>
Grew furious, by her merit over-priz'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hypſiphile</hi> comes next, mournfull, deſpis'd,</l>
                     <l>Wounded to ſee a ſtrangers love prevail</l>
                     <l>More then her owne a Greek. Here is the frail</l>
                     <l n="135">Fair <hi>Helena,</hi> with her the Shepherd boy,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe gazing looks hurt Greece, and ruin'd Troy.</l>
                     <l>'Mongſt other weeping ſouls, you heare the moan</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Enone</hi> makes, her <hi>Paris</hi> being gone.</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Menelaus,</hi> for the woe he had</l>
                     <l n="140">To loſe his wife. <hi>Hermione</hi> is ſad,</l>
                     <l>And cals her deare <hi>Oreſtes</hi> to her aid.</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Laodamia,</hi> that hapleſſe maide</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bewails</hi> Proteſilaus. Argia <hi>prov'd</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To <hi>Polinice</hi> more faithfull then the lov'd</l>
                     <l n="145">(But falſe and covetous) <hi>Amphiaraos</hi> wife.</l>
                     <l>The groanes, and ſighes of thoſe that loſe their life</l>
                     <l>By this kind Lord, in unrelenting flames</l>
                     <l>You heare: I cannot tell you halfe their names,</l>
                     <l>For they appeare not onely men that love,</l>
                     <l n="150">The gods themſelves, doe fill this mirtle grove:</l>
                     <l>You ſee faire <hi>Venus</hi> catch't by <hi>Vulcan's</hi> Art</l>
                     <l>With angry <hi>Mars: Proſerpina</hi> apart</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Pluto,</hi> jealous <hi>Juno,</hi> yellow hair'd</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Apollo,</hi> vvho the young god's courage dar'd;</l>
                     <l n="155">
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119955:9"/>
And of his trophees proud, laught at the bovv,</l>
                     <l>Which in Theſſalia gave him ſuch a blovv.</l>
                     <l>What ſhal I ſay? here, in a vvord, are all</l>
                     <l>The gods that <hi>Varro</hi> mentions, great and ſmall;</l>
                     <l>Each vvith innumerable bonds detain'd,</l>
                     <l n="160">And <hi>Jupiter</hi> before the chariot chain'd.</l>
                     <trailer>The end of the firſt Chapter.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="annotations">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119955:9"/>
                     <head>ANNOTATIONS
UPON
THE FIRST CHAPTER.</head>
                     <l>COnquerour, 87. line.] <hi>Julius Caeſar.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Egyptian Queen, 89. line.] <hi>Cleopatra.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Adoptive Sonne, 93. line.] <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A woman, 98. line.] Sabina Pompcia,</hi> whom
ſhe loved with much violence, yet killed her in
his anger; <hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Marcus the grave, 99. line.] Marcus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius,</hi>
who ſo doted on his wife <hi>Fauſtina,</hi> that
though hee had often notice ſhee abuſed his
bed, yet he would not divorce from her. <hi>Italian
Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Dionyſius, 101. line.] <hi>Tyrant of Syracuſe,</hi>
Italian Commentar.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Alexander, 102. line.]</hi> Tyrant of Theſſaly,
he was above meaſure fearefull, and yet was kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
by a wench whom he kept. The Story is not
worth relating, <hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Creuſa, 105. line.] Creuſa</hi> was wife to <hi>Aene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi>
before he ſee <hi>Dido,</hi> if ever he did ſee her. <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian
Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Antandrus, 106. line.] Antandrus</hi> is a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119955:10"/>
rock ſeated on the Aegean ſea, where he uſed
ſports many dayes together in honour of her fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls.
<hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And wonne his Love, 107. line.] Aeneas</hi> kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<hi>Turnus</hi> in a combat, and ſo revenged the
death of his friend <hi>Pallas,</hi> whom <hi>Turnus</hi> had
killed before: and wonne his miſtreſſe <hi>Lavinia,</hi>
in whom <hi>Turnus</hi> clamed intereſt, <hi>Virgil.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Phedra could not move, 108. line.] Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito</hi>
was ſonne to <hi>Theſeus</hi> by <hi>Hypolita</hi> the Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon,
<hi>Phedra</hi> wife to <hi>Theſeus</hi> was in love with
her ſonne in law <hi>Hypolito,</hi> and being juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
by him, accuſed him to his father, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
tempted her; on which he fled, and drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
in his flight, ſhe killed her ſelfe for grief of
his loſſe. <hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Forſaken Ariadne, 114. line.] Ariadne</hi> was
left aſleep in an Iland by <hi>Theſeus:</hi> who loved
this <hi>Phedra</hi> better then her, though ſhee had
brought him out of the labyrinth, and left her
father to goe with him: (a knowne Hiſtory.)</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Treachery, 117. line.]</hi> He had dealt treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly
with <hi>Ariadne,</hi> for the love of her ſiſter
<hi>Phedra,</hi> and ſhe required him with loving, and
falſely accuſing his ſon <hi>Hypolito.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Brave Heros, 119. line.] Theſeus <hi>led be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt</hi>
Phedra <hi>and</hi> Ariadne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Death, 121. line.]</hi> He rejoyced, as <hi>Petrarch</hi>
alledges, to ſee <hi>Phedra</hi> kill her ſelfe, becauſe ſhe
had been falſe to him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119955:10"/>
                        <hi>Miſery, 122. line.] Ariadne</hi> might rejoyce
both to ſee <hi>Phedra</hi> (for whom he had been falſe
to her) abuſe him, and to ſee his death before her
owne, <hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The next, 124. line.] Hercules.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Was cauſed by love, 126. line.]</hi> He was killed
by <hi>Paris</hi> in a treatie of marriage with his ſiſter
<hi>Polixena,</hi> whom <hi>Achilles</hi> loved.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Impatient Phillis, 127. line.] Demophon</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
occaſion to goe to Athens, ſet a time for his
returne, but ſtaying a little beyond his day, by
the croſſeneſſe of his affairs, and the winds, <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi>
jealous that he had forſaken her, very wiſely,
hanged her ſelfe, <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cruell, 130. line.]</hi> When <hi>Medea</hi> fled from her
father with <hi>Jaſon,</hi> ſhee tooke her brother with
her, and cut him in pieces, which ſhe ſcattered,
that the purſuers might be ſtayed by gathering up
his limbes, <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Grew furious, 131. line]</hi> Shee was revenged
on his inconſtancy and ingratitude after, by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
his new choice, <hi>Chreons</hi> daughter, a golden
veſtment, which was ſo inchanted or anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
that it ſtuck faſt to her, till it burnt her up.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hypſiphile, 132. line.]</hi> She entertaind <hi>Jaſon</hi> with
too much kindneſſe, as he paſſed by to Colchas.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Strangers love, 133. line.] Medea,</hi> whom
<hi>Jaſon</hi> brought back with him being no Grecian,
and therefore her diſgrace was the greater, by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119955:11"/>
the low eſteeme her rivall was in.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Shepherd boy, 135. line.] Paris</hi> who was bred
a ſhepherd by his mother, to avoid a propheſie,
that hee would bee the cauſe Troy ſhould bee
burned.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Enone, 138. line.]</hi> A Nymph in Ida, whom
<hi>Paris</hi> loved, when hee kept ſheepe on that
mountain.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>His wife, 140. line.] Helene,</hi> whom <hi>Paris</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
to Troy.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hermione, 140. line.]</hi> Shee was daughter to
<hi>Menelaus,</hi> and <hi>Helene</hi> being contracted to <hi>Ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes</hi>
firſt, ſhe was taken from him, and married
againſt her will to <hi>Pirhus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Oreſtes, 141. line.] <hi>He was ſonne to</hi> Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memnon,
<hi>beloved of</hi> Hermione.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Laodamia, 142. line.]</hi> She died for griefe on
the corps of <hi>Proteſilaus,</hi> when it came back from
Troy. <hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Argia, 143. line.]</hi> Wife to <hi>Polenice</hi> a The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,
ſhe was killed by <hi>Creon,</hi> for going to mourn
over her husbands grave.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amphyaraos wife, 145. line.] Eryphile,</hi> who
betrayed her husbands counſells, and was cauſe,
that againſt his will, hee tooke that journey, in
the which hee periſhed, <hi>Italian Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Proſerpina apart, 152. line.]</hi> To expreſſe
her anger, for <hi>Pluto</hi> had raviſhed her.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119955:11"/>
                        <hi>Young gods courage, 154. line.]</hi> Cupid.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>His Trophies, 155. line.]</hi> The skinne of <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thon</hi>
a Monſter, which hee had newly kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A blow, 156. line.]</hi> Strooke him in love
with <hi>Daphne,</hi> to try whoſe arrowes were ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt,
and teach him to brag.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119955:12"/>
                     <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <head>The Argument.</head>
                        <l>Brave Maſſiniſſa doth relate</l>
                        <l>His Love: Seleucus his hard fate.</l>
                     </argument>
                     <l>WEari'd, not ſatisfi'd, with much delight,</l>
                     <l>Now here, now there I turn'd my greedy ſight,</l>
                     <l>And many things I view'd: to write were long,</l>
                     <l>The time is ſhort, great ſtore of paſſions throng</l>
                     <l n="5">Within my breſt: when loe, a lovely paire,</l>
                     <l>Joyn'd hand in hand, who kindly talking were,</l>
                     <l>Drew my attention that way: their attire</l>
                     <l>And forrain language quickned my deſire</l>
                     <l>Of further knowledge, which I ſoon might gain;</l>
                     <l n="10">My kinde Interpreter did all explain.</l>
                     <l>When both I knew, I boldly then drew neare;</l>
                     <l>He lov'd our countrey, though ſhe made it feare.</l>
                     <l>O! <hi>Maſsiniſſa;</hi> I adjure thee by</l>
                     <l>Great <hi>Scipio,</hi> and her who from thine eye</l>
                     <l n="15">
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119955:12"/>
Drew manly tears (ſaid I) let it not be</l>
                     <l>A trouble, what I muſt demand of thee.</l>
                     <l>He lookt, and ſaid: I firſt deſire to know</l>
                     <l>Your name and qualitie; for well you ſhow</l>
                     <l>Y' have heard the combate in my wounded ſoul,</l>
                     <l n="20">When Love did Friendſhip, Friendſhip Love controul.</l>
                     <l>I am not worth your knowledge, my poore flame</l>
                     <l>Gives little light (ſaid I:) your royall fame,</l>
                     <l>Sets hearts on fire, that never ſee your face</l>
                     <l>But (pray you) ſay; are you two led in peace</l>
                     <l n="25">By him? (I ſhew'd their guide) your Hiſtory</l>
                     <l>Deſerves record: it ſeemeth ſtrange to me,</l>
                     <l>That faith and cruelty ſhould come ſo neare.</l>
                     <l>He ſaid; Thine owne expreſſions witneſſe beare.</l>
                     <l>Thou knowſt enough, yet I will all relate</l>
                     <l n="30">To thee, 't will ſomewhat eaſe my heavie ſtate.</l>
                     <l>On that brave man my heart was fixt ſo much,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Lelius</hi> love to him could be but ſuch;</l>
                     <l>Where ere his colours marched, I was nigh,</l>
                     <l>And Fortune did attend with victory:</l>
                     <l n="35">Yet ſtill his merit call'd for more then ſhe</l>
                     <l>Could give; or any elſe deſerve but he.</l>
                     <l>When to the Weſt the Romane Eagles came</l>
                     <l>My ſelf was alſo there; and catcht a flame,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119955:13"/>
A purer never burnt in Lovers breſt:</l>
                     <l n="40">But ſuch a joy could not be long poſſeſt!</l>
                     <l>Our nuptiall knot (alas!) he ſoone untide,</l>
                     <l>Who had more power then all the world beſide!</l>
                     <l>He car'd not for our ſighes; and though 't be true</l>
                     <l>That he divided us, his worth I knew:</l>
                     <l n="45">He muſt be blinde that cannot ſee the Sunne,</l>
                     <l>But by ſtrict juſtice Love is quite undone:</l>
                     <l>Counſel from ſuch a friend gave ſuch a ſtroke</l>
                     <l>To Love, it almoſt ſplit, as on a rock:</l>
                     <l>For as my father I his wrath did feare,</l>
                     <l n="50">And as a ſonne he in my love was deare;</l>
                     <l>Brothers in age we were, him I obey'd,</l>
                     <l>But with a troubled ſoul and look diſmaid:</l>
                     <l>Thus my dear halfe had an untimely death,</l>
                     <l>She priz'd her freedome far above her breath;</l>
                     <l n="55">And I th' unhappy inſtrument was made;</l>
                     <l>Such force th' intreaty and intreater had!</l>
                     <l>I rather choſe my ſelf then him t' offend,</l>
                     <l>And ſent the poyſon brought her to her end:</l>
                     <l>With what ſad thoughts I know, and ſhee'l confeſſe,</l>
                     <l n="60">And you, if you have ſenſe of Love, may gueſſe;</l>
                     <l>No heire ſhe left me, but my tedious moan;</l>
                     <l>And though in her my hopes, and joyes were gone,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119955:13"/>
She was of lower value then my faith!</l>
                     <l>But now farewell, and trie if this troup hath</l>
                     <l n="65">Another wonder; for the time is leſſe</l>
                     <l>Then is the taske: I pittied their diſtreſſe,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſhort joy ended in ſo ſharp a woe:</l>
                     <l>My ſoft heart melted: As they onward goe,</l>
                     <l>This youth for his part, I perhaps could love</l>
                     <l n="70">(She ſaid) but nothing can my minde remove</l>
                     <l>From hatred of the Nation; He replide,</l>
                     <l>Good <hi>Sophonisba</hi> you may leave this pride,</l>
                     <l>Your City hath by us been three times beat,</l>
                     <l>The laſt of which (you know) we laid it flat.</l>
                     <l n="75">Pray uſe theſe words t' another, not to me</l>
                     <l>(Said ſhe) if Africk mourned, Italy</l>
                     <l>Needs not rejoyce; ſearch your records, and there</l>
                     <l>See what you gained by the Punick warre,</l>
                     <l>He that was friend to both, without reply</l>
                     <l n="80">A little ſmiling, vaniſht from mine eye</l>
                     <l>Amongſt the croud: As one in doubtfull way</l>
                     <l>At every ſtep looks round, and fears to ſtray,</l>
                     <l>(Care ſtops his journey) ſo the varied ſtore</l>
                     <l>Of Lovers ſtaid me, to examine more,</l>
                     <l n="85">And trie what kinde of fire burnt every breſt:</l>
                     <l>When on my left hand ſtrayed from the reſt</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119955:14"/>
Was one, whoſe looke expreſt a ready minde</l>
                     <l>In ſeeking what he joy'd, (yet ſham'd to finde;)</l>
                     <l>He freely gave away his deareſt wife,</l>
                     <l n="90">(A new found way to ſave a Lovers life)</l>
                     <l>She, though ſhe joy'd, yet bluſhed at the change<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>As they recounted their affections ſtrange,</l>
                     <l>And for their Syria mourn'd; I tooke the way</l>
                     <l>Of theſe three Ghoſts, who ſeem'd their courſe to ſtay,</l>
                     <l n="95">And take another path: The firſt I held</l>
                     <l>And bid him turne; he ſtarted, and beheld</l>
                     <l>Me with a troubled look, hearing my tongue</l>
                     <l>Was Romane, ſuch a pauſe he made, as ſprung</l>
                     <l>From ſome deep thought; then ſpake as if inſpir'd,</l>
                     <l n="100">For to my wiſh, he told what I deſir'd</l>
                     <l>To know: <hi>Seleucus</hi> is (ſaid he) my name,</l>
                     <l>This is <hi>Antiochus</hi> my ſonne, whoſe fame</l>
                     <l>Hath reacht your eare; he warred much with Rome,</l>
                     <l>But Reaſon oft by Power is overcome.</l>
                     <l n="105">This woman, once my Wife, doth now belong</l>
                     <l>To him; I gave her, and it was no wrong</l>
                     <l>In our Religion; it ſtaid his death,</l>
                     <l>Threatned by Love; <hi>Stratonica</hi> ſhe hath</l>
                     <l>To name: ſo now we may enjoy one ſtate,</l>
                     <l n="110">And our faſt friendſhip ſhal out-laſt all date.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119955:14"/>
She from her height was willing to deſcend;</l>
                     <l>I quit my joy; he rather choſe his end</l>
                     <l>Then our offence; and in his prime had dide,</l>
                     <l>Had not the wiſe Phyſician been our guide:</l>
                     <l n="115">Silence in Love orecame his vitall part;</l>
                     <l>His Love was force, his Silence vertuous Art.</l>
                     <l>A fathers tender care made me agree</l>
                     <l>To this ſtrange change. This ſaid, he turn'd from me,</l>
                     <l>As changing his deſigne, with ſuch a pace,</l>
                     <l n="120">Ere I could take my leave, h' had quit the place.</l>
                     <l>After the Ghoſt was carried from mine eye</l>
                     <l>Amazedly I walkt; nor could untie</l>
                     <l>My minde from his ſad ſtory; till my friend</l>
                     <l>Admoniſht me, and ſaid: You muſt not lend</l>
                     <l n="125">Attention thus to every thing you meet;</l>
                     <l>You know the number's great, and time is fleet.</l>
                     <l>More naked priſoners this triumph had</l>
                     <l>Then <hi>Xerxes</hi> ſouldiers in his army led:</l>
                     <l>And ſtretched further then my ſight could reach<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l n="130">Of ſeverall Countreyes, and of differing ſpeech.</l>
                     <l>One of a thouſand were not knowne to me,</l>
                     <l>Yet might thoſe few make a large Hiſtory.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Perſeus</hi> was one; and well you know the way</l>
                     <l>How he was catched by <hi>Andromida:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="135">
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119955:15"/>
She was a lovely brownet, black her haire</l>
                     <l>And eyes. <hi>Narciſſus</hi> too, the fooliſh faire,</l>
                     <l>Who for his owne love did himſelfe deſtroy;</l>
                     <l>He had ſo much, he nothing could enjoy.</l>
                     <l>And ſhe, who for his loſſe, deep ſorrow's ſlave,</l>
                     <l n="140">Chang'd to a voyce, dwells in a hollow cave.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iphis</hi> was there, who haſted his owne fate,</l>
                     <l>He lov'd another, but himſelfe did hate;</l>
                     <l>And many moe condemn'd like woes to prove,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe life was made a curſe by hapleſſe love.</l>
                     <l n="145">Some modern Lovers in my minde remain,</l>
                     <l>But thoſe to reckon here were needleſſe pain.</l>
                     <l>The two, whoſe conſtant loves for ever laſt,</l>
                     <l>On whom the winds wait while they build their neſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>For <hi>Halcion</hi> dayes poore labouring ſaylers pleaſe,</l>
                     <l n="150">And in rough winter calme the boyſtrous ſeas.</l>
                     <l>Far off the thoughtfull <hi>Aeſacus,</hi> in queſt</l>
                     <l>Of his <hi>Epiria,</hi> findes a rocky reſt,</l>
                     <l>Then diveth in the floods, then mounts i'th' aire.</l>
                     <l>And ſhe who ſtole old <hi>Niſus</hi> purple haire</l>
                     <l>His cruel daughter, I obſerv'd to fly.</l>
                     <l n="155">Swift <hi>Atalanta</hi> ran for victory,</l>
                     <l>But three gold apples, and a lovely face,</l>
                     <l>Slackt her quick paces, till ſhe loſt the race:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119955:15"/>
She brought <hi>Hippomanes</hi> along, and joy'd</l>
                     <l n="160">That he, as others, had not been deſtroy'd,</l>
                     <l>But of the victory could ſingly boaſt.</l>
                     <l>I ſaw amidſt the vain, and fabulous hoaſt,</l>
                     <l>Faire <hi>Galatea</hi> lean'd on <hi>Atis</hi> breſt;</l>
                     <l>Rude <hi>Polyphemus</hi> noiſe diſturbs their reſt.</l>
                     <l n="165">
                        <hi>Glaucus</hi> alone ſwims through the dangerous ſeas,</l>
                     <l>And miſſing her who ſhould his phanſie pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>Curſeth the cruels Love transform'd her ſhape.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Canens</hi> laments that <hi>Picus</hi> could not ſcape</l>
                     <l>The dire enchantreſſe; he in Italy</l>
                     <l n="170">Was once a King, now a pie'd Bird; for ſhe</l>
                     <l>Who made him ſuch, chang'd not his clothes nor name,</l>
                     <l>His Princely habit ſtill appears the ſame.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Egeria,</hi> while ſhe wept, became a Well:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Scylla</hi> (a horrid rock by <hi>Circes</hi> ſpell)</l>
                     <l n="175">Hath made infamous the Sicilian ſtrand.</l>
                     <l>Next, ſhe who holdeth in her trembling hand</l>
                     <l>A guilty knife, her right hand writ her name.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pygmalion</hi> next, with his live miſtreſſe came.</l>
                     <l>Sweet <hi>Aganippe,</hi> and <hi>Caſtalia</hi> have</l>
                     <l n="180">A thouſand more; all there ſung by the brave</l>
                     <l>And deathleſſe Poets, on their faire banks plac'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cydippe</hi> by an apple fool'd at laſt.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="annotations">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:119955:16"/>
                     <head>ANNOTATIONS
UPON
THE SECOND CHAPTER.</head>
                     <p>A <hi>Lovely pair, 5. line.] Maſſiniſſa</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonisba:</hi>
The ſtory runs thus, <hi>Maſſiniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi>
King of a part of <hi>Numidia</hi> an aſſociate of
the Romanes, loving and much beloved of <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio:
Sophonisba</hi> was daughter to <hi>Asdrubale,</hi>
ſon of <hi>Giſco,</hi> a Principal man in the Citie of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage:
her father married her to <hi>Syphax,</hi> a
more conſiderable King of the ſame Countrey,
then <hi>Maſſiniſſa,</hi> and an aſſociate alſo of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,
with intention to debauch him from the
Romane friendſhip, which it did accordingly. It
came to paſſe in the progreſſe of the warre, that
<hi>Maſſiniſſa</hi> tooke <hi>Syphax</hi> priſoner, and entered
Cirrha his principall City victor: <hi>Sophonisba</hi>
preſented her ſelfe before him at the gate of the
Caſtle, and being beautifull and eloquent, to both
which her affliction added luſtre, ſhe beſought
him to take her for his priſoner, and either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
her from being led in triumph to Rome, or
kill her. <hi>Maſſiniſſa</hi> was ſoon taken, and as ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119955:16"/>
promiſed to performe her deſire, which
that hee might the more eaſily doe, hee married
her preſently. When he came to <hi>Scipio</hi> (after
much commendation and honourable intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
beſtowed upon him in publick) hee drew
him aſide, and reproved him ſharply for this raſh
act (being afraid that <hi>Sophonisba</hi> would make
him for her Countrey, as ſhe had done her other
husband.) <hi>Maſſiniſſa</hi> retired to his Tent, and
after a long inward debate, and many tears, at
laſt he compoſed a cup full of poyſon, and writes
to her with it, That ſince he could not performe
the firſt part of his promiſe, to make her free, (as
by marrying her hee hoped to have done) hee
would yet keep the laſt; deſires her to remember
whoſe daughter ſhe was, and that ſhe had been
wife to two Kings. When ſhee read the letter,
ſhe ſaid no more, but, If this be the beſt token my
Husband hath to ſend me, I accept it willingly;
but tell him, It would have grieved me leſſe, if
my marriage bed had not been ſo near my grave:
and with ſuch reſolution as theſe times thought
vertuous, ſhee drank up the poyſon chearfully.
<hi>Titus Livius.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That Lelius Love, 32. line.] Lelius</hi> was bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
friend to <hi>Scipio,</hi> yet <hi>Maſſiniſſas</hi> Love equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
that of <hi>Lelius.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Romane Eagles, 37. line.]</hi> The Romane
Enſinges, meaning <hi>Scipio,</hi> with the Romane ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119955:17"/>
for they carried an Eagle in their colours.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Seleucus, 101. line.]</hi> The ſtory is cleare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
here, That <hi>Seleucus</hi> King of Syria, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
married <hi>Stratonica,</hi> a young and beautifull
Ladie, <hi>Antiochus</hi> his ſonne by a former wife,
became deſperately in love with her, and
concealing it out of ſhame, or feare, or both, hee
fell ſick almoſt to death, which the Phyſician
finding by his Art, told the father there was no
ſafetie for his ſon, but by beſtowing his mother in
law on him: to which the father joyfully yeilded</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>With Rome, 103. line.]</hi> It was not this <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus</hi>
that had warre with the Romanes, but
another long after him, which <hi>Petrarch</hi> knew
well enough, but uſeth a figure of purpoſe to
mention <hi>Antiochus</hi> the great.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In his army, 128. line.]</hi> Being as they ſay,
700000. men.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Perſeus was one, 133. line]</hi> He was ſonne
of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Danaë.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>By Andromida, 134 line] Andromida</hi> was
an Ethiopian. The hiſtory is known, he ſaw her
tied naked to a rock, when he went to kill the
ſea Monſter that ſhould have devoured her.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iphis was there, 141. line.] Iphis</hi> hanged
himſelfe becauſe his miſtris deſpiſed him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Conſtant Loves, 147. line] Halcion,</hi> ſonne of
<hi>Aeolus,</hi> and <hi>Ceica</hi> daughter of <hi>Lucifer:</hi> He was
drowned in his return from conſulting with the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119955:17"/>
Oracle, ſhe having had an ominous dream, went
to the ſhore, where ſhee found his dead body
newly caſt up, and as ſhee was about to caſt her
ſelfe into the Sea, they were both turned into lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
birds of his name, <hi>Halcion,</hi> it is the bird cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
the Kings-fiſher; they build on the ſhore,
and the weather is calme all the while they
are hatching their young.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aeſacus, 151. line.] Aeſacus</hi> was ſonne to
<hi>Priamus. Epiria</hi> whom hee loved, flying from
his purſuit, was bit with a Serpent and died of
the wound, for griefe of which misfortune, hee
went to the top of a Rock, &amp; leapt into the Sea,
where <hi>Thetis</hi> in compaſſion, transformed him
into a bird, called a Dydaper or Diver.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>His cruell daughter, 155. line.] Scilla,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
to <hi>Niſus</hi> King of Megara; when <hi>Minos</hi> war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
againſt her father, and could not overcome
him, by reaſon of his purple hair in his head; ſhe
ſtole the haire and gave it to him, in hope to
gain his affection: By this means <hi>Minos</hi> became
victor, but in deteſtation of her unnaturall fact
rejected her, who being baniſhed and deſolate,
wandered till ſhe became a Larke: Her father
was turned into a Merling, and purſues her e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
ſince.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Swift Atalanta, 156. line.]</hi> A knowne Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,
all her ſuiters muſt out-run her, or bee kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led;
and ſhe being too ſwift to be matched with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119955:18"/>
ſpeed, <hi>Hyppomanes</hi> tooke three golden apples,
and caſt firſt one a good way off: then as ſhee
ran aſide to catch it, hee got ground of her, and
when ſhee approched hee threw another, and a
third, till he obtained the victory, by this cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
(not without her conſent.)</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Faire Galatea, 163. line.] Galatea</hi> was
daughter to <hi>Neptune:</hi> her lover <hi>Atis</hi> and ſhee
being together, his Giant rivall <hi>Poliphemus</hi>
came thither, and killed him with a great ſtone
as he fled.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Glaucus alone, 165. line.] Glaucus</hi> was a
fiſher, and ſeeing that the new haild fiſh by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
a kinde of herb upon the banke, revived,
and leapt againe into the Sea; He tried the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion
himſelfe, and followed them, by which
means he became a Sea-god: Hee loved <hi>Scilla,</hi>
but <hi>Circe</hi> loving him, and ſeeing her ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed
by him for the love he bare to <hi>Galatea;
Circe</hi> transformed her rivall into a Rocke: ſo as
<hi>Glaucus</hi> ſwims along without his Miſtreſſe, and
curſeth the loving Witch that cauſed it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Canens laments, 168 line.] Canens</hi> was
wife to <hi>Picus,</hi> a King in Italy of old: <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce</hi>
transformed him alſo to a Magpie, becauſe ſhe
could not obtain his love.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aegeria while ſhe wept, 173. line.] Aegeria</hi>
was a Nymph, or Goddeſſe that converſt with
<hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> in his ſolitary retirements,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119955:18"/>
whileſt he compoſed the Romane lawes, being
the firſt King of Rome after <hi>Romulus,</hi> So ſayes
<hi>Plutatch,</hi> and <hi>Titus Livius:</hi> yet <hi>Livius</hi> ſaith
alſo ſhe was his wife, by which it ſhould ſeeme,
that being as wiſe as her husband, ſhe had a good
hand in the buſineſſe. The Poets fained her to
weep her ſelf into a Well after his death, becauſe
there was a Well in the middle of that Grove
which he made for their conſultations.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Scilla a horrid Rock, 174. line.]</hi> See above in
the Annotations, 165.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Infamous the Cicilian ſtrand, 175. line.]</hi> That
is, hath made it dangerous for paſſengers.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Her trembling hand, 176. line.] Cannace,</hi>
daughter to <hi>Eolus,</hi> having had a childe by her
brother, her father cauſed cut the childe in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
and commanded her to kill her ſelfe, which
ſhe being compelled to reſolve on, writ firſt to
her brother, with the pen in the one hand, and a
knife in the other, to give him notice of her end,
that he might burie her childe and her.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>His live Miſtris, 178. line.] Pigmalions</hi>
miſtreſſe was a ſtatue of his owne cutting, on
which he grew enamoured, and prayed till it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
a live woman.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aganippe, and Caſtalia, 179. line.] Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nippe</hi>
and <hi>Caſtalia</hi> are two Fountains in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſus,
ſacred to the Muſes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Faire banks placed,</hi> 181.] Becauſe the Poets
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119955:19"/>
doe all drinke of theſe two Wells: <hi>Petrarch</hi>
will have the bankes to bee their ordinary reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
alive and dead.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cydippe by an apple foold, 182. line.]</hi> Her
Lover writ an oath, That ſhee ſhould marry
him upon an apple, and dropt it in <hi>Apollos</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
which ſhe finding and reading, he made her
beleeve ſhee had ſworne to make him her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119955:19"/>
                     <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <head>The Argument.</head>
                        <l>Love woundeth <hi>Petrarchs</hi> wary heart,</l>
                        <l>Who well deſcribes that dying ſmart.</l>
                     </argument>
                     <l>MY heart was fill'd with wonder and amaze,</l>
                     <l>As one ſtruck dumb, in ſilence ſtands at gaze</l>
                     <l>Expecting Counſel, when my friend drew neare,</l>
                     <l>And ſaid: What doe you looke? why ſtay you here?</l>
                     <l>What mean you? know you not that I am one</l>
                     <l n="5">Of theſe? and muſt attend? pray, let's be gone</l>
                     <l>Deare friend (ſaid I) conſider what deſire</l>
                     <l>To learn the reſt hath ſet my heart on fire;</l>
                     <l>My owne haſte ſtops me. I beleeve't (ſaid he)</l>
                     <l>And I will help; 'tis not forbidden me.</l>
                     <l n="10">This Noble man, on whom the others wait,</l>
                     <l>(You ſee) is <hi>Pompey,</hi> juſtly call'd, The great:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:119955:20"/>
                        <hi>Cornelia</hi> followeth, weeping his hard fate,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Ptolomies</hi> unworthy cauſeleſſe hate.</l>
                     <l n="15">You ſee farre off the Grecian General;</l>
                     <l>His baſe wife, with <hi>Aegiſthus</hi> wrought his fal:</l>
                     <l>Behold them there, and judge if Love be blinde.</l>
                     <l>But here are Lovers of another kinde,</l>
                     <l>And other faith they kept, <hi>Lyncus</hi> was ſav'd</l>
                     <l n="20">By <hi>Hypermneſtra</hi>: <hi>Pyramus</hi> bereav'd</l>
                     <l>Himſelfe of life, thinking his miſtreſſe ſlain:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thisbes</hi> like end, ſhortned her mourning pain.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Leander</hi> ſwimming often, drown'd at laſt;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hero</hi> her faire ſelfe from her window caſt.</l>
                     <l n="25">Courteous <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes</hi> his long ſtay doth mourn;</l>
                     <l>His chaſte wife prayeth for his ſafe return,</l>
                     <l>While <hi>Circes</hi> amarous charmes her prayers controule,</l>
                     <l>And rather vexe then pleaſe his vertuous ſoule.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Amilcars</hi> ſonne, who made great Rome afraid,</l>
                     <l n="30">By a mean wench of Spain is captive led.</l>
                     <l>This <hi>Hipſicrates</hi> is, the vertuous faire,</l>
                     <l>Who for her husbands deare Love cut her haire</l>
                     <l>And ſerv'd in all his warres: This is the wife</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Brutus; Portia,</hi> conſtant in her life</l>
                     <l n="35">And death: This <hi>Julia</hi> is, who ſeems to mone,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Pompey</hi> loved beſt, when ſhe was gone.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119955:20"/>
Looke here and ſee the Patriarch much abus'd</l>
                     <l>Who twice ſeven years for his fair <hi>Rachel</hi> choos'd</l>
                     <l>To ſerve: O! powerfull love increaſt by woe!</l>
                     <l n="40">His father this: Now ſee his Grandſire goe</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Sarah</hi> from his home. This cruel Love</l>
                     <l>O'recame good <hi>David;</hi> ſo it had power to move</l>
                     <l>His righteous heart to that abhorrid crime,</l>
                     <l>For which he ſorrowed all his following time.</l>
                     <l n="45">Juſt ſuch like errour ſoil'd his wiſe ſonnes fame,</l>
                     <l>For whoſe idolatry Gods anger came;</l>
                     <l>Here's he who in one houre could love and hate:</l>
                     <l>Here <hi>Tamar</hi> full of anguiſh wailes her ſtate;</l>
                     <l>Her brother <hi>Abſolon</hi> attempts t' appeaſe</l>
                     <l n="50">Her grieved ſoul. <hi>Sampſon</hi> takes care to pleaſe</l>
                     <l>His fancy; and appeares more ſtrong then wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Who in a traitreſſe boſome ſleeping lies.</l>
                     <l>Amongſt thoſe pikes and ſpeares which guard the place,</l>
                     <l>Love, wine, and ſleep, a beauteous widdowes face</l>
                     <l n="55">And pleaſing Art hath <hi>Holopherues</hi> taine;</l>
                     <l>She backe again retires, who hath him ſlain,</l>
                     <l>With her one maide, bearing the horrid head</l>
                     <l>In haſte, and thanks God that ſo wel ſhe ſped.</l>
                     <l>The next is <hi>Sichem,</hi> he who found his death,</l>
                     <l n="60">In circumciſion, his father hath</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119955:21"/>
Like miſchiefe felt; the City all did prove</l>
                     <l>The ſame effect of his raſh violent Love.</l>
                     <l>You ſee <hi>Ahaſhuerus</hi> how well he bears</l>
                     <l>His loſſe; a new love ſoon expels his cares:</l>
                     <l n="65">This cure in this diſeaſe doth ſeldome fail,</l>
                     <l>One naile beſt driveth out another nail.</l>
                     <l>If you would ſee Love mingled oft with hate,</l>
                     <l>Bitter with ſweet; behold fierce <hi>Herods</hi> ſtate,</l>
                     <l>Beſet with Love and crueltie at once:</l>
                     <l n="70">Enraged firſt, then late his fault bemoans,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Mariamne</hi> cals; thoſe three faire Dames</l>
                     <l>(Who in the liſt of Captives write their names)</l>
                     <l>Pocris, Deidamia, Artimeſia <hi>were</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>All good, the other three as wicked are:</l>
                     <l n="75">Semiramis, Biblis, <hi>and</hi> Myrrha <hi>nam'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who of their crooked wayes are now aſham'd:</l>
                     <l>Here be the erring Knights in ancient ſcroules,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lancelot, Triſtram,</hi> and the vulgar ſoules</l>
                     <l>That wait on theſe; <hi>Jiniver,</hi> and the faire</l>
                     <l n="80">
                        <hi>Iſond,</hi> with other Lovers: and the pair</l>
                     <l>Who, as they walke together, ſeeme to plain</l>
                     <l>Their juſt, but cruel fate, by one hand ſlaine;</l>
                     <l>Thus he diſcours'd: and as a man that feares</l>
                     <l>Approching harme, when he a trumpet heares,</l>
                     <l n="85">
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119955:21"/>
Starts at the blow ere touch't, my frighted blood</l>
                     <l>Retir'd; as one rais'd from his Tombe I ſtood:</l>
                     <l>When by my ſide I ſpi'd a lovely maide,</l>
                     <l>(No Turtle ever purer whiteneſſe had)</l>
                     <l>And ſtraight was caught (who lately ſwore I would</l>
                     <l n="90">Defend me from a man at Armes) nor could</l>
                     <l>Reſiſt the wounds of words with motion grac't;</l>
                     <l>The image yet is in my phanſie plac't.</l>
                     <l>My friend was willing to increaſe my woe,</l>
                     <l>And ſmiling whiſperd; You alone may goe</l>
                     <l n="95">Conferre with whom you pleaſe, for now we are</l>
                     <l>All ſtained with one crime: My ſullen care</l>
                     <l>Was like to theirs, who are more griev'd to know</l>
                     <l>Anothers happineſſe then their owne woe:</l>
                     <l>For ſeeing her, who had enthral'd my minde,</l>
                     <l n="100">Live free in peace, and no diſturbance finde:</l>
                     <l>And ſeeing that I knew my hurt too late,</l>
                     <l>And that her beauty was my dying fate:</l>
                     <l>Love, jealouſie, and envie held my ſight</l>
                     <l>So fixt on that faire face, no other light</l>
                     <l n="105">I could behold; like one who in the rage</l>
                     <l>Of ſickneſſe greedily his thirſt would ſwage</l>
                     <l>With hurtfull drinke, which doth his palat pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>Thus (blinde and deaf t'all other joyes are eaſe)</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:119955:22"/>
So many doubtful wayes I followed her</l>
                     <l n="110">The memory ſtill ſhakes my ſoul with feare.</l>
                     <l>Since when mine eyes are moiſt, and view the ground;</l>
                     <l>My heart is heavie, and my ſteps have found</l>
                     <l>A ſolitary dwelling 'mongſt the woods,</l>
                     <l>I ſtray ore rocks, and fountains, hils and floods:</l>
                     <l n="115">Since when ſuch ſtore my ſcattered papers hold</l>
                     <l>Of thoughts, of tears, of inke; which oft I fold,</l>
                     <l>Unfold, and teare: Since when I know the ſcope</l>
                     <l>Of Love, and what they feare, and what they hope;</l>
                     <l>And how they live that in his Cloyſter dwell,</l>
                     <l n="120">The skilfull in their face may reade it well.</l>
                     <l>Mean while I ſee, how fierce and gallant ſhe</l>
                     <l>Cares not for me, nor for my miſery,</l>
                     <l>Proud of her vertue, and my overthrow:</l>
                     <l>And on the other ſide (if ought I know)</l>
                     <l n="125">This Lord, who hath the world in triumph led,</l>
                     <l>She keeps in feare; thus all my hopes are dead,</l>
                     <l>No ſtrength nor courage left, nor can I be</l>
                     <l>Reveng'd, as I expected once; for he,</l>
                     <l>Who tortures me and others, is abuſed</l>
                     <l n="130">By her; ſhe'le not be caught, and long hath uſed</l>
                     <l>(Rebellious as ſhe is!) to ſhun his vvarres,</l>
                     <l>And is a Sunne amidſt the leſſer ſtarres.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119955:22"/>
Her grace, ſmiles, ſlights, her words in order ſet;</l>
                     <l>Her haire diſperſt, or in a golden net;</l>
                     <l n="135">Her eyes enflaming with a light divine</l>
                     <l>So burn my heart, I dare no more repine.</l>
                     <l>Ah, who is able fully to expreſſe</l>
                     <l>Her pleaſing wayes, her merit? no exceſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>No bold Hyperboles I need to feare,</l>
                     <l n="140">My humble ſtile cannot enough come neare</l>
                     <l>The truth; my words are like a little ſtream</l>
                     <l>Compar'd with th' Ocean, ſo large a theame</l>
                     <l>Is that high prayſe; new worth, not ſeen before,</l>
                     <l>Is ſeen in her, and can be ſeen no more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l n="145">Therefore all tongues are ſilenced; and I,</l>
                     <l>Her priſoner now, ſee her at liberty:</l>
                     <l>And night and day implore (O unjuſt fate!)</l>
                     <l>She neither heares, nor pitties my eſtate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hard ſawes of Love! But though a partiall lot</l>
                     <l n="150">I plainly ſee in this, yet muſt I not</l>
                     <l>Refuſe to ſerve: the gods, as well as men,</l>
                     <l>With like reward of old have felt like pain.</l>
                     <l>Now knovv I hovv the minde it ſelfe doth part,</l>
                     <l>(Novv making peace, novv vvarre, novv truce) vvhat art</l>
                     <l n="155">Poore Lovers uſe to hide their ſtinging vvoe:</l>
                     <l>And hovv their bloud novv comes, and novv doth goe</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119955:23"/>
Betwixt their heart and cheeks, by ſhame or feare:</l>
                     <l>How they be eloquent, yet ſpeechleſſe are:</l>
                     <l>And how they both wayes leane, they watch and ſleep,</l>
                     <l n="160">Languiſh to death, yet life and vigor keep:</l>
                     <l>I trode the pathes made happy by her feet,</l>
                     <l>And ſearch the foe, I am afraid to meet.</l>
                     <l>I know how Lovers metamorphos'd are</l>
                     <l>To that they love: I know what tedious care</l>
                     <l n="165">I feele; how vain my joy, how oft I change</l>
                     <l>Deſigne, and countenance; and (which is ſtrange)</l>
                     <l>I live without a ſoul: I know the way</l>
                     <l>To cheat my ſelfe a thouſand times a day:</l>
                     <l>I know to follow whiles I flee my fire:</l>
                     <l n="170">I freeze when preſent; abſent, my deſire</l>
                     <l>Is hot: I know what cruel rigour Love</l>
                     <l>Practiſeth on the minde, and doth remove</l>
                     <l>All reaſon thence; and how he racks the heart;</l>
                     <l>And how a ſoul, hath neither ſtrength nor Art</l>
                     <l n="175">Without a helper to reſiſt his blowes;</l>
                     <l>And how he flees, and how his darts he throwes:</l>
                     <l>And how his threats the feareful Lover feels;</l>
                     <l>And hovv he robs by force, and hovv he ſteales:</l>
                     <l>Hovv oft his vvheels turne round (novv high, novv lovv)</l>
                     <l n="180">With hovv uncertain hope, hovv certain vvo:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:119955:23"/>
Hovv all his promiſes be voyd of faith,</l>
                     <l>And hovv a fire hid in our bones he hath;</l>
                     <l>Hovv in our vains he makes a ſecret vvound,</l>
                     <l>Whence open flames and death doe ſoone abound.</l>
                     <l n="185">In ſumme, I knovv hovv giddy and hovv vain</l>
                     <l>Be Lovers lives; vvhat feare and boldneſſe raigne</l>
                     <l>In all their vvayes; hovv every ſvveet is paide,</l>
                     <l>And vvith a double vveight of ſovvre allaide:</l>
                     <l>I alſo knovv their cuſtomes, ſighs, and ſongs;</l>
                     <l n="190">Their ſudden muteneſſe, and their ſtammering tongues,</l>
                     <l>Hovv ſhort their joy, hovv long their pain doth laſt,</l>
                     <l>Hovv Wormvvood ſpoyleth all their hunni's taſte.</l>
                     <trailer>The end of the third Chapter.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="annotations">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:119955:24"/>
                     <head>ANNOTATIONS
UPON
THE THIRD CHAPTER.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>COrnelia followeth, 13. line] Cornelia</hi>
was laſt wife to <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, and
wept for the loſſe of his honour, being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
at Pharſalia by <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> and for
his death, being killed in her armes by <hi>Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomies</hi>
command, without other cauſe, but to
gaine favour of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who had got the better:
therefore it is juſtly called by <hi>Petrarch, Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi>
unworthy cauſeleſſe hate in the next
line.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Grecian Generall, 15. line.] Agamemnon</hi>
Generall of the Grecians that went againſt
Troy: He was in love with <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
to <hi>Priamus,</hi> whom hee carried home cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
with him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aegiſthus, 16. line.]</hi> In his abſence <hi>Clitem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtra</hi>
his wife entertained another, with
whom ſhe conſpired his death at his returne,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119955:24"/>
in this ſort; ſhe gave him a ſhirt cloſe at top,
and as hee was ſearching for a place to put
forth his head <hi>Aegiſthus</hi> killed him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lyncus was ſaved, 19. line.] Lyncus</hi> was
one of the ſonnes of <hi>Danoe.</hi> The Hiſtory runs
thus, <hi>Aegiſthus</hi> and <hi>Danoe</hi> being two brothers,
<hi>Aegiſthus</hi> had 50. daughters, and <hi>Danoe</hi> had
50. ſonnes; <hi>Danoe</hi> offered his ſonnes in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
to <hi>Aegiſthus</hi> his daughters, which <hi>Aegiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hus</hi>
would by no means conſent to, till the
other compelled him by force of armes: Then
hee gave a ſecret command to his daughters,
every one to kill her husband in the night:
They all obeyed, except <hi>Hypermnestra,</hi> who
ſpared her husband <hi>Lyncus</hi> and did not kill
him: A poore courteſie, but that the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
of the reſt made it ſeeme a great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pyramus bereaved, 20. line.]</hi> It is a known
Story, that <hi>Pyramus</hi> and <hi>Thisbe</hi> having made
an appointment in a wood, ſhe came thither
firſt, where ſeeing a Lion approch, ſhe let fall
her mantle, and hid herſelfe among the buſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es:
Her Lover came within a little while af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and ſee her mantle torne or trampled by
the Lion; This made him imagine ſhee had
beene devoured: ſo he killed himſelfe on the
place.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thisbies like end, 22. line.]</hi> When ſhee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119955:25"/>
came out of the buſhes and found him dead,
ſhee killed her ſelfe too with the ſame wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Leander ſwimming often, 23. line.]</hi> The ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
is cleare of it ſelfe, that <hi>Leander</hi> having uſed
to ſwimme the Helleſpont, was drowned one
time in a ſtorme, which when <hi>Hero</hi> ſee, in a
window, where ſhe ſtood expecting his arrivall,
for he periſhed neare the ſhoare, ſhee caſt her
ſelfe down from thence into the ſea.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Courteous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes, 25. line.]</hi> Hee ſtayed ten
yeares from his wife at the ſiege of Troy, and
tenne yeares more were ſpent in his journey
home.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>His chaſte wife, 26. line.]</hi> Of all the Grecian
wives, ſhe was moſt faithfull, though moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited,
<hi>Homer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Circes amarous charmes, 27. line.] Circe</hi>
was a famous witch, that kept him with her
inchantments againſt his will.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amilcars ſonne, 29. line.] Hanniball,</hi> the
great Carthagenian Generall: hee doted ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely
upon a poore mean wench in Puglia,
<hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hipſicrates, 31. line.]</hi> She was wife to <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridates</hi>
King of Pontus.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Portia, 34. line.] Portia</hi> was daughter to
<hi>Cato,</hi> and wife to that <hi>Brutus</hi> who killed <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius
Caeſar:</hi> a woman of a great and conſtant
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119955:25"/>
ſpirit, adorned with wiſedome, temper, and
love to her husband, of whoſe death being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſed,
ſhee put hot embers or coales in her
mouth, and ſo died.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Julia, 35. line.] Julia</hi> was daughter to <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us
Caeſar,</hi> and wife to <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, whom
ſhe loved ſo extremely: that one day his Robes
being ſtained with blood at a ſacrifice, and ſent
home; ſhee tooke a ſudden fright at the ſight of
the blood, fell in labour, and died: Yet as it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
happens, he loved her not ſo well, as he did
his next wife <hi>Cornelia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fierce Herods ſtate, line.</hi> 68.] <hi>Herod</hi> loved
his wife <hi>Mariamne</hi> furiouſly, yet put her to
death on a falſ accuſation, that ſhe had conſpired
his end. Hee had the miſerable and juſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to believe her innocent, and love her bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
after her death, <hi>Joſephus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Three faire Dames, 71. line.] Pochris, Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damea,
Artimeſia; Pochris</hi> was wife to one
<hi>Cefalous:</hi> who went every day abroad to hunt.
One day her jealouſie made her follow him,
and hearing him call for the freſh arie, ſhe roſe
from the place where ſhe was concealed, to ſee
what Nymph it was: He thinking it had beene
ſome wilde beaſt, ſhot an arrow, and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
her. When hee knew what ſhee was, hee
was much afflicted, but ſhee being paſt reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery,
deſired of him, as her laſt ſuite, that the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119955:26"/>
Nymph <hi>Aire</hi> might not ſucceed her in his
love, by which hee found her miſtake, and
cleared it: So ſhee died very well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deidamia</hi> bore <hi>Pirhus</hi> to <hi>Achilles,</hi> and
would never marry another whileſt hee was at
Troy, nor after his death.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Artimeſia</hi> was wife to <hi>Mauſſalus,</hi> King
of Caria, after his death, ſhee dried his heart,
beate it to powder, and mingled it with
her drinke, ſaying, There was no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Urne worthy to hold ſuch precious
aſhes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Biblis, Semiramis, and Mirrha,</hi> 75.
<hi>line.] Biblis</hi> loved her brother: <hi>Semiramis</hi>
loved her ſonne, yet ſome Authours thinke
it a calumnie: <hi>Mirrha</hi> loved her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lancelot, Triſtram, 78. line.]</hi> Knights of the
Round table.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jiniver, 79. line.] Jiniver</hi> or <hi>Guiniver,</hi>
was wife to King <hi>Arthur,</hi> and Miſtris to <hi>Lance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſond, 80. line.] Belle Iſond,</hi> wife to
<hi>Marke,</hi> King of Cornewell, and Miſtris to
<hi>Triſtram.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>By one hand ſlaine, 82. line.]</hi> The wife of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119955:26"/>
one <hi>Lancelot,</hi> killed by her husband; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
with his owne brother, whom ſhee uſed
too familiarly, <hi>Italian Commentary.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:119955:27"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <head>The Argument.</head>
                        <l>Himſelfe with other ſlaves of Love</l>
                        <l>Are all ſhut up in Venus grove.</l>
                     </argument>
                     <l>WHen once my will was captive by my fate,</l>
                     <l>And I had loſt the liberty, which late</l>
                     <l>Made my life happy; I, who us'd before</l>
                     <l>To flee from Love (as fearefull Deere abhorre</l>
                     <l n="5">The following huntſman) ſuddenly became</l>
                     <l>(Like all my fellow-ſervants) calme and tame:</l>
                     <l>And viewd the travels, wreſtlings, and the ſmart,</l>
                     <l>The crooked by-pathes, and the coſening Art</l>
                     <l>That guides the amarous flock: then whil'ſt mine eye</l>
                     <l n="10">I caſt on every corner, to eſpie</l>
                     <l>Some Ancient or Modern who had prov'd</l>
                     <l>Famous: I ſaw him, who had onely lov'd</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119955:27"/>
                        <hi>Euridice,</hi> and found out Hel, to call</l>
                     <l>Her deare Ghoſt back; he nam'd her in his fall</l>
                     <l n="51">For whom he died. <hi>Alceus</hi> there was knowne</l>
                     <l>Skilfull in Love and verſe: <hi>Anacreon</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe Muſe ſung nought but Love: <hi>Pindarus,</hi> he</l>
                     <l>Was alſo there: there I might <hi>Virgil</hi> ſee:</l>
                     <l>Many brave wits I found, ſome looſer rimes,</l>
                     <l n="20">By others Writ hath pleas'd the ancient times:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ovid</hi> was one: After <hi>Catullus</hi> came;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Propertius</hi> next, his Elegies the name</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Cynthia</hi> beare: <hi>Tibullus,</hi> and the young</l>
                     <l>Greeke Poeteſſe, who is receiv'd among</l>
                     <l n="25">The noble Troup for her rare Saphick Muſe.</l>
                     <l>Thus looking here and there (as oft I uſe)</l>
                     <l>I ſpi'd much people on a flowry plaine,</l>
                     <l>Amongſt themſelves diſputes of Love maintaine.</l>
                     <l>Behold <hi>Beatrix</hi> with <hi>Dant; Selvagia,</hi> ſhe</l>
                     <l n="30">Brought her <hi>Piſtoyon Cin; Guiton</hi> may be</l>
                     <l>Offended that he is the later nam'd:</l>
                     <l>Behold both <hi>Guidoes</hi> for their learning fam'd:</l>
                     <l>Th' honeſt <hi>Bullonian:</hi> The <hi>Scicilians</hi> firſt</l>
                     <l>Wrote Love in rimes, but wrote their rimes the worſt.</l>
                     <l n="35">
                        <hi>Franciſchin</hi> and <hi>Senuchio,</hi> (who all know)</l>
                     <l>Were worthy and humane: after did go</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:119955:28"/>
A ſquadron of another garbe and phraſe,</l>
                     <l>Of whom <hi>Arnaldo Daniel</hi> hath moſt praiſe,</l>
                     <l>Great maſter in Loves Art, his ſtile as new</l>
                     <l n="40">As ſweet, honours his Countrey: next, a few</l>
                     <l>Whom Love did lightly wound; both <hi>Peters</hi> made</l>
                     <l>Two; one, the leſſe <hi>Arnaldo:</hi> ſome have had</l>
                     <l>A harder warre; both the <hi>Rimbaldoes,</hi> th' one</l>
                     <l>Sung <hi>Beatrix,</hi> though her quality was known</l>
                     <l n="45">Too much above his reach in Mont-ferrat.</l>
                     <l>Alvernia's, <hi>old</hi> Piero, <hi>and</hi> Girault:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Flocchetto,</hi> who from <hi>Genua</hi> was eſtrang'd</l>
                     <l>And call'd <hi>Marſilian,</hi> he wiſely chang'd</l>
                     <l>His name, his ſtate, and countrey, and did gain</l>
                     <l n="50">In all: <hi>Jeffray</hi> made haſte to catch his bane</l>
                     <l>With ſails and oares: <hi>Guilliam</hi> too ſweetly ſung</l>
                     <l>That pleaſing Art, was cauſe he di'd ſo young.</l>
                     <l>Amareg, Bernard, Hugo, <hi>and</hi> Anſelme</l>
                     <l>Were there, with thouſands more, whoſe tongues were helme,</l>
                     <l n="55">Shield, ſword and ſpeare, all their offenſive armes,</l>
                     <l>And their defenſive to prevent their harmes.</l>
                     <l>From thoſe I turn'd, comparing my owne woe,</l>
                     <l>To view my countrey-folks; and there might know</l>
                     <l>The good <hi>Thomaſſo,</hi> who did once adorne</l>
                     <l n="60">
                        <hi>Boloigna,</hi> now <hi>Meſsina</hi> holds his urne.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119955:28"/>
Ah vaniſht joyes! Ah life too full of bane!</l>
                     <l>How wert thou from mine eyes ſo quickly tane?</l>
                     <l>Since without thee nothing is in my power</l>
                     <l>To doe; Where art thou from me at this houre?</l>
                     <l n="65">What is our life? If ought it bring of eaſe,</l>
                     <l>A ſick mans dreame, a fable, told to pleaſe.</l>
                     <l>Some few there from the common road did ſtray,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lelius</hi> and <hi>Socrates,</hi> with whom I may</l>
                     <l>A longer progreſſe take: O! what a paire</l>
                     <l n="70">Of deare eſteemed friends to me they were!</l>
                     <l>'Tis not my verſe, nor proſe, may reach their praiſe;</l>
                     <l>Neither of theſe can naked Vertue raiſe</l>
                     <l>Above her owne true place: with them I have</l>
                     <l>Reach't many heights; one yoke of learning gave</l>
                     <l n="75">Lawes to our ſteps, to them my feſtered wound</l>
                     <l>I oft have ſhew'd; no time or place I found</l>
                     <l>To part from them; and hope, and wiſh we may</l>
                     <l>Be undivided till my breath decay:</l>
                     <l>With them I us'd (too early) to adorne</l>
                     <l n="80">My head with th' honoured branches, onely worne</l>
                     <l>For her deare ſake I did ſo deeply love,</l>
                     <l>Who fill'd my thoughts (but ah!) I dayly prove,</l>
                     <l>No fruit nor leaves from thence can gathered be;</l>
                     <l>The root hath ſharp and bitter been to me.</l>
                     <l n="85">
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:119955:29"/>
For this I was accuſtom'd much to vexe,</l>
                     <l>But I have ſeen that which my anger checks:</l>
                     <l>(A Theame for buskins, not a Comick ſtage)</l>
                     <l>She tooke the God, adored by the rage</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch dul fooles, as he hath captive led:</l>
                     <l n="90">But firſt, Ile tel you what of us he made;</l>
                     <l>Then from her hand what was his owne ſad fate:</l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Orpheus</hi> or <hi>Homer</hi> might relate.</l>
                     <l>His winged courſers ore the ditches leapt,</l>
                     <l>And we their way as deſperately kept,</l>
                     <l n="95">Till he had reached where his mother raignes,</l>
                     <l>Nor would he ever pul or turne the reignes;</l>
                     <l>But ſcour'd ore woods and mountains, none did care</l>
                     <l>Nor could diſcerne in what ſtrange world they were.</l>
                     <l>Beyond the place, where old <hi>Aegeus</hi> mournes,</l>
                     <l n="100">An Iland lies, <hi>Phoebus</hi> none ſweeter burnes,</l>
                     <l>Nor <hi>Neptune</hi> ever bath'd a better ſhore:</l>
                     <l>About the midſt a beauteous hill, with ſtore</l>
                     <l>Of ſhades and pleaſing ſmels, ſo freſh a ſpring</l>
                     <l>As drownes all manly thoughts: this place doth bring</l>
                     <l n="105">
                        <hi>Venus</hi> much joy; 't was given her Deity,</l>
                     <l>Ere blinde man knew a truer god then ſhe:</l>
                     <l>Of which original it yet retaines</l>
                     <l>Too much, ſo little goodneſſe there remains,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119955:29"/>
That it the vicious doth onely pleaſe,</l>
                     <l n="110">Is by the vertuous ſhun'd as a diſeaſe.</l>
                     <l>Here this fine Lord inſulteth o're us all</l>
                     <l>Tied in a chaine, from Thule to Ganges fall.</l>
                     <l>Griefes in our breaſts, vanity in our armes;</l>
                     <l>Fleeting delights are there, and weighty harmes:</l>
                     <l n="115">Repentance ſwiftly following to annoy:</l>
                     <l>(Such <hi>Tarquine</hi> found it, and the bane of Troy)</l>
                     <l>All that whole valley with the Ecchoes rung</l>
                     <l>Of running brookes, and birds that gently ſung:</l>
                     <l>The banks were cloath'd in yellow, purple, green,</l>
                     <l n="120">Scarlet and white, their pleaſing ſprings were ſeen;</l>
                     <l>And gliding ſtreames amongſt the tender graſſe,</l>
                     <l>Thickets and ſoft winds to refreſh the place.</l>
                     <l>After when Winter maketh ſharp the Aire,</l>
                     <l>Warme leaves, and leaſure, ſports, and gallant cheare</l>
                     <l n="125">Enthrall low minds. Now th' equinox hath made</l>
                     <l>The day t' equal the night; and <hi>Progne</hi> had</l>
                     <l>With her ſweet ſiſter, each their old taske taine:</l>
                     <l>(Ah! how the faith in Fortune plac't is vain!)</l>
                     <l>Juſt in the time, and place, and in the houre</l>
                     <l n="130">When humble tears ſhould earthly joyes devoure,</l>
                     <l>It pleaſed him, whom th' vulgar honour ſo,</l>
                     <l>To triumph over me; and now I knovv</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:119955:30"/>
What miſerable ſervitude they prove,</l>
                     <l>What ruine, and what death, that fall in Love.</l>
                     <l n="135">Errours, dreams, paleneſſe waiteth on his chair,</l>
                     <l>Falſe fancies o're the doore, and on the ſtair</l>
                     <l>Are ſlipry hopes, unprofitable gain,</l>
                     <l>And gainfull loſſe; ſuch ſteps it doth contain,</l>
                     <l>As who deſcend, may boaſt their fortune beſt:</l>
                     <l n="140">Who moſt aſcend, moſt fall: a wearied reſt,</l>
                     <l>And reſting trouble, glorious diſgrace;</l>
                     <l>A duskiſh and obſcure illuſtriouſneſſe;</l>
                     <l>Unfaithful loyalty, and cozening faith,</l>
                     <l>That nimble fury, lazy reaſon hath:</l>
                     <l n="145">A priſon, whoſe wide wayes doe all receive,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe narrow paths a hard retiring leave:</l>
                     <l>A ſteep deſcent, by which we ſlide with eaſe,</l>
                     <l>But finde no hold our crawling ſteps to raiſe:</l>
                     <l>Within confuſion, turbulence, annoy</l>
                     <l n="150">Are mixt; undoubted woe, and doubtful joy:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vulcano,</hi> where the ſooty Cyclops dwel;</l>
                     <l>Lyparis, Strombolli, <hi>nor</hi> Mongibel,</l>
                     <l>Nor <hi>Iſchia</hi> have more horrid noiſe and ſmoke:</l>
                     <l>He hates himſelfe that ſtoops to ſuch a yoke.</l>
                     <l n="155">Thus were we all throng'd in ſo ſtrait a cage,</l>
                     <l>I chang'd my looks and hair, before my age,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119955:30"/>
Dreaming on liberty (by ſtrong deſire</l>
                     <l>My ſoul made apt to hope) and did admire</l>
                     <l>Thoſe gallant mindes, enſlav'd to ſuch a woe,</l>
                     <l n="160">(My heart within my breſt diſſolv'd like ſnow</l>
                     <l>Before the Sunne) as one would ſide-wayes caſt</l>
                     <l>His eye on pictures, which his feet hath paſt.</l>
                     <trailer>The end of the fourth Chapter.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="annotations">
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:119955:31"/>
                     <head>ANNOTATIONS
UPON
THE FOURTH CHAPTER.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ridice, 13. line.] Euridice</hi> was wife to
<hi>Orpheus</hi> a famous Greeke Poet, who made
a journey to Hell for her after her death,
and having recovered her from <hi>Pluto,</hi> on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
hee ſhould not looke backe, loſt her by
breaking his promiſe. Hee hated marriage ever
after, for which, or for his unnaturall Love to
boyes, hee was killed by women at a ſacrifice,
and they ſay, named his wife after his head
was off.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Alceus, 15. line.]</hi> An excellent, but laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Greeke Poet, <hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Anacreon, 16. line.] <hi>Another Greeke Poet.</hi>
Italian Commentar.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pindarus, 17. line.]</hi> An excellent Greeke
Poet, <hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Virgil, 18. line.]</hi> The Prince of Latine Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets,
who knowes him not? It ſeemes hee was
alſo in Love, <hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119955:31"/>
                        <hi>Ovid, Catullus, Propertius</hi> and <hi>Tibullus,</hi>
21. 22. and 23. <hi>lines.]</hi> All Latine Poets, and all
Lovers. <hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Greeke Poeteſſe, 24. line.] Sapho,</hi> ſhe firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented
thoſe verſes called Saphicks after her: a
better Poeteſſe then a woman, <hi>Italian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Dant, 29. line.]</hi> An Italian Poet, whoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe
name was <hi>Beatrix. Italian Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Piſtoyan Cin, 30. line.] Cin</hi> of Piſtoia, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Italian Poet, whoſe Miſtreſſe was named
<hi>Selvagia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Guiton may, 30. line.] Guiton</hi> was the beſt
Italian Poet of his time: and therefore <hi>Petrarch</hi>
thinkes hee ſhould have had the firſt place here.
<hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Guidoes, 32. line.]</hi> They were two Italian Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets
of one name. <hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sicilians, 33. line.]</hi> They were the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venters
of rimes, and thoſe very rude ones. <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian
Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Franciſchin</hi> and <hi>Senvchio, 35. line.]</hi> Two
Italian Poets, friends to <hi>Petrarch. Italian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A ſquadron, 37. line.]</hi> Here followes a troup
of obſcure provinciall Poets. <hi>Italian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Peters, 41. line.]</hi> Two unconſtant riming
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119955:32"/>
Lovers, of whom there cannot bee much ſaid
to much purpoſe, onely they with <hi>Arnaldo
Daniel,</hi> and the leſſer <hi>Arnaldo</hi> were provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
<hi>Italian Commentary.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rimbaldoes, 43. line.]</hi> There were two
Poets of that name: The firſt loved two or
three Miſtreſſes, and made verſes, &amp;c. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
loved but one, named <hi>Beatrix,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe
of Mont-ferrat, <hi>Italian Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Alvernia's, old Piero, 46. line.]</hi> A good
Poet that lived long: ſo there hath beene three
<hi>Peters</hi> in all.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Girault, 46. line.]</hi> Another Provinciall
Poet, but I know not why hee ſhould bee
here, ſince I cannot learne that hee had ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Wife or Miſtreſſe, <hi>Italian Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Flocchetto, 47. line.]</hi> Hee was a Merch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants
ſonne in Genua, but being of a good ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
hee travelled, and changed his Countrey;
from whence hee was called <hi>Marſilian:</hi>
hee turned religious at laſt, for diſcontent in
love: hee was alſo a Poet, <hi>Italian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jeffray, 50. line] Jeffray Ruder,</hi> hee fell
in love with the Counteſſe of Tripola, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,
and making a ſea-voyage to ſee her, fell
ſicke by the way: after hee was landed, the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119955:32"/>
Ladie came to viſite him, hee not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to viſite her, by which good fortune, well
ſatisfied, he died preſently after, <hi>Italian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Guilliam, line,</hi> 51.] <hi>Guilliam Gabeſten</hi>
of Roſiglion, loving, and too much loved of a
Ladie, named <hi>Soriſmonda,</hi> wife to <hi>Raimond,</hi>
Lord of a principall place in that Countrey:
his fine verſes diſcovered their Love to her
Husband, who killing him, cauſed dreſſe his
heart, and made her eat it, then told her
what it was: ſhee gave him a bitter anſwer;
with which, enraged, hee drew his ſword
upon her, who leaping over a Balcone to ſhunne
his fury, died of the fall, <hi>Italian Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amareg, 53. line.]</hi> There were two Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eticall
Lovers of that name.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bernard, 53. line.]</hi> An amarous Poet,
who turned religious at laſt, <hi>Italian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hugo, 53. line.]</hi> A pleaſing Poet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
much reſpected for his Art, but an ill Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nager
and died poore, <hi>Italian Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſelme, 53. line.]</hi> A worſe Poet, and
worſe Menager then the other, <hi>Italian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:119955:33"/>
                        <hi>Thomaſſo, 59 line.]</hi> A Poet, and friend
to <hi>Petrarch,</hi> who ſtudied with him in Bolognia:
it ſeems he died, and was buried in Meſſiana, <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian
Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lelius</hi> and <hi>Socrates, 63. line.]</hi> They were
two friends to <hi>Petrarch. Italian Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Many heights, 74. line.]</hi> That is, they found
out many myſteries of Learning, in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
ſtudies, <hi>Italian Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>My head with th' honoured branches, 80. line.]</hi>
His Miſtreſſe, her name being <hi>Lauretta,</hi> hee
wore Lawrell Garlands (as Emblems of her)
ſooner then he thought, his Poeſie deſerved that
honour.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>For buskins, 87. line.]</hi> Becauſe of the ſubject:
<hi>Laurettas warre with Cupid,</hi> being both Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall,
for ſhe made him priſoner, and mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke,
in regard of the dignitie of the Victreſſe,
and powerfulneſſe of the enemy: the Tragedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
underſtood here by buskins (a kinde of feet,
or legge-ornament which they wore) uſing a
more grave and weighty ſtile then the Comick,
<hi>Italian Commentar,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Orpheus or Homer, 92. line.]</hi> Two of the beſt
Greeke Poets.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aegeus mourns, 99. line.]</hi> The Aegean Sea,
called ſo from <hi>Aegeus</hi> father to <hi>Theſeus,</hi> and
King of Athens, who drowned himſelfe there,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119955:33"/>
thinking his ſonne was dead.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tarquin, 116. line.] Tarquin</hi> raviſhed
<hi>Lucrece,</hi> which was the ruine of his fathers
houſe, and made the Government bee changed:
a knowne Hiſtory.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bane of Troy, 116. line] Paris,</hi> who cauſed
the deſtruction of Troy, by carrying away <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi>
wife to <hi>Menelaus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Progne, 126. line.]</hi> The Swallow, her taske
is to build in the ſpring.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Her ſweet ſiſter, 127. line.] Philomel,</hi> or
the Nightingale: her caſe is to ſing, or mourne
if you will.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Time and place, 129. line.]</hi> Good-friday in
the Church, and at Maſſe as it ſhould ſeem; but
the <hi>Italian Commentary</hi> in the life of <hi>Petrarch,</hi>
conteſts much to prove that it was in the fields,
that he ſee her by hazard, as hee and ſhee were
both going to viſit the Church of Saint <hi>Varan,</hi> it
was Good-friday however.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vulcanus, 151. line.]</hi> Vulcanus or Vulcano,
Lyparis, Strombolli, Mongibell, and Iſchia,
all burning Iſlands and Mountains in the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terran
Sea.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Side-wayes caſt, 161. line.]</hi> The place ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
imperfect, but is not, for hee compareth
himſelfe in his laſt contemplation of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
of Lovers after his experience, (which hee
had not much heeded before) to a man, who
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119955:34"/>
neglecteth a piece of rare work or picture, by
haſte or other thoughts; and when hee is paſt,
conſiders it more ſeriouſly, either ſtanding ſtill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
or going on with his eye fixed on it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>The End of the Triumph of Love.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119955:34"/>
                  <p>THE
TRIUMPH
OF
CHASTITIE:
Written by
PETRARCH,
AND
TRANSLATED
Out of Italian,
BY
M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> ANNA HUME.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi>
Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to
the Kings moſt Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie,
1644.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119955:35"/>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:119955:35"/>
                  <head>THE
TRIUMPH
OF
CHASTITIE.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <head>The Argument.</head>
                        <l>Chaſtitie binds the winged god,</l>
                        <l>And makes him ſubject to her rod.</l>
                     </argument>
                     <l>WHen to one yoke at once I ſaw the height</l>
                     <l>Of Gods and men ſubdu'd by <hi>Cupids</hi> might;</l>
                     <l>I tooke example from their cruel fate,</l>
                     <l>And by their ſufferings eas'd my owne hard ſtate:</l>
                     <l n="5">Since <hi>Phoebus</hi> and <hi>Leander</hi> felt like paine,</l>
                     <l>The one a God, the other but humane.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:119955:36"/>
One fnare catcht <hi>June,</hi> and the Carthage Dame,</l>
                     <l>(Her Husbands death prepar'd her funerall flame,</l>
                     <l>'Twas not a cauſe that <hi>Virgil</hi> maketh one)</l>
                     <l n="10">I need not grieve, that unprepar'd, alone,</l>
                     <l>Unarm'd, and young, I did receive a wound,</l>
                     <l>Or that my enemy no hurt hath found</l>
                     <l>By Love; or that ſhe cloath'd him in my ſight,</l>
                     <l>And tooke his wings, and marr'd his winding flight:</l>
                     <l n="15">No angry Lions ſend more hideous noyſe</l>
                     <l>From their beat breaſts, nor claſhing thunders voyce</l>
                     <l>Rends Heav'n, frights Earth, and roareth through the aire</l>
                     <l>With greater force, then Love had rais'd, to dare</l>
                     <l>Encounter her, of whom I write; and ſhe</l>
                     <l n="20">As quicke and ready to aſſaile, as he:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Enceladus</hi> when <hi>Aetna</hi> moſt he ſhakes,</l>
                     <l>Nor angry Scylla, nor Charibdis makes</l>
                     <l>So great and frightfull noyſe, as did the ſhock</l>
                     <l>Of this (firſt doubtfull) battel, none could mock</l>
                     <l n="25">Such earneſt warre; all drew them to the height</l>
                     <l>To ſee what maz'd their hearts, and dimn'd their ſight.</l>
                     <l>Victorious Love a threatning dart did ſhow</l>
                     <l>His right hand held; the other bore a bow,</l>
                     <l>The ſtring of which he drew juſt by his eare;</l>
                     <l n="30">No Leopard could chaſe a frighted Deere</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:119955:36"/>
(Free, or broke looſe) with quicker ſpeed, then he</l>
                     <l>Made haſte to wound; fire ſparkled from his eye:</l>
                     <l>I burn'd, and had a combat in my breſt,</l>
                     <l>Glad t' have her company, yet 'twas not beſt</l>
                     <l n="35">(Me thought) to ſee her loſt, but 'tis in vain</l>
                     <l>T' abandon goodneſſe, and of fate complaine:</l>
                     <l>Vertue her ſervants never will forſake,</l>
                     <l>As now 'twas ſeen, ſhe could reſiſtance make:</l>
                     <l>No Fencer ever better warded blow,</l>
                     <l n="40">Nor Pilot did to ſhore more wiſely row</l>
                     <l>To ſhun a ſhelfe, then with undaunted power</l>
                     <l>She wav'd the ſtroke of this ſharp Conquerour.</l>
                     <l>Mine eyes and heart were watchfull to attend,</l>
                     <l>In hope the victory would that way bend</l>
                     <l n="45">It ever did; and that I might no more</l>
                     <l>Be barr'd from her; as one, whoſe thoughts, before</l>
                     <l>His tongue hath utter'd them, you well may ſee</l>
                     <l>Writ in his looks; O! if you victour be</l>
                     <l>Great Sir, (ſaid I) let her and me be bound</l>
                     <l n="50">Both with one yoke; I may be worthy found,</l>
                     <l>And will not ſet her free, doubt not my faith:</l>
                     <l>When I beheld her with diſdain and wrath</l>
                     <l>So fill'd, that to relate it, would demand</l>
                     <l>A better Muſe then mine: Her vertuous hand</l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:119955:37"/>
                     <l n="55">Had quickly quench't thoſe guilded fiery darts,</l>
                     <l>Which dipt in beauties pleaſure, poyſon hearts.</l>
                     <l>Neither <hi>Camilla,</hi> nor the warre-like hoaſt,</l>
                     <l>That cut their breſts, could ſo much valour boaſt;</l>
                     <l>Nor <hi>Caeſar</hi> in Pharſalia fought ſo well,</l>
                     <l n="60">As ſhe 'gainſt him, who pierceth coats of mail;</l>
                     <l>All her brave vertues arm'd, attended there,</l>
                     <l>(A glorious troup!) and marched paire by paire:</l>
                     <l>Honour and bluſhes firſt in ranke; the two</l>
                     <l>Religious vertues make the ſecond row;</l>
                     <l n="65">(By thoſe ſhe other women doth excell)</l>
                     <l>Prudence, and Modeſty, the twins that dwell</l>
                     <l>Together, both were lodged in her breſt;</l>
                     <l>Glory and Perſeverance ever bleſt:</l>
                     <l>Fair Entertainment, Providence without,</l>
                     <l n="70">Sweet courteſie and pureneſſe round about<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Reſpect of credit, feare of infamy;</l>
                     <l>Grave thoughts in youth, and what not oft agree,</l>
                     <l>True Chaſtitie, and rareſt beauty; theſe</l>
                     <l>All came 'gainſt Love, and this the heav'ns did pleaſe</l>
                     <l n="75">And every generous ſoule in that full height,</l>
                     <l>He had no power left to beare the weight!</l>
                     <l>A thouſand famous prizes hardly gain'd</l>
                     <l>She tooke; and thouſand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lorious palms obtain'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:119955:37"/>
Shooke from his hands; the fall was not more ſtrange</l>
                     <l n="80">Of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> when Fortune pleas'd to change</l>
                     <l>Her minde, and on the Romane youth beſtow</l>
                     <l>The favours he enjoy'd; nor was he ſo</l>
                     <l>Amaz'd, who frighted th' Iſralitiſh hoaſt</l>
                     <l>Struck by the Hebrew boy, that quit his boaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l n="85">Nor <hi>Cirus</hi> more aſtoniſht at the fall</l>
                     <l>The Jewiſh widow gave his Generall:</l>
                     <l>As one that ſickens ſuddenly, and feares</l>
                     <l>His life, or as a man tane unawares</l>
                     <l>In ſome baſe act, and doth the finder hate;</l>
                     <l n="90">Juſt ſo was he, or in a worſe eſtate:</l>
                     <l>Feare, griefe and ſhame, and anger in his face</l>
                     <l>Were ſeen, no troubled Seas more rage, the place</l>
                     <l>Where huge <hi>Typheus</hi> grones; nor Etna when</l>
                     <l>Her Giant ſighs, were mov'd as he was then.</l>
                     <l n="95">I paſſe by many noble things I ſee;</l>
                     <l>(To write them, were too hard a taske for me)</l>
                     <l>To her and thoſe that did attend, I go;</l>
                     <l>Her armour was a robe more white then ſnow;</l>
                     <l>And in her hand a ſhield like his ſhe bare</l>
                     <l>Who ſlew <hi>Meduſa,</hi> a faire pillar there</l>
                     <l n="100">Of Jaſp was fixt, and with a chain (firſt wet</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Lethe</hi> floud) of Jewels fitly ſet,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:119955:38"/>
Diamonds mixt with Topaſſes (of old</l>
                     <l>'Twas worne by Ladies, now 'tis not) firſt hold</l>
                     <l n="105">She catch't, then bound him faſt, then ſuch revenge</l>
                     <l>She tooke, as might ſuffice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my thoughts did change;</l>
                     <l>And I who wiſht him victory before,</l>
                     <l>Was ſatisfi'd, he now could hurt no more.</l>
                     <l>I cannot in my rimes the names contain</l>
                     <l n="110">Of bleſſed Maids that did make up her train<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Calliope</hi> nor <hi>Clio</hi> could ſuffice,</l>
                     <l>Nor all the other ſeven for th' enterpriſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet ſome I will inſert may juſtly claime</l>
                     <l>Precedency of others. <hi>Lucrece</hi> came</l>
                     <l n="115">On her right hand: <hi>Penelope</hi> was by,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe broke his bow, and made his arrowes ly</l>
                     <l>Split on the ground, and pull'd his plumes away</l>
                     <l>From off his wings: after <hi>Virginia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nere her vext father, arm'd with wrath and hate,</l>
                     <l n="120">Fury, and ir'n and Love, he freed the ſtate</l>
                     <l>And her from ſlavery, with a manly blow:</l>
                     <l>Next were thoſe barbarous women, who could ſhow</l>
                     <l>They judg'd it better die, then ſuffer wrong</l>
                     <l>To their rude Chaſtitie: the wiſe and ſtrong</l>
                     <l n="125">The chaſte Hebraean <hi>Judith,</hi> followeth theſe;</l>
                     <l>The Greeke that ſav'd her honour in the Seas.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119955:38"/>
With theſe and other famous ſoules I ſee</l>
                     <l>Her Triumph over him, who us'd to be</l>
                     <l>Maſter of all the world: Amongſt the reſt</l>
                     <l n="130">The veſtall Nunne I ſpide, who was ſo bleſt</l>
                     <l>As by a wonder to preſerve her fame.</l>
                     <l>Next came <hi>Herſilia</hi> the Romane Dame</l>
                     <l>(Or <hi>Sabine</hi> rather) with her valarous train,</l>
                     <l>Who prove all flanders on that ſexe are vain.</l>
                     <l n="135">Then 'mongft the forraign Ladies, ſhe whoſe faith</l>
                     <l>T' her husband (not <hi>Aeneas)</hi> caus'd her death;</l>
                     <l>The vulgar ignorant may hold their peace,</l>
                     <l>Her ſafety to her Chaſtitie gave place;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dido</hi> I mean, whom no vain paſſion led,</l>
                     <l n="140">(As fame belies her) laſt, the vertuous Maide</l>
                     <l>Retir'd to Aruns, who no reſt could finde,</l>
                     <l>Her friends conſtraining power forc't her minde;</l>
                     <l>The Triumph thither went, where ſalt waves wet</l>
                     <l>The Bayan ſhore, eaſtward; her foot ſhe ſet</l>
                     <l n="145">There on firme land, and did <hi>Avernus</hi> leave</l>
                     <l>On the one hand, on th' other Sybils Cave,</l>
                     <l>So to Lencernus marcht, the Village where</l>
                     <l>The noble Africane lies buried; there</l>
                     <l>The great newes of her Triumph did appeare</l>
                     <l n="150">As glorious to the eye, as to the eare,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:119955:39"/>
The fame had been; and the moſt chaſte did ſhow</l>
                     <l>Moſt beautifull; it griev'd Love much to go</l>
                     <l>Anothers priſoner, expos'd to ſcorne,</l>
                     <l>Who to command whole Empires ſeemed borne.</l>
                     <l n="155">Thus to the chiefeſt City all were led,</l>
                     <l>Entring the Temple which <hi>Sulpitia</hi> made</l>
                     <l>Sacred; it drives all madneſſe from the minde;</l>
                     <l>And chaſtities pure Temple next we finde,</l>
                     <l>Which in brave ſoules doth modeſt thoughts beget,</l>
                     <l n="160">Not by <hi>Plebeians</hi> entred, but the great</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Patrician</hi> Dames; there were the ſpoyles diſplaid</l>
                     <l>Of the faire victreſſe; there her palmes ſhe laid,</l>
                     <l>And did commit them to the Thuſcan youth,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe marring ſcarres beare witneſſe of his truth:</l>
                     <l n="165">With others more, whoſe names I fully knew,</l>
                     <l>(My guide inſtructed me) that overthrew</l>
                     <l>The power of Love: 'mongſt whom of all the reſt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hyppolito</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> were the beſt.</l>
                     <trailer>The end of this Chapter.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="annotations">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:119955:39"/>
                     <head>ANNOTATIONS
Upon the Triumph of
CHASTITIE.</head>
                     <p>PHoebus <hi>and</hi> Leander, 5. line.] Phoebus <hi>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi>
Daphne, <hi>and</hi> Leander Hero.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Juno, 7. line.] Juno</hi> loved <hi>Jupiter</hi> ſo much,
that ſhee was troubleſomly jealous, if ſhee can
be called jealous, that had ſo much wrong.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Carthage dame, 7. line.] Dido,</hi> ſhee burned
her ſelfe in her husbands funerall pile, leſt ſhe
ſhould bee compelled to marry an importunate
ſuiter, or bring warre on her Countrey.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Camilla, 57. line.]</hi> She was Queene of the
Amazons: it is ſaid, they cut off their right
breſts, that they might ſhoot with the more
eaſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Caeſar in Pharſalia, 59. line.]</hi> That famous
battell, in which he overcame <hi>Pompey</hi> the great
and made way to the Empire.</p>
                     <p>Religious vertues, 64. line.] <hi>Faith and Hope,</hi>
Italian Commentarie.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:119955:40"/>
The twinnes, 69. line.] <hi>Juſtice and Fortitude,</hi>
Italian Commentarie.</p>
                     <p>The Romane youth, 81. line.] Scipio, <hi>who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercame</hi>
Hannibal.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Typheus groans, 95. line.] Typheus</hi> was one
of the Giants that warred with heaven: there
was a mountaine throwne upon him, under
which when hee groanes, it ſends forth ſmoke,
fire, and ſtones<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with great noiſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nor Aetna, 95. line.]</hi> Another mountaine,
which was caſt upon <hi>Enceladus</hi> another Giant:
the ſmoke and fire of all theſe burning moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,
proceeds from the Giants that lie oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
under them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Slew Meduſa, 100. line.]</hi> The ſhield of
<hi>Perſeus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> which turned all that beheld it, to
ſtones.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jaſp. 101. line.] Jaſp</hi> hath a qualitie to make
one chaſte.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lethe flood, 103. line]</hi> Forgetfulneſſe, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
cure for Love, and the tooth-ake.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Diamonds, &amp;c. 104. line.]</hi> Diamonds is
thought maketh the wearers conſtant: <hi>Topaſſes</hi>
make chaſte, for which two cauſes they were
worn by Ladies of old; but I hope they are not
needfull now.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Calliope, &amp;c. 112. 113. line.]</hi> the nine
Muſes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lucrece, 114. line.]</hi> A knowne Story, ſhee
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119955:40"/>
killed her ſelfe after <hi>Tarquin</hi> had raviſhed her.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Penellope, 115. line]</hi> The chaſte wife of
<hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Virginia, 118. line.] Virginia</hi> being a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull
young Maid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was adjudged a bondwoman
by <hi>Appius Claudius,</hi> that hee might obtain his
owne baſe ends: her father ſeeing no other way
to preſerve her liberty and chaſtity, killed her,
which occaſioned the alteration of that govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
by which <hi>Appius</hi> had his power, and
gave liberty to the people.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Judged it better die, 123. line.]</hi> Their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,
fathers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> brothers, &amp;c. being killed and
chaſed by <hi>Marius,</hi> they hanged themſelves, <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian
Commentarie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Greeke, &amp;c. 126. line.] Hippo</hi> a Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
maide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who being embarked againſt her will
by one who intended to diſhonour her, leapt in
to the Sea, and drowned her ſelf, <hi>Italian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The veſtall Nunne, 130 line.]</hi> Called <hi>Tucia,</hi>
who cleared her ſelfe from a falſe accuſation,
by carrying water in a ſive.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hirſilia, 132. line.]</hi> Wife to <hi>Romulus,</hi> ſhee
with the other Romane wives, all Sabine wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
who had been ſtollen from their kindred,
ſeeing their husbands ready to fight with their
fathers, brothers, couſins, &amp;c. ranne in betwixt
them, and oppoſing themſelves to the naked
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119955:41"/>
ſwords, ſtaid the fury of the fight, brought them
to a parley, and ſo to an agreement.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Dido I mean, 139. line.] Petrarch</hi> it ſeems
was much troubled at the wrong done to <hi>Dido,</hi>
by <hi>Virgil;</hi> who to honour his <hi>Aeneas,</hi> will needs
have it, that ſhe forfeit her honour to him, when
in true Hiſtory, it is knowne hee never ſee her:
this he glanceth at in her defence three ſeverall
times, for which I thanke him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Retired to Arnus, 141. line.]</hi> One <hi>Piccarda,</hi>
who rendered her ſelfe a Nunne, but was taken
out by her friends, and compelled to marry, <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian
Commentar.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Baian ſhore, 144. line.]</hi> Baiae, is a Citie in
Campania, called ſo from the hot bathes that are
in it: it lieth alongſt the Coaſt of the Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran
ſea, ſouth-eaſt from the mouth of Tiber, and
giveth name to the Bay neare it, where <hi>Lauret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>
landed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Avernus, 145. line.]</hi> A great Lake nere
Baiae.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sybils cave, 146. line.]</hi> A cave not farre
from Avernus, where <hi>Sybilla</hi> called <hi>Cumea,</hi>
was wonted to give her anſwers.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Linternum, 147. line.]</hi> A little Village in
Campania, honoured by the death and buriall of
the elder <hi>Scipio.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>By Sulpitia, 156. line.] Sulpitia</hi> was a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
and learned Lady of Rome, who lived
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119955:41"/>
and wrote in the time of <hi>Domitian:</hi> it ſeemeth
ſhe hath beene choſen to dedicate that Temple
or Altar to <hi>Venus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> which hath power to curbe
unreaſonable paſſions, for the chaſteſt women
did worſhip <hi>Venus</hi> for that end, belike as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians
worſhip the Devil.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thuſcan youth, 163. line.]</hi> A beautifull yong
man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who pittying the miſeries of thoſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
that doted on him, and wearied with their
importunities, marred his owne face.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>My guide, 164. line.]</hi> His old Thuſcan
friend, who deſcribed <hi>The Triumph of Love</hi> to
him ere he was one of the traine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> doth now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe
<hi>The Triumph of Chaſtitie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hippolito</hi> and <hi>Joſeph, 169. line.] Hippolito</hi>
rejected the unlawfull Love of his ſtepmother,
and <hi>Joſeph</hi> the ſolicitation of his maſters wife.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119955:42"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119955:42"/>
                  <p>THE
TRIUMPH
OF
DEATH:
Written by
PETRARCH,
AND
TRANSLATED
Out of Italian,
BY
M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> ANNA HUME.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi>
Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to
the Kings moſt Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie,
1644.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119955:43"/>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:119955:43"/>
                  <head>THE
TRIUMPH
OF
DEATH.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <head>The Argument.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Lauretta</hi> meeting cruell Death,</l>
                        <l>Mildely reſignes her noble Breath.</l>
                     </argument>
                     <l>THe glorious Maid, whoſe ſoule to Heaven is gone</l>
                     <l>And left the reſt cold earth, ſhe who was growne</l>
                     <l>A pillar of true vallour, and had gain'd</l>
                     <l>Much honour by her victory, and chain'd</l>
                     <l n="5">That God which doth the world with terrour binde,</l>
                     <l>Uſing no armour but her owne chaſte minde:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="76" facs="tcp:119955:44"/>
A faire aſpect, coy thoughts, and words well weigh'd,</l>
                     <l>Sweet modeſtie to theſe gave friendly aid.</l>
                     <l>It was a miracle on earth to ſee</l>
                     <l n="10">The bow and arrowes of the Deitie,</l>
                     <l>And all his armour broke, who erſt had ſlain</l>
                     <l>Such numbers, and ſo many captive tain:</l>
                     <l>The faire Dame from the noble fight withdrew</l>
                     <l>With her choiſe company, they were but few,</l>
                     <l n="15">And made a little troup, true vertu's rare,</l>
                     <l>Yet each of them did by her ſelfe appeare</l>
                     <l>A theame for Poems, and might well incite</l>
                     <l>The beſt Hiſtorian: they bore a white</l>
                     <l>Unſpotted Ermine, in a field of green,</l>
                     <l n="20">About whoſe neck a Topas chain was ſeen</l>
                     <l>Set in pure gold; their heavenly words and gate</l>
                     <l>Expreſt them bleſt were borne for ſuch a fate.</l>
                     <l>Bright ſtars they ſeem'd, ſhe did a Sun appeare,</l>
                     <l>Who darkned not the reſt, but made more cleare</l>
                     <l n="25">Their ſplendour; honour in brave minds is found:</l>
                     <l>This troup with Violets and Roſes crown'd,</l>
                     <l>Chearfully marcht, when lo, I might eſpie</l>
                     <l>Another enſigne dreadfull to mine eye,</l>
                     <l>A Ladie cloth'd in blacke, whoſe ſterne looks were</l>
                     <l n="30">With horrour fill'd, and did like hell appeare,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:119955:44"/>
Advanc't, and ſaid, You who are proud to be</l>
                     <l>So fair and young, yet have no eyes to ſee</l>
                     <l>Hovv neare you are your end, behold, I am</l>
                     <l>She, vvhom they, fierce, and blinde, and cruell name,</l>
                     <l n="35">Who meet untimely deaths; 'tvvas I did make</l>
                     <l>Greece ſubject, and the Romane Empire ſhake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>My piercing ſvvord ſack't Troy, hovv many rude</l>
                     <l>And barbarous people are by me ſubdu'd?</l>
                     <l>Many ambitious, vaine, and amarous thought</l>
                     <l n="40">My unvviſht preſence hath to nothing brought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Novv am I come to you, vvhiles yet your ſtate</l>
                     <l>Is happy, ere you feel a harder fate.</l>
                     <l>On theſe you have no povver, ſhe then replide,</l>
                     <l>Who had more vvorth then all the vvorld beſide,</l>
                     <l n="50">And little over me; but there is one</l>
                     <l>Who vvill be deeply griev'd vvhen I am gone,</l>
                     <l>His happineſſe doth on my life depend,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall finde freedome in a peacefull end.</l>
                     <l>As one vvho glancing vvith a ſudden eye</l>
                     <l n="55">Some unexpected object doth eſpie;</l>
                     <l>Then lookes again, and doth his ovvne haſte blame:</l>
                     <l>So in a doubting pauſe, this cruell dame</l>
                     <l>A little ſtaid, and ſaid, The reſt I call</l>
                     <l>To minde, and knovv I have o'recome them all:</l>
                     <l n="60">
                        <pb n="78" facs="tcp:119955:45"/>
Then with leſſe fierce aſpect, ſhe ſaid, Thou guide</l>
                     <l>Of this faire crew, haſt not my ſtrength aſſaid,</l>
                     <l>Let her adviſe, who may command, prevent</l>
                     <l>Decrepit age, 'tis but a puniſhment;</l>
                     <l>From me this honour thou alone ſhalt have,</l>
                     <l n="65">Without or feare or paine, to finde thy grave,</l>
                     <l>As he ſhall pleaſe, who dwelleth in the Heaven</l>
                     <l>And rules on earth, ſuch portion muſt be given</l>
                     <l>To me, as others from thy hand receive:</l>
                     <l>She anſwered then; a farre we might perceave</l>
                     <l n="70">Millions of dead heapt on th' adjacent plain,</l>
                     <l>No verſe nor proſe may comprehend the ſlain</l>
                     <l>Did on deaths Triumph wait, from India,</l>
                     <l>From Spain, and from Morocco, from Cathai,</l>
                     <l>And all the skirts of th' earth they gathred were,</l>
                     <l n="75">Who had moſt happy liv'd, attended there;</l>
                     <l>Popes, Emperours, nor Kings, no enſignes wore</l>
                     <l>Of their paſt height, but naked ſhew'd and poore.</l>
                     <l>Where be their riches, where their precious jems,</l>
                     <l>Their Miters, Scepters, Roabs and Diadems?</l>
                     <l n="80">O miſerable men, whoſe hopes ariſe</l>
                     <l>From worldly joyes, yet be there few ſo wiſe</l>
                     <l>As in thoſe trifling follies not to truſt;</l>
                     <l>And if they be deceiv'd in end 'tis juſt:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="79" facs="tcp:119955:45"/>
Ah, more then blinde, what gain you by your toyle</l>
                     <l n="85">You muſt returne once to your mothers ſoyle,</l>
                     <l>And after times your names ſhall hardly know,</l>
                     <l>Nor any profit from your labour grow;</l>
                     <l>All thoſe ſtrange countreyes by your warlick ſtroke</l>
                     <l>Submitted to a tributary yoke;</l>
                     <l n="90">The fuell erſt of your ambitious fire,</l>
                     <l>What helpe they now? the vaſt and bad deſire</l>
                     <l>Of wealth and power at a bloody rate</l>
                     <l>Is wicked, better bread and water eat</l>
                     <l>With peace; a woodden diſh doth ſeldome hold</l>
                     <l n="95">A poyſoned draught, glaſſe is more ſafe then gold;</l>
                     <l>But for this Theame a larger time will aske,</l>
                     <l>I muſt betake me to my former taske.</l>
                     <l>The fatall houre of her ſhort life drew neare,</l>
                     <l>That doubtfull paſſage which the world doth feare;</l>
                     <l n="110">Another company, who had not beene</l>
                     <l>Freed from their earthy burden there were ſeene,</l>
                     <l>To try if prayers could appeaſe the wrath,</l>
                     <l>Or ſtay th' inexorable hand of death.</l>
                     <l>That beauteous croude conveen'd to ſee the end</l>
                     <l n="105">Which all muſt taſte; each neighbour, every friend</l>
                     <l>Stood by, when grim death with her hand tooke hold,</l>
                     <l>And pull'd away one onely haire of gold.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="80" facs="tcp:119955:46"/>
Thus from the world this faireſt flower is tane</l>
                     <l>To make her ſhine more bright, not out of ſpleen:</l>
                     <l n="105">How many moaning plaints, what ſtore of cries</l>
                     <l>Were uttered there, when fate ſhut thoſe faire eyes</l>
                     <l>For which ſo oft I ſung; whoſe beautie burn'd</l>
                     <l>My tortur'd heart ſo long; whiles others mourn'd</l>
                     <l>She pleas'd, and quiet did the fruit enjoy</l>
                     <l n="110">Of her bleſt life; farewell, without annoy,</l>
                     <l>True Saint on earth, ſaid they; ſo might ſhe be</l>
                     <l>Eſteem'd, but nothing bates deaths crueltie.</l>
                     <l>What ſhall become of others, ſince ſo pure</l>
                     <l>A body did ſuch heats and colds endure,</l>
                     <l n="115">And chang'd ſo often in ſo little ſpace?</l>
                     <l>Ah worldly hopes, how blinde you be, how baſe?</l>
                     <l>If ſince I bathe the ground with flowing teares</l>
                     <l>For that milde ſoule, who ſees it witneſſe bears;</l>
                     <l>And thou who read'ſt maiſt judge ſhe fetter'd me.</l>
                     <l n="120">The ſixt of April, and did ſet me free</l>
                     <l>On the ſame day and moneth: O! how the way</l>
                     <l>Of fortune is unſure, none hates the day</l>
                     <l>Of ſlavery, or of death, ſo much as I</l>
                     <l>Abhorre the time which wrought my liberty,</l>
                     <l n="125">And my too-laſting life; it had been juſt</l>
                     <l>My greater age had firſt been turn'd to duſt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="81" facs="tcp:119955:46"/>
And paid to time, and to the world the debt</l>
                     <l>I ow'd, then earth had kept her glorious ſtate:</l>
                     <l>Now at what rate I ſhould the ſorrow priſe</l>
                     <l n="130">I know not, nor have Art that can ſuffiſe</l>
                     <l>The ſad affliction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to relate in verſe</l>
                     <l>Of theſe faire Dames, that wept about her herſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Courteſie, Vertue, Beautie, all are loſt,</l>
                     <l>What ſhall become of us? none elſe can boaſt</l>
                     <l n="135">Such high perfection, no more we ſhall</l>
                     <l>Heare her wiſe words, nor the Angelicall</l>
                     <l>Sweet muſick of her voyce; whiles thus they cride</l>
                     <l>The parting ſpirit doth it ſelfe divide</l>
                     <l>With every vertue from the noble breſt,</l>
                     <l n="140">As ſome grave Hermite, ſeeks a lonely reſt:</l>
                     <l>The Heav'ns were cleare, and all the ambient Aire</l>
                     <l>Without a threatning Cloud, no adverſaire</l>
                     <l>Durſt once appeare, or her calme minde affright;</l>
                     <l>Death ſingly did her ſelfe conclude the fight;</l>
                     <l n="145">After, when feare, and the extreameſt plaint</l>
                     <l>Were ceaſt, th' attentive eyes of all were bent,</l>
                     <l>On that faire face, and by deſpaire became</l>
                     <l>Secure; ſhe who was ſpent, not like a flame</l>
                     <l>By force extinguiſht, but as lights decay,</l>
                     <l n="150">And undiſcerned waſte themſelves away:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:119955:47"/>
Thus went the ſoule in peace, ſo lamps are ſpent,</l>
                     <l>As the oyle fails which gave them nouriſhment;</l>
                     <l>In ſumme, her countenance you ſtill might know</l>
                     <l>The ſame it was, not pale, but white as ſnow,</l>
                     <l n="155">Which on the tops of hills in gentle fleakes</l>
                     <l>Fals in a calme, or as a man that takes</l>
                     <l>Deſired reſt, as if her lovely ſight</l>
                     <l>Were clos'd with ſweeteſt ſleep, after the ſpright</l>
                     <l>Was gone. If this be that fooles call to die,</l>
                     <l n="160">Death ſeem'd in her exceeding faire to be.</l>
                     <trailer>The end of the firſt Chapter.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="annotations">
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:119955:47"/>
                     <head>ANNOTATIONS
UPON THE
TRIUMPH
OF
DEATH.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>NOble fight, line,</hi> 13.] Her fight with
<hi>Cupid:</hi> See above in the <hi>Triumph of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Choice Company, 14. line.]</hi> The Ladies that
had been vertuous before her time, and now
waited on her Triumph, <hi>Lucrece, Penelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe,
&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>They bore a white, 18. line.]</hi> Their enſigne,
a white Ermine in a greene field, with a chaine
of Topaſſes ſet in pure gold: the white Ermine
was an Embleme of innocencie: The Topaſſes
of Chaſtity: and the pure gold of tride Vertue.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>On theſe 43. line.]</hi> Meaning the other La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
that waited on her, becauſe they were all
dead long before.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:119955:48"/>
                        <hi>There is one, 45. line.] Petrarch,</hi> whom
ſhe thought would be more hurt by her death
then her ſelfe, in regard of his extreme affection.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Another Company, 95. line.]</hi> The former
Company who were dead, could not bee ſory
for her death, becauſe ſhe would be nearer them,
but another company of Ladies, her friends and
neighbours, came to pray that death would let
her ſtay longer amongſt them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>One onely haire, 102. line.]</hi> Alluding to the
purple haire on the head of <hi>Niſus,</hi> which his
daughter ſtole, becauſe he could not die whiles
he wore it, as if <hi>Lauretta</hi> had had ſuch another:
or as if every body had one: See above in the
<hi>Triumph of Love,</hi> 2. Chap. 155. line.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>No adverſary, 142. line.]</hi> No wicked ſpirit,
meaning, that ſhe was troubled with no appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
at her death.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:119955:48"/>
                     <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <head>The Argument.</head>
                        <l>The happy ſpirit doth deſcend</l>
                        <l>To comfort her afflicted friend.</l>
                     </argument>
                     <l>THat night which followed the too-ſad decay</l>
                     <l>Of my beſt Sunne, whiles it was yet full day:</l>
                     <l>(Whence I remain as blinde) the Summer dew</l>
                     <l>Slides through the Aire, and faire <hi>Titonia</hi> now</l>
                     <l n="5">Beſtowes true dreames, (when like the growing yeare)</l>
                     <l>A Ladie (crown'd with orient jemmes) drew nere:</l>
                     <l>(With whom a thouſand other Crownes did move)</l>
                     <l>And ſtretching forth that object of my love,</l>
                     <l>Her hand; ſhe ſpoke, from whoſe ſweet words did flow</l>
                     <l n="10">Joy to my ſoule, and ſaid, Doe you not know</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="86" facs="tcp:119955:49"/>
Her, who hath rais'd your thoughts above the ſtrain</l>
                     <l>Of the low vulgar, as her love did gain</l>
                     <l>Place in your heart, then vvith a ſober looke</l>
                     <l>She ſet her ſelfe and me, cloſe by a brooke</l>
                     <l n="15">O're ſhadowed vvith a lavvrell and a beach:</l>
                     <l>Like one vvhoſe vveeping interrupts his ſpeech:</l>
                     <l>Muſt I not knovv the ſoul maintains my breath;</l>
                     <l>But doe you live, or are tane hence by death?</l>
                     <l>I anſwer'd, Pray inſtruct; I live ſaid ſhe,</l>
                     <l n="20">And you are dead, till you be joyn'd with me:</l>
                     <l>But time is ſhort, though vve deſire it long,</l>
                     <l>Take my advice, and curb your flovving tongue:</l>
                     <l>The day approacheth faſt, my ſad reply</l>
                     <l>Was this: Ah ſay, is it much pain to die?</l>
                     <l n="25">You lately tri'd and knevv, you'l ne'r obtain</l>
                     <l>True happineſſe, ſhe ſaid, if you remaine</l>
                     <l>In this ſo blinde and common errour; knovv,</l>
                     <l>Death is the end of priſon and darke vvoe</l>
                     <l>To vvell-bred ſoules, doth onely terrour prove</l>
                     <l n="30">To thoſe that place on earthy droſſe their love;</l>
                     <l>And even my death vvhich doth my ſoul annoy,</l>
                     <l>Could you conceive the leaſt part of my joy,</l>
                     <l>Would make you happy (having fixt her eye,</l>
                     <l>Whiles thus ſhe ſpake, devoutly on the skie)</l>
                     <l n="35">
                        <pb n="89" facs="tcp:119955:49"/>
Then clos'd her roſie lips, and ſilent ſtaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sickneſſe and Tyrants crueltie have made</l>
                     <l>Death bitter, I reply'd; 'Tis true, ſaid ſhe,</l>
                     <l>The pains we feel before death bitter be,</l>
                     <l>And helliſh torments worſe; but he whoſe minde</l>
                     <l n="40">Is ſtaid by heavenly hopes, ſhall truely finde,</l>
                     <l>Though weake and wearied, this laſt ſtep a ſhort</l>
                     <l>Sigh, and no more; as I drew neare the Port,</l>
                     <l>My body weake, my ſoul did much rejoyce;</l>
                     <l>Yet heard the whiſpering of mourning voyce;</l>
                     <l>Alas, for him who reckons every day</l>
                     <l n="45">A thouſand yeares, and ſtil in vain doth ſtay</l>
                     <l>On earth, and never more muſt ſee her face</l>
                     <l>On Sea or Land, and filleth every place</l>
                     <l>With that one Theame, and findeth no delight</l>
                     <l n="50">Of ought but her, to thinke, or ſpeake, or write.</l>
                     <l>My ſight I that way turn'd, from whence mine eare</l>
                     <l>Receiv'd the ſound, and ſaw 'twas ſhe whoſe care</l>
                     <l>Us'd to incite my Love, and temper thine:</l>
                     <l>Her face and ſpeech I knew, oft her divine</l>
                     <l>Wiſe councels, healing cordials were to me,</l>
                     <l n="55">With honeſt mirth and chearful gravitie;</l>
                     <l>When I with moſt felicitie was bleſt</l>
                     <l>In my firſt prime, and when thou lov'dſt me beſt:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="90" facs="tcp:119955:50"/>
When thy praiſe fam'd me moſt, even then my life</l>
                     <l n="60">Was little better then a bitter ſtrife,</l>
                     <l>Compar'd with that ſweet death, which few obtain;</l>
                     <l>No baniſht man call'd to his home again</l>
                     <l>Is more joy'd, then this paſſage pleaſed me:</l>
                     <l>But for the pitty that I had of thee</l>
                     <l n="65">I do adjure thee, by that faithfull Love</l>
                     <l>Thou knewſt on earth, but better know'ſt above;</l>
                     <l>Did ever Love, ſaid I, beget in thee</l>
                     <l>One thought to pitty my long miſery,</l>
                     <l>Not wronging thy great minde; the ſweet diſdain,</l>
                     <l n="70">Sweet mildneſſe of your looks in doubtfull pain,</l>
                     <l>Hath held my wiſhes long; ere I had ſaid</l>
                     <l>The words, a lightning ſmile, ſuch as oft paid</l>
                     <l>And eas'd the ſadneſſe of my wounded heart</l>
                     <l>I ſaw: Then ſhe replide; Nothing could part</l>
                     <l>My ſoule from thine, nor ſhal; but 'tdid behove</l>
                     <l>With outward coldneſſe to reſtrain thy love,</l>
                     <l>No other way would have preſerv'd our fame;</l>
                     <l>A rod deſtroyes not a kinde mothers name:</l>
                     <l>I ſtudied to conceale my Love, ſuch care</l>
                     <l n="80">And providence dwell not with hope and feare;</l>
                     <l>My countenance you ſaw, but not my heart,</l>
                     <l>I turn'd and ſtaid thy courſe with heedfull Art<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="91" facs="tcp:119955:50"/>
As one would tame a horſe: my cheeks have been</l>
                     <l>Oft dy'd with fain'd wrath, when my heart within</l>
                     <l n="85">Was a whole fire of Love; yet reaſon ſtill</l>
                     <l>Kept her owne place, and did command my will:</l>
                     <l>But when I found thee overcharg'd with woe,</l>
                     <l>I us'd my milder lookes, preventing ſo</l>
                     <l>Thy death, and my reproach; when I obſerv'd</l>
                     <l n="90">Thy paſſion grow too ſtrong, I then reſerv'd</l>
                     <l>My ſelfe, as if with griefe or feare oppreſt:</l>
                     <l>Theſe were my enſignes, and I found it beſt</l>
                     <l>To mixe diſdains with favours, this your ſongs</l>
                     <l>Have made already paſſe through many tongues;</l>
                     <l n="95">When I beheld the teares ſwimme in thine eye,</l>
                     <l>I ſaid, Without my help, I feare he'll dye:</l>
                     <l>Then gave ſome modeſt aid; when you were bold,</l>
                     <l>I ſaid, he muſt be curb'd: now pale and cold,</l>
                     <l>Now warme and freſh, now ſad, now full of joy,</l>
                     <l n="100">I kept thee ſafe, not without much annoy;</l>
                     <l>Glad t' have thus finiſht, 'twere enough reward</l>
                     <l>Could I believ't; thus trembling, as affeard,</l>
                     <l>Not with dry eyes, I ſaid, ſhe made reply,</l>
                     <l>Doe you diſtruſt, for what end ſhould I ly;</l>
                     <l n="105">A little bluſhing, then went on, If to</l>
                     <l>My partiall eye, the world eſteemed you:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="92" facs="tcp:119955:51"/>
I held me quiet, being throughly bleſt</l>
                     <l>In that true-love knot lockt within my breſt:</l>
                     <l>The faire report (if it be truth) I heare</l>
                     <l n="110">Thy praiſes have acquir'd me farre and neare,</l>
                     <l>I much eſteem, and never more did crave</l>
                     <l>But moderation in thy love to have;</l>
                     <l>That onely wanted; whiles with ſignes of woe</l>
                     <l>You would perſwade what I did throughly know,</l>
                     <l n="115">To open view you did your heart expoſe:</l>
                     <l>My coldneſſe hence, hence your diſtemper roſe:</l>
                     <l>In other things we did like friends agree,</l>
                     <l>Joyn'd by a Love, from all baſe paſſions free;</l>
                     <l>My heart was burnt with almoſt equal fire,</l>
                     <l n="120">At leaſt, when once I knew thy ſtrong deſire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>But mine I hid, whiles yours was open laid:</l>
                     <l>When you were hoarce, with having often praid,</l>
                     <l>For pittie, I was ſilent, ſhame and feare</l>
                     <l>Were cauſe my great Love did but ſmal appeare:</l>
                     <l n="125">Griefe is of no leſſe weight, becauſe conceal'd,</l>
                     <l>Nor more when by impatience 'tis reveal'd;</l>
                     <l>Deceit doth not increaſe, nor yet impaire</l>
                     <l>A truth; But ſay, Was not my Love then cleare</l>
                     <l>When I receiv'd the lines you ſent before</l>
                     <l n="130">
                        <hi>Your face and ſong?</hi> My Love dares ſay no more.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:119955:51"/>
My heart was ſtil with thee, though I reſtrain'd</l>
                     <l>My lookes; and you, as having vvrong, complain'd,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe I gave the moſt part, and vvithdrevv</l>
                     <l>The leaſt, yet was not that vvith-held from you;</l>
                     <l n="135">A thouſand and a thouſand times mine eye</l>
                     <l>Was turn'd with pittie on thy miſery;</l>
                     <l>And ever had continued ſtil the ſame,</l>
                     <l>But that I fear'd a danger in thy flame:</l>
                     <l>And not to leave you in ſuſpence, Ile ſhovv</l>
                     <l n="140">What I beleeve you vvil be glad to know;</l>
                     <l>In all the reſt I found a pleaſing fate,</l>
                     <l>Onely for one cauſe I diſlik'd my ſtate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>My place of birth did to my thoughts appeare</l>
                     <l>Too meane, and I ſtil grieve 'tvvas not more neare</l>
                     <l n="145">Thy flovvry ſeat, yet doe I vvel approve</l>
                     <l>Of any Countrey where I had thy Love;</l>
                     <l>Beſides, the heart in vvhich I place moſt truſt,</l>
                     <l>If me thou hadſt not known, 'tis like it muſt</l>
                     <l>Have elſewhere lov'd, ſo had I got leſſe fame;</l>
                     <l n="150">You do miſtake, my Love had been the ſame</l>
                     <l>Where ever you had liv'd, my Starres did raiſe</l>
                     <l>Me to ſo high a flame, I ſaid: much praiſe</l>
                     <l>And honour have attended me, ſhe ſaid,</l>
                     <l>How e're it be, but I too long have ſtaid:</l>
                     <l n="155">
                        <pb n="94" facs="tcp:119955:52"/>
Thy joy makes thee forget the wings of time,</l>
                     <l>Aurora now brings day, the Sun doth climbe</l>
                     <l>Above the Ocean, from her golden bed;</l>
                     <l>At laſt, about to part and leave me ſad,</l>
                     <l>She ſaid, If you have ought beſides make haſte</l>
                     <l n="160">And end your ſpeach before the time be paſt;</l>
                     <l>All my paſt ſuff'rings your kinde words make light,</l>
                     <l>I anſwered, But I grieve without your ſight,</l>
                     <l>And wiſh to know, if I am like to be</l>
                     <l>Long here, or if I ſoon may follow thee:</l>
                     <l n="165">She going thus replide; I do beleeve,</l>
                     <l>That without me on earth you long muſt live.</l>
                     <trailer>The End of the Triumph of Death.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="annotations">
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:119955:52"/>
                     <head>ANNOTATIONS
UPON
THE SECOND CHAPTER
OF THE
TRIUMPH
OF
DEATH.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>BEſt ſunne, 2. line.]</hi> Meaning <hi>Lauretta,</hi> who
dyed in the middeſt of her age, being but
33. yeares old.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Titania, 4. line.]</hi> Aurora the morning, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
Titania from Titan, the Sunne, who lodgeth
with her.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>True dreames, 5. line.]</hi> The morning
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119955:53"/>
dreames are held true, becauſe the fancie is then
moſt free from vapours.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A Ladie, 6. line.] Lauretta</hi> crowned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
ſhe was now a Saint.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Other crownes did move, 7. line.]</hi> Other
crowned Saints that came along with her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
hee thought they muſt dote on her, as hee
did.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Doe you live, &amp;c. 18. line.]</hi> The <hi>Italian
Commentary</hi> makes a long and needleſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
to defend the congruitie of this place, as
if all did not know that thoſe who dreame
they ſee a dead perſon appeare, as if alive,
doe ordinarily make ſuch a doubt in their
ſleepe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When I receiv'd, 129. line.]</hi> Hee had one
time, as hee uſed, ſent her ſome of his verſes, and
coming himſelfe juſt as they were preſented to
her, ſhee received them in his preſence, <hi>Italian
Commentary.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>My Love dares ſay no more, 130. line.]</hi> She
ſung a ſong, beginning thus, for an undirect ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
of her reſervation.</p>
                     <p>Flowrie ſeat, 145. line.] <hi>Florence.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Of any countrey, &amp;c. 146. line.]</hi> The ſenſe
here ſeemed cleare to mee, that <hi>Lauretta</hi> being
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119955:53"/>
well deſcended, but borne in Cabriers, an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure
village, ſhee was onely diſpleaſed with
that particular; yet the honour of his love was
recompence enough for that misfortune, and
any place good enough where ſhee had that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour:
and if ſhee had beene borne neare Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
where hee had his birth, ſhee might
have beene unknowne to him who had left it,
his parents being chaſed from thence by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
faction; and if hee had not ſeen her, it is
like hee might have loved another, ſo ſhould
ſhee have miſſed that honour, to which <hi>Petrarch</hi>
anſwers, That where ever ſhe had beene borne,
hee muſt needs have loved her, by the influence
of his Starres: but when I looke on the <hi>Italian
Commentary,</hi> I finde hee takes the meaning
quite other wayes, which I have expreſſed as
neare his ſence as I can, thus:
<q>
                           <l>Thy flowry ſeat, for though I well approve</l>
                           <l>Of that faire countrey where I had thy love:</l>
                           <l>Yet might that heart, in which I truſted, ſtray</l>
                           <l>To other beauties, and be turned away</l>
                           <l>By this defect, ſo had I got leſſe fame, &amp;c.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>As if ſhee had ſaid her greateſt misfortune
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119955:54"/>
was feare or jealouſie, that hee diſliking the
place in which ſhee lived (though ſhe thought
it ſweete enough) might change his affection,
and bee drawne to love ſome other<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Let him
that reads or compares, take the ſence hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth
moſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="translators_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:119955:54"/>
            <head>Advertiſement to the
Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt title page ſhould
have told thee that all
the three Triumphes were
tranſlated out of the <hi>Italian,</hi>
a circumſtance I conſidered
not then, ſince it is thought
neceſſary to ſay ſo much, I
wil now ſay more: I never ſaw
them, nor any part of them, in
any other language but <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi>
except the poore words
<pb facs="tcp:119955:55"/>
in which I have cloathed
them. If they afford thee
either profit or delight, I ſhall
the more willingly beſtow
ſome of my few leaſure hours
on turning the other three
Triumphs, of <hi>Fame, Time,</hi>
and <hi>Divinitie</hi> or <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Farewell.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:119955:55"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 19. line 13. reade amaſedly. p. 22. r. <hi>Maſſiniſſa</hi> was.
p. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. l. 8. r. mixed, for mingled. p. 33. r. blowes for wounds.
p. 35. l. 15. <hi>del.</hi> now. p. 54. l. 5 r. provincial Poets. p. 65. l. 22. r.
Linternum. p. 70. is figured falſe, in the 17. l. of it, read
know for knew, and in the 22. l. r. thy foul for my ſoul.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:119955:56"/>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119955:56"/>
            <l>WHen firſt my <hi>light</hi> did ſhine, you lik'd me well.</l>
            <l>Now that is gone; you hate my loathſome ſmell;</l>
            <l>You with prolongers made me live, and art</l>
            <l>Preſerv'd my <hi>light;</hi> but now <hi>Time</hi> acts his part,</l>
            <l>Triumphant <hi>Time,</hi> ſhews now my glaſſe is run</l>
            <l>And all muſt end, that ever was begun:</l>
            <l>Envy hath playd its part, and I do go</l>
            <l>To <hi>Coffin:</hi> as I do, all muſt do ſo.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Time</hi> breaths a ſhrewd and life-bereaving blaſt,</l>
            <l>Yet upward flyes my <hi>light,</hi> where it ſhall laſt.</l>
            <l>I'me glad to part from <hi>body,</hi> which I lov'd</l>
            <l>So deer, that many wayes and arts I prov'd</l>
            <l>This mudwall to maintain, and body ſave,</l>
            <l>But yet in ſpight of me 'twill go to grave.</l>
            <l>This is my comfort, <hi>Body,</hi> that thy tombe</l>
            <l>Which is thy <hi>grave,</hi> ſhall be thy mothers womb</l>
            <l>To bring thee once again unto the <hi>light,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And <hi>life,</hi> which <hi>death</hi> ſhall never know, or night:</l>
            <l>Then be content, though you and I depart:</l>
            <l>Yet <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> ſtill ſhall have one heart.</l>
            <l>And upward flyes my <hi>ſoul,</hi> where it ſhall dwell,</l>
            <l>Beyond the reach of <hi>Envy, Death,</hi> or <hi>Hell.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
