<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tyrants and protectors set forth in their colours. Or, The difference between good and bad magistrates; in several characters, instances and examples of both. / By J.P.</title>
            <author>Price, John, Citizen of London.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90972</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3349</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E738_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203206</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863250</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863250</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115440</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A90972)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115440)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 113:E738[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tyrants and protectors set forth in their colours. Or, The difference between good and bad magistrates; in several characters, instances and examples of both. / By J.P.</title>
                  <author>Price, John, Citizen of London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Cripps and L. Lloyd, and are to be sold at their shop in Popes-head Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.P. = John Price, an anagram of whose name ("Cri in hope") appears on E1v.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June [ye] 5th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Despotism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115440:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TYRANTS AND PROTECTORS Set forth In their Colours. OR, THE Difference between Good and Bad MAGISTRATES; In ſeveral Characters, Inſtances and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of both.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROV. 28. 15.</bibl>As a roaring Lion and a ranging Bear, ſo is a wicked Ruler over the poor people.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Chap. 16. 12.</bibl>It is an abomination to Kings to commit wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for the Throne is eſtabliſhed by Righteouſneſs.</q>
            <p>By <hi>J. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Cripps</hi> and <hi>L. Lloyd,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhop in <hi>Popes-head</hi> Alley. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115440:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115440:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Tyrants Teſt, and a Protectors Pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture, are worthy thy contemplation in theſe froward times; in the one thou mayeſt read what thy condition <hi>had been</hi> through Gods moſt righteous ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity: had he not graciouſly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the other what thy condition is, and mayſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect <hi>to be</hi> through his meer mercy ſo interpoſing. Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny makes Earth a hell, and a Tyrant is a Devil incarnate. Juſt Government makes Heaven on earth, and good Princes, <hi>Gods in the likeneſs of men.</hi> No
<pb facs="tcp:115440:3"/>
Government is hell broke looſe, where all would rule, and none <hi>be ruled;</hi> every mans <hi>luſt</hi> would be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans <hi>law;</hi> his wants meaſured by his <hi>will,</hi> and his <hi>deſerts</hi> by his <hi>deſires,</hi> which would render men <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> in fleſh; and daily tormentors to themſelves and others, and therefore any Government is better then none, Tyranny then Anarchy, but juſt Government baniſheth the wicked from a Nation, (as it did the evil Angels out of Heaven) making the remaining Inhabitants to <hi>ſhout for joy;</hi> Here thou ſhalt find a Tyrant tryed, and a Protector pourtraitur'd, by plain Characters, brief inſtances, and examples of both, (which truly conſidered with our own concernments in both reſpects) would muzzle the mouths of our mutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing murmurours, and render us more ſenſible of our preſent happineſſe, and thankful for it; thou ſhalt not here find a cenſorious Condemnation of the long and ſhort Parliaments, nor a flattering congratulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all publick tranſactions ſince their date; for although theſe be <hi>ad nos</hi> in reſpect of their events, yet are they <hi>ſupra nos</hi> in reſpect of our cenſures, this is my principle, this is my prayer, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in men have been wiſe, and done worthily for their Countreys Liberties, and the Saints Intereſt, <hi>God would remember it, and never forget it;</hi> and that wherein they have been weak, and failed in their duty, being but fleſh and blood, and men at beſt, though the beſt of men, <hi>God would forget it, &amp; never remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it;</hi> the Demonſtration of Tyranny, the Commendation of Magiſtracy, the characterizing of good and bad Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, in their principles and practiſes, with the effects thereof to themſelves, and their people, was the deſigne of
<pb facs="tcp:115440:3"/>
my heart, had the fact anſwered the fancy, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct the project. Reader, If thou beeſt a Son of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and a Citizen of <hi>Jeruſalem, which is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove,</hi> the <hi>peace that is within thy gates, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity that is within thy palaces,</hi> muſt needs render thee ſenſible of thy felicity by thy freedom from ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and fruition of liberty by our preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, thankful for it, and fruitful under it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept like <hi>Jeſſurun</hi> thou art waxen fat, and kickeſt up the heel, haſt turned thy grace into wantonneſs, and thy table be made a ſnare unto thee; if thou beeſt one of them that have thus converted their fulneſs into folly, and their liberty into licentiouſneſs, murmuring that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> (I mean) thy <hi>quondam</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers are thy preſent Protectors, and haſt forgotten the days of old, and the years of many generations, who hath ſown that crop in tears, yea in blood, which thou now reapeſt in joy, if that liberty will not ſatisfie, the like whereof is not in all the world, that liberty the like whereof the generations that are paſt did never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand; that liberty, a greater then which thou knoweſt not how to deſire (except it be to have power to ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannize it over thy brethren diſſenting from thee, as precious in the eyes of the Lord as thy ſelf, and it may be more in the truth then thy ſelf) not a Son of <hi>Belial</hi> ſuffered to moleſt thee, nor a dog to move his tongue againſt thee, If thou canſt not in this ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſit down with content, who will pity thee if thou riſeſt up, and fall? If thou wilt read and conſider the difference between good and bad Magiſtrates, thou mayeſt ſee the miſery which thy Fore-fathers felt, and our ſelves but lately feared under the one, and thy
<pb facs="tcp:115440:4"/>
preſent felicity, which our fore-fathers deſired, and we now enjoy under the other, the due and ſpiritual effects of which viſion upon all our hearts, through the Grace of our God in Jeſus Chriſt, is the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Friend, and Servant, J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 31. l. 32. <hi>for</hi> ſpoil you, <hi>read</hi> ſpoil him. p. 11. l. 34. for <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendum,</hi> r. <hi>violandum.</hi> p. 12. l. 13. <hi>r.</hi> profuſeneſs. p. 15. l. 32. <hi>for</hi> Aſſes <hi>r.</hi> Laſſes.</p>
            <p>Theſe, beſides ſome others, which I pray thee correct with thy Pen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115440:4"/>
            <head>A Tyrant, OR <hi>Homo Homini Demon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>1. <hi>TYranny is a Complication of Iniquity; whereby men (being Gods in Power) become Devils in practiſe, to terrifie and torture all that withſtand them in their deviliſh dealings. A Tyrant is a Devil in heart, a Man in ſhape, a Lyon in power, a Bear in practiſe, affrighting his People with his rage, and roaring and tearing them limb-meal with his teeth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r merc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of Tyrants are cruel: the Scripture calls them, <hi>roaring Lyon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, evening Wol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, that gnaw not the bones till the morning, Zeph.</hi> 3. 3. not ſatisfied ſo long as any thing is left, dealing by the people as the cruel <hi>Spaniards</hi> do by the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> of whom it is ſtoried, that they ſhew them favour when they do not for their pleaſure whip their nak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bodies with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oards, and dayly drop them with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acon: They cauſe the juſt to periſh, and the wicked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſh qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g the tears of the oppreſſed, making m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lody with their miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry and muſick with their ſigns. The oppreſſed <hi>Romans</hi> complain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115440:5"/>
               <hi>Pompey, Noſtra miſeria tu es magnus,</hi> Thou ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> become great by our miſeries: like thoſe Miſcreants in <hi>Micah</hi> 3. 3. they <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at the fleſh, and fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the skin, break the bones, and chop them in pieces as for the pot:</hi> Like thoſe <hi>American</hi> Canibals, who when they take a priſoner, feed upon him alive and by degrees, cutting off from his body now a meal and then a meal, which they roaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes, fearing up the wounds with a firebrand to ſtanch the blood, to the unutterable aggravation of his horror and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Such a Lyon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ampant was <hi>Nero, 2 Tim. 4 17. I was delivered out of the mouth of the Lyon;</hi> and the reſt of thoſe Monſters of mankind, the bloody Tyrants, Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Emperors, in the primitive Perſecutions; and their Romiſh Succeſſors, the ſame in cruelty, though not in profeſſion, ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing complaints againſt them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>m the people of God in the voyce of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> perſonating <hi>Sion, Jer. 51. 34. Nebuchadn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zzar King of Babylon hath devoured me, he hath cruſhed me, he hath made me an empty veſſel, he hath ſwallowed me up like a Dragon, he hath filled his belly with my delicates, he hath caſt me out.</hi> It is ſaid, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Tyrants in the firſt Perſecutions did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy twenty ſeven millions of people, and that with ſuch cruelties as were never heard of before. One mentions a cruel Tyrant, who to get monies of his miſerable Subjects, uſed to ſend for them firſt to the Court (as <hi>Charls ultimus Angliae</hi> did uſe to ſend for the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> and others that refuſed to pay Ship monies, &amp;c.) and if they did deny to pay according to his pleaſure, he would firſt knock out one of their t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth, and then another, until they did yield to pay the ſame; as <hi>Charls</hi> aforeſaid by himſelf or Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts did ſend perſons that would not pay his ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal and unjuſt demands to <hi>New-gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>A Tyrants Regiment is without Righteouſneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; he lives by Robbery with Authority, making his Will his Warrant, and his Luſt his Law: He is not a Magiſtrate, but a Malefactor; not a Preſerver, but a Perſecutor of Law and Equity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Righteouſneſs is a ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y in the Court of Tyrants (except un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned in their own intereſt,) where golden Angels (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if their name be Legion) are their ſacred Oracles, from whoſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115440:5"/>
mouth they receive, and ſo give ſentence accordingly, be it right or wrong, to the wreſting of Judgment: the Bribe proſpereth which way ſoever it turneth; <hi>making even wiſe men mad</hi> by their unrighteous ſentence: <hi>Their right hand is full of bribes, Pſal. 26. 10. Solomon</hi> ſaith, ſuch perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>trouble their own houſes, Prov.</hi> 15. 27. fire their neſts while they think to feather them: <hi>Fire ſhall conſume the tabernacles of bribery, Job</hi> 15. 34. It was an Oath taken by the very Heathen Judges, <hi>Audiam accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatorem &amp; reum ſine aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctibus &amp; perſonarum reſpectione,</hi> I will hear the Plaintiff and Difendant with an equal mind without aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction or reſpect of perſons. It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>corded, that <hi>Olanes</hi> ſat upon the fleyd skin of his father <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lanes,</hi> na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>led by <hi>Chambiſes</hi> on the Tribunal. There are more th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n whiſpers of very ſad ſtories of the bribery and baſeneſs of our la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Engliſh Court and the greateſt therein, taking mony on both ſides, and doing Juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce on neither ſide; but, as I ſaid before, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e conſumes the tabernacles of bribery: wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſs the woful deſolations of that wretched Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; the Husband hunted out of the world by the hand of Juſtice, and driven from light to darkneſs, the Wife baniſhed from the Land of her pleaſures, the Children in their ſeveral diſperſions in ſeveral places unwelcome to all, being a burthen to all. <hi>The Word of the Lord is tryed: The houſe of the wicked ſhall be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, Prov. 14 11. Brimſtone ſhall be ſcattered upon his habitation, Job</hi> 18. 15.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>He carries death at his tongues end, the peoples welfare is at his m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er pleaſure, where his word is there is power, and be his doings right or wrong who dares ſay unto him, What doſt thou? Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart is hard, his hands are heavy, and wo be to him tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eels their ſtroke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He hath long arms, and can ſtrike at a diſtance; he wants not a heart to conceive, a head to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ive, nor hands to execute his bloody Commands: It is ſaid, that <hi>Methridates</hi> with one Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter did ſlay fourſcore thouſand Citizens of <hi>Rome;</hi> none muſt croſs them in their deviliſh cruelty, except he will take a Bear by the tooth, or a Lyon by the beard. I dare not diſpute, ſaid a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher to <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor, with him that hath thirty Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115440:6"/>
at his command, <hi>neque in eum ſcribere qui poteſt proſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere</hi> nor write againſt him that can eaſily undo me: Againſt his word <hi>there muſt be no riſing up, Prov</hi> 30. 31. They will ride without reins, until unhors'd with <hi>Haman,</hi> and their honour of all becomes the hatred and ſcorn of all: <hi>His wrath is as a roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lyon, Prov.</hi> 19. 12. amazing al that are about them: as a late King of <hi>England,</hi> who (though he had more of the nature of a Fox then a L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, yet) would make h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Courtiers tremble with his ſparkling countenance, fierce, fiery, furious and ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enzy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like curſing and ſwearing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Nebuchadn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zzars</hi> rage againſt thoſe three Worthies in <hi>Daniel,</hi> was hot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er then his Oven (for he had deſtroyed them in his heart, when his Oven could not hurt them) for refuſing to obey his idolatrous Commands: and <hi>Herod</hi> by the word of his mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h hath bloody Executioners to murther poor innocent child<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en in a barbarous manner. Now <hi>curſed be the anger of</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yrants, <hi>for it is fierce; and their wrath, for it is cruel;</hi> by means whereof they live undeſired, they dye unla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, as <hi>Nerva, Valentinian;</hi> yea their ruine is the rejoycing of the people, as was that of <hi>Nero.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Cum mors crudelem rapuiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſaeva Neronem</l>
               <l>Credibile eſt mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os Romam agitaſſe jocos.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>When the wicked periſh, the City ſhouts for joy, Prov.</hi> 11. 11. Abſolute Power tick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es Tyrants; to deſtroy with a word, a nod, this is their glory. <hi>Caeſar</hi> told <hi>Met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llus,</hi> he could as eaſily deſtroy him as bid it to be done: And <hi>Caligula,</hi> ſpeaking to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, I laugh (ſaid he) to think that I can kill you with a nod of my head, and that this fair throat of my Wives ſhall be preſently cut if I but ſpeak the word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To have power to crucifie and power to ſave was <hi>Pilates</hi> pleaſure and delight.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>He makes his people tremble before him; he kills and ſaves, puts down and ſets up in the haughtineſs of his heart and pride of his power, perſons and principles at his meer diſcretion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> that having a Kingdom, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, glory and honour, in ſo much that all people, Nations and Languages feared and trembled before him, his heart was lifted up, and his mind hardened in pride, that whom he would he ſlew,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115440:6"/>
and whom he would he kept alive, and whom he would he ſet up, and whom he would he put down: You may judg of their diſpoſition by his own, and of his by his cruel decree againſt <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> who did him no wrong; like King like Courtiers, like Prince like Prieſt; for whom will they advance but either thoſe that are their likes, or whom they hope to make their likes? When <hi>Princes are roaring Lions, Zeph.</hi> 3. 3. they that are advanced <hi>Judges are evening Wolves,</hi> verſ. 3. <hi>The Prophets are light and treacherous, and the Prieſts do violence to the Law,</hi> verſ. 4. What a curſed crew is here? He doth not ſcatter, but gather the wicked about him, for they love their image; <hi>Regis ad exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum, &amp;c.</hi> Hence it is that Kings Courts in Cities and Countries as they remove from place to place, are little other ways then a moving Hell on Earth, where the Elect of Satan, the moſt curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſwearing, blaſpheming, laſcivious, proud, wanton, effeminate, baſe and beaſtly perſons, are gathered together, from all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, people and families of the whole Country, infecting all places where ever they come, rendring them (as it were) the very ſuburbs of Hell: Hence it was that where the Prince and the Prophet <hi>(Anglicè)</hi> the <note n="*" place="margin">Kings and Biſhops.</note> Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants had their Seats and their Seas, the Cities, Towns, Countries were the moſt debauch'd parts of the whole Nation.</p>
            <p>5. <hi>He will rule all, and be ruled by none; he throws away the bonds of Nature, Reaſon and Religion, and acts by his pride, pleaſure and paſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, not by God, Nature, Reaſon, Law: <hi>Exod. 5. 2. Pharaoh</hi> ſaid, <hi>Who is the Lord that I ſhould obey his voyce, and let Iſrael go? I know not the Lord, neither will I let Iſrael go<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pride compaſſeth them about like a chain, violence covereth them as a garment, Pſal.</hi> 73 6. Taking pleaſure in their pride and cruelty, until their pride bring them low, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29. 23. Their greatneſs and gallantry makes them ſwell and look loftily: <hi>Is not this great Babel that I have built for the houſe of my Kingdom, by the might of my power, and for the honour of my Majesty?</hi> ſaid proud <hi>Nebuchadnezzar:</hi> but God pluckt down his plumes, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115440:7"/>
ſtain'd all his glory, and ſent him to ſchool amongſt wilde beaſts, that he might learn better manners then to vye it thus with the great God of Heaven &amp; Earth. Sea the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ign and Ruine, the pride and puniſhment of <hi>Tyrus, Eze.</hi> 28. 27. becauſe his heart was lift<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d up, he ſaid, <hi>I am a God;</hi> but God threatened to darken his br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to ſhame his glory, and to bring him to the pit. I might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance likewiſe in <hi>Herod,</hi> who glittering in his ſhining garb (as <hi>Joſephus</hi> hath it) aſſuming the honour of God, was ungodded, yea unman'd by the baſeſt of vermin. The time would fail to ſpeak to <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adad Rabſhecha, Zenacherib. Antiochus, Nicanor,</hi> of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, of <hi>Nero,</hi> of <hi>Bajazet</hi> the great Turkiſh Emperor, with many others, whoſe pride, inſolency and haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs brought the wheel o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gods wrath ſo exempla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lry upon them, that they are made (ſome in ſacred, and others in other Hiſtories) perpetual monuments of Gods moſt fearful indignation; amongſt whom may we not bring the late King of <hi>England</hi> of bleeding memory, whoſe ſtubbornneſs, reſoluteneſs and unruleableneſs by Parliaments, Councels, or the wiſeſt of his people, brought him to ruine, becauſe they would not ſuffer him to command like a God without contradiction? He acted ſo like a Devil, murth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and maſſacring his people with fire and ſword, until the wrath of the Lord broke out upon him, like a Lion from the thicke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, devouring him by the hands of his own people, to the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rror and amazement of all the Princes round about: his Will was his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and his Reaſon his Will, and both his downfall.</p>
            <p>6. <hi>His Commonwealth is a common woe, where his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or Subjects as in a great Bridewell receive their work and their wages, their labour and their laſhes, their ſtripes and ſtipends, as his meer diſcretion, and the will of his Beadles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where a Tyrant rules, the Eſtates, Lives and Liberties of the People are not theirs, but his; not at theirs, but at his commands. <hi>Cato</hi> calls them, <hi>Fures publicos,</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ieves; another, <hi>Latrones cum privilegio,</hi> R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s by authority; the very Scabs of a Nation: <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5. 7. <hi>He looked for Judgment, but behold Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion</hi> (or a Scab,) <hi>for Righteouſneſs, but behold a Cry:</hi> Like that of the poor Subjects of <hi>Phalaris,</hi> whoſe delight it was to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115440:7"/>
ſee and hear their tortures and ſcreeches: as <hi>John Maria</hi> Duke of <hi>Millane,</hi> who took pleaſure to throw his people to be torn in pieces by fierce Maſtives. With the <hi>Spaniard</hi> it is ſin to enquire into Religion, and puniſhable by a perpetual cruel Inquiſition: With the <hi>French</hi> it is crime enough in the poor Husbandman to wear good clothes of his own getting, eat good meat of his own breeding; it is meat for his Maſter and his Attendants, too good for him. The great <hi>Turk</hi> hath his Bow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſtrings to ſtrangle his Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts at their pleaſure, whoſe commands muſt be obeyed, though they be to require whom he pleaſeth to throw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves headlong, and break them into pieces down ſteep Rocks and Clifts, leſt a worſe thing (if worſe may be) ſhould befall them.</p>
            <p>7. <hi>In ſtead of puniſhing offences he arms Offenders, whereby he becomes the greateſt Traytor, Murtherer and Thief, viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the greateſt Truſts of the Liberties, Lives and Livelyhoods of the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As God hath his good Angels to do his Will, <hi>viz.</hi> ſecure and defend, protect and preſerve his people; and the Devil his evil Angels for contrary ſervice: even ſo Tyrants, which are Satans firſt-born, have their Angels or Meſſengers, <hi>viz.</hi> whole Troops, Regiments, and Armies, to execute their curſed Commands: as <hi>Herod</hi> had his armed men ſent out to deſtroy poor Innocents; all Hiſtories recording the cruelty of Tyrants, mention their nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous and armed Agents, their ſwift M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſengers and Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of fury, who are commonly the ſcum, filth and froth of the Nation: hence it was, that when the late King ſet up his Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard againſt his Parliament and People, the vileſt, baſeſt, and worſt of the Nation did flow in unto him, whereof God made a great Sacrifice unto his Juſtice and Indignation by their utter ruine and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>8. <hi>He eats up the people like bread, and drinks their blood like ſweet wine, commanding all as if he made all, though he mars all, making his Creators his creatures, his Makers his meat, his Lords his Loons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115440:8"/>All men naturally are born free, made at firſt to command, and not to obey; and ſo lived, until from the Spring of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion they fell among themſelves to do violence and wrong; and foreſeeing that ſuch courſes muſt needs tend to common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, they agreed by common conſent to bind each other from mutual injury; and becauſe a mutual faith was not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient unto mutual peace, therefore they ordained Authority by mutual conſent, and betruſted ſome therewith to reſtrain by force and puniſhment the violation of common right, which Truſtees were not ſo made to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Lords and Maſters, but D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies and Commiſſioners to execute that Juſtice, which elſe every man by the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of Nature and Covenant muſt have executed for himſelf and for another: and why any man ſhould have lordſhip or authority over others but for this common end, is not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable: Rulers were made by the people, not the people by them; they were made for the people, not the people for them; they are each particular mans Lord by their own conſent for each mans peace, but they are ſervants to the whole for the good of all; no man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s bound to the Ruler in any matter of common pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, but he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bound to them all in common preſervation; the whole owe not their lives to any though never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o great on Earth, the greateſt oweth his li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to the whole, and is made great by God and man for ſervice, and not for Lordſhip ſake: wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſuch Truſtees turn Tyrants, what are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt Traytors? Is not Treaſon the betraying of juſt Truſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? the greater the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt, the greater the Treaſon, the worſe the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aytor: What greater Truſt then that of Governmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? which being once vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly and plenarily betrayed, the people are <hi>ipſo facto</hi> diſcha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d from their all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>geance: The affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mation, that the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in one body is inferior to on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſingle man who ever he be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is high Trea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on againſt the Dignity of Mankind. It was the ſaying of a Heath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, <hi>I rule not my people by Tyranny as if they were Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, but am my ſelf liable if I do unjuſtly to ſuffer juſtly:</hi> And <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperor, giving a naked ſword to one whom he made General of his <hi>Praetorian</hi> Forces, ſaid, <hi>Take this drawn ſword, to uſe for me, if I raign well; if not, to uſe it againſt me:</hi> But a Tyrant, what is he but <hi>carnivorum animal,</hi> a ravenous crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a devourer of the people?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115440:8"/>9. <hi>He makes no more conſcience of killing men, then Moles, of burning their Houſes, then Waſps neſts, of deſtroying whole Families, then Litters of Rots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Methridates</hi> did ſlay fourſcore thouſand Citizens of <hi>Rome:</hi> what need we inſtance the large volumes of cruel Tyrants? of their heading, hanging, burning, frying, roaſting, ſcalding, wracking, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, chopp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, flaying, their poor innocent ſubjects at their pleaſure, making paſtime with their pains, &amp; ſports with their ſpoils; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he rapes, robberies, murthers, burning and deſtroying of ſo many thouſand perſons, Cities, Towns, and Families by the late Tyrant in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> in his late bloody Wars, and Maſſacres, raiſed for the utter ruine of all thoſe that in the leaſt withſtood his tyrannical principles, and uſurpations.</p>
            <p>10. <hi>He holds himſelf accountable to none, but God alone, though he believes no more God in the Heavens, then man in the moon, pretending moſt to that which his Soul moſt abhors, Religion and Righteouſneſs, the Glory of God, and the good of the people, are moſt in his mouth, when his heart loaths them, and his conſcience ſerves him to ſay, and unſay, to ſwear, and forſwear, advance, and abaſe principles and perſons, to ſatisfie his luſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tyrants know no God but themſelves; <hi>Who is the Lord?</hi> ſaid <hi>Pharaoh: W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o can deliver out of my hands?</hi> ſaid <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar. Alexander</hi> the Great commanded himſelf to be held a God, and <hi>Apelles</hi> pictured him with a thunder-bolt, <hi>Lyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> with this poſie,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jupiter aſſerui terram mihi; tu aſſere coelum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let <hi>Jove</hi> take Heaven, ſo the Earth be min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>With which pictures <hi>Alexander</hi> was ſo delighted, that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that none ſhould take his pictures, but <hi>Lypſius</hi> and <hi>Apelles; Caligula</hi> braved his god <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and threatned him, though at every clap of thunder, or flaſh of lightning, he would run haſtily and hide himſelf under his bed like a wrigling worm. <hi>Tullius Hoſtilius</hi> ſaid, That Religion did but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffeminate mens
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115440:9"/>
minds, and unfit them for noble imployments, but one witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that even this <hi>Roman</hi> King fained to himſelf two new gods, <hi>viz. Pavorem, &amp; Pallorem,</hi> whom he carried about with him in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s own boſom, ſuch wretches not fearing him that made all things, are ſometimes affrighted with nothing; As <hi>Ahaz</hi> that trembled at the ſhaking of a leaf, and <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> who hid his head among thorns; and thence was taken and bound in ſetters, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. 11.</p>
            <p>A Tyrant wants not Paraſites that ſay to him as one ſaid to the Pope,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tu meritò in terris diceris eſſe Deus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou well deſerveſt here to be ſtiled a god.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>How did the peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-blow <hi>Herod</hi> with their flatteries? cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him up for a god, and God makes thoſe worms to devour him; the voice of a Tyrants heart is like that of <hi>Ninive, I am and there is none beſides me;</hi> or as <hi>Babylon, I will aſcend unto Heaven, and ſet my Neſt above the Stars.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>My r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>of receives me not, 'tis ayr I tread,</l>
               <l>At every ſtep I feel my advanc'd head</l>
               <l>Knock out a Star in Heaven, —<hi>ſaid</hi> Sejanus.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Attilas</hi> King of <hi>Hunnes</hi> arrogantly vaunted that the Stars fell before him, that the Earth trembled at his preſence: <hi>Caligula</hi> by certain Engines thundred and lightned as another <hi>Jupiter, I will aſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> above the height of the clouds, I will be like the Moſt High,</hi> ſaid the King of <hi>Babel: Cyrus</hi> cauſed this to be writ over his Sepulchre, <hi>I could do all things.</hi> But why then did he not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve himſelf from death?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zerxes</hi> was angry with the Mountains, Winds, Rivers, the Elements, if any of them croſt him, as if they were men under his pay: At <hi>Helleſpont</hi> he cauſed two millions of men to be w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>d over into <hi>Greece,</hi> where a ſuddain Tempeſt battering and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ating his Boat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, he cauſed the Sea to be ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nck with three hundred ſtripes, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt a pair of ſetters into it, to make it know to whom it was ſubject. I have heard of a ſtory of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> King, or rather a King of <hi>England,</hi> of very late dayes, (a great Hunter, that was his worthy Character) who being at <hi>Newmarket</hi> for his pleaſure ſake, &amp; hindered in his ſport by a long
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115440:9"/>
rain for many days together, with very little or no fair weather, began at laſt to be ſo really fretted thereat, that he was heard to ſay, That no King in the world was ſo little beholding to God Almighty as he, in that he ſhould wait a whole month together for a day of fair weather for his recreation, and could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it, or words to the like wicked purpoſe, that one day fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fair, great joy was at Court, all his Troop of Courtiers mounting upon their hunting Horſes, and he with them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about their game, the clouds frowned upon them, and at laſt a very great ſoaking ſhower of rain fell, at which the ſaid K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a mad fretting and frenzy fit, cryed out with curſing and ſweating, that the world ſhould be drowned, and therefore in a ſcorn rode up upon the brow of a Knap upon <hi>New-market</hi> Heath (if my memory fail me not in my information) where he ſaid, Give me a Bible, I'le prove the world muſt be drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, crying out again and again, Why do you not give me a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? at laſt a Bible was brought him, when he had it in his hands, he opened it, and turned and toſſed it, at laſt making a ſcornful mouth, he threw it over his left ſhoulder in deriſion, and ſo rod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> away.</p>
            <p>As for Promiſes, Vows, and Covenants, theſe are nothing with a Tyrant, he oftentimes promiſeth in the word of a King, and thinks his heart unſworn, his ſolemn Oaths, Vows, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, Proteſtations, Imprecations, and Execrations, he ſlips as eaſily as Monkies do their Collers, making election of thoſe only that ſerve his turn, and reprobates the reſt; So a Tyrants <hi>Maxim</hi> is out of <hi>Lucian,</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sceptrorum vis tota perit, ſi poedere juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> incipit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Scepters are vain that do on juſtice ſtand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>That <hi>Principi nihil eſt injuſtum quod fructuoſum,</hi> a Prince ought to account nothing unjuſt which is profitable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it is lawful <hi>Regni cauſâ ſceleratum eſſe,</hi> to do any wicked thing to procure abſolute Soveraignty. Again, that <hi>Regni cauſa jus violendum eſſe,</hi> That all Laws may be violated to make way for Domination; That <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi honeſta tantum dominanti lic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, praecario r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnatur,</hi> where it is warrantable for the Prince to do nothing but right and juſt things, he rules but by curteſie. Who can forget thoſe manifold imprecations of the late King in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115440:10"/>
caſes together with his Promiſes, Vows, and Oaths, and his common breach of all, and the juſt Sentence of God from his own lips, ſo frequently <hi>upon him, and his,</hi> and the execution thereof in the ſight of the world.</p>
            <p>11. <hi>His Court is commonly the Center of wickedneſs,</hi> a <hi>Burrough of Beaſts, a Den of Theeves, his H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll a Hell, his Chamber of Preſence the very Synagogue of Satan, his Chair of State, the Throne of iniquity, where with his ranting r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, his curſing Courtiers, his cunning flatterers, his fine fools, his gaudy Grandees, he ſatiates himſelf in his filthy deſires, and where looſneſs and licentiouſneſs, glut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ony and drunkenneſs, chambering and wantonneſs, ſtrive and envyings, blaſphemies and beaſtlineſs, profuſneſs, prophaneneſs, and all kind of wickedneſs do ran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and reign</hi> cum Privilegio Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio.</p>
            <p>Tyrants Courts are commonly the very Sourſe of ſin, the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, the ſpring of the wickedneſs of the Nation, from whence flows ſuch bitter waters, as infect the whole Countrey, like Prince, like Prieſt, like Prophet, like people, like Court, like Countrey; the Chambers of Tyrants, what are they but the very Chappels of <hi>Venus?</hi> where their Beds, Pallets, Couches, are the very Altars whereon thoſe abominable ſacrifices of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs are ſo abundantly offered; their Kitchins, Pantries, Cell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, Butteries, are ſtuft and fill'd with the ſacrifices of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> where men break their brains, as ſwine do their bellies with quaffing: It was ſaid of <hi>Bonoſus,</hi> the drunk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Emperour, that he was born <hi>non ut vivat, ſed ut bibat,</hi> not to live, but to drink: and being overcome by <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bus,</hi> he hanged himſelf, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom it was j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſted, that a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d hung there, and not a man. <hi>Darius</hi> King of <hi>Perſia</hi> commanded this inſcription to be ſet over his Sepulchre: <hi>I was able to hunt luſtily, to drink wine ſoundly, to bear it out bravely. Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Wine as raging,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly joyneth drunkards and railers together, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6 9. being both commonly found in one perſon. And are not the Courts of Tyrants commonly filled wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h ſuch roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing boyes as theſe? whoſe heads and hearts are overcharged
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115440:10"/>
with ſurfeiting and drunkenneſs, what Governours are theſe like to make, who are ſo ungoverned? theſe jolly companions are (like locuſts) all belly, where they bury their wits, their reaſon, their underſtanding; Nay, their throats are open Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres, where their whole families are buried alive, digging their grave with their teeth; Hence it is, that ſo many Courtiers of the late K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, having their hundreds and thouſands by their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and preferments, whoſe glittering garbs in former days ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them like blazing Stars in the ſtreets, drawing all eyes after them, are now creeping up and down with thin cheeks, and ragged raiments, and their poor families pining in penury, being buried before they were born, (I mean) through their Parents pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſeneſs, neglecting to make due proviſion for their poſterity: much meat, much malady: a glutton ſhall not want wo, luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is attended with beggery: the Apoſtle joyns gluttony and drunkenneſs, chambering and wantonneſs, as birds of a feather in one neſt, or perſon; And where do theſe Ravens build ſo much, as in Kings Palaces, <hi>Eſt Venus in vinis,</hi> Whoredom is commonly uſhered in with drunkenneſs, hence it is that the Whore hath a Cup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n her hand, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. 4. When <hi>Lot</hi> was drunk, he quickly ſtaggered, reeled, ſtumbled, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll into the Whores di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch; where he ſo beſoild himſelf, that his name will never be clean again. What <hi>proviſion</hi> (or catering) <hi>for the fleſh,</hi> (as the word is <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 13.) <hi>to fulfill the luſts thereof,</hi> is to be found in the Courts of Tyrants? I have heard of a great Duke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the late Kings days, whoſe mornings drink, <hi>de die in di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> was ſo tempered, and conditioned, that a Gentleman of <hi>London</hi> upon a certain morning v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſiting the ſaid Dukes Steward (being of his acquaintaince) the ſaid Steward paſſed by with a cup in his hand, his friend asked him what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e had there in the cup: the Steward replyed I have my Lords mornings draft: th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed he might taſte it, which accordingly he did, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a little ſup of it, the operation whereof was ſo, that he profeſt he had much to do to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orbear incivilities upon every wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that he met, being ſo ſtrangely and unexpectedly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come therewith, that he lockt himſelf up within d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors all that day, fearing leaſt he ſhould be overcome with fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y. A b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with wine, or int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing drinks, ſoam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut fil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hineſs,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115440:11"/>
ſaid a Father: Wine is the milk of <hi>Venus,</hi> ſaid another, by which a man being once overcome he is become a child, one without ſtrength, a fool and no man, <hi>quia non ratione ſed affectu rapitur,</hi> becauſe he is not rul'd by reaſon, but affection, led about by the noſe even of women: <hi>Thou ſhalt be as one of the fools in Iſrael,</hi> ſaid <hi>Tamar</hi> fitly to her libidinous brother <hi>Amnon, 2 Sam.</hi> 13. 13. What woful waſte hath this ſin made of the eſtates, perſons, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, bodies and ſouls of many of our late Courtiers?</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Corpus, opes, animam, famam, vim, lumina ſcortum</l>
               <l>Debilitat, perdit, necat; aufert, eripit orbat.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Take the meaning hereof from the mouth of <hi>Solomon, Prov. 6. 26. By means of a whoriſh woman a man is brought to a piece of bread, and the adultereſs will hunt for the precious life.</hi> The Prod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gal ſoon waſted his eſtate when he fell among harlots: The whoriſh woman, like the horſeleech daughter, hath no other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage but Give, give: <hi>What pledg ſhall I give,</hi> ſaid <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem, Gen. 31. 12. Thy ſignet, thy bracelets, Gen. 37. 18. Ask what thou wilt, thou ſhalt have it,</hi> ſaid <hi>Herod</hi> to hit M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nion. This ſin <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth Kings,</hi> ſaid <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 31. 3. It layd waſte the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience even of <hi>David</hi> himſelf: The eyes of Courtiers (like <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi>) how oft were they gazing after <hi>Bathſheba</hi>'s, looking to luſt? <hi>Job</hi> would not look, that he might not think upon a maid: When the <hi>eyes are full of adultery they cannot ceaſe to ſin,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter, 2 Pet. 2. 14. Sampſons</hi> eyes firſt betrayd him to luſt, and therefore they were firſt pul'd out, and he led away captive unto <hi>Gaza</hi> for gazing upon his <hi>Dalilah:</hi> By theſe loop-holes of luſt and windows of wickedneſs (I mean the eyes) the Devil getteth into the very heart. One wittily upbraided a certain wanton, that he had not pupils, but punks in his eyes. A Philoſopher obſerving one to have wanton eyes, ſaid to him, that the difference was not much whether he committed wickedneſs with his upper or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts. Were not our late mincing Minions called Ladies of the Court (I ſpeak not of them all) ordinarily attired on purpoſe to catch the eyes of their male companions, in ſo much as that it was hard to ſay, whether the greateſt part of their bodies were clothed or naked? as if they made ſhambles of their ſhoulders, and merchandiſe of their fleſh. I have heard of a Biſhop invited to one of their houſes to dinner, and obſerving the Ladies naked
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115440:11"/>
back and breſts, ſaid to her to this purpoſe, Madam, it is time to ſhut up your ſhop-windows; upon which ſhe preſently caſt a vail upon her neck and ſhoulders, and never was obſerved to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo afterwards: <hi>Luſt not after her beauty, neither let her take thee with her eye-lids, Prov.</hi> 6. 25. ſome render it, <hi>neque te capiat ſplendoribus ſuis,</hi> let not her glitterings gain thee, leſt ſhe ruines thee; <hi>Flagitium &amp; flagellum ſicut acus &amp; filum:</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery ſucceeds iniquity, as the thred the needle; they are linked together with chains of Adamant. We need not mention the licentiouſneſs and luſts of the perſons and Courts of <hi>Auguſtus, Julius, Tiberius, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ogabalus, Caligula, Commodus, Domician, Proculus,</hi> and others of the Roman Emperors, who as they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in pomp, ſtate and greatneſs, ſo this ſin of wantonneſs and laſciviouſneſs did reign amongſt them; for almoſt all Princes or Courts of Princes in Chriſtendom have been obſerved to indulge, if not even to court that waſting wickedneſs. I have heard of a Kings Court not far off, where it was ſaid to be held a kind of a piece of gallantry, and a thing in faſhion, for the Noble men (falſly ſo called) to know no difference between their own and their fellow-Courtiers Ladies, and the Ladies the like in reſpect of other men, and no great matter of offence to the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band or wife that it ſhould be known, becauſe it was then the faſhion; and that it too much favored of Puritaniſm to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>find within the bounds of Matrimony. May we not well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Engliſh Court Ladies paintings, their pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chings, their criſpings, their curlings, their caps and feathers, the cocking of their beavors, their ſtilletto's, their man-like apparel, their ſlaſht ſleeves, their jetting, their ſtrutting, their leg making, with the reſt of their antique apparel and poſtures? O how many families bodies and ſouls have periſhed by them? how did they rejoyce to do evil? it was their meat, drink and ſport, to be merry with the Devil: Thoſe light Aſſes are ſaid by <hi>Solomon</hi> to flatter with their lips; their lips were nets, their hands bands, their words were coards to draw men as calves to the ſlaughter; <hi>Her houſe inclineth to death, Prov. 2. 18. Terence</hi> calleth harlots, <hi>Cruces; quia invenes macerant &amp; affligant.</hi> It was ſaid of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth as a by-word, <hi>Eum per eandem partem animam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fudiſſe, per quam acceperat.</hi> Pope <hi>John</hi> the twelfth being taken
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115440:12"/>
with an Adultereſs, was ſtab'd to death by her husband. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Great, and <hi>Otho</hi> the third, loſt their lives by their luſts: <hi>Her paths are unto the dead, viz.</hi> where thoſe hell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites are giving themſelves over to fornication, and going after ſtrange fleſh, ſhall <hi>ſuffer the vengeance of eternal fire:</hi> The harlot is a deep ditch, a narrow pit, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 27. and <hi>whoredom and wine and new wine taketh away the heart, Hoſea</hi> 4. 11. that is, bereave a man of his noble principles of wiſdom, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, underſtanding: Hence Adulterers are ſaid to be voyd of underſtanding, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. 32. a wound and diſhonor he gets; he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>abs his name, his family, his conſcience, his body, his ſoul; that ſin renders men paſt feeling, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 28. of a dead and dedolent diſpoſition, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 18. 19. yea impudent and impenitent: Hence it is, that neither the ſtrange woman, nor he that goeth unto her, return again, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2. 19. that is very rarely, if ever. Are not theſe the very characters of many of our late wanton Courtiers, men and women of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>baucht conſciences and converſations, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, impenitent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aring, mocking and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ffing at all means of recovery, waſting their precious times in Plays, Paſtimes, Masks, and ſuch fool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ies, ſpending their wits and parts in Complements and Courtſhips, riſing up in the morning wreaking from their beds of luſts, no ſooner up but their luſtful drinks are tempered for them, then to their powdering, trimming and tiring, then to their devotion to their bellies, I mean their gluttonous dinners; then to Black-fryers, or other places, to ſee Plays, to offer up their evening ſacrifices to the Devil; then to their junkets and jollities, and then again to their beds of luſts, and thus they wheel'd about their time <hi>de die in diem:</hi> Theſe wretched female wantons, what were they but, as one wittily ſaid of the Italian women <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies at their doors, Goats in their gardens, Devils in their houſes, Angels in the ſtreets, and Syrens in their windows,</hi> where they ſit in <hi>their whoriſh attire,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> hath it, <hi>with their ſubtil heart,</hi> or as ſome render it, truſſed up about the breſts with their upper parts naked, <hi>Prov. 7. 10. Erat nudo collo, &amp; pectore, corde tenus, &amp;c.</hi> with their bare necks and breſts; <hi>Nudato pudendo ut ad concubitum homines accenderat,</hi> which I forbear to eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh; by means whereof how many men have been be witched? making them become voyd of underſtanding, even as brutes;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115440:12"/>
               <hi>Nos animas etiam incarnavimus</hi> (ſaid one,) as if their very ſouls, reaſon and conſciences were even turned into a lump of fleſh; though theſe ſeem pleaſant a while, yet the end thereof is death: Luſt blears the underſtanding, making men beleeve there is ſweet ſence in ſinning but is it any other then as a man faſt aſleep, and in a ſweet and pleaſant dream on the top of a ſteep Rock or Clift, who ſtarting ſuddenly for joy falls down and daſheth himſelf in pieces by his unexpected fall? Theſe men and women will come at laſt (as ſome of them doubtleſs have upon their death-beds) to ſee and ſay, that not only this is vanity, but vexation of ſpirit: When this ſin hath brought home its reward, a diſeaſed body, a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rplexed conſcience, a diſtreſſed ſoul, then the guilty perſon cries out too late, filling the ayr with doleful cries: as one ſaid, <hi>Totum vitae meae tempus perdidi quia perdite vixi,</hi> How have I loſt the chief of my time, the flower of mine age, the ſtrength of my body, the marrow of my bones, the vigor of my ſpirits, the whole of my eſtate, and eternal life for a few ſinful pleaſures and ſenſual delights? It is ſaid of the Mole, how true I know not, that he begins to ſee when he is about to dye, and not before; <hi>Oculos incipit ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rire moriendo, quos clauſos habuit vivendo:</hi> Thoſe mole-ey'd Minions may ſee too late their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition; their pleaſure will be gone, their pain laſteth.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Principium dulce eſt; ſed finis amoris amarus,</l>
               <l>Laeta venire Venus, triſt is abire ſolet.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The pleaſures of ſin are but for a moment, like the crackling of thorns under a pot, much noiſe, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttle fire, much light, little heat, a blaze ſoon blaſted, before the pots can feel the thorns: They, and their p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſure are ſna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cht away together; their Sun goes down at noon day. Mettals in the fire are moſt glaring when neareſt melting: The fiſhes ſwim merrily down the ſtreams of <hi>Jordan,</hi> but fall ſuddenly into the dead Sea, where preſently they dye, and know <hi>Jordan</hi> no more. What's become of thoſe gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Grandees, roaring Roiſters, with their glittering Gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls and mad Mates, the wanton Wag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ails of our Engliſh Courts, who fleared when they ſhould have feared, and laughed when they ſhould have lamented? <hi>how ſoon are they put out as the fire of thorns? Pſal.</hi> 118. 12. Did not our Engliſh Courts ſwarm with theſe luſtful Locuſts almoſt in all Ages, and the chiefeſt therein
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115440:13"/>
commonly chief in theſe ſins? <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth had his holy Whore (as he was uſed to call her) that came out of a Nunnery at his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck to ſatisfie his luſt. May not large volumes be fil'd with the hiſtorical Narrations, and that according to truth, of the pride, gluttony, drunkenneſs, wantonneſs, luxury, laſciviouſneſs of the Kings and Courts of this Nation in their conſtant ſucceſſion one after another, until the hand of Vengeance did put a full ſtop hereunto by that fatal Blow at <hi>White-hall</hi> Gate, 1648. They are extinct, dead, and buried; and I wiſh ſuch an immoveable ſtone may be layd upon the mouth of their Sepulchres by our preſent and ſucceſſive Governors, that they may never riſe again, that as their names, ſo their ſin may rot and conſume away; and the eyes of this Engliſh Nation may never behold ſuch vanity at Court any more, where laſciviouſneſs and luxury were accounted meer peccadilloes, not worthy repentance or remorſe.</p>
            <p>12. <hi>He commonly wades through blood to his bloody Throne, and having once ſcared his conſcience by ſpilling the blood of a Father or Brother to attain the Crown, he can eat the fleſh, and drink the blood of millions of his people to ſatisfie his luſts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reluctance, and judgeth it his right to wrong whom he will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tyrants are men of blood, fierce, fiery, furious ſpirits, croſs, curſt and cruel diſpoſitions; the world is fill'd with volumes of their vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lanies in this kind; all Ages and Countries without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception have wofully felt the truth hereof; in ſo much as if men had the uſe of their mental ears, as they have of their corporal, the cries of the thouſands and ten thouſands, millions and tens of millions of the ſlain and murthered by the hands of Tyrants would be ſo great, that they would hardly hear the living for the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d. The Turkiſh, Spaniſh, Roman, French, Scottiſh, Engliſh Hiſtories, are they not ſtufft and cram'd with innumerable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the cruelty of Tyrants, and their pleaſure therein? No ſight pleaſed <hi>Hannibal</hi> better then a ditch running over with mans blood. <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rls</hi> the nineth of <hi>France,</hi> Author of that bloody M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cre in <hi>France,</hi> looking upon the dead carkaſs of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral that ſtank by long keeping unburied, uttered this wretched ſaying, <hi>Quam ſuaviter olet cadaver inimici?</hi> How ſweet is the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115440:13"/>
ſmell of an enemies carkaſs? And the Queen Mother of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> beholding the dead bodies of her Proteſtant Subjects whom ſhe had ſlain in Battel, ſaid, that ſhe never ſaw a finer piece of Tapiſtry in all her life. To ſpend time on this were to waſte a candle before the Sun: <hi>Englands</hi> Chronicles, the Books of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, the late bloody Maſſacres and Wars in <hi>Ireland, England, Scotland,</hi> are freſh and bleeding evidences of the bloodineſs of Tyrants. I ſhall not here ſpeak of the death of Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> the bloody Maſſacres of the Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by whoſe Commiſſions and Commands how cruelly and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully they have been carried on: God hath made inquiſition for blood, he hath remembered and not forgotten the complaint of the poor; he hath cut off <hi>Saul</hi> and his bloody houſe according to his word, <hi>Pſal. 55. 23. Bloody and deceitful men ſhall not live out half their days:</hi> They are cut off before their time; their branches ſhall not be green, but ſhaken off as the unripe Grape from the Vine, and caſt off as the flower of the Olive, <hi>Job</hi> 15. 32, 33.</p>
            <p>13. <hi>Prerogative Pleaders are his Orthodox Preachers, that make his mouth their Oracle, his Dictates their Doctrines, all Scriptural Precepts of the Subjects duties the only Canonical, but the duty of Princes Apocryphal writings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tyrants have their Chaplains according to their Religions, who rather preach from their Maſters mouths then to their ears, and principle the people according to their humors to maintain their Prerogative: Hence we ſhall find in Scripture, that wicked Kings had their Prieſts and Prophets of their own tempers, who did always charm the people into baſe ſlavery by their baſe preachings: <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3. 3. When the Princes in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were rearing Lions, and her Judges evening Wolves, <hi>her Prophets were treacherous,</hi> betraying the poor people by their cheating charmings into a ſtupid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ordid and ſilly ſubjection. Wicked Kings, Princes, Prieſts and Prophets are chain'd together, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. 26. they commonly keep one Court and one Councel; and as they live together in ſin, ſo periſh together commonly in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4 9. You may ſee how theſe wicked Prieſts and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115440:14"/>
did cling together againſt <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> who proteſted againſt their flatteries and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alſities, <hi>Jer.</hi> 26. 7, 8, 10, 11. See again their curſed Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ederacy in doing evil in the ſight of the Lord, <hi>Jer. 32. 32. Ahab</hi> had a mind to make War againſt <hi>Ramath Gilead,</hi> for the enlargement of his Territories; he had no ſooner ſignified his royal pleaſure herein, but his whole Kingdom of Prieſts and Prophets allarms the people to War, and promiſe them ſucceſs in the Name of the Lord; yea one of them, <hi>viz. Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dekiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Chenaanah,</hi> like an Ape, did imitate the cuſtom of the Prophets of the Lord, and makes himſelf Iron horns, carries them unto the King, as if ſent by a very ſpecial Commiſſion, and tells him, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, With theſe horns ſhalt thou puſh the Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, until thou haſt conſum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d them;</hi> but you know they all told lyes in the Name of the Lord: and one <hi>Michaiah,</hi> that ſpake the truth, they buffeted and impriſoned: And was it not thus in <hi>Englands</hi> Courts during the Rule of Tyrants amongſt us? No ſooner had the late King a reſolution to war with the <hi>Scots,</hi> his native Countrymen, but all the Pulpits from <hi>White-hall</hi> round the Nation did allarm the people to riſe up with him, promiſing them ſucceſs in the Name of the Lord. Were not thoſe wicked Kings, Prieſts and Prophets of the Engliſh Nation link'd together as with chains of Adamant, in ſo much that if the one be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, the other muſt fall: hence grew that ominous Proverb, <hi>No Biſhop no King,</hi> which fell out accordingly: How hath God deſtroyed thoſe dens of Lions, thoſe Magpyes neſts, thoſe black Ravens that deceived the people with their rough garments? I am no adverſary to the lawful Miniſtry; and let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth, and my pen drop from my wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered right hand, rather then I ſhould willingly ſpeak or write againſt the Lords true Meſſengers; but meer pretenders of the Lords meſſage, when they utter only viſions of their own hearts, are the abomination of my Soul.</p>
            <p>14. <hi>The greatneſs of his height cauſeth giddineſs in his head, and at laſt his fall; Though his neſts be among<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſtars, the hand of Juſtice will reach him; and though he dwells in the clifts of the Rocks, yet thence will it fetch him out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115440:14"/>Pride is unſatisfied with preferment: ambitious Tyrants are ſtill riſing up above the top of their places, where they loſe their footing, and periſh by falling. Pride maketh a man drunk with his own conceits, uſhereth in his own deſtruction, his Sails be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greater then his Ship, his heart then his head, his projects then his pate, he is frequently overſet, and at laſt, himſelf his houſe, his fam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly are overwhelm'd in miſery: <hi>Pharaoh, Adoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezeck, Agag, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>buchadnezzer, Haman, Herod,</hi> with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others, are experimental inſtances, and woful witneſſes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Zerxes</hi> having covered the Seas with his Ships, was (by a juſt hand of God for his prodigious pride) forced to fly from <hi>Grecia</hi> in a poor fiſher-boat, where (had not the <hi>Perſians</hi> that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re with him caſt themſelves into the Sea, to ſave the life of their King) he had been devoured in the waves that regarded not his greatneſs. The ſame S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nators that accompanied proud <hi>Sejanus</hi> to the Senate, conducted him the ſame day to priſor; they that were ready to kneel down to him as their God, did ere long drag him with contempt to the Goal. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>giſmund</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> beholding the greatneſs of his Army, hearing of the <hi>Turks</hi> advance, ſcornfully ſaid to this purpoſe, We need not fear the <hi>Turks,</hi> nor the falling of the Heavens upon us, for we are able with our ſpears and halberts, to held them up, if they ſhould fall; who afterwards was ſhamefully beaten, and glad to fly away in a ſmall boat to ſave his life. <hi>Bajaret</hi> the terrour of the world, how powerful was his pride, how dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful his downf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, when coapt in a cage, carried up and down therein a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Monſter of men to be ſeen of men, daſht out his own brains againſt the grates thereof. <hi>Pompe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Ceſar</hi> ſtrive for preheminence, and what ever was the pretended, yet the reall cauſe was, that the one could not endure a Superiour, nor the other an Equal. Catholick Monarchy is the white in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that Tyrants aim at: <hi>Non ſufficit Orbis,</hi> is the Tyrants Motto; See their language, <hi>Geneſis 11. 4. Let us build us a Tower, whoſe top may reach to the Heavens, and let us make us a Name.</hi> See the pride and the plague, the Majeſty and the miſery, the glory and grave of every Tyrant, elegantly ſet out by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> in his <hi>Chap. 14. 11. Thy pomp is brought down to the grave, and the noiſe of thy viols, the worm is ſpread under</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115440:15"/>
               <hi>thee, and the worms cover thee; how art thou fallen from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, O Lucifer, Son of the Morning? how art thou cut down to the ground which did weaken the Nations? For thou haſt ſaid in thy heart, I will aſcend into Heaven, I will exalt my Throne above the Stars of God, I will aſcend above the heights of the clouds, I will be like the Moſt High, yet thou ſhalt be brought down to hell, &amp;c.</hi> Their Exaltation often proves (like <hi>Hamans</hi>) the heightening of their Gallows, or Gibbet: as once a <hi>Daniſh</hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntate in this Nation, K. <hi>Knute,</hi> cauſed the head of a falſe perſon to be ſtruck off, and ſet upon the higheſt part of the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> therein performing his promiſe to a Traytor in advancing him above any Lord in the Land. What got moſt of the <hi>Ceſars</hi> by their tyranny? pride, glory, and haſty preferment: <hi>Niſi ut citius interficerentur,</hi> to be kill'd the ſooner. What do they ordinarily but purſue their own deſtiny? As the <hi>Panther</hi> having a violent deſire after the poyſonful <hi>Achonite,</hi> (which men hang up above his reach) who leaps and skips and mounts to catch it, but cannot come at it, and at laſt he wearies himſelf, breaks, and kills himſelf, and ſo is taken. <hi>Aliena appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo propria amiſit,</hi> was the inſcription written in a Cup made of the Duke of <hi>Muſcoviah's</hi> skul, taken by the <hi>Tartarian</hi> in battel, <hi>All covet, all loſe:</hi> the whole hiſtory of the late King is <hi>approbatum eſt,</hi> of this truth.</p>
            <p>15. <hi>To bring him to puniſhment is Gods will, and mans work; With God is no reſpect of perſons, and in executing of juſtice the Prince and the Peaſant muſt fare alike.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Tyrant betraying his truſt, breaking his faith, deſtroying the end of his Power, Government, and Greatneſs, regarding nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Law, nor common good, reigns only for himſelf, and his faction, and becauſe his power is great, his will boundleſs, and exorbitant, committing wrongs, oppreſſions, murther, maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacres, rap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, adulteries, deſolation and ſubverſion of his good people, is to be ſeized upon, ſecured, and executed, as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enimy of his Countrey or People. It was the ſaying of an <hi>Heathen</hi> Poet,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>—<hi>Victima haud ulla amplior</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115440:15"/>
                  <hi>poteſt magiſque opima mactari Jovi,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>quam Rex iniquus</hi>—</l>
               <l>—There is no Sacrifice</l>
               <l>ſo rich, ſo fat, ſo pleaſing unto God,</l>
               <l>as Tyrant ſlain.—</l>
            </lg>
            <p>To inſiſt much upon this point, were but <hi>actum agere,</hi> ſo much having been lately written from able and learned pens up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion of the execution of the late King: <hi>Beuchanon</hi> hath ſeveral hiſtories and inſtances of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Proceedings againſt their wicked Governours, in the year 1559. The <hi>Scotch</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants claiming promiſe of their Queen Regent for liberty of conſcience, ſhe replyed like a Tyrant, That promiſes were not to be claimed of Princes beyond what was profitable; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they told her to her face in Parliament, that then they did renounce their Allegiance, and ſo betook themſelves to Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. The holy Scriptures are clear for it, <hi>Numb. 35. 32. No ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction ſhall be taken for the life of the murtherer,</hi> be he what he will be, high or low, rich or poor, King or Begger, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture makes no diſtinction; if a murtherer, he muſt die for it: <hi>He which is guilty of death, ſhall ſurely be put to death.</hi> If God maketh no difference, who is that man that pretends himſelf a Miniſter of God, an Embaſſadour of Jeſus Chriſt that dares ſo much prevaricate from his meſſage, as to ſay, That Kings and Princes muſt be diſpenſed withall, and not called to an account, though they ſhould ſhed the blood of their innocent people, ſo directly contrary to the very Letter of the Scripture. <hi>Nero</hi> was condemned to death by the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate, <hi>Tarquinius ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> depoſed by the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily put their Princes to death for breaking their truſts, and offending the Laws of the Commonwealth: <hi>Eugenius</hi> the eighth, being the 62 King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> was put to death for his miſgovernment: <hi>Cum nec amicorum, nec Sacerdotum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitionibus quicquam moveretur, poſt tertium r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gni ſui an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num in Coetu procerum omnibus in ejus exitium conſentientibus periit, ſocii ſcelerum &amp; flagitiorum in crucem acti, &amp; ipſi gratum populo ſpectaculum prebuere.</hi> When no admonitions of friends, Miniſters, would ſerve turn for to reclaim him, they conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and agreed together to cut him off by the hand of juſtice in a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115440:16"/>
publick manner, and himſelf, and accomplices, were rendred ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſpectacles of juſtice unto the people. When <hi>Rehoboam</hi> ſhall tread in the ſteps of his fathers unjuſt exactions, and upon the complaint and petition of his people for their juſt rights and priviledges, he ſhall refuſe to hear them, to eaſe them, but tells them, <hi>I will add to my Fathers yoke, he chaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſed you with whips, but I will chaſtiſe you with Scorpions:</hi> Ten parts of 12. of his people caſt him off, made war againſt him. What, ſaid they, if this be the caſe, that we muſt be whipt and ſlaſht by this proud Tyrant, and at his will, and the will of his curſed Courtiers, and his green-headed Grandees; Away with him, <hi>what portion have we</hi> in this Tyrant? <hi>To your tents, O Iſrael,</hi> Arm, arm, let him now look to himſelf, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. from the firſt to the twenty one <hi>ver.</hi> his grave Councellors told him plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Verſ. 7. If thou wilt be a Servant unto this people, and ſerve them, and ſpeak good words to them,</hi> treat them kindly; <hi>they will be thy ſervants for ever.</hi> Where you may ſee (<hi>i.</hi>) that the King was made ſo to be <hi>their Servant,</hi> and not to Lord it over them. And ſecondly, That when Kings are <hi>Servants to the people,</hi> the people are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ready and free, and willing <hi>ſervants,</hi> yea vaſſels <hi>unto them;</hi> Love will compel them: But when they perceive that <hi>they have no portion in him,</hi> he ſhall have as little in them: By how much the greater the perſon is that off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nds, by ſo much the greater is his fault, by ſo much the greater his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ought to be. And I believe that that late exemplary piece of juſtice at <hi>Whitehall.</hi> Gate upon the late Tyrant, was one of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atteſt, richeſt, and moſt acceptable Sacrifice that hath been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up unto the moſt righteous God that loveth righteouſneſs in this Nation before that day: And that the zeal of our Judges in executing petty thieves, robbers, and murtherers at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> was but as the tything of Mint and Cummin, in compariſon of that great thing of the Law then done.</p>
            <p>16. <hi>His light ſhall be put out, his ſparks ſhall not ſhine. Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors ſhall make him afraid on every ſide, &amp; his own Counſel ſhall caſt him down, his roots ſhall be dried up beneatlh, and above ſhall his branches be cut off: His remembrance ſhall periſh from the Earth: and he ſhall have no name in the Street.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115440:16"/>His triumph is but ſhort, and his joy but for a moment, though his Excellency mount up unto the Heavens, and his Head reaches unto the Clouds, yet ſhall he periſh for ever like his own dung, he ſhall flye away as a dream, and be chaſed as a viſion of the night; the eye which ſaw him ſhall ſee him no more, neither ſhall his place any more behold him. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, That a violent bloody<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Tyrant <hi>ſhall flee to the pit, let no man ſlay him: Prov.</hi> 28. 17. Let no man mediate for him, leſt he pay down as <hi>Ahab</hi> did, life for life, people for people. 1 <hi>King. 20. 42. When Tyrants periſh, the righteous increaſe, Prov.</hi> 28. 28. They ſwarm like B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es in a Sun-ſhine day. When the wicked riſe, good men skulk and hide their heads; as <hi>Moſes</hi> fled from <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh, David</hi> from <hi>Saul, Eliah</hi> from <hi>Ahab, Obadiah</hi>'s Clients from <hi>Jezabel, Jeremiah</hi> from <hi>Jehoiakim, Joſeph</hi> and the Child Jeſus from <hi>Herod,</hi> &amp;c. But wherein they dealproudly, God is above them, He ſeeth their day is coming, He ſits in Heaven and ſcorneth theſe ſcorners. The Moſt High cuts off the Spirit of Princes, he is terrible unto theſe tyrannical Kings of the Earth, thoſe ſcourges of the World. God ſo ſubdued <hi>Senache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib,</hi> as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> in memory of it did ſet up his Statue in the Temple of <hi>Vulcan,</hi> with this inſcription: <hi>Let all that behold me, learn to fear God.</hi> Tyrants ſhall be ſure ſooner or later to meet with their match; <hi>The blood-thirſty man ſhall not live out half his dayes.</hi> God will at laſt appear to their fearful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, to be glorious in holineſs, fearful in praiſes, doing wonders of wrath and ruine upon bloody <hi>Pharaohs,</hi> he will tear out thoſe bowels that are fill'd and ſtuft with the blood of the poor, and make inquiſition for their blood; then will he remember, and not forget the complaint of the poor, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hath fulfill'd his threatnings againſt Tyrants in our eyes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed our Nation from thoſe men of blood, that they may fall and fall in all the parts of the world and never riſe up again, eſpecially in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation. That God would melt all Crowns, and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Potentates of the Earth, into a Crown &amp; S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>epter for the Head, and hand of Jeſus Chriſt, putting all Pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities under his feet, making our Government peace, and Exactors Righteouſneſs, that violence be no more heard
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115440:17"/>
of in our Land, nor deſolation, nor deſtruction within ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Borders: Let all the people</p>
            <trailer>CRI IN HOPE,</trailer>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115440:17"/>
            <head>A Protector, OR <hi>Homo Homini Deus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>JUſt Government is Gods Ordinance for mans good; the form thereof, mans appointment with Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation; the end thereof, mans felicity and Gods glory: and, a juſt Governor is a Protector of both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Inſtitution of Government is of God, the Conſtitution of man, the Governors themſelves of both, <hi>viz.</hi> Gods permiſſion and mans election: <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST GOVERNMENT IS GODS ORDINANCE; The Powers that be are ordained of God, Rom.</hi> 13. 1. Mans ſin was the cauſe of his ſubjection to all mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, but Gods mercy did inſtitute the ſame to preſerve him from ruine by his own wickedneſs; had not man ſinned, there had been a prior<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty, but not a ſoveraignty: there had been a reverence in the child to the father as the inſtrument of his production, but no ſubjection, becauſe no juſticiating power had been ſtabliſhed, there being no need of it; the eternal Law written in every mans heart would have been every mans guide, had it not been for ſin; ſin uſhered in ſubjection as a curſe at the heels of it; <hi>Gen. 3. 16. Thy deſire ſhall be to thy huſband, he ſhall rule over thee;</hi> her diſobedience expos'd her to ſubjection by Gods Ordinance. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty and ſubjection are Gods appointment <hi>FOR MANS GOOD; He is the miniſter of God to thee for good, Rom.</hi> 134, Sociableneſs, or <hi>appetitus convivendi,</hi> is the impreſs of Nature:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115440:18"/>
and the reaſon thereof, mutual preſervation and accommodation, which cannot be without Government: Sin hath brought ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row upon the world; <hi>Sin entered into the world</hi> in the van of a black and bloody Regiment, ſorrows, pains, aches, hunger, thir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, ſhame, &amp;c. with <hi>death through ſin</hi> in the rear; Conſcience of guilt brings fear of death: hence one end of ſociety is preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and becauſe men need ſecurity from miſery and ruine by one another, therefore hath God appointed Government and Governors among themſelves for the good of all, the form of which Government is le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t by God to their own diſcretion, who hath only confin'd them within the limits of this general rule, His <hi>GLORY and THEIR FELICITY:</hi> Forms of Government are no more perpetual then perſons themſelves; Neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires Government, convenience forms: Were it not for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the line and pale of every mans property would quickly be trodden down; mens boundleſs appetites would be their purveyors, and their wants would be meaſured by their wills: Confuſion makes men deſire order, and convenience the forms thereof: No Government is the worſt Government; and where none rules, none will be ruled, but all quickly ruin'd: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy is the worſt Tyranny; Better it is to be under the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the great Turk then the rabble rout: The forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are mans ordinance, ſo called by the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 11, 14. No form being divine or natural in its riſe or root, we find in Scripture ſeveral forms allowed by God, <hi>viz.</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments by Patriarchs, Generals, Judges, High Prieſts, and Kings: in other Hiſtories we read of Governments by Popes, Monarchs abſolute and conditionate, by Dukes, Senators, Conſuls, Dictators, &amp;c. which argues no one form above another to be <hi>jure divino,</hi> but that every or any form lawful, if conducing to <hi>THE PEOPLES FELICITY AND GODS GLORY:</hi> The power of Government whereſoever ſetled is <hi>fiduciary,</hi> and not <hi>inconditionate;</hi> and whileſt their Truſtees draw all their lines into this Center, <hi>Gods glory in the peoples welfare,</hi> they may walk ſecurely upon the higheſt battlements of honour and dignity: but if their projects and practiſe be <hi>ſole ſoveraignty,</hi> puff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up with a vain opinion of puiſſance and grandure, though for a time they proceed and proſper, and ſay within themſelves,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115440:18"/>
               <hi>they ſhall ſee no ſorrow,</hi> yet they ſhall find at laſt their buildings to totter, and the conſequence tragical to themſelves and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: for when the peoples Pilot proves a Pirate, not ruling, but ruining them, the hands and hearts of God and men will be ſwift Avengers of ſuch perfidiouſneſs: <hi>The Peoples protection</hi> is the end of Government; and therefore a juſt Governor is <hi>the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Protector;</hi> and what is he? what doth he?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He really eſteemeth the Publique Safety the chief So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty; that he is more the peoples, then the people his; that he was made for them, not they for him; that the State at large is the abſolute chief, and the chief, ſo called, the States ſervant, which he judgeth his Crown, and not his Croſs; his glory, and not his ſhame; carnal policy is not his ſtudy, but his peoples peace, his care and prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His head is full of publique principles, and his heart full of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience thereof; he ſtudies the peoples right, and his own duty; he projects their protection, peace, and plenty, as the great ends of his Office; his deſign is not to multiply gold and ſilver, he deſires not the peoples coyn with their curſes; he well conſiders that though moneys be the ſinews of War, yet the peoples aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are the joynts of peace: he renders himſelf unto the people matter of praiſe unto God for him, not of prayers unto God againſt him; he ſtrives to be the peoples pleaſure, not their plague: All cannot chuſe but do well when thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uleſt well, ſaid the Senate to <hi>Severus</hi> the Emperor. Carnal policy, which ſome call King-craft, is not his ſtudy; that <hi>ſubtle trade,</hi> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly Kings and great perſons drive in the world: <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Calves were ſet up by this artifice, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. When he had gotten the Crown (from <hi>Rehoboam</hi>) over the ten Tribes, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted with himſelf how and which way he might faſten it upon his head, and he had his Polititians very nimble about h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe him herein; and forgetting how he got the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſulting with God for his eſtabliſhment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> way to eaſe the people from their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edious trav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115440:19"/>
to their annual Sacrifices, and ſets up two golden Calves, and ſo keeps the people at home to ſerve God in their deviſed (call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed doubtleſs) Divine Service. And the Text notes, that the thing that ſteard him in his project, was not his defection in judgement touching the true Worſhip of God at <hi>Jeruſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m:</hi> but <hi>verſe</hi> 26, 27. His heart did miſgive him, that if the people ſhould go up to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> (within <hi>Rehoboam's</hi> Territories) to offer ſacrifice, they would turn again to their old King, the Power, the Polices, the Pulpits of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> would reduce them to the old Houſe and Family of <hi>Rehoboam</hi> again, but this policy of his was his ruine at laſt, as appears in the ſtory. A good Prince takes heed of his own heart, and Councellers, and any undue way<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to eſtabliſh his greatneſs. A Chriſtian Prince well conſiders true piety hath the promiſe of Exaltation, ſo his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining it, will be his ejection, and therefore takes heed of warping againſt his judgement and conſcience, of offering vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to his honeſt and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons principles, through the advice of Polititians to ingratiate himſelf with the people; he knows that the heart of man is deceitful above all things, and therefore it concerns him to look unto it: When <hi>Saul</hi> was firſt called to be King, he did real<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, <note n="*" place="margin">Veraciter ſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſavit de honore regni.</note> the burd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of Government, the meanneſs of his birth, parentage, and breeding came upon his heart, his perſonal unmeet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unfitneſs for ſo great dignities and honours refl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted upon his mind: but after he had once king'd it, and enjoyed the Honours, Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors, Glory, Retinne, and Revenues of the Crown, he could not bear it, to think that the Crown ſhould now be alienated from his own Fam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly; he forgot his parentage, his pedegree, nothing but greatneſs and grandeur now in his eyes, and the Counſels God touching the tranſlation of the Kingdom unto another Family, he could not brook i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He was little in his own eyes at firſt, but big enough at laſt, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9. 21. compared with <hi>Chap. 15. ver.</hi> 17. As alſo 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 29. compared with 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 30, 31. Simplicity will preſerve, carnal policy pollutes, and deſtroys. <hi>Solomon</hi> gives excellent counſel in this caſe, <hi>Prov. 15. 24. The way of life is Above to the wiſe, that he may depart from Hell beneath.</hi> True wiſdom is from above, and it leads to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115440:19"/>
life, A Crown in the next world is a Crown indeed: this is but a Croſs to it. Chriſtian Policy makes a Chriſtian Prince to eſteem that low counſel only worth regarding that will make a man wiſe in the latter end, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19. 20. He thinks not here of an eſtabliſhment, he minds his mortality, and 'tis his wiſdom to be frequently (in meditation) at his own ſuneral, making every tombe his Teacher, every mounment, a Monitor, his bed, his grave, his ſheets, his winding-ſheets,</p>
            <q>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Somnus mortis, ſic lectus imago Sepulchri.</q>
            <p>He conſiders his time fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, his glaſs runs. <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> had his S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pulcher in his Garden to ſeaſon his delight: true wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom provides for ſuturity: This will make the Evening of a man's days, as the day-breaking to everlaſting Glory. It provides for him <hi>Malorum ademption<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m bonorum adeption<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</hi> Freedom from evil, fruition of good. I have read of the cuſtom of ſome Countrys, that in the Coronation of their Kings, amongſt other ceremonies, two grave ſtones were brought him by a Maſon, who did uſe theſe words to him,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elige ab his Saxis ex quo invictiſſime Caeſar</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>ipſe tibi tumulum me fabricare vel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Chuſe, mighty Sir, under which of theſe ſtones,</l>
               <l>your purpoſe is ere long to lay your bones.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>He remembers that this is not his reſt, but a reſt remaineth to the people of God. He that is wiſe will be wiſe for himſelf, that is, for his Eternal intereſt, and takes h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed of carnal craſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs in carnal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes; his zeal for God, his w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ys, his people, his countrey, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe will advance good Rulers, and theſe will preſerve him &amp; therefore he knows no councel, no cunning, no craft, that is c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to theſe. It was a moſt prophane ſaying of a wretched Cardinal, <hi>viz.</hi> That he would not part with his part in <hi>Paris,</hi> for <hi>Paradiſe:</hi> He mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s much of wiſe Councellers, but takes heed of cunning ones, he takes heed, leſt <hi>any about him ſpoil you</hi> by policy, as the Apoſtle cautioned the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> againſt ſpoyling through philoſophy, leſt he being led away by their errour, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all from their ſted<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſtneſs, ſimplicity, and integrity: carnal counc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s are not of Gods Counc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, they cannot underſtand his mind: <hi>Try the ſpirits,</hi> they will be ſoon found out.</p>
            <p>He takes he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d upon whom he confers honours, relations,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115440:20"/>
family, conſanguinity, meer policy, or outward reſpects, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teer him not, in preferring men to honour and truſt; he honours thoſe whom God honours: Gods command to <hi>Moſes</hi> in this caſe is to this purpoſe, <hi>Exod. 18. 21, 22. Thou ſhalt provide out of all the people able men, ſuch as fear God, men of truth, hating co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, and place ſuch over them to be Rulers of thouſands, Rulers of hundreds, Rulers of fifties, Rulers of tens, &amp;c.</hi> Men that are fit for places of Government ſhould be drain'd from the dregs, ſifted from the bran of the ordinary ſort of people: This was <hi>Davids</hi> and <hi>Solomons</hi> practiſe; ſuch Judges <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> promoted, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. 6, 7. It was obſerved of the late Lord <hi>Ireton,</hi> both in <hi>England</hi> and in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (the very mention of whom melts the ſpirits of thoſe that well knew him,) that he took notice of good men, and of thoſe eſpecially that were leaſt ſolicitous after preferment, and ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt fit for it, and them he advanced and preferred before they ever knew of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He dares not rule in the peoples ruine, nor advance himſelf in their downfall; his pattern in the Mount is the King of Righteouſneſs, who though Lord of all, was ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant unto all, and ſacrificed himſelf for them, not them for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His heart is ſet upon the peoples health, his thoughts upon their thriving; he rejoyceth, lamenteth, is pleas'd or pain'd, he lives and dyes with them. When <hi>Joſeph</hi> was exalted, he was <hi>in the place of God</hi> unto the people. <hi>to preſerve life, Gen.</hi> 50. 19. compared with Chap. 45. 5. He doth not burthen the people, but bears their burthens, as <hi>Moſes</hi> and the ſeventy Elders, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. 16. When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſell before their enemies, <hi>Ioſhua</hi> their Prince, their Saviour. was as ſenſible as if his blood did run out of their veins, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 7. 6, 7. he took not away his peoples in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, but did <hi>cauſe them to inherit, Deut.</hi> 31. 7. He ſpoils not his people, but <hi>ſaves them out of the hands of them that ſpoileth them, Iudg.</hi> 2. 16. as thoſe Judges did: He is their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer from oppreſſors, as <hi>Othniel</hi> was, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3. 9. and <hi>Ehud,</hi> verſ. 15. and <hi>Gideon, Iudg.</hi> 6. 14. He is Gods Love-token to the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115440:20"/>
people, as <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> and <hi>Chaleb,</hi> and <hi>Gideon,</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> &amp;c. Whereas Tyrants are given in wrath, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26. 17. He knows he is ſet upon a Hill, yea upon a Mountain, and cannot be hid. Heavenly bodies enlighten not their own orb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> only, but ſend forth their rays to them that are under them. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> being in the Mount, convers'd with God, and his face did ſhine among the common people: His life i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one ſaith, <hi>Coelum quoddam lucidiſſimis virtutum ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> exornatum,</hi> a very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſparkling with variety of virtues as with ſo many bright ſtars: The peoples eyes are upon him, and his example will be their patte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n: <hi>Mobile mutatur ſemper cum Principe vulgus;</hi> Like Prince like people: Common people are like a flock of Cranes, as the firſt fly all follow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Princes are the peoples Looking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs; the Court and the City and the Country will dreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves according to them: Men are more apt to be led by their eyes then their ears by pattern then precept: He conſiders Gods eyes are upon him, and ſo are the Devils; good men look upon him with joy, wicked men look upon him with fear; If he be a pious Prince, his tripping would be their tickling, his fall their feaſt: He conſiders his burthens are great, his cares are many, his buſineſs much, his agitations various, the ſolemn Oath of God is upon him; all theſe do argue that the requiſites for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are not ordinary nor few. He waits upon God, and looks up unto him for wiſdom and ſtrength. The Mariners eye is upon the ſtar, when his hand is on the ſtern; ſo is his: if he miſteers, the whole is in danger. <hi>Sauls</hi> ſlaughter of the Gibeoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, 2 <hi>Sam. 21. 1. Davids</hi> luſt, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 10. his pride, 2 <hi>Sam. 24. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> idolatry, 1 <hi>King. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 30, 31, 32. Iorams</hi> wickedneſs, 2 <hi>Chron. 21. 12 13. Achaz</hi> ſins, 2 <hi>Chron. 28. 19. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> rebellion, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20. 42. brought miſery to their people; theſe Pilots by their ill ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erage did ſplit their Veſſels, and many of their people periſhed thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He judgeth his Honors relative, and therefore obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; having once accepted the dignity of Government, he cheerfully ſubmits to the burthens thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:115440:21"/>He conſiders, That what he hath, (as Ruler) he hath it not from himſelf, and therefore not for himſelf; his honours are the fruit of his painful atchievements: which do not leſſen, but lengthen, not eaſe, but increaſe his burdens,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fructus honos on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ris, fructus honoris onus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Labours bring honours, honours labours bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>It was the ſaying of <hi>Luther,</hi> that <hi>Politici &amp; Eccleſiaſtici labores maximi ſunt,</hi> Magiſtrates and Miniſters have the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt burdens. Had we not buſineſſes and cares, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ears above any private perſon, we ſhould be equal to the gods, ſaid <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus.</hi> Good rulers bear the peoples <hi>incumbrances, burthens, and ſtrifes,</hi> Crowns have their car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s with good Princes, their croſſes, their ſcratches; the ſenſe whereof they feel more at their hearts, then their Crowns on their heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He rules by rule, and not by roat; the Word of God, the Laws of men conſonant therewith, are his rules of ruling, and not his own luſt, eſteeming it his greater glory ſo to be ruled, that he might ſerve the whole, then otherwiſe to rule to ſerve Himſelf; Prerogative, Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and baſe Flatterers, he hates in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He eſteems himſelf more obliged to God, then the people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath received more from God then they; he knows himſelf to be under the ſtrickeſt Laws, not over the meaneſt ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Under the Law were commanded by God to write the Copie of the Law of God in a Book, and the <hi>Jews</hi> ſay, that though the Kings Father left him a Book of the Law, yet was he to write a Book thereof with his own hands, which he was to carry with him whitherſoever he went, from <hi>Deut.</hi> 17, 18, 19. And according to this is Gods ſaying to <hi>Joſhuah, This Book of the Law ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, but thou ſhalt meditate therein day and night, Ioſh.</hi> 1. 8. A good Ruler <hi>ſerves the Lord with reverence, Pſal.</hi> 2. 11. He caſts himſelf before him to do him reverence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29. 1. And as for the Laws of men in their reſpective Territories, it was <hi>Platoes</hi> ſaying, That the Prince is not above Law, but the Law is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115440:21"/>
the Prince; the Magiſtrate ſhould be a ſpeaking Law, a living Law, as exemplary in obedience to the Law, as he is emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in rule over all the people under the Law. It is moſt true, that <hi>the Chief Magiſtrate may do only that which is juſt,</hi> and moſt falſe, that <hi>all is juſt that he doth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Saul</hi> was as much bound not to hurt <hi>David,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> not to touch the Lords Anointed. To rule over the people by meer coactive power is beaſtly, not manly. A manly Prince would rule over the wills of men by their conſent: A Lion, a Bear, a Wolf, rules over the weaker by meer power. A good ruler deſires power directive, not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive, voluntary, not violent, by counſel, not command, by conſent, not compulſion: he takes no pleaſure to rule in his Commonwealth, as the Lion in the Forreſt. A Protector truly ſo called, cannot think himſelf wiſer then all, nor above all, but to the making and executing of Laws, to the Government of himſelf and people, he will have the conſultation and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the wiſe amongſt them: it is Gods Charactar of a Tyrant, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 9, 10. To rule by meer power, to take the people under him, and make them his Horſes, his Aſſes, his Slaves, and Vaſſals, minding altogether his own might, not the peoples right: but God's Charactar of a Protector is of another nature, <hi>Deut. 17, 20. viz.</hi> he is ſuch an one whoſe <hi>heart is not lifted up above his brethren:</hi> he is a Fellow-Subject to the Laws, though the chief Executioner thereof; he takes no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage from the Letter of the Law to gratifie himſelf, and grieve his people, (as the late Tyrant) and his Predeceſſors; he well conſiders that common Juſtice, Peace, and Safety are the great Ends of Rule and Rulers, that Laws themſelves are no longer binding, but as relative to thoſe great ends, that Religion, Reaſon, Nature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Grace, all do promote the publick Good: That the intent of Law is nothing leſs then the Princes roially in the peoples ruine, that the ſoul of the Law is preferrable above the ſhel, the life above the letter. <hi>Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m facit ac is qui legem tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greditur qui ſaeva verborum praerogativa fraudulenter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ira juris ſententiam abutitur.</hi> He doth as bad as tranſgreſs the Law who fraudulently abuſeth the rigid prerogative of words, contrary to the true intentional Sentence of the Law. He hath a piercing eye over pretended friends and flatterers, he knows
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115440:22"/>
his houſe will be haunted with theſe, do what he can. <hi>Many will ſeek the Rulers favour,</hi> more then the favour of God, for there they hope to find themſelves, he takes heed whom he truſts, and bleſs himſelf from his <hi>pretended friends,</hi> and prays with <hi>David</hi> to be delivered from lying lips, and a deceitful tongue, who will ſpeak fair, congratulate his victories and happineſſe, it may be preſent him with offerings and gifts: But as one ſaid, <hi>Timeo Danaos &amp; dona ferentes.</hi> And ſaith another,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Munera magna quidem miſit, ſed miſit in hamo;</l>
               <l>Et piſcatorem piſcis amare poteſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <p>When their words are as ſmooth as oyl, there is war in their hearts: It is ſomething under his fifth rib which they aim at in their Courtſhips and Complements; though they bring milk and honey in their Lordly d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh, yet he takes heed of ſecurity and ſleep at ſuch a time; for they watch their opportunity to make uſe of their nail and hammer; they are like Cur-dogs that would ſuck out blood by licking, and in the end deſtroy without biting. A Squire being ſent out of <hi>Spain</hi> to poyſon Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> anoynted the pummel of her Saddel with poyſon in a ſecret manner, as if he had been doing ſomewhat elſe, crying out with a loud voice, <hi>God ſave the Queen.</hi> When <hi>Gifford, Hodgſon,</hi> and others, had ſet <hi>Savage</hi> on work to kill the ſaid Queen; They firſt ſet ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a book to perſwade the <hi>Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> to attempt nothing againſt her, <hi>Caveatur oſculum Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carioticum:</hi> The kiſſes of <hi>Judas</hi> are dangerous, he takes heed of poyſon in a golden Cup: <hi>Jeſuits</hi> at this day kiſſe and kill together familiarly <hi>officioſè occidunt,</hi> as one ſaid of falſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, <hi>Eſocietate Ieſu fuit qui Ieſum tradidit:</hi> His Familiar that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e bread with him at his table: When the kiſſe was nigh, the ſwords and ſtaves were not far off: he knows that men that are moſt gloſing are frequently cloſing with him for miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, <hi>Joab, Iudas, Abſolom, Ahitophel,</hi> are moſt dangerous in their kiſſes: there are kiſſing Cut-throats, who can be affable to their enemies, and diſguiſe their hatred in commendations, while they privily lay their ſnares, men Italienated that can ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute with mortal imbracements, and clapſe in thoſe arms which they hope to embrew in their deareſt blood, like unto <hi>Hacket</hi> hanged in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, who imbracing his honeſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115440:22"/>
Schoolmaſter, bit off his noſe, and did eat it down before his face: Of all perſons he makes not flatterers of his Councel. <hi>Auguſtus</hi> complained when <hi>Varus</hi> was dead, that now he had none left that would deal faithfully and plainly with him: he bewares of confidence in unfaithful men, who will prove like the Brooks of <hi>Temah, Job</hi> 6. 17. which ſwell'd in rain, and fail'd in droughts; they will be like <hi>Egypt</hi> to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> broken reeds, whereon if he leans, they will not only fail him, but pierce and deſtroy him: <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> was killed in the very Councel-Chamber by ſuch flattering Councellers, <hi>A pluribus amicis quam inimicis,</hi> by moſt of his pretended friends: The <hi>French</hi> Proverb, <hi>When the Spaniard comes to parl of a peace, then double bolt the door;</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> in former dayes would make no conditions with them, becauſe they well knew their <hi>Machiavilian</hi> Hereſie: <hi>Fides tamdiu ſervanda eſt quamdiu expediat.</hi> I ſhall ſay no more to this, but to pray that God would preſerve our faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Rulers from unfaithful men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Chriſtian Prince ſtudies Princely principles, not Machivilian policies, and well remembers that he is Gods Servant, though his Servants Lord, and that he is bound to keep them free.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He well knows that goodneſſe is the way to greatneſſe, and grace to glory, that righteouſneſs and peace through Gods Ordinance are linked together with chains of Adamant, that when his ways pleaſe the Lord, he need not fear his friends or foes, that the Throne is eſtabliſhed by righteouſneſſe, ruined by wrongs, that though wickedneſs may build his houſe for a time, yet a wo from God will deſtroy the foundation, <hi>Ier.</hi> 22. 13. That Heavens friendſhip is his greateſt ſecurity, that true piety is the beſt policy, to attain and maintain his power and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: The Saints juſt liberty is his ſtudy, and men of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting principles he cannot bear.</p>
            <p>Men that judg themſelves bound in conſcience to puniſh others that are not of their judgment and conſcience; men that are not very ambitious that others ſhould know as much as themſelves,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115440:23"/>
and yet very zealous to have them puniſhed, becauſe they know not as much as themſelves: iron-hearted men; like that Tyrant that would caſt the men of his diſpleaſure upon an Iron bed, and if any were longer then the bed, he would have them cut off by ſo much the ſhorter, and if any were ſhorter, he ſhould be ſtretcht out unto that length: Theſe perſons had rather that people ſhould diſſemble <hi>their</hi> opinions, then own their <hi>own.</hi> The men of my meaning are very diſcernable; they are ſuch as pretend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Embaſſadors for Chriſt, and that with great majeſty and authority impoſing upon all men in the name of the Lord, and yet in the face of all men neglecting, nay deſpiſing his great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of Loving the Brethren. It is known to God, and my conſcience, and all men that know me, know, that I am no adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the publique Miniſtry, but a cordial Aſſertor of their ſacred Office according to the utmoſt of my poor abilities againſt Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers; well conſidering that though they may differ amongſt themſelves in the explication of ſome of the terms of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy; as alſo, that though they work not Miracles as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did to confirm their doctrine, which two particulars are the greateſt pretended Arguments impleading their Function, yet they agree in the grand import of their Maſters meſſage, <hi>viz. the grace of God bringing Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt, and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to live godly, righteouſly and ſoberly in this preſent evil world;</hi> which is the ſum of the Goſpel; and that this having been already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Miracles from Heaven in the firſt eſtabliſhment thereof in the world, needs no more Miracles for its confirmation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (thoſe doctrines only wanting Miracles for their credit that are <hi>extra</hi>-Scriptural, pretended revelations, ſtrong perſwaſions and impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon mens hearts, having no greater authority then their own fancies, viſions born in their own brain, carryed on with fury, violence, pride and paſſion, and moſt importunely preſt upon the conſciences of men in the Name of the Lord without any Scripture.) I ſay, theſe conſidered with the like, I am no enemy to the publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>que Miniſtry, and do heartily congratulate good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates favour towards godly Miniſters, and the preſent courſe and hopeful endeavors of our preſent Rulers in ſeeking ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> able and fit men to preach the Goſpel in the Commonwealth; I wiſh
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115440:23"/>
them proſperity in the name of the Lord: But the men of my meaning in my humble Caution, are eaſily known by ſome or all of theſe Characters.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Men that will be of the Kings Religion, be he of what Religion he will, and are clamorous againſt all that cannot wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-cock it like themſelves; men that are not Okes, but O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rs, warping and winding this way or that way as the hand of their bountiful Patrons and Benefactors will wreath them; as of old, like Prince like Prieſt, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. 27. Men may eaſily diſcern their dawbing with untempered morter. The Court in former days never wanted theſe black Paraſites; they are known by their flattering titles they give, trying if they can trade by exchanging flatteries for favours.</p>
            <p>2. They mind earthly things; Watch them, you will ſee the center of their circumference (be the circle never ſo great) will be themſelves and families, places, profits, preferments, gratui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, theſe are ſweet Veniſon after hunting; pluralities, non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſidence, neglecting Gods flock by other perſons, are little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the unpardonable ſins, but <hi>pluſquam</hi> pluralities can down with themſelves without ſtraining, and the ſilver bell that hath the greateſt ſound is the faireſt call for their ſo doing, and the ſtill voyce of God ſpeaking to their conſciences is not heard through the noiſe thereof: their happineſs is not ſo much to be envyed as their unhappineſs to be pitied; neither is the ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able attendance of good men of this tribe about our preſent Rulers and families in the leaſt impleaded in theſe lines, nor their bounty or favour towards them, provided their attendance be not with the great neglect of thoſe grand duties incumbent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them by the Word of God, by Covenant and Conſcience, and that they improve their intereſt, opportunities and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages with them for the Common Peace of all their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the faith, however differing in opinion from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The men (of my meaning) of perſecuting of princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for conſcience ſake, are always found defaming, vilifying and reproaching their diſſenting brethren unto the Rulers, by cloathing their opinions with ugly names, as dangerous, diſmal, and dreadful things (taking advantage from their impoſſibility
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115440:24"/>
through their much buſineſs to examine the truth, and to make their own eyes their judges in the caſe, to ſave them a labour by telling them in their own manner, what men hold, and how dangerous thoſe things be, never informing (either through their own ignorance or malice) in what ſence, with what cautions, limitations, and reſtrictions, they maintain, or deny, and upon what grounds and arguments, they aſſert their judgements, it is no hard thought to ſuppoſe; (for there is reaſon enough) that there are men of worth, learning, excellency, and holineſs, whoſe names and reputations ſuffer ſhipwrack by the men of this Charact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, when any knotty, painful, and laborious buſineſs, (pertinent to their function) in times of ſtraits, appear neceſſary to be done; the men of their quarrel are then in eſteem, but when the cloud is over, and the work is done, and the Sun ſhines again, they have then done with them, they are ſhut up again in darkneſs under their black reproaches and ſcandals, and if they have but the liberty of their private Confines, Societies, and Companies, it is reward ſufficient, if not too much for all their labours; like the ſubtle Ape that took the Spaniels foot to reach the cheſnut out of the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and then eats the kernel, and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts him gone, leaving the burnt Spaniel to ſeek out a plaiſter: Well, the other world will make up all. A wiſe Prince cannot but judge ſuch diſingenuity much unworthy their function, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Men of perſecuting principles for conſcience ſake, are frequently known by this charactar, <hi>viz.</hi> They bring their opinions to the Scriptures, and fetch them not thence, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their <hi>id eſt,</hi> before the <hi>Scriptum eſt,</hi> their interpretation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Text. Men that <hi>Caedem Scripturarum faciuut,</hi> as one ſaith, that murther the Scriptures, yea that torture and torment them, like <hi>Amboyna</hi> Tyrants, to make them confeſs, and own ſuch things, as were never in their meaning. The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> preferred their traditional interpretations before the Text, and could not bear any expoſition, though never ſo ſound againſt their falſe gloſſes, though never ſo rotten, and that upon this ground, it is the general received opinion, and orthodox doctrine of all the Rabbies, Doctors and Fathers: <hi>Non tam ovum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vo ſimile,</hi> One egge is not ſo like another as thoſe then;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115440:24"/>
and theſe in our dayes. Did they prefer their falſe gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſes before the true Text? ſo do theſe. Were they more zealous of their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional doctrines, then of the Letter of the Scriptures? ſo are theſe. Were they fiery Adverſaries to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n differing from them, though more learned, more holy, more ſerviceable to God and the world, then themſelves? ſo are theſe. Did they ſtir up the people againſt D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſenters from them? ſo do theſe. Did they bring forth their raylings inſtead of reaſons? ſo do theſe. Did they ſtrive to inſnare, and catch at words and expreſſions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect to the ſence and meaning of good men, to make them obnoxious to men in authority? ſo do theſe. Did they falſely miſrepreſent them to men in place and rule? ſo do theſe. A wiſe Prince will beware of theſe men that <hi>dig</hi> for evil againſt their brethren, to defame them, that the ruler may diſfavour them. It is <hi>Solomons</hi> character of an ungodly man, to <hi>dig up evil,</hi> and whoſe lip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are as burning fire, who <hi>ſow ſtrife, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate chief friends,</hi> men that will pick up, <hi>dig out</hi> all that may be, and more then truth to injurie the men of their controverſie. When the <hi>Manichees</hi> could not anſwer <hi>Auſtins</hi> arguments, they hit him in the teeth with his youthful follies, whereunto his reply was only this, <hi>Quae vos reprehenditis ego damnavi,</hi> What you diſcommend in me, I have long ſince condemned: and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious <hi>Papiſts</hi> did the like to <hi>Beza,</hi> reprinting his wit-wanton Poems on purpoſe to diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e him, and objecting his former miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages whereof he had repented, he replied to one that did twit him in the teeth with it, <hi>Hic homo invidet mihi gratiam Chriſti,</hi> This man en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies me the grace of Jeſus Chriſt: And thus <hi>Miriam</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Num.</hi> 12. 1. being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>retted that God ſhould declare his Counſels to <hi>Moſes</hi> only, and that he ſhould have the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it, and not they, had nothing to object againſt him, but an old matter of ſeveral years date, <hi>viz.</hi> his marrying with an <hi>Aethiopian:</hi> I ſhall ſay no more about theſe men, but wiſh all good rulers may never be troubled with ſuch as theſe: <hi>White-Hall</hi> formerly was very rarely without them; their <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſms</hi> and <hi>Maxims,</hi> are dangerous. It was of old, <hi>No Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, no King:</hi> which was more ominous then neceſſary, and the end of it was to engage the King to aſſert the Biſhops, and to aſſiſt them in their tyranny and executing their cruel cenſures
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115440:25"/>
by his civil Sword. We have other ſaying<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the ſame ſence, and for the ſame end, though in other expreſſions: <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>the Sword of the Magiſtracy and the Sword of the Miniſtry muſt go together:</hi> which is a truth in a ſingular, but not vulgar ſence; or (if you pleaſe) in an <hi>Engliſh,</hi> not <hi>Scottiſh</hi> ſence, that is, to protect, (not puniſh) the people of God for keeping a good conſcience. That <hi>Magiſtratus eſt cuſtos, &amp; conſervator utriuſque tabulae,</hi> A true ſaying in a qualified ſence, though many times very ill applied: The Papiſts made <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniſts,</hi> the Biſhops; Browniſts, and Separatiſts, the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; Sectaries, and Hereticks; there are ſtill that ſucceed them in their ill trade, and are about an evil work, <hi>viz.</hi> making wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Anabaptiſts, Blaſphemers, Arminians, Socinians, Pelagians, and I know not what of thoſe whom the Spirit of God through grace by the belief of the Goſpel hath made the bleſſed ſervants of the moſt High God, Kings, and Princes, and Parliaments have been daſht in pieces at this ſtone by too much complyance with the men of this Character. And the Chriſtian care of our late Rulers, and preſent Protector, and caution of them hitherto hath opened the mouths of many Saints of different apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, agreeing together as one man, with one heart and lip, in prayers and prayſes to God for them and him: and I wiſh with all my ſoul, and that for the peace and happineſs of my Country, that that Spirit, Judgment, and Conſcience of theirs, and of him, in this reſpect may be redoubled upon his Succeſſours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His loftineſs in place provokes lovelineſs in practiſe, the more high the more humble, and like the Sun above he comforts and cheriſheth thoſe that are under him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His greatneſs doth better him, and not betray him into pride, and vanity, his <hi>HIGHNESS</hi> is his peoples happineſs, he is like an Angel of God amongſt them to protect and defend them, not as a Lion among beaſts to terrifie and torment them, he is their glory, and not their grie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, their ſongs and not their ſighs; <hi>When the righteous are in authority the people rejoyce, Prov.</hi> 29. 2. becauſe he is a mercy, and not a miſchief unto them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115440:25"/>
               <hi>His great project is rather to be beloved then feared of the people, and by doing every man right, and no man wrong, he ſets up his Throne in every mans heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is noted by the <hi>Indians</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians God is a good God, who doth good, but their God (who is the Devil) they count good when he doth them no hurt, and therefore they ſerve him not in love, but in fear: The Lord reigns making the earth to rejoyce thereby; and ſo ſhould Princes be the triumph, and not the terrour of their Territories.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His greatneſs provokes his goodneſs to commenſure herewith in the middeſt of his glory; he remembers his ſhame, and the deep ſenſe of his own demerits keeps him humble under popular Applauſe, knowing that his receipts are great, his talents many, his accounts proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he is always reckoning of his reckoning day: Pride, paſſsion, and wilfulneſs, incident to greatneſs, are his conſtant caution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His heighth humbles him, and his humility exalts him, his ſenſe of his emptineſs draws his heart after God for fulneſs. Pride brings a Tyrant low, but honour upholds the humble in ſpirit, <hi>Sequitur ſuperbos ultor, à tergo Deus,</hi> Vengeance follows the proud man at the heels; the judgment of God upon <hi>Pharaoh, Adonibez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ck, Agag, Haman, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rod, &amp;c.</hi> are much in his heart, his religion teaches him to be pure, peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be entreated, he (like Chriſt) ſeeks not his own glory, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God ſeeks it, and keeps it for him, <hi>John</hi> 18. 30. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not for himſelf, and therefore is God for him; under per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal injuries he ſits down with content, but publick wrongs rouze him up to contend; his heart is hunted out of his earthly holds, he ſees the uncertainty of earthly glory, the vanity, the non-entity of outward pomp, their impotency to help in the evil day, their impoſſibility to ſtretch to Eternity: That outward greatneſs is but a conceited wall, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18. 11. He well conſiders that God humbles the haughty, lifts up the lowly, as the lower
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115440:26"/>
the Ebbe, the higher the Tide; ſo his humiliation ſhall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed his exaltation, he looks not ſo much upon his fine feathers, as his foul feet, which is ballace to his bottom, and prevents the danger of his Broad-Sails, in the ſwelling and Surging Seas of outward pomp and greatneſs, he bluſheth (not bleſſeth himſelf) under popular applauſes; prayſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do more preſs him, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n pleaſe him, and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate upon him then gratifie him; the higher his head is before men, the lower his heart before God, he does wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily in <hi>Euphrata,</hi> and therefore is he famous in <hi>Bethleh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m:</hi> his ſame attends his vertue, as the ſhadow the body, he hath no tongue to praiſe himſelf: <hi>Haec ego f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci</hi> proves men no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>Faeces,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Luther.</hi>) Self-brags ſhews mens dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gs and droſs, not their valour and ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tue. <hi>Laus proprio ſordeſcit in ore,</hi> he that comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nds himſelf, vomits out of his own mouth his own ſhame, nauciating the ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>acks of ſtanders by: <hi>Moſes</hi> glory was not known to himſelf, but to thoſe that beheld him, his face did ſhine, but he knew it not, his ears (are not tickled but) tingle, when he hears men ſpeak of his worth and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs. When an elegant Speech was made in the commendation of <hi>Charls</hi> the fifth, by a great perſon, reherſing his noble and famous acts: the Emperour modeſtly replyes; That <hi>he accepted of the Oration, becauſe it did admoniſh him not ſo much what he had been, as what he ought to be.</hi> He remembers what he was when he ſees what he is. It is ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ied of <hi>Agath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cles,</hi> who of a Potters ſon, became King in <hi>Scicily;</hi> that he would ever be ſerved in earthen veſſels; and of one <hi>Willigis,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> being a Wheel-wrights<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Son, that he cauſed wheels to be hanged up a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d down the walls from his Palace with theſe words over them in Capital Letters, <hi>Willigis, Willigis recole unde Venris,</hi> Mind thy beginning. It was good counſel given by <hi>Placilla</hi> the Empreſs to her Husband <hi>Theodoſius:</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Sir, what you were la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely, and what you are now, this will make you mindful of your duty, and give God the glory: A man as good, as great, conſiders what he <hi>muſt</hi> be, as well as what he <hi>was,</hi> and <hi>is,</hi> he makes account of his accounts, and is frequently reckoning his reckonings; his Maſters <hi>Redde ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> is much in his mind, his receipts are in his eyes, and his account current in his heart, and his <hi>quietus eſt,</hi> is the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115440:26"/>
of his deſires, his even reckonings make long friendſhip between God and him, he is often caſting up his books, leſt his books ſhould caſt him up at laſt, which makes him diligen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, watchful, humble and low in his own thoughts, the noiſe of the feet of them that buried his Predeceſſours, is much in his ears, he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the ſound of his own paſſing bell, and in his thoughts goes to his own Funeral; he conſiders that as he hath had a time to be born, ſo he will have a time to die, and that he is every day <hi>drawing on,</hi> towards his <hi>drawing on:</hi> that his laſt day ſtands, but all the reſt runs, that the mortal Sythe is Maſter of the royal Scepter, and that it mows down as well the Lilies of the Crown, as the Crown of the Lilies; he remembers that though his Palace be built of hewen ſtone, yet his life is immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red within mud-walls in a clay cottage, and earthly taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, that his foundation is the duſt ready to be ſhattered and ſcattered with every blaſt, that he is but <hi>terra friabilis,</hi> crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, looſe earth: Pride, paſſion, and ſelf-will, are his conſtant caution.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Pride, he that ſaith he hath no pride, cannot want it, this made a devil of an Angel, and threw him down from his Throne with a vengeance. God reſiſteth a proud perſon, (as in battail-array,) It is God's reſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion (not) to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n (all glory but) <hi>the pride of all glory, and bring into contempt all the</hi> proud, (though) <hi>honorable of the Earth, Iſai.</hi> 23. 8. He hath his day for the proud and lofty; for every one that is lifted up, he ſhall be brought low, his lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty looks ſhall be humbled, and the Lord alone ſhall be ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, he pulleth down the proud, and lifteth up the lowly: He doth carefully cautelouſly, yea very curiouſly look to himſelf, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t his valour, his victories, his greatneſs, his Highner, his Armies, his Navies, the crowchings of his enemies, the applications of the great Princes of other Nations, his great houſes, his revenues, his a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tendance do ſteal in upon him, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagure his heart, ſeize it and take it before he is aware, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry him into captivi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y under pride and vanity, and bring him to ruine without remedy; he well remembers that <hi>by humility, and the fear of the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are riches, and honour, and life, Prov.</hi> 22. 4. When pride cometh in, ſhame cometh on, but while he is humble, God is at his right hand, ſo that he ſhall not fall, if he
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115440:27"/>
grows proud, he will know him at a diſtance, yea afar off. And therfore he ſtudies God, who pulleth down and ſetteth up whom he pleaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, whoſe are all Kingdoms, Power, and Glory; and he ſtudies himſelf, his duſt and aſhes, his heart, his lip, his life in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, he watcheth and prayeth againſt pride and vanity, which will make him humble and happy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, His own Paſſion is his own pain and ſorrow: Commonly Princes think they may be paſſionate by priviledg and peeviſh by prerogative. <hi>Moſes</hi> was an excellent General, an eminent Governor, and his meekneſs did add much to his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: Anger is little better then a ſhort Devil, and he that gives way to <hi>it,</hi> gives <hi>place to him.</hi> He that is big with wrath, breeds contention, and brings forth tranſgreſſion in abundance: A fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious man is a man maſter'd by furies, and (as the <hi>Perſian</hi> Kings to their Concubines) is a ſlave to a ſlave. Anger may ruſh into the heart of wiſe men, but it <hi>reſteth</hi> and <hi>rooſteth</hi> only in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of fools: The haſty man never wants woe. One counſelled <hi>Auguſtus</hi> to determine nothing raſhly when he was angry, but that he ſhould firſt repeat the Greek Alphabet: <hi>Ambroſe</hi> taught <hi>Theodoſius</hi> in that caſe to repeat the Lords Prayer. He that is ſlow to anger is of great underſtanding, but he that is haſty of ſpirit exalteth folly. 'Tis true, it's good to be angry, and not to ſin, but then a man muſt be angry at nothing but ſin, and not as it is an offence to man, but to God, nor yet ſo angry as to be unfit for prayer: <hi>Moſes</hi> was angry at the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> golden Calf, but could pray for them; Chriſt at the unbelief of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> but was grieved for the hardneſs of their hearts. Right anger is a very tender vertue, and ſuch as by reaſon of mans unskilfulneſs may be eaſily corrupted, and made dangerous. The Spirit of Prayer, Meditation, Communion with God, and the ſpirit of frowardneſs, will never mingle: the Spirit of Prophecy came not upon <hi>Eliſha</hi> until his heat was over; and his anger was charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the muſick of a Minſtrel, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 3. 15. A froward heart ſhall depart from God, a meek and quiet ſpirit is of great price with him. God deals above the thundering, tempeſtuous, and bluſtering clouds, and meets with men in the cool of the day, ſpeaking and appearing in the ſtill voice. He that is ſlow to anger is better then the mighty. U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruly paſſions (ſaith one) are
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115440:27"/>
thoſe <hi>Turks</hi> with whom we muſt ever make war: thoſe <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> with whom who ever made peace, gained nothing but repentance; a deadly fewd muſt be between good Princes and their luſts, which war in their members, fighting againſt their ſouls. A paſſionate perſon, though he be not drunk, yet is he not his own man: It's a ſhame for a Prince to have his luſts his lords, and his vices his vanquiſhers; He that ruleth his ſpirit, is better then he that taketh a City,</p>
            <q>Vince animos iramque tuam qui caetera vincis,</q>
            <p>Victory over himſelf yeilds him greater glory, richer ſpoyls, then all other victories: Here to overcome will is his glory, to be overcome his ſhame.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Self-will</hi> is not his will, knowing that <hi>Sic volo, ſic jubeo, &amp;c.</hi> is the Tyrants Charactar, and very incident to men in power, and their will is frequently their wo. King <hi>Charls</hi> was a <hi>probatum eſt</hi> of this. <hi>Joſiah</hi> one of the moſt famous Kings recorded in the Book of God, for piety and goodneſs, yet he never conſulting the Prophets, reſolutely would go to war con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to counſel, which coſt him his life, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35. 22. to the great loſs and lamentation of all his good people: <hi>Conſilii ſatis eſt in me mihi,</hi> is the ſaying of <hi>Solomons</hi> fool, in whoſe <hi>eyes his own ways is right, Prov. 12. 15. But he that hearkneth to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel is wiſe.</hi> A perſon ſuſpecting his own judgement, and taking adviſe of wiſer then himſelf, ſeldom miſcarries. A wo is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to that Land whoſe King is a Child, that is, weak, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and uncounſelable; as <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> who was a child at forty years old, whoſe father was a man at twelve; for age is no juſt meaſure of wiſdom: <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſe choſe him an excellent Councel of State, whom <hi>Rehoboam</hi> refuſed to hear, being as wilful as his father wiſe, being heady, high-minded, he loſt ten Tribes by his wilful and churliſh breath. It was ſaid of old, <hi>Romani ſedendo vincunt,</hi> Wiſdom is better then ſtrength, prudence ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth puiſſance, and counſel courage, which made <hi>Agamem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> ſet ſuch a price upon <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes:</hi> Where no counſel is the people fall, but in the multitude of Counſellers, (truly ſo called) there is ſafety; It is not titles, but truths; not the name of counſels, and counſellers, but the proper natures of them, that will bleſs him, and the people under him. It is reported of <hi>Xerxes,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115440:28"/>
that in his expedition againſt <hi>Greece,</hi> he called his Princes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but gave them neither freedom of ſpeech, or councel, <hi>leſt I ſhould ſeem</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>to follow mine own counſel I have aſſembled you, but do you remember, that it becomes you rather to obey, then to adviſe.</hi> To have a wiſe Councel that muſt not adviſe, or a weak Councel that cannot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, is much the ſame in the ſigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of God, and wiſe men: for a Prince to reſolve to follow the advice of his Councel, and yet to command them to give no counſel but what he tells them, he will follow, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as if one ſhould promiſe to maintain me ſo long as I live, provided I live no longer then he will maintain me. He hath weighty Affairs in his head, in his heart, on his hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; therefore all his purpoſes are eſtabliſhed by wiſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, which makes his proceedings neither unconſtant, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable: <hi>Deliberandum eſt diu quod ſtatuendum eſt ſemel.</hi> He conſiders long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re he reſolves upon any weighty enterpriſe, A Chriſtian Prince firſt of all, and above all adviſeth with God, <hi>Wo be to the rebellious children, that take counſel but not of me, Iſai. 30. 1. David</hi> had able Counſelle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s about him, but his chiefeſt were Gods teſtimonies. <hi>Pſal. 119. 24. Thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are my delight and my Counſellers.</hi> Princes have had their Remembrancers, Moniters, Councellers, as <hi>Themiſtocl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naxagores, Alexander</hi> his <hi>Ariſtotle, Scipio</hi> his <hi>Panaetius</hi> and <hi>Polybbius;</hi> but it is reported of <hi>Scipio Africanus</hi> that it was his cuſtome before day to go <hi>in Cellam Jovis,</hi> and there to ſtay <hi>quaſi conſultans de Republica Jove,</hi> adviſing with God about his Commonwealth: <hi>David</hi> in all his ſtraits asked counſel of the Lord: <hi>With good ADVICE make war,</hi> ſaid <hi>Solomon.</hi> Great matters require great advice: The Souldiers rule is, <hi>Non ſequi non ſugere bellum:</hi> neither to follow after war, nor to fly from it: and it is the Chriſtians Motto: <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c temere n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c timidè.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He well underſtands his ſlippery ſtanding, that he is a man in nature, though a God in Name; that the end of all is alike to all, though no mans dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger like to his: That heighth of place endangers down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115440:28"/>
               <hi>that the pinacle of preferment is a dreadfull poynt, which cauſeth his caution in all his ſteerage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He conſiders that his honours are attended with dangers, his Crown with cares, he knows that to keep and maintain the love of God, and the peoples good will coſt him ſtudy, for it, requires skill, That the Rulers duty is not ſoon learnt, that his work is great, his ſtrength is ſmall, his dangers many, his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs curious, his head, his heart, his hand, with much diligence are all imployed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He is the poor means Patron, the widows Husband, the Orphans Father, the good mans pleaſure, the bad mans terrour, affable in ſpeech, facile in acceſs, amiable in countenance, reſpecting no mans perſon, but every mans cauſe, thereby he becomes the deſire of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Work of the Ruler is to judge the poor, that's his duty, and his eſtabliſhment. <hi>James</hi> the fourth of <hi>Scotland,</hi> was for this called <hi>The poor mans King.</hi> Help, O King, ſaid the poor woman to <hi>Jehoram.</hi> If thou wilt not hear and right me, why doeſt thou take upon thee to be King? ſaid the poor woman to <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedony:</hi> It is a mercy to have Judges. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do audeant quae ſentiunt.</hi> So that they have courage to do what they judge fit to be done. A juſt Ruler is (as one ſaith of a juſt Law) a heart without affection, an eye without laſt, a mind without paſſion, a treaſury which keepeth for every one what he hath, and diſtributeth to every one what he ſhould have. Such a Prince ſhall ſit firm on his Throne, the hearts of his people wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l be his Life-Guard, and God his Protection, ſuch an one is like God, the poor mans refuge in the time of trouble, in him the Fatherleſs find mercy, and he will cauſe the widows heart to ſing for joy, if her cauſe be juſt, his conſcience pleads it with him, he regards not the greatneſs of her adverſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> goodneſs of her cauſe; he is no ſecret accepter of perſons, <hi>Job</hi> 13. 10. he hears cauſes without prejudicial impiety, and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly examines them without ſiniſter obliquity: and ſincerely
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115440:29"/>
determins them without ſinful partiality. It was ſaid of <hi>Cato,</hi> that he was one <hi>A quo nemo unquam rem injuſtam petere au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debat,</hi> So juſt as no man durſt make any unjuſt requeſt unto him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He eſteemeth royalty without righteouſneſs, as emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent diſhonour, guilded putrifaction, glorious baſeneſs, riches, retinue, ſplendor, and greatneſs, no better then meer Pageantry, ſhews and ſhadows of Nobleneſs, which cauſeth his vigilancy over his own heart, and his own family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Righteouſneſs is the way to ric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, goodneſs makes men glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. It was ſaid by one of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, <hi>Bonus Deus Conſtantinum magnum tantis t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrenis implevit muneribus quanta optare nullus auderet,</hi> The good Lord heaped ſo much outward happineſs upon (his faithful Servant) <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, as no man ever durſt to have wiſhed more; his glory (like <hi>Sarah's</hi> beauty) conſiſteth in the hidden man, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 4. He knows that <hi>Dignitas in indigno eſt ornamentum in luto,</hi> That a jewel of gold in a ſwines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nout, is as comely as gay clothes upon vile perſons, painted Sepulchres. <hi>Solomons</hi> wiſdom ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him more honourable then all his glittering and golden glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: the juſtice, wiſdom, righteouſneſs of a pious Prince, theſe are Ornaments of grace, and Crowns of glory, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. 8, 9. Riches, honours, delights, pleaſures, life, length of days, ſeed, and poſterity, are all entailed upon piety and holineſs; outward pomp, greatneſs and glory ſuck out the goodneſs of the heart, (as the Ivy from the Oak) except there be curious caution; What are they but inſufficient and unſatisfactory, often provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to vice, and hinderanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of vertue? The Order of nature is inverted, when vile men are exalted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12. 8. It is a foul incongruity, and of very evil conſequence, vile perſons are loathſom, though veild with velvets, and the children of Satan though in Sattin.</p>
            <p>He hath great vigilancy over <hi>his own family;</hi> he ſees who they are, and what they are: every officer, every ſervant he keeps, is of his own choyce or approbation: He cannot rule well
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115440:29"/>
in the Church, much leſs in the Nation, that ruleth not his own houſe well: He bewares of an <hi>Achitophel,</hi> a <hi>Doeg,</hi> an <hi>Haman.</hi> It was ſaid of a Prince of <hi>Germany,</hi> That <hi>eſſet al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſi eſſet apud alios,</hi> He would be another man, were he with other men. He takes heed who gets the royalty o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his ear, leſt he doth with him what he liſt. <hi>David</hi> would not know, <hi>i. e.</hi> own a wicked perſon, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. 4. and verſ. 7. <hi>He that worketh deceit ſhall not dwell within my houſe, he that telleth lyes ſhall not tarry in my ſight;</hi> An hypocrite, an Iſmaelite ſhall not dwell wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h him: He takes heed of proud ſervants; knowing that men will be apt to miſtake him in them, and think they read him in them. A wicked perſon in his family is as an <hi>Achan</hi> in the Army, a <hi>Jonas</hi> in the Ship. 'Tis his honour and wiſdom to be loved and feared of his family; which he will never be, except they be wiſe and honeſt: <hi>He that delicately bringeth up his ſervant, ſhall have him become ſon at the length, Prov. 29. 21. Solomon</hi> himſelf (that ſometimes knew better how to give good counſel then to take it) entertains <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> gave him great power in his houſe, admitted him into ſo much familiarity, that he let looſe the bridle of domeſtical diſcipline unto him, in ſo much that he took ſtate upon him as a young Maſter in the houſe, and ſoon after turn'd Traytor: See the like in <hi>Abner, Iſhboſheths</hi> ſervant, who grew ſo haughty, that he muſt not be ſpoken to; and ſo <hi>Zimri,</hi> whom his Lord and Maſter <hi>Elah, 1 King.</hi> 16. 11. advanced Captain over half of his charets, being thus like a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſet on horſeb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ides without reins to the ruine of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and whole houſe:</p>
            <q>Aſperius nihil eſt humili dum ſurgit in altum.</q>
            <p>It is with a Ruler in reſpect of evil ſervants, as with a creature called Millipeda, the more feet it hath the flower it goeth: cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ſervants hinder the courſe of Juſtice; this reflects upon their Lords. His frowns are upon evil, and his <hi>favors upon wiſe ſervants,</hi> which is <hi>Solomons</hi> counſel, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. as was <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi> towards <hi>Joſeph, Darius</hi> towards <hi>Daniel, Henry</hi> the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght towards <hi>Cromwell,</hi> who for his wiſdom and faithfulneſs he raiſed from a mean perſon (ſon to a Blackſmith) to be Maſter of his Jewel-houſe, Baron of <hi>Okeham</hi> in <hi>Rutland</hi>-ſhire, then Knight of the Garter, Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> Lord great Chamberlain, and at laſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115440:30"/>
his Vicar General. A wiſe ſervant may have rule over a ſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſhonor to the father, and diſcredit to the ſon. Amongſt his ſervants ſome may be wiſer, ſome better, ſome more in Gods favour then others: He lets ſuch have rule over his houſhold by his commiſſion, and ſuffers not the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ambles to domineer over the Ceda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. The le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity, luxury, idleneſs, wantonneſs of the <hi>quon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> Court at <hi>White-hall,</hi> together with their concomitants, were none of the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt <hi>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ns</hi> of their deſtruction. It is obſerved by one, that among all the ſervants, pleaſures and delights which <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> had, he got him no fool or Jeſter, which formerly Princes could not be without in this Nation, no not when they ſhould be moſt ſerious. It is recorded of <hi>Henry</hi> the third King of <hi>France,</hi> that in a ſolemn P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ceſſion at <hi>Paris</hi> he could not be without his Jeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, who walking between the King and the Cardinal, made mirth to them both: Was not here ſweet devotion? The truth is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir religious actions were all in jeſt, their wicked in earneſt: I hope no ſuch vile and vicious perſons will be ever found more in our Engliſh Courts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He is the joy of the juſt, the delight of their ſouls, the breath of their noſtrils: He lives beloved, he dyes deſired, is buried with lamentations, his generation is bleſſed, and his name is had in everlaſting remembrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Death of <hi>Joſiah</hi> ſtruck the heart of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> making their eyes as fountains of tears, and their mourning ſo gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at, that it grew to a Proverb, <hi>The mourning of Hadadri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the valley of Megiddon, Zach.</hi> 12. 11. His memory ſhall be bleſſed, his name ſhall be heir to his life, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhall enjoy the fruit of his vertue, <hi>His children are bleſſed after him, Prov.</hi> 20. 7. His righteouſneſs is inherited by his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and laid up in everlaſting remembrance, and his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſhall be unto an incorruptible Crown of Glory, which is undefiled and fadeth not away, with the whole Family of God, and the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, where he ſhall receive a prepared Kingdom, and dwell among thoſe Manſions, ſhining as the Sun in the Firmament, for ever, and ever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
