<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The generall junto or The councell of union, chosen equally out of England, Scotland, and Ireland, for the better compacting of three nations into one monarchy, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Parker, Henry, 1604-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P402</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.18[1]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R211946</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870614</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870614</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123007</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A91231)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123007)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 246:669f18[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The generall junto or The councell of union, chosen equally out of England, Scotland, and Ireland, for the better compacting of three nations into one monarchy, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Parker, Henry, 1604-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed, Anno Dom. 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. By Henry Parker.</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: [on recto of fly leaf]: "NB. The Generall Junto by Hen Parker Esq. A Declaration Concerning ye Generall Accompts of ye Kingdome [illegible] the nature &amp; necessitie of them stated [illegible, folowed by a flourish]"; "The Generall Junto but fifty of them printed at the Charge of Sr John Danvers &amp; never to be sold but given to particular friends"; "N:11 of 24 [crossed out] 12 Fb".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123007:1"/>
            <p>The Generall
JUNTO,
OR
THE COVNCELL
OF
UNION,
Choſen equally out of England,
<hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the better compacting
of three Nations into one Monarchy, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>Trojugenis</hi> Paries quid amantibus obſtas?</l>
               <l>Quantum erat, ut ſineres toto nos corpore jungi?</l>
            </q>
            <p>Printed, Anno Dom. 1642.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:123007:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123007:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123007:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123007:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:123007:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123007:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN a <hi>Perſon</hi> of ſo great <hi>Worth</hi> as <hi>Your ſelf, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi>
and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> muſt needs be not onely <hi>diffuſive,</hi>
but <hi>attractive</hi> alſo, and that farre more then in <hi>inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
men.</hi> The <hi>boldneſſe</hi> therefore aſſumed by me at this
time, in tendring to <hi>Your View</hi> and <hi>Judgement</hi> this <hi>poor
Eſſay</hi> (a weak <hi>endeavour</hi> of <hi>Service</hi> to our <hi>Countrey</hi>
(of which <hi>You</hi> are ſo true a <hi>Lover</hi>) will appear (I hope) the
more excuſable: For as thoſe <hi>Parts</hi> which deſerve <hi>Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
in <hi>You,</hi> cannot but command <hi>Offices</hi> of <hi>Hommage</hi>
and <hi>Gratitude</hi> from all <hi>good men;</hi> ſo thoſe <hi>Parts</hi> which
render <hi>You humble,</hi> and <hi>gentle,</hi> and <hi>willing</hi> to pardon
other mens <hi>Miſtakes,</hi> will induce you to interpret well that
<hi>Hommage</hi> and <hi>Gratitude. Sir,</hi> I have a very
low conceit of this <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> as it is now by me faſhion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
but I have a ſtrong <hi>Imagination,</hi> That it might prove
<hi>Publiquely</hi> advantagious, if it were by <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
men</hi> better <hi>formed</hi> and <hi>compleated.</hi> I have
therefore purpoſely left a large <hi>Margent</hi> to my ſhort <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi>
that a better <hi>pen,</hi> and <hi>direction</hi> might <hi>change</hi> and
<hi>ſupply</hi> my failing <hi>Invention,</hi> and take the ſame <hi>liberty</hi>
to <hi>expunge</hi> the <hi>vanities</hi> of my tedious <hi>expreſſions.</hi> If
there be any thing here tha may but adminiſter the leaſt <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion</hi>
or <hi>hint</hi> to your <hi>Worth</hi> to be a more <hi>beneficiall
<pb facs="tcp:123007:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Patriot,</hi> I ſhall think it a happy <hi>Service;</hi> if not, yet let not
my fruitleſſe <hi>wiſhes</hi> want your <hi>excuſe;</hi> and you ſhall <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige</hi>
me to be</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Yours moſt humbly <hi>devoted</hi> in all <hi>Service</hi>
and <hi>Obſervance</hi> to my utmoſt power, H. PARKER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:123007:5"/>
            <head>The Generall Junto, or the
Councell of Union, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O perſwade to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and commend <hi>now</hi> the
benefit of it to <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
would (I think) be unneceſſary: it
will be ſufficient to make an <hi>Overture,</hi> how
a further, and more <hi>intimate <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> may be maintained
amongſt us. <hi>Divide, &amp; impera,</hi> is fit Advertiſement
for a <hi>Nero</hi> to take, which aims onely at the diſſipati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and perdition of his Subjects; and for a <hi>Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel</hi>
to give, which aims onely at the pleaſing of ſuch
Maſters as <hi>Nero</hi> was: Good Princes, from honeſt
Counſellors, have ever received contrary advice;
and indeed it were impoſſible, that the very eſſence of
<hi>God</hi> ſhould be <hi>Love, Peace,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> if there were
any good to be expected from <hi>Diſſention;</hi> or that it
ſhould be <hi>Sathans</hi> proper title to be a <hi>Spoyler,</hi> a <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer,</hi>
and a <hi>Scatterer from the beginning,</hi> if Amity and
Concord could be dangerous. It is true, <hi>Vnity</hi> in large
and ſpreading <hi>Dominions,</hi> is not altogether ſo eaſie to
be preſerved, as in States of narrower bounds; nor is
Government ſo feaſible over ſeverall Nations, in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
Continents divided, and by ſeverall Laws, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:123007:6"/>
Cuſtomes eloigned, as over one Countrey cloſe ſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated
and compacted. And yet 'tis frequently ſeen,
That Art and Induſtry in prudent Princes, overcome
naturall hinderances and obſtructions, and many
times by <hi>Politique</hi> Nerves and Ligaments happily
knits and conjoyns men together, whom Nature hath
placed farre aſunder. The Poet having in contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
before him a fair Pile of building curiouſly ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented,
gives theſe words to his admiration;
<q>
                  <l>Si lapis eſt unus; dic quâ fuit Arte levatus?</l>
                  <l>Si duo, vel plures; dic ubi congeries?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The juncture of many ſtones in a building may be
ſcarce perceivable; and where it is not altogether ſo
exquiſite, yet (if Art be not too much wanting) they
may prove as firm, as fit for duration, and do as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
Offices to the whole Fabrick, as if they were all
one ſolid Rock or Quarry. And after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
in <hi>Politicall</hi> Bodies, an <hi>Artificiall</hi> coalition or coag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation
ſometimes proves as vigorous, as that
which is more <hi>Naturall,</hi> if it be wiſely conſtituted,
and orderly diſpoſed. Howſoever, as no kindely
means of Union amongſt Nations ought to be neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
ſo no violent means ought to be uſed, for both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes
may prove equally pernicious and deſtructive
to the ends which we propoſe. <hi>Philip</hi> in the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi>
was too rigorous a proſecutor of <hi>Vnion;</hi> for whilſt
he would confide in no <hi>Vnion</hi> betwixt the <hi>Dutch</hi> and
<hi>Spaniſh,</hi> but ſuch as ſhould wholly change the <hi>One</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:123007:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Nation, and covert it (as it were) to all purpoſes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the other, he wholly rent <hi>Both</hi> of them aſunder,
and temerated that tie, which otherwiſe in time by
gentle means might have grown ſufficiently valid.
And in my opinion, we in <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland</hi>
have of late, in our endeavors of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation,
been as much too remiſſe, as <hi>Philip</hi> was too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe,
and have neglected to prepare ſuch further
Barres, and hoops as might have bound us yet more
neer together. To make this appear, is the intent of
this diſcourſe at this time; wherein, for Methods ſake,
I ſhall confine my ſelf to theſe three points:</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, I ſhall endeavour to unfold <hi>What
the nature of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place, I ſhall ſet forth</hi> that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion which
is already ſetled betwixt England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland,
and wherein it is yet imperfect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the laſt place,</hi> I ſhall give ſome Demonſtration of a
new Ordinance, whereby <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion may be further improved,
and perfected in all His Maieſties ſeverall Dominions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Politicall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is obſervable for its ſeverall <hi>kindes,
orders,</hi> and <hi>degrees.</hi> One <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is more <hi>Externall,</hi> and
another more <hi>Internall</hi> in kinde; But that which is <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall,</hi>
and ſeated (as it were) in the hearts of Nations,
and is held together by the bonds of true Amity, is
farre to be valued before that which is <hi>Externall</hi> only,
and conſiſts in meer <hi>Politicall</hi> Acts, and Pacts, be they
never ſo many or ſtrong. Thus the <hi>Scots</hi> have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:123007:7"/>
affected the <hi>French,</hi> and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> the <hi>Spaniards,</hi>
by I know not what kinde of Natural Sympathy; and
had not many other ſtrange Obligations croſſed the
ſame, their hearts could hardly ever have been tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered
for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> It is therefore true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
noted, That <hi>Vires Imperii in conſenſu ſunt Obedienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,
&amp; Omnis poteſtas fundata eſt in Voluntate:</hi> and ſayes
another, <hi>Errat longè qui credit Imperium ſtabilius aut fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius
eſſe, quod vi adjungitur, quàm quod facilitate &amp; cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentia.</hi>
The <hi>Romanes</hi> being to grant peace to a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
Nation lately ſubdued, asked firſt upon that
Peace granted, What fidelity they ſhould expect
from the Petitioners: it was anſwered, <hi>That if the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
of Peace were granted with Clemency, they could not
but be entertained with ſincerity; but if the terms of the
Conquerours were rigorous, the engagements of the Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
could not but be the leſſe faithfull.</hi> And this ſtout an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
in <hi>Suitors</hi> did not diſreliſh their more ſtout Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors.
Had <hi>Portugall</hi> joyned <hi>hearts</hi> with <hi>Spain,</hi> as it
did <hi>hands</hi> (as doubtleſſe it had, if Love or Charity,
and not too much violence had made the Contract)
this late Divorce had not ſo ſoon happened; for it
were very behoovefull for both thoſe Nations, if
they could agree to yoke ſweetly together, and their
mutuall conflicting againſt each other may probably
draw on the ruine of both. <hi>Dum ſinguli pugnant, Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
vincuntur.</hi> Two Nations ſeated together in one
competent proportionable Continent, are like two
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123007:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Merchants trading at Sea in one Bottome, being both
equally owners of the ſame; an unfriendly partition
makes each Moity unſerviceable, but a wiſe partner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
doth not onely preſerve, but enrich both. I wiſh
therefore the Government may be ever ſweetned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
us in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by <hi>Juſtice,</hi>
and <hi>Equality;</hi> for what attracts love amongſt Nations,
we all know; and how far the Attraction is general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
helpfull, we all know; and how farre Nations
naturally deſire that help, we all know. Smaller Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions
are leſſe ſubject to inteſtine diſtempers and
miſcarriages in Government, but are more obnoxious
to forraigne violence of Invaders; and therefore if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall
Conditions might be equally rendered, it were
unnaturall for Nations not to affect <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> The <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>
Towns in <hi>Helvetia,</hi> though of ſeverall profeſſions
in Religion, and <hi>Ariſtocratically</hi> governed, yet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here
lovingly in one Symmetricall Body together,
and this is by the ſweetneſſe of <hi>Equity;</hi> for certainly
the Ligaments of one and the ſame Religion under
Rule Monarchicall, were much more available to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitate
and corroborate <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Orders</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> are next obſervable; for the
foot is united to the head as well as the heart, but not
after ſo honourable a manner; the heart obtains prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
and ſuperiority above the foot, notwithſtanding
the force of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion:</hi> Now this Order is to hold onely
in One and the ſame Body particularly conſidered,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:123007:8"/>
but not in ſuch <hi>Principall Integrall</hi> parts as may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
in <hi>ſeverall</hi> bodies for ſome purpoſes. Where
ſeverall Kingdoms are united, one muſt not be the
head, the other the foot; <hi>Integrall</hi> parts may have ſuch
order in themſelves, but not among themſelves; for
all muſt equally partake both of ſuperiority and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority:
ſome in each Nation may enjoy command, and
undergo burthen; and 'tis not neceſſary that this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
be aſſigned wholly to command, and that to bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then;
for <hi>Order</hi> may be ſufficiently preſerved by <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality</hi>
in each Nation, without inequality of any
one Nation over the other. <hi>Rome</hi> in this was not more
<hi>noble</hi> then wiſe, for as ſhe did admit all Nations to an
<hi>Equality</hi> of <hi>Priviledges,</hi> and <hi>Franchiſes</hi> with her ſelf, ſo
by the ſame admiſſion ſhe did extend her bounds into
all Nations, ſhe merited to be called <hi>Terrarum Dea,</hi>
becauſe ſhe would truely be <hi>Communis Patria,</hi> and
<hi>Mundi compendium.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Haec eſt in gremium quae victos ſola recepit,</l>
               <l>Humanumque genus communi nomine fovit.</l>
               <l>Matris, non Dominae ritu.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>The number of the Senators wanting a recrew in
the Raigne of</hi> Claudius, <hi>ſome diſpute was thereupon
between the</hi> French, <hi>and the</hi> Italians; <hi>the</hi> French <hi>ſought
to have their Nation honoured with an equality of
Election to that degree; the</hi> Italians <hi>held it derogatory
that other Nations ſhould participate therein: but</hi>
Caeſar, <hi>like a true</hi> Romane <hi>in that, gave his deciſion in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123007:8"/>
favour of the</hi> French, <hi>alleadging for his reaſon, That
his Anceſtors had enlarged the Empire by this cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
Aſſociation of Strangers; and that the</hi> Lacedae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians
<hi>by their rigid Inhoſpitality, and diſdain of
others, had fruſtrated their own Victories, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
their growing Fortunes. That miſerable
Schiſm and Revolt of the</hi> Ten Tribes <hi>from the Line
of</hi> David, <hi>was occaſioned by an unequall diſtribution
of favour and indulgence; and (Oh) how great a wound
did the true Worſhip of God receive in the bloody
purſuance of that unnaturall Quarrell?</hi> Judah <hi>claims
to be neerer in Blood to the King, then</hi> Iſrael; Iſrael
<hi>being ſo injured, claims to have ten parts in the King
by a more conſiderable intereſt, then that of Blood:
and how curſed a thing was it, that ſuch fond claims
ſhould one moment of time reſt undecided? I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
here but aſſume the Kings Perſon, and thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulate
with both conteſting Parties. YOU MEN OF
JUDAH,</hi> I am bound to love and honour you by the ties of more
immediate Conſanguinity; but in Civill Negotiations by the
Laws of Soveraignty, which exceeds Naturall Affections, I
am as firmly obliged, and as neerly allyed to Iſrael as to you.
You are to me Both as One and the ſame Body, and to be orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized
by a vertue and reſidence in every part, as well as in the
whole Totall. <hi>You men of Iſrael,</hi> You are the greater and
more conſiderable proportion of my Subjects; and if I muſt
needs be dilacerated, and ſuffer a diſſection by your abſurd
Contention, you are to receive the greater ſhare of me. But
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123007:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to what purpoſe is ſuch violence, or what Juſtice can be in it?
for the right of <hi>Judah</hi> to me, is the ſame in Nature as yours,
and wholly incorporated with yours, that it can ſuffer no juſt
Partition; and if it could, your Advantage thereby would be
none at all. <hi>Royalty</hi> is as the Sun, and ſends forth beams in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſible,
and ſufficient for all; and if all were blinde as one
man, that one man ſhould enjoy no more light then he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
when all did partake in his happineſſe. <hi>You men
of Judah and Iſrael,</hi> Let the peace of the Naturall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
compoſe this your groundleſſe diſpute, the left hand quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels
not with the right for precedence, they both receive from
the Head in equall meaſure, and remain officiouſly tributary to
the Head in equall manner. When I put on Magiſtracy,
I did withall put off Affinity in matters of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Tros, Rutiluſve fieret nullo diſcrimine habebam. <hi>As
I ſhall expect from you nothing but equall ſervice and loyalty, ſo
do you expect from me nothing but equall Love and Protection.</hi>
Had <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> been thus treated, when the
Coles of Emulation were firſt blown by malignant
Mutiners, ſo great a flame had not riſen therefrom:
for Partiality is the fewell of Diſcontent; and where
that is taken away, the beame of Juſtice keeps all in
Peace and Awe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Juſta pari premitur veluti cum pondere libra:</l>
               <l>Prona nec hâc plus parte ſedet, nec ſurgit ab illâ.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, though it were commendable in
<hi>Cleo,</hi> at his firſt Arrivall unto Publique Rule, to call
his friends together, and diſcard them as to all Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:123007:9"/>
Affairs; ſo this condemns not <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> if in
Domeſticall, or meer naturall offices, he gratifie his
former friends before others. But this is obvious, and
I come now to the <hi>Degrees</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As that <hi>Vnion</hi> which is betwixt Brothers, is of more
vigour then that between ſervants, becauſe it is more
<hi>internall,</hi> and that betwixt ſervants of the ſame Rank
and Condition, then where great diſtances and diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities
are, becauſe it is more <hi>equall;</hi> ſo that <hi>Vnion</hi> is
moſt ſure and inviolable, and moſt intenſe in <hi>Degree,</hi>
where both theſe Atrributes (<hi>internall,</hi> and <hi>equall</hi>) do
moſt eminently meet and concenter: where the moſt
zealous affection of the <hi>Heart</hi> naturally, and the moſt
exact Equality of <hi>Intereſts</hi> Politically doth cement
and cloſe People together, there <hi>Vnion</hi> is in it's moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
ſtrength and perfection; then it is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
ſtiled <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity it ſelf.</hi> This is that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> which I
ſhall pray to ſee eſtabliſhed betwixt <hi>England, Scotland,</hi>
and <hi>Ireland;</hi> then which, there can be none more <hi>inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate</hi>
in <hi>kinde,</hi> more <hi>equall</hi> in <hi>Order,</hi> more <hi>perfect</hi> in
<hi>Degree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. In the next Place therefore, having this for our
Aime, we muſt conſider what advantages theſe three
Nations have already, conducing to ſuch <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and
what the Hinderances are, which ſeem moſt to indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
us, and make us averſe from the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thoſe things which are of favourable Aſpect, and
more propitious to the uniting of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
are,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:123007:10"/>
Firſt, That both Nations are ruled by one <hi>Head,</hi>
and owe Allegiance to the ſame <hi>Maſter;</hi> and even this
hath a ſtrong Unitive power in it, and ſuch as works
<hi>internally,</hi> as well as <hi>externally;</hi> for we ſee the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
and <hi>Netherlanders</hi> are many wayes engaged in the
ſame Intereſts, and have had many interchangeable
Obligations and endearments (as things are now bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced
in <hi>Europe</hi>) and yet by reaſon of their depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
upon ſeverall Potentates, there cannot be ſetled
betwixt them that certain Correſpondence and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence,
as might be, if one Scepter commanded both.
And we ſee the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> under
one Prince, hath planted new Affections in both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
as hath been atteſtated by many Noble Offices
of Friendſhip, needleſſe now to be repeated.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is the ſame Profeſſion of <hi>Religion</hi>
in both Kingdoms; and this of all Bonds ought to be
the moſt indiſſoluble, for it is ſomething more then
meerly <hi>Phyſicall,</hi> or <hi>Ethicall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The ſame name of <hi>Britain</hi> is common to
both, the ſame Language ſpoken by both; and this,
together with their great ſimilitude in Complexions,
and diſpoſitions, teſtifieth the ſame Antient extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and kindred.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The ſame Sea ſurrounds both, immuring
them from all the world beſides, and by Conſequence,
the ſame ends ought to ſteer both, ſince no other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
can be more helpfull by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> or pernicious by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123007:10"/>
               <hi>Diſ-union:</hi> and ſince both joyned together make up but
one, and that no very conſiderable large <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, The ſame Laws of God and Nature are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced
and known by Both; and if their Laws of
<hi>Monarchy, Municipall Cuſtomes,</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> be
not the very ſame, they are very little diſagreeing;
that variety which is in them is very conſiſtent with
Harmony.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The ſame Impreſſions have been made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
both by late <hi>Offices</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Brotherly Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi>
hath been yeelded, that not onely all old Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
are drowned therein, but alſo both Nations for the
future are more enflamed to merit of each other.</p>
            <p>All theſe things tending to the great Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> thoſe things which ſeem repugnant to
the ſame by able <hi>Politicians</hi> might be much corrected,
or wholly removed. As for the <hi>Independence</hi> of each
Kingdom, that is no barre at all to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> for whilſt
the line of King <hi>James</hi> remains unſpent, the Crowns
are utterly inſeparable, and as really marryed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
as to all purpoſes of mutuall defence and comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
as <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and <hi>Arragon,</hi> or any Kingdom whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.
And if any doubt were of Separation by the
extinguiſhment of that Royall Race (which God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert)
I do not ſee but that by conſent of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,
that doubt may be prevented, without injury
to either. And as for the <hi>Diſtance</hi> and <hi>Extenſion</hi> of
both Kingdomes, that can be no barre to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123007:11"/>
               <hi>France</hi> in its Circuit and dimenſions is equall to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and yet is but one entire
Monarchy, and hath been aſſembled in one Generall
<hi>Parliament,</hi> and therein conſiſts the ſoul of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi>
And the meer holding of ſeverall <hi>Parliaments</hi> in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
Counties, poſſibly at the ſame time, the ſame Head
regulating all by faithfull <hi>Diſpatches,</hi> and <hi>Miſſives</hi> is
no hinderance, but that the ſame underſtanding may
be in all, and work the ſame effects, as One and the
ſame could. If there be any thing worthy to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted
upon ſeeming oppoſite to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> tis the different
<hi>Revenues</hi> of both Kingdoms, and ſome diſadvantages
cauſed thereby to each: for it will be ſaid, That <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
as the richer, draws away ſome Priviledge therby
from <hi>Scotland;</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> being the leſſe plentifull
in Treaſure, draws away much of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.
But I ſhall anſwer this hereafter; and ſo for
the preſent I ſet my Sayls for <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe things which are apt to promote <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> are,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That both Kingdoms have not onely one
<hi>Head,</hi> but are one <hi>Body</hi> alſo, inſeparably knit to that
<hi>Head,</hi> no independance or poſſible ſeverance remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
but ſuch as ſhall be violent and injurious. <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
hath formerly been ſubject to ſeverall Princes,
but all thoſe independant Principalities are now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated,
and connaturalized by Act of <hi>Paliament,</hi>
and reduced to a perfect Unity of Dominion; and yet
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123007:11"/>
all <hi>England</hi> is not more it ſelf, and one with <hi>England,</hi>
then <hi>Ireland</hi> is in all that is Eſſentiall to Dominion. By
the Laws of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> both the Kingdoms
are ſo connexed and coinveſted, that <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Cornwall</hi>
are not more individed from <hi>England,</hi> then <hi>Ireland</hi> now
is. <hi>Wales</hi> is ſtill a Principality, and <hi>Cornwall</hi> a Dutchy,
but neither are independent. So that nothing in truth
remains, but the meer names or titles; and the inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance
of <hi>Ireland</hi> being in the ſame manner taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> is indeed but an <hi>Integrall</hi>
member of the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> Neither is <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
dependent; becauſe it is independent, we tearm it
rather annexed, and by that we mean wholly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiated.
The addition of <hi>Ireland</hi> to <hi>England</hi> is
like the Naturall growth of a man at full yeers, which
makes him not another Creature then what he was, in
the narrow confinement of the Cradle, but ſtill leaves
him One and the ſame. <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> are uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by two Royall Lines centring in our King; but
one and the ſame Line conveighs <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi>
and that Line is indiviſible; ſo that though the King
be Owner of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> yet he is not Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
of <hi>England, quatenùs</hi> Owner of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or Owner
of <hi>Scotland, quatenùs</hi> Owner of <hi>England,</hi> but he is
Owner of <hi>Ireland quatenùs</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe ſome of the <hi>Rebells</hi> now pretend to an
<hi>independence,</hi> and ſome upbraid the <hi>Rebells</hi> with a meer
<hi>ſervile dependence,</hi> I will a little ſtep out of the way, to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:123007:12"/>
encounter with both theſe Incendiaries, and perturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
of our Peace.</p>
            <p>Againſt the <hi>Iriſh Rebells</hi> I ſhall maintain, <hi>That the
Kings Title to</hi> Ireland <hi>is of a mixt Nature, partly by the
Victories of his Anceſtors, and partly by Conſent of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,
and in both points ſtrongly fortified by a long, unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned,
uninterrupted poſſeſſion.</hi> And what more can be
added? No Prince of <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> can hold one foot of
Land by any title more cleer and undefeſeable then
where all theſe clayms are wreathed together. And
in this reſpect <hi>Ireland</hi> is further united to <hi>England</hi> then
<hi>Scotland</hi> is, for <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> are two Bodies joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
under one Head; but <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> are but
one Body, and have but one Head, they are not ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
juſtly as <hi>Scotland</hi> is. <hi>Conqueſt</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> both have
conjoyned them, and except the ſame, nothing can
dilacerate them. And thus upon the <hi>Norman</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt
<hi>England</hi> loſt it's Independence, and became One
with <hi>Normandy;</hi> for if nothing but the hand of War
twiſted their Titles, nothing elſe can untwiſt them.</p>
            <p>Againſt the enemies of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which object the
right of <hi>Conqueſt</hi> (as ſome did lately at my Lord of
<hi>Straffords</hi> Tryall, to juſtifie his cruell oppreſſions) I
ſhall maintain, <hi>That the right of Conqueſt doth not afford
any true Warrant for Oppreſſion.</hi> In <hi>Conqueſt</hi> three things
ought to be ſearched into, Whether it be <hi>juſt, totall,</hi>
and <hi>pure</hi> or no. If it be juſt (as we will ſuppoſe the
<hi>Normans</hi> to be) it onely ejects the Deſſeiſor, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:123007:12"/>
it ought to look no further then the Proſtration of the
Competitor. If <hi>Harold</hi> will not do right to <hi>William</hi>
but by Compulſion, this ſhall not inſlave the whole
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; nay, <hi>Harold</hi> being in poſſeſſion, thoſe
of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> which take up Arms, and wait the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion
of the ſword, in a caſe to them doubtfull, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
juſtly be charged of Treaſon. Twas not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
that <hi>William</hi> did forbear to diſpoſſeſſe thoſe of our
Anceſtors, which had born no Arms againſt him, he
ought to have holden his hands alſo from thoſe which
had been Active in their former <hi>Maſters</hi> Service, the
Cauſe of both being diſputable. Of unjuſt <hi>Conqueſts</hi>
nothing needs to be ſaid.</p>
            <p>In the next Place alſo, if <hi>Conqueſt</hi> extend it ſelf over
a whole Nation, if the Conqueror have no Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
Party therein to favour his Claym, if he enter
without any Profeſſions of Clemency (as ſcarce any
Prince ever entred) yet even thus he is not diſobliged
and acquitted of the Laws of God and Nature; nor is
entitled to a Right of ſpoyling, waſting, and inthral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
of Gods People. Gods Law is indefinite, and
reacheth to all Kings, as well clayming by the Sword,
as by any other Paction, <hi>That they ſhall not heap up
Treaſure, or multiply Horſes, or lift up Themſelves againſt
their Brethren.</hi> Our <hi>Magna Charta</hi> doth not limit our
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings ſo farre, it reſtrains not from filling the
<hi>Exchequer,</hi> or encreaſing their Guards; and if they
will arrogantly contemn us as ſlaves, and not embrace
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:123007:13"/>
us as Brethren, it affords us no cleer Remedy. But
we ſee Gods <hi>Charter</hi> intimates that Princes were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained
for the Protection of the People, and not the
People created for the Drudgery of Princes. And
therefore it doth not onely prohibite all Actuall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
(as the Law of <hi>England</hi> doth) but it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
reſtrains from all Power of Oppreſſion, nay it
curbs all haughty thoughts, the very ſeeds of Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
<hi>Paraſites</hi> may aſcribe nothing but <hi>Divinity</hi> to
<hi>Princes,</hi> and inſult over <hi>Subjects</hi> as meer <hi>Beaſts of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi>
and ſo as a main <hi>Axiome</hi> of State, above all things
inculcate the raiſing of <hi>Money</hi> and <hi>Ammunition,</hi> and
dejecting of the People. But God preſcribes the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
His Law aims at the humbling of <hi>Monarchs,</hi>
and endearing of their Charge to them, and diſſwading
from all ſtrength and Confidence, but in the unfailing
<hi>Magazin</hi> of the Peoples hearts. Of that Conqueſt
then which is not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall,</hi> and without all Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
from the Countrey Conquered, 'little needs be
ſaid; for it is moſt evident, that neither <hi>England</hi> nor
<hi>Ireland</hi> was ever ſo over-run.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing to be enquired after in <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> is it's
Abſoluteneſſe from all Quarter, and freedome from
Conditions offered, or accepted: and if it be the moſt
<hi>pure Conqueſt</hi> that can be imagined, yet it doth not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve
the <hi>Winners</hi> from the ties of common Piety, and
Civility. I need not inſtance in Religious <hi>Moſes,</hi> who
out of zeal to ſave the <hi>Community,</hi> from deſtruction,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:123007:13"/>
offered to forgoe his Intereſt in Heaven; or in holy
<hi>David,</hi> who to exempt <hi>Gods Flock</hi> from the raging
Plague, prayed that it might be diverted upon him
their <hi>Shepherd. Paganiſme</hi> may inſtruct us ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in this. <hi>Alexanders</hi> Conqueſts in the Eaſt were as
pure and unmixt as any, yet it is a great Addition to
his fame, That he treated the <hi>Perſians</hi> with the ſame
indulgence as the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> ſhewing himſelf an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually
tender <hi>Shepherd</hi> to both, and complying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
rather with <hi>Plato</hi>'s Politiques then <hi>Ariſtotles. Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>
alſo an <hi>Emperour,</hi> as unlimited as any, confeſſing
himſelf born for his <hi>Countrey,</hi> not for <hi>Himſelf,</hi> made
theſe words good: <hi>Ita ſe Rempublicam geſturum, ut ſciret
populi rem eſſe non Propriam. Paſtor populi non ſui-ipſius,
ſed ſubditorum quaerit commodum, &amp; Officio ſuo ſemper fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur
utilitati conſulens &amp; ſocietati.</hi> I wiſh a <hi>Chriſtian</hi>
had ſpoke this, or that no <hi>Chriſtian</hi> did diſapprove it;
it were vain to purſue this further. Howſoever, I
deny not the due Operation of a <hi>juſt, totall,</hi> and <hi>unmixt</hi>
Conqueſt (though I ſcarce ever read of any ſuch) for
<hi>Conquerors</hi> coming in by Violence, cannot be aſſured in
a ſtrange Nation, without ſome Violence at firſt, but
that which is <hi>Policy</hi> before Eſtabliſhment, is not <hi>Juſtice</hi>
after it. And ſecondly, Though <hi>Victors</hi> ought not to
induce any Conditions contrary to Gods Law, or
grievous to the Conquered; yet perhaps they are not
bound to reſtore all former extraordinary Immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
in ſo ample a manner as they were before enjoyed.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:123007:14"/>
And thirdly, <hi>Conqueſts</hi> have great force in taking away
Competitions, and extinguiſhing concurrent pretence
of Titles; and as to the Crown it ſelf, they cut off all
independency, as is now apparant in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
parts of <hi>England</hi> now incorporated, and conſolid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated
into one numericall <hi>Maſſe</hi> thereby. But they
are moſt wretched <hi>Politicians</hi> that ground upon <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi>
(be it rightfull, totall, and without Conditions
granted by the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> or contracted by the <hi>Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi>
or not) a Right of deſtroying and inthralling, and
an exemption from all Law for the preſent: And yet
they which by Conqueſt aboliſh all Rights of the
People, and that beyond all Power of Reſtitution for
the future are further oppoſers of truth, and Enemies
to Mankinde. Had the Conqueſts of <hi>England</hi> and
<hi>Ireland</hi> at firſt been juſt over the whole Nations, and
that without all Pactions of Grace (as they were not)
and without all Conſent of the People; yet that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
all ſubſequent Oathes and Grants of our Kings,
and Agreements of the Nations ſhould be utterly
voyd, and all the Laws of God and Nature of no Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
but that our Kings are left ſtill to their own Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretions,
and Arbitrary, Abſoute Prerogatives is an
inference to be wondered at amongſt Rationall Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that qualifies <hi>Ireland</hi> for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is,
That the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion is ſo farre dilated and
known there. The well-wiſhers of <hi>Popery</hi> pretend
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:123007:14"/>
for the upholding of their own blinde ſuperſtition,
<hi>That Conſcience is not to be forced, and that without Bloody
force Papiſts are not to be reduced.</hi> This weak Pretence
hath done unſpeakable Miſchief both in <hi>England,</hi> and
<hi>Ireland</hi> (as appears this day by our unnaturall Wars)
and we have been not onely very ignorant, but very
wicked, I fear, and very guilty in admitting it. That
force which borders upon Cruelty is not to be uſed, I
would not that it ſhould be done to <hi>Babel</hi> by way of
Retaliation, as <hi>Babel</hi> hath done to us; But certainly
<hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are reſponſible for all thoſe ſouls, whom
they may reclaim by <hi>Politique</hi> ſeverity, and do not;
and we ſee what effects <hi>Politique</hi> ſeverity hath produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
in <hi>Denmarke, Sweden, Scotland, &amp;c.</hi> without effuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of blood; and he that will deny the ſame, that it
might have been as effectuall in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi>
muſt alleadge ſome ſtrange or unexpected Reaſon.
'Tis not ſo difficult to draw from falſity, as from truth,
to make a <hi>Turk</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> as a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> a <hi>Turk.</hi> And as
for the Populacy of any Nation, we know they are to
be driven by Shoals, almoſt into any Religion, where
the Magiſtrate, and Spirituall Miniſter co-operate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether:
The frequent and ſuddain Converſions, and
Perverſions of ſundry Nations in all Ages, teſtifie this
to be a matter of no great difficulty. And as for ſome
few of the more knowing and Conſcientious ſort, the
meer want of a Toleration, their own Paucity (if ſome
other Encouragement be not ſupplyed by Conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:123007:15"/>
&amp;c.) in ſome reaſonable time would wear them
out. And if the breeding of their children within
theſe laſt 60 yeers had not been omitted; nay, if coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
under hand had not been afforded to <hi>Papiſts,</hi>
theſe Wars had never happened: But now things ſo
ſtanding, 'tis juſt in <hi>God</hi> that <hi>Papiſts</hi> be ſo cruell to Us
in <hi>Temporalls,</hi> as we have been to Them in <hi>Spiritualls.</hi>
'Twere Advantagious for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> that we were All of
<hi>One,</hi> but more eſpecially of the true, pious, charitable
<hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> And though this Advantage
hath been hitherto neglected, yet ſtill we have Power
enough, by the Grace of God, to provide better for
the future.</p>
            <p>The third help to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is, That Nature hath pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
both our Iſlands like twins in a remote Angle of
the World; and as if ſhe intended more to eſtrange
<hi>Ireland</hi> then <hi>England,</hi> ſhe hath further ſeated her from
the Commerce of forraigne Nations; and it may be
ſuppoſed, that they are both divorced from <hi>Others,</hi>
that they may be wedded to <hi>Themſelves.</hi> And ſurely
as <hi>Ireland</hi>'s love and vicinity is very uſefull unto <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
ſo <hi>Englands</hi> cheriſhing fidelity muſt needs be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally
neceſſary unto <hi>Ireland.</hi> Did the <hi>Iriſh</hi> depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Protection of <hi>Spain,</hi> or ſome other diſtant
Countrey to guard them from the Forces and <hi>Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do's</hi>
of <hi>England,</hi> that Protection could not but coſt them
very dear; for beſides the Calamities of endleſſe War,
in a Nation ſo intermingled, the very Burdens of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:123007:15"/>
would perhaps prove as grievous, as the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters
of their Aſſaylants. <hi>Flanders</hi> now by its
ſubjection to <hi>Spain,</hi> is made the Theatre of affliction,
almoſt beyond hope of Redreſſe; and though ſhe
draw from <hi>Spain</hi> many Millions for her defence, yet
without doubt ſhe is more wretched by ſerving <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi>
then <hi>Philip</hi> is weakned by ſupporting her.</p>
            <p>It is fourthly probable, that both Nations were an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently
deſcended from the ſame originall Plantations
and Colonies, and if the name of <hi>Hiberno-Britaines</hi>
may not be applyed to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> as <hi>Cambro-Britaines</hi> is
to the <hi>Welſh;</hi> yet now <hi>Scottiſh, Engliſh, Welſh,</hi> and the
mixt <hi>Iriſh</hi> being ſo indifferently blended in <hi>Ireland,</hi>
and congregated (as it were) at a generall determinate
<hi>Randevouz,</hi> and the ſame Language being ſo general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
current, and the temperature of the <hi>Clime,</hi> and the
Congruity of the Antient Natives in diſpoſition ſo
inclining to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> it muſt be wilfull neglect in Us,
if we do not cloſe yet more amiably together.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, In Laws, Cuſtomes, and Conſtitutions for
Peace and War, there are lively Reſemblances.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Facies non una duabus,</l>
               <l>Nec diverſa tamen; qualem decet eſſe ſororum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Nay if there be not altogether the ſame Lineaments
in both, yet there is more then a Siſterly correſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Though ſome execrable Offices have of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:123007:16"/>
late been done in <hi>Ireland</hi> againſt our Nation, yet we
muſt account that Quarrell to be <hi>Religious,</hi> not <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall;</hi>
for we ſee they have not ſpared the <hi>Scots;</hi> they
have not ſpared the <hi>Engliſh Iriſh;</hi> they have been cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell
to all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> of what Countrey ſoever. The
ſame <hi>Whoriſh Inchantreſſe</hi> alſo, which is now bloody in
<hi>Ireland,</hi> hath ever been ſo in all Countryes: the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
characters her <hi>by making her ſelf drunk with the blood
of the Saints, and dipping her Garments in the ſame Dye.</hi>
The ſame falſe Religion hath formerly made <hi>England</hi>
flame with mercileſſe Executions, and <hi>Spain</hi> grone un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
Diabolicall Tortures, and <hi>France</hi> ſwim in inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
Maſſacres.</p>
            <q>Quae Regio in Terris, Noſtri non plena cruoris?</q>
            <p>Let Cruelty be the certain <hi>Teſt</hi> of falſe religion, and
let <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all Nations abide the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
of the ſame. For <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are ſo farre from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying
their known Enemies, that they are cruell to
themſelves in ſparing, where they hope leſſe of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ſpared. <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are not bound alwayes from
doing, as they have been done to by their enemies, or
from diſabling and repreſſing future Malice in their
enemies; yet <hi>Ireland</hi> is a witneſſe this day, that they
are more prone to favour unappeaſable foes, then to
prevent the moſt horrid treaſons. But I leave this as
remediable hereafter. As for the ſeparation and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion
of that Sea, which runs betwixt <hi>England,</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:123007:16"/>
               <hi>Ireland,</hi> I conceive it to be no conſiderable hinderance
of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> for we ſee <hi>Venice,</hi> and <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Countries by the Art and happineſſe of juſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
love and embrace at a further diſtance,
though other People are alſo interjacent, as are not
here. And if any other heart-burning or diſtaſte
have happened of late betwixt the Nations, by Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
or Miſ-government (as perhaps hath befallen as
eminently amongſt our ſelves) the Redreſſe and Cure
thereof will not be hopeleſſe.</p>
            <p>3. I come now to my <hi>Overture</hi> it ſelf; whereby fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> may be promoted and confirmed amongſt
us. That <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>State</hi> which ſhall moſt equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
diffuſe, and breath abroad into all Nations govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
under the ſame Scepter, the ſelf-ſame Meaſure of
right and benefit, ſhall be moſt effectuall and vertuous
to unite thoſe Nations. Now it ſeems to me, that ſuch
an <hi>Ordinance</hi> is now wanting in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and
<hi>Ireland,</hi> and yet that nevertheleſſe it is not difficult to
be framed and reduced into Act. In <hi>England</hi> there
are divers <hi>Courts of Iuſtice,</hi> and <hi>Councells of State,</hi>
whereby Government riſeth from the <hi>Baſis</hi> to the
<hi>Pyramis,</hi> by a farre Symmetricall <hi>Conus;</hi> and there is
not any matter of concernment to the Crown of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
for which there is not a proper Place appointed,
and proper Perſons aſſigned to attend, and tranſact the
ſame for, and under, or together with the King. The
ſame Policy alſo is in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> for matters
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:123007:17"/>
peculiar to <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> but in <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
and <hi>Ireland</hi> for matters concerning all three
Kingdomes, or that remain in debate betwixt any
two of them, beſides the <hi>Kings</hi> ſole Breſt (thereby too
much over-burthened) there is not any other <hi>Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>
aſſiſtant, and common to all the Nations to which
the ſame may be committed. And yet in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
this <hi>Chaſma</hi> in Government is more irregular, and
of more dangerous Conſequence, being it concerns
Great Generall matters, and high Points, then a low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
defect would be, in buſineſſe of a more narrow and
private Nature; for if the <hi>King</hi> be ſerved and attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by ſuch Councellors ſo choſen and qualified as He
is <hi>Lord</hi> of our Kingdome, is it not more expedient,
that he have the ſame Service and Aſſiſtance as He is
<hi>Lord</hi> of three Kingdoms? Some few yeers ſince, ſome
of the <hi>Kings</hi> Subjects under an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Commiſſion,
and others under a <hi>Scottiſh,</hi> met it <hi>Greenland</hi> to fiſh, and
upon a Qneſtion of their ſeverall Grants blood was
drawn, and force carryed it for the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> out of this
fire a Nationall flame might have been kindled, and
till this day the blood remains unexpiated, and the
Controverſie undertermined. Not long ſince alſo the
<hi>King</hi> was deeply incenſed againſt the whole <hi>Scottiſh</hi>
Nation, and the <hi>Scots</hi> complayned of Violations to
them offered. In this unhappy <hi>Diſpute</hi> the <hi>King</hi> ſo
engaged, was the ſole <hi>Judge;</hi> and yet the <hi>Engliſh</hi> being
neither <hi>Parties</hi> nor <hi>Judges,</hi> nor having any Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:123007:17"/>
or witneſſes, or otherwiſe, were to incurre gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
danger of Ruine, to decide this with their ſwords.
Although in all private Suits and Queſtions of <hi>Right</hi>
betwixt the King and any Vaſſall of any one of His
Kingdoms, the King ever referreth Himſelf (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to his Oath) to qualified and indifferent ſworn
Judges, yet here the lives of Millions being endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and the Honours of Nations engaged, the <hi>King</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
by the Sword muſt give judgement. That which
then happened to <hi>Scotland</hi> upon as ſmall a ground, may
perhaps hereafter become the caſe of <hi>England,</hi> and (for
ought I know) is now happened to <hi>Ireland.</hi> But to
what reaſon or equity can this ſeem commenſurate,
that whole Nations ſhould be worſe provided for in
points of judgement, then the pooreſt Members of
each Nation. And as it is in <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> and <hi>Pleas</hi>
of the Crown, ſo it is alſo in matters of <hi>Honour,</hi> and
Acts of <hi>State,</hi> 'tis injurious and repugnant to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi>
that any one Nation ſhould be debarred from an Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
of Priviledge, or Advantage, or intereſt in the
King and His moſt generall Actions and Councells.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Reſult</hi> then is, That to make <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> perfect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
the three Nations ſome <hi>Common Court</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi>
and <hi>Councell of State</hi> muſt be erected, to which each Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
or any Member of each Nation, in a Nationall
difference, may have recourſe with equall Confidence
for the redreſſing of all <hi>Injuries,</hi> for the deciding of all
<hi>Controverſies,</hi> for the preventing of all <hi>Dangers,</hi> for the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:123007:18"/>
removing of all <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> and for communicating of
all <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Court-Benefits,</hi> and for the tranſacting of all
matters of <hi>Generall concernment. Charles</hi> the eighth,
then made <hi>Brettaign</hi> One with <hi>France,</hi> when he level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
and equalized both in <hi>Parliament,</hi> poſſeſſing both
Nations One of Another, <hi>par my, &amp; par tout;</hi> for by
this means the ſame Crown overſhadowed and ſpread
its wings over Both, inveſting both with the ſame
Propriety in it ſelf. In the ſame manner alſo <hi>Wales</hi>
and <hi>England</hi> did Inter marry, and of two became One;
for there is no Burden of the Crown whereunto the
<hi>Engliſh-man</hi> is not now as lyable as the <hi>Welſh-man,</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
or immediately, nor no Priviledge of the
Crown whereunto the <hi>Welſh man</hi> is not equally inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled
with the <hi>Engliſh-man.</hi> The ſame muſt alſo be
brought to paſſe betwixt <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi>
or elſe the ſame perfection of Amity and Unity can
never be eſtabliſhed; and that can never be, but by the
ſame, or very like means. Where there is the ſame
<hi>Law</hi> to limit the <hi>Judge,</hi> and the ſame <hi>Judge</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce
and execute according to the true intent of that
<hi>Law,</hi> and where both conteſting <hi>Parties</hi> are equally
intereſſed, both in the <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Law,</hi> the judgement
is ever finall and ſatisfactory to Both; and thus it is
with <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> but thus it is not as yet with
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and therefore between <hi>England</hi>
and <hi>Wales</hi> there is no fear of Diviſion, but betwixt
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> there is; and the King alone
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:123007:18"/>
ought not in all Caſes to be both the <hi>Iudge</hi> and the <hi>Law,</hi>
or can fully ſatisfie all; for the <hi>King</hi> may have more
neer Naturall relation to one Kingdom then another,
and by other reſpects more by as't to favour the one
Kingdom then another, &amp; without aſſiſtance he is not
competent for all things. And therefore the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
of that Aſſiſtance that it be equall and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall,
and truſted by all, is of great and weighty mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
And this is true in matters of <hi>State,</hi> where no
<hi>Law</hi> is written, but in matters of <hi>Right,</hi> where <hi>Laws</hi> are
as requiſite almoſt as <hi>Iudges,</hi> it is neceſſary that both
<hi>Partyes</hi> be as fully aſſured in the <hi>Laws</hi> which are to
regulate the <hi>Iudges,</hi> as the <hi>Iudges</hi> which are to enlive the
<hi>Laws.</hi> And this cannot be, unleſſe all our <hi>three Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>
have equall Conſent and concurrence in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
to ſit as <hi>Iudges,</hi> and to paſſe <hi>Laws,</hi> or to convene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatively
and vertually in ſome leſſe <hi>Court</hi> and
<hi>Councell,</hi> branching (as it were) out of the <hi>Parliament,</hi>
ſeverall, and approaching alſo in power as neer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
as may be. <hi>Nationall Parliaments</hi> ſhall ſtill
move in their proper Orbs, taking Cognizance of all
particular Nationall Affairs, and this new erected <hi>Seat</hi>
or <hi>Table,</hi> though it may have much of <hi>Parliamentary</hi>
vigour in it, eſpecially in the vacancy of <hi>Parliaments,</hi>
as to Caſes of Generall Conſequence; yet it ſhall have
no <hi>Iuriſdiction</hi> at all in meer <hi>Nationall Expedients.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this means (as I conceive) the <hi>Three Kingdomes</hi>
ſhall be contempered into <hi>One</hi> indiviſible <hi>Monarchy,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:123007:19"/>
and be made One ſolid Naturall Body, and ſuch <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi>
entertayned as ſhall be to the Advantage of all three
Nations, and to the diſadvantage of no One; ſuch as
ſhall diſtribute all <hi>Priviledges</hi> equally to be enjoyed,
and all <hi>ſervices</hi> equally to be born, and leave behinde
no ſhew of <hi>inequality</hi> to be a ground of envie or diſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.
'Tis true, the <hi>King</hi> cannot be corporally preſent
in all the Nations at once, but whatſoever the benefit
of a <hi>Royall Court</hi> may be, the diſpoſing of that is left Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary
to the <hi>King;</hi> and this may ſeem perhaps great
Inequality to thoſe Nations which have leſſe attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
in them. The meer Reſidence of a <hi>Prince,</hi> if it be
a Commodity, it goes many times accompanied with
divers great Diſcommodities; and as the <hi>Sun,</hi> though
it be the moſt auſpicious of all Celeſtiall Bodies, yet it
doth not alwayes inrich thoſe Tracts of Earth moſt,
which it moſt violently heats with its torrid perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular
beams: ſo neither doth the Majeſticall Court
of a <hi>King</hi> alwayes make thoſe Territories moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py,
which enjoy it at leaſt Diſtance. But be this Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit
what it will, in this, <hi>England</hi> intruſts as much to
the Kings meer Diſcretion, as either <hi>Scotland</hi> or <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
knowing that without unnaturall force he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be reſtrained in it, nor without cutting <hi>Monarchy</hi>
into Mammocks, that all Countries or Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
can be thus ſatisfied; and preſuming that no <hi>King</hi>
will ever withdraw Himſelf where he may be moſt
uſefull, or ſo confine His Perſon to one Place, as that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:123007:19"/>
His influence ſhall be wanting in any part of His Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions,
no Umbrage can be taken of Emulation in
this. And as for all other things, <hi>Equality,</hi> that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable
<hi>Centre</hi> of the Univerſe, and <hi>Impartiality,</hi> that
bleſſed <hi>Ballance</hi> of Government, ſhall be moſt exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and Mathematically purſued in this new erected
<hi>Synedrion;</hi> the <hi>Heptarchy</hi> of <hi>England</hi> ſhall not be more
aboliſhed then the <hi>Tritarchy</hi> of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and
<hi>Ireland.</hi> I need not therefore ſay any more of this <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
Junio,</hi> or <hi>Court</hi> it ſelf, or of the end for which it
is ſo convocated, 'tis ſufficient that I have fancyed it
to be equally choſen out of all the <hi>Three Nations,</hi> for
the making them into <hi>One</hi> by an equall diſpenſation
of all <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Priviledges,</hi> and an exact Diſtribution
of <hi>Burdens</hi> and <hi>Chaſtiſements.</hi> I ſhall onely now adde
ſomthing of ſome <hi>Requiſites,</hi> and <hi>Qualifications</hi> due to it.</p>
            <p>That this Counſell may be effectuall for thoſe ends
for which it is ordained, all Parties ſhould equally
confide in it, for which Purpoſe it muſt be dependent
upon the <hi>King,</hi> as <hi>Parliaments</hi> now are, and alſo be
choſen equally out of all Three Nations by <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
and in each Nation of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> or
ſeverall Ranks in number proportioned for their
mutuall Aſſurance. <hi>For Example,</hi> I will ſuppoſe a
<hi>Trienniall Parliament</hi> in each Nation ſetled, and the
ſame <hi>Parliament</hi> to nominate a convenient number in
each Nation for their own Order to be indued with
power as their ſtanding <hi>Committees,</hi> to continue from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:123007:20"/>
one <hi>Parliament</hi> to another, and no longer, unleſſe for
an Honour and Teſtimony of Publique Confidence
they be then longer continued. I will wiſh alſo, that
in all Caſes nothing be determined by fewer then one
of the <hi>Nobility,</hi> and two or three of the <hi>Commonalty</hi> of
each Nation, and that Plurality of Votes in groſſe, may
not carry any thing but Plurality of Kingdoms. And
if any high difficulty ariſe betwixt Kingdome and
Kingdom, let it be reſerved for further Reſolution in
all three <hi>Parliaments.</hi> And if it happen that there be
not one of the <hi>Nobility,</hi> or two or three of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty</hi>
ſurviving from <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>Parliament,</hi> then
the King to chuſe and ſupply that Temporary fail.
Conſidering it alſo as a <hi>Councell of State,</hi> Let it aſſiſt the
King in all <hi>Embaſſages,</hi> and Publique Treaties, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
Him ſuperintend all forraigne Plantations and
Myſteries of Trade. Let it have a confined Power
to mingle the Nations in Blood by Inter-marriages, to
conform them in Language, Manners, and Religion,
and to reward all Nationall offices of friendſhip, and
to puniſh all Publike Enmities; and let it's authority
be greater then that of the <hi>Privy Councell.</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering
it as a <hi>Court of Juſtice,</hi> Let it hold Cognizance
of all Publique Quarrells and Diviſions; Let it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
all Incendiaries, declaring themſelves either by
words or Actions; Let it uphold all Orders of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality,
and cut off all oppoſers of the ſame. And
for this purpoſe let it obtain a <hi>Iuriſdiction</hi> in ſuch Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:123007:20"/>
Nationall Cauſes, equall at leaſt to that of the
<hi>Kings Bench.</hi> And that they may the better eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh
<hi>Generall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> by preventing and removing all
Occaſions of Diviſion and Emulation, and by ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying
and corroborating the ſureſt Nerves of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
Affection and Correſpondence, Let the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
of theſe <hi>grand Councellors</hi> be ſacred, their
Maintenance Honourable, at the Charge of their
reſpective States, and let ſeverall Parliaments
derive or conſigne Power to them, and demand Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
from them, as Occaſion ſhall require. Let the
place of their Reſidence, and the times of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening
be deſigned by the King, as reaſon of State
ſhall bear, and let them attend His Pleaſure as the
<hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>Councell,</hi> and as the Judges of the
<hi>Kings Bench</hi> now do. Let all Warres, eſpecially
with forraign States, be undertaken by their Advice;
And let the Levies of Men, Money, and Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition
be proportioned in all the three Kingdoms by
their Diſcretion, and let all Truces and Leagues be
made and preſerved as they ſhall counſel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To conclude,</hi> My hope is that by ſome ſuch whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
Conſtitution <hi>Ireland</hi> may be better reduced, and
the like <hi>Rebellions</hi> for the future prevented, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
other States, by the Harmony of our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi>
invited into an <hi>Incorporation</hi> with us, till we all
grow up into a Body equall, and able to poyſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:123007:21"/>
with any State now in <hi>Europe.</hi> But I leave the further
Maturation of this <hi>Overture</hi> to men of profounder
knowledge, and ſtronger judgements.</p>
            <p>Let the <hi>Motto</hi> of King <hi>James</hi> be never forgotten,</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Faciam Eos in Gentem Vnam.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
