<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An elegie upon the death of the right Honourable &amp; most renowned, Robert Devereux Earle of Essex and Ewe, Viscount Hereford, Lord Ferrers of Chartley, Bourchier Lovaine, late Generall of the Forces of the Parliament of England, who deceased the 14. of September, 1646.</title>
            <author>Rowland, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92027</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2073</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.10[97]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210643</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869421</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869421</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162630</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A92027)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162630)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 246:669f10[97])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An elegie upon the death of the right Honourable &amp; most renowned, Robert Devereux Earle of Essex and Ewe, Viscount Hereford, Lord Ferrers of Chartley, Bourchier Lovaine, late Generall of the Forces of the Parliament of England, who deceased the 14. of September, 1646.</title>
                  <author>Rowland, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Austin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 23.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Essex, Robert Devereux, --  Earl of, 1591-1646 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Elegiac poetry, English.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:162630:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <head>An Elegie upon the death of the right Honourable &amp; moſt renowned,
<hi>ROBERT DEVERE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>X,</hi> Earle of <hi>ESSEX</hi> and <hi>Ewe,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Hereford,</hi> Lord <hi>Ferrers of Chartley,</hi>
               <hi>Bourchier</hi> and <hi>Lovaine,</hi> late GENERALL of the Forces of the PARLIAMENT of <hi>England,</hi>
who deceaſed the 14. of <hi>September,</hi> 1646.</head>
            <l>CAn Englands noble Champion [ESSEX] die?</l>
            <l>That kept us ſafe from hoſtile Tyrannie)</l>
            <l>Can he (I ſay) from us to's duſt depart,</l>
            <l>(Ne're to returne) and we not lay't to heart?</l>
            <l>Can we (whoſe <hi>Shield</hi> he was) not ſenſibly</l>
            <l>Bewaile our loſſe of him with weeping eye?</l>
            <l>O Heavens forbid! unworthy Nation we,</l>
            <l>Should we of his great worth unmindfull be.</l>
            <l>Though he's extinct, yet let Poſterity</l>
            <l>Keep up his name, that did (our Liberty</l>
            <l>Safely for us and them to keep) expoſe</l>
            <l>Himſelfe, unſafely, to the rage of Foes.</l>
            <l>He prick'd the timpany of their great pride,</l>
            <l>Teaching refluxes to the flowing-tide</l>
            <l>Of thoſe that fought ſo for Prerogative;</l>
            <l>Therefore, (though He be dead) His Name will live.</l>
            <l>He firſt did lay our preſent <hi>Strengths</hi> foundation,</l>
            <l>(Which proſpers well) t' unſlave our Britiſh Nation,</l>
            <l>And oft did hazard's life in bloody fight,</l>
            <l>Yet knew no quarrell but the publike right,</l>
            <l>For which he forc't Foes fortitude to flight:</l>
            <l>Therefore we grieve his Obſequie to write.</l>
            <l>He that the Victor was, is now the Prize:</l>
            <l>For he which gat us many Victories,</l>
            <l>Is vanquiſhed himſelfe, and forc't to lye</l>
            <l>At feet of death, who hath the victory.</l>
            <l>"See then that Proweſſe, though it purchaſe praiſe,</l>
            <l>"Purchaſe it cannot health, or length of daies.</l>
            <l>"Both great, and good, yea valiant men muſt die,</l>
            <l>"When death (impartiall) ſtrikes them, they muſt lie</l>
            <l>"In duſt: the paſſing bell will tole for them,</l>
            <l>"That rang, erewhile, the Beggars <hi>Requiem.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>"The way he's gone, is not a way untrod,</l>
            <l>"But is decreed by the eternall God,</l>
            <l>"To be the way, that ev'ry man muſt go:</l>
            <l>"Aſwell a Friend, as he that is a Foe.</l>
            <l>"Death takes excize of all, and his is paid,</l>
            <l>"His ſoul's at's place, his bodie's to be laid</l>
            <l>"Where they in their beſt judgments do think fit,</l>
            <l>"Who with what elſe he left, have right to it.</l>
            <l>But is there not more in good ESSEX'S death</l>
            <l>Then yet I've ſaid? let's feare he's gone from th'earth</l>
            <l>As one we were unworthy of: becauſe</l>
            <l>Our ſinnes againſt Gods ſin-forbidding Lawes</l>
            <l>Have th' Almighty incens'd and made him frown,</l>
            <l>And in his wrath againſt us, to caſt down</l>
            <l>This ſo great Pillar, that he might be ſet</l>
            <l>In better place, and there more glory get,</l>
            <l>For ſins (we know) bring ſorrowes back with fears.</l>
            <l>And we may now lye pickl'd up in tears,</l>
            <l>For that our Patriots ſo faſt do dye</l>
            <l>Before our peace be made up perfectly.</l>
            <l>"Great God! let thy offended wrath ſurceaſe,</l>
            <l>"Behold thy people, ſend thy people peace:</l>
            <l>"Turn not ſo faſt our Nobles into duſt:</l>
            <l>"Be mercifull (dear God) as well as juſt.</l>
            <l>"If thou proceed to do as thou'ſt begun,</l>
            <l>"We ſhall be droſſe when all the gold is gone.</l>
            <l>"'Tis thou, 'tis thou alone, didſt ſend this Griefe,</l>
            <l>"'Tis thou, 'tis thou alone muſt ſend relieſe.</l>
            <l>"O then recruit our loſſe, increaſe our friends;</l>
            <l>"And ſo for what thou'ſt done make us amends.</l>
            <l>"To thee alone our Sorrowes do appeale,</l>
            <l>"<hi>Earth</hi> hath no wound too hard for <hi>Heaven</hi> to heale.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Rowland.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <head>AN EPITAPH
FOR
HIS TOMBE.</head>
            <l>ALL you who paſſe here by draw neere;</l>
            <l>And with your tears bedew what's here.</l>
            <l>For they've as marble eyes as hearts,</l>
            <l>That cannot weep a tear in parts,</l>
            <l>But, like dull Stoicks, quite forbeare,</l>
            <l>When they do ſee, and read, or heare,</l>
            <l>Who lies herein: that <hi>ESSEX</hi> is</l>
            <l>The man, an Earle renown'd by his</l>
            <l>Moſt noble birth: whoſe father Queene</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Eliza</hi> had in great eſteeme.</l>
            <l>And he himſelfe, by <hi>Parliament,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To b'Englands <hi>Generall</hi> had conſent,</l>
            <l>And fought our Battells. Now he's dead,</l>
            <l>Do not you rudely o're Him tread,</l>
            <l>Who hath So ſtout a Champion prov'd,</l>
            <l>And was therefore So greatly lov'd,</l>
            <l>That <hi>Fame</hi> hath his victorious browes</l>
            <l>Oft duly crown'd with Lawrell boughs.</l>
            <l>Who then to grieve will ſpare the coſt,</l>
            <l>That <hi>England</hi> ſuch a <hi>Peere</hi> hath loſt?</l>
            <l>And that no more of that ſame Blood</l>
            <l>Is left, to do England more good.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Rowland.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>AEtatis Suae 56</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A MOVRNEFVLL CLOVD</hi>
Ouer vaylinge the face of England for the sorrowfull
death of his Exelence Robert Deuourux Earle of Eſsex and Ewe Vicout
Herryford Lord Ferreres of Chartley Boucher and Louaine Lord General
of all the Parlaments forces, &amp; and dyed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 24 of September 1646.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>BASIS VIRTVTVM CONSTANTIA</p>
                     <figDesc>depiction of tomb</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Hîc jacet in tumulo, praeclaro Sanguine natus;
<hi>ROBERTUS DAVEREUX,</hi> Miles fortiſsimus Armis.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="epitaph">
            <head>EPITAPHIUM
in obitum
ROBERTI DEVEREUX,
Nobiliſsimi &amp; Illuſtriſsimi
ESSEXIAE COMITIS.</head>
            <l>ESSEX Caſtellum Patriae, fortiſſimus HECTOR,</l>
            <l>Belligerans validè, generoſo Stemmate natus,</l>
            <l>CIVIB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S &amp; murus, necnon tutela COLONIS,</l>
            <l>Bellonae Conjux armatos duxit apertè,</l>
            <l>Et Patriae fixus, Regi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> fidelis in ARMIS,</l>
            <l>Candida Magnificis floruerunt cuncta potenti,</l>
            <l>INVICT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, ſtabilis, necnon quo juſtior ALTER</l>
            <l>Haud Pietate fuit, nec Bello Major &amp; Armis.</l>
            <l>Vota, proces, lachrymas, jam deſine (Candide Lector,)</l>
            <l>Invito ſcelere, ac fortuna repoſuit Altis:</l>
            <l>Parce tuis lachrymis, donârunt Numina CAELOS:</l>
            <l>Flebilis in tumulo, multi doluere Colores.</l>
            <div type="epilogue">
               <head>Epilogus.</head>
               <l>Coeli animam, terrae Corpus, forteſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dolorem,</l>
               <l>Et Mundus Nomen, clara<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> facta ferunt.</l>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>XIV. Calend. Novemb.
M.DC.IVL.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Tho. Thorne Londinenſis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Publiſhed according to Order.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London, <hi>Printed by</hi> R. Auſtin.
1646.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
