<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reasons of the Dissenting Brethren against the third proposition, concerning presbyterial government· Humbly presented.</title>
            <author>Westminster Assembly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92287</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E27_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209981</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868825</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868825</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121181</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A92287)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121181)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 5:E27[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reasons of the Dissenting Brethren against the third proposition, concerning presbyterial government· Humbly presented.</title>
                  <author>Westminster Assembly</author>
                  <author>Goodwin, Thomas, 1600-1680.</author>
                  <author>Westminster Assembly (1643-1652). Answer of the Assembly of Divines unto the reasons of the seven Dissenting Brethren, against the proposition of divers congregations being united under one Presbyteriall government.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.M. for Ralph Smith at the Bible in Corne-Hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on F1r: Tho. Goodwin [and six others].</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary order to print.</note>
                  <note>"The answer of the Assembly of Divines unto the reasons of the seven Dissenting Brethren, against the proposition of divers congregations being united under one presbyteriall government" has separate title page dated 1644; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "about feb: 5th 1644"; the 5 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Westminster Assembly (1643-1652)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121181:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REASONS OF THE Diſſenting Brethren againſt the <hi>Third Propoſition,</hi> CONCERNING PRESBYTERIAL GOVERNMENT.</p>
            <p>Humbly preſented.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Ralph Smith</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Corne-Hill.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:121181:2"/>
            <head>Die Lunae, 23. Decemb. 1644.</head>
            <p>ORdered by the <hi>Commons</hi> aſſembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, That three hundred and no more, of <hi>The Reaſons of the diſſenting Brethren againſt the third Propoſition touching Presbyteriall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and <hi>The Anſwer and Solution of the Aſſembly to the ſaid Reaſons,</hi> be forthwith Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; And that the care of the exact Printing thereof be referred to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Byfield:</hi> And the Printer is injoyned (at his perill) not to Print more then Three hundred of them.</p>
            <p>It is further Ordered, That no man preſume to Re-print, Divulge or Publiſh the ſaid <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> and <hi>Anſwers,</hi> or any part of them, till fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther order be taken herein by either or both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:121181:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:121181:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:121181:3"/>
            <head>REASONS againſt the <hi>Third Propoſition,</hi> concerning Presbyteriall Government, and the Proofes thereof: <hi>Viz.</hi> The Scripture holds forth, that many particular Congregations may be under one Presbyteriall Governement. <hi>Humbly Preſented.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>If many Congregations having all Elders already affixed reſpectively unto them, may be under a Presbyteriall government: Then all thoſe Elders must ſuſtaine a ſpeciall relation of Elders to all the people of thoſe Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations as one Church and to every one as a Member thereof.</item>
                     <item>But for a company of ſuch Elders already affixed, &amp;c. to ſustaine ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, carries with it ſo great and manifold incongruities, and inconſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, with what the Scripture ſpeaks of Elders in their relation to a Church committed to them, and likewiſe with the Principles of the Reformed Churches themſelves, as cannot be admitted.</item>
                     <item>And therefore ſuch a Government may not be.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <div type="major_proposition">
               <head>The firſt Propoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat according to the Scriptures, ſuch a Presbyteriall Government neceſſarily drawes ſuch a ſpeciall relation, is evinced by parts thus.</p>
               <p>1. They muſt have the relation of Elders to all and every one of the Members; for Church and Elders are Relatives. And the Argument for the Presbyteriall government is taken by the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall Divines from this; That many Congregations in Scripture, are made one Church, and the Elders thereof Elders of that Church.</p>
               <p>2. That relation they have, muſt be a more ſpeciall relation, as is evident from the practiſe and principles of this government. For when the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Shires are divided into ſeverall Presbyteries or Deanries, the Elders (though Neighbours) of a bordering Presbyterie, intermeddle not with the Congregations under another Presbyterie, and yet Neighbour Elders. It is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121181:4"/>
therefore a ſpeciall relation puts the difference, that thoſe of theſe Presbyteries do judge the Congregations under them, as having a ſpeciall relation to them, ſuch as not to other Congregations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="minor_proposition">
               <head>The minor Propoſition.</head>
               <p>For the proofe of which, we preſent theſe incongruities as follow.</p>
               <p>Firſt, this breeds many incongruous diſproportions to the Order ſet by Chriſt, about the Officers of the Church.</p>
               <p>1. To extend a Paſtors power of ordinary ruling beyond the extent of his ordinary teaching, is againſt the order which Chriſt hath ſet (and all extent of power muſt as well have an Inſtitution of Chriſt, as the power or office it ſelfe, the difference of Evangeliſts and ordinary Paſtors lay in extent of power,) but the extent of a Paſtors ordinary ruling power, is but to that Flock as his whole Flock which he is able to feed. The firſt <hi>Propoſition</hi> is confirmed, firſt by Scripture, ſecondly by Reaſon.</p>
               <p>Firſt by Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> Chap. 20. Verſe 28. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves and to all the flock over the which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Overſeers to feed the flock of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own blood.</hi> Whence firſt we ſee the ſpeciall limitation of their extenſive power and relation [<hi>to a flock</hi>] and [<hi>all in that flock</hi>] is by the Holy Ghoſt, and not by man, and therefore is not to be extended by man, further then the Holy Ghoſt hath appointed.</p>
               <p>2. The extent of that relation <hi>to that flock, and the whole flock they feed,</hi> and <hi>to feed all that flock alike.</hi> And if they be preaching Elders, then to feed by preaching, and therefore are Overſeers to them to feed them, and this becauſe they feed them.</p>
               <p>3. He ſpeaks to preaching Elders eſpecially, that feed by doctrine: for he propounds his own example to them, Verſe 20. <hi>That he had revealed the whole counſell of God.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> ſeconds <hi>Paul</hi> in this, 1 <hi>Peter,</hi> Chap. 5. Verſe 2. <hi>Feed the flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof. The flock <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> among you:</hi> is that flock any of them had relation to as his flock reſpectively. <hi>Peter</hi> here writing unto the Churches in ſeverall Nations Chap. 1. Verſe 1. whereas in <hi>Acts</hi> 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Verſe 28. the charge is to the particular El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Epheſus</hi> to that whole flock; therefore that note of reſpectiveneſſe is here put <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> among you: that is, that flock which reſpectively belongs to you, as <hi>Coloſſians</hi> Chap. 1. Verſe 17. <hi>Who is for you a faithfull Minister,</hi> that is, your proper Paſtor: So the flock <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is your ſeverall proper flocks that belong to you. And hereby it appears that their overſight is not extendible be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their feeding. Thus alſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. Verſe 7. <hi>Remember them that have the rule over you, and have ſpoken to you the word of God;</hi> which he ſpeaks of preaching Elders, and of ruling Elders (of whom he ſpeaks Verſe 17.) <hi>Obey
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121181:4"/>
them that have the rule over you, for they watch for your ſoules, as thoſe that muſt give an accompt.</hi> And whether theſe places note out two ſort of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Preaching Elders, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. and Ruling Elders, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. or but one ſort, and ſo but ſeverall acts of the ſame Office, however if but one, yet ſtill the ordinary rule over them was not farther extendible then their ordinary preaching; if two ſorts of Officers, they being Officers together in the ſame Church, if the Paſtors power of ruling extends no farther then his preaching, then the meere ruling Elders power, or his that is aſſiſtant to him, muſt extend no farther then the Paſtors alſo; this is the naturall obligation to obedience, and ſo is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſet the bounds of the extent of ordinary Church power. 'Tis one ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument uſed againſt Epiſcopall power, that they are inforced to obey him that ſpeakes not the word to them, nor watches over their ſoules; And this holds as well againſt theſe Presbyteriall Officers, when a man to be excommunicated comes before ſuch, if he ſayes I am not bound to obey you in ſuch authoritative way, nor doe I owe a ſubjection as to a power of cenſure in you, for many, yea moſt of you, never ſpake the word unto me, nor did watch over my ſoule; nay, perhaps the man can ſay, he never ſaw their faces afore.</p>
               <p>And it availes not to ſay that they may occaſionally preach; for take two places more, the 1 to the <hi>Theſ. chap. 5. ver.</hi> 12. ſpeaking of reſpect to their Officers, <hi>Know them that labour among you, and are over you in the Lord and admoniſh you:</hi> Theſe two <hi>labour,</hi> and <hi>are over you,</hi> are commenſurable; that is, who make it their calling to have the care of you, which the many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Elders in a common Presbyterie cannot. And labour, in what? <hi>Tim.</hi> Epiſt. 1. chap. 1. ver. 17. expounds it, <hi>That labour in the word and Doctrine: The Elders that rule well,</hi> are worthy of <hi>double honour, especially thoſe that labour in the word and Doctrine.</hi> And expound this latter known place, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Teaching Elders only, or ruling and teaching both (as the Reformed Churches doe) however it affords this to us; that the extent of ruling in either the one or the other, is but as large as teaching: And if it be meant of <hi>Teaching Elders</hi> only, that both rule and labour in the word and Doctrine, yet if they be limited in labouring in the word (as they are being fixed Paſtors to their own Congregations) then in ruling. And if it be meant of ruling Elders (as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from them) yet their ruling is but of the ſame extent, that the others la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring in the word is, and that is extended but to one Congregation.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, Reaſon is for this; For in a Paſtors Office in which Preaching and Ruling are joyned, yet his power of ruling flowes in him from, and is the adjunct of his power to preach, and to be ſure it is not extendible further; and however yet there is the ſame proportion of either, and then by juſt reaſon the extent of the Church which is the ſubject of his ordinary ruling cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended larger then what is the ordinary ſubject of his preaching, and ſo theſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121181:5"/>
relations are of equall limits; If a father hath the power of governing, as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then it is extendible only to thoſe he is a father to. And that a Paſtor hath his ordinary ruling power annexed to his ordinary power of preaching, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, If not upon this ground, then upon ſome other, not by any ſpeciall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty or Office, over and above this of preaching, for then he ſhould be ordained a ruling Elder over and above his being firſt a Preaching Elder as a new faculty given him, or by being made a Ruler firſt, and then this of preaching ſuperadded, as the Biſhops firſt made Deacons then Presbyters. But</p>
               <p>Secondly, All the keyes are given him at once, the keyes of ruling with the keyes of knowledge, the power of the ſtaffe intrinſecally followes, his being a Paſtor or Shepheard; and though the one is a power of meere order, namely that of Preaching, and that of his Ruling be a power of juriſdiction (to be exerciſed with others and not alone) yet ſtill his receiving power to joyne with others in thoſe acts of Rule of juriſdiction is from this his power of Order, and the ordinary extent of his authority therein, is extendible no farther then his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary call to preach. Yea</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The extent of the power of the Apoſtles themſelvs, in ruling in all the Churches was founded upon, and extendible with their commiſſion to preach in all Churches, and their very call and obligation being not to preach in a ſet fixed relation, as ordinary Paſtors calling is, but to all Churches in all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: Hence their power of ruling was anſwerable; It was their very call to be univerſall Paſtors, and therefore univerſall Rulers; yea and in reference to thoſe that are without, their authority of ruling was narrower in the extent of it then of their preaching. The Apoſtles might preach to Heathens, and their call was ſo to doe, to convert them, but they had not power to rule all men: <hi>what have I to doe to judge them that are without?</hi> But in this way of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall governement, though they alſo may occaſionally preach where they may not rule, yet the proportion of their ordinary ruling, is extended beyond the proportion of their ordinary preaching, which it was not in the Apoſtles themſelves.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It breeds an incongruous diſproportion between the Offices of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Preaching Elders compared among themſelves, for this Governement makes the Extent of the Ruling Elders Office and relation, to be larger then that of their Teachers or Paſtors; For the Paſtor, <hi>quâ Paſtor,</hi> is limited to his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation he is fixed to for the ordinary performance of his Office, as the Deacons alſo are; but the Ruling Elders Office, <hi>quâ Ruling Elder,</hi> is exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded over all theſe Congregations in this Presbyterie. The <hi>Ruling Elder</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes his Office in the higheſt perfection of it, as to admoniſh, excommunicate in all theſe Churches, but the Paſtors are limited in the higheſt work of their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121181:5"/>
Callings, Preaching being more excellent then <hi>Ruling,</hi> yea then baptizing unto one Congregation; That in the firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Tim. Chap. 5. Ver.</hi> 17. (interpret it as you will) juſtifies this.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It perverts the order and diſtinction of <hi>Teaching Elders,</hi> and meere <hi>Ruling Elders</hi> (as the reformed Churches call them) or Church Governours (as the Aſſembly) That whereas Chriſt hath made ſome Teaching Elders, and ſome Ruling Elders, and theſe diſtinct in this, that the Preaching Elders Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is to preach and rule, the Ruling Elders Office only to rule: this frame of Presbyteriall government, makes one perſon not only to doe both theſe works, (which in a particular Congregation every Paſtor doth) but formally to be both thoſe Offices, in reſpect of a double relation he doth ſuſteine, namely, a Paſtor to be a Preaching Elder to the Congregation where he is fixed, and a meere ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elder to the reſt of the Congregations of a Claſſicall Church: for it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, when a Paſtor in a particular Congregation is in this common Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, what ſort of Officer he is to that Presbyteriall Church? An Elder he is, becauſe he doth the work of an Elder; A Teaching Elder to that Church he is not, for to that whole Church <hi>he labours not in the word and Doctrine. Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy, Epiſt. 1. Chap. 5. ver.</hi> 17. Therefore a meere ruling Elder he muſt be, and ſo the ſame man beares two ſorts of Offices, and by this meanes there are two ſorts of meere ruling Elders, whereas in a particular Congregation, a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor though he rules, yet he ruleth as a Paſtor to that Congregation. And this diſorder and confuſion is further ſet out, in that, by this meanes the ſame Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer hath a full relation to one Church, and but halfe a relation to another, and cauſeth him to performe the whole of his Office to one Church (the particular Church) he hath relation to, and but the halfe thereof to the other.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, It makes an incongruous diſproportion between the Extent of the relation of thoſe two Offices of Elders and Deacons unto a Church. If the Scriptures had intended many Churches making one Church, and the Elders of thoſe many Churchers to have been Elders in common to thoſe Churches as one Church, then in like manner the Deacons of all thoſe Churches ſhould make up a common Deaconrie, and be Deacons in common unto all thoſe Churches in an ordinary way as the other are Elders: But this is contrary to the practiſe of the Reformed Churches, though ſubject to the Presbyteriall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, in which the Deacons have the ordinary relation of Deacons in no reſpect extended further then to a particular Congregation, nor doe they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Acts of that Office in an ordinary way to other Congregations, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to neighbour Congregations then to any other; much leſſe is there a common Deaconſhip of them all, and why ſhould not the later be erected over all thoſe Churches as one Church, as well as a common Elderſhip? eſpecially if in matters of this nature, <hi>par ratio</hi> ſhould carry it; every Church, <hi>quâ
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121181:6"/>
Church,</hi> being a body, hath relation to all its Officers as Organicall members thereof; So. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. and the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. And the Apoſtle writing to <hi>Philippi,</hi> a Church in a City, he writes to the Biſhops [<hi>the Elders</hi>] and the Deacons as both alike Officers of that Church. And <hi>Acts Chap.</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. The Deacons of the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (if there were many Congregations as our brethren ſuppoſe) were choſen by the whole multitude when gathered together by the 12. And therefore were Deacons of that whole Church as well as the Elders, Elders thereof. Now if the Deacons Office ſhould thus be extended to all the Congregations as the Elders is, then why ſhould not each Church be bound to bring contributions to the Deacons of each Church, and to be diſtributed in common? and ſo our purſes ſhould be ſubject to the Deacons in common, as farre as our perſons to the Elders in common, and they might challenge the ſame power in their Office over the one that the Elders doe over the other, and then alſo each Congregation were in an ordinary and ſtanding obligation bound to releeve all the Poore in thoſe Churches, as well as thoſe in their own Pariſhes, not only by the common law of Charity, but by virtue of ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of their being one Church, which relation in all theſe things, doth beget the like Obligation that it doth in government, and ſo all things of this nature ſhould be alike common to all and each, and there ſhould be a common Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury for this one great <hi>Diaconat</hi> Church, as we may in a paralell alluſion to that other name of Presbyteriall call it.</p>
               <p>A ſecond head of Incongruities and Inconſiſtencies which will follow upon it, are in the mutuall duties required, and that doe neceſſarily follow upon this ſtanding relation for a conſtant government of theſe Elders to all this people of theſe Churches, and of the people to theſe Elders.</p>
               <p>1. From the People to all theſe Elders, according unto what the Scripture ſpeakes of as due to ſtanding Elders, they owe at leaſt honour and eſteeme; yea, maintenance to all their Elders, whether thoſe that ordinarily rule them or preach to them, and they owe it for both, <hi>Tim.</hi> Epiſt. 1. Chap. 5. ver. 17. and 18. <hi>Let the Elders that rule well, be counted worthy of double honour, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe that labour in the word and Doctrine.</hi> Which honour is expreſſed by the Analogie of that law, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. not to <hi>muſle up the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the corne.</hi> And this is certainly due to Elders, for all, that is the work or Elders, whether performed apart or together by way of juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in a Presbyterie; And it cannot be denied, but that their conſtant ruling as in the Presbyterie, is one great part of the work of Elders, and ſo muſt be here intended, for which an eſpeciall honour is due. And as they are to feed all and every one in the flock, as <hi>Acts 20. ver.</hi> 28. ſo maintenance and honour is due from all this people to all and every one of theſe Elders, as well to thoſe that rule, as thoſe that labour in the word and Doctrine. And in reaſon, if the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121181:6"/>
Elders that rule well (and performe the leſſer acts of ruling) in their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Congregations, and the Presbyteries thereof are to have this honour in their relations, then all thoſe Elders that rule well in the common Presbyterie (and performe the greateſt acts of ruling) are to have the like from all that Claſſicall Church, the emphaſis being put upon <hi>ruling well,</hi> and in thoſe acts done by them the excellency of ruling conſiſteth, and the precept is not to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Presbyteries in ſome abſtract notion, but Elders: becauſe the particular perſons of the Elders are to be the object of it, and thoſe moſt who excell moſt in that rule, that <hi>rule well</hi> or beſt; but when there are many Congregations that have their proper fixed Paſtors and Elders whom they maintaine for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming one part of the Elders worke (for they performe but one part of it) how ſhall they performe this due to all the reſt for that other part of it? and it is due from every perſon as he is able, or he cannot performe his duty, how bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome, how confuſed would this be? And then how to proportion this, ſuppoſe it ſhould not be maintenance, but honour and eſteeme, this people will not be able to judge, not only for that they cannot be preſent at their worke and ſo cannot judge of it, but becauſe either it muſt be proportioned to them as conſtant <hi>Preaching-Elders,</hi> or as <hi>Ruling;</hi> not as to Preaching Elders, for they labour not to them as ſuch; the ground upon which it is required is, <hi>That they tread out their Corne,</hi> and to honour and eſteeme them as Ruling Elders only, were to honour preaching Elders below the ranke and degree of their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. So</p>
               <p>Secondly, It brings the like Incongruities upon the performance of thoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Elders, which the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> indifferently requires of all thoſe that it acknowledgeth to be Elders unto a people, and therefore no ſuch conſtant relation of Elders to ſo many Churches may be. As firſt, Praying with the ſick, <hi>Send for the Elders of the Church to pray for them,</hi> James chap. 5. ver. 14. What, are theſe Elders of a Presbyteriall Church bound hereto? this duty lyes in common upon Elders of Churches, and how ſhall we diſtinguiſh when the Scripture doth not. Secondly, <hi>Viſiting from houſe to houſe,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample inſtructs the Elders of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Acts <hi>chap. 20. ver.</hi> 20. Thirdly, <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over mens ſoules, as thoſe that muſt give an accompt,</hi> Heb. <hi>chap. 13. ver.</hi> 17. To watch, is not to ſtay till cauſes are brought by appeales or ſo from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, but perſonally to obſerve and overſee them, as ſoules committed to them, which they muſt give an accompt for. Fourthly, Of Preaching, If Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Elders <hi>in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon.</hi> The Biſhops, they ſaid the flock was theirs, and the whole care committed to them: and to ſalve the incongruity of not being able to preach themſelves to them, they profeſſed a derivative dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated power to inferior Paſtors, whom they called their Curats. This was plaine dealing: but theſe Elders make all the whole flock theirs, and this from thoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121181:7"/>
Scriptures that ſpeake of Elders and flock, and themſelves not Curats, and ſo perſonally obliged according to the rules in Scripture, and yet cannot performe it, which is a worſe Incongruitie.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, that they may part theſe duties among them, <hi>ubi Scriptura non diſtinguit, nec nos debemus diſtinguere.</hi> Now all thoſe duties that are ſpoken of Elders to the flocks, they are without diſtinction, as in reſpect of the object to whom they are extended. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to thoſe of <hi>Epheſus, Feed the flock.</hi> Peter the like to thoſe he writes to, <hi>The flock,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> reſpectively, <hi>To feed and to take the overſight of them.</hi> The author to the <hi>Hebrewes, To watch over their ſoules;</hi> And to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> he deſcribes them to be thoſe that are over them, and labour and admoniſh them. When thoſe Injunctions are thus laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all, how ſhall the conſcience of Elders be able to part and diſtinguiſh their diſcharge of them, and to ſay, though I am an Elder in common to all in theſe Congregations, yet I am bound but to governe them in greater matters, and to admoniſh them as with others, when publickly met in a Conſiſtorie, and am bound to no other acts of Elderſhip; and yet to this particular Congregation, I am obliged to private admonition, rule, watchfulneſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where hath the Scripture ſet theſe bounds, or thus parted them? And therfore certainly all theſe places hold forth ſingly, only the Elders and their duties of a particular Church fixed thereto, as knowing no other: 'Twas neceſſary Chriſt ſhould have ſet the bounds and given the diſtinction, and not indifferently lay all theſe upon all. And either in theſe places the duties of Elders in a common Presbyterie are contained, and that, under the notion of Elders to thoſe, or they are not to be found in the New Teſtament; And all theſe may be brought in ſeverall Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments alone by themſelves againſt the maine Propoſition, though here they come in only as branches of the Minor.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, This is inconſiſtent with the ordinary way of the Call of Elders held forth in the word, and the Principles of the Reformed Churches.</p>
               <p>There are two parts of this Call. Firſt, <hi>Choice.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Ordination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt for <hi>Choice, Chamier</hi> in the name of all the Reformed Churches, allowes the people this, the approbation of their Elders, and ſo in <hi>Scotland.</hi> And if the Apoſtles themſelves allowed them the choice of the Deacons that had the charge of the Church treaſury, and took care of their bodies; then much more of their Elders that have to doe with their conſciences. Looke what ever right of the people is in the choice of them that ſhould preach to them, there is as much reaſon they ſhould have the exerciſe of it in the choice of thoſe Elders that in a common Presbyterie doe rule over them, for they performe one part of the Elders duty, namely Ruling, as the Preaching Elders doe the other; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the equity of the ſame law, that ſpeakes of Elders indefinitely, if they chooſe any Elders as Elders to them, they are to chooſe theſe alſo, there being
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121181:7"/>
no diſtinction put of chooſing Preaching Elders only, but Elders indefinitely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And further, the greateſt and higheſt acts of power over them, are committed in an ordinary way unto them, as of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> of all puniſhments the moſt formidable, there is put as much, if not more then every mans life (that is a member of that Claſſicall Church) into their hands, the enjoyment of all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances for ever: And ſo the power of depoſing their Miniſters already fix'd to them, and of refuſing to ordaine them, they ſhall approve; And therefore in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, of all other the perſons of the Biſhops, who had the power of all thoſe, were choſen by all the people, and by Panegyricall meetings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And it is ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened by this further paralell; A Miniſters Call hath two parts, firſt, <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which belongs to the Elders. Secondly <hi>Choice,</hi> in which the people have ſome intereſt: Theſe Elders as Elders in common, and theſe Congregations as one Church be relatives, and ſo that intereſt which a Church, <hi>quâ Church</hi> hath, is commenſurable to the intereſt of theſe Elders, <hi>quâ Elders:</hi> If therefore in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining, all the Elders in a common Presbyterie, doe joyne to ordaine an Officer, then all the people, <hi>quâ Church,</hi> muſt joyne in chooſing or approving him; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can their common right of chuſing be ſwallowed up by the intereſt of their Elders ordaining him. And if it be ſaid they all chooſe by vertue of the generall law of combination, as in the Shires Parliament men; The conſtitution of the State makes the one, if the like be found in Scripture it will be ſufficient; but if not, but that this intereſt muſt be common to the people of the Claſſicall Church, it is asked when a fix'd Paſtor is to be choſen to a particular charge, what Office he ſhall be choſen to by the people of the other Congregation? Not to a Paſtors Office, he is not to be ſuch to them; if to be a Ruling Elder only, then beſides that he hath two Offices as afore; ſo now he muſt have two choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and two Ordinations: We chooſe him for our Paſtor, ſayes the particular Church he belongs to, and we, ſay the other, to Ruling. And beſides, in his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the people have an intereſt of preſence and joyning in the faſting and prayer at his Ordination: and this therefore muſt be performed, either in a pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyricall meeting of all, which cannot be, or in all the ſeverall Churches, which will multiply the Ordination of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="confirmation">
               <head>The major Propoſition confirmed.</head>
               <p>IN regard that the maine Argumentation of ſuch as contend for a Presbyteriall government (as in their writings and otherwayes appeares) is from the mention of the Elders of ſuch and ſuch a Church as, <hi>Jeruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> having many Congregations (as they ſuppoſe) the conſequence of the Major was taken ſo much for granted as on all ſides agreed on, as it was leſſe inſiſted upon the firſt day; but being denied and anſwered thus, <hi>that they bear not the relation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121181:8"/>
of Elders, but of a Preſbyterie,</hi> becauſe, <hi>quod convenit toti quâ toti non convenit cuilibet parti;</hi> And that if Elders, yet in <hi>ſenſu compoſito non diviſo,</hi> As a Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell is a Colonell to a particular Regiment, but in a Councell of War, not ſo to all Regiments: A head of a particular Tribe is an head to his own Tribe divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, but not ſo to all the Tribes, and the like.</p>
               <p>For that Logicall Axiome, 'tis true, <hi>quod convenit toti quâ toti non convenit cuilibet parti,</hi> and ſo here, that which doth <hi>competere toti,</hi> to the whole of theſe Elders, belongs not to every part; for take them all as met together, they are a Presbyterie, and accordingly each Elder is not a Presbyterie to all theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, nor doth the Argument ſuppoſe it, but only that if they be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Presbyterie to all theſe Congregations, that they then beare the relation of Elders. As take an heape of ſtones, 'tis true each ſtone is not an heape of ſtones, but each ſtone is a ſtone in that heape. So this Company of Elders, muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed both a Presbyterie, and alſo Elders to this whole people and every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them: which is farther proved thus;</p>
               <p>1. The Scriptures would have the people looke at them and honour them as Elders in all acts of ruling as well as in preaching, and eſpecially wherein the moſt and chiefe of ruling lyes, and wherein the excellency of their ruling is ſeen; They rule moſt and beſt when met in this common Presbyterie; upon that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation we are to honour them, as performing this rule, and under that relation they muſt be ſaid to performe it: <hi>The Elders that rule well, are worthy of double honour, eſpecially thoſe that labour in the word and Doctrine.</hi> Tim. <hi>Epiſt. 1. chap. 5. ver.</hi> 17. And beſides, otherwiſe we deſtroy the relation of Elders, <hi>quâ Elders,</hi> in the higheſt acts of governing, which are exerciſed only in a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie.</p>
               <p>2. The New Teſtament doth indifferently and promiſcuouſly uſe the word Presbyterie and the word Elders, of the ſame perſons in relation to the ſame people; and therefore to whom theſe Elders are ſuppoſed to be a Presbyterie, they muſt beare the relation of Elders, <hi>Matthew chap.</hi> 21. 23. thoſe that are called <hi>Elders of the people,</hi> are called, <hi>Luke 22. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie of the people:</hi> ſo as if they related as a Presbyterie to the people, to the ſame people they related as Elders.</p>
               <p>Secondly, For that diſtinction of their being Elders only in a community to all thoſe Congregations as one Church, <hi>in ſenſu aggregato,</hi> but not <hi>in ſenſu di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo,</hi> to every perſon thereof, as was inſtanced in Burgeſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Firſt, This Church as it is <hi>totum aggregatum,</hi> is but an abſtract notion, but the rule and government of the Elders in a Presbyterie, falls upon perſons in particular, and every member of that Church; if therefore they be Elders in the Presbyterie to that Church, it muſt be that they are Elders to every perſon therein. Againe it muſt be remembred where we are, namely upon what the Scriptures hold
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121181:8"/>
forth, ſo the Propoſition runneth. And if there had been thoſe differing relations of Elders, which from thoſe ſimilitudes in Common-wealths, Armies, and the Univerſities are given, it were neceſſary the Scripture ſhould have held it forth by like differing names and reſpects, or by differing charges whereby it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that this relation obligeth them to this duty, and this other relation to that, which being not done is therefore to us a fiction. That it was neceſſary ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the inſtances themſelves, As in that of the Tribes, there were gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Elders of all the Tribes, and there were (and perhaps ſome of them the ſame men) that were Heads and Elders of the particular Tribes. But as this was a differing relation and reſpect in the ſame, or diverſe perſons, ſo they had names and titles of difference and diſtinction: For the Heads generall as we may call them, were called Elders of the people. The particular Elders of particular<note place="margin">Matth. 21. 33.</note> Tribes, were called by way of diſtinction from them, Elders of ſuch Cities, Families, &amp;c. And there were as diſtinct lawes given in ſuch caſes, the Elders of the ſeverall Tribes did ſuch and ſuch particulars in their Tribes reſpectively, and the generall Elders had reſerved caſes of Blaſphemy, &amp;c. ſet downe by the Law. So in that inſtance of the Heads of Colledges, and Heads of the Univerſity, there is as a differing, ſo a diſtinguiſhing Character: the names are changed, the particular bodies are called Colledges, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Body the Univerſity, and their ſeverall ſpeciall relations to their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges is expreſſed by the Title of Maſters of ſuch and ſuch Colledges, and the other by the title of Heads to the Univerſity. Yea, and accordingly there are differing ſtatutes, the locall ſtatutes for each Colledge a part, or for Colledges as Colledges, and the duties of Maſters in their ſpeciall relations, and there are ſtatutes for the Univerſity and their duties as Heads thereof: and this diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and difference was neceſſary, if there were this differing relation. But for the caſe in hand, if we come to the New Teſtament to finde out theſe ſeverall juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions and relations of Elders, therein we ſtill reade but ſimply and ſingly <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> as Relatives, no ſuch note of diſtinction. And alſo ſpeaking of the duties of Elders to the people, and people to Elders, it ſpeaks ſimularly and univocally: ſo as whoever will take upon them to be Elders, all thoſe duties fall upon them, let them diſtinguiſh how they can. And to confirme this, the Inſtances in the Minor ſerve. <hi>And where the Scripture doth not diſtinguiſh, we are not to distinguiſh.</hi> And if the Elders of a particular Congregation are Elders to that Church, both in <hi>ſenſu diviſo</hi> and every member thereof, and alſo in <hi>ſenſu compoſito,</hi> in their Presbyteries unto the whole, then thoſe generall Elders muſt bear the like relation to that Claſſicall Church and every Member of it, elſe the difference is ſo vaſt, and the conſequent difference of duties thereupon depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch, as it was neceſſary a diſtinction ſhould have been made in Scripture, that each might know their duties.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:121181:9"/>If all the Records, Lawes, and Ruled caſes of this Kingdome, ſhould in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe the ordinary government thereof, have made mention only and ſingly of Burgeſſes (as the Rulers) and of Corporations (as the Correlate to them) and uſed no other diſtinguiſhing word, and there were undeniably Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes of every Incorporate Towne continued from antiquity: if any would af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards pretend that this word <hi>Corporation</hi> was intended by our Anceſtors to import an Aſſociation or Community of many of theſe Corporations into one Shire, and that by Burgeſſes of thoſe Corporations were meant a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of all thoſe Burgeſſes in one body for government, and ſo pretend the ſame names without diſtinction, and ſay they were alſo meant: yea, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if the Lawes and Charters concerning ſuch Burgeſſes in each Corporation, the duties given them in charge by the lawes in their relations to their Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, did runne without any diſtinction of what the Burgeſſes in the ſuppoſed greater Corporation ſhould doe, in that relation and community from what the ſame Burgeſſes in their leſſer Corporations in a more proper relation: Yea, and if the Duties ſet downe in thoſe lawes mutually betweene Corporations and thoſe Burgeſſes ſhould argue an inconſiſtency with the governement of Burgeſſes over many Corporations in common (as the <hi>minor</hi> here ſhewes it to be in our caſe) but all naturally fall in with that of Burgeſſes over ſingle Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: In this caſe to ſay that therefore this Kingdome did hold forth, there might not be (that is according to the lawes thereof) ſuch a government of the Burgeſſes of Corporations over many, were not this a right way of arguing to overthrow ſuch a pretence.</p>
               <p>And if in anſwer to ſuch arguments it ſhould be ſaid, that both theſe might be conſiſtent: For that in forein States, and Kingdomes, and Societies, there are Burgeſſes of particular Corporations, and there are Burgeſſes in an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Parliament, ſo called by way of diſtinction, met in common, for the ordinary government of all thoſe Corporations in common, and therefore the like may be here in this. The reply were eaſie, that what ever ſuch diſtinction there is in other States, yet the queſtion is of ſuch Burgeſſes as the Lawes of this State hold forth, the queſtion is of ſuch Burgeſſes as this Kingdome hath ſet up, where there is no diſtinction of Burgeſſes of Corporations, and Burgeſſes in Parliament mentioned. But on the contrary only, one ſingle uniforme ſtile and title in the lawes, namely, Burgeſſes of the Corporation, and duties ſuited thereunto. Now parallel to this caſe are our Arguments, and the Anſwers gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thereto. Laſtly, if they be Elders only <hi>in ſenſu aggregato,</hi> yet ſo farre as they are acknowledged thus Elders, ſo farre will many of the incongruities in the <hi>minor</hi> follow them, and fall upon them, as that ſtill they are but meerly ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elders, and that there be Deacons <hi>in ſenſu aggregato.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="exceptions_to_proof">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:121181:9"/>
               <head>Reaſons againſt, and exceptions to the firſt proofe of the firſt Aſſertion. <hi>viz.</hi> That the Church of Jeruſalem conſisteth of more Congregations then one from the multitude of Believers.</head>
               <p>FIrſt <hi>Reaſons</hi> to ſhew there were not more then could meet in one place.</p>
               <p>The Holy Ghoſt hath from firſt to laſt as on purpoſe ſhewed this, as if his ſcope had been aforehand to prevent and to preclude all reaſonings to the contrary.</p>
               <p>1. In the beginnings of that Church, their meetings are ſet out to us by two Adjuncts. Firſt, that they met <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>with one accord</hi> in the ſame duty of prayer, <hi>Acts</hi> Chap. 1. Verſe 14. And ſecondly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>together in one and the ſame company,</hi> Verſe 15. Which therefore is there and uſually tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>in one place.</hi> And that here by theſe words the intent of the Holy Ghoſt is to ſhew their meeting in one and the ſame Aſſembly, is evident. For whereas in the 15 Verſe 'tis ſaid, <hi>Peter stood up in the middest of them,</hi> as therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent together in one company, he addes, <hi>And the number of them that were</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>Preſent together in company, were an hundred and twenty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. Then Chap. 2. Verſe 1. Another meeting of theirs for worſhip at <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecost</hi> is continued to be expreſſed in the ſame phraſes a ſecond time, <hi>They were all with one accord in one place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. Then when about three thouſand, yet ſtill ſome of their meetings then for ſome acts of worſhip are recorded to have been as before <hi>with one accord,</hi> as joyning unanimouſly in the ſame duty, and in ſtead of that former expreſſion <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> uſed of the former meetings, there is the mention of the place it ſelfe, where they met, ſet downe to ſupply it, and ſo to interpret it, and ſhewes it was ſtill in one Aſſembly, Verſe 46. <hi>They continued daily with one accord in the Temple,</hi> as mentioning the very place where they had their moſt frequent meetings which were for hearing, as being there altogether in one Aſſembly; and not as comming thither only for Jewiſh worſhip: For it is ſaid of theſe as of the former meetings mentioned, which were proper to themſelves, <hi>That they continued with one accord.</hi> And though they held theſe meetings in this place for preaching, that the Jewes might be preſent to hear, &amp;c. Yet that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred not, but it was a Church meeting to them, wherein they continued with one accord; which expreſſion is ſtil uſed of al their Chriſtian meetings through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Story, <hi>Acts 1. 14. Acts 4. 24. Acts 5. 12. Acts</hi> 15. 25.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:121181:10"/>4. When there was a further addition to theſe, Chap. 5. Verſe 1. (whether to five thouſand or no is ſpoken to afterwards) yet in that Chapter, he making a deſcription of their State, in almoſt all the very ſame particulars by which he had done it before, Chap. 2. from Verſe 43. unto the end (as by the paralell com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring of theſe two paſſages of the Story will appear;) he laſtly ſpeaking of a meeting of theirs (which is the point in hand) as carefully puts in, as in the former. Verſe 14. <hi>And they were all with one accord in Solomons Porch,</hi> the ſame words he had uſed Chap. 2. Verſe 46. Their union and joyning together <hi>with one accord</hi> being carefully indigitated, and the place named in ſtead of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as was obſerved before. And that the [All that met] were not the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles only, appears not only by the forementioned paralell of this with Chap. 2. Verſe 46. where their being <hi>with one accord</hi> in the Temple, is ſpoken of all the multitude, and ſo here. But ſecondly, that all the Apoſtles ſhould be met <hi>with one accord</hi> in any duty, and not the people who are ſaid <hi>to continue in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Prayer,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>with one accord</hi> ſtill in the ſtory of this Church referring to communion in ſome holy duty, as Chap. 1. Verſe 14. and Chap. 4. Verſe 24. is moſt unlikely. And <hi>Solomons</hi> Porch was a place large enough to hold them, and fitted for preaching and to hear, which in <hi>John</hi> 10. Verſe 22. is called <hi>the Temple;</hi> and ſo is the place intended in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. Verſe 46. <hi>They met in the Temple,</hi> that is, <hi>in the Porch of Solomon.</hi> It was the outer Court as <hi>Joſephus lib. 20. cap.</hi> 8. It was the place where CHRIST uſed to walk and preach, and the Apoſtles alſo, Chap. 3. Verſe 11. <hi>The multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ran to Solomons Porch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5. When againe upon mention of this multiplication of Diſciples, the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons are to be choſen, the <hi>Apoſtles called the multitude</hi> Chap. 6. Ver. 2. and not perſons ſelected, but all; for Verſe 5. they are called <hi>the whole multitude,</hi> and they are ſpoken to as together, <hi>For the ſaying pleaſed the whole,</hi> and <hi>the whole choſe ſeven men out from among them, and ſet them before the Apoſtles,</hi> Ver<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. as being <hi>in one place</hi> together, <hi>and they prayed</hi> (in which the multitude had an intereſt to joyne with them) <hi>and laid on them hands.</hi> And this meeting was certainly a Church meeting, and yet ſtill <hi>in ſome one place;</hi> and therefore though it might follow that alwayes they ſhould not have met together in one, yet they both did and could.</p>
               <p>6. After that great diſperſion mentioned <hi>Chap. 8. ver.</hi> 1. Then as they might more conveniently meet in one place and aſſembly, ſo that they did ſo, it is as carefully recorded, that ſo the Holy Ghoſt might hold forth this from the firſt unto the laſt mention of this Church, <hi>Acts 15. Acts 21. 22. The multitude muſt needs come together.</hi> And to interpret <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or with one accord, which the Holy Ghoſt carries through all, to be intended of the joyning of the ſame perſons in the ſame act of worſhip (for which they ſtill did meet)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121181:10"/>
is genuine; for it imports that which is the ſpirit and life of publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which of all other actions done by a multitude is to have the neareſt union of ſpirits, as that wherein the Communion of Saints in worſhip con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts. And then naming the place where they met alſo it muſt needs import <hi>Oneneſſe</hi> of Aſſembly, which alſo holds forth in this example this duty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That as <hi>Saints</hi> when met in worſhip ſhould joyne with one accord, ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in a place together, ſhould as farre as poſſibly may, joyne themſelves to one Aſſembly; and this carries with it ſuch an appearance as is not in the other ſenſe. And that the Holy Ghoſt ſhould in the ſame Story of the ſame Church ſet forth the unity of their firſt meetings, as in one and the ſame individuall Aſſembly, by this expreſſion of being <hi>in one,</hi> and <hi>with one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, Acts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Chap. 1. Chap. 2. and in the next mention not farre off, carry along one of the ſame expreſſions, namely [<hi>with one accord</hi>] and together therewith ſhall name the place of their meeting, and yet in the latter intend not One, but meetings in ſeverall companies in that place. This we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſubmit to better judgements.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="exceptions">
               <head>Secondly Exceptions.</head>
               <p>1. For the mention of five thouſand, Chap. 4. Verſe 4. This cannot be evinced from that place that the five thouſand were a new number added to the three thouſand. The words are theſe, <hi>Howbeit many of them that heard the word, believed, and the number of the men</hi> was about five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand. But that this number of five thouſand ſhould refer to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, is not certaine; ſeeing both the Greek will bear it and favour it, as well to be meant of the number that heard, as of the men that believed; and of the two, that former is the more probable, that he ſhould ſay of the men that heard they were five thouſand, and that of them that heard many believed, this ſounds well, and is no way forced; but five thouſand men to be converted at once, is that which was never afore nor ſince. And the great converſion that our Divines have inſtanced in, is the three thouſand, <hi>Acts</hi> Chap. 2. and not in this five thouſand. And if the ſcope of the Holy Ghoſt therein, why the number of the men that heard ſhould be here recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be five thouſand be asked after, it was to ſhew what had occaſioned the perſecution which he had ſpoken of in the Verſe before. Namely this, that ſuch a multitude of the people ſhould be taught and preached to; this fretted the Phariſees that came upon <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John;</hi> and with this agrees<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Beza</hi> in 2 Cor. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3 <hi>Steph. Budeus,</hi> Eu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ath.</note> the ſecond Verſe, that <hi>they were grieved they taught the people;</hi> the effect whereof is, that <hi>many of them that heard believed,</hi> notwithſtanding this perſecution, but how many of theſe is not certaine. And <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:121181:11"/>
and many others of our proteſtant Writers judge this number not to be of this new acceſſion of Converts, but the totall number including the former, and the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, although tranſlated men, is when put alone (as there) all one with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Females, as well as Males, which eſpecially may be ſo taken, becauſe it is ſpoken of ſuch a promiſcuous auditory. And if any ſhould affirme it meant of Males only, and them now converted, it would make a greater Miracle then any other recorded, eſpecially when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ſaid to be converted, Verſe 2. that did alike runne to ſee the Miracle.</p>
               <p>2 <hi>Exception</hi> is, That it may be ſuppoſed that all that are mentioned to be converted remained not conſtant members of that Church abiding at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> untill the diſperſion; and ſo, though the Holy Ghoſts ſcope may be to ſhew the increaſe of Converts to the faith, yet not of ſuch as continued all that while at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and our reaſons for that are theſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt thoſe three thouſand who were converted, Chap. 2. were not ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led dwellers at Jeruſalem, but ſtrangers, Commorants of the ten Tribes, which were diſperſed in all thoſe Countries mentioned in the 2 Chapter, Verſe 9. who came up to the feaſt of Pentecoſt, as the manner of the Jewes was, <hi>Acts</hi> 21. 20, 27, 28. Jewes that lived in <hi>Aſia</hi> came to the feaſt of Pentecoſt as <hi>Paul</hi> alſo did, compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 16. And the word which is tranſlated <hi>Dwellers at Jeruſalem,</hi> is interpreted by an eminent Critick, Sojourners at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> during this Feaſt, although the word<note place="margin">Mede Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atribe.</note> ſignifies both, and to that end quotes the <hi>Septuagint</hi> in 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 17. 20. where <hi>Elijah</hi> cries unto the Lord, ſaying, <hi>O Lord my God haſt thou alſo brought evill upon the Widow,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> with whom <hi>I ſojourne onely?</hi> and that which confirmes it is, that they are ſaid to be dwellers or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Meſopotamia</hi> and <hi>Judea,</hi> and <hi>Capadocea,</hi> Verſe 9. They could not fixedly belong as dwellers to both, they were therefore rather ſojourners in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> now at the Feaſt, though fixed dwellers in all thoſe places: For if they were fixed dwellers in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to what end whileſt they were at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhould the Evangeliſt tell us they were ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journers in <hi>Meſopotamia;</hi> and they muſt needs rather be dwellers there, becauſe they are ſaid to underſtand every one his own language. And that which ſtrengthens this is, that in the Greek there is this difference in the words in Verſes 5 and 9. in that they are ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Hieruſalem. As for the preſent there, yea, and as to come <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from out of every <hi>Nation:</hi> but in the 9 Verſe he changeth it, and ſaies, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as inhabiters of <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> and thoſe other Countries
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121181:11"/>
where their fixed poſſeſſions were. And therefore Verſe 14. he cals them Men, <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Dwellers</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as two ſorts, and Verſe 22. <hi>Men of Iſrael;</hi> the ſtile given thoſe of the ten Tribes ſcattered, <hi>Men devout,</hi> as Verſe 5. who came up at thoſe ſolemne times, having wives and children and their families at home, to whom they uſed after a time to returne. Now although theſe were added and made members of that Church, and are ſaid to continue in the Apoſtles doctrine: yet that will not neceſſarily imply that they continued all the time till the diſperſion at Jeruſalem; but whileſt they were there, they were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, they cleaved to the Apoſtles: but to think that many of them comming as ſtrangers ſhould not go downe to their wives and children, which Nature taught them to provide for, and religion taught them to take care of their ſoules, or fetch them up to them: ſo as this might well be a fluid Church, ebbing and flowing as touching the reſidence of its members: yea, ſome of theſe were of <hi>Judea,</hi> Verſe 9. and ſo of the Country about; and of them might be Churches erected in their proper dwellings is rationally ſuppoſable. For in that perſecution in <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 1. it is ſaid that <hi>Paul</hi> perſecuted Diſciples in other places then at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> Acts 26. 10. <hi>Which things I alſo did at Hieruſalem,</hi> (ſaies he) and in other places at <hi>Damaſcus.</hi> And alſo it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by this, that upon the ceaſing of <hi>Pauls</hi> perſecution it is ſaid <hi>Acts 9. 31. then had the Churches reſt through Judea and Galilee,</hi> and are ſaid to be at reſt in diſtinction from the perſecution raiſed, Chap. 8. 1.</p>
               <p>3 <hi>Exception</hi> is, that they in thoſe Countries and times had often great Aſſemblies conſiſting of many thouſands hearers at once, that did and could heare, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 1. Chriſt preached to <hi>Myriads,</hi> many thouſands; and <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 45. almoſt a whole City came to heare the word of God by <hi>Paul.</hi> And at <hi>Charenton,</hi> how many thouſands may and do heare, is well knowne; and ſo in many places of England. And <hi>Moſes</hi> ſometime ſpake in the eares of all the people, and ſo <hi>Ezra</hi> Chapter 10. Verſe 9. and 10. And 'tis knowne by experience, that as in hot Countries they may ſee as far againe, through the pureneſſe of the aire, ſo they may heare at a farre greater diſtance, then in our colder Climate.</p>
               <p>4 <hi>Exception</hi> is, that this being the firſt Church, and whereof all the Apoſtles were the Officers, thoſe therefore that dwelt there would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly abide together as one Church without parting or dividing, even till they came to the utmoſt proportion that the conſtitution of a Church was capable of; and ſo <hi>Maximum quod ſic, And continue together in one,</hi> for the more united ſtrength and glory of holding forth the name of Chriſt in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121181:12"/>
one body, united for the honour of Religion and communicating in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances together.</p>
               <p>5 <hi>Exception</hi> is, that they had during all this time of their multitudes untill the perſecution of <hi>Paul</hi> aroſe, the greateſt freedome and liberty even to the utmoſt; <hi>for the people magnified them,</hi> Chap. 5. Verſe 12. <hi>they had favour with all the people,</hi> Chap. 2. Verſe 47. Inſomuch, that although the Rulers fell upon two of them, <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> yet they were enforced to let them go, finding nothing how to puniſh them, becauſe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Chapter 4. 21. Beſides that, it was no new thing amongſt the Jewes for Sects to have great multitudes to follow and cleave to them, and to preach in any place, as in <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> and to baptize openly as <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> did.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answers_to_appendix">
               <head>Reaſons and Anſwers to the Appendix added to the former Proofes, <hi>viz.</hi> That the diſperſion mentioned in <hi>Acts 8. 1.</hi> doth not ſimply prove ſuch a ſcattering, as that there might not remaine more Congregations then one in that Church, <hi>Acts 9. 31. Acts 12. 24. Acts 21. 20.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus having ſhewed the multitudes not ariſing to that number, but, that they might meet in one, now after the diſperſion much leſſe, and to that end let the greatneſſe of the Perſecution be conſidered to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the greatneſſe of this diſperſion; Its called not a Perſecution only, but a great <hi>Perſecution,</hi> both <hi>extenſively</hi> and <hi>intenſively,</hi> for the extent of it to all ſorts of perſons, entring into every houſe, <hi>verſ</hi> 3. and for the height of it, it being to impriſonment, even unto death, <hi>Chap. 22. 4. Acts</hi> 26. 10. It is alſo called, <hi>a making havock of the Church,</hi> verſ. 9. The object of this Perſecution was not Preachers only but Chriſtians of all ſorts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently, for it is ſaid indefinitely to be upon the Church, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. and <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. It is call'd an entring into every houſe, <hi>hayling men and women:</hi> and in <hi>Chap. 26. Paul</hi> ſpeaking of this very Perſecution (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he had a ſpeciall hand) ſayes <hi>verſ. 10. that hee impriſoned many of the Saints</hi> (not Preachers only) and <hi>ver.</hi> 9. his aime was promiſcuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and ſo any that profeſſed his Name: Unto this end compare the varying the expreſſion uſed by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:121181:12"/>
when ſpeaking of this Perſecution, and of another mentioned <hi>Acts</hi> 12. 1. there it is ſaid, <hi>Herod ſtretched forth his hand to vexe certaine of the Church;</hi> but here it is againſt the Church in <hi>Jeruſalem, Men and women in every houſe,</hi> and all except the Apoſtles; the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> [<hi>except</hi>] there is to ſhew, that none of the Apoſtles were ſcattered, though the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of others were; if men guifted fled away, then others alſo, except we ſuppoſe the people more couragious to ſtay by it then the Teachers. And whereas it is ſaid, that theſe that were diſperſed, went about prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the word, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. Firſt, It argueth not that Preachers only or chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were diſperſed; for (as <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith) it comes in to ſhew what was the fruit of the diſperſion; and we may well ſuppoſe women and whole families to have been ſcattered abroad, who yet preached not: And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, It was ordinary in thoſe times, for men that were not by Office Miniſters, occaſionally to teach the word in private wayes of converſe, yea and otherwiſe; And that is not call'd teaching, which is by way of Sermon to a multitude, for <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. of this chap. <hi>Philip</hi> in private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference taught the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> as <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla</hi> taught <hi>Apollos;</hi> and they are not called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as having an Office, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as referring to the act, the work they did; And that the word ſeemes to ſound as if they made it their worke. It may well be attributed to the zeale of thoſe dayes to gaine Proſelites, and not to an Office committed to them; they went not forth by miſſion but perſecution; And here the many Congregations are brought but to an <hi>(it might be)</hi> and the grand Propoſition it ſelfe, is but an <hi>(it may be,)</hi> And how can <hi>it may be,</hi> be proved by an <hi>it might be?</hi> eſpecially in ſuch things as need have a ſtrong foundation for matters upon which ſo great alterations are like to be made: But it is ſaid, that it appeares that <hi>there were multitudes of beleevers there after that time,</hi> by <hi>Acts 9. 31. Acts 12. 24. Acts</hi> 21. 20.</p>
               <p>Firſt, For <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 31. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſignifies not ordinarily a great number made up, but an increaſe (<hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 12. &amp; 1 <hi>Pet. 1. 2. Grace be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied,</hi> it is the ſame word) not in number, but in meaſure. Againe they are the Churches of <hi>Judea, Galilee,</hi> and of <hi>Samaria;</hi> But what is all this to prove that there were ſo many in the Church of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> as could not <hi>meet in one?</hi> For <hi>Acts</hi> 21. 20. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> how many thouſands doth not argue it; For firſt it was the Feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> when <hi>Paul</hi> came now up to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 16. it is ſaid of this journey, that <hi>he <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>asted if poſſible, to be at Hieruſalem upon the day of Pentecoſt:</hi> When the <hi>Jewes</hi> out of all quarters came to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and the great concourſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121181:13"/>
that then would be there at the Feaſt, moved him to aime to be there at that time; And by the journall of <hi>Paul</hi> thither, from his firſt ſetting out from <hi>Philippi, chap. 20. ver.</hi> 6. which was when the Paſſeover was ended, eight weekes before this enſuing Feaſt of <hi>Pentecost,</hi> and alſo by compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the dayes of his travailing, which the Holy Ghoſt hath recorded, <hi>verſ. 16. 21. Acts</hi> 21. 2. it appeares he came in few weekes unto <hi>Tyre,</hi> but 40. miles off from <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> time enough to come to the Feaſt; and no wonder if at the Feaſt he found thouſands of the Jewes, and this is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the 27 verſe, for the Jewes which laid hold on him in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, were as it is ſaid, Jewes of <hi>Aſia,</hi> not of <hi>Judea.</hi> Secondly, The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, being put without any other word of number, ſignifies no more then a great multitude; as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or a greatneſſe, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as <hi>Plato</hi> hath it; and being put indefinitely, is all one to ſay thouſands, or many; as the Latins alſo uſe a definite for an indefinite, as <hi>Sexcenta poſſum proferr<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> decreta,</hi> as <hi>Tully</hi> ſpeakes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="answers_to_proof">
               <head>To the ſecond Proofe of the firſt Head.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the many Apoſtles and other Preachers in this</hi> Church of Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; For if there were but one Congregation, then each Apoſtle preached but ſeldome, which will not ſtand with <hi>Acts 6. 2.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Firſt, For the Apoſtles.</head>
                  <p>THey tooke all opportunities to fill their hands with worke, preaching daily in the Temple and in every houſe, <hi>Acts 5. 42. Chap. 2. 46. Paul</hi> alſo taught in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> as <hi>publickly</hi> in the Congregation, ſo from houſe to houſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 20. Alſo when any in the places abroad in <hi>Judea,</hi> or elſe where, were converted (and many Churches were then erected in <hi>Judea</hi>) the Apoſtles went abroad, as <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. ſhewes; and beſides, how were the twelve imployed, when for forty dayes they met in an upper roome, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. and had but an hundred and twenty for their flock.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Secondly, For the many Teachers.</head>
                  <p>In thoſe times there were many guifted men that were not Officers, who occaſionally inſtructed others, as <hi>Aquila</hi> did <hi>Apollos,</hi> yea thoſe guifts were ſo plentifull, that in that one Church of <hi>Corinth, 1 Cor.</hi> 14. 23.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121181:13"/>
almoſt all of them had <hi>Doctrines, Prophecying, speaking with tongues,</hi> and yet theſe were not Officers, ſo as if Congregations ſhould be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied according to the number of ſuch guifted men, then there would have been almoſt as many Teachers as members of Congregations. And the powring out of the Holy Ghoſt, which was more ordinary then, did not make every man a Teacher by Office, for then all thoſe in <hi>Samaria</hi> ſhould have been made teachers, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. And that not any of thoſe were in Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, ſeemes evident by this; That when the Deacons were choſen, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. there is no mention made of Elders in their Ordination, in which if any Elders had been, they had had an intereſt: We reade <hi>Acts</hi> 15. When there were Elders, though Apoſtles were alſo then in that Church, both are mentioned together. And it appeares the Apoſtles had managed all the affaires of that Church untill then; thoſe Deacons being the firſt choice of any ſort of Officers, the work of Adminiſtration of all ſorts having layen on the Apoſtles hands.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="answers_to_proof">
               <head>To the third Proofe of the firſt Head.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The diverſitie of Languages amongſt the Beleevers, <hi>Acts 2. 8, 9, 10, 11.</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> the 6. doth argue more Congregations then one in the Church of Hieruſalem.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>FIrſt, 'Tis true, there were in that ſecond of the <hi>Acts, Out of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> that heard the Apoſtles ſpeake in the ſeverall Languages of the Countries they were borne in; but yet theſe were all either Jewes or Proſelites, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, worſhippers, as <hi>ver.</hi> 5. who came up to worſhip, and ſome parts of the worſhip were audible; and though borne in other Countries (the Jewes being diſperſed) yet all were generally learned, and underſtood the Hebrew tongue, the language of their own Nation, even as to this day the Jewes and their Children doe; which ſeemes evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the ſtory in the 20, 21, and 22. Chapters of the <hi>Acts, Paul</hi> came up with divers <hi>Grecians</hi> to the Feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt, Chap. 20. ver.</hi> 4. unto which the Jewes out of all quarters came, and being all at a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne meeting in the Temple, <hi>chap. 21. ver.</hi> 27. The Jewes out of <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſtrangers, ſtirred up all the people againſt him, and when, <hi>chap. 22. ver. 2. He made a speech to them, and they heard he spake the Hebrew tongue, they kept ſilence and heard him patiently:</hi> And further thoſe mentioned
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121181:14"/>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2. did underſtand all of them <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon; and though others ſpake beſides <hi>Peter</hi> to them in their own language, the wonderfull things of God, yet that was but a preparatorie ſigne to them; as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 22. making way for their Converſion, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11, 12, and 13. but the meanes of their Converſion was <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon after; and it was he alſo, that gave direction to them all what to doe to be ſaved: and therefore it muſt be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of ſome one common tongue, they all underſtood, and thoſe gifts of languages given to the Apoſtles, were not out of a neceſſity to inſtruct thoſe new Converts only, but to fit them when they ſhould goe abroad into all the world, and to be a ſigne to the Jewes at preſent to convince them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for the <hi>Grecian</hi> Widdowes, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. the <hi>Helleniſts</hi> that lived amongſt the Jewes, might well be ſuppoſed to underſtand Hebrew; and that theſe had not ſeverall Congregations from the reſt, appeares by this; That the whole multitude together met, and choſe the Deacons, It was a joint act, and if of differing languages, wherein the one underſtand not the other, occaſioning ſuch a diſtinction of Congregations (as the Proofe would hold forth) how could they all have agreed in <hi>one meeting</hi> on the <hi>ſame man?</hi> but the argument as well holds againſt the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall Aſſociation of thoſe Congregations into one Church, people and Elders,</hi> unto which and in the communion and exerciſe whereof ſuch Correſpondencies and Intercourſes are needfull, as they require one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon language.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answers_to_proofs">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:121181:14"/>
               <head>To the ſecond Branch of this Argument.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That all theſe Congregations were under one Presbyteriall <hi>GOVERNMENT.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>PROOFES.</head>
               <p>1. <hi>Becauſe they were but one Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though it bee one, yet they not beeing more then could meet in one, the Argument concludes not.</p>
               <p>2 <hi>Proofe. The Elders of that Church are mentioned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is no mention of any Elders in this Church, untill after the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Diſperſion, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. And ſo the weight of this Argument will depend upon the proofe of this; That after the diſperſion there were many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, which the Reverend Aſſembly doth not ſo poſitively affirme. The proofe of their being ſuch a Presbytery as the Propoſition intends, doth depend upon this their being called Elders to that Church, wee no where read them called a Presbytery, and that therefore they are Elders, but they are therefore a Presbytery (as here it is argued) becauſe they are Elders to that Church; Now if they bee Elders in common, becauſe a Presbytery, (as was ſaid in anſwer to the firſt Argument) then they are not to bee argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Presbytery onely, becauſe they are Elders in Common; For then the Argument runnes <hi>in Circulo;</hi> And the chiefe and firſt reaſon of their being Elders (for no other is mentioned) is accordingly held forth in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Elders to that Church in common, whereas according to Presbyteriall Principles, there is a primary relation of Elders, <hi>quà</hi> Elders, to their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular fixed Congregations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reasons_against_proof">
               <head>Reaſons againſt the third Proofe of the ſecond Branch, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Apoſtles did the ordinary Acts of Presbyters as Presbyters in the Church of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> doth prove a Presbyteriall Government in that Church before the diſperſion.</head>
               <p>The Proofe of the whole depends upon this Propoſition: for though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the diſperſion there had been many Congregations, yet not under El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, but Apoſtles: Now it is granted that the ſubſtance of Miniſteriall Acts were one and the ſame in Apoſtles and Evangeliſts who were extraordinary, and in other ordinary Miniſters. But firſt, though for the Act of Miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121181:15"/>
power, it was the ſame in the Apoſtles, and them, yet in the extent of power (which is the point in queſtion) therein the Apoſtles Juriſdiction over many Congregations is not the patterne of Presbyteriall Elders over many, for the Apoſtles power was univerſall over all Churches, and upon that was founded their power over thoſe Congregations ſuppoſed many; And Epiſcopacie may as ſtrongly argue and inferre, that becauſe in <hi>Crete</hi> (by Apoſtolicall warrant) <hi>One man [Titus]</hi> did ordaine Elders, &amp;c. That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there may bee one man [<hi>a Biſhop</hi>] that hath power to ordaine, &amp;c. in and over ſeverall Churches. And this Argument will bee ſtronger from the inſtance of an Evangeliſt, for Epiſcopall power then this of Apoſtolicall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> government, for the Presbyteriall, by how much it is the more inferior Office, but that of the Apoſtles is more immediate and tranſcendent, and ſo the power of an Evangeliſt is neerer to an ordinary ſucceſſion, and it will as well follow, that any one Presbyter alone might governe many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, becauſe one of theſe Apoſtles might, as that becauſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did governe theſe joyntly, that therefore many Presbyters over ſeverall Congregations may.</p>
               <p>Secondly, each of theſe Apoſtles, as hee had by vertue of his Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Commiſſion the power of them all, ſo hee had relation of Miniſterie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all theſe ſuppoſed Congregations unto every perſon thereof for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of all ſorts of duties, of preaching to them, admoniſhing them, &amp;c. But thus in the Presbyteriall government over many Congregations fixed, and their Paſtors and Elders fixed to them, the ſeverall Elders are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to have the relation of Elders to each Congregation, but make up one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Elderſhip in common as united over all theſe. But the Apoſtles here have the relation to both, and therefore if this Apoſtolicall frame bee made a Patterne, then it followes that all the Elders of theſe Congregations were directly and immediatly Elders to each Congregation and every member of them, and not onely of a common Presbytery, for ſo the Apoſtles were.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If it bee alledged that thoſe acts of government, performed by them in that Church, were for the ſubſtance of them ordinary Acts, ſuch as Presbyters per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, and that therefore anſwerably their perſons themſelves are in them to bee conſidered as Elders, becauſe that the Apoſtles were not onely Apoſtles, but Elders alſo, as</hi> John Epiſtle 2. Verſe 1. <hi>And</hi> Peter Epiſt. 1. Chap. 5. Verſ. 1. <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might and did act as Elders in ordinary Acts of Church government, and are therefore therein to bee look't at, as a juſt patterne to us, and to have ruled theſe Congregations of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>as a Colledge or body of Elders united, conedſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo to act as common Presbyters taking the conſent of the Church, as</hi> Acts. 6. <hi>as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they did in every Church where they came joyning with the Elderſhip thereof,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121181:15"/>
as Elders, and not as Apoſtles, and therefore that they might give a patterne, and Example of an ordinary Presbytery, eſpecially ſeeing that what they thus did, they did as an united body to many Congregations conſidered as one Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is anſwered to the firſt, that although the Apoſtles are called Elders, yet they are ſo called virtually, not formally, and but becauſe Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip containes all Offices in it, ſo as they are Elders but upon this ground, that they are Apoſtles, and therefore <hi>John</hi> in that very Epiſtle where hee ſtiles himſelfe an Elder, hee yet writes Canonicall Scripture as an Apoſtle, and takes on him to threaten <hi>Diotrephes</hi> as an Apoſtle, to remember him, which as a formall Elder hee could not have done; and ſurely thoſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which Chriſt diſtinguiſheth, <hi>Epheſians 4. Hee gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Teachers,</hi> the ſame perſon is not formally both, though virtually he may bee; All that they did in that Church of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> they are ſaid to act as Apoſtles, their preaching is called the <hi>Apoſtles doctrine,</hi> their bringing their monies to them, as to the Officers of that Church, is to them not as Elders, but as Apoſtles, <hi>They laid it downe at the Apoſtles feet;</hi> yea in that Act of ordaining the ſeven Deacons, it is ſaid, <hi>They ſet them afore the Apoſtles, (Chap. 6. Verſ. 6.) and they laid on their hands;</hi> And it is very hard to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and ſay that the men were Apoſtles, but the power they acted by was as Elders, when the name of an Apoſtle imports the Office; Yea in that very Act of government about Deacons they muſt needs act as Apoſtles, for they doe not ſimply ordaine the men, but doe anew, by vertue of Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall authoritie, inſtitute the Office of Deacons by declaring Chriſts mind, which none but Apoſtles could immediatly and at firſt have done, ſo as the ſame perſons in this ſame Act inſtanced in, muſt act partly as Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and partly as Elders, and by what infallible rule ſhall wee diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>they acted here as it were in a joynt body or in Collegio over theſe many Congregations.</hi> It is anſwered, that an Aſſociation of Elders in an Elderſhip over many is not argued from hence. For firſt, they had all ſingly the ſame power which they exerciſed joyntly, and that they ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe it joyntly here to that end to give a patterne for Elderſhip, is not eaſy to prove; they exerciſed it together, becauſe it fell out that they were toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it was fit none of them ſhould bee excluded, but it depended not upon this union of all in a body, as Acts of Elders in a Presbytery do, as Parliamentary power is not the reſult of Parliament men, but as aſſembled in Parliament; yea and the authoritie of Juriſdiction thence ariſeth, not ſo here; Our Apoſtle might have done that which all here did, yea may it not bee ſaid that becauſe two Apoſtles, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> ordained <hi>Elders in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121181:16"/>
every Church, Acts</hi> 14. as joyned in the ſame Act, and ſo acting not as Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, but joyntly, that therefore two Elders aſſociated may doe the like? Secondly, it is hard to ſuppoſe that theſe Apoſtles, when all together, ſhould act with an inferiour power to what they put forth in a like caſe alone. If <hi>Peter</hi> had beene himſelfe alone in a Church new planted then and there, hee muſt bee ſuppoſed to act as an Apoſtle, becauſe hee alone governed; And ſhall theſe Apoſtles, when they are all in one and joyne all together in one Act, bee yet ſuppoſed to fall lower in their power under the formall exerciſe of it? Thirdly, if they had acted as Elders in a Colledge, they might miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry as Elders doe; and ſo the minor part of them have been ſubject to Excommunication of the greater. And what power was there on earth to have excommunicated an Apoſtle who held his Office immediately from Chriſt, and who whilſt hee was in that Office had power over all Churches?</p>
               <p>To the third, viz. <hi>That they in their Proceedings did joyne with others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As in this choyce of the Deacons they did joyne with the multitude, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo when they came to any other Churches they uſed to doe.</hi> Neither doth that argue, that they acted not as Apoſtles but as Elders. For firſt, they joyned in Acts with others, and joyned others with themſelves, wherein they yet acted as Apoſtles; thus in writing Scripture they joyned others with them, as <hi>Paul</hi> joyned <hi>Silvanus</hi> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians;</hi> and not meerely in the ſalutation, for the expreſſions runne in their names alſo in that Epiſtle, and <hi>Act. 15. The Apoſtles, Elders,</hi> yea and <hi>Brethren</hi> joyned in a Letter to the Churches; But theſe as Apoſtles (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo called in diſtinction from the Elders) and the reſt according to their ſeverall intereſts, as the Brethren did all according to their intereſts, ſo the Elders and the Apoſtles in theirs. So in ordaining <hi>Timothy</hi> the Presbytery laid on hands, yet they as a Presbytery and <hi>Paul</hi> as an Apoſtle, for elſe a Presbytery had not had power to ordaine an Evangeliſt. Yet ſecondly, the Apoſtles did where ever they came leave the Elders and people to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of that right belonged to them, although they joyned with them; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did therein lie their Apoſtolicall authority, to doe all alone; for then they ſeldome or never acted as Apoſtles in Churches: <hi>Paul</hi> alone excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated not that Corinthian, and yet as an Apoſtle wrote to have it done by them, (for it was Canonicall Scripture) and therefore although that this Church of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> ſhould chooſe their Deacons, is a juſt exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the priviledge of a Church (for if the Apoſtles when they were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent allowed this intereſt to Churches, then Elders ſhould much more) yet what the Apoſtles did by an Apoſtolicall power in theſe Congregations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee drawn into example for Officers in that thing wherein their power Apoſtolicall lay, which was to exerciſe acts of juriſdiction in ſeverall Churches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:121181:16"/>Neither fourthly, will that helpe it, <hi>That they exerciſed this Government in theſe Congregations</hi> (ſuppoſed many) <hi>as conſidered to bee one Church.</hi> For if they acted not as Elders, then the correlate to it, namely, <hi>Church,</hi> could not bee conſidered as Presbyteriall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reasons_against_proof">
               <head>Reaſons againſt the fourth and laſt Proofe of the ſecond Branch. <hi>Viz.</hi> That the Elders did meet together for Acts of Government, <hi>Act. 11. ult. Act. 15. 4. 6. 22. Act. 21. 17, 18.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Firſt, the Argument from <hi>Acts</hi> 11. ult. lies thus, <hi>There were Elders in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea that received Almes,</hi> verſe 29<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 30. compared; <hi>Therefore the Elders of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem did meet together for Acts of Government.</hi> In this Argument, as the perſons are miſtaken, ſo the Act for the Elders of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> are not menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, but of <hi>Iudea,</hi> as by comparing verſes 29, 30. it appeares. And by this it might bee as well argued, that the Elders in <hi>Judea</hi> met for Presbyteriall Government, as that the Elders of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſeeing their Almes were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to the Elders of <hi>Judea,</hi> as it is there ſaid. The receiving Almes (which is the onely Act that is mentioned) was not an Act of Government, for Deacons may meet to receive Almes, and yet meet not for Acts of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For that ſecond place mentioned, <hi>Acts</hi> 21. 20. where it is ſaid, <hi>Paul came in to James, and all the Elders were preſent:</hi> although wee read that all the Elders were preſent, yet that they met for Acts of Presbyteriall government, appeares not; the occaſion of the meeting was <hi>Pauls</hi> entertainment, whom ſome of the brethren had received at his firſt comming, <hi>verſe</hi> 17. and now the Elders meet to receive him alſo. A Chriſtian duty of love and reſpect due to ſo great and famous an Apoſtle, and <hi>Paul</hi> went not as cited, but to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit and ſalute them, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Acts that paſſed were none of them Presbyteriall, for <hi>Paul</hi> gave them an Hiſtoricall relation of what things God had wrought by his Miniſtery, the matter of which relation was intended to provoke them as Brethren and fellow-labourers, to glorify God (as <hi>ver.</hi> 20. is ſaid they did) and not to give them an account, as to a Conſiſtory, that met for Government. Such narrations the Apoſtles made even to whole Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> at <hi>Antioch, Act. 14. 27. When they had gathered the whole Church together</hi> (which Church was of no more then to meet in one Aſſembly) they rehearſed in like manner, as here, all that God had done by them; and how hee had opened <hi>a doore of Faith to the Gentiles.</hi> Neither
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121181:17"/>
will the advice they gave to <hi>Paul</hi> to prevent the ſcandall and offence the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would take at him, argue authority, much leſſe government: Neither was there any Act of Government put forth over their own Churches if ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed many.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Reaſons againſt the alledging, <hi>Act. 15.</hi> for the meeting of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for Presbyteriall Acts of Government.</head>
                  <p>1. If it were a meeting of Elders for Acts of Government, then it was a Presbyteriall meeting for Acts of Government: But that it was no ſuch meeting appeares, becauſe there was nothing done in it, that may ſeem to have any bond in it, but ſuch as bound the Churches of <hi>Antioch, Syria, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licia,</hi> as much as <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but this cannot bee in any Presbyteriall meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for Acts of Government: For ſuch meetings have onely authoritative power over their own Church.</p>
                  <p>2. The ſcope and end of this meeting was to give ſatisfaction to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended Brethren of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and dogmatically to declare their judgements in a difficult caſe of Conſcience, not to put forth any Act of Juridicall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er upon any, as appeares in the matter of their debate, and the iſſue of all. Of which more fully afterward. And if it bee ſaid that <hi>Peter</hi> reproved ſome of their own Members preſent, ſuch as had taught the neceſſity of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall Law, <hi>Why tempt you God, &amp;c.</hi> This was not delivered as an Act of Government formally, by any vote of the Presbytery, but in the way of Diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>But it was affirmed <hi>to bee ſufficient to confirme the Propoſition, if it bee a Synodicall meeting.</hi> Presbyteriall and Synodicall, both it cannot bee; for Synods, they are or ought to bee extraordinary and occaſionall, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries are ſtanding and ordinary, Synods are made up of Commiſſioners ſent from Presbyteries, and Presbyteries are made up of the Elders of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregations. The Members of Synods are Elders of ſuch Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which are (according to the principles of Presbyteriall Government) compleat Churches, having full power of juriſdiction for all Acts of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment within themſelves; but the members of Presbyteries are Elders of ſuch Congregations which are neither compleat Churches, nor have within themſelves full and compleat power. And theſe cannot bee one. The Elders of the Presbytery of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> (when this once became a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod by the addition of the Elders of other Churches) ceaſed to bee any longer a Presbytery to that Church, and muſt become with them a new bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to all the Churches, theſe other Elders did come from. And then to
<pb facs="tcp:121181:17"/>
argue theſe Acts done by theſe (because the Elders of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were preſent and Members of this Synod) were Presbyteriall Acts of the Elders of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> is all one as to go about to argue from the Acts of Government put forth by a Parliament at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to the power of the Burgeſſes and Common Councell of the City of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> becauſe there the Parliament ſits, and the Burgeſſes of that City are parts and members of that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Or, as if the Kingdome were governed by County Courts, and out of thoſe County Courts, Knights, and Burgeſſes ſhould bee choſen to make up a Parliament, when the Parliament is met, there can be no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument drawn from the power of a Parliament to prove the power of a County Court. Or from the power of a County Court to prove the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of a Parliament. Thus Synods are made out of Presbyteries, therefore wee cannot argue from the power of Synods to the power of Presbyteries; or from the power of Presbyteries to the power of Synods.</p>
                  <p>But ſecondly, wee deny it to have been ſuch an ordinary formall Synod. The juriſdiction of Synods is founded upon this neceſſary requiſite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, That there bee Commiſſioners from all thoſe Churches repreſenting them, preſent, or called to bee ſo. And the power of the juriſdiction can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach nor extend further then to ſuch Churches as have ſent Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners thereunto. The weight then of this Synodicall power depends on the proofe of this, That all thoſe Churches ſent Commiſſioners to this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, which if either it bee not proved, or the contrary thereunto found true, the authority of thoſe decrees (as from thoſe Elders here) will prove not to have been Acts of Government, further then the Apoſtles authority, who joyned in it, was ſtamped on it; to affirme that Commiſſioners from them all were preſent, becauſe the decrees did binde them, is to begge what is denyed, when another juſt reaſon may bee given of their binding, if any ſuch authority were in them: and our reaſons to the contrary are theſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Wee finde a deepe ſilence about it: For wee read but onely of two Churches between whom it was tranſacted, they of <hi>Antioch</hi> ſending to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and their Elders there, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. 27, 28. compared with <hi>chap.</hi> 15. 2, 3. and the Meſſengers which were ſent from this Aſſembly going onely to <hi>Antioch, ver.</hi> 30. 31. as thoſe who were chiefely troubled; onely the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit redounded to all they wrote to, yea, although <hi>Paul</hi> came through <hi>Phenice</hi> and <hi>Samaria, ver.</hi> 3. yet wee read not a word of any of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of thoſe parts, their ſending of any Commiſſioners unto this Synod, as had it been intended ſuch certainly they would, and there was this ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall reaſon, why thoſe of this Church were thus electively ſent unto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were the Mother Church from whom the Word of God came, and from whom thoſe men that troubled them had gone forth, and had
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121181:18"/>
pretended to teach what they had received from them; and beſides they were in an eſpeciall manner verſed in this queſtion, it being about the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of their law; and there alſo ſome of the Apoſtles were preſent, (how many wee know not, for diſperſed they had been long before) and if any number of others out of thoſe other parts of <hi>Judea,</hi> had come up hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it would have been ſaid, as <hi>Act. 11. ult.</hi> The Elders of <hi>Judea,</hi> not onely of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> yea, it is not ſo much as ſaid, that they that were ſent from <hi>Antioch</hi> were of the Elders of that Church, but that they ſent <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and certain others of them.</p>
                  <p>And ſecondly, the contrary ſeemes cleere, namely, that thoſe Letters and Decrees were written and ſent onely from the Elders of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and not from all thoſe Churches: For firſt, the Decrees are every where attributed to the Elders in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> So <hi>Chap. 16. 4. The Decrees of the Apoſtles and Elders in Jeruſalem.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Now the uſuall ſtile of the New Teſtament, is by way of diſtinction of Churches to ſay the Church in ſuch a place, the Elders in ſuch a place, as the Church of <hi>Antioch, Act.</hi> 13. 1. and the Church at <hi>Corinth, 1 Cor.</hi> 1. 1. and by the like reaſon the Elders in ſuch a place doe ſignifie the proper Elders of the Church in that place or City, whileſt but one, and therefore, if by the Elders in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> had been meant in this place onely the Elders met from all Quarters at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> as the place of that Aſſembly, there had been a great ambiguity, ſeeing the more uſuall and proper import of that expreſſion is to note out the fixed ſtanding Elders of a place, and the Church in a place. Again, ſecondly, in the fourth verſe <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> are ſaid to bee received of the Church and Apoſtles and Elders, namely of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar relation to it. Yea, thirdly, the ſtanding Elders of that place aſſumed to themſelves to have written the Decrees, <hi>Chap. 21. 25. As touching the Gentiles wee have written and concluded.</hi> Fourthly, and accordingly the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of their Letter is made the ſpeciall Act of that Church, and the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders thereof, <hi>ver.</hi> 22. It pleaſed the <hi>Apoſtles and Elders with the whole Church</hi> (that is) of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as <hi>verſe 4. to ſend choſen men,</hi> and the Letters run thus, <hi>The Apoſtles, Elders and Brethren.</hi> Fifthly, the matter of the Letter ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues it, <hi>ver. 24. Foraſmuch as certain that went out from us have troubled you with words, to whom wee gave no ſuch Commandement.</hi> How could this bee ſaid by a Synod of the Elders of thoſe Churches, which were themſelves trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by them? It is manifeſt therefore they came out from this Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who wrote this, and they pretended the Apoſtles Doctrine; which is called a Commandement, becauſe the Apoſtles taught no other, then what Chriſt commanded, as <hi>Matth. 28. ult.</hi> And to ſay the Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was from the more eminent part, namely, the Elders of that Church
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121181:18"/>
had been derogatory to the Synod, if it had been ſuch a meeting. And ſixth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if the Elders of all thoſe Churches had been preſent, there had been leſſe need for the Apoſtles and Elders of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to have ſent choſen men to carry the Letters, and withall to ſhew the grounds of thoſe their judgements by word of mouth, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. 27. 31. This needed not, if their own Elders had been preſent, and ſo had been to have returned; and if they were ſent as Meſſengers from the Synod, then to all the Churches as well as to <hi>Antioch,</hi> and why doe they then goe no further then unto <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch? ver.</hi> 33. Yea, and although <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> delivered thoſe reſults to all the Cities, yet, as it ſhould ſeem accidentally and not principally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, they goe not on purpoſe chiefely to deliver thoſe decrees, but <hi>ver.</hi> 36. of <hi>chap.</hi> 15. it was <hi>Pauls</hi> motion upon other grounds to go viſit the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in every City, where they had Preached, and ſo but occaſionally deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered theſe Decrees, <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. 4. So as they came to them not as ſent in a mandatory way, as to Churches ſubject to that Synod by a Synodical Law, (as ſuch Canons are uſed to bee ſent) but as the judgement onely of this Church, and the Apoſtles delivered them for their edification.</p>
                  <p>And in the third place, If there were any further authority or juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in their Decrees, it was from the Apoſtles, who were preſent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred in it, and who had power over all the Churches; and accordingly though the Elders in the whole Church were preſent and joyned with the Apoſtles, <hi>Quantum in ſe,</hi> to conſent and approve their Decrees with that ſeverall reſpective kinde of judgment proper unto them, yet all the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority put forth over theſe Churches was that tranſcendent authority of the Apoſtles, which is not now left in all the Elders of the world joyned together; and that therefore theſe Decrees made, and the deciſion of theſe queſtions here, were by infallible Apoſtolicall authority, and to that end they ſubjoyned that Apoſtolicall Seale, <hi>It ſeemed good to us and the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And although the ordinary Elders, yea, and the whole Church joyned in this, yet but according to their Meaſure, Analogy, and Proportion of their faith, even as in writing ſome Epiſtles <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Silvanus</hi> joyned with <hi>Paul,</hi> but yet <hi>Paul</hi> onely wrote Apoſtolically, and the authority in them is looked at as his; or elſe becauſe perhaps they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Holy Ghoſt falne on them through the Apoſtles Doctrine then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered (which was then uſuall) perſwading their hearts unanimouſly (though afore diſſenting, as <hi>ver.</hi> 25.) to accord, in that reſpect they might ſpeak this in ſuch a ſenſe, that no aſſembly of men wanting Apoſtolicall preſence and inſtruction, may now ſpeak. And although it may bee object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That then this Letter and theſe Decrees ſhould bee formall Scripture, and ſo binde us ſtill,</hi> it is anſwered; That they are Scripture, and written for our learning; and if the caſe were the ſame upon which they obliged
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121181:19"/>
them then, (<hi>viz.</hi> matter of offence) that then they would binde us now: but the things being enjoyned, but as <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, things of a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added caſuall neceſſity and not abſolute, in caſe of offence onely and not ſimply for the things themſelves, therefore now the neceſſity being ceaſed, the obligation ceaſeth, yet ſo as the equity of the rule and ground theſe were commanded upon, <hi>to abſtain from things that will offend our brethren,</hi> doth hold in like caſes to the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>And laſt of all, there is no act of ſuch authority and government put forth in it, which the Propoſition intendeth; which will appeare, if wee ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſider the <hi>occaſion and riſe of it,</hi> or the <hi>iſſue and reſult of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was not a ſet or ſtated meeting by common agreement of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but <hi>Antioch</hi> ſends to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> unknowne to them; there are no ſummons ſent to ſend up Delinquents, nor can wee finde theſe diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are ſent to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to bee cenſured by thoſe Eccleſiaſticall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhments in which, Government doth properly lye and conſiſt; The ſubject matter ſent to them for their deciſion was meerely matter of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>about this queſtion, verſe 2. and about this word, verſe</hi> 5. Namely, whether the Ceremoniall Law was to bee obſerved? Concerning which they wrote their judgements dogmatically, which they were called to doe, being thus ſent unto; Neither doth it argue that it was more then to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine this queſtion doctrinally they came up for, becauſe that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> could have decided that before, being themſelves Apoſtles, and that therefore their comming up was for diſcipline againſt Delinquents; for as the caſe ſtood, they liſtened not to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> as Apoſtles, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the judgment of the other Apoſtles; For indeed <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> did declare their judgements, the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>contention, ver.</hi> 3. being attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted unto them as contending againſt the falſe Teachers for the Truth; and ſo as even the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> reſted not in their deciſion: Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> might have as Apoſtles cenſured thoſe Delinquents without comming to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as wel as by Apoſtolique authority have deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the queſtion. For Apoſtolicall power extended to Diſcipline as well as Doctrine. If it bee ſaid <hi>That even doctrinally to deliver the truth when it is done by a company of Elders hath authority or power in it,</hi> as when Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Goe and teach, all power is given unto mee:</hi> It is granted an Authoritie exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in doctrine and ſo to bee in Synods, but yet not Juriſdiction, which the Propoſition intends, which is when doctrines are delivered <hi>ſub paena,</hi> under the penaltie of that Eccleſiaſticall puniſhment of Excommunication if not received. One Miniſter alone hath a dogmaticall authoritie as a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to rebuke, exhort, and yet acts of Juriſdiction are not his alone, but of others conjoyned with him.</p>
                  <p>Neither, ſecondly, doth the titles given to theſe reſults of theirs argue a Juriſdiction
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121181:19"/>
in that they are called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 4. For although the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is uſed for an Imperiall decree <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 1. yet but rarely, and more commonly (as <hi>Stephanus</hi> and <hi>Budaeus</hi> obſerve) for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine &amp; opinion in matters morall or ſpeculative, as <hi>Platonis Dogma, &amp;c.</hi> and thence is tranſlated to import the Judgements of Divines given in matters Theologicall although delivered with certaintie. And ſo the uſing of this word implyeth the ſubject to have beene doctrinall onely and ſo delivered. And further the ſubject matter of this deciſion being about rules and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and the not obſervation of them, the [<hi>Dogma</hi>] is elegantly, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps on purpoſe, given to theſe Apoſtolicall Canons by way of oppoſition and contradiction to thoſe that taught and obſerved ſuch rules, who are ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in ſo doing, <hi>Coloſſians</hi> 2. 20. being led away by the falſe <hi>Dogmata,</hi> or <hi>Heterodox theſes</hi> of falſe Teachers that enjoyned them. And for that other word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> tranſlated [<hi>ordained,</hi>] it plainely notes out but this, that theſe doctrinall <hi>Theſes</hi> were the joynt declared and avowed Judgement and concluſions of theſe (and ſo anſwereth to thoſe other words in their letters <hi>(It ſeemeth good unto us, being with one accord, &amp;c.</hi>) Apoſtles and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders thus met with <hi>one accord</hi> agreeing therein, and particularly and una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly ſo judging; and therefore when <hi>James</hi> gives his judgement hee uſeth the ſame word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (Verſe 19. of this 15. Chap.) <hi>This is my judgement,</hi> which being voted and agreed upon by the reſt they are called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Neither doth this argue any act of authoritie that the things here declared to bee obſerved are indifferent, for ſome of them come under a morall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and all come under the caſe of offence.</p>
                  <p>Neither doth the language they commend thoſe to them in, ſound of that Juriſdiction or government intended in the propoſition; for although they ſeeme to ſpeake as guided infallibly in their reſolution, [<hi>it ſeemed good to us and to the holy Ghoſt</hi>] yet their expreſſions are carried ſo as to avoyd Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, thoſe words, <hi>To lay no other burthen,</hi> if any, muſt import this Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction; but theſe words, as <hi>Ludovicus de Dieu</hi> hath well obſerved, are (as they may bee) taken paſſively, therein agreeing with the Syriack tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation; <hi>It ſeemed good to and the holy Ghoſt, that no other burthen bee laid on you,</hi> that whereas theſe Teachers of the circumciſion had gone about by their doctrine to bind the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> upon mens conſciences, and to put on them <hi>a burthen too heavy for them to beare,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes Verſ. 9. and had taught this to bee the commands of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and the judgement of the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> They diſclaime this, and profeſſe they would have no ſuch burthen put upon them, and that they gave theſe Teachers no ſuch commandement, that is, never delivered or uttered any ſuch Doctrine to bee commanded. And if it bee taken actively, yet the declaring it to bee the command of Chriſt is the impoſition here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121181:20"/>
for the ſame words are uſed of the Teachers who yet had not aſſumed by vertue of an Eccleſiaſticall authority to impoſe theſe things but by way of Doctrine, So Verſe the tenth, <hi>Why tempt you God to put a yoake upon the necke of the Diſciples?</hi> Verſ. 5. And it is well knowne that in the Scripture phraſe to teach and to declare, though by way of Doctrine, and to preſſe mens conſciences with things as the commands of God, is ſaid to bee a binding and impoſing a burthen on them. So of the Phariſees (and theſe were of the ſect of the Phariſees, of whom, and to whom that was ſpoken, Verſe 5.) it is ſaid, <hi>Matth. 23. 4. that the Phariſees bind heavy burthens and grievous to bee borne, and lay them on mens ſhoulders;</hi> which is ſpoken but of a doctrinall declaring and preſſing mens conſciences with the rigour of the Law; and this is ſo well knowne to bee the Language of the Jewes, that it need not bee inſiſted on.</p>
                  <p>Neither doth it follow that if they may lay theſe burthens by way of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, they may cenſure for the neglect of them, for every Miniſter in his Sermon impoſeth thoſe burthens whilſt they urge and declare theſe duties to men, and yet have not power Eccleſiaſtically to cenſure them, for though it being a command of Chriſt they could not but hold it forth as ſuch and ſo urge it; yet not by way of Juriſdiction, but with theſe ſoft words, <hi>which if you obſerve you doe well.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, although theſe falſe Teachers had ſubverted their faith, and againſt their owne light, had avouched their Doctrine to bee the doctrine of the Apoſtles, which deſerved the higheſt cenſure being a ſinne ſo ſcandalous, yet they proceeded not to cenſure them by way of admonition or excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication (which are acts of government) but onely do declare their ſinne and errour, and give their Judgement of it. Whereas in the cloſe of the proofe from the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for many Congregations to bee under one Presbyteriall government, it is aſſerted whether theſe Congregations bee fixed or not fixed it is all one to the truth of the propoſition; this reaſon is offered againſt it. There is this difference, every Congregation having Elders fixed to it is a Church; for the relation of Elders and Church is mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, <hi>Acts 14. 23. They ordained Elders in every Church;</hi> This relation of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to a Church is a ſpeciall diſtinct relation to that Congregation of which they are Elders, ſo as they are not related to other Congregations, and theſe Congregations are <hi>Eccleſiae primae,</hi> Churches formed up though uncompleat, as being according to <hi>our Brethrens</hi> opinion, members of a more generall Presbyteriall Church.</p>
                  <p>But if Congregations have no fixed Officers they are not Churches ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Principles. Now it makes a great difference as to the truth of the Propoſition, whether many Churches may bee under the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one, or whether many Congregations which to them are no Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121181:20"/>
may bee under the government of one? Whatſoever <hi>our Brethren</hi> ſhew of divers Congregations to bee under the government of a Church Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, yet they no where ſhew any one patterne or example in Scripture wherein many Churches were under the power of one, nay nor where any one Church was under the power of another.</p>
                  <p>And laſtly, if there were many Congregations in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> having their Officers fixed to them, and not in common, then during the time before the diſperſion the Apoſtles muſt bee thoſe Officers that were thus fixedly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of to thoſe ſeverall Congregations, ſome over one, others over ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as ordinary Elders now are. Now ſuppoſe this number of Beleevers to have beene as many thouſands as is argued, at 10. or 12000. ſoules, and theſe to bee divided into as many Congregations as might bee divided to twelve Apoſtles ſeverally to watch over; Or ſuppoſe the ſeverall Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made up of 2000. (which is an alotment ſmall enough to bee ſet apart for the paines of two Apoſtles.</p>
                  <p>Hereupon great incongruitie doth follow, that Apoſtles are brought to the ſtate and condition and worke of Pariſh Miniſters, to whom yet it was committed, and inſeparably annexed to their Office, yea and conſtituted it, as Apoſtles, to have the care of all Churches; and if when the Churches were multiplyed and diſperſed into ſeverall Countries, they were to have the care of them, then much more when they were in one Citie. Some of the writers againſt Epiſcopacie, (when thoſe that write for it alledg the inſtance of <hi>James</hi> abiding at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as the Biſhop of that Church) have judged it a debaſing of the Apoſtolicall power to limit it to one <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Church: but this poſition doth debaſe all the Apoſtles at once, much more it makes them not Biſhops to many Churches, but ordinary Elders, in that one or two of them perhaps, are over one ſingle Church; yea, and which is yet more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, if theſe Churches and their government were like to thoſe under the Presbytery, and no materiall difference betweene them and ours, theſe Apoſtles were in their ſeverall Pariſhes not onely ſubordinate in their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to the common Presbytery of all the Apoſtles, but limited to leſſer Acts of government, for ſo the leſſer Elderſhips in the Churches under the Presbyteriall government are confined onely to examine, and admoniſh, and prepare for the greater Presbytery, and therein not enabled to ordaine Elders over the Congregation, or excommunicate a member: <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> joyned together were by this principle not enabled to it. And yet if we doe not ſuppoſe ſuch a limited government in thoſe ſeverall Congregations, here can bee no patterne for the Presbyterian government as it is practiſed. Or if otherwiſe wee ſhould ſuppoſe them fixed Officers for teaching onely to one of thoſe Congregations, and to have no government at all over it, but
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121181:21"/>
to bring all to the common Presbytery of Apoſtles, that is a greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruitie then the former; for this caſts them below the condition of our Pariſh Elders, for unto them the greater Presbytery doth allow ſome meaſure and part of the Government, but ſuch a ſuppoſition would allow Apoſtles none in their ſeverall Congregations.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <head>The Scripture holds forth that many Congregations may be under one Presbyteriall Government.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 1.</head>
                  <p>BY particular Congregations either firſt an Aſſembly of Chriſtians meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for worſhip onely, as to heare, pray, &amp;c. or ſecondly, an Aſſembly ſo furniſhed with Officers as fit for Diſcipline having a Presbytery, is meant; in the latter ſenſe, which is that the proofs are brought to confirme, and that that is practiſed where this government is ſet up, the propoſition is equivalent to ſuch an aſſertion as this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Many Presbyteries may bee under one Presbyteriall government, as thus, many Parochiall Presbyteries may bee under one Claſſicall, many Claſſicall, under one Provinciall, &amp;c. which is the ſame as to affirme that one Presbytery may bee over another, as the Biſhops affirme. That one Presbyter may bee over another, this is evident, if you aſſert a Presbyteriall government may bee over a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is compoſed of a Presbytery and people: for it cannot bee ſaid to bee over a Congregation, if it bee over the people onely, that is not over their Presbytery alſo, for then the Presbytery will be Independent, and the people under two Presbyteries coordinate and not ſubordinate, which ſtands not with common reaſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 2.</head>
                  <p>This then being the Aſſertion, it is thus argued againſt. A Presbytery over a Presbytery, or power over power neceſſarily implyeth two ſorts of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries, or Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdictions, ſpecifically diſtinct or at leaſt more then numerically. A greater or leſſer vary not the kind in a Phyſicall or The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologicall conſideration, but in a Politicall it doth; Hee that hath a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter power then I have, that is a power over my power, a power to order, direct or correct the power I have, this mans power and mine differ as two ſorts or kinds of power. And although this ſuperior Presbytery bee made up of Presbyters ſent as Commiſſioners from the congregationall or paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiall Presbyteries, yet this hinders not at all but that they may bee thus
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121181:21"/>
diſtinct; For ſome Cities and townes corporate their Officers are ſent up, &amp; ſit as Members of Parliament, yet this Honorable Houſe hath a power di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſuperior to that which is in <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Yorke,</hi> though the ſuperior Presbytery bee made up of Presbyters from ſeverall Congregations, yet it is not made up of Presbyteries, it hath the perſons materially conſidered, but not that power formally conſidered: for as while the Parliament ſits and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Burgeſſes from Burrough townes ſit as Members in it, theſe Townes notwithſtanding ſtill retaine all the power thoſe Corporations were ever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with; ſo particular Congregations whilſt ſome of their Elders ſit in the Claſſicall Presbytery, have Elderſhips or a Presbytery ſtill. Now that it is very probable the Scripture holds not forth two ſorts of Presbyteries thus ſpecifically diſtinct, may bee thus argued.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 3.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, where the Scripture holds forth diſtinct ſorts in any kinde, there will bee found either diſtinct and proper names and titles, or at leaſt ſome adjunct or difference added to that which is common or generall; In the Apoſtles times there were Presbyters over Presbyters, Apoſtles were ſuperior to Prophets, and Prophets a diſtinct order from Teachers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Therefore in 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Corinth. 12. God hath ſet ſome in the Church: Firſt Apoſtles, ſecondarily Prophets, thirdly Teachers, after that Miracles, then gifts of Healings, &amp;c.</hi> They have not onely particular names and titles, but ſpeciall notes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction added, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as in <hi>Geneſis</hi> 1. where no diſtinction in names is given, The Sunne, Moon, and Starres of Heaven, are all called Lights, yet there are termes of difference added, they are called firſt great Lights, and then the greater to rule the day, and the leſſer to rule the night.</p>
                  <p>Throughout the New Teſtament wee finde this word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but in three places, whereof there is but one that holdeth out the Government in hand, and in that place you have the naked word onely without the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of any ſuch expreſſion, greater, leſſer, ſuperiour, inferior, or any kinde of adjunct, that can poſſibly put a thought in us, of more Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries then one. Notwithſtanding ſo uſefull are peculiar diſtinct names where there are diſtinct ſorts or kindes of adminiſtration, as it is not omitted by any Church in their Ordinances for Government; in <hi>Scotland</hi> the loweſt is termed a Conſiſtory, the next a Claſſis or Presbytery, the third a Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Synod, the fourth a Generall Aſſembly. The <hi>French</hi> in theſe termes, <hi>Conſiſtories,</hi> and <hi>Colloquel,</hi> and <hi>Synods:</hi> ſo in the Epiſcopall Republique there was the like varietie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 4.</head>
                  <p>Secondly, As the Scriptures hold forth nothing in any title or name to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121181:22"/>
diſtinguiſh, no more can wee thence diſcover any ſorts of Government dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in nature; for tryall of this, let it bee ſuppoſed there is a Parochiall or Conſiſtorian Presbytery for one ſort, there is another ſort wee call Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall, what Scripture gives light by any kinde of reaſoning to warrant the ſetting up one of thoſe above, or over the other? Doe you read any where God hath ſet in his Church, firſt Presbyteries, ſecondarily Claſſes, then Conſiſtories? Or is there any thing in the word directing a different compoſition or conſtitution in theſe?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 5.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, For the <hi>materiale,</hi> the Perſons that theſe Presbyteries are made up of, are the ſame; The Conſiſtory hath gifted men ſet apart to the Office of the Miniſtery; Thoſe that are in a Claſſicall Presbytery are no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe qualifyed, nor indeed doth the Scripture require any thing but a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteration to qualifie men for any ſort, if there were ſorts of Presbytery.</p>
                  <p>That there is a greater number of Presbyters in the one then in the other, this alters not the ſtate in reſpect of the matter; for if the number bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, that is, ſo many as two or three may agree, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. it ſufficeth. The Honourable <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> is to all Parliamentary purpoſes as much a Houſe, when but two or three above forty, as when foure hundred. Nor doth this alwayes fall out that all Claſſicall Presbyteries have a greater number then ſome Parochiall. Scriptures have determined neither how few will conſtitute a Claſſicall Presbytery, nor how many may bee in a Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiall: Practice many times maketh them equall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 6.</head>
                  <p>Secondly, Now for the <hi>Formale,</hi> the uniting of this matter into a <hi>Conſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> or <hi>Caetus,</hi> Presbyters become united into a Presbytery in the Claſſicall, by having Paſtorall charges in ſuch a diviſion, whoſoever commeth ſo to be diſpoſed of, hee is no ſooner Paſtor to ſuch a Pariſh, but hee is <hi>eo nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> Member of ſuch a Claſſis. The Presbyters of a Parochiall Presbytery are as neerely united and more: They are united in the choyce and call of the ſame Congregation they governe, and united in the whole work of the Miniſtery over the ſame people; ſo that they are not onely fellow Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, but fellow Labourers in the ſame Vineyard. There is therefore no juſt ground for ſuch a diſtinction or difference between Presbytery and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery in reſpect either of the matter or the forme.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 7.</head>
                  <p>Thirdly, Nor thirdly, do wee finde any thing in the Scriptures making them, as from different imployments, or functions, to differ; firſt, wee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and ſo it is in the propoſition, the one is ſuperiour, the other inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; But how can you ſay the Scriptures have made this difference, when
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121181:22"/>
there is not a word ſpoken this way in any place. Presbyterian Writers themſelves in ſome expreſſions ſeem to take away utterly ſuch difference as this; in one place you ſhall read the Claſſis can doe nothing, <hi>renitente Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia,</hi> but it is <hi>null</hi> and invalid; Thus the Aſſertion for Diſcipline, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouches <hi>Zepperus, Zanchy,</hi> and others as of this opinion. The Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though but <hi>minima Eccleſiola,</hi> yet may reforme, that is, ſuſpend, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, &amp;c. <hi>Renitentibus correſpondentiis.</hi> So <hi>Voetius</hi> in his <hi>Theſes, &amp; deſperata cauſa Papatus, lib. 2. Sect. 2. c.</hi> 12. Surely according to what theſe Reverend Divines have expreſſed, it is hard to bee ſaid, which of theſe Presbyteries hath the greater or ſuperiour power.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 8.</head>
                  <p>Secondly, the imployment or work of a Presbytery is to ordain, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, ſuſpend, admit Members, appoint times for worſhip and the like. The Claſſicall Presbytery reſerve ordination, and excommunication to themſelves, but the other are left to the Parochiall Presbytery: Thus ſome Presbyterians divide the work. Others poſſibly otherwiſe. But how can wee affirm any ſuch deſignment from the Scriptures, if you have not two ſorts, either in name or nature to bee found there? and none of theſe Acts or Adminiſtrations but may bee done by that one the Scripture mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, which doubtleſſe they may, ſeeing Ordination ſeemeth to bee ſpecifyed in the Text; if the greater, then doubtleſſe the leſſer. The Paſtor in one place is ſaid to <hi>exhort,</hi> in another to <hi>comfort,</hi> in another to <hi>viſit the ſicke,</hi> this will not warrant diſtinct ſorts of Paſtors, for there being but one ſort ſpoken of in Scriptures, wee muſt interpret all theſe ſeverall Adminiſtrations to belong to that one.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 9.</head>
                  <p>It was not found an eaſie work in this <hi>Aſſembly</hi> to finde two ſorts of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, teaching, and ruling. Notwithſtanding all the Scripture hath ſaid of theſe, and in ſome places, ſo plaine, as if of purpoſe to diſtinguiſh them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If it bee ſo hard a matter by Scripture light to hold forth two ſorts of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, it muſt needs bee more difficult to finde out two ſorts of Presbyteries, eſpecially ſeeing (as it is generally granted, and this by the Presbyterians themſelves) that for above fifty yeeres after Chriſt, and in the Apoſtles times, there was but one kinde of Presbytery.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 10.</head>
                  <p>It hath been the wiſdome of States to keep and preſerve the bounds and limits of their Judicatures evident, and diſtinct, and as free from contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie as may bee. If Laws and Ordinances about matters of <hi>m<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um</hi> and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> and ſuch inferiour claimes ſhould not bee ſo evident, the authority of theſe Courts will bee in a readineſſe to relieve wrongs and injuries through
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121181:23"/>
ſuch miſtakings. But Controverſies and claſhings about theſe high and publique intereſts are no other in the iſſue then the dividing of a Kingdome within it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Is man wiſer in his Generation then <hi>Jeſus Chriſt? Hee is our Law-giver, the Government is laid upon his ſhoulders; hee is the wonderfull Counſellor, the Prince of Peace.</hi> And therefore ſurely though other matters of practice and duty ſhould have obſcurity in the rule. Yet it is moſt probable hee hath ordered Authority and Juriſdiction with the Officers and Offices, for the managing of it ſo evident, as not to put us to ſearch in a dark corner for directions. Wee cannot bee ſaid to bee cleere in our rule when wee are thus inforced out of one word, and but once uſed, to raiſe ſo many Thrones, or Formes of Government, eſpecially it being foreſeen by Chriſt that ſuch is the nature of man as nothing occaſions more bitter contention then that luſting which is in us to have Authority and juriſdiction over others.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sic ſubſcribitur:
<list>
                     <item>Tho. Goodwin,</item>
                     <item>Philip Nye.</item>
                     <item>Jer. Burroughes,</item>
                     <item>Sidrach Sympſon.</item>
                     <item>William Bridge,</item>
                     <item>William Greenhill,</item>
                     <item>William Carter.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Concordat cum Originali.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Adoniram Byfield, <hi>Scriba.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <pb facs="tcp:121181:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
