<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Act and proclamation, that none come from Ireland without sufficient testimonial. Edinburgh, 22. February, 1661.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1037</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.26[67]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210943</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869691</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869691</idno>
            <idno type="VID">163949</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A92471)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 163949)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 247:669f26[67])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Act and proclamation, that none come from Ireland without sufficient testimonial. Edinburgh, 22. February, 1661.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: the second 1 has been crossed out and replaced with "1660" in both caption and imprint dates.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:163949:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <head>ACT And PROCLAMATION, That none come from Ireland without ſufficient Teſtimonial.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Edinburgh, <date>22. February, 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as it is informed, That many Seditious and Turbulent perſons, Miniſters and others, in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> finding that the Adminiſtration of his Majeſties Authority and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is now happily eſtabliſhed in that Kingdom, doth not ſute, nor will comply with their Phanatick principles and factious practices, are comeing over into this Kingdom expecting ſhelter, that they may be the more enabled to carry on their deſigns, in perverting the Allegiance of the Subjects, and ſubverting the Peace of the Kingdom: And the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of Parliament conſidering how much it doth concern the publick Peace, that ſuch Waſps and unworthy perſons, enemies to all lawfull Authority, and to whom it is naturall to ſtir up Sedition, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Peace, wherever they are, and therefore cannot well be allowed in any well conſtituted Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſhould have no countenance in this Kingdom: Therefore the Kings Majeſty, with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and conſent of His Eſtates of Parliament, doth hereby declare, That no perſons whatſoever, coming from <hi>Ireland</hi> without a ſufficient Paſſe and Teſtimony in writ, from the Lord Iuſtices Council, or any having power from them, or from the Sheriff of the County, or Mayor of the City where the ſaids perſons lived, of their peaceable carriage and conformity to the Laws, ſhall be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any reſidence, reſſet, or ſtay within this Kingdom: But that it ſhall be lawfull to, likeas all Sheriffs, Magiſtrates and Iuſtices of Peace are required hereby to ſeaze upon, and impriſon all ſuch perſons, wanting ſuch Teſtimony; And who ſhall not willingly remove out of the Kingdom within fifteen dayes after the intimation hereof unto them (excepting from this clauſe all ordinary known Trafficking Merchants) And His Majeſty, with advice aforeſaid, ordains, That all ſuch perſons as ſhall come over with any ſuch Teſtimony, that within fifteen dayes after their Landing, they make their appearance before the Parliament; or in caſe of their not ſitting, before his Majeſties Privy Council, or ſuch as ſhallbe warranted by them, and make known the reaſons of their coming hither, and give ſuch ſurety as ſhall be thought fit, for their peaceable carriage; otherwiſe, to remove off the Kingdom within fifteen dayes: Wherein if they failȝie, Magiſtrates, Sheriffs, and all others, publick Miniſters, are hereby ordained, as they will be anſwerable upon their duty, to Apprehend, Secure and Impriſon them, till ſuch courſe be taken, as ſhall be thought fit, with ſuch Seditious and Factious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. And ordains thir preſents to endure for one year, and longer, as ſhall be thought fit by the Lords of his Majeſties Privy Council; And to be printed, and publiſhed at the Mercat-Croſſes of <hi>Edinburgh, Glaſgow, Air, Irwin, Wigton, Kircudbright,</hi> and all other places needfull, where-through none pretend ignorance hereof.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>A. Primeroſe,</hi> Cls. Reg.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Edinburgh, Printed by Evan Tyler, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
