<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second humble addresse of those who are called Anabaptists in the county of Lincoln Presented to His Majesty, Charles the Second, King of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.26[59]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210922</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869671</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869671</idno>
            <idno type="VID">163941</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A92812)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 163941)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 247:669f26[59])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second humble addresse of those who are called Anabaptists in the county of Lincoln Presented to His Majesty, Charles the Second, King of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Grantham, Thomas, 1634-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Simon Dover, in Martins near Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660. [i.e. 1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Praying for the redress of their grievances.</note>
                  <note>The first 'e' on the title page is printed backwards.</note>
                  <note>Signed by Thomas Grentham (i.e. Grantham) and 29 others.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 6."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  England --  Lincolnshire --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:163941:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <head>THE SECOND HUMBLE ADDRESSE Of thoſe who are Called ANABAPTISTS IN The County of Lincoln.</head>
            <head>Preſented to His MAJESTY, CHARLES the Second, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>May it Pleaſe Your Majeſty,</opener>
            <p>ONce more to permit Your Diſtreſſed (yet Faithful) Subjects, to ſpread their Innocency and ſorrow of Heart before You; it ſeems it muſt needs be that Offences do or ſhall come; but the Wo is deſervedly their Portion (only) by whom the Offence cometh: And were it not that we had that ſtrong Fort <hi>Innocency</hi> to fly unto, we durſt not in this miſerable Day once dare to make our Addreſs unto You.</p>
            <p>But having this to ſupport us in this Tottering Age, we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore boldly (yet in all Humility) ſolemnly declare, That not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the many wicked Practiſes ſpoken of, or done againſt Your Majeſty and Government; yet is our Hearts and Hands Clean and Pure here-from, as utterly Abominable, and held in great deteſtation in our Judgements and Principles, as is further Declared by our Addreſs formerly; according to which former Addreſs, we hold our ſelves bound, as alſo by Your great Favours to us vouchſafed, when by Your Princely Favour permitted to be preſent with Your Self, we are abundantly engaged; ſo have we made it, and ſo ſhall we make it (the God of Heaven and Earth aſſiſting of us) our great Care to Diſcharge our Duties in every Reſpect to the utmoſt of our Ability, as becomes the Children of God, and Subjects to the King.</p>
            <p>We have not wanted hearty Deſires to ſignifie our Opinions and Reſolutions touching the Government of this Nation, and of our deportment under the ſame, by a general Agreement of all our Brethren, in the ſame Form of Profeſſion with us, but have been prevented partly by the unſeaſonableneſs of the time; and partly by the negligence of ſome betruſted in the Buſineſs; and partly by the unhappy Tumults and Diſturbances made and committed by men who fear not to ſpeak evil of Dignities: And Laſtly, We are altogether Incapacitated for ſuch an undertaking by your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties late <hi>Proclamation,</hi> prohibiting all Meetings of ſuch as are denominated <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O King, we muſt confeſs there is too notorious Cauſe for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſince Clemency and Mercy hath been abuſed; but the abuſers of Mercy ought (only) to feel the ſmart of their miſdoings: But Oh let the Innocent have the Reward of their Innocency, even the Continuation of Mercy, ſo will Your Throne be Eſtabliſhed in Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>When we read Your Letter from <hi>Breda,</hi> and the Revival there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in Your <hi>Declaration for Eccleſiaſtical Affairs;</hi> and Your Princely Promiſes to us, when by Your Clemency permitted to be preſent with Your Self.</p>
            <p>O King, when we remember theſe things, we are ready to ſay (not why was the Kings Proclamation ſo haſty, but) why was the extention thereof ſo large? Shall the Righteous ſuffer with the Wicked? God forbid. Muſt your peaceable Subjects be judged Rioters, whilſt many unpeaceable ones (ſuch as Swearers and Drunkards) are freed from that judgement? The Lord will not accompany ſuch proceedings.</p>
            <p>Our humble Requeſt from theſe Premiſes are, That there may be a Righteous diſtinction in the Adminiſtration of Puniſhment; leſt the Cryes of the Innocent and their ruined Families come up before the Lord, whilſt your Priſons are filled with ſuch as whoſe Prayers have come up to the Throne of Grace on Your Majeſties behalf, and can approve their hearts to the Lord in reſpect of Loyalty and good Fidelity to Your Majeſty, and Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Nation under Your hands.</p>
            <p>It is indeed matter of ſorrow, to ſee how the notorious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane do rejoice at the preſent ſufferings of the innocent; who therefore are occaſioned to pray, that wiſdom may be given from God unto Your Majeſty to execute the Law juſtly, puniſhing the Evil-doer, and preſerving all that do well.</p>
            <p>But to avoid Prolixity (O King) be pleaſed to know, that Your poor Subjects dare not refuſe their innocent Meetings, wherein their work is ſincerely to Worſhip God, &amp; pray for Your Majeſty, and for all men as in duty they are bound, ſeeing the Authority by which they are dehorted from the neglect of their Aſſemblies, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 25. is greater than any, whereby Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty can enjoyn the neglect thereof.</p>
            <p>And therefore though it coſt us the loſs of all that we have and are, as to things of an outward conſideration; yet dare we not ſhrink from ſo great a loſs.</p>
            <p>Yet are we Reſolved in the ſtrength of God, not to Rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any of Your Majeſties Commands: But in caſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſcionably Act, we humbly purpoſe and heartily pray for ſtrength to ſuffer patiently and joyfully; and therefore cheerfully and faithfully do once more ſubſcribe our ſelves Your Humble and Obedient, though at this inſtant your Impriſoned and Diſtreſſed Subjects and Petitioners,
</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Thomas Grentham</item>
                     <item>Will. Burton</item>
                     <item>John Thorpe</item>
                     <item>Rich. Crawforth</item>
                     <item>Valentine James</item>
                     <item>Richard Drewry</item>
                     <item>John Kelſay</item>
                     <item>John Skiritt</item>
                     <item>John Lupton</item>
                     <item>John Watts</item>
                     <item>Edward Sharpe</item>
                     <item>Charles Warwike</item>
                     <item>Will. Lillye</item>
                     <item>John Allan</item>
                     <item>Robert Drewry</item>
                     <item>Chriſtoph. Ording</item>
                     <item>Rich. Hanſon</item>
                     <item>John Green</item>
                     <item>Will. Pridgon</item>
                     <item>Daniel Cheeſman</item>
                     <item>Ralph James</item>
                     <item>Rob. Cox</item>
                     <item>Tho. Brampton</item>
                     <item>John Norfolke</item>
                     <item>Richard Mathin</item>
                     <item>Will. Smith</item>
                     <item>Tho. Renolds</item>
                     <item>Rich. Wray</item>
                     <item>Will. Heart</item>
                     <item>Tho. Muksworth.</item>
                  </list>Subſcribed in behalf of themſelves, and the ſeveral Congregations unto which they are Relared in the County of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Simon Dover,</hi> in <hi>Martins</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
