<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triumph of beautie· As it was personated by some young gentlemen, for whom it was intended, at a private recreation. / By James Shirley.</title>
            <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1149_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202316</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203565</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863487</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863487</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170122</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A93180)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 165:E1149[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triumph of beautie· As it was personated by some young gentlemen, for whom it was intended, at a private recreation. / By James Shirley.</title>
                  <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 [i.e. 28], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley, and are to be sold at his shop, at the signe of the Princes Armes in St Pauls Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLVI. [1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also issued as part of his: Poems, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>P. 28 misnumbered 30.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170122:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRIVMPH OF BEAVTIE. As it was perſonated by ſome young Gentlemen, for whom it was intended, at a private Recreation.</p>
            <p>By JAMES SHIRLEY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, at the Signe of the Princes Armes in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard. MDCXLVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170122:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170122:2"/>
            <head>THE Triumph of Beauty.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Bottle, Crab, Clout, Toad-ſtoole, Shrub, Scrip, Hobbinoll, Shepheards: <hi>they overtake, and hang upon</hi> Bottle, <hi>and cry:</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
                  <hi>Bottle,</hi> a <hi>Bottle!</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>I am out of winde. So, ſo, are we all here? good men and true ſtand together, and heare your charge. Hum, hum.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bottle</hi> has ſomething in him. I knew him of a little one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scr.</speaker>
               <p>A very ſucking Bottle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Peace <hi>Scrip</hi> and <hi>Hobbinoll, Toad-stoole</hi> draw a little nearer,—you all know—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Crab.</speaker>
               <p>What doe you know?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Silence neighbour <hi>Crab,</hi>—which of you all is ſo wiſe, as to know what I would ſay now?
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170122:3"/>
why there's it, &amp; yet you will be prating ignorant Pup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies and a man ſhould knock your braines out— You all know, I ſay—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay agen, we know not. <hi>Bottle</hi> you forget your ſelfe, you call'd us all ignorant Puppies. But now, and now agen you ſay we all know.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>—The Prince excuſe me, you all know <hi>Paris</hi> the Prince of <hi>Troy.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
               <p>We know him now, but it was a myſterie for many yeares.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ho.</speaker>
               <p>Our young Lord and Maſter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Why very good then, and yet I muſt bee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted? No, no, <hi>Bottle</hi> is a drie coxcombe, an emptie foole. Bo'y te'e; make the Prince merrie your ſelves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scr.</speaker>
               <p>Nay <hi>Bottle,</hi> ſweet <hi>Bottle,</hi> ſweet <hi>Bottle;</hi> you will never leave this peeviſh humour <hi>Crabbe;</hi> come, he is ſorrie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I am ſorrie; but will you not give a man leave to ſpeake?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Speake? yes, but then you muſt not talke and bolt ſuch peremptorie queſtions, when I miſ-call you for your owne good. What is't to me, and the Prince ſhall take a convenient twig, or drowne himſelfe in one of his melancholy fits: I can live, when you have all betaken your ſelves to Hempe, I can. Only I preferre the publick good before all the world, and and the Prince before that, and my ſelfe before the Prince, and my wife before my ſelfe, and your wife neighbour before her: I know what's what. But what's all this? unleſſe we be reconciled and perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly divided among our ſelves. I know you all love me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170122:3"/>
               <speaker>Scr.</speaker>
               <p>I love <hi>Bottle with my heart.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>But the Prince is another manner of man, though I ſay't, and every day falls away with a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of melancholy; if we ſhall joyne our Panniers, to make him merry with ſome rare and pleaſant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice —why; your old friend and <hi>Bottle,</hi> and ſo forth. Now let every man ſpeake his opinion freely, as his owne want of diſcretion ſhall direct him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ho.</speaker>
               <p>Some new device? there be a thouſand new devices, and a man could but remember one on 'em.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sc.</speaker>
               <p>Stay ſome ſtrange ſhapes <hi>Bottle.</hi>—Silence, what doe you thinke and wee ſhould all be Fiſhes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>He ſayes well for ſilence, this muſt conſiſt of Mutes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scr.</speaker>
               <p>I can play a Mute rarely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Crab.</speaker>
               <p>You the Mute? as if no-body could ſpeake but you: you the Mute?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ho.</speaker>
               <p>And the river hard by, will ſerve us rarely to act in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scr.</speaker>
               <p>And when we dance under water, no bodie can ſee our footing. And you love me, let me be a Whale: oh I can foot it curiouſly; and I can drinke like a Fiſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>No. I doe not like theſe Water-works. I was in a faire election to be drown'd at the laſt ſheep-ſhearing; and the Cramp is a thing to be conſidered. No Water-works.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>What doe you ſay to Birds: a Device of Birds?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Birds? You'll be an Owle too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>I have been taken for one in a tree a hundred times.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170122:4"/>
               <hi>He counterfeits the voice of an Owle.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>No, I have thought of a conceit—dee hear? we ſcorne fiſhes, they are dull, phlegmatick things, and your Birds at beſt are melancholly matters. What doe you think of—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>Beaſts then: let us all be Beaſts <hi>Bottle.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Be all Aſſes will you not? Bou'y tee agen. Play the fooles your ſelves, doe, and ſee how the Prince will like it, if <hi>Bottle</hi> be out. I am a puppy, I? no, no.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scr.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, nay, honeſt <hi>Bottle:</hi> did you not bid e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man ſpeak according to his diſcretion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>I grant you; but is there diſcretion in a Beaſt? Let us all play the Beaſts quotha? Oh, I could bee as muſty as the Prince now; but I am of too ſweet a nature to flie out: which makes you preſume. Well, now or never, will you be rul'd yet?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>Now, and never too, <hi>Bottle?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
               <p>A <hi>Bottle,</hi> a <hi>Bottle.</hi> Silence, breake Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Why then, I'le make you all Princes or Lords, or ſomething elſe that ſhall bee little better: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are all Shepheards, wee'll doe a thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to our callings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <p>That, that <hi>Bottle.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>What doe you ſay? if we act the Tragedie of the golden Fleece?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
               <p>How? a Tragedy to make the Prince merry?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>There's the conceit: if he doe not laugh at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man of us, Ile loſe my part of the next poſſit, neighbour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170122:4"/>
               <speaker>Scr.</speaker>
               <p>He cannot chooſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>You all remember the ſtory of <hi>Jaſon,</hi> that ſail'd to <hi>Colchos,</hi> with <hi>Hercules,</hi> and a Company of Blades, where he kill'd the Brazen-footed Bulls, and the fierie Dragons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Let me ſee, how many Actors are wee?— The number will ſerve, well let me ſee, firſt, who ſhall doe <hi>Hercules</hi> in the Lions belly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>Belly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Why in the Lions skinne, 'tis all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shr.</speaker>
               <p>Ile doe <hi>Hercules.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>Let <hi>Shrub</hi> doe <hi>Hercules,</hi> he has plaid afore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shr.</speaker>
               <p>I have a Club already, and I know where a terrible Lion is, if any man will but flea off his skin for me: Let me alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Hee ſtruts and ſpeaks ſmall.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <p>A <hi>Shrub</hi> a <hi>Hercules.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Who ſhall do Lady <hi>Medea</hi> the Kings daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that fell in love with <hi>Jaſon,</hi> and bewitched the Dragon?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Toad.</speaker>
               <p>I'le doe the Lady, and the Kings daughter, and for a Witch I am right by the mothers ſide.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>[He ſpeaks big.]</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
               <p>His very voice will conjure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Toad.</speaker>
               <p>Who playes <hi>Jaſon</hi> my ſweet-heart?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>Is <hi>Jaſon</hi> a man or a woman?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jaſon</hi> is a Kings ſonne, and Captaine of a ſhip call'd <hi>Argo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Crab.</speaker>
               <p>For a Prince or an Emperour, I know where a choice might be made. But I have no heart to the Captaine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170122:5"/>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Your reaſon neighbour <hi>Crab.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Crab.</speaker>
               <p>I know not which limbe I can beſt ſpare, and Carpenters makes but ſcurvie legges. At Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball, or Fifty-Cuffes, I feare no Prince under the Moon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>You fight againſt no bodie but Bulls, and fiery Dragons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
               <p>Doe I not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>And they muſt bee all faſt aſleep when you kill 'em; Nay, <hi>Hercules</hi> himſelfe muſt take your part too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Crab.</speaker>
               <p>Nay then let me alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Now my Maſters, who ſhall doe the Dragon?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scr.</speaker>
               <p>Is it a he, or a ſhe Dragon?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>No matter which.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scrip.</speaker>
               <p>What doe you think of my wife? ſhe'll do't. She does the Dragon at home, 'twod do a mans heart good to be out of the houſe; no body is able to endure her; ſhee is a flying Dragon, and will fit yon rarely—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>We wo'not be troubled with women; and you'll do't your ſelf; well and good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scr.</speaker>
               <p>Rather then the play ſhall not goe forward my wife ſhall teach me my part.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you meane I ſhall have no part? Shall <hi>Hobbinoll</hi> play nothing? <hi>Clout</hi> has no part neither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhall be <hi>Medeas</hi> Brother, <hi>Abſirtus,</hi> a little childe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall bee too tall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt be cut a peeces, and have your limbs throwne about the waves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Crab.</speaker>
               <p>And when your legges, and your head are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170122:5"/>
cut off, you will be no bigger then a childe: wee'll take a courſe to make you little enough. And <hi>Clout,</hi> doe you ſee? you ſhall be the ſhip, hung all round about with Flags, and fine things, we cannot come to <hi>Colchos</hi> without you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clout.</speaker>
               <p>Shall I play the Ship? let me alone to carrie my body ſwimming.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Crab.</speaker>
               <p>Have a care you doe not leake before the Prince; and bee ſure to carry a good winde in your Poop-Clout. But ſtay, all this while, who ſhall doe the golden Fleece? <hi>Bottle,</hi> you forget that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>The chiefe part in the Play, and one that muſt weare the beſt cloathes too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Crab.</speaker>
               <p>Why let ſome body elſe doe <hi>Jaſon,</hi> and Ile doe the golden Fleece.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scr.</speaker>
               <p>Or I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>Or I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>To.</speaker>
               <p>Or any body—Or what if we left out the golden Fleece?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>What if you left out the play? the golden Fleece out? why 'tis the name, and the onely rich thing in the Play.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scr.</speaker>
               <p>Why then leave out the Ship.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and goe by land to <hi>Colchos.</hi> May not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body doe two parts. Let <hi>Scrip</hi> doe the Dragon and the Kings daughter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
               <p>Or leave out the little boy; he has but a ſmall part.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>Ile be cut in pieces a hundred times firſt, leave out <hi>Hercules</hi> and you will, or <hi>Jaſon:</hi> if I doe not fit you <hi>Crab.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shr.</speaker>
               <p>Why <hi>Hercules,</hi> left out, good-man <hi>Hobbinoll?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170122:6"/>
               <speaker>Toad.</speaker>
               <p>No mutiny <hi>Shrub,</hi> neighbour <hi>Crab.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Shrub <hi>ſtrikes</hi> Hob: <hi>they all fight.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>So ſo, we ſhall have a Tragedy indeed; have a care of the Kings daughter among you. Hold, they'll teare <hi>Clout</hi> all to peeces, Have a care of the Ship.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
               <p>Sinke or ſwim, I care not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clout.</speaker>
               <p>Oh my Ribs!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>He that gives the next blow ſhall loſe his ſhare, if he be not turn'd out of the Company. What my Maſters, you ſhal not fall out about this golden Fleece: I kept that part for my ſelfe I warrant you; you ſhall not fall out about ſharing: I am reſolved the golden Fleece is mine, as I am the beſt Actor, and Maſter of the Company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clout.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bottle</hi> indeed had no part before: So, ſo, then we are all friends, and fitted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hob.</speaker>
               <p>When ſhall we have out parts? oh <hi>Bottle</hi> how I thirſt! when our parts?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Part? why you muſt doe it inſtantly, the Prince ſtayes for't.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shr.</speaker>
               <p>How? the Lion is to be kill'd, whoſe skin I muſt weare when I play <hi>Hercules.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clout.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you thinke, I can doe the ſhip, and have not halfe my <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acklings about me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scrip.</speaker>
               <p>And I have not practiſed to ſpit fire yet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> knew what a company of ſots you would be. You'll be <hi>Hercules,</hi> and you'll be a Whale, and you'll be a Ship, and you'll be a Dragon, and you will be a Lady. You Actors? you Animals, to undertake a Play, and aske when you ſhall have your parts; Oh I am aſham'd! but there is no remedy, with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170122:6"/>
ſuch dull capacities: do you remember the Antick Dance, I taught you laſt? that ſhall ſerve for this time. The Prince Keeps his old walke: be ſure to be within reach of my voice, when I call you. Get be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde the trees; I ſpy him. <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Paris.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>What is it to be ſprung of Kingly race,</l>
               <l>Or have the bloud of <hi>Priam</hi> in my veines,</l>
               <l>Yet dare not call him Father? he was cruell,</l>
               <l>Thus for a dreame to baniſh me his ſight,</l>
               <l>And my deare mothers armes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <stage>within.</stage> So ho, ho, ho.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>This buſie ſhepheard will afflict me ſtil</l>
               <l>With his unſeaſonable mirth; I am</l>
               <l>Onely in love with Melancholy; Pleaſures</l>
               <l>Are tedious to my ſoule; Muſt I be ever</l>
               <l>Confin'd to woods? are Beaſts or men more wilde</l>
               <l>Than they, companions for a Prince? are theſe</l>
               <l>Fit ornaments of State? is this a Pallace?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <stage>within.</stage> So ho, ho, ho.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Again? would I could hide me from the world;</l>
               <l>I will goe ſeek my dwelling in ſome rock</l>
               <l>Where never day ſhall be acquainted with me;</l>
               <l>The Sun whoſe beams cheare all the world beſide,</l>
               <l>Shines like a Comet o're my head.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Bottle.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>So ho, ho, ho.</p>
               <p>I thought we had loſt you: why how now? ſtill in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170122:7"/>
this humour? will your highneſſe never be a Change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling? De'e heare Sir; I met your your Nurſe at the bottome of the Hill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What Nurſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>The charitable Beare that gave you ſuck; for though you be a Prince borne, your Parents would not be at the charge to bring you up at Court; Miſtris <hi>Urſula,</hi> and I, have have been the beſt friends to your bloud Roiall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I prethee leave me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Leave my young Prince in a wood? A word to the wiſe—are not you in love?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>In love? with what?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, I doe not know what wilde beaſt hath entangled you: but I have a ſhrewd ſuſpition; for thus ſimply did <hi>I</hi> look by all report, when I was in love too, it had almoſt undone me, for it infected me with Poetrie; and <hi>I</hi> grew witty to the admiration of all the Owles in <hi>Ida.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſhall heare my Verſes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heigh-ho, what ſhall a Shepheard doe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That is love, and cannot woe?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By ſad experience now I finde,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That Love is dumbe as well as blinde.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Her haire is bright, her forehead high,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then am I taken with her eye:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Her cheeks I muſt commend for gay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But then her noſe hangs in my way.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Her lips I like, but then ſteps in</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Her white and prettie dimpled chin.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But then her neck I doe behold,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fit to be hang'd in chaines of gold.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170122:7"/>
                     <hi>Her breaſt is ſoft as any Downe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beneath which lies her Maiden-towne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So ſtrong and fortifi'd within,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There is no hope to take it in.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>And ſo forth. But <hi>I</hi> thank my dutifull father, hee cur'd me with a Flaile, and moſt learnedly threſh'd blinde <hi>Cupid</hi> out of my ſides. <hi>I</hi> had been no <hi>Bottle</hi> of this world elſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>If thou doſt love mee, doe not interrupt me, <hi>I</hi> would be private.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> would be loath to be unmannerly, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Princely recreation: but I ſee no temptations, nothing in the likeneſſe of a Petticote. What would you be private for?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> have ſome ſerious thoughts to examine, if thou wilt uſe thy diligence to keep off thoſe that rudely would diſturbe my preſent retirement: truſt me, Ile reward thy care with my beſt weather.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bottle.</speaker>
               <p>Weather? You are wiſe; doe you think, Sir, I have ſo little honeſty, to be Sir <hi>Pandarus</hi> to your Melancholy. <hi>Illo, ho.</hi>—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What, art thou mad?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>You are little better: if you can get their conſent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Whoſe conſent?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hobinoll, Crab, Toad-ſtoole,</hi>— <hi>Illo ho,</hi> boyes. Some friends of yours, that ſent me to hunt out your Highneſſe, your humble Subjects and Play-fellowes, that have a minde to be merrie.—To tell you true, we have taken notice of your ſullen diſpoſition; and therefore halfe a dozen, have penn'd a dance to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170122:8"/>
revile your ſpirits. Simple as I appeare, my head had a hand in it. If you doe heare an Oration over and above, by way of a preparative to the Phyſick we intend, ſo. I name no body: all the Shepheards wit is not a wool-gathering. Therefore ſtir not my deare Prince, as you will anſwer the contempt of our autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity at your perill. <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>What a ſtrange rudeneſſe am I forc'd to obey?</l>
               <l>Unhappy <hi>Paris!</hi> thy ungentle ſtarres,</l>
               <l>Not onely have decreed thy cruell Exile,</l>
               <l>From thoſe delights thy bloud and birth ſhould chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge,</l>
               <l>But by their fatall doome vouchſafe thee not</l>
               <l>To enjoy a quiet miſerie.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Bag pipes are heard. Enter</hi> Bottle.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bot.</speaker>
               <p>Hold thou unlearned Bag-pipe: for now I am to act a Speech unto the ſonne of <hi>Priam.</hi> Hum, hum.</p>
               <l>Moſt noble Prince!<stage>You muſt not lie down yet.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Moſt noble Prince! behold thy <hi>Bottle</hi> here,</l>
               <l>Thy well-beloved <hi>Bottle</hi> does appeare,</l>
               <l>With many more that ſhall be ſeen hereafter,</l>
               <l>To tickle thy kinde ſpleen into a laughter:</l>
               <l>With feare and wit, or without feare and wit,</l>
               <l>We come, as it becomes, to friske a bit,</l>
               <l>In a ridiculous round: and therefore lye</l>
               <l>Thee downe and laugh, <stage>Now you may lye down, ſo.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Thee downe and laugh, for we doe meane, whereby</l>
               <l>It may be ſaid in a well-written dance</l>
               <l>To ſhew thee ſport, our heeles for to advance.</l>
               <l>Which is an excellent thing. Baniſh thy feares,</l>
               <l>Oh lovely Prince, bred up amongſt the Beares,</l>
               <l>And beare with us.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170122:8"/>
               <hi>The Shepheards enter, and dance. On the ſuddain other Muſicke is heard; and</hi> Mercury <hi>deſcending; the Shepheards run in.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>What miſt doth dwell about my eyes? I feele</l>
               <l>Their heavy curtaines fall; welcome ſoft ſleep,</l>
               <l>The cure of all unreſt. helpe to repaire</l>
               <l>The broken ſilence of my braine, diſtill</l>
               <l>Thy Balme into my wounded thoughts; oh ſee</l>
               <l>I doe obey, and throw my cares on thee. <stage>Dormit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <lg type="song">
               <head>A Song.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ceaſe warring thoughts, and let his braine</l>
                  <l>No more diſcord entertaine,</l>
                  <l>But be ſmooth and calme againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yee Cryſtall Rivers that are nigh,</l>
                  <l>As your ſtreames are paſſing by,</l>
                  <l>Teach your murmurs harmony.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yee windes that wait upon the ſpring,</l>
                  <l>And perfumes to flowers do bring:</l>
                  <l>Let your amorous whiſpers here</l>
                  <l>Breath ſoft Muſick to his eare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yee warbling Nightingales repaire</l>
                  <l>From every wood, to charme this aire,</l>
                  <l>And with the wonders of your breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Each ſtriving to excell the reſt.</l>
                  <l>When it is time to wake him, cloſe your parts,</l>
                  <l>And drop downe from the trees with broken hearts</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <sp>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170122:9"/>
               <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
               <l>Young <hi>Priam's</hi> ſon, and darling of the gods,</l>
               <l>I <hi>Mercurie,</hi> winged Meſſenger of <hi>Jove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By his command have leſt his ſpangled Court,</l>
               <l>And through the ſilver Orbes deſcend to tell thee,</l>
               <l>That he hath choſen thee to be the Judge</l>
               <l>Between three Deities, which ſhall beſt deſerve</l>
               <l>This golden Ball: <hi>Juno</hi> his Queen of heaven,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> the goddeſſe of faire Arts, and Armes,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Citherea,</hi> Queen of Love and Beautie.</l>
               <l>Shake off thy clouds of ſleep, and freed from all</l>
               <l>Diſtractions, prepare to heare them plead</l>
               <l>Their glories here. Imperiall <hi>Juno</hi> drawne</l>
               <l>Be her proud Birds, is ſtooping from her Coach.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Jove</hi>-borne maid already hath diſmounted</l>
               <l>The <hi>Paphian</hi> Queen with her young Archer drawne</l>
               <l>By Swans more white than <hi>Rodopcian</hi> ſnow,</l>
               <l>Is now deſcending from her Chariot,</l>
               <l>And on the green Pluſh of this <hi>Ida</hi> hill</l>
               <l>They all move to thee with celeſtiall pace.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paris</hi> awake, <hi>Jove</hi> doth his Herald call,</l>
               <l>To the moſt worthy give this golden Ball.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Aſcendit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>What have I ſeene? what ſtrange</l>
               <l>But heavenly dreame hath <hi>Pariſ</hi> had:</l>
               <stage>He ſpies the Ball.</stage>
               <l>Yet this preſents more then an emptie ſhadow,</l>
               <l>I'me ſure it grew not here; there are no trees</l>
               <l>That beare ſuch fruit in <hi>Ida;</hi> ſuch as theſe</l>
               <l>Grew in the Orchard of <hi>Hesperides,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ever guarded by a watchfull Dragon.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Jove</hi> hath gather'd it and ſent it me.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170122:9"/>What's here inſcrib'd? <hi>This to the beſt deſerver!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I am not then deluded; it is fit</l>
               <l>I ſhould obſerve with all obedience</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Joves</hi> command.</l>
               <stage>Soft Muſick.</stage>
               <l>What ſacred change is this?</l>
               <l>Such harmony muſt needs ſpeak the approach</l>
               <l>Of the Celeſtiall powers.</l>
            </sp>
            <lg type="song">
               <head>Song of <hi>Juno</hi> within.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Jove <hi>ſent thee</hi> Paris; <hi>what is mine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>be ſafely bold;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And for that trifle I reſigne</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi> a wreath of gold.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Obey then and command, thou canſt not be</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juſt to thy ſelfe, if not to me.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Pallas.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Twice happy in thy choiſe: be wiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi> ere thou diſpence</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This Treaſure, give thy Reaſon eyes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi> and blinde thy ſence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus Armes and Arts thy humble name ſhall raiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alike to Wreathes of Oakes and Bayes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170122:10"/>
                  <head>Venus.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>She, whom all ſuppliants elſe implore </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>is here made thine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And will for this a gift reſtore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi> no leſſe divine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The beſt of pleaſures thus enjoy, and trie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Where Beantie Courts who can denie.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Chorus.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Examine Princely Shepheard</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi> here the Offerings which we ſend thee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How for that narrow golden ſphere,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi> Wealth, Fame and love attend thee.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And judge by this, how large theſe honours be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>None to each other yeeld, yet all to thee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <stage>Juno, Pallas, <hi>and</hi> Venus <hi>at ſeverall places appea</hi> Juno <hi>attended by a King and a Senator.</hi> Pallas <hi>by a Souldier, and a Philoſopher.</hi> Venus <hi>by</hi> Hymen <hi>and</hi> Cupid. <hi>They dance: At the cloſe, all remove, but the three goddeſſes.</hi> Paris <hi>kneeles.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juno.</speaker>
               <l>Put off thy wonder <hi>Paris,</hi> and collect</l>
               <l>Thy ſcattered ſences in our Temples, we</l>
               <l>Expect thoſe hummble adorations</l>
               <l>And ſacrifice from Mortalls, that doe bring</l>
               <l>Petitions to our Altars. We are come</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170122:10"/>
                  <hi>Juno, Minerva,</hi> and the Sea-borne Queen,</l>
               <l>From our bright Pallaces, to ſue to thee:</l>
               <l>(Thinke it no ſtaine to our Celeſtiall nature)</l>
               <l>That golden Ball, ſent thee by <hi>Jove,</hi> to be</l>
               <l>Her prize, whoſe merits can obtaine it from</l>
               <l>Thy equall ſentence of us three, hath brought</l>
               <l>Our competition hither; be juſt <hi>Paris,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And live for ever happy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>How ſhall <hi>Paris,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe yeares are green, &amp; too unripe for judgment,</l>
               <l>Decide the worth of three ſuch Deities.</l>
               <l>Which not a counſell of the gods themſelves,</l>
               <l>Hath wiſedome to determine?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juno.</speaker>
               <l>We will plead</l>
               <l>Our owne deſerts before thee, to which give</l>
               <l>Thy fixt attention, and heare <hi>Juno</hi> firſt</l>
               <l>Court thy election.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Humbly I attend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juno.</speaker>
               <l>Ile not inſiſt, that I am with the vote</l>
               <l>Of all the gods firſt both in place and title:</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Olimpian</hi> Empreſſe, <hi>Joves</hi> wife and ſiſter,</l>
               <l>Theſe are but names and ſhadowes of my greatneſſe,</l>
               <l>And which doe rather fright, than win from mortalls,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſenſe muſt let in objects to the ſoule:</l>
               <l>Know <hi>Paris,</hi> with that Scepter I controule,</l>
               <l>Not skies alone, but all this under world:</l>
               <l>Kingdoms and Crowns are mine, all wealth contain'd</l>
               <l>In <hi>Neptunes</hi> watry circle, or the veines</l>
               <l>Of earth as ſubject to my gift and largeſſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <l>With favour of great <hi>Junoes</hi> Empire,</l>
               <l>She that diſpoſeth golden Mines at pleaſure,</l>
               <l>('Tis ſtrange) ſhould hold contention for a Ball.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170122:11"/>
               <speaker>Juno.</speaker>
               <l>I doe, and will reward it with more Treaſure</l>
               <l>Then his ambition knowes how to aske:</l>
               <l>Not that I prize that poore and narrow globe,</l>
               <l>But that I hate, <hi>Pallas</hi> ſhould be competitour,</l>
               <l>Or any with <hi>Saturnia;</hi> give it me,</l>
               <l>And I will furniſh thee with the ſame mettall,</l>
               <l>To build thy ſelf a Pallace, about which,</l>
               <l>The yellow <hi>Tagus,</hi> and <hi>Iberus</hi> ſtreames,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſian Pactolus,</hi> and the <hi>Indian Ganges,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall flow with golden ſands: let thy Birth <hi>Paris,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Put thee in minde what 'tis to be a Monarch.</l>
               <l>I will adorne thy Temples with a wreath,</l>
               <l>Whoſe flame ſhall dimme bright <hi>Ariadnes</hi> Crowne,</l>
               <l>Embelliſh'd with the glorious Lamps of heaven:</l>
               <l>Name but the bounds and limits of thy Empire;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſia</hi> ſhall bow, and all her ſtubborne Princes,</l>
               <l>Like petty homagers ſhall kneele before thee,</l>
               <l>And lay their ſhining Scepters at thy feet;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Europe</hi> ſhall proſtrate all her Provinces,</l>
               <l>And glorie in her ſervitude, incline</l>
               <l>To me, and <hi>India</hi> ſhall ſend thee Pearles,</l>
               <l>As tribute to beſtow upon thy Queens;</l>
               <l>The precious <hi>Ermynes</hi> ſhall without purſuit</l>
               <l>Preſent thee with her skins: and the cold climes</l>
               <l>Bring home rich Furres, and Sables to adorne thee.</l>
               <l>The ſervile roomes within thy Pallace, ſhall</l>
               <l>Have <hi>Babilonian</hi> hangings, and rich ſhapes,</l>
               <l>Wrought by the needle of <hi>Semyramis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The fiſh ſhal bring thee purple to the ſhore.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Panchaia</hi> ſend thee Spice, and wealthy Gummes,</l>
               <l>Such as the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Bird doth fill her neſt with,</l>
               <l>When ſhe prepares for ſacrifice. The ſpoiles</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170122:11"/>Of Silk-worms ſhal make proud thy meaneſt grooms.</l>
               <l>What ſhall I ſay, preſent that Ball to me,</l>
               <l>And in exchange Ile give the world to thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Juno</hi> hath ſaid; and were not <hi>Pallas</hi> here,</l>
               <l>Might tempt thee <hi>Paris</hi> to forget thy ſelfe:</l>
               <l>Her promiſes are vaſt, and full of State,</l>
               <l>But weigh'd with what <hi>Minerva</hi> can beſtow,</l>
               <l>They ſhrinke to aire, and thou <hi>Ixion</hi>-like,</l>
               <l>Embracing <hi>Juno</hi> doſt but graſpe a cloud.</l>
               <l>Nay, if thou doſt examine well her gifts,</l>
               <l>How 'ere their flattering ſound affect thy eare,</l>
               <l>Or their poſſeſſion court thy eye with ſhew,</l>
               <l>And ſpecious glories, thou ſhalt finde within,</l>
               <l>They have diſguis'd a poiſon, that doth lurke</l>
               <l>To infect thy minde, and kill with their corruption</l>
               <l>Thy intellectuall Beauties, by ſoft eaſe</l>
               <l>A ſordid avarice, coward thoughts, and all</l>
               <l>The traine of Luſt and Lethargies that hang</l>
               <l>Upon a Maſculine ſoule; where thy acceptance</l>
               <l>Of what is in my power, ſhall make thee ſcorne</l>
               <l>Theſe things of care and golden ſlaverie,</l>
               <l>That foole and flinty conſciences adore,</l>
               <l>And grasp'd, like theeving ſands ſteal through our fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</l>
               <l>Ile give thee Wiſedome <hi>Paris,</hi> in which name</l>
               <l>I comprehend all harmony of earth,</l>
               <l>And heaven, and make thee kinſe-man to the gods.</l>
               <l>Nature ſhall open her darke boſome to thee,</l>
               <l>And give thee leave to rifle all her wonders:</l>
               <l>The Virgin Arts ſhall court thee to be call'd</l>
               <l>Their Oracle, and whatſoe're the extent</l>
               <l>Of that wide Orbe containes, whoſe bounds ſhut up</l>
               <l>The univerſall creature, ſhall unveile</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170122:12"/>Their beauties, and be proud to enrich thy knowledge.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juno</hi> and <hi>Pallas</hi> promiſe gallantly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
               <l>Yet this concludes not, what <hi>Minerva</hi> can</l>
               <l>Beſtow upon her <hi>Paris;</hi> if the Arts</l>
               <l>Inflame thee not, or doe appeare leſſe active,</l>
               <l>And glorious to meet thy fierce Ambition.</l>
               <l>Fame ſhall want breath to tell the world what tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs</l>
               <l>Shall Crowne thy name in warre, if <hi>Pallas</hi> arme</l>
               <l>Thy breaſt with courage, which my bounty throwes</l>
               <l>To thy acceptance; if that Ball be mine,</l>
               <l>Ile give thee a ſpirit <hi>Trojan,</hi> and ſuch conqueſts</l>
               <l>By thy owne valour, as at once ſhall fright,</l>
               <l>And pleaſe the hearers faith: Nations ſhall tremble</l>
               <l>To mention thy great Acts, whoſe memory</l>
               <l>Shall out-live all Egyptian Pyramids,</l>
               <l>And bloome when Winters have defac'd the world,</l>
               <l>And feeble time ſhall droop and halt with age:</l>
               <l>Trophies ſhall fall in dutie to thy ſword,</l>
               <l>And Captive Princes wait upon thy Chariot.</l>
               <l>Some ſhall build Statues, others invent games,</l>
               <l>Some Temples to thy name, while holy Prieſts</l>
               <l>And Virgin Quires ſhall make it their Religion,</l>
               <l>To pay thee ſongs, and Crowne thy images</l>
               <l>With ever-ſpringing Garlands. Be wife, <hi>Paris,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reſolve to make that golden Circle mine,</l>
               <l>Both Arts and Armes ſhall make their glories thine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <l>What words? what argument to move thee <hi>Paris</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is left for <hi>Cytherea?</hi> Mighty <hi>Juno</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Woes thy ambition with State and Kingdomes,</l>
               <l>Courting thy Genius in a ſhower of gold:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> not onely will inſpire thy ſoule,</l>
               <l>With valour, on which victory ſhall waite,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170122:12"/>And Crowne thy head with her immortall Laurells,</l>
               <l>But make thee rich in Science, and uncloud</l>
               <l>The ſacred beauties of all Art and Nature.</l>
               <l>Theſe bounties ſeem to have left <hi>Venus</hi> nothing;</l>
               <l>But when my power and gifts come to the Ballance,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paris</hi> ſhall ſee their glories, thinne and light,</l>
               <l>Fly into aire: I am the Queen of love:</l>
               <l>Thinke but how poore are <hi>Pallas</hi> victories,</l>
               <l>When I have made her greateſt ſouldiers tame,</l>
               <l>Forc'd 'em look pale, and tremble, ſigh and weep,</l>
               <l>Ready to give their ghoſt up at a frowne,</l>
               <l>And thinke my ſmile or kiſſe their onely heaven.</l>
               <l>Her Oracles of Wiſedome and Philoſophy</l>
               <l>Have been my fooles, &amp; all their ſtrength of learning,</l>
               <l>But able to expreſſe great Loves ſupremacie,</l>
               <l>And my dominions boundleſſe. What doe I</l>
               <l>Boaſt the extent of my command on earth?</l>
               <l>When under my Diviner Enſignes march</l>
               <l>Etheriall Troops? my power confeſt by <hi>Jove</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſway in heaven: and what are all the treaſures</l>
               <l>And gifts of <hi>Juno,</hi> Kingdomes pil'd on Kingdomes?</l>
               <l>Which at the beſt but multiply thy cares</l>
               <l>To keep, if Love be not propitious to thee?</l>
               <l>Who can diſcharge a thouſand ſtings upon</l>
               <l>Thy heart, and make it priſoner when I pleaſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juno.</speaker>
               <p>The goddeſſe of vexation we allow thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <l>But theſe are not the motives to incline</l>
               <l>Thy thoughts young Prince to me; thus fear, not love</l>
               <l>Should plead for me, although the torments are</l>
               <l>High and conſuming, where I fixe diſpleaſure,</l>
               <l>The joyes I poure upon my favourites</l>
               <l>Shall be my Orators, whoſe endleſſe charmes</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170122:13"/>Are above counter-magick, and ſhall tie</l>
               <l>Thy ſoule in everlaſting chains of love.</l>
               <l>Poets have feign'd <hi>Elyſium</hi> after death,</l>
               <l>Which thou ſhalt here poſſeſſe; and all the pleaſure</l>
               <l>Of thoſe bleſt ſhades, they talke of in their ſongs,</l>
               <l>Shall ſpread themſelves before thee, which thou ſhalt</l>
               <l>Poſſeſſe as Lord, not Tenant to the Groves.</l>
               <l>It ſhall be ever ſpring, and ever Summer,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Paris</hi> ſhall inhabit, all rude aires,</l>
               <l>The killing dewes, tempeſt, and lightning, ſhall</l>
               <l>Be ſtrangers to thy walkes, which the Weſt winde</l>
               <l>Shall with their ſoft and gentle gales perfume.</l>
               <l>The Laurell and the Mirtle ſhall compoſe</l>
               <l>Thy Arbours, inter-woven with the Roſe,</l>
               <l>And honey-dropping Wood-bine; on the ground</l>
               <l>The flowres ambitiouſly ſhall croud themſelves</l>
               <l>Into Love-knots, and Coronets, to entangle</l>
               <l>Thy feet, that they may kiſſe them, as they tread,</l>
               <l>And keep them priſoners in their amorous ſtalkes.</l>
               <l>The Violet ſhall weep when thou remov'ſt,</l>
               <l>And the pale Lilly deck her innocent cheek</l>
               <l>With Pearles to Court thy ſtay; the <hi>Hyacinth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When thou art paſſing by her, ſhall diſcloſe</l>
               <l>Her Purple boſome to thee, proud to be</l>
               <l>Saluted by thy eye, and being left,</l>
               <l>Bluſh, droop, and wither, like a Love-ſick Virgin.</l>
               <l>Doth <hi>Paris</hi> thirſt? Rivers of <hi>Nectar</hi> flow</l>
               <l>In every chryſtall channell: wouldſt thou feed,</l>
               <l>The trees ſhall bow under their heavenly fruit,</l>
               <l>And offer their <hi>Ambroſia</hi> to thy gathering.</l>
               <l>Nor ſhalt thou be alone, a thouſand Nymphes,</l>
               <l>Fairer then ever thy eyes gaz'd upon,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170122:13"/>Shall wait upon my darling, and with ſport</l>
               <l>Make thy delight immortall: theſe at laſt</l>
               <l>To crowne thy joyes ſhall lead thee to a Miſtris,</l>
               <l>Compar'd to whom, their beauties have no name;</l>
               <l>In whoſe leaſt part more wonders ſhall invite</l>
               <l>Thy amaz'd eye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> than all the Queens of earth</l>
               <l>Can boaſt together<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and this beauties heaven</l>
               <l>Will I beſtow on <hi>Paris,</hi> in whoſe love</l>
               <l>He ſhall poſſeſſe more raptures, than are ſands</l>
               <l>In all the glaſſe of time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juno</speaker>
               <l>Fine aery Bleſſings;</l>
               <l>A ſmall Art will diſtinguiſh 'twixt us three</l>
               <l>Who can deſerve thee beſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>I am tranſported,</l>
               <l>And firſt my humble gratitude preſented</l>
               <l>For this, an honour above all, that has</l>
               <l>A name in ſtory, lent to grace a mortall,</l>
               <l>And give me patience you deviner natures,</l>
               <l>If it diſtract, and fright my weaker counſells.</l>
               <l>It is not ſafe to thinke, what language then</l>
               <l>Shall have the confidence to expreſſe thoſe thoughts</l>
               <l>That merit to be ſtifl'd? I muſt tremble</l>
               <l>To be my ſelfe, and ſpeak: Yet if I dream not,</l>
               <l>I am commanded to reſigne this Ball,</l>
               <l>Not mine, but hers, of you three beſt deſerving:</l>
               <l>Is't not a ſinne to name one beſt? oh pardon!</l>
               <l>That I had leave to whiſper in the eare</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Jove</hi> two minutes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
               <l>It was meant by him,</l>
               <l>You ſhould declare your ſelfe to us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <l>Be confident,</l>
               <l>And wiſedome guide the ſentence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170122:14"/>
               <speaker>Juno.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis expected,</l>
               <l>Be therefore bold and wiſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>I feele new courage</l>
               <l>Infus'd; there's ſomething ſpreads through every part,</l>
               <l>And chides my timerous youth into reſolve</l>
               <l>Of ſomething that muſt be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <l>It muſt be welcome,</l>
               <l>We are prepar'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Great <hi>Juno,</hi> I not dare</l>
               <l>To queſtion your vaſt power, the world and you</l>
               <l>Shut all up with one circle, wealth and kingdomes</l>
               <l>Are able to ſtrike blinde with their temptation;</l>
               <l>The eyes of young ambition, and my birth</l>
               <l>Had ſure thoſe ſeeds of glorie; but my fate</l>
               <l>Has ſtifled 'em, and made them ſo familiar</l>
               <l>With ſhades and humble thoughts, I cannot finde,</l>
               <l>My ſoule now fit for thoſe deſires.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jun.</speaker>
               <l>Deſpiſe</l>
               <l>My gifts? periſh in wants unpittied.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
               <l>Nay ſtay, and heare one more concluded <hi>Juno.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Ball is not beſtow'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis ſome unhappineſſe,</l>
               <l>I look not with that admiration</l>
               <l>Upon <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nerva</hi>'s gifts. <hi>Philoſophy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That teacheth to contemplate heaven and nature,</l>
               <l>Carries ſome trouble with it: and for Armes,</l>
               <l>There are enow will bleed to be triumphant,</l>
               <l>A Limbe to me is better than a Lawrel</l>
               <l>Purchas'd with wounds; your pardon, if I think</l>
               <l>The Queen of Love to be preferr'd, accept</l>
               <l>The Ball bright <hi>Citherea,</hi> and with it</l>
               <l>The humble heart of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170122:14"/>
               <speaker>Jun.</speaker>
               <l>Am I thus</l>
               <l>Neglected by a Boy? how I deſpiſe him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
               <p>I pitie the fond youth. <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>They are both gone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <p>Diſpleaſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Their anger frights not me,</l>
               <l>So I be welcome here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <l>Be confidentt <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Cupid.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Love ſhall confirme it: ſee my ſon appeares.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cupid,</hi> I thought thou hadſt been loſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
               <l>Though blinde,</l>
               <l>I never loſe my way to Beautie: Mother,</l>
               <l>I all this while but hover'd in the aire,</l>
               <l>To heare how <hi>Paris</hi> would determine, and</l>
               <l>Rejoyce in Beauties triumph, and thy juſtice</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Let <hi>Juno</hi> fret, and <hi>Pallas</hi> frowne,</l>
               <l>Nature to all ſucceeding times ſhall prove,</l>
               <l>Wealth, Arts, &amp; Arms muſt yeeld to conquering Love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
               <p>That name belongs to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Cupid</hi> will no doubt agree.</l>
               <l>Love dwels with Beautie, they together move;</l>
               <l>There is no Beautie where there is not love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
               <l>For this choiſe, young <hi>Paris</hi> know,</l>
               <l>While powerfull <hi>Cupid</hi> hath a Bow,</l>
               <l>A golden ſhaft, or skilfull hand,</l>
               <l>All ſhall move at thy command.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>You both make <hi>Paris</hi> happy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <l>But where are</l>
               <l>Our traine of Graces, and the pleaſant Houres,</l>
               <l>To entertaine our Darling? Where is <hi>Hymen?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where is Delight?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
               <p>Mother they both appeare.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170122:15"/>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Hymen <hi>and</hi> Delight</stage>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="song">
                        <head>SONG.</head>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Hym.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Come yee Graces come away.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Yee pleaſant Houres why doe you ſtay?</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Both.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Vpon your Mistris wait.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Hym.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>See where in ſtate</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The Queen of Love and Beautie is.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>On ſuch a ſolemne night as this,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Sacred to kiſsing:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>What bold Nymph dare be miſsing?</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Hym.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>They come, they come, behold</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The modeſt Graces.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>The</hi> Graces <hi>and</hi> Houres <hi>Enter.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>For loves ſake mend your paces,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And bluſh not to be bold.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Hym.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <hi>The Houres have loſt their wings, I feare,</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>No, they appeare.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <lg>
                           <head>Chorus.</head>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And</hi> Ida <hi>green</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Is now the Court of</hi> Paphos <hi>Queen:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170122:15"/>
                              <hi>Where every one doth welcome ſing</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>To</hi> Venus, <hi>and their new made King.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>They all bow to</hi> Venus.</stage>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <l>All theſe wait</l>
               <l>On me, and I command them to attend</l>
               <l>On lovely <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Let me dwell ever</l>
               <l>With <hi>Citherea, Ida</hi> is turn'd heaven.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <p>Now let us dance, theſe pleaſures are not active.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>They dance; after which a Song. The Houres ſteale off.</stage>
            <lg type="song">
               <l>How dully all your joyes doe move,</l>
               <l>Delight is crippled here.</l>
               <l>Your motion ſhould be like to that above,</l>
               <l>This is too thick a ſphere.</l>
               <l>The feather-footed houres are fled away,</l>
               <l>Aſham'd to ſtay:</l>
               <l>Then follow, flie, oh come,</l>
               <l>You muſt make haſte,</l>
               <l>If you will taſte</l>
               <l>Loves new Elyſium.</l>
            </lg>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <l>We want ſome of our Nymphes <hi>Eunomia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Faire <hi>Diche,</hi> and <hi>Irene,</hi> are they gone?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170122:16"/>
               <speaker>1. <hi>Grace.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Although we did entreat them ſtay,</l>
               <l>The pleaſant houres are ſtolne away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ven.</speaker>
               <p>Which way.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <l>That way,</l>
               <l>To the <hi>Elyſian</hi> Bowers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
               <p>Wee'll flye, and overtake the happy houres.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
