<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the right honorable the house of peeres now assembled in Parliament The humble petition of the knights, gentlemen, freeholders and other inhabitants of the county of Oxford.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-03">2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94617</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.4[65]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210282</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869094</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869094</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160687</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A94617)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160687)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 245:669f4[65])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the right honorable the house of peeres now assembled in Parliament The humble petition of the knights, gentlemen, freeholders and other inhabitants of the county of Oxford.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Lords.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1]  p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for F.L. and W.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641 [i.e. 1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:160687:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO
THE RIGHT HONORABLE
THE HOVSE OF PEERES
Now aſsembled in Parliament.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of the Knights, Gentlemen, Freeholders
and others Inhabitants of the County of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Petitioners being very ſenſible of thoſe preſſures under which the whole Kingdome growneth; and having
ever ſince this happie Parliament began, with patience waited for a finall redreſſe, and a perfect reformation of the
Church and State; ſeeing much hath been indeavored for the eaſe of our grievances, and much more might have beene
done, had it not beene (as we humbly conceive) for the oppoſition of the ill affected parties of Popiſh Lords and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops;
as not being the firſt in this way of Petitioning, are conſtrained to repreſent to your Honours our juſt feares
and diſtractions, arriſing from that Barbarous and bloody rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> wherein innocent blood of many thouſand Proteſtants
hath beene cruelly and inhumainely ſhed, without reſpect to Age or Sect, threatning the ſubvertion of the Proteſtant Religion, and the
irreparable loſſe of that Kingdome; to the emboldning of the Popiſh and malignant parties of this Kingdome to the like attempt
if opportunity be put into their hands, which may produce (which God forbid) as ſad effects in this, from the not paſſing the Bill for
impreſſing of Souldiers, wherby a ſufficient aide may be ſent, to the ſpeedy reliefe of our Brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> from the late unparalleld
breach of the Privilige of Parliament, from the not putting of this Kingdome into a poſture of defence, and the Cinque Ports into ſafe
hands in whom the King and Parliament may confide; notwithſtanding the many Petitions put up in this behalfe: from the Papiſts
not beeing diſarmed, and forſaking their owne houſes, and privately living in places where they are not knowne: which juſtly caſts jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies
into us, that they have in hand ſome deſperate plot as yet undiſcovered: from the great increaſe of Arminianiſme in our Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity,
and the inſolency of that partie: From the not puniſhing of Delinquents; and from the continuance of many corrupt and
ſcandalous Miniſters, which grow more impudent and incorrigible by the delay of puniſhment: Laſtly, from the not concenting of
this Honorable Houſe with the Houſe of Commons, in the paſſing of many motions for the common good. All which have beene
the cauſe of the totall decay of Trade and want of coyne throughout the Kingdome, to the great impoveriſhing thereof, and without
which it will not be able long to ſubſiſt.</p>
            <closer>We therefore your Potitioners, doe humbly pray, that a ſpeedy remove all of theſe our grievances with the cauſes; and of the Votes
of the Popiſh Lords and Biſhops out of this Honorable Houſe, which (we humbly conceive) are not conſiſtent with the Honour of the
King and Parliament, and the ſafety of this Kingdome, and your Petitioners to the utmoſt hazard of our lives and eſtates will be ready to
defend the King and Parliament againſt all oppoſers whatſoever.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_requests">
            <head>The Heads of the Petition.</head>
            <p>1. THankes, to be given to the Lords for voting downe the Biſhops, with our earneſt deſire that they would doe as much for the Popiſh parties.</p>
            <p>2. That our ſea Townes, Forts, and Caſtles, may be ſpeedily garded and put into the custody of ſuch, which in whom we may ſafely confide.</p>
            <p>3. That the Kingdome may be put into a poſture of defence.</p>
            <p>4. That for the better diſarming of Papists an oath may be administred, not onely to the Masters of Families, but to their Servants and Tennants,
for the better finding out where their armes are, ſince the former courſes of ſearching only, are moſt commonly fruſtrated.</p>
            <p>5. That all Papists may be enioyned to keepe their owne houſes in theſe dangerous times, that they may not have their meettings in <hi>London</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where,
whereby they may know each others minds, and ſo enabled to put in execution their dangerous deſignes.</p>
            <p>6. That they would be pleaſed to have an eſpeciall eye unto the Vniverſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> that that Seminarie might not be over-whelmed with Popery,
Arminianiſme, and ſuperstition, that their Alters, Images, and Crucifixes, may be demoliſhed, that Governours of Colledges may be questioned, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
they did not demoliſh them, according to the order ſet forth by the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>7. That a Preaching Miniſtrie may be planted throughout the whole dioceſſe, ſince there are neere upon 280. Pariſhes, and not above thirty Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
that are constant Preachers.</p>
            <p>8. That they would be pleaſed to take into conſideration the multiplicity of dignities and preferments that ſome Heads of Houſes, every where
you ſhall finde ſome to enioy a rich Lordſhip worth many 100. <hi>per annum,</hi> a Denery, a Preband, and two fat Parſonages, and ſeldome Preach at either.</p>
            <p>9. That further care may be taken for the ſuppreſsing of the Rebells in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London, <hi>printed for</hi> F. L. <hi>and</hi> W. W. 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
