<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King and Queen, a proclamation for prohibiting the importation, or retailing of any commodities of the growth or manufacture of France</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1689-1694 : William and Mary)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96584</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2598</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42666</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875554</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875554</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152514</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A96584)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152514)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2299:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King and Queen, a proclamation for prohibiting the importation, or retailing of any commodities of the growth or manufacture of France</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1689-1694 : William and Mary)</author>
                  <author>William III, King of England, 1650-1702.</author>
                  <author>Mary II, Queen of England, 1662-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Charles Bill, and Thomas Newcomb ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Given at Our Court at Hampton-Court the Eighteenth day of May, 1689. In the First Year of Our Reign."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Foreign trade regulation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Commerce --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:152514:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <head>By the King and Queen, A PROCLAMATION For Prohibiting the Importation, or Retailing of any Commodities of the Growth or Manufacture of <hi>France.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>William R.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the King and Queén's moſt Excellent Majeſties, Conſidering the great Prejudice and Damage to the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Artificers and Handicrafts, and the general Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhment of this Kingdom, by the extraordinary Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Uſe of the Commodities and Manufactures of <hi>France:</hi> And Reſolving with the help of Almighty God by a Iuſt and neceſſary War, to Deliver this Kingdom, and other Their Dominions, from the Injuries, Aggreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and Dangers done, made, and occaſioned by the <hi>French</hi> King, did Iſſue Their Proclamation bearing Date the Twenty fifth day of <hi>April</hi> laſt, Intituled <hi>(A Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Prohibiting the Importation of all ſorts of Manufactures and Commodities whatſoever, of the Growth, Production, or Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>France</hi>
               </hi>) which War Their Majeſties have lately Declared. Now Their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties finding it expedient to alter the ſaid Proclamation, and to the Iutent to render Their Royal Purpoſes more duly and effectually Practicable, Have thought fit by and with the Advice of Their Privy Council, to Diſcharge the ſaid Proclamation; and by the ſame Advice, do hereby Publiſh and Declare, and ſtraitly Charge and Command, That no Goods, Merchandizes, or Commodities whatſoever of the Growth, Product, or Manufacture of <hi>France,</hi> or of the Dominions of the <hi>French</hi> King, ſhall at any time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Five and twentieth day of this inſtant <hi>May,</hi> be brought or Imported into any of Their Majeſties Realms or Dominions, or any Port or Creek of the ſame; Or if ſo brought or Imported, ſhall not be Retailed, Uttered, Bartered or Sold by any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Perſons whatſoever, upon pain of Confiſcation and Forfeiture thereof to Their Majeſties Uſe; Of which Confiſcation and Forfeitures, Their Majeſties are pleaſed the Informer ſhall have one Moiety; And hereof Their Majeſties Pleaſure is, That all Perſons whom it may Concern, do take Notice at their Peril; And to that End, do ſtraitly Charge and Command as well all and every the Officers of the Admiral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as alſo all and ſingular Cuſtomers, Comptrollors, Searchers, Waiters, and other Officers, and all other Their Loving Subjects, that they and every of them reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively take ſpecial Care, that this Their Royal Pleaſure and Command be put in due Execution.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at Our Court at <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> the Eighteenth day of <hi>May,</hi> 1689. In the Firſt Year of Our Reign.</dateline>
God Save King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and Queen <hi>MARY.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Charles Bill,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Newcomb,</hi> Printers to the King and Queen's moſt Excellent Majeſties. 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
