<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An elogie or eulogie on the obits of the Right Honourable Ferdinando Lord Fairefax vvho dyed upon Munday, the 13th of March, anno Dom. 1647.</title>
            <author>Walker, Henry, Ironmonger.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.11[137]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210830</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869586</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869586</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162790</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A96987)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162790)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 246:669f11[137])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An elogie or eulogie on the obits of the Right Honourable Ferdinando Lord Fairefax vvho dyed upon Munday, the 13th of March, anno Dom. 1647.</title>
                  <author>Walker, Henry, Ironmonger.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (port.)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at London by Robert Ibbitson, dwelling in Smithfield neere the Queens head Tavern,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: H. Walker, S. S. Theol.</note>
                  <note>Verse - "Far more divine, and cleer, is now, Lord Fairefax gone,".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "march. 20th 1647"; after 'Theol' at end of text: "a coxcome".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fairfax, Ferdinando Fairfax, --  Baron, 1584-1648 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Elegiac poetry, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:162790:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <head>AN ELOGIE <hi>OR</hi> EULOGIE ON THE OBITS of the Right Honourable FERDINANDO Lord FAIREFAX<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> VVho dyed upon Munday, the 13th of <hi>March, Anno Dom.</hi> 1647.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of standard bearer</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Fairfax</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of tomb</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of standard bearer</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div type="acrostic">
               <head>A CROSTICKE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>F</hi>AR more DivINe, AND cleer, is nOw, LORD FAIREFAX gone,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi>bove; to praiſe <hi>JEHOVAH,</hi> at his Royall Throne;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>R</hi>emote from Earth: He ſwift to Heaven aſcended (high)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>D</hi>ect in a wreath of Tryumph, (peircing through the skie.)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi>nto Celeſtiall glory (upon Angels wings)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>N</hi>ow <hi>Halelujahs</hi> to the Lord of Hoſts he ſings.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi>dieu, brave Honour, <hi>England</hi> with briniſh teares may ſay,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>N</hi>ight clad in ſable blacke, mournes for the loſſe of day.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>D</hi>eath hath be friended Heaven with the <hi>Fathers</hi> ſoul,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O</hi>n whoſe meeke <hi>Son;</hi> let Angells miriads of bleſſings roule.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>L</hi>ight (ſhining downe from Heaven) the darkeſt cloud expells,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O</hi>n Earth; when Sun with glittering moſt bright excells:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>R</hi>iſeth in ſplendor, aſcends with ſmiles: But ſets in diſmall turning,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>D</hi>eath thus hath vail'd our light, and left us all in mourning.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <hi>F</hi>airefax;</hi> valiant, and true: For <hi>Englands</hi> peace he ſtood,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi>nd to his wife, kindred, neighbours, was wiſe and good,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi>uſt unto all; And mercifull; As orbs of Stars.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>R</hi>eliefe ſhin'd comfort, from his ſparkled hands. And bars</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>E</hi>ffectuall, for truths defence he did erect:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>F</hi>alſe hypocrites unmaske, and wickedneſſe detect.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi>nd now his ſoul's in glory (though <hi>Xenius</hi> mount above)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <hi>X</hi>anthius</hi> his Son is here; The Generall of love.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="etymology">
               <head>The Etymologie of his name from the Hebr<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>חקפ ארפ אד ןינ יד דרפ</p>
               <p>Faradh-dhi-nin da Fere-Fakahh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Hebrew of the Lord</hi> Fairfaxes <hi>name, tranſlated into</hi> Engliſh.</p>
               <p>He hath ſeparated a ſufficient Sonne, that wounded the wild Aſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <lg>
                  <head>An ELOGIE.</head>
                  <l>Renowned <hi>Fairfax,</hi> whom the State did love</l>
                  <l>Is now ASSENDED to His GOD above,</l>
                  <l>Hee liv'd and dy'd in Honour, full of years:</l>
                  <l>His death ſets ſluces ope, to powre out tears.</l>
                  <l>When wicked men began to riſe,</l>
                  <l>The godly Party to ſurprize,</l>
                  <l>And make them ſlaves</l>
                  <l>To many Knaves,</l>
                  <l>To ſpoyle our Goods</l>
                  <l>And ſpill OUR Bloods;</l>
                  <l>He parted with his Son moſt dear</l>
                  <l>Who of their holes did them all clear,</l>
                  <l>The Father's dead, and gone to reſt above,</l>
                  <l>The Son hath wrought our peace, if wee had Love.</l>
                  <l>By God Almighties power, then let us all,</l>
                  <l>Give him the Glory, and Love, reciprocall.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <byline>By H. Walker,
S. S. Theol.</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at London by Robert Ibbitſon, dwelling in Smithfield neere the Queens head Tavern, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
