<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>L--gley C--s his lamentation in New-gate who lies there in danger of his ears for printing and publishing sedition and treason, for this five years last past : a song.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42983</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38876068</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38876068</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152307</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A97311)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152307)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2292:7b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>L--gley C--s his lamentation in New-gate who lies there in danger of his ears for printing and publishing sedition and treason, for this five years last past : a song.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Dean, Bookseller ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes 3 lines of music following title.</note>
                  <note>Printed on verso of Wing (2nd ed.) N673, "A new miracle, or Dr. Nomans safe return ..." ; formerly identified as Wing C7690A.</note>
                  <note>Langley Curtis was a London printer who published works supporting Titus Oates in the Popish Plot.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Curtis, Langley.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152307:1"/>
            <head>L—GLEY C—S
His Lamentation in New-Gate;
Who lies there in danger of his Ears for Printing and Publiſhing Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
and Treaſon, for this Five Years laſt paſt. A SONG.</head>
            <p>
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>COME Whigs out of faſhion, of me take compaſſion,</l>
               <l>my Ears are in danger, my caſe may be yours;</l>
               <l>Long, long have I reigned diſturbing the Nation,</l>
               <l>now, now am made Captive to the higher Powers:</l>
               <l>With Pacquet &amp; Pamphlets, abus'd <hi>Church</hi> &amp; <hi>Chaplets,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>C—s</hi> Damn'd Courants did abuſe the <hi>King</hi> ſo,</l>
               <l>That none can defend us, till <hi>Tyburn</hi> befriend us,</l>
               <l>and ſend us a Hunting for <hi>Tapskie</hi> below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>The loſs of our Charter, and <hi>Colledge</hi> the Martyr,</l>
               <l>his Flayls are all ſeiz'd, and our Arms made a prey;</l>
               <l>We have loſt <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> both <hi>Jew, Turk,</hi> and <hi>Tartar,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>no Plots nor Caballs to recover the Day:</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Tony</hi> left ſquinting, our Cauſe has been ſinking,</l>
               <l>and our Party for <hi>Tyburn</hi> advancing you know;</l>
               <l>There's none can defend us, till <hi>Tyburn</hi> befriend us,</l>
               <l>and ſend us a Hunting for <hi>Eſſex</hi> below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>The Law for a Livery, will put me i'th Pillory,</l>
               <l>a damn'd hard Wooden Ruff for a Saint of the Cauſe;</l>
               <l>Had a Tory my place, I wou'd flear and look merrily,</l>
               <l>with hardened Brick-batts I'de pelt him with blows.</l>
               <l>When my Head peepeth thorough, the <hi>Tories</hi> will <hi>hollow,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>at poor</hi> L—gley C—is <hi>cry</hi> O Raree Show;</l>
               <l>Now none will defend us, till <hi>Tyburn</hi> befriend us,</l>
               <l>and ſend us a Hunting for <hi>Ruſſel</hi> below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>Poor <hi>Colly</hi> was Whipt too, for ſtretching an oath or ſo,</l>
               <l>and Damn'd <hi>Tory Rutland,</hi> too hard for us all;</l>
               <l>Theſe dayly misfortunes will all our Deſigns undoe,</l>
               <l>would his <hi>Founain</hi>-Tavern wou'd ſink, burn, or fall.</l>
               <l>But alas I am Gailed, and muſt not be bailed,</l>
               <l>as we ſerv'd the Papiſts, muſt we be ſerv'd ſo?</l>
               <l>There's none will defend us, till <hi>Ketch</hi> does befriend us,</l>
               <l>and ſend us a Hunting for <hi>Walcot</hi> below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Wou'd I were with <hi>Patience,</hi> I'de keep in his Stations,</l>
               <l>and ſave both my Ears, for the Doctor may want,</l>
               <l>I fear they'l be crapt if I live till next Seſſions,</l>
               <l>then <hi>Prance</hi> for his Swearing, may ſweat and look blank,</l>
               <l>But after a Coller, oft cometh a Halter,</l>
               <l>my Neck like my Ears are in danger, you know,</l>
               <l>There's none can defend us, till <hi>Ketch</hi> doth befriend us,</l>
               <l>and ſend us a Hunting for <hi>Sidney</hi> below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>Poor <hi>A—ld</hi> is Pounded, for Lying Confounded,</l>
               <l>by <hi>Wooſter,</hi> which he did moſt baſely defame:</l>
               <l>Poor <hi>Giles</hi> he was Pillar'd, 'cauſe <hi>A—ld</hi> was wounded,</l>
               <l>tho' by his own hands, Sir, in <hi>Jack-an-Apes-Lane;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now <hi>Giles</hi> he is Bailed, and <hi>A—ld</hi> is Goaled,</l>
               <l>there may lie and Rot too, for ought that we know:</l>
               <l>There's none will defend us, till <hi>Ketch</hi> doth befriend us,</l>
               <l>and ſend us all head-long toth' Old <hi>Rump</hi> below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mowbery</hi> and <hi>Balderen,</hi> Swore more like Fiends, then men,</l>
               <l>they both have been perjur'd ten thouſand times o're:</l>
               <l>They had but one Wife, and ſhe ſtill lay between them,</l>
               <l>they being our Saints, tho' ſhe cou'd be no Whore;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dangerfield</hi> Swore too, all ſorts of Oaths, black and blew,</l>
               <l>tho' he had been Carted, and Pillar'd before,</l>
               <l>Yet they ſtill eſcaped, tho' worſe no Hell raked,</l>
               <l>Then why may not <hi>I,</hi> that can Rebel no more?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>Yet that fortunate Hour, they got out of the Tower,</l>
               <l>both <hi>Wildman</hi> and <hi>Trenchard.</hi> Old <hi>Charlton</hi> and all:</l>
               <l>I may find Friends too, tho' <hi>Jefferies</hi> lookt ſower,</l>
               <l>and Pardon perhaps, when I come to <hi>White-hall;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Guineys five Thouſand too, (for Printing of Treaſon) due,</l>
               <l>like ſome for Ploting; a kind Recompence;</l>
               <l>While others for Loyalty, in the Goal dayly Dye,</l>
               <l>I'le into the Country, and live like a Prince.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for</hi> J. Dean, <hi>Bookſeller in</hi> Cranborn-ſtreet, <hi>in</hi> Leiceſter-Fields, <hi>near</hi> Newport-Houſe, 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
