<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The island of Assada, neere Madagascar impartially defined, being a succint, yet plenary discription of the situation, fertility and people therein inhabiting. Clearely demonstrating to the adventurer or planter, the right way for disposing his adventure to his most commodious advantage; advising people of all degrees, from the highest to the lowest, how suddainly raise their estate and fortunes· By Lieutenant Colonell Robert Hunt, governour thereof.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Hunt, Robert, Lieutenant Colonel.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A86908</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing H3744</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason E778_17</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R202470</IDNO>



<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99862734</IDNO>


<AVAILABILITY><P>This text has been selected for inclusion in the EEBO-TCP: Navigations collection, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities. To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication ( http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86908)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 167339)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 119:E778[17])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="4">The island of Assada, neere Madagascar impartially defined, being a succint, yet plenary discription of the situation, fertility and people therein inhabiting. Clearely demonstrating to the adventurer or planter, the right way for disposing his adventure to his most commodious advantage; advising people of all degrees, from the highest to the lowest, how suddainly raise their estate and fortunes· By Lieutenant Colonell Robert Hunt, governour thereof.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Hunt, Robert, Lieutenant Colonel.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 6 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[London] :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for Nicholas Bourne, at the south entrance of the Royall Exchange.,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>[1650]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Annotation in Thomason copy: "1650", "Aug. 10th".</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2016-01-29.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Assada (Madagascar) --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2009-02</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2009-04</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2009-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Lauren Proux</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2009-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Lauren Proux</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2009-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A86908">
<STC T="W">H3744</STC>
<STC T="T">E778_17</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99862734</BIBNO>
<VID>167339</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>The Island of ASSADA, Neere MADAGASCAR Impartially defined, being a succint, yet Plenary Discription of the Situation, Fertility and People therein Inhabiting.</P>
<P>Clearely demonstrating to the Adventurer or Planter, the right way for disposing his Adventure to his most Commodious advantage; Advising people of all degrees, from the highest to the lowest, how suddainly raise their Estate and Fortunes.</P>
<P>By Lieutenant Colonell <HI>Robert Hunt,</HI> Governour thereof.</P>
<P><HI>Mercatura, si tenuis, sordida si magna splendida, quaerenda pecunia primum.</HI></P>
<P>Printed for <HI>Nicholas Bourne,</HI> at the South entrance of the Royall <HI>Exchange.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="declaration">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD><HI>A DECLARATION, SHEWING, The Grounds and Reasons, with the Motives that induced Lieut. Col.</HI> Robert Hunt, <HI>to undertake the Voyage and Adventure, for setling a Plantation upon the Island called</HI> Assada, <HI>neere</HI> Madagascar; <HI>Published for satisfaction of his Friends, who earnestly desire the same.</HI></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">D</SEG>Eare Friends; It may seeme strange to some of you, that I, who through the blessing of God, had a comfortable provi∣sion for my out-ward subsistance in my owne Native Coun∣try, should now travell so farre abroad, and leave a Wife so deare unto me, so many neere Relations and Christian Friends, together with places of preferment which were offered me at home; But the truth is ever since I had the Honour to be imployed by those Noble Lords, and other Adventurers, by providence as Governour there; In which voyage, having seene shose Sou∣therne Plantations, beholding the Sweetenesse. Pleasantnesse, and Profitablenesse of them, as Nurseries of Trade to <HI>England;</HI> And considering the onely end of my comming into the World was to glorifie God in my Generation, which ac∣cording to the light of nature given me, I am perswaded that nothing more would conduce to that end, then endeavouring to make knowne God in the World, and to be usefull and serviceable to my Native Country, both which in this undertaking my Eye is fixed upon. For the First, I am perswaded the Lord hath a great worke by his Servants to make knowne the Lord Jesus
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>Christ, to the poore Heathen in these Eastern parts of the World, and I shall much rejoyce if the Lord shall please by me to open a doore for that purpose. For the second, the setling a Plantation in those parts, is likely to be of great advantage to this Common-wealth, in the increase of Trade and Navigation, since the discovery of this Island of <HI>Assada</HI> to me; I had longing thoughts and earnest desires of going thither, looking upon it as a worke of great concern∣ment for the future to this Nation, and out of our first attempt, I hope God in his due time will doe great things, therefore let none contemne the enterprise of small things; My purpose is by the blessing of the Almighty to endeavour the Settlement of an honest and just Government there, nearest to ehe Lawes of this Land, for greatest incouragement and securily to Adventurers; and for the better carrying on this worke, my Intentions are to settle two or three Godly men as Agents, at the King of the North end of <HI>Madagascars</HI> Court, whose worke shall be to indeavour to informe him and his people in the know∣ledge of the Gospell of Jesus Christ and to keepe a loving and peaceable corres∣pondency with them.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<P>FOr Information of such who desire to Adventure or Plant there, I shall now lay downe a Discription of the Situati∣on of the Island of <HI>Assada</HI> (as presented to me.) This Island lyeth Thirteene degrees in the Latitude of <HI>Barbadoo's,</HI> and is a∣bout that bignesse and goodnesse, and reported by them who have beene upon it, to be good Land, and to afford large Sugar-Caines, Rice, Corne and Cattle upon it, with store of Fruits, Fish, &amp;c. and whatsoever will grow upon <HI>Barbadoo's</HI> is likely to grow there, being all the yeare summer, and at one and the same time the Trees doe beare Buds, greene and ripe Fruits, it hath small hills and vallies, with fresh running waters and ly∣eth about nine miles from the great Island of <HI>Madagascar,</HI> and there are not above fifty or sixty poore people upon the island, which the King left to tend Cattle, to Fish and Plant Sugar∣Caines, which at time of the yeare they may carry to <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Bay,</HI> to sell to the <HI>Arabians;</HI> about ten yeares since there <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> foure or five hundred people gotten from <HI>Madagascar,</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣volted from the King, they made Warre with him divers <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>and pillaged the <HI>Arabian</HI> Junks, in which time an English Ship touching there, the King offered them, if they would helpe him to carry his men over to the Island, he would give them the Island, and halfe the people to be their servants: but they refu∣sing it, he having no Boats, but some few Canoes, which would carry not above 3. or 4. men at once in them, and not knowing how to get 40. men over to the Island, made rafts of Timber and so wafted them over to the Island, subdued the re∣volters, leaving but the number as aforesaid: so that my inten∣tions is to buy this Island of the King for the Accompt of the Adventurers, and to give him full conrent and satisfaction for it, He having first freed and promised it, or any other place in his Country to the English, we shall desire to promote his Trade and benefit which he is desirous of; And those which have been with him assures me, we need not question a free saile of our cōmodities, at a reasonable value: neere this Island are di∣vers small Islands without any people inhabiting them, which may be usefull to us.</P>
<P>This Island for bignesse is reckoned 16. miles square, and hath a good Harbour, where we intend by Gods blessing to build a Fort and Towne, and there to set down our selves: It is beleeved that this Island would maintain neere a hundreth thou∣sand people in way of Trade and Plantation, if once well plan∣ted, having enough besides, for above 200. <HI>Sugar</HI> works, be∣sides other Commodities.</P>
<P>The Commodities we hope to raise, are <HI>Sugar, Indico, ginger, cot∣ton wooll, Tobacco, Rice,</HI> and <HI>Pepper, &amp;c.</HI> And for provisions, <HI>Corne; Cattle, Hoggs, Poultry, Rice, Gravances, Potatoes, Oringes, Lem∣mons,</HI> and <HI>Pines,</HI> with other fruits, very usefull and at farre easier Rates, then at <HI>Barbadoes,</HI> (as for instance,)
<TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL>A Plantation of 300. Acres of Land to plant a large Sugar-work, will cost at <HI>Barbadoes</HI></CELL>
<CELL>2000, pound.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>20. English servants to transport with Provision,</CELL>
<CELL>300. l.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>100. Negroes servants at 25. l. and 30. l, apiece,</CELL>
<CELL>2700. l.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Toole, Cloathing, and severall necessaries,</CELL>
<CELL>300. l.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>20. Cattle of severall sorts,</CELL>
<CELL>700. l.</CELL>
</ROW>
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
<ROW>
<CELL>The like at <HI>Assada,</HI></CELL>
<CELL>6000. pound.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>300. Acres of Land purchased at 12. d. the acre,</CELL>
<CELL>15. l.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>20. English servants to transport and furnish,</CELL>
<CELL>300. l.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>100. Negroes at 20. s.</CELL>
<CELL>100. l.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Tooles cloathing, &amp;c.</CELL>
<CELL>200. l.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>20 Cattell of severall sorts,</CELL>
<CELL>25.. l.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>And for all manner of cloathing and Tooles may be had neare hand for the 3. part it cost at <HI>Barbadoes,</HI></CELL>
<CELL>640. l.</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
<P>So that the proportion will hold for a greater or lesser work of <HI>Sugar, Indico, Cotton, Ginger,</HI> and <HI>Tobacco, &amp;c.</HI> And whereas at <HI>Barbadoes</HI> they relate they plant 16. hund. or 20. hund. of Sugar, each servant, 160. l. or 200. l. of <HI>Indico,</HI> 1000. l. of <HI>Cotton-wooll,</HI> 20. hund, weight of <HI>Ginger,</HI> 1500. weight of <HI>Tobacco,</HI> in a yeare, its hopefull to raise those Commodities farre Cheaper then at <HI>Barbadoes:</HI> we hope to build small Vessels, to trade to our Neighbouring Countries, and vend the same at as good rates as they are like to be worth at <HI>London</HI> for ready money, and other Commodities which are usefull to vend in <HI>India:</HI> And by that meanes preserve the Coyne of this Nation, and in a short time, when once setled, may invest our selves at our Returnes with East <HI>India</HI> Commodities, bringing home thence as much com∣modities as usually came to this Nation, and save the sending out of a 1000 l. <HI>per annum</HI> of Silver, fully providing our selves of men from <HI>Arabia Madagascar, Africa,</HI> and <HI>India,</HI> to Plant some to be free men, others servants. One <HI>English</HI> man will go∣verne ten of those Nations: thus may Men, Women, and chil∣dren be bred up in the knowledge of God, and in time this Island lying so well for Trade, may be a scale of Trade to the <HI>English,</HI> for those parts of the World, <HI>as Batavia</HI> is to the <HI>Dutch,</HI> and <HI>God</HI> to the <HI>Portingalls,</HI> who have 20, times their number of Strangers live amongst them, and under their Go∣vernment.</P>
<P>The Island of <HI>Madagascar,</HI> which lyeth in sight of this Island of <HI>Assada,</HI> is 900 miles long, it hath seven Kings in it, the chief
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>lives at the North end, the Commoditie it affords, is <HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i Ambergreese, Iron, Tortle shels, Landall-wood, Ibony wood, Druggs, &amp;c. Augustine Bay</HI> where our <HI>English</HI> usually touch to water and buy Cattell, is the worser part of the Island, in regard there is usually no Trade with any other Nation: nor any Townes, nor provisions for Planting, their being but a small number of peo∣ple which are Cow-keepers, &amp;c.</P>
<P>Whereas at <HI>Assada, Bay,</HI> an English Ship putting in there in her Voyage to <HI>India,</HI> found a small Towne called <HI>Antasia,</HI> where the <HI>Arabians</HI> lades divers Junks of <HI>Rice,</HI> yearly in exchange for <HI>Cullivers, Knives,</HI> and <HI>India</HI> Commodities, from thence our English travelling up to the Kings Town, about 20. miles up in the Land, passed through two Villages about a mile long, well inhabited with people, there being about them fields of <HI>Rice,</HI> and <HI>Sugar Caines,</HI> with hundreds of Cattell; their build∣ings are of Timber two stories high, open to walke in the hot weather, the upper Roomes to lodge in. The people naturally are very kinde and courteous, the North part for 2 hundred miles in length, is governed by a King, whom they went unto, to obtain licence to trade, he and his women dwelling in a Pal∣lace about a quarter of a mile round, at the end of which is a small Towne, like a Parke in it, about 500. Oxen feeding, the people are generally his slaves, he useth our English court∣eously, shewed them his Treasure, which was a Massy Silver Staffe, some peeces of Eight, peeces of cloth of Gold, of Sattin and silke stuffes, <HI>Arabian</HI> Coates, which the <HI>Arabians</HI> brought from <HI>India,</HI> being bought of them for <HI>Ambergreese, Tortle-shels,</HI> which are his owne Commodities.</P>
<P>He invited our men to come againe, and promised all his Country should be at their command.</P>
<P>So that notwithstanding the dissolving of the Plantation at <HI>Augastines Bay,</HI> where those that know it dare say, there is nei∣ther good fresh water, nor wood to build withall, nor Provi∣sion, nor Gardens for mans use: But it is a Marsh ground, like <HI>Sandwitch <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ownes in Kent,</HI> not sit for Plantation, which is an en∣couragemen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to proceed in this designe.</P>
<P>Thus you have heard in part what is related to me, by those who have been neare 8. Mone<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="uom" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e upon the place, men of honest
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>conversation, who <HI>I</HI> beleeve deales truly with me, and the same is confirmed in the generall in Print by English and Portugall writers, for those fellow Souldiers, Country men and dearest friends of mine, that resolve to travell, I doe beleeve, by Gods blessing, that not any part of the World is more advantagious for a Plantation, bring every way as well for pleasure as well as profit, in my estimation. And for those that have either little or much to adventure, they may imploy it this way, and those which have nothing, if they come over, for foure yeares as ser∣vants to their Adventurers, they shall have Meate Drinke and Apparell provided, and at the end of the terme in recompence of their service, have as much Land to Plant on as they can im∣ploy, with six Moneths provisions, and three <HI>Negros</HI> servants, which at <HI>Barbadoo's</HI> were worth a 100. pound, which if endu∣striously imployed, may raise their Fortunes every yeare as much.</P>
<P><HI>And to my Honourable and worthy Adventurers, my humble sute is, that you would take care of sending me timely supplyes of men, that I may be more enabled to goe on with those de∣signes proposed; which I forbeare to mention in publique, untill a more convenient time for the some,: And by the blessing of God I doubt not of a good issue.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

