<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Joyfull nevves from the Princes fleet at sea; containing a narrative of the several fights and ingagements, between the two Navies, the Bristoll Men of War, and the London and Yarmouth Marchants, since the first of Aprill 1649. With the resolution of the Princes sea-men touching the Parliament and Army and two of them adjudged to die, and to be hang'd up at the main masts, for declaring against the proceedings of prince Rupert. As also the manner how they were rescued from him by the rest of the mariners. Likewise, a great victory obtained by Col. Jones in Ireland, against the Marquesse of Ormond. And the proposals of the Lord Inchiquins army, to be sent to the parliament of England. Published by authority.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A87414</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing J1150</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason E550_20</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R205648</IDNO>



<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99864967</IDNO>


<AVAILABILITY><P>This text has been selected for inclusion in the EEBO-TCP: Navigations collection, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities. To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication ( http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87414)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117200)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 85:E550[20])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Joyfull nevves from the Princes fleet at sea; containing a narrative of the several fights and ingagements, between the two Navies, the Bristoll Men of War, and the London and Yarmouth Marchants, since the first of Aprill 1649. With the resolution of the Princes sea-men touching the Parliament and Army and two of them adjudged to die, and to be hang'd up at the main masts, for declaring against the proceedings of prince Rupert. As also the manner how they were rescued from him by the rest of the mariners. Likewise, a great victory obtained by Col. Jones in Ireland, against the Marquesse of Ormond. And the proposals of the Lord Inchiquins army, to be sent to the parliament of England. Published by authority.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 6 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Aprill 12. ... Printed for R. Williamson,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1649.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2016-01-29.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Great Britain --  History, Naval --  Stuarts, 1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Naval operations --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2013-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Enrique Valdive</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Enrique Valdive</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A87414">
<STC T="W">J1150</STC>
<STC T="T">E550_20</STC>
<STC T="C">R205648</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99864967</BIBNO>
<VID>117200</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>JOYFULL NEVVES <HI>FROM</HI> The Princes Fleet at Sea; containing a Narrative of the several Fights and Ingagements, between the two Navies, the <HI>Bristoll</HI> Men of War, and the <HI>London</HI> and <HI>Yarmouth</HI> Marchants, since the first of <HI>Aprill</HI> 1649. With the Resolution of the Princes Sea-men touching the Parliament and Army and two of them adjudged to die, and to be hang'd up at the main Masts, for de∣claring against the proceedings of prince <HI>Rupert.</HI> As also the manner how they were rescued from him by the rest of the Mariners. Likewise, a great Victory obtained by Col. <HI>Jones</HI> in <HI>Ireland,</HI> against the Marquesse of <HI>Ormond.</HI> And the proposals of the Lord <HI>Inchiquins</HI> Army, to be sent to the parliament of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Published by Authority.</HI></P>
<P><FIGURE>
<FIGDESC>woodcut of ships at sea</FIGDESC>
</FIGURE></P>
<P><HI>Aprill</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>2. <HI>London</HI> Printed for <HI>R. Williamson,</HI> 1649.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="account">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<LETTER LANG="eng">
<HEAD>JOYFULL NEWES From the Fleet at SEA, And a Narrative of the severall Fights and Ingage∣ments between the two Navies, since the first of <HI>Aprill,</HI> 1649.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Ince my last of the second of this instant, we have received certain information of the further proceedings of the Prin∣ces Fleet, and that they have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Navy into three Squadrons; the first commanded by Prince <HI>Rupert,</HI> who is to guard the Irish Seas, and to attend the motion of Col. <HI>Jones</HI> Governor of the City of <HI>Dublin</HI> for the Parliament of <HI>England;</HI> the second, by Prince <HI>Maurice,</HI> who with 20 Sayle is
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>to attend the motion of Captain <HI>Moulton</HI> in the We∣stern Riding; the third by Captain <HI>Jerden,</HI> designed for the Lands-End, to attend the motion and coming out of the parliaments Summers Fleet; all which, though numerous in shipping, yet weakly man'd, and dare not engage, unlesse with great advantage, the Sea∣men begin to moulter in their affections, and shew a great dislike of the proceedings of their Officers; for divers who have escaped at their coming into Creekes, do declare, That they begin to languish for their late perfidious Revolt, and would fain make a recantation, and that if once they could have the opportunity to come ashore, are unanimously resolved to desert the princes service: however, if they cannot purchase their liberty one way, they are resolved to faciliate it ano∣the; and that upon a neer Engagement with the Parlia∣ments Fleet, it is believed they will take the same reso∣lution as the Land Souldiers have formerly done, and (upon good articles and conditions) deliver up their Officers to mercy, &amp;c.</P>
<P>Some action hath lately hapned between divers Mar∣chants, and prince <HI>Manrice</HI> his ships, and much hurt done on both sides; but after some dispute, and severall boardings, the Victory fell to the Marchant Men of War, who sunk two of the revolted ships, wherin was 50 piece of Ordnance, and chased the rest above seven Leagues, but by reason of a storm, they were forced to desist from further pursuit, and to leave them to the mercy of the raging Billowes.</P>
<P>These ships are said to be bound for <HI>London, Lyn,</HI> and <HI>Yarmouth,</HI> who hold conjunction together for the safety and preservation of their Marchandize.</P>
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
<P>Since which time we have received other joyfull in∣telligence from the <HI>Maurician</HI> Fleet, and it is likewise confirmed by two men of War who last night cast anchor in this Harbour: they purport, that upon their crossing the Western Channell, they were set upon by six of the princes ships, who gave them 12. broad sides, but were answered again with another Volley from the Sons of <HI>Mars,</HI> and after a hot conflict, be∣came victiorious, killing many of their men, chasing the rest, some taking their pursuit without a Mast, o∣thers without a stern, and their Sayls all rent and torn. But by reason of the distempers of the Sea, and the dangerous breaches they had received from the Ene∣mies round shot, were forced to strike in here for re∣fuge, for the repairing and new rigging of their ships. Those who have been in action with them, report them to be as cowardly an Enemy, as ever engaged upon the Neptune Seas, and that 30 of the parliaments ships wel man'd, will (in all probability) soon expell the fury of 60 of theirs.</P>
<P>We heare that Capt. <HI>Moulton</HI> is in a defensive po∣sture, and that he sayles sometimes within sight of the princes Fleet, but declines engagement at present.</P>
<P>We likewise hear of a great insurrection arising in prince <HI>Ruperts</HI> Squadron, the manner thus: two Sea∣man speaking some words touching the unjustnesse of their cause, and the unlawfulnesse of their engagement, being over-heard, were brought before the prince, and (according to Martial Law) were adjudged to die, and to be hang'd up at the main Mast, but the Seamen hea∣ring thereof, unanimously rescued him from the po∣wer of the Marshal; other Captains were summoned, to see the princes tyranny performed, but their Mariners likewise joyntly resolved not to execute the same.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Bristoll</HI> <DATE>7. <HI>Aprill,</HI> 1649.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
<P>The COMMONS of <HI>England</HI> assembled in parlament taking into their serious consideration, the great prejudice &amp; apparent danger that might be∣fall this City and Nation, if the four Aldermen for∣merly committed to the Tower, <HI>viz.</HI> Alderman <HI>Bunch</HI> Alderman <HI>Langham,</HI> and — and the late Lord Ma∣jor should be continued any Office, or publique em∣ployment, after mature deliberation in reference ther∣unto, Ordered, that the said four Aldermen, and the late Lord Major <HI>Reynaldson</HI> should be disabled Aldermen of the City of <HI>London,</HI> or bear any Office or Employ∣ment in this Common-wealth, and that the Common-councell do proceed to the election of new Aldermen in their steads.</P>
<P>And upon information given, that there was matter of proof sufficient for convicting Major Gen. <HI>Browne,</HI> now prisoner to the parl. the House spent some time in debate thereof, and at the last came to this Result:</P>
<P><HI>Resolved by the Commons of</HI> England <HI>assembled in par∣liament,</HI> That the said Major Gen. <HI>Brown</HI> shal be forth∣with brought to his Tryall.</P>
<P><HI>Resolved. &amp;c.</HI> That a Charge be drawn up against him, for the convicting him of such crimes and misde∣meanours, as shall be exhibited and made good upon matter of proof; it appearing that there is sufficient testimony and witnesse, <HI>viz.</HI> 1 That he hath beene a great Instrument in abetting and promoting the last Rebellion in <HI>Kent, Essex,</HI> and severall other parts of this Nation. 2 That there had been severall levyes of mo∣ney, and that he had received the sum of 10000, <HI>li.</HI> for the better faciliating and carrying on of that trayterus work and design, against the Parl. and people of <HI>Eng∣land,</HI> &amp;c. For these, and many other crimes and misde∣meanours, he is adjudged (in the name of the Comons
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>of <HI>England</HI>) to be brought to a fair and legal tryal, but the time and place not yet prefixed.</P>
<P>The honorable Court of parl. have also taken into their serious consideration, the manifold hardens and oppressures of the people of this Nation, and have de∣bated a way for the prevention thereof for the future and have ordered a Declaration to be brought in con∣sisting of severall particulars touching Religion, the composing of all differences, the redressing of grievan∣ces, the easing of the people from all burdens and hea∣vy oppressures, and the setling of this distracted church and common-wealth, as it shall stand enacted and con∣firmed for the future; and to the end that the people of this Nation may receive a little glimpse of their future freedom, I shall here insert the chief heads of the groundwork of their Declaration, <HI>viz.</HI> 1 That the Ministery of the Gospel shal not have their Tythes ta∣ken away, until another way be provided for them as a sufficient maintenance. 2 That the Government to bee established in <HI>England,</HI> shal be the <HI>presbyterian govern¦ment,</HI> and to be erected in such a manner, that the pu∣rity and splendor of the Gospel may shine forth tho∣row out all corners of this Nation. 4 That a way shall be provided for admission of all such churches as tend to godlinesse, and the advancement of the sacred Word of Jesus Christ, and to be without disturbance. 4 That all such Ministers, or other persons whatsoever, who shal endeavour to promote sinne, and dishonour the truth, shall bee supprest, and proceeded against accor∣ding to the penalty of their Crime or Fact. These, and other particulars, are now in debate, which will sud∣denly be of maturity for the publike view. The com∣mons have also ordered that the committee of the Ar∣my
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>be required to bring in an Act, with certain Rules how to take off the Monster of Nature <HI>Eree quarter,</HI> &amp; all other charges from the people, and therefore resol∣ved, that a committee should be nominated to advise with his Excellency, and the Officers of the Army, in relation thereunto.</P>
<P>Letters from <HI>Chester</HI> say, That renowned Col. <HI>Jones</HI> is marched forth into the field with 3000 Horse and Foot, and hath fallen upon some of the Enemies quar∣ters within 20 miles of <HI>Dublin,</HI> put many to the sword relieved two castles, who were in great distresse, and even at the last gasp of being devoured by the barba∣rous and bloud-thirsty Rebels; After which he mar∣ched up further into the Country, whose endeavours and motion being crowned with prosperous successe, returned again to the City, with some provisions and necessaries for the relief of his Souldiery, and the di∣stressed Inhabitants thereof: From whence wee also hear, that the Lord <HI>Inchiquins</HI> Briggade, consisting of 4000 Foot, and 2500. Horse, decline engagement with <HI>Ormond</HI> against the English, and that there are divers proposals in a preparative way to be presented to the parliament of <HI>England,</HI> consisting of severall Branches touching a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Act of Oblivion, their joyning with Colonell</HI> Jones, <HI>and their reception into future pay;</HI> All which will prove Instrumentall motives, for reducing that Kingdom from tyranny and oppression, and restoring of it, to its just liberty and freedom.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="imprimatur">
<P>Imprimatur, </P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>TH<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>O: JENNINGS.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

