<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A True and authentick copy of the most horrid and stupendious oath, whereby the French king confirmed his alliance with the Turks faithfully translated from the French historiographer, Du Ribier, in his memoirs, whereof the Latin original is here annexed.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A94893</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing T2414A</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R42929</IDNO>



<IDNO TYPE="oclc">ocm 38875954</IDNO>


<AVAILABILITY><P>This text has been selected for inclusion in the EEBO-TCP: Navigations collection, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities. To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication ( http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94893)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152453)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2297:16)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A True and authentick copy of the most horrid and stupendious oath, whereby the French king confirmed his alliance with the Turks faithfully translated from the French historiographer, Du Ribier, in his memoirs, whereof the Latin original is here annexed.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed for R. Bentley, and are to be sold by R. Baldwin,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1694.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Caption title.</NOTE><NOTE>Imprint from colophon.</NOTE><NOTE>"Licens'd, Feb. 22. 1693 [i.e. 1694]. D. Poplar."</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in: Cambridge University Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2016-01-29.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM TYPE="topical term">Political satire, English.</TERM><TERM TYPE="geographic name">France --  Politics and government --  1643-1715 --  Humor.</TERM><TERM TYPE="genre/form">Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2013-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Anne Simpson</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Anne Simpson</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A94893">
<STC T="W">T2414A</STC>
<STC T="C">R42929</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">38875954</BIBNO>
<VID>152453</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>A True and Authentick COPY, Of the Form of The most Horrid and Stupendious OATH, WHEREBY The <HI>French King</HI> Confirmed his Alliance with the <HI>TURKS.</HI></HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Faithfully Translated from the <HI>French</HI> Historiographer, <HI>Du Ribier,</HI> in his Memoirs, whereof the Latin Original is here annexed.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="oath">
<HEAD>The True Form of the Oath.</HEAD>
<P>BY the Great and High God, Merciful and Gracious, Maker of Heaven and Earth, and of all Things that are in them; and by the Holy Gospel, by the Holy Baptism, by Saint <HI>John</HI> the Baptist, and by the Christian Faith; I Promise and Swear, to Declare all Things I shall know, to the Most High Lord <HI>Sultan</HI>— whose Reign God be pleased to strengthen; I will be a special Friend to his Friends, and an Enemy to his Enemies; I will be a Redeemer to the <HI>Turks</HI> Prisoners, from the hands of his Enemies, nothing shall be fraudulently done on my side. And in case I neglect to do it; I shall be an Apostate, and a Prevaricator against the Commands of the Holy Gospel, and of the Christian Faith; I will say the Gospel is false; I will deny that Jesus Christ is living, and that his Mother was a Virgin; I will slay a Hog upon the Font of the Baptism, and Curse the Priests of the Altar; I will commit Fornication upon the Altar with Lasciviousness, and receive upon my self all the Curses of the Holy Fa∣thers. So help me God from his High Place.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 LANG="lat" TYPE="translation of oath">
<HEAD>Here follows the Original Copy in <HI>Latin.</HI></HEAD>
<P><HI>PER Deum Magnum &amp; Altum, Miseri∣cordem &amp; Benignum, Creatorem Coeli &amp; Terrae, &amp; omnium quae in eis sunt, &amp; per Sancta haec Evangelia, per Sanctum Baptisma, per Sanctum Johannem Baptistam, &amp; per Fidem Christianorum, Promitto &amp; Juro, quod omnia quae novero, aperta erunt Altissimo Domino Sul∣tano, — cujus Regnum Deus fortificet; Ero Amicus suorum unicus, &amp; inimicus inimicorum, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o Redemptor Captivorum Turcarum ex vincu∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Hostium ejus; nihil in mea parte fraudulen∣tum erit. Quod si hoc neglexerim ero Apostata;</HI></P>
<P><HI>Mandatorum Sancti Evangelii, Christianaeque Fidei Praevaricator, dicam Evangelium falsum <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse, negabo Christum vivere, &amp; Matrem ejus Vir∣ginem fuisse; super Fontem Baptismatis Porcum interficiam, &amp; Altaris Presbyteros maledicam; super Altare Fornicabor cum Luxuria; &amp; San∣ctorum Patrum maledictiones omnes in me reci∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iam. Ita me Deus respiciat ex alto.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="response">
<P>GOod God! What a complication of Im∣piety, Blasphemy, Contradiction, Ex∣travagancy, and Folly, is there in this <HI>Oath,</HI> and how Guilty are both those, who Swear such an <HI>Oath,</HI> and those who prescribe it to be Sworn!</P>
<P>We see by this <HI>Oath,</HI> the <HI>French</HI> King prays to <HI>God</HI> to prosper the <HI>Sultan's Reign;</HI> and en∣gages to do his utmost endeavours to promote his Interests against his <HI>Enemies,</HI> who are the Christians, and to be their <HI>Enemy</HI> in the <HI>Turks</HI> behalf; and <HI>in case he neglects to do it,</HI> he consents to be <HI>an Apostate from the Christian Faith;</HI> that is, unless he strives with all his power to overthrow the <HI>Christian Interest</HI> and <HI>Faith,</HI> and the <HI>Holy Gospel, he will be an Apo∣state from the Christian Faith. Nothing,</HI> says he, <HI>shall be fraudulently done on my side.</HI> How! can there be any thing more fraudulent and treacherous, than to call God for a Witness of such an execrable <HI>Oath,</HI> contrived against God himself? Is it not a horrid fraud, to call the <HI>Gospel</HI> and the <HI>Baptism Holy,</HI> and at the same time, to say, that in case he does not himself all what in him lies to destroy both; <HI>the Gospel,</HI> and <HI>the Christian Faith will be false.</HI> But we are much beholding to him for his Moderation, in <HI>committing</HI> only <HI>Fornication upon the Altar,</HI> tho' he does it <HI>with Lascivi∣ousness,</HI> for he might as well for ought I know, have committed the Crime of <HI>Sodomy.</HI></P>
<P>A Prince, who offers to do such Things as are mentioned in this <HI>Oath,</HI> in case he does not keep such an abominable <HI>Oath,</HI> is guilty of all those Crimes already; and does no better, than if he had said, <HI>I Swear by the Most High God,</HI> to Kill <HI>my Father and my Mother, and all my Relations, and in case I do not perform my Vow, I am resolved to say there is no God;</HI> such is the Religion of <HI>the Most Christian King.</HI></P>
<P>It was <HI>Francis</HI> the I. who, first of all the <HI>French</HI> Kings, took this astonishing <HI>Oath,</HI> as it is reported by the <HI>French</HI> Historiographer <HI>Du Ribier, in his Memoirs;</HI> he was then in∣gaged in a War against <HI>Charles</HI> the Vth Empe∣rour, so that he thought fit to make an Al∣liance with the <HI>Turks,</HI> to get some Succour
<PB REF="2"/>from them; and indeed, they sent a great Fleet and Army to help him, under the Com∣mand of their Admiral and General <HI>Barba∣rossa,</HI> who Landed in <HI>France;</HI> and did in <HI>Provence</HI> and the County of <HI>Nyssa</HI> great mis∣chiefs, more a great deal than to the Empe∣ror's Subjects. <HI>Du Ribier</HI> reports, that none in the <HI>French</HI> King's Council opposed this <HI>Oath,</HI> but only <HI>Chancellor du Prat,</HI> who was mightily against it, but could not prevail, so that it was taken by <HI>Francis</HI> accordingly.</P>
<P>But it may be, some will say, tho <HI>Francis</HI> the Ist. took that <HI>Oath,</HI> it is not certain, that <HI>Lewis</HI> the XIVth. has taken it, in making Al∣liance with the <HI>Turks.</HI> I confess indeed, no Historiographer has relate <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> as has been done of his Pred<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 chunk" DISP="…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> 'tis no wonder, for such things are carefully kept secret during his Life, and shall not be known before his Death; Methinks there is little Reason to doubt he has done it also, or some other worse, and this for the following Rea∣sons. 1st. It is the constant practice of all the Princes and States, when they have once prevailed upon another State to Treat an Alliance with them, upon Terms, and Forms, and Expressions Favourable, Advantagious, and Honourable to their own Party, never to change any thing of them in the following Treaties or Alliances with the same, unless there has been a great Change made also in the respective Fortunes of those States, and that which was the less potent then, is become the more powerful or predominant. We do not see there has been any such alteration or mutation made amongst those two great Nations, the <HI>French</HI> and the <HI>Turks;</HI> and this has certainly still as great advantage now over <HI>Lewis</HI> the XIVth, as she had over <HI>Francis</HI> the Ist, when he took this <HI>Oath.</HI> 2. <HI>Francis</HI> the Ist. was certainly, as appears by his History, far less Ambitious, and a Better, and Greater Man in all respects, than <HI>Lewis</HI> the XIVth ever was. 3. There must needs be a horrid Ingagement between them, against the Chri∣stians, since we see every year, what efforts the <HI>French</HI> King makes against <HI>Germany</HI> in the <HI>Turks</HI> behalf, and that the <HI>Turks</HI> persist in continuing this War, so extremely ruinous to them, against their Custom. But howe∣ver it be, it can be easily proved, he has done much worse in that respect, than his Prede∣cessor ingaged to do, so that we cannot do him any injury, in thinking he has taken the same <HI>Oath,</HI> or a worse one, if possible. For suppose <HI>Lewis</HI> the XIVth, has not taken the same <HI>Oath,</HI> yet it cannot be denyed, that he is more guilty, for having done without <HI>Oath,</HI> what <HI>Francis</HI> the Ist, had ingaged by <HI>Oath</HI> to doe, but did not actually perform it. This took that <HI>Oath,</HI> Transported with a great Passion against <HI>Charles</HI> the Vth, Emperour, but the other does it in cold Blood. And we do not see by <HI>Francis</HI> his History, he has done any great mischief to Christians, in be∣half of the <HI>Turks,</HI> comparable to what <HI>Lewis</HI> the XIVth has done. 'Tis worse ten times to commit a Crime without threatning; than to threaten without committing of it.</P>
<P>By all the Tenour of this present <HI>French</HI> King's Conduct, we see he has Sworn, I know not how many <HI>Oaths</HI> upon the <HI>Holy Gospel</HI> and <HI>Baptism,</HI> in several Alliances and Trea∣ties with most States in <HI>Europe,</HI> and with his own Subjects also, and has broken as many times his <HI>Oaths.</HI> This is as much as to say, the <HI>Gospel</HI> and the <HI>Christian Faith are false,</HI> and to <HI>deny that Christ is Living.</HI> When he does condemn one year by all his Universities, the <HI>Pope's Infallibility,</HI> and his <HI>Authority above the Council,</HI> his <HI>Power over the Temporals of Princes, and of Deposing them when he pleases;</HI> and another year admits the <HI>same Infallibility of the Pope,</HI> and his <HI>Almighty Power</HI> both in <HI>Heaven and Earth, &amp;c.</HI> Is it not as much as to say, the <HI>Gospel is false,</HI> and <HI>the Christian Faith,</HI> a trifle? When he pretends to impose Laws upon Mens Consciences, and force them to believe what he pleases, and will be called by the Name of <HI>Providence,</HI> of <HI>Immortal,</HI> of <HI>Divine Majesty,</HI> is it not as much as to <HI>curse the Gospel and the Christian Faith?</HI> As for his being a <HI>special Friend</HI> to the <HI>Turks, and an Enemy to his Enemies,</HI> every body knows what mischiefs he has done to <HI>Germany,</HI> in behalf of the Infidels, and how he helps them with all kind of Officers and Engineers against the Emperour, the <HI>Polonians,</HI> and <HI>Venetians,</HI> and has exhausted almost all the Mony of his Kingdom for their sake, postponing his own Subjects Interest, to theirs, and treating them as Enemies to the <HI>Turks:</HI> So that 'tis evident, he must have taken his Predecessor's <HI>Oath</HI> with the <HI>Turks,</HI> or some other more execra∣ble <HI>Oath,</HI> since he has done a great deal worse, and is without Comparison more Ambitious, and Irreligious than <HI>Francis</HI> the Ist was, and stands in greater need of the <HI>Turks</HI> help, for his unjust Designs.</P>
<P>We have here also a true Character of the <HI>Turks</HI> Genius, who prescribed the <HI>French</HI> King such a Contradictory and Blasphemous <HI>Oath,</HI> upon which they could not rely in the least, if they had had any Honesty or Judgment. For how could they imagine, that a Man profes∣sing himself to be a Christian, and calling the <HI>Gospel Holy,</HI> and <HI>the Baptism Holy,</HI> &amp;c. would oblige himself seriously and in earnest, to deny all the Truths of the Gospel, in case he failed himself of his word; that is, to believe that God should be false, because he should have been false himself. For 'tis just the same, as if a Christian Prince, did exact from the <HI>Sultan</HI> such an <HI>Oath,</HI> whereby the <HI>Sultan</HI> should Swear by his Holy <HI>Alchoran,</HI> and the Holy <HI>Mahometan</HI> Faith, and by his Great Prophet <HI>Mahomet,</HI> that he would be faithful to Christians, in destroying the <HI>Mahometan</HI>'s Interest; and in case he did neglect to do it like a Knave, <HI>Mahomet</HI> would be a Knave also, and his <HI>Alchoran</HI> a Fable, and that he would hereafter Worship a Hog in his <HI>Mosque,</HI> and commit Adultery upon <HI>Mahomet</HI>'s Tomb. Certainly, no Man of any Honesty or Judg∣ment, would impose such an <HI>Oath</HI> upon any other Man. The <HI>Turks</HI> did it only out of a blind and inveterate aversion they bear to the Christian Religion; they pretended to raise thereby a great Triumph to <HI>Mahomet,</HI> over our Saviour. For how is it possible other∣wise, to trust to such an <HI>Oath,</HI> which none but a Treacherous and Unworthy Man can take, of what Religion soever he may be?</P>
<P>Licens'd, <HI>Feb.</HI> 22. 1693. <HI>D. Poplar.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="colophon">
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI> Printed for <HI>R. Bentley,</HI> and are to be Sold by <HI>R. Baldwin,</HI> 1694.</P>
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

