<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A true relation of the severall negotiations which have pass'd between his Majesty the King of Svveden and His Highness the Elector of Brandenburgh. Translated out of French.</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">True relation of the several negotiations which have passed between his Majesty the King of Sweden. English</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A95270</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing T3045</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R232949</IDNO>



<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99898084</IDNO>


<AVAILABILITY><P>This text has been selected for inclusion in the EEBO-TCP: Navigations collection, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities. To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication ( http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95270)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133421)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2557:28)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A true relation of the severall negotiations which have pass'd between his Majesty the King of Svveden and His Highness the Elector of Brandenburgh. Translated out of French.</TITLE><TITLE TYPE="alt" I2="0">True relation of the several negotiations which have passed between his Majesty the King of Sweden. English</TITLE><AUTHOR>Charles X Gustav, King of Sweden, 1622-1660.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Friedrich Wilhelm, Elector of Brandenburg, 1620-1688.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[2], 61, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>[s.n.],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>printed in the year 1659.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Signed and dated at end: Dated from Collen on the Spree, the 14th of Aug. 1658. O. Barron of Suerin, D. Weiman,.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2016-01-29.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Prussia (Germany) --  Foreign relations.</TERM><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Sweden --  Foreign relations.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2013-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Geremy Carnes</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-07</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Geremy Carnes</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A95270">
<STC T="W">T3045</STC>
<STC T="C">R232949</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99898084</BIBNO>
<VID>133421</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>A TRUE RELATION OF THE Severall Negotiations which have pass'd between his Majesty the King of <HI>SVVEDEN,</HI> AND His Highness the Elector of <HI>BRANDENBƲRGH.</HI></P>
<P>Translated out of French.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed in the Year 1659.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="account">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A TRUE RELATION OF SUCH Passages as hapned in the Iourney Undertaken by the Baron of <HI>SUERIN,</HI> and the Honourable M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>WEYMAN, Deputies</HI> on the behalf of the <HI>Prince Elector</HI> of <HI>Bran∣denburg</HI> to the <HI>King of Sweden.</HI></HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">In the Moneths of <HI>May</HI> and <HI>June</HI> 1658.</HEAD>
<P>IT is not without a great deal of <HI>regret,</HI> that we are <HI>enforced</HI> to begin this Relation by complaints, against those who are the causes of the desolation of our beloved and dear Countrey: But its the very last extremity which exacts them at our hands, and which obligeth us to make a sad refle∣ction on the pitifull estate wherein we have seen <HI>Germany</HI> in∣gaged, by the Forces of those, who, <HI>under the cloak of Liberty and Religion,</HI> have in such a lamentable manner extenuated that <HI>fair body,</HI> as they have left it but a bare <HI>skeleton:</HI> there is not so despicable a <HI>German,</HI> who hath but one sole drop of bloud left in his veins, that cannot be sensible hereof, and who can cease from sighing, at the rehersall of the calamities wherewithall his Countrey hath been afflicted. <HI>We have dearly bought our Sla∣very, at the expence of our Estates, our Goods, our Bloud, our Honour, and our reputations; and we have forgot what we once our selves were, to establish the Names of those, who were scarce ever heard of, less known in the Empire. Nor have they onely setled the Seats of their Dominion on our Frontiers, but even our fairest and most beautifull Provinces along the Elve, the Weser, and the Oder, do groan under the intollerable captivity of their Government; Strangers do triumph over our Liberties,</HI> and they make a mockingstock of Religion, whilest under the pretence thereof, they have possessed them∣selves
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>of all <HI>Pomerania,</HI> and those other great Estates and Ter∣ritories which they enjoy in the rest of the <HI>Empire.</HI></P>
<P>It seemed that at length God would have pity on us, and that by <HI>the Peace of Munster</HI> he would in some manner disbur∣burden us of our miseries; wherfore all men did generally return their thanks and acknowledgments to the Almighty thereon, since all men beleeved they might have enjoyed their own in peace, and might have reaped the fruit of their labours in quiet, under their own vines and figg-trees; and those who had overwatched and outlaboured themselves during the last commotions and disorders, hoped now to carry their hoary heads in peace to their graves.</P>
<P>But the <HI>Swedish Seepter</HI> was no sooner departed the hands of a Woman, whenas it became <HI>a burning torch</HI> in the hands of her Successor, to kindle again the wars in <HI>Germany;</HI> the first sparkles whereof appeared in the Swedish Forces before <HI>Bre∣men,</HI> and the full flames not long after burst out throughout all <HI>Poland,</HI> that famous Kingdom, which so often, and so glo∣riously stood in stead of a bulwark and defence to all Christen∣dom; being on all sides at once set upon by an infinite num∣ber of strangers, craved the aid and assistance of all the world; whenas, <HI>this present King of Sweden,</HI> took his time to fall upon its back, whilst it was involved in a warre with all those other <HI>Barbarians;</HI> and entring it, <HI>by the way of its Protestant Provin∣ces,</HI> did menace it with no less then <HI>a totall destruction;</HI> which it escaped by a meer miracle: for as all the world must needs know, had not the Almighty put to his helping hand, we had not seen it in the condition it is in at this day.</P>
<P><HI>His Elector all Highness of Brandenburg,</HI> having born the great∣est brunt of these disasters, foreseeing that this fire was like to consume the best part of Christendom, used his possible en∣deavours <HI>to stifle it in the embers;</HI> and after it had blazed forth, <HI>by his earnest and frequent beseeching the King of Sweden,</HI> to reflect on the consequences of this business, and the abominable scan∣dall which would be given to all the world, <HI>by so unjust an In∣vasion,</HI> and even moved him to give ear to a reasonable and advantagious Peace: but instead of gaining upon the <HI>said Kings minde,</HI> his <HI>Electorall Highness</HI> found himself necessitated to leavy
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>Forces, as well for the defence of his own Territories, which were assaulted by the <HI>Swedes,</HI> as to comply with that obliga∣tion he stood engaged in, unto <HI>the Crown of Poland.</HI> True it is, that the success was not answerable to his expectations, nor to the justice of his Forces; but an extream necessity, and an overpowring Force, constrained his Highness <HI>to treat with the</HI> Swedes, <HI>and to agree with them in such a manner as they themselves would; and tht fatall misfortune of Poland,</HI> brought a generall re∣volution on the whole Kingdom, in which it seemed, that all the severall Estates and Orders thereof, generally, and unani∣mously conspired, to the ruin of that Crown.</P>
<P>Now, <HI>his Electorall Highness wanting the Power of a Protector in chief, necessity</HI> did in some manner dispence with him in the duty of a vassall; so that his waring against <HI>Poland,</HI> may be in some way excused, by the enforced necessity which plunged him therein: however, both <HI>Poland</HI> and <HI>Sweden</HI> do full well know, that amidst the greatest successes of the Swedish Armies, and even during those Triumphs, in which his <HI>Electorall High∣ness</HI> might justly claim so great a part, he had alwayes a heart bent to Peace, and continually embraced the Proposals thereof with joy.</P>
<P>Insomuch that the Polonian affairs, meeting with such a change, by reason of the Denmark Warre, the King of <HI>Sweden</HI> was forced to quit <HI>Prussia,</HI> and in a manner, to relinquish and renounce those Treaties which he made with his <HI>Electorall Highness,</HI> whom the King himself counselled, <HI>to heed his own affairs, and to prevent those disasters which threatned the Ducall Prussia, by the best means he could.</HI> And accordingly by his said Majesties counsell, his Electorall Highness, took his resolution on the present conjuncture of affairs, and did again <HI>reconc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le himself to the Crown of Poland;</HI> with this Proviso however, <HI>That both Parties should chiefly minde the Peace with Sweden;</HI> and that in case either, or both were so unfortunate as not to bring their good intentions to a desired effect, as then, his <HI>Electorall Highness</HI> should remain in a full and entire liberty, <HI>to act in the Empire, in relation to his own Interest, and in conformity to the Peace of Munster.</HI></P>
<P>And immediately, notice was given hereof to the <HI>King of
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>Sweden,</HI> and it was represented unto him, That by reason of the complying with the said Treaty, his <HI>Electoral Highnesse</HI> could not any longer give the Swedish Troopes passage through his Territories; nor permit that any prohibited Mer∣chandises should be unloaden in his Ports. And his Majesty was at the same time requested to think upon the <HI>Peace with Poland,</HI> assuring him that it might be obtained on very advan∣tagious Termes for the <HI>Swedes:</HI> Whereupon the said King declared unto his <HI>Electoral Highnesse,</HI> That he was very much inclined thereunto; assured the States of <HI>Ʋpper-Saxony,</HI> who were assembled at <HI>Liepsig, That he would no more march through the Empire into Poland,</HI> and told <HI>Mounsier de Lombres</HI> (the French Ambassadour, who alwaies most vigorously seconded the King his Masters good intentions, towards the procuring of a Peace betwixt the two Crownes) That he would not only restore <HI>Prussia,</HI> by reimbursing it in a manner for the charges of the War, but that also he would immediately nominate his Plenipotentiaires to Treat on the Peace with <HI>Poland:</HI> All which Declarations, gave great hopes for a Peace in the North.</P>
<P>But, <HI>the King and Crown of Poland,</HI> considering that the King of <HI>Sweden</HI> would obtain a great advantage from such a meet∣ing to the above-said purpose, by <HI>the jealousie which the</HI> Musco∣vites would <HI>harbour thereon,</HI> and by the just cause which the other Allyes would have to complain of such a particular Treaty; they thought it not fitting to engage themselves in such like Negotiations, the event whereof was very uncer∣tain, and would ruine them, in the opinion of all their Friends. And indeed, they perceived that the King of <HI>Sweden</HI> would not explain himself, as to the summe which he demanded for recompence of <HI>Prussia.</HI> And finally, That since his successes in <HI>Denmark,</HI> he required so immense a summe, as was altoge∣ther unpossible for the Crown of <HI>Poland</HI> to procure, or pay.</P>
<P>Moreover, his <HI>Electoral Highnesse,</HI> perceiving that the State of Affairs in <HI>Denmark,</HI> had changed all the King of <HI>Sweden</HI>'s resolutions, and that he had proceeded to open threats against the said <HI>Elector;</HI> he found himself obliged, to his great grief, to prepare against his violence, whilest he used all the possible
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>and imaginable good Offices toward the advancing and pro∣moting of the Peace between the two Crowns: And the po∣sture into which the said <HI>Elector</HI> hath put himself, as well by those Alliances which he hath made with his Neighbouring Princes, as by the care which he hath taken to preserve his Army, and to put his places in defence, did not at all hinder him, to apply his thoughts to devise a meanes to beget a Peace between <HI>Poland</HI> and <HI>Sweden;</HI> with a resolution however, That in case he met with too great difficulties therein, at least to hinder the Swedish Forces from marching through the Territories of the Empire, and getting that way into <HI>Poland,</HI> thereby to prevent the ruine of the <HI>Ʋpper-Saxony Cerele;</HI> and those iconveniencies which the Swedes would cause him to suffer, to the prejudice of their verball assurances of the con∣trary, given at the Assembly at <HI>Leipsig,</HI> and at the Dyet at <HI>Franckford,</HI> of their good and reall intentions: And ilke man∣ner, by this meanes, to <HI>endeavour to save and preserve all</HI> Germany <HI>from the devastations by Fire and Sword, wherewithall the King of</HI> Sweden <HI>had threatned it.</HI></P>
<P>Whereupon, his <HI>Electoral Highnesse,</HI> by his Letters of the 10th of <HI>March</HI> of this present year (annexed and marked,
<NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Proof 1.</NOTE>) re∣quested his said Majestty to evidence his good intentions to∣wards the Peace with <HI>Poland,</HI> and to let him see the effects of the Promise which he made unto him thereon; the said King answered him on the 10th of <HI>April</HI> next ensuing (annexed
<NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Proof 2.</NOTE>) and told him, That he had long since named his Com∣missioners for the said Treaty of Peace, but that the <HI>Polander</HI> witnessed so small an inclination thereunto; as that he durst not any longer promise himself any such thing.</P>
<P>Moreover, the <HI>Earl</HI> of <HI>Slippenbach,</HI> having at the same time invited the <HI>Baron</HI> of <HI>Suerin</HI> (his Electoral Highnesse of <HI>Brandenburghs,</HI> chief Minister of State) to give him a meeting at <HI>Prentslou,</HI> in the <HI>Marck of Brandenburgh;</HI> he there shewed him a <HI>project or draft of an alliance which the King of</HI> Sweden, <HI>pre∣tended he would make with the King of</HI> Denmark, <HI>and with some other Princes and States of Europe;</HI> and pressed him, on the be∣half of the King his Master, to move his <HI>Electoral Highnesse</HI> to send his Ambassadours thereon, unto his Majesty, and the said
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>Count, continuing his earnest pressing of the same, by his Letters of the first of <HI>May</HI> (annexed and marked
<NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Proof 3.</NOTE>) his said <HI>E∣lectoral Highnesse,</HI> who was the rather induced to incline unto a Peace, by how much he knew that the preservation of his own Estates and Territories did partly depend thereon; gave ear unto the counsel which was given him by the publick Mini∣sters of <HI>France,</HI> &amp; <HI>England,</HI> and also by his Neighbouring Prin∣ces; by his nearest Allyes and Kindred, the <HI>Dukes</HI> of <HI>Bruns∣wick,</HI> and <HI>Lunenburgh,</HI> and the <HI>Landtgrave</HI> of <HI>Hesse;</HI> and no∣minated for this <HI>Embassy, the Baron of Suerin,</HI> and the Ho∣nourable Mr. <HI>Weyman,</HI> one of his <HI>Privy Counsellors of State:</HI> which Ambassadours departed from <HI>Berlin</HI> on the 13th day of the Moneth of <HI>May</HI> last past, and being arrived at <HI>Kiel,</HI> they were very well received in that place, <HI>the Prince of</HI> Sulsbach, <HI>and the Earl of</HI> Slippenbach, coming thither to complement them on the behalf of the <HI>King,</HI> treated them, end entertain∣ed them with a great deal of civility; and in that place, they heard the King was at <HI>Flensbourg:</HI> So that being arrived at <HI>Gottorp</HI> (where they had order to <HI>negotiate</HI> several things with <HI>that Duke,</HI> being a <HI>Prince of the Empire</HI>) they gave notice there∣of to the King, who having sent them word by the <HI>Count Pa∣latin of Sultsbach,</HI> That it was his desire they should come to <HI>Flensbourg.</HI> they immediately repaired thither.</P>
<P>At their arrival, they were lodged by the Kings order, and as soon as they had sent their Letters of Credence unto the Court, a Person of quality came to complement them on the Kings behalf; which good beginnings, caused as great joy in all those who desired passionately the setling of a Peace, as the Ambassadours themselves, who flattered themselves, but with over-slender hopes, which vanished in a moment after: <HI>They demanded audience, but they were put off, and delayed by several pretentions, whilest divers persons were imployed to penetrate into the secret of their Instructions. And the</HI> Swedes <HI>would needs know, whether they were ordered to mention a Peace with</HI> Poland, <HI>and the restitution of</HI> Prussia; <HI>and they were given to understand, That it being unlikely his Majesty could not hear such Propositions with∣out being displeased, might make a difficulty to give them audience, which they demanded, because it would tend only to exasperate the
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>mindes of both Parties. But that in case the said Ambassadours had the least power to treat on a particular agreement, and to renew the former Amity between his Majesty and his Electoral Highness, To renounce and forego, the alliance which he had made with</HI> Poland <HI>and the other Confederates, and to promise that his said Highness would joyn his Forces to the Swedes, thereby to constrain their common Enemies to make a Peace, as then his Majesty would receive the said Ambassadours, and hear them with joy.</HI></P>
<P>Which unacustomed and irregular way of proceeding, did so much surprize the said Ambassadours, as that they could not choose but complain thereof; and did declare, That they could not be admitted unto audience, because it was known that they had, order to motion a Peace, as if that Sacred and Pious name of <HI>Peace,</HI> ought to have been accounted as an abomination, and ad horror; and must needs render those odious, who interposed therein. However, they professed that there should not be any thing in their Proposals which might displease the King, but that they desired to be excused, if before their being admitted to audience, they discovered not their Embassy any further: Notwithstanding, instead of advancing their audience, they soon discovered that the said Embassy was not acceptable; and that the King of <HI>Swe∣den,</HI> because he could not expect or hope to engage his <HI>E∣lectoral Highnesse</HI> in a particular Treaty; made use of all the meanes he possibly could, to save himself from the reproach which might be cast upon him; That he would not give ear to the Proposals of a Peace.</P>
<P>So likewise, they only endeavoured to prolong the busi∣nesse, and to elude the good intentions of his <HI>Electoral High∣ness,</HI> and publiquely began to laugh at, and deride the said Em∣bassy, begetting daily new difficulties, and alledging that it would be requisite to <HI>nominate Commissioners,</HI> who should en∣ter upon a conference with his <HI>Electoral Highness Ambassadours,</HI> in the presence of the <HI>Duke</HI> of <HI>Lunenbourg</HI> and <HI>Hesses</HI> Ambas∣sadours, before they were admitted to an audience by the King; To propound unto them, and to know several things of them, before which, they could not enter upon any Treaty with them; which was only done a purpose, indirectly to
<PB N="8" REF="6"/>dismisse the said Ambassadours, by so unjust a Proposal; or in case they should have been so weak as to have condescend∣ed to such a Conference, of that nature, and to have acknow∣ledged so unlawfull a power; To have obtained those ad∣vantages thereby, which they might have hoped from those Tales and Stories which they would have divulged throughout the whole world, to the prejudice of the repu∣tation and interest of his Electoral Highnesse.</P>
<P>And the <HI>Swedes</HI> did apparently the rather desire the In∣tervention of the <HI>Lunenbourg</HI> and <HI>Hessian Ambassadours,</HI> at this pretended conference, that they might thence gain this ad∣vantage to <HI>embroile</HI> his <HI>Electoral Highnesse,</HI> with those said Princes; in case their Deputies and Commissioners should not be satisfied with the said Ambassadours proceedings, or that they themselves might take a pretence and occasion to break with them, in case their Testimonies should condemn the King of <HI>Sweden</HI>'s Proceedings. The Lords <HI>Mevius, Kley</HI> and <HI>Erenstein,</HI> who were nominated Commissioners in the be∣half of the King of <HI>Sweden;</HI> for the said conference, accor∣dingly signified the Kings resolution unto the said Ambassa∣dours, on the 22th of <HI>June.</HI></P>
<P>Whereunto the said Ambassadours made Answer, and alledged, That they were very much surprized at the advice they had received, not believing that in the present conjun∣cture of affairs; when as they might have hoped and pro∣mised themselves an audience from the King, such a Propo∣sition could be made unto them: wherefore they desired time to resolve upon a definitive Answer thereon, and the which they would send to the Lord <HI>Mevius.</HI> But before they took their said Resolution what to answer, they visited the <HI>Lu∣nenbourg</HI> and <HI>Hessian Ambassadours,</HI> who were as much sur∣prized as themselves, and could not imagine nor compre∣hend, why the <HI>Swedes</HI> would oblige them to be present at a conference, <HI>at which they neither would nor could intervene,</HI> either as <HI>Judges, Parties,</HI> or <HI>Witnesses.</HI></P>
<P>Insomuch that the said Ambassadours sent back word in writing, to the Lord <HI>Mevius</HI> (marked and annexed
<NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Proof 4.</NOTE>) That their Instructions, commanding them in express
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>termes, to address themselves unto the King of <HI>Sweden</HI>'s own Person, to demand audience of him; and that the pro∣posing of a conference before the audience, being an extraor∣dinary and unusual a thing, they could not in any wise assent thereunto: whereon they desired him to excuse them to the King, and to obtain from his Majesty that audience which they had so often and so earnestly desired.</P>
<P>The said Commissioners made answer to the foregoing Note, in somewhat brisk termes (annexed and marked
<NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Proof 5.</NOTE>). That his Majesty having deemed it necessary, in reference to the advice he had received of the said <HI>Electoral Highnesse</HI> En∣gagements with his Enemies, to cause certain Propositions to be made unto them; that the Ambassadours might dispose themselves to hear them, if they pleased, as well as the other Orders which they had received from his Majesty, which they would declare in the presence of the Ambassadours of <HI>Lunenbourg</HI> and <HI>Hesse.</HI></P>
<P>Which said Proceeding, being quite and clean contrary to the accustomed Formes on the like Cases, <HI>constrained</HI> the <HI>Hessian</HI> Ambassadours to repair to the King, and the <HI>Lunen∣burgers</HI> to see the Commissioners, and of their own accords to tell them, That they could not consent to, nor ap∣prove of the same; and that they should think themselves very unfortunate, to be made use of in such a ticklish con∣juncture, to engage his Electoral Highnesse of <HI>Branden∣bourg</HI>'s Ambassadours in so ill a contrived conference, and meeting. But all their Offices and the Endeavours which they used, proved useless. And the last Answer which was returned to them, <HI>specified</HI> very particularly; <HI>That it must and should be so, and that his Majesty used not these kind of Proceedings without just cause.</HI></P>
<P>Whereupon the Ambassadours wrote unto the Count of <HI>Slippenbach</HI> (annexed and marked
<NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Proof 6.</NOTE>) and told him, That since his Majesty did continue to refuse them an audience, and that the dignity and reputation of their Master, did not per∣mit their longer stay in a place, where they were treated with so much scorn, they desired him once more, to know of his Majesty, whether he would command them any thing
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>back to the Prince Elector their Master, and for the last time to supplicate the King, to vouchsafe them that audience, which they had so earnestly and often intreated.</P>
<P>The Count returned them an answer the same day at night being the 23th, and sent them word (annexed and marked
<NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Proof 7.</NOTE>.) That having shewn the King their Letter, his Majesty witnessed, That he made difficulty to admit them to an audience, untill such time as they had power to reconcile and settle the former amity; without which he could not admit of the said Em∣bassie, nor make a distinction between a declared Enemy, and a Prince, who was entred into a league with his Enemies.</P>
<P>Whereupon, The Ambassadours, perceiving that there was nothing more to be expected for them, they took their leaves of the Ambassadors of the Electorall Colledge, and of the Am∣bassadours of <HI>Lunenburg</HI> and <HI>Hesse;</HI> and telling them, That they should be guilty and responsible for all those things which might happen to the prejudice and dishonour of the dignity of his Electorall Highness their Master, in case they should any longer stay, waiting upon the King: they therefore departed from <HI>Flensburg</HI> on the 24th. of <HI>June,</HI> betimes in the morning; and at their departure they left a Letter with their Host (an∣nexed and marked
<NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Proof 8.</NOTE>,) by which the Baron of <HI>Suerin,</HI> sent word to the Earl of <HI>Slippenbach,</HI> That with a great deal of reluctancy he departed from a place, where he had hoped to have met with an occasion to have laid a stable and firme foundation of an eternall Peace between the Princes of Chri∣stendom; but since he had sent him word, that his Majesty desired he should be accompanied with a more ample Instru∣ction, and Commission, then that which he had brought along with him; he deemed it fitting to retire himself with his Col∣league to <HI>Hamborow,</HI> there to expect his Electorall Highness further Orders.</P>
<P>True it is, that one of the Kings Trompeters was imme∣diately sent after the Ambassadours, who overtook them at <HI>Rensbough,</HI> where he delivered them a Letter (annexed and marked
<NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Proof 9.</NOTE>.) by which the Commissioners sent them word, That they had been the more surprised at their precipitated departure,, in as much as the Ambassabours of <HI>Lunenburg</HI>
<PB N="11" REF="7"/>and <HI>Hesse,</HI> had the day before declared, That the Conference it self was not so much objected against, as the interv<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ning of other strange Ambassadours, and that his Majesty having condes∣cended that they should have a private meeting; they desired the Ambassadours either to return back again, or to repair to some neutrall place where the Treaty might be begun.</P>
<P>And upon the said Letter, the Ambassadours might hap∣pily have resolved to have returned to <HI>Flensbourg,</HI> had it not been accompanied by another Paper (annexed and marked
<NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Proof 10.</NOTE>.) which made them see; That not only they could not expect any good from the said Conference, but that also they were looked upon as Heralds, who rather came to declare warre, then like Ambassadours from a Prince, who only seemed to desire Peace. Wherefore they contented themselves to return this answer to the Letter (annexed and marked
<NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Proof 11.</NOTE>.) Declaring, That they wondred, they were blamed for parting from <HI>Flens∣bourg,</HI> after they had made so long a stay there, and had not seen the King, and not so much as perceived any appearance to be treated, or dealt withall, according to the Dignity of their Character.</P>
<P>And being arrived at <HI>Hamburrough,</HI> they returned a more ample answer unto the said Commissioners Letters, and also unto the Writing which was sent unto them (annexed and marked
<NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Proof 12.</NOTE>.) and told them, That however they were resol∣ved to have expected his Electorall Highness commands in that place; yet having maturely reflected on what the said Commissioners had sent them, they deemed it requisite to give his said Electorall Highness a verball account thereof, and to receive his positive Order thereon.</P>
<P>But at their return to, and arrivall at <HI>Berlin,</HI> they found the <HI>Prince Elector</HI> so well advertised of the King of <HI>Swedens</HI> pro∣ceedings, as that he would not permit his said Ministers to re∣turn towards him: but to the contrary, he caused them to send the Writing which you will finde annexed at the end of this Relation (marked
<NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Proof 13.</NOTE>.) unto the said Commissioners, in answer to their former exhibited Paper.</P>
<P>And to the end that no man may have cause to doubt of the truthes afore-specified, and that all the world may be the better
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>able to judg of his said <HI>Electorall Highness proceedings, and of his willingness and affectionate desires to the begetting of a Peace, whilest the Swedes did endeavour to ingage him in a new Warre against his own Countrey;</HI> we have thought good to add hereunto those <HI>Proofs</HI> which we have before alledged; and we shall remit our selves to the judgment of all disinteressed and unconcerned persons, <HI>Whether on the one part, there be not a great deal of reason to blame the proceedings of those who make a mocking stock of God, and of the whole world, by using of his Name, to colour their violences and outragious dealings? and on the other part, there be not a ne∣cessitated constraint, to take up Arms, in, and for the defence of ones Countrey, the preservation of the Empire, and the maintenance of the bonour of the German Nation?</HI></P>
<P>So that the true and entire knowledg which we have of ei∣ther parties intentions, hath engaged us to divulge this unto the world, and to communicate unto all men these ensuing Proofs, which have been copied out of the very orginall Let∣ters themselves.</P>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>The first Proof. <MILESTONE N="a."/></HEAD>
<HEAD>His Electorall Highness of <HI>Brandenburgs</HI> Letter to the King of <HI>Sweden.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Most Serene and Puissant King, my most honoured Cousen, and Brother.</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><HI>I</HI> Had well hoped, that your Majesty having ended the Denmark Warre, would have caused the Treaty with <HI>Poland</HI> to have been set on foot, and that you would have authorized the same by your pre∣sence: But having heard that your Majesty was passed into <HI>Sweden,</HI> I would not omit by this occasion to give you a visit, by this Letter humbly and amicably to request you, to remember your promise, and without any further delayes, to cause the Treaties of Peace with <HI>Po∣land</HI> to be advanced; your Majesty hath made me hope it should be effected, and have so often promised it me, as that having absolutely assured it to all the interessed parties, I hope you will disingage the promises which I have made unto them thereon: and forasmuch as my preservation and assurance doth entirely depend upon the speedy
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>conclusion of the said Treaty, you Majesty cannot doubt but that I will contribute what lieth in me to accomplish the same; so likewise shall I alwayes preserve a most sincere Friendship for your Majesty and the Crown of <HI>Sweden;</HI> which I also know is the intention of the King and Crown of <HI>Poland.</HI> I remain—Signed thus; Your Majesties most humble Brother and Servant</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>FREDERICK WILLIAM Elector.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE>From <HI>Collen</HI> on the <HI>Spree,</HI> <DATE>the 10<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>March</HI> 1658.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>The second Proof. <MILESTONE N="b."/></HEAD>
<HEAD>The King of <HI>Sweden</HI>'s Answer to his Electoral Highnesses Letter.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Most serene Prince Elector, welbeloved Cousen and Brother:</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>YOur Letters of the 10th of <HI>March,</HI> were safely delivered to me, and I do thereby perceive, not only the passion which you bear towards the advancement of the Peace of <HI>Po∣land,</HI> but that you do assure me, I shall meet with the same affection and sincerity in the King of <HI>Poland</HI>'s intentions; but likewise see the paines you do promise, to take in the promoting of so godly a work, and the Amity and Friend∣ship, which you tell me, you will constantly preserve for my Person and my Crown: wherefore I would not omit to an∣swer the said Letter, and to tell you, as your good Friend and Cousen, That you do know I have long since nominated Commissioners to treat on the Peace of <HI>Poland;</HI> and that I have given them sufficient instructions, and full power, as well before, as since the Conclusion of the Treaty with the King of <HI>Denmark,</HI> and express Orders, incessantly to labour in the promoting of so good a work: Insomuch, that it is neither mine nor my Ministers faults (who were alwaies ready to proceed, being sufficiently impowered) that the Peace of <HI>Poland,</HI> and of its Allyes, hath not long since been concluded: But the insolent and arrogant answers which the <HI>Polanders</HI> returned to the Ambassadour <HI>de Lombres,</HI> touching
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>the said Pacification, hath given me cause to believe, That they harbour a quite contrary design, then to make a Peace. Insomuch, as that I am obliged to pitty those who give cre∣dit to what the <HI>Polanders</HI> do averre thereon, whilest in their hearts they harbour no other designes, save to oppress and ruine others; and whilest their Councils only tend to the ru∣inating of the neighbouring Provinces. Moreover, you may rest assured, that during my absence, nothing was o∣mitted or neglected, which might tend to the said advance∣ment of the Peace, since my Commissioners (who were fully instructed and furnished with sufficient powers) might have done the same things, and even more then I my self could, had I been present; as it doth plainly appear, by those Declarations which I have thereon made, and which may also be easily perceived by the very nature of all the said Ne∣gotiations. Wherefore you may with more reason, make your applications to the King of <HI>Poland,</HI> and represent unto him, <HI>as you do very wisely alledge it in the said Letter;</HI> How much it doth concern you, that the said <HI>Peace be forthwith concluded.</HI> Besides which, you may remain assured, That I have with so much the more joy, seen the Protestation which you do make of the continuance of your friendship to∣wards my Person and Crown; as that lately it was reported to the contrary: And that they would needs make me be∣lieve, That you had harboured, and taken resolutions very prejudicial to the good of my Affairs. However, I alwaies conceived, That being convinced in your conscience of the sincerity of my intentions, and that being fully perswaded of the affection which I bear towards the preservation of your Person, and of your Estates, you could not possibly be ren∣dred capable to give ear to those things which might be told you, nor believe those things which might be averred unto you to the contrary; farre less, to change that Friendship whereof you have so often given me such great assurances: But that you would have a great deal of reason to imploy all kind of meanes, to the end, that <HI>by Proposals of a reasonable and advantagious Peace,</HI> I may be delivered from so great a number of Enemies, as do on all sides declare themselves
<PB N="15" REF="9"/>against me. You do know, that I have several times in writing, assured you of the constancy of my friendship; which makes me beleeve, that on your part, you will retain the same inclination to cultivate it, and to relinquish those things which may either alter or destroy the same: Finally, I do not doubt but that the Almighty will continue to bless my de∣signs, will confound the counsels of my enemies, and will dispose the hearts of my neighbours to Peace, and to a reason∣able agreement. It is that which I desire with all my heart; to the end that Peace being setled in our neigbourhood, my Subjects may enjoy that tranquillity, which I do endeavour to procure them. The good God preserve you many year, and grant you a perfect health and all prosperity. From <HI>Gotten∣burg</HI> the 10th. of <HI>April.</HI> 1658. Signed thus</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your dilections, Friend, Brother, and Cousen, CHARLES GUSTAVE.</SIGNED>
<POSTSCRIPT>
<HEAD>POSTSCRIPT.</HEAD>
<P>In case you would be pleased to explain your self a little more upon the present conjuncture of Affairs, unto my Resident in your Court, or unto any other of my Ministers in <HI>Pomerania,</HI> untill such time as I shall be returned to the Army (which will be suddainly) you will extreamly oblige me.</P>
</POSTSCRIPT></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>The third Proof. <MILESTONE N="c."/></HEAD>
<HEAD>The Lord of <HI>Slippenbach</HI>'s Letter to the Baron of <HI>Suerin.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>My Lord the Baron,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>THe zeal which I do bear to the service of his Electoral High∣nesse, and the part which I do take in his concernments, do give me the liberty to write unto him, and to beseech him, not to fail in the sending of your Excellence in good time towards his Ma∣jesty of <HI>Sweden:</HI> I have thereunto added my thoughts on the present conjuncture of affairs, although it be not necessary to send water to the Sea; I have seen, not long since, in <HI>Furmans Almnack,</HI> that
<PB N="16" REF="10"/>the Moneth of <HI>May,</HI> doth promise a great deal of good luck to the read Eagle, and I am perswaded that it doth signifie nought else, save the reconciliation of his Electoral Highnesse, and the renew∣ing and cementing of his Friendship with the King of <HI>Sweden;</HI> after which, I doubt not but all the world will send and complement him, on the good conduct, wherewith all he shall have provided for the preservation of his Estates: God grant this good work may be effected. I beseech your Excellency to send me word, about what time you do intend to set forwards, that so I may meet you by the way: I desire you also not to mention former Treaties, assuring you, That we shall no sooner have entered upon a Negotiation, but his Electoral High∣ness shall therein find his assurance and contentednesse; and by what I see in the Copy of the Letter which his Majesty doth write unto his Electoral Highnesse, which I have just now received: I dare say, That there is not a happier Prince then his serene High∣nesse. I remain your Excellencies most humble Servant, Signed thus;</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>CHRISTOPHER CHARLES de SLIPPENBACH.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>The fourth Proof. <MILESTONE N="d."/></HEAD>
<HEAD>The Elector of <HI>Brandenbourg</HI>'s Ambassadours Reply to the Swe∣dish Commissioners notification of a Conference.</HEAD>
<P>THe Prince Elector of <HI>Brandenbourg</HI>'s Ambassadours, do kiss the hands of the <HI>Lord President,</HI> of Mr. <HI>Kley,</HI> and Mr. <HI>Ehrenstein,</HI> and do make known unto them; That ha∣ving reflected upon the advice which they received from them, and that having sound by their Instructions, that his Electorall Highness doth expresly ordain them to demand audience of the King of <HI>Sweden</HI> himself; and having more∣over pondred, how that it is not the custome of Ambassa∣dours, to enter into any Conferences before they have had audience; they beseech them, not only to excuse them, in that they cannot condescend thereunto, but also to make their excuses thereon to his Majesty; and to know of him, when it may please him to give them audience; since his Electorall Highness would have just occasion to be displeased with them, in case they should suffer themselves, to be deluded thus any longer.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="proof">
<PB N="17" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>The fifth Proof. <MILESTONE N="e."/></HEAD>
<HEAD>The Swedish Commissioners Answer, to the Brandenburg Ambassadours refusing a particular Conference.</HEAD>
<P>THe Deputies nominated by the King, do kiss the Brandenburg Ambassadours hands; and do give them notice, that his said Majesty, reflecting on his Electorall Highnesse, being so farre enga∣ged with his Enemies, as that he accounts him a common Enemy▪ hath deemed it necessary to cause certain Propositions to be made unto them; which are no other save such, as (according to the custom of all Nations, ought to be made before they are admitted to the hearing; which they have desired, because that the granting of the same doth depend partly thereon, so that the said Ambassadours, may dispose themselves to hear the said Propositions, in the presence of the Am∣bassadours of <HI>Lunenburg</HI> and <HI>Hesse,</HI> as well as the other Orders which they have received from his Majesty, to communicate unto them.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>The sixth Proof. <MILESTONE N="f."/></HEAD>
<HEAD>The Baron of <HI>Suerin</HI>'s Letter to the Earl of <HI>Slippenbach.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>My Lord the Count,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>WE had reason to beleeve, that his Electorall Highness Embassie, which is an unquestionable proof of the sin∣cerity of his intentions, and of his reall inclinations to a Peace, would have been the more acceptable to the King, by reason that his Majesty being as yet at <HI>Gottenborow,</HI> had witnessed unto him, that he would be very glad thereof, and that he caused the Prince Palatine of <HI>Sultsbach,</HI> to invite us to come unto this Town: But we are much astonished to finde the contrary: Nor shall we inlarge upon all the other circumstan∣ces which gives us cause to beleeve it; only we cannot any longer dissemble, that we are very much surprised at the dif∣ficulties which are made, in the giving of us a hearing; it is become the common discourse in all companies, and people do talk of it about the streets, in so much as this refusall to ad∣mit
<PB N="18" REF="11"/>us to audience, being extreamly prejudiciall to his Ele∣ctorall Highness: we are constrained to beseech your Excel∣lence, to do us the favour, to know of his Majesty, whether he hath any thing to command us unto his Electorall High∣ness; forasmuch as we shall not be able to excuse our longer stay in this place to his Electorall Highness, since we see no appearance at all of effecting any thing here: We have so ma∣ny reasons which debarre us from entring into any conference with the Kings Commissioners in the presence of the Lunen∣burg and Hessian Ambassadours, as that we doubt not, but they will be capable to satisfie his Majesty, and to oblige him to condescend to the audience which we have demanded: but since we are again pressed thereunto, and that in such a man∣ner, as we can by no means condescend unto, being altogether unusuall and irregular; we dare not ingage our selves in a buisness, which is without a president, unless we had his Ele∣ctorall Highnesses express Order for the same: Wherefore we most humbly beseech your Excellency, not to press us any farther thereunto, whereon we shall expect your speedy an∣swer, and proffer unto you our most humble service, as being</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Excellencies most humble servants, OTTON Baron of <HI>Suerin,</HI> and D. WEYMAN.</SIGNED>
<POSTSCRIPT>
<HEAD>POSTSCRIPT.</HEAD>
<P>Since we cannot be admitted to deliver this Letter our selves, we be∣seech you to put it into his Majesties hands.</P>
</POSTSCRIPT></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>The seaventh Proof.</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Earl of <HI>Slippenbachs</HI> Answer to the Baron of <HI>Suerin.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>My Lord Baron:</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><HI>I</HI> Hhave shown his Majesty the Letter which your Excellency wrote uuto me, and the King told me he made a difficulty to give you audience, because you had not power to treat on the reestablishing of the Friendship, betwixt his Majesty and his Electorall Highness; without which his Majesty cannot resolve to admit of this Embassie,
<PB N="19" REF="11"/>nor make a difference between a declared Enemy, and an Ally of his Enemies, and as the <HI>Romanes</HI> say: <HI>The dignity of the Com∣monwealth permits not that the Ambassadours of Enemies be heard in the Senate.</HI> For in case you intend to speak of the Peace of <HI>Poland,</HI> and the other interessed Parties, you take upon your selves the quality of Mediators; which is a thing inconsistent with that alliance, which hath been made with his Majesties Enemies: In case you mean to propound conditions of Peace, and at the same time de∣clare, that if we accept not of them, you will be obliged to remain united with <HI>Poland,</HI> and to put that Treaty in execution which you have made with that Crown; you must needs become Judges, or ra∣ther Heralds, by declaring warre against us. Wherefore his Ma∣jesty will ot hearken to any Proposals, save such as may conduce to a particular Peace, and may advance the reestablishing of the friend∣ship betwixt his Majesty and his Electorall Highness; because the Peace of <HI>Poland</HI> must be negotiated by Mediators, and not by such as have taken party, and declared themselves: You know how I have alwayes assured you, That notwithstanding all what is past, his Ma∣jesty would be glad to see you, in case you came accompanied with power to cement the former Friendship, and to quit the alliance of his Enemies: But seeing in lieu of coming hither upon that account, we know, that since your departure from <HI>Berlin,</HI> the enterchangeably delivery of the Treaty, made with the house of <HI>Austria</HI> hath been per∣formed: That the Gunpowder, which his Majesty sent into <HI>Prussia,</HI> hath been stopt at the <HI>Pilliw:</HI> That a Garrison hath been put into <HI>Frawenburg;</HI> and that since all other things have been done, whereon his Majesty hath reason to be ill satisfied; he will determinately know, what he is to trust to from the Elector: Whereunto his Majesty doth add, That in case you will yet send for a Power, to confer upon a particular Treaty, he will nominate Commissioners and Deputies on his behalf, who shall meet in any neutrall place, such a one as shall be agreed upon: but that otherwise he is fully resolved, not to admit you to an audience; nor to receive any thing on the behalf of a Prince who is entred into an alliance with his Enemies. I am grieved to the heart, when I do reflect upon the present conjuncture of affairs, and when I consider that labyrinthe, wherein his Electorall Highness hath engaged himself, by the conference at <HI>Bromberg,</HI> and by the assembly of so many Ambassadours, as were lately at <HI>Berlin;</HI> God
<PB N="20" REF="12"/>grant, that the issue thereof may prove a reestablishing of the Friend∣ship with his Majesty, a renouncing of the alliance with his Enemies; without which I cannot well see how possibly his Electorall Highness can escape the dangers and disorders wherewithall he is threatned, although one moitie of the world should rise up in arms against us, but few of them should passe into <HI>Sweden</HI> with us: I beseech you but to reflect on the alliance which you have made; whether the victories it may produce, will advance the glory of God, the setling of the Protestant Religion, or the assurance of his Electorall Highness: I know that one day you will be mindfull of me. I hope and wish to remain</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Excellencies most humble Servant, <HI>Signed</HI> CHRISTOPHER CHARLES SLIPPENBACH.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE>Dated from <HI>Flensburg</HI> <DATE>the 23. <HI>June</HI> 1658.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>The Eighth Proof. <MILESTONE N="h."/></HEAD>
<HEAD>The Barron of <HI>Suerin</HI>'s second Letter to the Count <HI>Slippenbach.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>My Lord the Count,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>ALthough I have occasion to be glad to take my self home-wards, after so displeasing a Voyage, since I see by your Excellencies former Letter. That his Majesty will not at all change the resolution, he hath taken, to refuse us audience: yet I am constrained to confesse, that I never de∣parted from any place, with so much regret, as I had to leave this Town; <HI>by reason that no ear would be given to the generall Peace, of which I had well hoped to have here laid the first Foun∣dations.</HI> I dare yet hope, that God, who hath the hearts of Kings in his keeping, will also move his Majesty, and dis∣pose it, to preferre an honourable and advantagious Peace be∣fore a destructive War to all <HI>Christendome:</HI> And since your Excellency specifieth in your Letter, certain particulars upon which his Majesty desireth we may have more ample in∣structions, I am resolved to retire my self, with my Collegue to <HI>Hambourg,</HI> whence we shall dispatch an express to his <HI>Electoral Highnesse,</HI> and there expect his Orders, which we
<PB N="21" REF="12"/>will not fail to communicate unto you. And thus taking leave of you, I remain, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>From <HI>Flensbourg</HI> <DATE>the 24 of <HI>Jun.</HI> 1658.</DATE></DATELINE>
<POSTSCRIPT>
<HEAD>POSTSCRIPT.</HEAD>
<P>THe Ambassadours of the Electoral Colledge told us yesterday, that his Majesty was resolved to take his march through the Markequisate of <HI>Brandenbourg,</HI> I humbly beseech your Ex∣cellency to remonstrate unto his said Majesty, the disorders which will accrew thereby, and to endeavour to direct him from that re∣solution: For as the said March, must needs be to the prejudice of his Electoral Highnesses Subjects, so he is not at all obliged to permit the same. He hath hetherto most religiously kept and observed the Peace, and is resolved so to do: But if there be a pleasure taken in the breaking of it with us, he will rely upon God and the Emperour, who will not fail him. If there remains any thing else to be made known unto us, it may be sent to us in writing to <HI>Ham∣bourg.</HI></P>
</POSTSCRIPT></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="9" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>The ninth Proof. <MILESTONE N="i."/></HEAD>
<HEAD>The King of <HI>Sweden</HI>'s Commissioners Letter to the Prince Elector of <HI>Brandenbourg</HI>'s Ambassadours.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>My Lords,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>WE were the more surprised at your precipitated depar∣ture, by reason it bereaved us of the occasion to pro∣pose unto you, by the Kings Order, those meanes, which without all doubt, might have prepared the way to an ac∣comodation, and to a Peace, had they not been avoided: as soon as we understood yesterday by the Ambassadours of <HI>Lu∣nenbourg</HI> and <HI>Hesse,</HI> That the conference it self distasted you not so much, as their intervention, his Majesty was pleased to have so much complaisance, as to consent that they should not be present: Wherefore we had resolved this morning, to have given you a visit without them: So that we cannot imagine why you should shun the said conference, when as this Objection was removed. But for as much as his Majesty doth alwaies passionately desire to make Peace, and to give
<PB N="22" REF="13"/><HI>Christendome</HI> rest, we thought it our duties to fend unto you that, which we had Orders to tell you by word of mouth, and to leave it with you in writing: you will thereby see, that there hath not any thing been done, save what was very re∣quisite, and which ought not to have been done in the like conjunctures; and you will thereby acknowledge the since∣rity of our intentions: Insomuch, as that you will be obliged to avouch, that you cannot blame us, but your selves, in case it taketh not effect; We remit our selves to your choice; ei∣ther to return, or nominate a Neutrall Place, where we may begin our Negotiations; his Majesty doth sufficiently manifest by this Declaration, that he will permit the Treaty to be be∣gun; and after you shall have shewn sufficient power for the same, he will do all whatsoever can be expected from him, for the re-establishing of that friendship which his Electoral Highness hath declined and violated, by several acts of Hosti∣lity. We remain</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>My LORDS,</SALUTE> <SIGNED>Your humble Servants, <HI>Signed</HI>
<LIST>
<ITEM>DAVID MEVIUS,</ITEM>
<ITEM>SUEDER DIDERICH KLEY,</ITEM>
<ITEM>EDUARD ERNSTEIN.</ITEM>
</LIST></SIGNED>
<DATELINE>Dated from <HI>Elensbourg</HI> on <DATE>the 24<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>June,</HI> 1658.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="10" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>The tenth Proof. <MILESTONE N="k."/></HEAD>
<HEAD>The Proposition which was sent in writing by the Swedish Commissi∣oners after the <HI>Brandenbourg</HI> Ambassadours.</HEAD>
<P>IT is most assured, that the Law of Nature, and the Customes ad∣mitted by all people, do permit a Sovereign to receive and Treat Ambassadours, according to the quality and deserts of those Princes, by whom they are sent, and according to the nature of the buisness whereon they are to Treat; wherefore his Majesty believes, that it cannot be ill taken, if by vertue of that liberty, which is as free to him as to all other Kings, he doth constitute Commissioners, and causeth a Proposition to be made to the <HI>Brandenbourg</HI> Ambassa∣dours: The which he deemed the more requisite to be done, by reason that the Prince their Master, hath made it appear, that he will not be his friend. For although that his serene Electoral Highness did
<PB N="23" REF="13"/>desire and seek for the alliance with his Majesty, from the very time that deliberations were as yet but on foot in <HI>Sweden;</HI> whether or no the Polish War should be undertaken: and that his said High∣nesse, did not only encourage his Majesty to this enterprize, but also promised by a formall Treaty, his Asistances and Forces against <HI>Poland:</HI> However, all the world doth know, That he hath renoun∣ced the said alliance with his Majesty: It was to have been perpe∣tual, and undissolvable, but his Electoral Highnesse rent it asunder without any necessity, which might not, at least, have been di∣spene't withall, since he might have avoided the same, by doing or by suffering that to be done, which would have been very feazible; and not at all regarding the particular favour which his Majesty did him, to offer him a neutrallity upon such reasonable conditions, as would not have been prejudicial to his Majesties affairs: And as if it were a small matter to contract to friendship with a declared ene∣my of his first Allyes, his Electoral Highness ceased not therewith neither, but passed on further, and hath made a League, in which the King is treated, and stiled, the common enemy. He promiseth his favour and assistance to the Kings declared enemies, not only in <HI>Prussia,</HI> but also in the Empire; and bespeaks his share of those Conquests which are pretended to be made in those States which his Majesty did and doth there possesse, contrary to the express promise which he had made to his Majesty, to be assisting unto him in the defence thereof, with all his might, against all Parties whatsoever; which appears manifestly by the Articles of the Treaty which was Negotiated and at <HI>Velau,</HI> and finally concluded and signed at <HI>Brom∣berg.</HI></P>
<P>His <HI>Electoral Highness,</HI> after he had held private intelligence with the King of <HI>Denmark,</HI> entred upon a Negotiation with him, during the same time when as the King had declared War against him, and whilest his Armies were in those Kingdomes; he exhort∣ed the King of <HI>Denmark,</HI> to continue the War, and to reject Peace; not contenting himself to encourage him herein, but also promising him a speedy relief, and to make a powerfull diversion in those Pro∣vinces where his Majesty had his Armies: All which Treaty was carried on at <HI>Coppenhagen</HI> by the same Ambassadour, who had proferred his Princes Mediation to procure a Peace between <HI>Sweden</HI> and <HI>Denmark;</HI> although since, it was continued by another, and
<PB N="25" REF="14"/>finally concluded at <HI>Cologne</HI> on the <HI>Spreé.</HI></P>
<P>But to compass this promised relief, a more powerfull establish∣ment was requisite, wherefore a Negotiation was commenced with the most serene King of <HI>Hungary</HI> for an alliance; which at first was only to have been defensive, but afterwards came to an offensive one, which was speedily concluded and compleated with so much animo∣sity, as that not only his Majesty was therein treated as the common enemy of <HI>Christendome,</HI> but also the Treaty was filled with all that possibly could be alledged against the greatest Enemies those Al∣lyes had; and it was resolved, not only to set upon those places which his Majesty had in <HI>Poland,</HI> but also to take and share amongst the said Allyes, those Provinces which do belong unto him in the Empire.</P>
<P>Nor did his Electoral Highnesse remain satisfied, to permit these particulars to be set down in writing, but did also pass on to commit acts of hostility, as followeth: He gave passage and Provisions to the <HI>Polanders,</HI> and suffered them to over-run, pillage, and burn <HI>Pomerania;</HI> he hindered those Leagues which his Majesty caused to be made in the Empire, although the same are permitted unto all Princes indifferently, seeing they were not burdensome to any one; and that they were only to be imployed in the defence of his Territories: He commanded his Subjects to quit his Majesties service, against the Liberties which the Lawes of the Empire give them: he caused to be stopt in the Haven of <HI>Pillou,</HI> those Powders and other Muni∣tions of War, and Provisions which the King had sent to his Places in <HI>Prussia,</HI> contrary to the Treaty of alliance, and against the Law of Nations; and he opposed himself in the Assembly of the Lower <HI>Circle</HI> of <HI>Saxony,</HI> unto that security which the Estates of that <HI>Circle</HI> were obliged to give him against the invasion of the King of <HI>Denmark;</HI> crying down his Majesties actions, and testifying his hatred and malice, by animating and stirring up all the world a∣gainst him, as against the common enemy; at such a time when as his Electoral Highness had not any occasion to complain of his said Majesty, but when the King did give him the greatest proof of his Friendship and good will.</P>
<P>All men do know, and it is most assured, that his Electoral Highnesse hath promised the King of <HI>Denmark</HI> relief, that he hath sollicited the conjunction of the <HI>Austrian</HI> Armies; and that to this end, the Forces of the Allies did often shew themselves in <HI>Ger∣many,</HI>
<PB N="24" REF="14"/>when as there did not any enemy at all appear, and when as there was not any thing at all to be apprehended: That he hath de∣sired asistance from all parts, as against a declared enemy; and that he had endeavoured to render the Kings best actions odious: Inso∣much, as it is void of all doubt, but that he would absolutely have declared himself, had it not been for the Justice and Prosperity of his Majesties Armies.</P>
<P>And although these undeniable Proofs (which have been but too much confirmed by the publick report of them) did manifest his Electoral Highness ill intentions, yet his Majesty never changed his good will, which he ever bore towards one who threatned him, although he least deserved it; having declared whilest he was yet at <HI>Gottenbourg,</HI> that in case his Electoral Highnesse would depute any of his Ministers towards him, accompanied with sufficient Power to cement and settle the former Friendship again, his Majesty would alwaies be found willing to embrace the same.</P>
<P>But his Electoral Highness was so farre from answering these Testimonies of Friendship, that, notwithstanding the foregoing Declarations; and as soon as his Ambassadours were departed <HI>Ber∣lin,</HI> he did ratifie that Treaty which was made with the most serene King of <HI>Hungary,</HI> against his Majesty, as against a common enemy; did again cause to be arrested in the <HI>Pillau,</HI> those Powders and Amunitions which were sent to the Royal <HI>Prussia,</HI> and did put a Garrison in <HI>Frawenberg,</HI> which the <HI>Austrians</HI> had abandoned, although he had no title to the same; and that according to the Trea∣ties between the King and the Elector, and according to the Mili∣tary Lawes, that place ought to have remained in the Kings possession: however, he refused to admit the <HI>Swedish</HI> Troops into the same, caused the Officers to be pursued, filled the Assemblies with com∣plaints; without cause of Justice, sent to demand aide from all Parts, as against a declared enemy; and did all he could, to manifest his disaffection and ill will, and the small inclination he bore to the Peace.</P>
<P>Insomuch, as that the King finding himself obliged to assure him∣self of his Electoral Higness intentions, and to know whether he was to Treat with the Ambassadours of a Prince, in Peace, or at enmity; (since by what we have before alledged, it could not otherwise
<PB N="26" REF="15"/>be conceived;) he thought, that by vertue of the Law of Nations, and the Customes admitted by all Kings and people, to name Com∣missioners, who might Penetrate into the Princes intentions, who might know the subject of the Embassy; and who might see the Am∣bassadours power, before he resolved (during this uncertainty) whether he should admit them or no. True it is, that his Majesty permitted the Ambassadours to come to this Town, but not with an in∣tent thereby to tye up his own hands, and to forego that freedom which he hath, to cause the necessary Precautions to take place. To the con∣trary, without their coming hither, how could we have learn't of them those things which we desired to know? And we could not have told how to have regulated those things which were requisite, before we proceeded to a Negotiation; to the end, we might judge by the nature of those affairs, wherewith they were intrusted, in what manner we should Treat them: and thereon, to resolve, whether or no, in the audience which should afterwards be granted unto them, they should be consi∣dered either as Friends or Enemies: As also, to resolve, whether the Dignity of the King, and the Present state of affairs, would per∣mit to receive them at all.</P>
<P>And forasmuch as the Ambassadours of <HI>Brunswick, Lunen∣berg,</HI> and of <HI>Hesse,</HI> were come in the behalf of their Superiours, to proffer their Mediations, it was thought good to invite tdem to be present at the Conference; to the end, they might be Witnesses of the Justice, Sincerity, and Integrity, whereon we should have proceeded on his Majesties behalf: We cannon imagine why the Electors Am∣bassadours would not condescend thereunto. They alledge indeed, that it is a thing without a President, contrary to the usuall Formes and Customes, and prejudicial to the Dignity of his Electoral High∣nesse. But as the Execution of a thing which is just and rea∣sonable in its self, ought not to be hindered, because no example can be alledged thereof: so likewise ought it to have been con∣sidered, that in all this, there is nothing contrary, to what Princes are accustomed to do, by profferring their Mediation and good Offices unto two Parties; and that there is nothing in it, which doth repugne the equity or dignity of his Electoral Highness, since the King hath done all, what in reason could be desired of him, with∣out the prejudicing of his Interests.</P>
<P>But the refusall which the Ambassadours made, to enter into a
<PB N="27" REF="15"/>Conference, in the presence of a third Party, doth render their Em∣bassy to be suspected; and the rather, when the Ambassadours of <HI>Lunenburg</HI> having desired to be excused (because they foresaw the Ambassadours of <HI>Brandenbourg,</HI> would not give way thereunto) the King would willingly have so much complyance for both Par∣ties, as to exempt them, that so no retardment might ensue upon the Treaty.</P>
<P>Now the chief Point of this our Proposition, is, That his Ma∣jesty having deemed it fit, before all things, to know the intention of his serene Electorship, hath commanded us to ask you, whe∣ther his said Electoral Highness, will disingage himself from the Interests of his Majesties Enemies, and renew the Treaties of Peace and Friendship, which seem to be changed, by those things which we have before alledged; as also: to know what power you have to proceed hereon: So soon as his Majesty shall be assured of the one, and shall know that you have sufficient power for the other, he will immediately give command for the beginning of the Treaties; and in case you have not sufficient Power, his Majesty permits you to stay in this Town, untill such time as you have received them: Or otherwise, doth con∣sent that the Treaties may be held in any other Newtrall place; as at <HI>Kiel, Sleswick,</HI> or <HI>Hambourg:</HI> And as soon as his Ma∣jesty shall have notice thereof, he will nominate Commissioners, and will ordain what else shall be requisite to cause the Treaty to take effect. This is that which we have thought good to repre∣sent unto you, and also to assure you of our humble services, so farre as they shall not be repugnant to that Duty which we owe unto our King.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Given at <HI>Flensbourg</HI> on <DATE>the <HI>23</HI> of June <HI>1658.</HI></DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="11" TYPE="proof">
<PB N="28" REF="16"/>
<HEAD>The eleventh Proof. <MILESTONE N="l."/></HEAD>
<HEAD>The Ambassadours of <HI>Brandenburgs</HI> Letter, in Answer to the King of <HI>Swedens</HI> Commissioners.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIRS;</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>VVE received those Letters which you wrote unto us from <HI>Flensbourg,</HI> on the 24 <HI>June,</HI> and to tell you the truth, we are in a manner astonished, that you should send after us, and that we are accused to have precipitated our departure; and that likewise the fault of all that which hath hapned is cast upon us: We were sent, if not at the request, yet at least not against the desire of his Majesty, by a Prince Elector of the Empire, who is his Kinsman and Neighbour: we were at our arrivall received by his Majesties Ministers, and at their request, we drew nigh, as we may say, even to the gates of his Court, and, if after our so long sojourning there, (as that we could not any longer have stayed, without our detracting from the grandure and dignity of his Electorall Highness) we at length departed thence: You may consider if you please, that it was a meer constraint; and after those unque∣stionable proofs which we had received of the design there was to have treated his Electorall Highness as a declared Ene∣my; which was evident, not only by the generall report there∣of which was come to our ears, but also by the Express Letters from the Lord of <HI>Slippenbach,</HI> which you will find hereunto an∣nexed; for which we were very sorry. And those Letters which we have written unto the said Count upon this subject, in answer unto his, do sufficiently denote the same: but by reason they were delivered late enough, and that we assured∣ly beleeve you have not seen them, we do think fitting to add thus much, That we shall alwayes most powerfully second the great inclinations which his Electorall Highness harbour∣eth towards a Peace, and towards an accommodation; we shall expect his Orders thereon at <HI>Hamborow;</HI> and as soon as we shall have received them, we will not fail to give you no∣tice
<PB N="29" REF="16"/>thereof; and shall answer unto all, what may be expected from</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Dated at <HI>Rensbourg</HI> on <DATE>the 25. <HI>June.</HI> 1658.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE> <SIGNED>&amp;c.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="12" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>The twelfth Proof. <MILESTONE N="m."/></HEAD>
<HEAD>A second Letter from the Brandenburg Ambassadours to the Swedish Commissioners.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIRS:</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>BEfore we left <HI>Rensbourg,</HI> we returned you an Answer to the Letter you wrote unto us from <HI>Flensbourg;</HI> but being on our jouaney, and ready to take Coach, we contented our selves only to write the more succinctly unto you, by how much we are perswaded of the high prudence of the King your Master, and therefore do firmly beleeve, that he cannot desire more at our hands, since it must needs be evident, that being at so great a distance from our Court, it was not in our powers to return unto the place from whence we came, but much against our wills; and far less to engage the interest and dig∣nity of the Prince our Master, in writing, without his Electorall Highness express order. Wherefore we were resolved without any delay, to have represented the whole unto him by our Letters; to the end that having received his commands thereon, we might the better have made answer from <HI>Hamborow,</HI> to those things which you desire to know of us.</P>
<P>We do not deny but that the buisness is of so great importance, as that all things ought to have been essayed rather then to break, and by a precipitated resolution, to have frustrated the effects of our Embas∣sie, from which all Christendome might justly expect so considerable an advantage: We still do beleeve the same, and therefore we shall use all possible means to justifie our proceedings; and to let the world see, That if the success proves not answerable to our desires, we shall at least have satisfied our consciences, by the integrity of our Councils, and the sincerity of our Intentions.</P>
<P>But we think our selves obliged to give you notice, That having more maturely considered on what behoved us to do; we have thought it fitting to change the resolution which we had taken, to expect his Electorall Highness command in this place, conceiving it to be more
<PB N="30" REF="17"/>expedient that we go to <HI>Berlin</HI> with all speed; because a personall negotiation hath something more in it then can be expected to be ef∣fected by writing, and at least we shall reap this satisfaction by our voyage, that by a speedy and faithfull report of all the buisness, we shall bring it to a resolve without any delay; we doubt not but you will be of the same minde, and that consequently you will take pa∣tience, and expect such answers as we shall return unto you, so soon as we shall be arrived at our Court.</P>
<P>And as to what concerns the business it self, we have seen and ex∣amined the writing which you sent us, together with the Letters; and we hope you have so good an opinion of us, as to beleeve that we are not altogether so ignorant in the debating of affairs, nor so much void of reason, but that it would be very easie for us to make answer to the chief heads of the said Manifest; and clearly to demonstrate, That it is full of Equivocations, of words whose sense and meaning are obscure, and containeth severall things which are as much disso∣nant unto the Piety of our Prince, as from Truth it self: whereof we are so well assured in our consciences, as that we are willing to beleeve, That the said Peece was not sent unto us from the King, nor were those Writings compiled out of the Registers of those Persons, who had an inspection in buisness; but by such as were transported by an unfor∣tunate precipitation, or by a false and sad preoccupation, without any knowledg at, all of the foregoing passages; nor reflecting in the least upon those things which are to ensue; not being so discreet as to consider what they did, and were wilfully resolved to trouble the Peace of Christendome, by new affected quarrels, in stead of setling and reestablishing the same by new and well grounded alliances. But since the Honour of, and even his Electorall Higness conscience, art engaged in this concerment, we shall desire you not to take it ill, that we enter no further thereon at this present, but that we leave the re∣sentment thereof unto himself.</P>
<P>There is but one thing which we finde our selves obliged to touch on, by the by, which is that in your writing, you say the King hath chang∣ed his resolution, and that he would have so much complaisance or indulgence (according to the Latin original word, they are your own words) for the Ambassadours of <HI>Lunenbourg</HI> and <HI>Hesse,</HI> as to dispence with them so far, as that they might not entervene at the Meeting or Conference, which he had caused to be propounded unto
<PB N="31" REF="17"/>us: But we crave your pardon, if we averre, that you do maintain with too much assurance, a thing which is not so: For the said Am∣bassadours themselves, and the Kings Ministers, do full well know, as you your selves Sirs (who are Persons of Honour) can testifie; that we knew nothing thereof, and that the least word thereon was not told unto us: the last Letters from the Lord of <HI>Slippenbach,</HI> and the visits which were made to the said Ambassadours, to take our leaves of them, are manifest Proofs to the contrary; and do plainly evidence, that there was no appearance at all for us, to expect an audience, in such a manner as was due unto us; nor that the King would alter the resolution, which he he had taken, to make us serve as an example unto Posterity; and to expose us un∣to an unavoidable affront, such a one, as was not to be repaired, in∣stead of treating of us as Ambassadours, from a Prince Elector of the Empire.</P>
<P>But we can with more truth alledge, That we never refused to admit of the Ambassadours of <HI>Lunenbourg</HI> and <HI>Hessen;</HI> by reason that the subject our of Embassy, being just and plausible, we had no reason at all, to debarre the Ministers of those Princes from the Cognisance thereof, who professe a most particular friendship to our Master; neither did we ever hinder the Kings Ministers from visiting of us, nor never refused to enter into any Conference with them: But we would not, nor could not consent into a Con∣ference, the manner, place, and time whereof was prescribed us. We believed it was not expedient, but very unseasonable, because it was to have preceed our audience; besides, we had reason to suspect the said Conference; neither would we acknowledge that superiori∣ty, whereby it was intended to have enforced us thereunto: Or ra∣ther, we would not accept of that, which the Ambassadours them∣selves could not approve of. For we came not thither to debate, or for to enter into a contestation with the Kings Ministers, but we were there in the quality of Ambassadours, for to demand Audience of the King: We appeared there (I say) because the King had de∣sired it, and because his Ministers had invited us thither, had re∣ceived us, had entertained us, and had done us several other Civili∣ties: After all which, not to be admitted unto audience, to have the same deferred and delayed, and finally, absolutely refused; which was never yet done by any Prince, who had once received Ambassa∣dours
<PB N="32" REF="18"/>into his Court, since it is to the Person of the Prince, and not to his Ministers, That Ambassadours do make their addresses. This was the thing at which we were offended, and this was the cause why, to our great grief, we departed.</P>
<P>Nor can you alledge, That we precipitated our said departure, since it could easily be imagined, that after so long a stay, we were not like to beg for an audience, which in Justice ought not to have been refused us.</P>
<P>But all these things are so well known unto you, as that we shall not need to adde any thing else hereunto; being ascertained in our Consciences, that you must needs acquiesse unto those Truths, which we have alledged. Moreover, we remain,</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>SIRS,</SALUTE> <SIGNED>&amp;c.</SIGNED>
<DATELINE>Dated from <HI>Hamborrow</HI> on <DATE>the <HI>30</HI> of <HI>June 1658.</HI></DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="13" TYPE="proof">
<HEAD>The thirteenth Proof. <MILESTONE N="n."/></HEAD>
<HEAD>A third Letter from the <HI>Brandenburg</HI> Ambassadours, in Answer to the Proposition in writing, sent after them by the Swedish Commissioners.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Sirs,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>NO Person whatsoever, who hath the least insight and knowledge of the state of our Affairs, can be igno∣rant, That the Piety, and the Interest of our Elector, doth oblige him earnestly to endeavour the generall Peace; and to see it maintained, and preserved throughout all <HI>Christen∣dome.</HI> For all men, who profess themselves to be versed in the managing of publique affairs, must needs avouch; That this <HI>Prince, whose Prudence is of as large an extent, as his Provinces,</HI> by interesting himself in the establishing of the publique tranquility of the Christian world, doth at the same time, include the setling of his own private security; because his Principalities bordering on most of the Domini∣ons of the Princes of <HI>Germany,</HI> it is unpossible for him to preserve them, but by his keeping a perfect good intelligence betwixt his Neighbours.</P>
<P>His <HI>Electoral Highness</HI> hath so well accomplished the same,
<PB N="33" REF="18"/>as that being unreproachable upon this account, he thought himself not bound to be offended, when by our relation, he heard the ill Treatment, which we received by your King, and saw the calumnies, wherewith all he finds himself slandered, by that Paper which you sent unto us from <HI>Flensbourgh.</HI></P>
<P>This <HI>great Prince,</HI> is willing to forget and pass by the par∣ticular wrongs; which are done unto his Person, to bewail poor <HI>Germany,</HI> which is like to be involved in new disorders: However, he cannot choose but detest the <HI>Ingratitude</HI> of those, <HI>who cloak their pernitious designes;</HI> and the rage, by which they endeavour to continue the Warres, by such un∣just pretentions.</P>
<P>Our <HI>Prince is rendred guilty,</HI> because he hath not quite ruined himself for your Kings sake; and he is threatned with a Warre, because he cannot any longer second an o∣thers <HI>ambition,</HI> without the exposing of his Person, and his Dominions, to a finall ruine. And moreover, he is at this present, reproached with that, which the King did former∣ly esteem the most of all in him; <HI>when he confessed, that he should never be able, to acknowledge those, Obligations, for the which he stood engaged to his Electoral Highnesse:</HI> Just as if there were a great deal of advantage to be reaped, by finding out a pretence to ruine a Friend, unto whom a man is over-ob∣liged; and a great deal of glory to be taken, in the pillaging of a Creditours House, thereby to find wherewithall to pay a Debt, which would otherwise reman unsolved. They affect to render all the Princes actions odious, without re∣flecting on those things, which he hath formerly done; and instead of the dissembling, or at least, excusing those things, which might be blamed in the conduct of a Friend, so great a pleasure is taken in the crying down of the same; as it seemes they are glad to have met with something, where∣on they might frame a pretended quarrell against him.</P>
<P>Neither can it be with any other design, that his Electorall Highness is accused, <HI>To have solicited the Warre against</HI> Poland; <HI>to have quitted the alliance, without any necessity; to have made a
<PB N="34" REF="19"/>new one with</HI> Poland, <HI>and with the House of</HI> Austria; <HI>to have endeavored to engage the King of</HI> Denmark <HI>in the same; to have promised relief to the one, and to have demanded it from the other; to have given passage to the enemies; to have recalled his Subjects out of the Kings service; to have hindred his Leagues; to have seized the Gunpowders:</HI> and to have done several other things, without the making of any distinction, either of time of places, with as much affectation as injustice. It would be a very easie matter for us, to reply on all the Accusations, in such a manner, as thereby we might manifest the justice of our Cause, and the integrity of our Intentions; if so be our Prince, who is not capable of our unworthiness and low actions, had not rather remit himself thereon, unto your own Consciences, then to render you ashamed, by those Answers, which he would return to your re∣proaches.</P>
<P>However, we cannot choose but tell you, That there is so much the less appearance of what you alledge; <HI>That his E∣lectorall Highnesse should have sought unto you for your alliance, to make War against</HI> Poland; as that you cannot tell why he should have done so? what advantages he could thereby reape? or what glory he should thereby ac∣quire?</P>
<P><HI>Warre,</HI> certainly cannot be pleasing, save only unto those, who are <HI>transported, either by ambition or covetousnesse;</HI> or who through poverty, are constrained to live by Thefts, and Rob∣ing of other mens Estates: Unto such (I say) as take a delight amidst the publick calamities, and esteem their only tortures to consist in Peace and Tranquility; who reverence vice, and who account of Pillagings, Murders, Violations, Sacriledges, and the other inseparable disorders, which are tyed to a Warre, as heroick Vertues, and as qualities be∣coming a King. But <HI>our Prince,</HI> was alwaies incapable of such unworthy thoughts: <HI>For he sucked Piety from his Mothers Breasts, and he inherited the love of Justice, and the fear of God, from his Predecessors.</HI></P>
<P>We full well know, that those Warres which are not al∣together necessary, prove oftentimes the most saddest unto
<PB N="35" REF="19"/>those who wage them: Wherefore <HI>we did disswade the Polo∣nian Warre, by divers and sundry Embassies. The Town of</HI> Stetin, <HI>doth very well know, that we abhorre the very thoughts of that Warre, and that we never had a hand therein, but when we were constrained thereunto;</HI> which you cannot likewise deny, in case you do but call to mind, how that the <HI>Polonian Warre</HI> was no sooner resolved on, but that at the same time, <HI>you resolved likewise to engage the Elector therein, whether he would or not:</HI> And we were so farre <HI>from pressing you to Warre against</HI> Poland, <HI>that</HI> Wittenberg <HI>was already entred that Kingdome, when your Ambassadours came to this Town, to seek unto us, or rather to threaten us, and constrain us, to enter into an alliance with you.</HI></P>
<P>We could hardly believe, that you could have the impu∣dence, to reproach us in this wise, unless you had had assured proof thereof: Wherefore we required to know of those persons, which make up his Electorall Highness Council, whether or no their deliberations could in any wise have given cause for the said Accusation: We have runne over the Drafts of all the Letters, which were thereon written, and we have perused all our Registers, to discover, whether hap∣pily your cunning, the necessity of those times, and the state of affairs as then (which were capable, to have moved the firmest constancy, and the resolutest determinations) might have extorted from us, any thing implying the same: But we can take God to witness, That we could not light upon any thing in the least, <HI>That might cause us to suspect our having failed in our fidelity to</HI> Poland, <HI>or of our amity to</HI> Sweden.</P>
<P>For our <HI>Elector</HI> could never sufficiently move the entring on a Peace unto all your Ambassadours, nor to recommend it unto those, who sided with <HI>Sweden.</HI> True it is, that <HI>he gave ear to your Propositions; That he accepted those advantages, which you proffered him, purposely to gain him to your party;</HI> and, <HI>That he did receive your Presents:</HI> But all this he did <HI>with an upright heart, and on purpose to preserve them for the right owners, least they might fall into the hands of strangers.</HI></P>
<P>The refusall which you made, to condescend to a Peace
<PB N="36" REF="20"/>with <HI>Poland,</HI> and the Warre wherewithall you threatned the <HI>Ducall Prussia,</HI> did constrain his Electorall Highness, to enter into a Negotiation with you; and engaged him in a Trea∣ty, by which he alwaies hoped he might meet with an occa∣sion to serve you, as well as the <HI>Polanders;</HI> to preserve both the one and the other, by a good Treaty of Peace, and to give a Testimony of his constant Fidelity to <HI>Po∣land.</HI></P>
<P>For which purpose, our Ambassadours were continually with you, and never departed your Court, who incessantly pressed you to come to a Peace, and who amused you, whilest we were not as yet gotten into a posture to defend our selves: However, we sticked not to take up Armes, to continue our Leagues, and to pass with our Army into <HI>Prussia,</HI> notwithstanding our oppositions and threatnings. You may well remember, Gentlemen, what passed as then, and what the Elector did, to endeavour to beget a Peace, or to uphold the justice and equity of the <HI>Polonian</HI> Forces, by the conjunction of his own; till such time, as that he saw, he could not obtain any thing at your hands, that was just, nor overcome your obstinacy to destroy all: Wherefore he rather chose to expect the very last extreamities, then to fail in that Fidelity, wherein this <HI>generous and good Prince</HI> stood ingaged to the Crown of <HI>Poland.</HI></P>
<P>Both the Royal <HI>Prussia,</HI> and the House of <HI>Austria,</HI> and the States of the United <HI>Provinces,</HI> can witness those endea∣vours, which were used by his Electorall Highness, for to ingage them in an alliance, which might be sufficient to oppose these <HI>Ʋsurpations:</HI> And we heartily grieve, that the success thereof, did not answer our Expectations: However, we shall alwaies retain this satisfaction to our selves, <HI>That the Elector never changed his mind, and that he never failed in his duty, but by constraint; No not with</HI> Poland <HI>its self.</HI></P>
<P>His <HI>Elector all Highness,</HI> could have wished withall his heart, to have seen the said Kingdome in a better condition: But in regard that the King himself had deserted it; that the Sena∣tours had abandoned the management of affairs; that the Souldiers were possessed with a general cowerdize; that all
<PB N="37" REF="20"/>Subjects were treacherous; and that even those, who were born, and payed to fight in the defence of that Common∣wealth, had taken up Armes against her: He was con∣strained, even to give way to those great Evils, which had overwhealmed the whole State.</P>
<P>Insomuch, that there cannot be any unbyassed dsiinterressed party, but will praise the Electors prudence, who in the pre∣serving himself, by the meanes of a Treaty, remained in a condition, both to preserve <HI>Poland</HI> and <HI>Sweden</HI> together.</P>
<P><HI>Poland</HI> itself, is discreet and rational enough, to acknow∣ledge it, and to avouch: That all necessary meanes are honest and lawfull; and that the Obligation of the Lord, and of the Subjects, being reciprocall. The Subject cannot be blamed for having failed, to defend the Lord, in case the Lord hath failed to protect the Subject. And wherein <HI>Poland</HI> is more equitable then you are, for being sensible of her sad enforced destiny, she bewailes ours; not accusing us to have quitted her party, because she knows we were constrained thereunto; although she likewise full well knows; That in case the <HI>loss of the battell of</HI> Warsowe <HI>be not wholly due to our Army, yet at least it did not a little contribute thereunto.</HI></P>
<P>Wherefore, we conjure you <HI>(Gentlemen)</HI> without passion, to reflect upon the tye, which lieth upon us to endeavour the begetting and preserving a Peace between <HI>Poland</HI> and <HI>Sweden,</HI> and to maintain their power in a just equality; as also to judg <HI>how little appearance there is, that we should have obliged your King, to take up Armes against</HI> Poland: And whether it be not a very dishonest part to alledge: <HI>That we endeavoured to make an alliance for a Warre, which of necessity, must have proved de∣structive to our selves?</HI></P>
<P>We only desire you chiefly to consider, how and in what matter you can possible blame our <HI>reconciliation</HI> with <HI>Poland?</HI> And with what equity the King can condemn our proceed∣ings at <HI>Bromberg?</HI> seeing he approved of what had passed at <HI>Koningsberg.</HI> And truly, since you were not ashamed to im∣pose a Law, and a necessity on a Prince your Friend, and to constrain him to act against the Lord of his Mannor, the King ought to harbour so much generosity, as not to be dis∣pleased
<PB N="38" REF="21"/>to see that reunited again by a secret destiny, which was disunited by your violence and force. Princes do not proceed like common people: They are not accustomed to pick groundless quarrels; nor are they transported by cholar: Their Fortune is above all that. So likewise, <HI>do they not undertake any Warre, but with a resolution to obtain a Peace.</HI></P>
<P>We were constrained to side with you, and so long as the State of our affairs did permit, as to stay by you, we upheld your party with Fidelity, and never abandoned you, till you had deserted us; and had left us to the discretion of Fortune, without either hopes of a Peace, or of a Relief: Nor can you be ignorant in what a condition the Kings Forces were in, when we drew off, after the Battell of <HI>Warsow;</HI> and in what a manner the Enemies recruted themselves after the said loss; which instead of quite ruining them, restored all their affairs, and put a double proportion of courage into them: We found them marching at our heels, when we thought we had laid them along; and we found them pur∣suing us in the reare, laying all waste, wheresoever they past, and putting all to fire and sword; in their pursuite mena∣cing us (even after their defeate and flying away) <HI>more like Victors, then overcome men.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Transilvanian</HI> trembled, the <HI>Muscovite</HI> threatned us, and the King of <HI>Denmark</HI> thwarted all your designes by a new Warre, whereby the King was obliged to abandon the whole, to march unto the relief of the Principality of <HI>Bremn.</HI> In regard whereof, we could not refuse to hearken unto the Remonstrances of our Subjects, to the Prayers of our Friends, and to the proffers of our Enemies; or rather, <HI>We were con∣strained to make a Peace with</HI> Poland, and to accept of those conditions which were proffered us, although they had been farre less equitable then those, which were grant∣ed us.</P>
<P>Now this being the true state of the buisness, <HI>Can you with reason alledge, that the Elector abandoned you? Can you with equi∣ty be displeased thereat? Are you in a capacity to threaten him?</HI> And can you hinder him to agree with the Enemy? and by
<PB N="39" REF="21"/>a Treaty, to endeavour to preserve his Estates, the which you could not defend. An invincible necessity might have induced him, had there been one to have preferred his Inte∣rest before anothers: But nature it self, even from our Child∣hoods, doth teach us to avoid our own ruine, by all meanes possible. That which necessitates, doth justifie; and where necessity reignes, there is no Law▪ For in a storm, each man seeks his own preservation, though to the loss of other mens goods.</P>
<P>We confess; that the King wished us better luck, and that he used all meanes possible to retain his <HI>Electoral Highnesse</HI> on his party; to which end, he caused several Propositions to be made: He desired that we would make use of his Coun∣cil, and he made us hope, he would make Peace with <HI>Poland;</HI> and that he would return to the Army, within six weeks time; which proved meer words, and nothing more was intended. But we stood in need of effectuall and powerfull relief against the enemy, who was already gotten into our Countrey, whilest the King having <HI>abandoned Prussia,</HI> and his other Allyes, was departed from thence, and was order∣ing his Affairs in <HI>Germany.</HI></P>
<P>Insomuch, as that all men must needs perceive, there was no choice left to be made at that time; and that his <HI>Electoral Highnesse,</HI> being not able any longer to resist the strength of necessity, was constrained to bethink himself of minding his own buisness, and to preserve himself by meanes of a Trea∣ty. Wherein we only made use of the Kings Example, who was farre cunninger then we, when he abandoned his <HI>Conquests</HI> in <HI>Poland,</HI> and his <HI>Friends</HI> in <HI>Prussia,</HI> to <HI>defend his E∣states in</HI> Germany; rather then other mens any where else: But however, he hath been so much the more unjust, that having failed of his word, through a less pressing necessity, he finds fault, that in an utmost extreamity, we have followed his Example.</P>
<P>You would willingly perswade us, <HI>That we might have avoid∣ed that necessity; by doing, or suffering such things to be done, as ought to have been done; and the which would have been very easie.</HI> But we attribute this to the good reallity with which you are
<PB N="40" REF="22"/>used to proceed in all your other affairs, even to the prejudice of your best Friends: Nor can we choose but admire the dexteri∣ty whereby you could penetrate so deep into our affairs, as not only to discover those secrets, which we were desirous to have kept from the knowledg of others; but also those which were unknown to our selves: But as you have so good an opinion of your own buisness, take care you be not deceived in ours: For if every one ought to be beleeved, as to his own concern∣ments, we must confess, that your affairs being almost in a de∣sperate condition, because your subtilty could not overpoise those Forces, which were a falling upon you from all sides; <HI>How was it possible for us to hope to preserve our selves?</HI></P>
<P>Lay aside, I beseech you, that passion which hath possessed you; let not the success of your Armies, blot out the memory of what is past; and permit us to represent unto you the evils of a War, whenas not necessary: and call to minde those streights and agonies, which caused you so often <HI>to long for an honourable Peace;</HI> and those vowes which you continually made, that you would not suffer your self to be transported by the flattering appearances of the good success of your Ar∣mies; which resolves were more then once by you taken; nay, as often as the wrath of God, or rather his goodness, endeavoured to bring you to reason, through the prosperity of the <HI>Allyes Forces.</HI> And if as yet you cannot attribute any faith to our words, we beseech you only to reflect on the <HI>Condition of Prince</HI> Regotsky; <HI>consider him, and be more herein jointly with us: Remember, what this good Prince, who hath don<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> so much for you, is come to, and in what a manner you have relieved him;</HI> although he be happier then we, by reason that you pitty him, for having lost himself for your sakes; <HI>whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>as you reproach the Elector, because he would not perish with you.</HI></P>
<P>But not to enlarge upon these Afflictions, the remembrance whereof cannot choose but be very sensible to those who re∣tain any sparkles of humanity and tenderness; let us set what you mean, by your endeavouring to perswade us, <HI>That we might have avoided the encountring of all these misfortunes, in case we would have done that which</HI> (according to your own
<PB N="41" REF="22"/>advice) <HI>was necessary and easie.</HI> We ingeniously confess, that we cannot perceive your meaning; but we very well re∣member, to have seen you so surprised, and astonished in ad∣versities, <HI>That you believed, you both bought, and could perswade his Electoral Highnesse, that there was a necessity he should joyn his Forces unto yours, and so to perish joyntly with you. The one (indeed) was very necessary for your service alone, and the other ve∣ry easie, both to yours and ours.</HI> You would have us to reject the just complaint of our good Subjects; to despise the cruell threatnings of our enemies, and yet by a more then Stoicall indifferency, we should have sat cross-armed, and looked upon the several devastations of our Provinces.</P>
<P>And to the end, that there might be nothing wanting to that inviolable friendship which you retained for us, your Ambassadours ceased not mean while to represent, <HI>That the Elector would do well to yeild</HI> Prussia <HI>to the King, as a Province which could not choose but be burdensome and chargeable to the Prince Elector; and that we should do well to put our Ports into his hands.</HI> Without doubt, because we should not reap the dis∣pleasure, to see them perish in our own; and that we might at least receive the satisfaction, to see them taken from the <HI>Swedes,</HI> who doubtless would be so good unto us, as to <HI>re∣compence us for the same, out of those Conquests they should make in</HI> Poland, <HI>and</HI> Silesia; <HI>or it may be, to induce us, to give them that in a generous way, which they had a mind one day to take a∣way from us.</HI> They would have ingaged us to have entred <HI>Silesia</HI> with our Army, and to have made up our share, by the <HI>ruine of the Empire of</HI> Germany; without their reflecting on the Obligation which the Elector oweth unto the Empe∣ruor, and the assurances which the King himself had so often given, That he would never molest or trouble the repose thereof. They were so ill advised, as to counsell us to set upon others Estates, at such a time, when we could not hin∣der the <HI>Polanders</HI> from falling into our own; nor to re∣gain the Capitall City of their Kingdom, and the chief Peace of our Conquests: And all your policy consisted, on∣ly to blow into our cars, that there was a necessity to pro∣tract and delay the Treaties, to gain time, and to make us
<PB N="42" REF="23"/>hope that the King would speedily return again into <HI>Prussia.</HI> And you so well compassed your designes thereby, as that whereas we both could have, and ought to have made use of the occasion, and have concluded our Treaty immediately, we only finished it at the end of four Moneths; neither did we sign the Treaty with <HI>Poland,</HI> save after we discovered that your King did but dally with us, whilest our condition grew every day worse and worse; and that the <HI>Polanders</HI> took advantages at the small appearance of relief, which we could promise our selves from the King of <HI>Sweden:</HI> Where∣in, to our thinkings, we proceeded so warily, as you your selves cannot condemn it. Insomuch, as though you will hardly avouch it, save in an indirect manner: However, we hope that one day you will come to your selves again, and that you will be more rational.</P>
<P>We full well know, that it is not your custom to harbour any complaisance for your Friends: Insomuch, as that by your boasting, <HI>to have permitted the Elector to enter into a Nego∣tiation for a Newtrality,</HI> you confess you have done more, then you believed you were bound to do; because you do in some manner acknowledge, that amidst our humane actions, there happens some conjunctures which oblige us to give way unto necessity. But although we speak with so much advantage of you, we do not intend to lessen the glory which we ac∣count due to your King, who being desirous to give a finall proof of his friendship unto his <HI>Electoral Highnesse,</HI> who com∣plained that he alone was exposed to the discretion of the ene∣mies, contrary to the Treaty between them; <HI>did not permit him</HI> (for he could not have done less to one of his Subjects) <HI>but counselled him as his Friend and Kinsman, to make a Trea∣ty of Newtrality with</HI> Poland; we are not a little obliged to you however, for what you say thereon, since we could hardly perswade our selves you had been capable to averre, That we did well to make a Treaty of Newtrality, whilest you reject that Treaty, by which we quit your alliance; and to acknowledge the necessity of the one, whilest you abso∣lutely condemn the other.</P>
<P>We beseech you <HI>(Gentlemen)</HI> to consider, that your
<PB N="43" REF="23"/>censure is either too severe, or rather unjust: Whereas ac∣knowledging the necessity, you refuse to admit the Lawes of Tyranny; Nature it self teacheth, that in some things, you must of necessity go from one extreamity to another. A man cannot stop himself, being on a Precipice; and a River that overflowes, cannot be stopped by one sole ditch: The revolutions of great things, cannot be small; and those things which are well interwoven, cannot be unsowed; you must either tear them, or cut them asunder. We could not remain allyed with you, and seek the Friendship of the <HI>Poles.</HI></P>
<P>For you your selves (Swedish Sirs) alledge, <HI>That one must be either a Friend, or declared Enemy, to a Prince who hath an Army on foot.</HI> And for all this, you would have us remain Neutrall with the <HI>Poles;</HI> that is to say, you would have us become their Enemies, whilest they are Victorious; and you would have us remain your Friends in your misfortunes. As if it were as easie to us, not to bear down whatsoever we should meet withall in our fall, after you shall have ingaged and forced us on the Precipice, as it hath been easie for us to hinder our selves from falling. Undeceive therefore your selves, and learn of us, <HI>That never a Victorious party granted a Newtrality to a declared Enemy:</HI> And that it was by a secret disposall, and decree of God, we were forced to take part with the <HI>Poles;</HI> and that otherwaies your pretended Newtra∣lity could not save us.</P>
<P>And hereon it is, that you so mainly fly out, and endea∣vour to cry down our proceedings, with a great deal of ani∣mosity; and wherein the <HI>Polanders</HI> themselves, have been farre more reasonable then you, who had exclaimed against us, before we ever had assisted the Enemy in the least: And although it may seem, we have preferred warre before Peace, yet however we not any waies alter the resolution which we have taken, incessantly to labour for accommoda∣tion; and farre from repenting our selves of that agreement which we have made with the <HI>Polanders,</HI> we are fully per∣swaded, that it is the only meanes to preserve each other, and to beget an honourable and reasonable Peace between the two Crownes.</P>
<PB N="44" REF="24"/>
<P>Moreover, those Injuries and Aspersions which you cast upon us, do so much the less concern us, as by them you mani∣fest, That you only have regard to your own Interests; and that all those, who will go about to make themselves sure of the Swedish friendship, must resolve to labour in the establish∣ing of their Dominion, even at the expences of their Goods and Liberties.</P>
<P>We are ashamed to represent unto you, in a large discourse, all those things which you know we have done for you; nei∣ther are we disposed to reproach you with the proofes of the friendship and good will which our Prince hath testified unto you in such a manner, as well as those Obligations you are indebted to him for what he did at the execution of the first Treaty; you your selves do know it full well, and your Letters which do so often promise an external acknowledg∣ment thereon to his Electorall Highness, will alwaies testi∣fie the same unto posterity. It sufficeth us, <HI>That the Plaines of</HI> Warsawe, <HI>that all</HI> Massow, <HI>and</HI> Poland <HI>to boot, doth pub∣lish it.</HI> Nor can your warlike Exploits be mentioned, with∣out the specifying of our shares at the same time; and that it is very well known, <HI>It was our Money, and our Forces, which supported your drooping Fortune.</HI> And which is more then all this, <HI>By un unheard of prodigality, we have set you up again, e∣ven with the perill of our life, and the forfeiture of our reputa∣tion.</HI></P>
<P>However, we do not deny, that we ever undertook a∣ny Warre, save with a resolution to let slip no occasions to make Peace, and to re-establish the publique tranquility; to which end, we often stopped your extravagancies, by pro∣positions of an accommodation, which we did not only pro∣mote, but also urged them most pressingly, even in the midst of our Victories. For we represented unto our selves warre with all its sequell of evils; we conceived that the advanta∣ges of our Armes were to be made use of, to smother the said fire, as also to disperse the very ashes of it. And we deemed, <HI>That it was only the part of Thieves and Murderers, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> wage Warre, for the love of Wirre it self.</HI> And that it is a sad disaster, to declare against God, and against all men, by boast∣ing
<PB N="45" REF="24"/>and glorying, in the sacrifysing of the life, the honour, and the souls of an infinite number of Christians, to our am∣bition. True it is, that your King hath often given ear to these and the like overtures, and hath ever desired the <HI>Elector to make up a Peace upon tollerable Conditions.</HI></P>
<P>Now, if he, who was the cause of the warre, both would, and could do it; Why do you <HI>(Gentlemen)</HI> find fault that we have done it? We, who had only taken up Armes in his be∣half? Why would you not have us rid our selves of a warre which we did not begin? And why will you not have us make such a Peace, which makes us hope to obtain that o∣ther which we are engaged, through our Interest to procure and establish a Peace betwixt two Kings who are our Neigh∣bours? This very consideration, and this very necessity, con∣strained us to side with the <HI>Polanders,</HI> purposely to procure a Peace for you, and to restore quietness to the others.</P>
<P>VVherefore we beseech you to spare us, and not to abuse and slander our Prince, who is the best of your Friends. VVe have sided with the <HI>Polanders,</HI> that's true, but it was through constraint; nor can the Treaty which we have made, be pre∣judicial unto you, in case you be capable of reason; and therefore you cannot reproach us, for having Treated an alli∣ance at <HI>Bromberg;</HI> the conditions whereof cannot displease you at all; unless that you are displeased to see thereby, that we have undertaken to re-establish Peace and quietness in our Territories. VVe protest before God, that we have no other intention; and we ought to believe, That an ho∣nourable Peace would not be undispleasing unto you. And this hope, was chiefly confirmed unto us by the French Am∣bassadours, who did not only assure all the world of the in∣clination you bore to Peace, but h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hath also declared in wri∣ting, That you were ready to restore <HI>Prussia</HI> for a summe of Money: wherein also, we proffered our asistance from the very time we were at <HI>Bromberg.</HI></P>
<P>For being obliged to give you notice, that we were entred upon an alliance with <HI>Poland,</HI> we could not any more give you entrance into our Ports, nor passage through our Terri∣tories; to which we were glad to adde, <HI>That</HI> Poland <HI>only de∣sired
<PB N="46" REF="25"/>a Peace:</HI> That according to all appearance, the agreement might be made in few daies; and that if it pleased the King, to make known his Intentions to the Elector, and to Intrust him with the Conditions, there should be no Treaty capable to engage him to take up Arms against him, in case the King would submit to any thing that was reason: The Count of <HI>Slippenbach,</HI> your own Ambassadour, could not choose but praise his <HI>Electoral Highness</HI> good Intentions, and approved of the Treaty which was made with <HI>Poland;</HI> of which he said, His King had no great reason to complain: and himself con∣fessed, That those things might be excepted without offence, which you could not with equity have hoped to have posses∣sed one day.</P>
<P>VVherefore you are the more unjust, and not willing to remember all those passages, you change your opinion, and likewise altring your Tenents. After several sad reproaches, you have the impudence to alledge, <HI>That his Electoral High∣ness, hath promised to succour the</HI> Polanders <HI>in the Empire.</HI> But this you shall never be able to prove; The Treaty speakes quite contrary. And had you but the least friendship for the Elector, and for the Truth it self, you will easily perceive, <HI>That the sole refusall which he made, to give passage to the Polish Troops through</HI> Pomerania <HI>into</HI> Holstein, <HI>was that which saved you.</HI> True it is, that the said <HI>Polanders</HI> made one irruption into the Swedish <HI>Pomerania:</HI> but it is also true, that this hap∣ned whilest the Elector was with his Army in <HI>Prussia;</HI> and the loss which we sustained thereby, doth sufficiently denote our innocence.</P>
<P>Thus you see (Gentlemen) how you thrive by your Ac∣cusations; for all your following discourse, even to the end, is in the like style. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ndeed, you talk much, <HI>of the intel∣ligence we should have held with the King of</HI> Denmark, <HI>and what a design we had to joyn our Forces to Warre upon you:</HI> But this you must prove: You do accuse, without proofes, and do slander without fear of being punished. In the conjuncture of affairs, at the time, we were threatned, we were sought unto; de∣signes were fomented against us, and proffers were made un∣to us, as unto a Prince, who had not as yet declared himself:
<PB N="47" REF="25"/>and to my thinking, that we had the civility to hearken to those Proposals, it cannot be misinterpreted, since it is nei∣ther in our power not to hear, or not to suffer another to speak.</P>
<P>Why would you not have it left to the Electors choice, to give ear to those Propositions which were made? to answer them? and to treat upon them since you were not prejudiced, neither his Electorall Highness engaged thereby? We cannot beleeve that your King intends to debarre <HI>a free Prince</HI> from his liber∣ty, especially such a one as doth not acknowledg him in the least. But because we cannot imagin, that a <HI>Prince</HI> who pro∣fesseth generosity should possibly be capable to harbour such a conceit; we shall rest satisfied by urging you to prove, not, that we never began, but that we ever ended those Negotia∣tions: not, that we have not only begun, but also that we have concluded, signed, and ratified the said Treaties; as then we shall willingly beleeve your allegations, although otherwise there is but little faith to be given to you.</P>
<P>That which you alledg concerning the House of <HI>Austria,</HI> is most abominably false: But patience; we can dispell these Illusions as well as the others: All men know at what a val∣lue the said House is in <HI>Germany;</HI> wherefore we shall not need to answer your allegation, which we account meerly as a thing which partly is not at all, or if there be any thing of it, it is so remote from truth, as that we shall only say, <HI>Had you not threatned us, we had not needed to have troubled our selves with alliances;</HI> and that we beleeve, the Elector might have made an alliance with as great a Prince of <HI>Germany,</HI> without asking you leave; unless you already perswade your selves to be Masters of the liberties of all the Princes of the Empire. But we have just reason to complain, whenas this said alliance, having not passed the tearms and limits of a just and lawfull defence; you take occasion thereby to cry us down, as if we had conspired against you; because you hope to draw this advantake thence, <HI>That your Calumnies, though never so false, will alwayes leave some impressions in mens mindes, capable to make us odious:</HI> all the world knows, we alwayes abhorred Warre, neither did we ever enter into any Negotiation whatsoever,
<PB N="48" REF="26"/>no not with your selves, but our ends were for Peace. We endeavoured to make Friends on all sides, that we might the better compass the aforesaid ends; and we confess, that we were not sorry sometimes to see the great prosperities of the victorious checked by small adversities, to render them the more capeable of reason.</P>
<P>Nor can we forbear to tell you that you are besides your wits, when you alledg, <HI>That we shared the Estates and Province<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of your King, and that we have treated him as a common Enemy.</HI> You may say what you please; but you are so farre from proving of it, that to the contrary, we will give whatsoever you please, <HI>That in case you undertake nothing against your Neigh∣bours, that your Armies enter not into the Empire, that you leave the Prince Elector and his Estates in tranquillity,</HI> we will not on∣ly never pretend any thing of <HI>Sweden,</HI> nor upon your other Estates in <HI>Germany;</HI> but that also we shall alwayes retain that respect and consideration for the <HI>Kings Person,</HI> which we owe to his deserts, and to the advantage of his birth which he hath had in one of the most Illustrious Families of all <HI>Germa∣ny:</HI> wherefore we can hardly resolve to adde hereunto, That this Alliance, of which you so much talk, which hath been negotiated with so much circumspection, and the conclusion whereof hath for a great while together been delayed, even by the consent of the House of <HI>Austria;</HI> purposely to debarre you from all evasions of refusing the Peace, was not concluded and ratified, till such time as it was known, that you decla∣red your selves publikely against the Peace; and after they began openly to disclaim that security which was promised us against their threatnings and violences.</P>
<P>The same reason hinders us from answering those things which you alledg, concerning <HI>succours, leavies, garrisons, ren∣dezvous of Armies, ceising of Gunpowder,</HI> &amp;c. for we can very wel justifie our selves by one word, <HI>denying what you say, That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> have not hindred your leavies; That we demanded no succours against you; That we disturbed not your assembling of your Troops.</HI></P>
<P>As to the other things you reproach us with, they are such indifferent and free voluntary ones, as that we might do by them as we pleased our selves, without the offring you any in∣jury at all.</P>
<PB N="49" REF="26"/>
<P>And as concerning your <HI>Gunpowder,</HI> you may thank your selves, we had given your King notice thereof long time before; and we had so deeply engaged our selves to the <HI>Po∣landers,</HI> that we would not permit any ammunitions of warre <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o pass, as that we could not break our word, unless we were minded to have exposed our selves again to those hostilities which we chose to avoid by the said alliance which we made with them.</P>
<P>Which being so, and that there is not any thing to be re∣plied thereunto, it doth of necessity hence arise, <HI>That we have not committed any act of hostility against you in the Empire, and that we sided not with the Polanders save upon constraint.</HI> Insomuch as that without all doubt, in case you had been as much in∣clined unto Peace, as we alwayes were, it would be an easie matter to preserve it amongst us, and that on both sides we might enjoy a profound tranquility, and by a happy succes∣sion leave to our Posterities the Estates which the Almighty hath entrusted under our Government. The very name of <HI>Warre</HI> ought to be terrible; nor truly can it be pleasing, save only unto such ears as bear no respect to those things which are above them, nor fear of those which are below them. But we of all men abhor it the more, by how much we cannot endure it amongst those whose proximity of Neighbourhood or the bond of Amity, ought to contain within the streighter limits and tyes of conjunction. Would to God you had har∣boured the same thoughts, and God grant as yet you may pos∣sess them: truly it is a part of your duty; and, if so be the charming name of Peace, if the continuall prayers of the peo∣ple, if the just apprehensions of ill successes of an unjust war, and if the sense of the wrath of God, which hath been so rash∣ly provoked, are not sufficient to cause you to change your re∣solutions; at least you ought to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>sider (if possibly you can) That the hopes of an inconsiderable advantage, ought not to have so great an ascendent upon you, as meerly in a frolick and in an humour, to cast a faithfull Friend, into an irreco∣verable enmity.</P>
<P>You full well know, we have <HI>sworne</HI> to the Alliance which we have made with <HI>Poland:</HI> and since you enforced us there∣unto,
<PB N="50" REF="27"/>it was a part of your prudence to have endeavoured the regaining of a Friend, who had not as yet offended you; in∣stead of declaring warre against him, and reducing him to the last extremity: unless it turns more to your advantage <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> have constrained him to declare himself against you. Now if there be any fault in this which we have done, surely you that have enforced us thereunto cannot scape innocent.</P>
<P>The <HI>Interests of Religion,</HI> which are alledged, are very con∣siderable; 'tis true, but the means to preserve them were pro∣pounded unto you, as well as the others; since the <HI>Polanders</HI> proffered to have a care thereof, and to remedy all those par∣ticulars which might have induced you to wage warre; and all this with the more certainty as to Religion, in that the conscience and the Religion of the Elector found their securi∣ty in the Soveraignty of <HI>Prussia,</HI> which the King had granted unto him. But we must likewise confess, That you did not greatly heed Religion, <HI>whether or no you judg wisely and piously, that she may be perswaded, but not commanded: that it is not war∣fare, but a godly life; not force or violence, but sufferings to Martyr∣domes which establish it:</HI> or whether you really know, that there is no place in the world where the pretence of Religion is of less effect in martiall affairs, as in <HI>Poland.</HI> For it is most true, and we know it by experience, that the warre hath most of all shaken the state of our Religion; and whereas in times of peace we enjoyed an entire liberty of conscience through∣out all <HI>Poland,</HI> the warres were no sooner begun there again, but in hatred unto your forces, they persecuted those who made profession of the Protestant Religion; whereas Peace would have preserved the same, and also by a Treaty you might have had great advantages granted for the furtherance of the same.</P>
<P>But truly, this is not th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 chunk" DISP="…"/>ing which we can expect from you; for <HI>how can those be zealous as to concernments of Religion, who are manifestly unjust? by demanding and possessing of Prussia!</HI> who violate all the Laws of Friendship, to become Masters of the <HI>Baltick Sea?</HI> We have seen you stirre Heaven and earth, tosse all things topsiturvy, make no distinction betwixt Friends or Enemies, party or party, to compass your designs,
<PB N="51" REF="27"/>which you have laid to joyn all these spatious and great Pro∣vinces to your Crown.</P>
<P><HI>This is an effect and mark of your Religion,</HI> but whereof till now we had not learnt the rules, when you say (for you do not at all disguize it) <HI>that Kings are the Masters of all.</HI> It is a pretious and pious Notion to say, That the <HI>Polanders</HI> are obli∣ged in conscience to defend Christendome from the invasions of so many Enemies and barbarous Nations, whilest your poverty permits you to be pious, and puts you in a most bles∣sed condition, if your ill fortune shut you up at home, where you will alwaies reap this comfort, by the assurance you have, that you may alwayes unpunished assault others, without your fearing of being assaulted by others in your own homes. In case your King be resolved to continue the warres, which we hardly beleeve, he would not be a little troubled to beget the same minde in all those of his party. <HI>It would prove a new unheard of kinde of Justice, to prefer warre before peace;</HI> Prussia <HI>before the interests of the whole world; and your particular Laws to the Almighties.</HI></P>
<P>In regard whereof, the Prince Elector being sensibly touch∣ed with all these disorders, and seeing that the state of affairs required him to take a strong resolution either to prevent and remedy them, or to perish: he would essay whether his ex∣ample might prove capable to bring you back unto reason; or at least in case our sinnes would not permit us to hope that, to try whether all honest men might not be perswaded, <HI>That it was not his fault the Peace was not made, and that all the North at this present doth not enjoy a profound Tranquillity.</HI></P>
<P>But since this hath not succeeded, by reason that your King, not being satisfied with his too unadvised rejecting our Em∣basie, endeavours moreover to cast a blame upon us, which he knoweth cannot be excused on his part: you will therefore not take it ill (Gentlemen) that we both remit you, and our selves, unto the judgement of the whole world, as to what is past, that so they may immediately decide this first que∣stion, <HI>viz.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Whether or no, in the present conjuncture of affairs, the Elector can be blamed, for having sent Ambassadours to the King?</HI></P>
<PB N="52" REF="28"/>
<P><HI>Whether or no his Majesty hath done well, to send us back again without hearing of us?</HI></P>
<P><HI>Whether it may not be said, That the King by refusing to acknow∣ledg us, otherwaies then in the quality of Ambassadours from Ene∣mies, hath not declared Warre against the Electorall Highness? and whether, by refusing of the Peace, he hath not infringed the same?</HI></P>
<P>We are willing to remit our selves hereon, unto your own selves (Gentlemen,) and we have so good an opinion of your prudence, and of your justice, as that we perswade our selves, your belief is the same with ours, <HI>That the Motions which in∣duced the Elector to depute this Embassie, are good and Religious, and that the Parties which were employed therein, did behave them∣selves like Persons of Honour;</HI> and therefore we conceive we ought not to insist any further thereon. For since we had no other design, save to preserve that Friendship which we had contracted with you, and to procure a just and honourable Peace between the two Crowns, to your advantage, to the content of all our Friends and Allyes, and for the repose and peace of our consciences; <HI>me thinks, we might have gone directly to the King, although we had been your declared Enemies; we might have done it, I say, because you had approved of it:</HI> for I pray, what other means have you, speedily to remedy those disor∣ders which afflict us? You are all Learned men, and you know that one Associate may act for the other; and moreover it may easily be perceived, that our Prince did send this Embassie unto you with a very good intention; not as an Enemy, but as a Friend; not with your thoughts, but with his own. Do but consider I pray, with how much moderation we have taken notice of you; that even since the peace of <HI>Denmark,</HI> and since it was known that this Embassie was resolved on, neither your King, nor his Ministers, have not in the least denied those obligations you owe unto us. For you approved of all, you did not condemn that which we had done with <HI>Poland,</HI> with the House of <HI>Austria,</HI> and with <HI>Denmark,</HI> you found no fault therewith; and you continued to make us hope, that notwithstanding all that was past, we should live in a good understanding together: you sought to us for our
<PB N="53" REF="28"/>friendship, and you publikely praised the prudence and sin∣cerity of his Electorall Highness.</P>
<P>The King himself, writing with his own hand to the Ele∣ctor, indate the 10th of <HI>April,</HI> saith, <HI>That it concerned the Elector to make the Peace with</HI> Poland; <HI>and that therefore his Majesty could not expect from his Electorall Highness (as from a most faithfull Friend) save all kind of good offices, and such ad∣vices whereof he might make use, to deliver himself from so many Enemies as had declared themselves against him.</HI></P>
<P>The Count of <HI>Slippenbach</HI> having desired the Conference at <HI>Prenslou,</HI> after he had produced by the Kings Order, those pretended Treaties of <HI>Denmark</HI> and <HI>Austria,</HI> and after se∣verall discussings on all sides, did not only press this Embas∣sie; but also having received those new Orders which the King had sent him from <HI>Gottemburg;</HI> he protested both by word of mouth, and by writing, that there could not be any thing done which would be more acceptable to the King.</P>
<P>The Lord <HI>Wolsberg,</HI> your Resident in our Court, continued his Offices hereon with so much urgency, as that we shall not need to specifie Mr. <HI>Tophson</HI>'s and Mr. <HI>Blondel</HI>'s instances which they added, on the behalf of the King of <HI>France,</HI> and of <HI>Eng∣land;</HI> nor the severall Embassies which the Dukes of <HI>Bruns∣wick, Lunenburg,</HI> and the Lantsgrave of <HI>Hess,</HI> have sent unto us, as upon the same account: Insomuch as that it needs not to be wondred at, if the Elector, who of himself had a great inclination to Peace, at length did yeeld to the counsils of so many illustrious Personages.</P>
<P>Having therefore left <HI>Berlin,</HI> and having reached your Garrisons, we were there very well received, particularly at <HI>Kiel;</HI> where the Prince of <HI>Sulsbach,</HI> did us more honour then we could have expected: we know not whether the King may have repented himself in having been so prodigall of his first Civilities; which however, we can scarce believe from his generosity, although we have reason to apprehend it, by that which followed after: However, we owe very much to the obliging fault which that Prince may have committed, by taking the paines, to come purposely <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Gottorp,</HI> and di∣vert us, during the tediousness, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 chunk" DISP="…"/>ings long absence
<PB N="54" REF="29"/>might have caused: <HI>He not only received us with a great deal of civility,</HI> and assured us, <HI>That the King retained a particular af∣fection for the Elector; but he also feasted us at his House, and did us the honour to visit us in our lodgings.</HI> The Count of <HI>Slippen∣bach,</HI> arrived likewise much about the same time, and used us with the same respects and civilities, on the behalf of the King.</P>
<P>As soon as we heard the King was arrived in <HI>Holstein,</HI> we went speedily to <HI>Gottorp;</HI> and that we might not fail in the usual formes, and accustomed manners of proceeding, we would not advance to <HI>Flensbourg,</HI> without the Kings express assent: For the Prince of <HI>Sulsbach</HI> having advertised the King of our arrivall, we had notice, that the King left us to our Liberties, either to expect him at <HI>Gottorp,</HI> or to go to him to <HI>Flensbourg,</HI> whether we went, and found a House appointed for our reception; And we were complemented in our lodgings, however with a kind of coldness, after we had communicated our Letters of Credence.</P>
<P>After which, they began to delay and deferre our audi∣ence; and finally, <HI>Seeing you could not dive into the particulars of our Commission, nor know what we had to say concerning the Peace, and touching the restitution of</HI> Prussia, <HI>and that there were no more hopes left, to make us renounce those alliances which we had made, to engage us on your side, and involve us blindly in a Warre, which you are resolved to continue and prosecute, to establish your Dominion:</HI> You began publickly to witness an adversion against us, to reproach us with things which were not, and to <HI>refuse us audience.</HI> And that there might be nothing wanting to the entire affront, you intended to put upon us; you would have rendred us guilty, and have caused us to ap∣pear as criminals before your selves, and before the Ambassa∣dours of <HI>Lunenbourg</HI> and <HI>Hesse; which was not the way to enter into a Conference, but into a Contest.</HI> You had prepared your selves, not to have payed us with reason, but to have charged us with injuries; and instead of having disposed things to∣wards a reconcilion you did but exasperate them, purposely to bring them to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> open rupture: It was not your intent to make up the breaches in the presence of those Princes Ambas∣sadours,
<PB N="55" REF="29"/>which are our common Friends, but to render them irrecoverable; to embroyl us with them, and thence to have obtained a plausible pretence, <HI>to have sent us away without the gi∣ving us an audience.</HI></P>
<P>Truly we are ashamed to recount all these particulars; you very well know, <HI>that we alwaies protested, we were so farre from being charged with declarations of Warre, as that we were laden with propositions, which could not choose but be welcome.</HI> But because we have formerly enlarged upon this point in the Letter which we wrote from <HI>Hamborrow;</HI> we believe we may conclude, that his <HI>Electorall Highness intention being good, pious, and glorious;</HI> and the Embassie well ordered and consented unto; doubtless, no body will stick to a∣vouch, <HI>That the King by his so evill intreating us, and by not r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣garding us as he ought to have done, hath violated the peace, and hath too rashly rejected our amity.</HI></P>
<P>For in case the King reflected upon the Teaty which the E∣lector made with <HI>Poland;</HI> why did he not regard us as <HI>Am∣bassadours from an Elector of the Empire?</HI> since you your selves would be otherwise considered <HI>then Swedes,</HI> and otherwise then <HI>Princes of the Empire; and that in Sweden you would be Enemies, but in the Empire friends to the King of Poland?</HI> If he knew the E∣lector was his Enemy, why did he desire him to send his Am∣bassadours? why did he receive them? and why did he treat them civily? and if he received them, <HI>why did he refuse them audience?</HI> so wise a King as himself, ought either not to have received them, or having received them, ought not to have denied them audience, unless he will assume that authority to himself <HI>to abuse the Princes of the Empire, by rejecting and driving away the Ambassadours,</HI> however we are loath to be∣lieve so much of him.</P>
<P>You alledge it is true, <HI>that the dignity of the Common-wealth permits not an audience to be given to the Ambassadours of an Enemy in the Senate.</HI> But how can you believe that the Elector was the Enemy? since he laboured in <HI>Prussia,</HI> towards the procuring of an Agreement, even with your consents; and that he rather endeavoured Peace then Warre, and how can you convince him of the least hostilities in the Empire, un∣less you conceit you build them upon imaginary apprehen∣sions;
<PB N="56" REF="30"/>or upon the uncertain reports which are spread a∣broade, against which there are other remedies then force and violence; Time would have taught you the one, and the divine providence accompanied by an innocent precauti∣on, would have cured you of the other.</P>
<P>But suppose the Elector had declared himself against you that could not justifie you neither; For the example of seve∣rall Pagans would have taught you, <HI>that there is nothing ought to hinder the hearing of an Ambassadour,</HI> no not from declared Enemies: were it but to let the world see, <HI>that you only wage Warre to obtaine Peace.</HI> The first Christians would have made a scruple of conscience to have done otherwise; But to desire a Prince to send his Ambassadours, to make much of them, to receive them at Court, and afterwards to send them away again, refusing them audience; is a thing not only un∣heard of, but against all piety, against the publick faith, and against the Law of Nations.</P>
<P>We marvell that you endeavour to excuse this reproach by the Maxime, <HI>That the Law of Nations and former customes, per∣mit the receiving of Ambassadours, according unto the dignity of the Prince which sends them; and in relation unto the nature of the buisness whereon they are to Treat;</HI> all which is just as much as nothing; For that is only to be understood, as to the cere∣monies and exterior honours which are usually done to the persons of Ambassadours; which is not our dispute: we are agreed as to the ceremonies; insomuch as that if you would deliberate, whether you should receive the Embassie or no, whether the Elector should be considered as a declared Ene∣my, or as a suspected Prince, who was ready to Arme against you; that you might have done at least, if you could have con∣ceived us to have been such, before your having approved of our Embassie, by your receiving of us. We do not deny, but that sometimes Ambassadours may be refused to be recei∣ved; but to deny those Ambassadours audience, who have been received, this we deny expresly; and do judg it the more extravagant, since in things of so high an importance, Sovereigns cannot proceed with too much circumspection.</P>
<P>We likewise say, that it is an unheard of thing, to go about
<PB N="57" REF="30"/>to oblige an Ambassadour, who hath been received, and acknowledged as such, to declare the subject of his Embassie, and his secret Instructions, before he hath spoken with the par∣ty unto whom he is sent; and likewise to endeavour to force him to undergo a kinde of Interrogatory before Commissio∣ners, <HI>this is very impertinent.</HI></P>
<P>All men know that the Character of an Ambassadour, is most holy and inviolable between Princes and Soveraignes, and that from all ages, and amongst all people, they have been received with honour and respect, and that their persons are held in the more veneration, by reason they represent those Kings and Princes by whom they are sent. Now whether this be performed or no, by those manner of proceedings which you use, we desire you your selves (Gentlemen) to judge.</P>
<P>Truly we believe that there is not one amongst you, who would not be offended; if a friend having appointed you an houre to come and visit him, should let you stay in the Hall, and should send to know of you by a Foot-boy or some o∣ther of his donestick Servants, that thing which you would not disclose save unto himself; But there is great deale of dif∣ference between Princes and particuler Persons: wherefore we beseech you to consider, whether the most barborous Nations in the world would not be laughed at, should they undertake to examine those Ambassadours which are sent unto them, and require of them the subject of their Embassie; and consequently whether this kind of proceeding be not im∣pertinent, and insusportable, especially among such as pro∣fess civillity; and whether it be a thing to be endured, that the secret which an Ambassadour hath express Order to com∣municate to none save the Prince unto whom he is sent, should be extorted from him.</P>
<P>We should have derogated from that Character where∣withall our Prince had honoured us, had we been so ill ad∣vised, as not to have made a distinction betwixt the Prince and his Ministers: Truely Gentlemen, you shall hardly be able to perswade it us; and therefore we beseech you not to build too much upon the Maxime which you so often use,
<PB N="58" REF="31"/>and which makes you swerve so farre from the mark, <HI>th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the dignity of the Commonwealth permits not to hear Enemy Am∣bassadours in the Senate.</HI> This is no generall rule, nor ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you make use of that which was heretofore said only up on the accounts of those who came as Spies (and who would be heard without having asked audience) against us; who came upon the publick Faith, who were invited received, and honoured as Friends, and therefore ought not, nor could be gainsaid, nor put by, unless you did it purposely to offend us, wilfully to faile in the point of civillity, and mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> cruelly to outrage us.</P>
<P>But we have said too much hereon, the thing being so clear and manifest; <HI>The Lacedemonians, the Florentines, the Duk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of Nevers, and the Lord of Langey,</HI> have by their example shewn us what is to be done on the like occasions; to wit, <HI>rather to withdraw then to be affronted.</HI> Wherefore we shall only adde one word, that at the same time you treated <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> so ill, your Resident who was with the Electors person a <HI>Berlin,</HI> was there lodged and defrayed, was admitted to au∣dience as often as he pleased to demand the same, and re∣ceived all the other civilities which could be conferred upon a publick person.</P>
<P>We confesse we could not imagine what their designe should be, by these your two different manner of actings, and we had rather remit our selves thereon unto others, then to become too importunate, by an overcurious search∣ing thereinto; We desire not to penetrate into your reasons, and we will leave it to the discretion and liberty of others to give your proceedings the blame or praise they may deserve. But our Prince Elector, who doth nothing but what he would have all the world know; troubles himself not at all hereat; or in case he had remained there to hinder his Electo∣rall Highness from the declaring of himself; our Prince who only aspires after Peace, desired nothing so much as that e∣ven during the midst of the Wars.</P>
<P>We may easily believe, that you did it purposely to en∣tertain and amuse us, till such time as the affairs of <HI>Denmark</HI> being regulated, the King might have proceeded in another
<PB N="59" REF="31"/>manner with us. <HI>But our generous Prince</HI> vallues this not a straw, for having not at all offended the King, he needed not to apprehend any thing upon that account neither.</P>
<P>And if it be not in regard of what is before said, at least be pleased to tell us, why did the Lord <HI>Wolfsberg</HI> continue to re∣maine by your orders in our Court, and to be admitted to au∣dience at all times, whilst you refused it unto us at yours? Why do you go about to make the world believe, that the Elector hath declared himself against you, <HI>by treating with Poland,</HI> since even after the said Treaty, you have had your Ministers near to the Elector, and have lived in good amity with us? Our in∣nocence will not suffer us to suspect the faith of so great a King.</P>
<P>But if we be not deceived in the good opinion we had har∣boured of him, the ill treatment which we have newly re∣ceived, will not alarm his Electorall Highness, but only serve to confirme those advices, which have been given us from all sides; that it is not from this day you have a minde to quarrell us. That you have long since harboured that de∣sign which you do now disclose, and that the spoiles of <HI>Den∣marke</HI> will help you to bring forth that which you have been a hammering and hatching ever since the beginning of the War. That all your protestations of friendship, and acknow∣ledgments, have been but so many complements and flatter∣ings which your refined wits and shallow braines make use of to hide their unlimitted ambition by, untill such time as you shall be in a capacity to manifest it, without shame or feare; as it is usuall to those who seek glory otherwise then through the footsteps of virtue; to endeavour to render those guilty, whose Estates they could not possibly assaile, unless they made them profest Enemies.</P>
<P>You know how often you have spoken to us concerning <HI>Prussia,</HI> the <HI>Pillauw,</HI> and <HI>Pomerania;</HI> you know how great a trouble it was to you to disguise and cloake your insatiable covetuousness, even during our greatest friendship, as well as the troubles and cares which you have caused his Electorall Highness by your unjust and violent demands.</P>
<P>After all which, we cannot doubt but you must judg (Gen∣tlemen) that by your treating of us as you have done, you
<PB N="60" REF="32"/>have not done any good either for your selves, or for us; and that your King had done more prudently for the common good of affairs; <HI>If after his inviting of us, receiving and honour∣ing of us as friends, he had not turned us off, as Criminals, and sent us back as Enemies.</HI> You may easily judge, in case you have the least inclination for Peace; that we ought to have been heard, although you had taken us for common declared Enemies, and that since we were not so as yet, you ought thereby to have testified, that you had some respect at least to our friend∣ship. <HI>By giving audience to the Ambassadors of an Elector, you would have manifested that you had not any designe against the Em∣pire; and by admitting the Prince of Brandenburgs Ambassadours, that you had not yet stifled the resentments of an Allye by him, that you had not renounced the duties of Neighbourhood, and that you were still mindefull of what he hath done for you some years since.</HI></P>
<P>But since it seems it was not consistent with your pleasure; The Elector findes himself forced to say, that he is sorry to meet with so great an obstinacy, whether it proceeds from an animosity, from a neglect, or by reason of the passing pro∣sperous successes of your forces, and the flattering (though be∣guiling) hopes which you have thence received.</P>
<P>This his Electorall Highness hath commanded us to send you back, in answer to your troublesome and uncivill Let∣ters which you wrote unto us from <HI>Flensburg;</HI> and with so much the more quietness of mind, as he hopes to be able to rectifie yours; protesting, that he is so little moved at the in∣justice of your proceedings, as that he despiseth all whatsoever you shall be able to undertake against the confidence which he reposeth in the justice of his Cause, and to the prejudice of the repose of his conscience.</P>
<P>But to the end you may know his true intentions, he doth declare unto you; that having only taken up Armes with a regret, or against his will, and that having sided with your Party, only when your violence, and the very last necessity en∣forced him to joyn with you; His resolution is, most punctu∣ally and religiously to performe the promise he hath made to his Allies, <HI>and to imploy without any reservation at all, whatsoever God hath given him, in the procuring of the preservation of the Peace of the Empire.</HI></P>
<PB N="61" REF="32"/>
<P>That he wisheth you all prosperity in those things which you shall undertake with justice; insomuch, as that in case your King can resolve to come to a Peace, the Elector will la∣bourtherein with all his might, and will even give way, that it may be compassed in a manner at his charges.</P>
<P>But and if the King will not hearken to an accommodati∣on, his Electorall Highness doth protest, that he will make use of all the meanes which God, nature, the justice of his Cause, and the bublick faith will permit him to employ, for to endea∣vour to withstand and repell the violence which shall be of∣fered him.</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>Signed thus, Gentlemen,</SALUTE> <SIGNED>Your humble Servants, <HI>O.</HI> Barron of <HI>Suerin, D. Weiman,</HI></SIGNED>
<DATELINE>Dated from <HI>Collen</HI> on the <HI>Spreè,</HI> <DATE>the 14<SUP>th</SUP> of <HI>Aug.</HI> 1658.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

