<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Two terrible sea-fights: the first, between 35 sail of English and the Dutch fleet, near the Isle of VVight, on the 28 of October, 1652. The second, betwixt one of Parliaments Frigots, and two Dutch men of war near Pllmouth; [sic] with the event and success thereof: also, a relation of the ships and prizes that have been taken ou [sic] sides, since the beginning of the wars between England and Holland. Likewise, the tryal of six witches at Edenbourgh in Scotland; and the sentence denounc'd against them to be ty'd up by the thumbs, and to be burnt with lighted candles under the soles of their feet, and in their mouthes.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A95484</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing T3539</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason E679_4</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R206746</IDNO>



<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99865853</IDNO>


<AVAILABILITY><P>This text has been selected for inclusion in the EEBO-TCP: Navigations collection, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities. To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication ( http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95484)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166344)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 105:E679[4])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Two terrible sea-fights: the first, between 35 sail of English and the Dutch fleet, near the Isle of VVight, on the 28 of October, 1652. The second, betwixt one of Parliaments Frigots, and two Dutch men of war near Pllmouth; [sic] with the event and success thereof: also, a relation of the ships and prizes that have been taken ou [sic] sides, since the beginning of the wars between England and Holland. Likewise, the tryal of six witches at Edenbourgh in Scotland; and the sentence denounc'd against them to be ty'd up by the thumbs, and to be burnt with lighted candles under the soles of their feet, and in their mouthes.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>8 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>printed by R. VVood,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1652.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb. 2".</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2016-01-29.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM TYPE="topical term">Trials (Witchcraft) --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM TYPE="topical term">Anglo-Dutch War, 1652-1654 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM TYPE="geographic name">Great Britain --  History, Naval --  Stuarts, 1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2013-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2013-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Pas</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>John Pas</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2014-03</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A95484">
<STC T="W">T3539</STC>
<STC T="T">E679_4</STC>
<STC T="C">R206746</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99865853</BIBNO>
<VID>166344</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>Two terrible SEA-FIGHTS:</P>
<P>The First, Between 35 sail of English and the Dutch Fleet, near to the Isle of VVight, on the 28 of October, 1652.</P>
<P>The Second, Betwixt one of the Parliaments Frigots, and two Dutch Men of war near Pllmouth; with the event and success thereof: Also, a Relation of the Ships and Prizes that have been taken on both sides, since the beginning of the Wars be∣tween England and Holland.</P>
<P>Likewise, The Tryal of six Witches at Edenbourgh in Scotland; and the Sentence denounc'd against them to be ty'd up by the Thumbs, and to be burnt with lighted candles under the soles of their feet, and in their mouthes.</P>
<P>LONDON: Printed by R. VVOOD, 1652.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Copie of a Letter from Edenborough in Scotland, shewing the cruel and bloo∣dy proceedings of the Scottish Kirk, a∣gainst divers supposed Witches; And how they were sentenc'd to have their thumbes tied behind them, and to bee whipt by two Highlanders, and after∣wards they set lighted Candls under the soles of their feet, and in their mouthes, till they confessed themselves guilty of that which was laid to their charge.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">O</SEG>N Wednesday last, being the 20 instant, the English Commissioners for Admini∣stration of Justice, sate upon Criminal matters at Edenborough: The first day was spent in reading their Commission from the
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>Commissioners at Dalkeith, calling the Sheriffes of the se∣veral counties on this side of the Frith, and those that ap∣peared not were fined 200 l. Scotch each. Afterwards the Gentlemen of the several counties, who were to do their service, were called, and such as appeared not fined 100 li. Scotch; and then several Delinquents were called, and such set down for Tryal, and fining of several persons for A∣dultery, Incest, and Fornication, for which there were a∣bove 60 persons brought before the Judges in a day. And it is observable, That (such is the malice of these people) that most of them were accused for facts done divers years since, and the chief proof against them was their own con∣fession before the Kirk. One Ephraim Bennet (a Gunner in Lieth) was indicted, convicted, and condemned for co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ning of money; also two English men <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ondemned for killing one Scotch-man in March last. But that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> ob∣servable, is, that some were brought before <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣ches, wo whereof had been brought before the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the time of the Arm <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> coming into Scotland and having confest it were turned <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ver to the civil <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Court demanding how they came to be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. They declared, that they w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to do it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y the ex∣ceeding torture they were put to, which was by tying their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>humbs behind them, and then hanging them up by them whil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> two Highl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> whips them: after which they set lighted candles <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o the soles of their feet, and be∣tween their toes; then burned <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hem by putting lighted candles into their mouthes, and then burning them in the head: 6 were accused, and 4 died of the torture. The Jud∣ges are resolved to have an accompt of the ground of this cruelty. It is very probable there will shortly be more dis∣coveries of this kind of Amboyna usage; On Wednesday last the Marq. of Argyle came to Edenbourgh; and soon
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>after came the joyful tydings of the release of all our pri∣soners. Unto which may be added the happy success of our Navy at sea against the U<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llander, who have taken since the beginning of the Wars about 163, and the enemy have surprized of ours about 57 Colliers and others.</P>
<P>The Fleet of the States of Holland is not so forward, as it was thought it would be; It was said they would be re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣dy the 26 of this moneth (which is to morrow) but it is well if they get ready by the 26 of the next. It was noised a while there should be no lesse then one hundred and twelve men of war, but it will be hard if they set out but 70. for men are scarce and monies flow. There are about four hundred Merchant men to set forth for <HI>Spain, France, the Streights, India, Guinny, Turkey, and Portugal;</HI> and for these they intend to make way through the Channel with a strong convoy, which if they can, they will then think they have sufficiently vindicated their reputation to the world, that they can make way for their trade under your noses.</P>
<P>The Diet of the Empire is now at hand, to be kept at Reghensburgh; th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> King of Scots hath one Tailor with the Emperour to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his affairs; but things are not in such a posture, that he and the Princes can or ought in res∣pect of their own occasions, to interest themselves in his. Besides the Empire hath had a short breathing time of peace, having been long exhausted, and but little time to recruit and replenish; and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="murp" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t is thought their own affairs will take up no lesse then 3 years time to dispatch, and put them in order.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Edenburgh</HI> <DATE>28 <HI>October,</HI> 1652.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>The Copy of another Letter dated at Newcastle; certifying, that there are 100 sail of Colliers ready to put to sea, with the next Winde.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>SOme of the Dutch Free-boters (with whom this coast is very much pestered) have surpri∣sed four small Vessels (between Barwick and the Holy-Island) that were coming from Scotland: And meeting with a small Bark belonging to Scar∣borough homeward bound, chased her a whole fore-noon, and at last forced her to run ashore near Flamborough head, where the Countrey people coming to her rescue, the Skellums were forced to leave her. Here is about a hundred of lusty Colli∣ers, and a very strong convoy to conduct them, lye all ready at the mouth of the River, and onely wait for a fair gale of winde, to speed them to their wished Port. There came in here lately a small Ves∣sel from Yarmouth, by which we understand that some of the Hollanders made an appearance upon that coast, and chased two small Vessels into Soale Bay, but upon sight of some of our men of warre,
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>they tacked about, and now those parts are very cleer of them.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Newcastle,</HI> <DATE><HI>Octob.</HI> 28. 1652.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<HEAD>The Copy of a Letter from Plimouth, concerning the Engagement of the En∣glish and Dutch Fleets between the Isle of VVight and Portland.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>ONe of our Frigots (scouting out) met with two Flemish men of warre, with whom she maintained a very desperate fight for the space of two hours, in which time she so shatter'd their tac∣kle that the Butterboxes declined Engagement, and night approaching our men could not follow the pursuit, but in their return to the Fleet, they took a Dutchman laden with Wine and strongwater, and a Frenchman laden with salt. It was reported here by the Owner of a Hive which came from Fal∣mouth, that on Thursday the eight and twenty of October, about thirty of the Parliaments ships be∣longing
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>to General Blake, were engaged with the Dutch Fleet, and that there had been a very fierce and bloudy Fight between them near to the Isle of Wight, but what was the Event or success thereof he could not resolve, they being said to be engaged at his coming from thence; therefore I shall wave the further relation hereof till further confirmation; Onely this I can assure you (for I have it from very good hands) that on the fourteenth instant, there was a very considerable Fleet of Hollanders descri∣ed to pass by Falmouth, which (as they supposed) was bound for the Straits; and that one of our men of War lighted on one of their straglers (a very rich ship) and brought her into Falmouth. Thus desi∣ring you to take this in good part, and excuse me for being no larger; for though I am willing to serve you with intelligence, yet I would not be ac∣counted a broacher of falsities, or publisher of un∣truths. 'Thus in haste I rest.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Plymouth,</HI> <DATE><HI>Octob.</HI> 26.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

