<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2008-12-15</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Check for blanks. Checked for signatures. Checked for #s. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Corrected 21 $-groups. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N05805">
<STC T="E">7373</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99020152</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="half title">
<PB REF="007373_0000_102B8B7D9A586E38"/>
<PB REF="007373_0001_102B8B7F337C3CA0"/>
<P>Mr. <HI>BURR</HI>'s DISCOURSE, <HI>&amp;c. January</HI> 1, 1755.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="007373_0002_102B8B81713D8B88" MS="y"/>
<P>A DISCOURSE DELIVERED At <HI>NEW-ARK,</HI> IN <HI>NEW-JERSEY.</HI> JANUARY 1, 1755. Being a Day set apart for <HI>solemn Fasting</HI> and <HI>Prayer,</HI> on Account of the late Encroachments of the <HI>French,</HI> and their Designs against the <HI>British</HI> Colonies in AMERICA.</P>
<P><HI>By</HI> AARON BURR, <HI>A. M. President of the</HI> COLLEGE <HI>of</HI> NEW-JERSEY.</P>
<Q><P>O Lord, what shall I say, when Israel turneth their Backs before their Enemies.</P>
<BIBL><HI>Jos. vii. 8.</HI></BIBL></Q>
<Q><P>And the Lord said unto Joshua, fear not, neither be thou dismayed; take all the People of War with thee, and arise, and go up to <HI>Ai,</HI></P>
<BIBL><HI>Jos. viii. 1.</HI></BIBL></Q>
<P><HI>NEW-YORK:</HI> Printed and Sold by HUGH GAINE, at the Printing Office in <HI>Queen-Street,</HI> between the <HI>Fly</HI> and <HI>Meal-Market,</HI> M,DCCLV. [<HI>Price,</HI> ONE SHILLING, AND THREE COPPERS.]</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="preface">
<PB N="iij" REF="007373_0003_102B8B84040CB288"/>
<HEAD>THE PREFACE.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>HE Substance of what is here offer∣ed to the Public, was the Ap∣plication of a Sermon, preach'd in the former Part of the Day, from <HI>Hosea</HI> ix. 12. <HI>Woe also to them, when I depart from them;</HI> which is suppressed, lest it should swell the Pamphlet too much, and the Dis∣course thrown into such a Form, as to have no necessary Dependance upon it.</P>
<P>MY constant Hurry of Business, made it doubtful for some Time, whether, or not, I should comply with the Importunity of those Friends who requested this Publication: Which is the Reason why it was delayed.</P>
<P>BUT, when, on farther Reflection, I tho't it might be a Means of awakening in my Countrymen, some Sense of their Danger, and
<PB N="iv" REF="007373_0004_102B8B8631A53698"/>Duty, in this dark and critical Day, I readily consented.</P>
<P>FOR tho' this has been, and no doubt will still be done in a better Manner, by those who have more Leisure, and a further Acquaintance with our political Affairs; yet, as it appear'd of Importance, that these Things should be set in various Lights, and made as public as possible at such a Season, when so much depends on our being una∣nimously alarm'd, to the Defence of our Lives and Properties; I chearfully offer this Mite, such as it is, to the Abundance others are doing, towards saving their Country from impending Ruin.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="5" REF="007373_0005_102B8B888782E1D0"/>
<HEAD>A DISCOURSE, &amp;<HI>c.</HI></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>E have this Day, <HI>My Brethren, sanctified a Fast, called a solemn Assembly,</HI> to humble ourselves before God, for the crying Sins of the Times; to deprecate impending Judg∣ments, and implore Direction and Assistance from Heaven, against our <HI>Enemies,</HI> who, by their <HI>unrigh∣teous Encroachments,</HI> on our Properties, and the <HI>Preparations</HI> they are making against us, seem to threaten the Ruin of our Country.</P>
<P>I PRESUME, it will not be thought unsuitable to the Occasion, to give you some historical and political Account, of the <HI>Power</HI> and <HI>Policy</HI> of our Enemies, and their wicked Designs against us; that we may have a proper Sense of our Danger, and be excited to our Duty, in the present <HI>critical Juncture.</HI> To this Purpose, it will be proper we should look back to the Source and Spring of our present Troubles; which are well known to be the <HI>boundless Ambition</HI> of the late Kings of <HI>France,</HI> and their insatiable <HI>Thirst</HI> after arbitrary Power, and universal Monarchy.</P>
<P>WHOEVER considers, that <HI>France,</HI> from a small and inconsiderable Kingdom, in a few Centuries, is become one of the most numerous and powerful in Europe, and by what <HI>arbitrary</HI> and <HI>unrighteous</HI> Methods, her Dominions have been extended; will be convinc'd, that all Encroach∣ments
<PB N="6" REF="007373_0006_102B8B8A6581A388"/>from such a dangerous Enemy, should be guarded against, with the utmost Precaution.</P>
<P>IN King HENRY the VIth's Time, the <HI>English</HI> possessed a great Part of their present Dominions
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Normandy, Picardy, Champaine,</HI> and the <HI>Isle of France.</HI></NOTE>, and even <HI>Paris,</HI> the Metropolis, where he was crowned
<NOTE N="§" PLACE="foot">1431.</NOTE>. Their Territories since that Time, have been vastly enlarged, and very much at the Expence of the <HI>just Rights</HI> of their Neighbours; especially by the present <HI>reigning Family,</HI> who are known by the Name of the House of <HI>Bourbon.</HI>—The first indeed of this Race, <HI>Henry</HI> IVth, who came to the Throne 1589, while a Protestant, discovered a very different Spirit, from his degenerate Offspring.—Tho', from Reasons of State, he was induced to declare himself a <HI>Roman Catholick,</HI> yet he had so great a Regard to Justice and Gratitude, as to establish the famous <HI>Edict of</HI> Nantz
<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">So called, because published in that City, 1598.</NOTE>, in Favour of the <HI>Protestants,</HI> who had advanced him to the Throne. This has done more Honour to his Memory, than all the warlike Exploits, whereby he acquir'd the Name of GREAT. But his Successors and Posterity, the <HI>Lewis</HI>'s, have, for above one Hundred Years past, been the <HI>Plague</HI> and <HI>Scourge</HI> of <HI>Europe,</HI> and rendered their Reigns infamous, by persecuting the Protestants, in Violation of the most <HI>solemn Engagements;</HI> whom <HI>Lewis</HI> the XIVth, in a Letter to <HI>Cromwel,</HI> acknowledged, were some of the best and most peaceable Subjects he had.</P>
<P>THE <HI>Scheme</HI> for absolute Power, and universal Monarchy, was concerted, in the Minority of <HI>Lewis</HI> the XIIIth
<NOTE N="‡" PLACE="foot">He succeeded his Father, 1610, at about 9 Years of Age.</NOTE>, by that haughty and aspiring Minister, Cardinal <HI>Richlieu.</HI> By Bribes and Force, depriving the Parliament of <HI>Paris</HI> of their Privileges, he endeavoured by every Stratagem, to render the <HI>King</HI> absolute, and to enslave the Subject; envying the <HI>Protestants</HI> the Privileges granted them by <HI>Henry</HI> IVth, he raised a severe Persecution against them; took away all the Places given as a Security, that the <HI>Edict of</HI> Nantz should be observed; the last and most
<PB N="7" REF="007373_0007_102B8B8BF2E3F058"/>important of which, <HI>viz. Rochelle,</HI> (being shamefully forsaken by King <HI>Charles</HI> the Ist. notwithstanding repeated Assurances of Assistance) after a terrible Siege of <HI>two</HI> Years, surrendered <HI>October</HI> 8th, 1628. Here we may date the Beginning of <HI>arbitrary Power,</HI> in <HI>France.</HI> In this Reign also, her Territories were considerably enlarged, and the Foundation of her future <HI>Greatness</HI> and <HI>tyrannizing</HI> over her Neighbours, was then laid.</P>
<P>LEWIS XIVth, being in the 5th Year of his Age, at the Death of his Father, 1643, <HI>Cardinal Mazarine</HI> (equally noted for his Pride and Covetousness) was admitted into the Administration, who effectually prosecuted the <HI>Plan</HI> laid by his Predecessor; rendered the Crown wholly absolute; bereft the Subjects of the little Remains of Liberty; and upon them, and their Posterity, rivetted the Chains of an abject <HI>Slavery.</HI></P>
<P>IN the Beginning of his Administration, <HI>France</HI> made herself dreaded among her Neighbours, by a Series of Victories obtained in <HI>Flanders,</HI> against <HI>Spain,</HI> under the celebrated <HI>Prince of Conde,</HI> at a prodigious Expence of Blood. Tho', in the End, very little Advantage was derived from them, yet they served to show how little Regard was had to the <HI>Lives</HI> of their Fellow-Creatures. Soon after, indeed, his proud Designs, of extending the <HI>French</HI> Dominions, were, for a While obstructed, by the civil Broils and intestine Wars, which, at that Time, prevailed in the Nation: They also met with an effectual <HI>Check,</HI> for a Season, by the Valour of the <HI>English,</HI> under <HI>Cromwel,</HI> when Disputes with <HI>France</HI> were easily and speedily settled, without any Bloodshed. Witness, that haughty Minister's being obliged, by a <HI>single Message,</HI> contrary to his Intentions, to deliver up <HI>Dunkirk</HI> to the <HI>English</HI> Ambassador
<NOTE N="§" PLACE="foot">Delivered to <HI>Lockhart,</HI> 1659.</NOTE>; and to stop the <HI>Duke of Savoy</HI> from persecuting the <HI>Protestants,</HI> tho' he pretended it was not within his Jurisdiction. But, notwithstanding the Confusion of a Civil War, at the celebrated Treaty of
<PB N="8" REF="007373_0008_102B8B8E48615ED8"/><HI>Westphalia,</HI> he had the Art and Policy to secure the Sove∣reignty of <HI>Alsace,</HI> and some Parts of <HI>Lorrain,</HI> to the Crown of <HI>France.</HI></P>
<P>No sooner had <HI>Lewis</HI> XIVth taken the Reins of Go∣vernment into his own Hands, than he acts the <HI>Tyrant</HI> over his own People, and discovers his <HI>ambitious Designs</HI> of enslaving the Rest of <HI>Europe.</HI> Finding no better Pretence for falling on his Neighbours, he lays claim to <HI>Flanders,</HI> and <HI>Franché-Comté,</HI> by his Wife <HI>(Maria Theresia</HI> of <HI>Spain)</HI> tho' she had expressly renounced all claim to it, on her Marriage; <HI>which,</HI> by a Series of <HI>bloody Battles</HI> and <HI>Sieges,</HI> at the Expence of Millions of <HI>Lives,</HI> he subdued: Tho' he was obliged to resign the latter; yet, at the Treaty of <HI>Aix-la-Chapelle</HI>
<NOTE N="§" PLACE="foot">1668.</NOTE>, he got confirmed to the Crown of <HI>France,</HI> almost all the Places he had taken in <HI>Flanders.</HI></P>
<P>IN 1672, without the least plausible Pretence for War, he makes the most formidable Preparations, to subdue the <HI>United Netherlands,</HI> and wholly to extirpate the <HI>Dutch Common-Wealth.</HI> The <HI>States General,</HI> in a very submissive Manner, requested that his Majesty would let them know, if those <HI>mighty Preparations</HI> were designed against them: To whom that <HI>haughty Monarch</HI> made no other Reply, but, <Q>That he should employ his Troops in such a Manner, as his Dignity deserved, which did not require him to give an Account to any one.</Q></P>
<P>ALL the Places that lay in his Way, fell an easy Prey to his victorious Arms. The Provinces of <HI>Utrecht, Overissel,</HI> and <HI>Guelders,</HI> with all the adjacent Places, being subdued, <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> the <HI>Metropolis,</HI> was just on the Point of being surrendered. So near and evident did their Ruin appear, that the most noted Families, who were fond of their <HI>Liberties,</HI> had actually prepared for a Remove to the <HI>East-Indies;</HI> chusing rather to live in the <HI>Extremities</HI> of the <HI>Earth,</HI> than become the <HI>Slaves</HI> of a <HI>Tyrant.</HI> But divine Providence prevented their total Overthrow, which seemed inevitable, by sundry favourable Interpositions. Heaven
<PB N="9" REF="007373_0009_102B844E34823AF0"/>rais'd up at that Time, the <HI>great Hero</HI> of his Day, <HI>King</HI> WILLIAM, then <HI>Prince of Orange,</HI> who, by his singular Wisdom and Valour, put a Stop to that <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> which seemed to threaten all <HI>Europe.</HI> In these wicked and ambi∣tious Designs, of destroying the <HI>Dutch,</HI> and enslaving Mankind, to the Amazement of all <HI>Europe,</HI> he was assisted by King <HI>Charles</HI> the IId, who, as <HI>Voltaire</HI> justly observes, "was active in nothing, but his Pleasures;" unless, as he might have added, in persecuting his own Subjects, and promoting the <HI>Grandeur</HI> and <HI>Power</HI> of <HI>France,</HI> which it was so evidently the Interest of <HI>England</HI> to humble. To support the Expence of his extravagant Pleasures, and this <HI>unnatural War</HI> with the <HI>Dutch,</HI> which in scandalous Violation of publick Faith, he had undertaken, he sold those very important Places, <HI>Dunkirk</HI> and <HI>Mardyke,</HI> to the King of <HI>France</HI>
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">1662.</NOTE>; <Q>at a Price, <HI>says the above mentioned Author,</HI> glorious to the Purchaser, and shameful to the Seller:</Q> And to compleat the Scandal of that debauched and effeminate Reign, soon after added <HI>Nova-Scotia</HI>
<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">1667.</NOTE>.</P>
<P>THE King of <HI>France,</HI> altho' obliged to quit most of his Conquests in the <HI>Netherlands,</HI> yet at the Treaty of
<NOTE N="‡" PLACE="foot">1678.</NOTE> <HI>Nemiguen,</HI> acted like the <HI>Arbiter</HI> of <HI>Europe,</HI> and had confirmed to his Dominions, several advantageous Places
<NOTE N="§" PLACE="foot">The Country of <HI>Burgundy, Valenciennes, Cambray</HI> and <HI>Ypress.</HI></NOTE>. The barbarous Orders he gave, for <HI>reducing to Ashes,</HI> that sine large Country the <HI>Palatinate</HI>
<NOTE N="‖" PLACE="foot">There were about fifty Castles, many well built Towns and Villages, in it.</NOTE>, showed his Cruelty to be equal to his Ambition. The wretched People drove off in the dead of Winter
<NOTE PLACE="foot" N="¶">February 1689.</NOTE>; their Houses, and their very Graves ransack'd by merciless Soldiers, afforded such a tragical Scene, that even a <HI>French</HI> Author, who labours to set all his Conduct in the most favourable Light, says, "all Europe look'd upon it with Horror;" and that those who hitherto only blamed, while they admired his Ambi∣tion, now exclaimed aloud against his Barbarity.</P>
<P><PB N="10" REF="007373_0010_102B8B90A6F2FA50"/>
THE King of <HI>Spain</HI>'s
<NOTE PLACE="foot" N="¶">1700.</NOTE> dying childless, and leaving his Dominions, by Will, to the <HI>Duke</HI> of <HI>Anjou,</HI> Grandson to <HI>Lewis</HI> XIVth, gave a new Specimen of his <HI>Treachery,</HI> and <HI>boundless Ambition.</HI> Some of the Powers of <HI>Europe,</HI> being sensible of the Danger that would arise from the Union of two such <HI>powerful Monarchies,</HI> entered into what is known by the Name of the <HI>Partition Treaty</HI>
<NOTE N="|" PLACE="foot">August <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, 1698.</NOTE>. To this the King of <HI>France</HI> acceded, with pompous Expressions of his Desire to preserve the <HI>Peace</HI> of <HI>Europe,</HI> declaring that a <HI>Will,</HI> from the King of <HI>Spain,</HI> in Favour of his <HI>Family,</HI> should not alter him. But his own, and his Father's <HI>solemn Renunciations,</HI> (on their Marriages) his <HI>public Faith</HI> twice given, appeared to him as <HI>solemn Trifles,</HI> when a new Opportunity presented, of <HI>aggrandizing</HI> his Family. Immediately on the Death of <HI>Charles,</HI> he accepts the <HI>Will,</HI> seizes the <HI>Kingdom of Spain,</HI> in Right of his Grandson, tho' advised against it, by one of his principal Ministers, as what might involve him in a bloody and expensive War; but the Prospect of so greatly increasing his <HI>Grandeur</HI> and <HI>Power,</HI> had too many Charms to be resisted. The Execu∣tion of his <HI>ambitious</HI> Designs, was for some Time prevented, by the Grand Alliance
<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">This was made by the Union of the Emperor, Great-Britain, the Dutch, and the King of Sardinia.</NOTE> formed by King <HI>William.</HI> Surpri∣zingly successful were the Consequences of that <HI>Confederacy,</HI> in the succeeding Reign of Queen <HI>Anne.</HI> That renowned General, the Duke of MARLBOROUGH, by his Valour, and good Conduct, almost reduced <HI>France</HI> to the last Extremity; and had he been continued, might, the next Campaign, have carried his Arms to the Gates of <HI>Paris;</HI> dictated Terms of Submission to that <HI>baughty Monarch,</HI> and so prevented the sad Calamities of the last War, and the Grounds of our pre∣sent melancholly Apprehensions. But the <HI>Queen,</HI> under the Influence of <HI>wicked Counsellors,</HI> taking an unhappy Turn, at the Close of her Reign, discarded one of the <HI>bravest Generals</HI> the <HI>English</HI> ever had; turned out a wise, faithful, and truly patriot Ministry, and put in a Set of <HI>mercenary</HI>
<PB N="11" REF="007373_0011_102B8B92F848F368"/>and <HI>treackercus Men,</HI> who miserably betrayed her, and sacrificed to Gain, the <HI>Honour</HI> and <HI>Interest</HI> of their <HI>Country;</HI> shamefully abandoned their <HI>Allies,</HI> and patched up a separate Peace with <HI>France</HI>
<NOTE PLACE="foot" N="¶">At Utrecht, 1713.</NOTE>, on Terms the most scanda∣lous, and disadvantageous. To behold the Manner in which <HI>England,</HI> after all her glorious Conquests, accepted Conditions of Peace, from a <HI>vanquished</HI> Tyrant, 'tis hard to say, whether among our Neighbours, it created more <HI>Mirth</HI> or <HI>Contempt.</HI> To hear the <HI>King</HI> of <HI>France,</HI> talk of acknowledging the <HI>Queen's Title;</HI>—insisting on an equiva∣lent for <HI>Dunkirk;</HI>—demanding and receiving <HI>Cape-Breton</HI> as an Equivalent for <HI>Newfoundland,</HI> with many Hardships on our Trade;—and to see the <HI>Pretender</HI> banish'd no far∣ther than <HI>Lorrain,</HI> was Matter of Astonishment to all who knew that he had been a little before humbly suing for Peace, and that it was in our Power to have prescribed to him what Terms we pleased.</P>
<Q><L>—<HI>Quid non mortalia Pectora cogis</HI></L>
<L><HI>Auri sacra Fames?</HI></L></Q>
<P>THE sad Effects of the treacherous Conduct of <HI>that Ministry,</HI> we groan under to this Day; and had not the sudden Death of the <HI>Queen,</HI> and Accession of King GEORGE the Ist, to the Throne, prevented, should have felt it in a very different Manner. For, as <HI>Voltaire</HI> says, (who cannot be suspected of Prejudice against them, since he endeavours to justify that <HI>scandalous Peace</HI> they made) <Q>It is certain, that the new Ministry of Queen ANNE, had secretly formed a Scheme for establishing the Son of <HI>James</HI> IId, on the Throne. Queen <HI>Anne</HI> herself, influenced by her Ministers, began to listen to the Voice of Nature, and entered into the Design, of settling the Succession on her Brother, whom she had proscribed against her Inclination.</Q> And indeed this has appeared beyond all Contradiction, by a Letter of <HI>Lord Bolinbroke</HI>'s, lately published.</P>
<P><PB N="12" REF="007373_0012_102B8B94D6B412A0"/>
THE <HI>Duke of Burgundy,</HI> Great Grandson to <HI>Lewis</HI> XIVth, succeeding to the Throne on his Death
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">1715.</NOTE>, when a Minor of about five Years old, the <HI>Duke of Orleans</HI> was appointed Regent of the Kingdom, under whose Administration <HI>Europe</HI> enjoyed a little Respite from the <HI>Treachery</HI> and <HI>Ambition</HI> of <HI>France.</HI> But, as soon as the present King <HI>Lewis</HI> XVth, was capable of taking the Government into his own Hands, he discovered the same <HI>aspiring Spirit and Thirst</HI> after <HI>universal Power,</HI> for which his Predecessor was so remarkable.</P>
<P>'TIS still fresh in our Memory, what <HI>Wars</HI> and <HI>Tumults</HI> he raised in <HI>Europe</HI> 1733, under a Pretence of revenging the Affront he received, by the Rejection of his Father-in-Law <HI>Stanislaus,</HI> from being <HI>King of Poland,</HI> and Choice of the <HI>Elector of Saxony</HI> in his Room. Tho' the <HI>Russian Army</HI> was the principal Cause of this, he takes no Notice of them, but instigates the <HI>King of Spain</HI> and <HI>Sardinia,</HI> to join him, in falling on the <HI>Emperor</HI> CHARLES VIth;—takes away his Dominions in <HI>Italy;</HI>—procures the <HI>two Sicilies</HI> for the <HI>King of Spain's second Son, Don Charlos,</HI> a Branch of the House of <HI>Bourbon;</HI>—and gets the Dutchies of <HI>Barrois</HI> and <HI>Lorrain,</HI> annexed to the <HI>Crown of France.</HI> To this, more by his Policy, than his <HI>Power,</HI> he persuaded the <HI>Emperor</HI> and <HI>Duke of Lorrain,</HI> to consent, upon a solemn Engagement, that he would join the <HI>King of Prussia,</HI> and other Powers of <HI>Europe,</HI> in guaranteeing what is called the <HI>pragmatic Sanction;</HI> by which all the hereditary Dominions of the late <HI>Emperor,</HI> were secured to his <HI>eldest Daughter</HI>
<NOTE N="‡" PLACE="foot"><HI>Maria Theresia</HI> married to <HI>Francis Stephen,</HI> Duke of <HI>Lorrain,</HI> afterwards Grand Duke of <HI>Tuscany,</HI> now Emperor of <HI>German.</HI></NOTE>. But in <HI>open Violation</HI> of his publick Faith, as soon as she had succeeded to the hereditary Dominions of the <HI>House of Austria,</HI> on the Death of her Father
<NOTE N="§" PLACE="foot">1740.</NOTE>, he joins the <HI>King of Prussia,</HI> in taking away <HI>Silesia</HI> and <HI>Bohemia;</HI> got the <HI>Duke of Eavaria</HI> chosen <HI>Emperor;</HI> carried his Arms even to the Gates of <HI>Vienna,</HI> and would have stripped <HI>that Lady</HI>
<PB N="13" REF="007373_0013_102B8B966841B5B8"/>of the greater Part, if not all, her Dominions, had not Providence interposed, and given a new Turn to the Affairs of <HI>Europe,</HI> by the Death of the <HI>Duke of Bavaria,</HI> and <HI>King</HI> GEORGE the IId coming seasonably to her Relief: whose Example <HI>Holland, Sardinia,</HI> and even <HI>Russia,</HI> soon after followed. This put a Stop to the aspiring Views of <HI>France,</HI> raised the <HI>Queen of Hungary</HI> from the Brink of Ruin to which she was reduced, and by the Election of her Husband, to the Head of the Empire
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">September 1745.</NOTE>, restored to her Family, the Imperial Dignity. The Assistance his Majesty afforded the House of <HI>Austria,</HI> in Faithfulness to his Engagement, of guaranteeing the <HI>Pragmatic Sanction,</HI> which the <HI>King of France</HI> had so perfi∣diously violated, provoked him to declare War against us
<NOTE N="§" PLACE="foot">March 4th, 1744.</NOTE>, when we had been already for some Years engaged in one with <HI>Spain.</HI> The repeated <HI>Insults</HI> and <HI>Injuries</HI> we received from <HI>that Nation,</HI> in which they have been always aided and countenanced by <HI>France;</HI> their searching and plun∣dering our Ships in the <HI>West-Indies;</HI> seizing the Effects of our <HI>South-Sea-Company,</HI> &amp;c. after much Patience, and many fruitless Complaints, obliged us to declare War against them
<NOTE N="|" PLACE="foot">October 1739.</NOTE>, and we should easily have brought them to Terms, and got Restitution for the many <HI>Abuses</HI> we received, had not <HI>France</HI> come to their Assistance, which put us under a Necessity of maintaining the War against <HI>both Nations,</HI> for many Years. I need not acquaint you, with the various Success, and Event of that <HI>dangerous</HI> and <HI>expensive War;</HI> 'tis fresh in every one's Mind; and how little to the <HI>Credit</HI> and <HI>Interest</HI> of our Nation, it ended, is no Secret. It is true, we gained some Advantages <HI>by Sea,</HI> and were signally smiled upon, in taking <HI>Cape-Breton,</HI> an Acquisition which will be celebrated by Posterity, to the lasting Honour of <HI>New-England!</HI> Had it continued in our Possession, such is its <HI>Situation,</HI> and <HI>Strength,</HI> that it would have been an <HI>unspeakable Loss</HI> to the <HI>French,</HI> and a <HI>vast Security</HI> to us, against any <HI>future Insults</HI> from them.
<PB N="14" REF="007373_0014_102B8B9828147B98"/>Was that <HI>Key</HI> of their Part of <HI>America,</HI> yet in our Hands, it would not be in their Power, to give us <HI>new Troubles</HI> at this Day. But the <HI>King of France</HI> carried all before him in <HI>Flanders;</HI> was every where victorious over the <HI>Allied Army,</HI> far inferior to his own in Number. This Superiority was much increased, by the <HI>Duke</HI>'s being oblig'd to withdraw his Forces, for the Nation's Defence, against a <HI>dangerous Rebellion,</HI> formed in Favour of the <HI>Pretender</HI>
<NOTE N="|" PLACE="foot">1743.</NOTE>, so that at the Treaty of <HI>Aix-la-Chapelle</HI>
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">1748.</NOTE>, we were forced to deliver up that <HI>important Fortress</HI> and <HI>Harbour,</HI> for the Return of those Places he had taken in <HI>Flanders,</HI> to the <HI>Queen of Hungary.</HI> The giving up his Conquests at this Place, <HI>Voltaire</HI> mentions, as a most <HI>unexpected and unparal∣lelled Instance of Moderation, in the King of</HI> France. I confess, if there had been any Moderation in it, it would have been <HI>unexpected,</HI> and <HI>unparallelled,</HI> in a <HI>French</HI> King; but had he considered the vast Importance of <HI>Cape-Breton,</HI> to <HI>France,</HI> he would have seen, it was <HI>Necessity,</HI> not <HI>Mo∣deration,</HI> that induced him to quit his Acquisitions. Thus after a great Expence, increasing the national Debt to above 70,000,000, with the Loss of a Multitude of Lives; <HI>France</HI> and <HI>Spain,</HI> were left in the Possession of all their former Territories. <Q>FRANCE, <HI>says the above mentioned Writer,</HI> at the Peace, was re-established on the same Footing, as at that of <HI>Utrecht,</HI> and became more flourishing;</Q> consequently more dangerous.</P>
<P>THE <HI>House of Bourbon,</HI> the present reigning Family, is now arrived to a very high Pitch of <HI>Grandeur</HI> and <HI>Power,</HI> being in Possession of <HI>France, Spain, Italy, Sicily,</HI> and <HI>Naples,</HI> together with large Dominions in <HI>America;</HI> and they are so connected together, that it is highly probable, they would join against any other Power in <HI>Europe.</HI> I know that Alliances by Blood and Marriage, signify little with the Princes of this World, unless, as is the Case with <HI>France</HI> and <HI>Spain,</HI> they are united in Interest too: I may add also, in the same ambitious Design of aggrandizing
<PB N="15" REF="007373_0015_102B8B9A0AE3C3F8"/>their Family. And what makes them the more to be dreaded, is the Prospect, that the <HI>King of Prussia</HI> may join them on a new Rupture, who, seems at present, to hold the <HI>Ballance of Europe,</HI> in his Hands; and is supposed to have no less than 150,000 well disciplined Troops at Com∣mand.</P>
<P>SINCE the Revolution, <HI>Great-Britain</HI> has been the principal Means of restraining the <HI>lawless Ambition</HI> of <HI>France,</HI> and preventing her farther <HI>unrighteous Encroach∣ments,</HI> on her Neighbours: It may therefore be expected, that every <HI>Scheme</HI> which their <HI>Policy</HI> can invent, or <HI>Perfidy</HI> execute, will be attempted to weaken and destroy us.</P>
<P>WE are well assured, that <HI>Lewis</HI> XIVth, made repeated Efforts, to restore King <HI>James;</HI> and at his Death, declared his pretended Son, <HI>King of England,</HI> contrary to his solemn Engagement, at the <HI>Treaty of Ryswic</HI>
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">1697.</NOTE>: And indeed <HI>France</HI> has, at the Expence of her <HI>public Faith,</HI> from Time to Time, secretly countenanced, and encouraged the <HI>Pre∣tender;</HI> even in Times of Peace, keeping up the Spirit of the <HI>jacobitish Party,</HI> who are madly bent upon <HI>enslaving</HI> themselves and their Country; and stands always ready at any favourable Juncture, openly to assist him.</P>
<P>JUST before the breaking out of the last War, <HI>the King of France</HI> fitted out a Fleet at <HI>Dunkirk,</HI> with 16,000 Troops to invade <HI>England,</HI> in Favour of the <HI>Pretender;</HI> and had not Providence rais'd a Storm, which prevented their Land∣ing, just as they were on our Coasts, it is not improbable they might have accomplished their <HI>wicked Design,</HI> as the <HI>Nation</HI> was at that Time, unconcerned about, and unpre∣pared for, such an Event. 'Tis hard to say, whether such a <HI>perfidious Enemy</HI> is most to be dreaded, in <HI>War</HI> or <HI>Peace.</HI> Certain, however, it is, that Experience teaches us the Necessity of keeping a watchful Eye upon him, at <HI>all</HI> Times; and of what Importance it is, that we should en∣deavour to crush his <HI>pernicious Schemes</HI> in the <HI>Bud.</HI></P>
<P>THE <HI>French,</HI> not only exceed us in Times of Peace, in extending their Trade, and augmenting their Forces, but
<PB N="16" REF="007373_0016_102B8B9C81D934A0"/>use every Art and Stratagem to acquire some new Advan∣tage, against a Time of <HI>War;</HI> while we lie asleep, and are utterly unconcerned about it.—That pernicious Fort at <HI>Crown-Point,</HI> built in a Time of <HI>Peace,</HI> and evidently in our <HI>King's Dominions,</HI> still remains, as well a Monument of our <HI>Weakness</HI> and <HI>Stupidity,</HI> as of their <HI>Treachery</HI> and <HI>Policy.</HI> What Mischief it has done, and is still like to do, to our <HI>Frontiers,</HI> our <HI>Trade</HI> and <HI>Interest</HI> with the <HI>Indians,</HI> none can tell. Our fatal Error in not seasonably preventing that, might, methinks, learn us Wisdom in the <HI>present Day.</HI></P>
<P>EVER since the Peace, our <HI>Public Prints</HI> have been filled with Accounts of the various Methods <HI>France</HI> has taken, in Conjuction with <HI>Spain,</HI> to increase their <HI>naval Force,</HI> and put themselves in a Posture of disputing with us, the <HI>Domi∣nion of the Seas.</HI> By the best Advices the <HI>Ships of War</HI> they have built since the Peace, amount to above 100 Sail.— In Lewis XIVth's Time, 1664, a <HI>French</HI> Author says, <Q>They were in want of Officers, Sailors, Manufactures, and in short, every Thing necessary for the Construction and Equipment of Shipping, not having above 15 or 16 Ships of the lowest Rate.</Q> But they have made so great Improvements since, that they bid fair to rival, if not exceed the <HI>English,</HI> in <HI>that</HI> which has hitherto been their great <HI>Security</HI> and <HI>Glory.</HI>—By these brief Hints, it appears exceeding evident, that <HI>France</HI> is grasping at a <HI>universal Mo∣narchy,</HI> and bent, <HI>per Fas, et Nefas,</HI> on accomplishing the wicked Design. And as her Schemes for effecting this in <HI>Europe,</HI> have hitherto, by the Interposition of divine Pro∣vidence, and the <HI>Strength</HI> of the <HI>Alliance</HI> formed against them, been defeated; she is now undoubtedly making the same Attempt in <HI>America.</HI></P>
<P>WE have heard of the <HI>Policy</HI> and <HI>Perfidy</HI> of <HI>France,</HI> of her <HI>arbitrary Power, Popish Tyranny</HI> and <HI>Bigotry;</HI> we are now like to feel the <HI>bitter Fruits</HI> that flow from them. The <HI>Cloud</HI> gathers thick and dark upon us. 'Tis manifest beyond Dispute, that the <HI>King of France</HI> has for these many Years, been laying <HI>Schemes</HI> to enlarge his Dominions in <HI>America,</HI> and distress us. Tho', by the <HI>Treaty of Aix-la∣all</HI>
<PB N="17" REF="007373_0017_102B8B9E8CC28290"/>Things were to remain on the <HI>same Footing,</HI> as before the War; yet, no sooner was it ratified, than he be∣gins to send Colonies to <HI>neutral Islands;</HI>—projects a Settle∣ment in <HI>Nova-Scotia;</HI>—raises a Dispute about the <HI>Limits;</HI> embroils the Affairs of our <HI>Indians;</HI>—labours to draw them off from our <HI>Alliance;</HI>—and enters <HI>unreasonable Claims,</HI> ut∣terly inconsistent with the Safety and Prosperity of our <HI>infant Colonies.</HI> To lull us asleep, he made <HI>sham Pretences</HI> of settling a Line between the <HI>French</HI> and <HI>English</HI> Territo∣ries in <HI>America: Commissioners</HI> were appointed; much Time and Money spent, in fruitless Negotiations at the Court of <HI>France;</HI> which answered no End, unless to convince every Body, that he never had a Design of settling it any other∣wise than by the SWORD: And for a <HI>Decision</HI> this Way, he has made the most artful and diligent Preparation. It is now sufficiently known, that the <HI>French</HI> have been forti∣fying themselves on our back Parts; laying in great Quantities of <HI>Provision,</HI> and Magazines of <HI>warlike Stores,</HI> as if they had actually concluded on War. While we have been wholly secure. The <HI>Master-Piece</HI> of their <HI>Policy</HI> has been lately discovered, tho' long since concerted, <HI>viz.</HI> their compleating and securing a Communication between St. <HI>Lawrence</HI>'s River and the <HI>Missisippi.</HI> They are in Pos∣session of <HI>two Forts</HI> on the Lake <HI>Ontario,</HI> and have lately built two or three below the Lake <HI>Errie,</HI> on a Branch of the River <HI>Ohio,</HI> that empties into the great River <HI>Missisippi;</HI> the Mouth of which they have long possessed. By the best Advices they have very much fortified, and well-manned these <HI>Forts;</HI> so that now they have actually surrounded the <HI>British Colonies,</HI> and are in Possession of a vastly extended Country, from <HI>Cape-Breton</HI> to the <HI>Bay of Mexico.</HI> Enough has been said of late in the <HI>public Prints,</HI> to render it indis∣putable, that their Settlements on the <HI>Ohio</HI> are within our <HI>King's Dominions.</HI> 'Tis sufficient to observe that they were made without their <HI>Consent,</HI> and against their <HI>Inclination,</HI> on Lands belonging to the <HI>Indians</HI> in our <HI>Alliance,</HI> which have been confirmed to them, under the Protection of <HI>Great-Britain;</HI> and so, are inconsistent with both the
<PB N="18" REF="007373_0018_102B8BA02DC42408"/><HI>Letter</HI> and <HI>Spirit,</HI> of their <HI>Treaties:</HI> And if we suffer them quietly to possess what they have so unrighteously seized upon, and to go on fortifying themselves, there requires no Spirit of Prophesy to foretel, that it must sooner or later prove <HI>fatal</HI> to these <HI>Colonies.</HI> All Communication with the powerful and numerous Tribes of our <HI>Indians,</HI> will unavoidably be cut off; our profitable <HI>Trade</HI> with them wholly lost, and our <HI>Frontiers</HI> constantly exposed, to all the <HI>barbarous Cruelties</HI> which woful Experience hath taught us, those <HI>savage People,</HI> under the Influence of <HI>French Policy,</HI> are capable of committing. The <HI>Line of Forts</HI> they have already between <HI>Canada</HI> and the <HI>Missisippi,</HI> gives them an un∣known Advantage, to draw off the <HI>Natives</HI> from <HI>our Alliance.</HI> To effect which, no Pains or Cost, are spared, no Stratagem is left untried. We are well assured, they keep <HI>Missionaries</HI> con∣stantly among them, to inculcate the distinguishing Principles of their Religion; and what appears still more important in their Eyes, to infuse into their Minds, Prejudices against the <HI>English,</HI> and attach them to the <HI>French</HI> Interest. They have been unwearied in their Pains, since the last Peace, in alienating their Affections from us. For this Purpose, they have desired Liberty to send <HI>Missionaries</HI> among the <HI>Six Nations,</HI> and have lately sent them an <HI>Invitation</HI> to come and settle at <HI>Canada.</HI> Should they succeed in these Attempts, the Consequence would be very pernicious. Our Frontier Settlements would be broke up, and all Hopes of driving the <HI>French</HI> from their <HI>Encroachments,</HI> be very much at an End.</P>
<P>THEY are a <HI>warlike People:</HI> Governor SHIRLEY in one of his Speeches, if I don't mistake, supposes they have 16,00 or 17,00 fighting Men; and having the most of the other <HI>Tribes</HI> under their Influence, are <HI>powerful Friends,</HI> and would be very <HI>dangerous Enemies.</HI></P>
<P>THE <HI>Twightwees,</HI> a numerous Tribe, in whose Country the <HI>French</HI> have lately built <HI>Forts,</HI> some Years ago entered into an Alliance with the Governor of <HI>Pennsylvania,</HI> which they have hitherto faithfully preserved. In 1751, they espoused our Cause, and revenged the Affront, which the
<PB N="19" REF="007373_0019_102B8BA22F3FDB10"/><HI>French</HI> put upon us, in siezing and imprisoning our <HI>Traders,</HI> by bringing two of theirs to <HI>Philadelphia,</HI> and delivering them up to the <HI>Government.</HI> But unless some speedy and vigorous Step be taken to secure them and ourselves, their <HI>Friendship</HI> will be inevitably lost, as they will be obliged to join the <HI>French</HI> in their own Defence.—Our weak and ill-concerted Measures to dispossess the latter, have very much sunk our Interest with the <HI>Indians.</HI> Since <HI>Colonel Washington</HI>'s Defeat, they appear wavering and show an unusual Degree of Coldness. Our formal Way of <HI>Treaties,</HI> and giving <HI>Presents,</HI> signifies very little; half the Money well laid out in erecting <HI>Fortresses</HI> in their Country, and supporting proper <HI>Missionaries</HI> to reside among them, would be much more to the Purpose. However, at pre∣sent, it is Madness for us, by our <HI>dilatory Methods</HI> of proceeding, to increase the Advantage the <HI>French</HI> already have in their Hands, for depriving us of those <HI>necessary Allies,</HI> who will have it very much in their Power, to turn the <HI>Scale</HI> in the present Dispute. Our Eyes must surely, by this Time, be open, to see that the Schemes they have hitherto, so secretly laid, and artfully conducted, tend to, and if not seasonably prevented, will issue in, the utter Destruction of all our <HI>Provinces.</HI> And if we view our Enemies, in a <HI>religious,</HI> as well as <HI>political</HI> Light, we shall see the Necessity of guarding against them with all possible Care.</P>
<P>THEIR established Religion is <HI>Popery;</HI> which, beside all it's other <HI>Corruptions,</HI> disposes them from Principle, to be cruel to <HI>Protestants.</HI> They are early taught as undoubted Truths, <HI>That there is no Salvation out of the Church of Rome;—That all who separate from it are damnable Heretics;— That no Faith is to be kept with them;—That it is highly meritorious to use the most cruel Methods of reclaiming such, and bringing them back into the Bosom of that</HI> Mother of Harlots;—<HI>and that all such as are obstinate, ought to be extirpated from the Face of the Earth.</HI> And what we are to expect, if God should deliver us into their Hands, we
<PB N="20" REF="007373_0020_102B8BA4AB7B2638"/>may learn from what <HI>our Brethren</HI> have suffered, whose Lot has been cast among them.</P>
<P>THE beginning of the <HI>Reformation</HI> in <HI>France,</HI> was <HI>A. D.</HI> 1124; which spread very much, 1160, by Means of one <HI>Peter Waldo,</HI> of <HI>Lyons,</HI> from whom they were called, <HI>Waldenses.</HI> And tho' there was a Persecution rais'd against it, from its first Commencement, it was, by divine Pro∣vidence, wonderfully preserved, and carried on. To pass by numberless cruel and inhuman Methods, to destroy the <HI>Protestants,</HI> and suppress the <HI>Reformation,</HI> in the four following Centuries, I have only Time now to remark, That in 1572, there was the most <HI>barbarous Massacre,</HI> committed on the <HI>Protestants,</HI> at <HI>Paris,</HI> where some of their chief Men, being invited, under an Oath of Safety, to solemnize the Marriage of the <HI>King of Navarre,</HI> were, at a Signal, by the Toll of the Bell, fallen upon, and <HI>inhumanly butchered</HI> by the <HI>Papists,</HI> their being at the same Time an <HI>Insurrection</HI> against them in the other Parts of the Kingdom. By all Accounts, a great Number, and by some, not less than 100,000, were slain in this <HI>perfi∣dious Manner.</HI> But detestable as their Conduct was, the News of it was receiv'd with Joy, at <HI>Rome.</HI> They found a great Deliverer in <HI>King</HI> HENRY IVth; who, as hath been observed, was indebted to the <HI>Protestants,</HI> for his Crown, when the Papists, with the <HI>King of Spain,</HI> under the Influence of the <HI>Pope,</HI> were in League against him. To reward their Fidelity, or rather, being sensible how just and equitable it was, he established the <HI>Edict of Nantz,</HI> by which free Liberty of Conscience, in religious Matters, and Access to all Places of Honour and Trust, were secured to them; declared it to be <HI>perpetual</HI> and <HI>irrevocable;</HI> put 100 <HI>fortified Places</HI> into their Hands, as a <HI>Security,</HI> that it should ever be observed. This was confirmed, by LEWIS XIIIth, tho' it was repeatedly violated in the Course of his Reign. The same <HI>Edict</HI> was confirmed also by LEWIS XIVth, and by him too declared <HI>perpetual</HI> and <HI>irrevocable;</HI> yet by the continual Remonstrance of the <HI>Clergy,</HI> and Insinuations of the <HI>Jesuits,</HI> a cruel Persecution
<PB N="21" REF="007373_0021_102B8BA6C460E920"/>was carried on against them, through a great Part of his Reign, which was very much increased, towards the Close of it, when he acted, as if he was determined to extirpate them from his Kingdom.</P>
<P>IN 1681, he published a <HI>Declaration,</HI> by which their Children were permitted, at the Age of 7 Years, to renounce their Religion. <Q>In Consequence of this, (<HI>says a French Writer</HI>
<NOTE N="§" PLACE="foot"><HI>Voltaire</HI>'s Life of <HI>Lewis</HI> XIVth.</NOTE>) great Numbers of Children were seized in the Provinces, with a View to make them abjure, and Troops quartered on their Parents.</Q> At the Close of the Year 1684, he set on foot the <HI>Hellish Method</HI> of converting them, by <HI>Dragoons.</HI> The principal Men were assembled together, and ordered to <HI>abjure their Religion;</HI> and upon such as re∣fused, the Soldiers were let loose to treat them in the most inhuman and barbarous Manner. According to some Accounts near 500,000 Families were plundered. And to cut them off from that last and only Refuge, <HI>flying their Country,</HI> a <HI>Proclamation</HI> was issued, <HI>confiscating</HI> all Estates that were sold, if the Seller departed the Kingdom within a Year after: And as if this was not enough, Soldiers were quartered on the <HI>Frontiers,</HI> to seize any that attempted to make their Escape; and such as they could apprehend, were confined to the <HI>Gallies.</HI> Multitudes however found Me∣thods of escaping, and took Refuge in <HI>England, Holland,</HI> and other <HI>Protestant Countries,</HI> where they were kindly re∣ceived, especially by <HI>King William,</HI> their great <HI>Patron;</HI> <Q>50,000 Families <HI>(says Voltaire)</HI> in the Space of three Years, left the Kingdom.</Q></P>
<P>To convince you that I don't aggravate the Matter, hear the Words of a Letter from his Prime Minister
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>The Marquis de</HI> Louvois.</NOTE>, dated 1685, <Q>It is his Majesty's Pleasure, that such as refuse to conform to his Religion, be proceeded against with the utmost Rigour, and that not the least Indulgence be shewn to those who affect the foolish Glory of being the last to comply.</Q> And to use the Words of the above men∣tioned Author, <Q>While all the Churches of the Refor∣med,
<PB N="22" REF="007373_0022_102B8BA86C658250"/>were thus every where demolished, and Abjurations demanded in the Provinces, with an armed Force, the <HI>Edict of Nantz</HI> was at last revoked, in the Month of <HI>October,</HI> 1685; which compleated the Ruin of the <HI>Protestant Cause,</HI> already weakened and undermined on all Sides.</Q> This may satisfy us, that no Security from a <HI>Popish Prince,</HI> for our religious Liberties, can ever be obtained. <HI>Promises</HI> and <HI>Oaths, even Edicts,</HI> declared <HI>per∣petual,</HI> stand for nothing, when made with <HI>Hereticks.</HI> With such <HI>Bigotry</HI> and <HI>blind Zeal,</HI> does their Religion inspire them, that they will persecute their Subjects, against all the known and consest Rules of good Policy.</P>
<P>THEY had indeed some Respite from the <HI>Fury</HI> of their <HI>popish Adversaries,</HI> while the <HI>Duke of Orleans</HI> was Regent of the Kingdom: But it has since been renewed again with the same Cruelty, under his present Majesty, <HI>Lewis</HI> XVth; who, in the Year 1745, published an <HI>Edict,</HI> making it <HI>im∣mediate Death,</HI> for any Ministers that officiated; <HI>perpetual Imprisonment</HI> for the Women, and <HI>Gallies</HI> for the Men, who attended; and few of the succeding Years, to the present Time, have been without Instances of the <HI>barba∣rous Treatment</HI> they have met with from <HI>popish Bigots.</HI></P>
<P>IN the Year 1752, a Gentleman from <HI>Languedoc,</HI> writes thus, <Q>The Persecution is fiercer than ever, the Papists demand Abjuration of all that have been married, or had their Children baptized in Protestant Assemblies, and on the Refusal, the Mothers are proclaimed <HI>Whores,</HI> and the Children <HI>Bastards.</HI> They seize on Father, Mother, and Children, and force them into <HI>Romish Churches, &amp;c.</HI></Q> And by the latest Advices, <HI>Persecutions</HI> still con∣tinue in <HI>France,</HI> as furious as ever. A Letter from <HI>Paris,</HI> dated <HI>September</HI> 25, 1754, gives the following melancholly Account. <Q>The Persecution of the unhpapy <HI>Protestants,</HI> has been long carried on with great Rigour, and no Measures are neglected, either to disturb their As∣semblies, or seize their Ministers. This appeared very particularly the 19th of <HI>June</HI> last, near <HI>St. Foy,</HI> in the <HI>Perigord,</HI> where an Assembly of Protestants being held
<PB N="23" REF="007373_0023_102B8BAAEA5090B8"/>the Night before, a <HI>Detachment of Troops</HI> lay in <HI>Ambus∣cade</HI> near the Place, to wait for their breaking up, and then fell upon these unhappy People, who could make no Resistance, and dangerously wounded a great many of them: But, this is nothing to the Distress occasioned in <HI>Languedoc,</HI> and the <HI>Cevennes,</HI> by a general Search which was ordered to be made there the 3d of <HI>August</HI> last, for which all the Troops that were in those Provinces, were employed, except those which serve to garrison the <HI>Forts</HI> and <HI>Citadels:</HI> They were ordered to march in the Dead of the Night, and with all imaginable Silence, to invest certain <HI>Towns, Villages,</HI> and <HI>Country Houses;</HI> a List of which was given to every commanding Officer. At Break of Day, the Search was begun with all Rigour imaginable. The Soldiers burst the Doors open with their <HI>Muskets,</HI> and entering with their <HI>Bayonets</HI> at the End of them, ransack'd every Corner of the Houses, destroying every Thing that came in their Way, and sparing neither Furniture nor Persons. In short, the Places they went to, could be compared to nothing but a Town taken by Storm.</Q></P>
<P>THUS you see, <HI>My Brethren,</HI> the <HI>Power</HI> and <HI>Policy,</HI> the <HI>Treachery</HI> and <HI>Cruelty,</HI> of our <HI>Foes,</HI> have a dark and threat∣ning Aspect upon us. But I have a more distressing and affecting Scene to open to your View: I mean, our Ex∣posure to the <HI>angry Resentments of Heaven,</HI> from those crying Abominations, which, at this Time, so greatly abound. To declaim against the prevailing Iniquities of the Day, is far from being a delightful Theme; but should we, who are set as <HI>Watchmen on the Walls</HI> of God's <HI>Jerusa∣lem,</HI> neglect to <HI>declare to his People, their Transgressions, and their Sins,</HI> we should betray our Trust, act beneath our <HI>sacred Character,</HI> and involve our selves deeply in the <HI>public Guilt.</HI></P>
<P>'TIS no less lamentable to be thought of, than true in Fact, that our Nation is greatly degenerated, and become extremely corrupt. <HI>We are a sinful People, laden with Iniquity.</HI> From what kind of Heaven-daring Wickedness
<PB N="24" REF="007373_0024_102B8BACC00F9060"/>are we free? If we begin at the Height of <HI>Atheism,</HI> and descend to the lowest Pitch of <HI>Sensuality,</HI> and <HI>beastly Uncleaness,</HI> what Exception can be made? Are we not in all these Respects defiled? To such a Degree of Wicked∣ness have some profane Sinners arrived, as not only, like the <HI>Foot, to say in their Heart,</HI> but openly proclaim, <Q>That there is no God;</Q> and employ the very <HI>intellectual Powers</HI> he has given them, in disputing against the <HI>Author</HI> of their Being. And what Multitudes live and act, as if they believed not his Existence; or, as if they thought <HI>he was altogether such an one as themselves?</HI> How many make a Scoff and Banter of revealed Religion, pouring Contempt on the Gospel, and all its Glories; <HI>denying the Lord that bought them, and bringing swift Destruction on themselves.</HI></P>
<P><HI>INFIDELITY,</HI> has of late Years, been spreading fast in the Kingdom, and is evidently growing on the present Generation. Books, that turn the <HI>divine Oracles</HI> into Ridicule, and tend to unhinge Men's Minds, from all <HI>Principles of Religion,</HI> have been industriously propagated.</P>
<P>THE lamentable Increase of <HI>Profaness,</HI> in our Day, must be manifest to the most careless Observer. What Numbers of thoughtless, stupid Sinners, show an utter Disregard to all that is <HI>sacred</HI> and <HI>solemn;</HI> fill the Ears of all that hear them, with their vain Oaths, and horrid Imprecations; interline their filthy Discourses, with the <HI>venerable Name</HI> of the ever blessed Deity; and in meer Sport, or, on every slight Provocation, wish Damnation to themselves, and all around them. 'Tis easy to see, how this infamous Practice destroys all <HI>Reverence</HI> for an <HI>Oath;</HI> opens a Door to <HI>Perjury,</HI> and the whole Train of direful Consequences that flow from it. And what shall we say, as to the various Kinds of <HI>Luxury, Lewdness,</HI> and vile <HI>Debauchery,</HI> which so much prevail? It is a Shame to speak of the sordid Methods invented by corrupt Minds, for the Gratification of their <HI>brutish Lusts;</HI> tho' many of these <HI>unclean Wretches,</HI> glory in their Shame, <HI>declaring their Sin, like</HI> Sodom, <HI>and hide it not.</HI>—Nay, too often many turn Factors for the Devil, and labour to promote his Kingdom,
<PB N="25" REF="007373_0025_102B8BAF91BBDF08"/>by spreading their <HI>fatal Infection</HI> among all with whom they converse: Affecting, to this Purpose, are the Words of the present Bishop of <HI>London:</HI> <Q>Have not, <HI>says he,</HI> all the Abominations of the publick Stews, been opened to View, by lewd Pictures, exposed to Sale at Noon Day? Have not Histories or Romances of the vilest Prostitutes, been published? intended meerly to display the most execrable Scenes of Lewdness; Lewdness re∣presented without Disguise, to inflame the corrupt Passions of the Youth of the Nation; and the quick Sale those Pictures and Books had, is a deplorable Circumstance, and sad Instance of the corrupt Disposition of many among us.</Q> And that this <HI>excellent and pious Letter,</HI> should be lampooned in the public <HI>News-Papers,</HI> is a flagrant Evidence to what a Height Impiety is arrived. And if the Sinners of our Land have not gone the same Length in all those beastly Pleasures, and detestable Abo∣minations, 'tis evident they make swift Advances, and great Improvements in <HI>those Mysteries of Iniquity.</HI></P>
<P>TIME would fail me, to speak of the open Contempt, every where cast on God's holy Day; all the Ordinances of his House, and all the Riches of his Grace, offered in the Gospel; nor can I easily describe the Gluttony and Drunkenness, Robbery and Deceit, Oppression and Vio∣lence, Pride and Covetousness, for which our Land mourns. <HI>We look far Judgment, but behold Oppression;</HI> for <HI>Righteous∣ness, but behold a Cry.</HI>—Will any enquire, where are those Enormities to be found? Have we not Reason rather to say, where are they not to be seen? What sad Defects and Corruptions, are to be found among all Ranks and De∣grees, Sexes and Denominations; among Rulers and ruled; high and low, rich and poor.—'Tis not my Business to accuse and condemn; nor would I here affirm any Thing. Would to God, that <HI>Pride</HI> and <HI>Ambition, Bribery</HI> and <HI>Extortion, Debauchery</HI> and <HI>Uncleanness,</HI> were banished from the <HI>British Court.</HI> O! that <HI>just</HI> and <HI>righteous Men</HI> always stood around our <HI>King, who feared God,</HI> and <HI>bated Covetousness.</HI>—How lamentable is it, when Vice
<PB N="26" REF="007373_0026_102B8BB186CF4170"/>comes recommended to the lower Sort of People, by the Practice of the Great, and is connived at, and even coun∣tenanced by those, whose Business it is to suppress it! Would to God there was nothing of this found among the Rulers of our Nation and Land;—that they were all <HI>Terrors to evil Doers,</HI> as their Office obliges them to be!</P>
<P>ARE those of the <HI>sacred Profession</HI> free from a Share in the <HI>public Guilt;</HI> who should be the <HI>Salt of the Earth,</HI> the <HI>Light of the World,</HI> to keep it from Darkness and Corrup∣tion? Are all God's Ministers <HI>cloathed with Salvation,</HI> then may his <HI>Saints shout for Joy.</HI> But if it be too evident to be denied, that the <HI>Pride</HI> and <HI>Covetousness,</HI> the <HI>Ignorance</HI> and <HI>Sloth,</HI> the <HI>carnal</HI> and <HI>sensual Lives</HI> of too many among those of <HI>that Order,</HI> have made the <HI>Offerings of the Lord to be abborred,</HI> and deeply wounded Religion in the House of its Friends. What shall we say? Must we not confess? Must we not lament, with the Prophet
<NOTE N="‖" PLACE="foot"><HI>Isaiah,</HI> i. 5, 6.</NOTE>, <HI>That the whole Head is sick; the whole Heart is faint; from the Sole of the Foot, even to the Crown of the Head, there is no Soundness, but Wounds, Bruises and putrifying Sores.</HI> These Things bring the <HI>Wrath of God</HI> on a guilty World. <HI>Sin</HI> is the <HI>fatal Source</HI> of all the Calamities and Woes that have ever over-spread the human Race. When ever it prevails, it threatens the Destruction of a People, both from its na∣tural Tendency; and as it lays them open to the desolating Judgments of <HI>Heaven.</HI> This may be affirmed of all Kinds of Iniquity, especially of that <HI>abominable Luxury,</HI> and <HI>ex∣travagant Taste</HI> for lawless Pleasures, which are so much the Source of all the Corruptions of our Day. We may well say with the Poet, <HI>Soevior Armis incubuit Luxuria</HI>
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">More fatal than destructive Arms, — fell Luxury prevail'd.</NOTE>.</P>
<P>IN sacred and profane History, we meet with mournful Accounts, of <HI>ruined States and Kingdoms,</HI> whose Destruction sprung from this <HI>Cause. In the Days of</HI> Noah, <HI>they were</HI>
<PB N="27" REF="007373_0027_102B8BB313EC0D48"/><HI>eating and drinking; marrying, and giving in Marriage:</HI> wholly regardless of the divine Threatnings; so immersed in sensual Pleasures, that <HI>the Imaginations of their Hearts, were wholly evil,</HI> till God was provoked to destroy them from off the Face of the Earth, by a <HI>Deluge. Sodom</HI> and <HI>Gomorrah set forth as an Example, suffering the Vengeance of eternal Fire;</HI> are a standing Monument to a guilty World, of the awful Danger arising from sensual and luxurious Indulgences.—<HI>Fullness of Bread, Idleness,</HI> and the too common Consequences, <HI>abominable Uncleanness,</HI> brought that tremendous Judgment of Heaven, on their guilty Cities. This drew down sudden and surprising Destruction on <HI>Babylon</HI>
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">CYRUS got into the City, by the Stratagem of turning the Course of the River, that run thro' it; seized on the King and Nobles, as they were feasting in the Palace, and so buried in Luxury and Sensua∣lity, that they were not able to make any Resistance.</NOTE>, of old, the most powerful and magnificent City, in the then known World. 'Tis affectingly described by the Prophet <HI>Isaiah,</HI> xlvii. 8, 9. <HI>Therefore hear now this thou that are given to Pleasures; that dwellest carelessly, that sayest in thy Heart, I am, and none else besides me. I shall not sit as a Widow, neither shall I know the Loss of Children. But these two Things shall come to thee in a Moment; in one Day, the Loss of Children, and Widowhood; they shall come upon thee in their Perfection, for the Multitude of thy Sorceries, and for the great Abundance of thine</HI> Enchantments. This was exactly accomplished, in the Night when the <HI>King saw the Hand Writing on the Wall.</HI> God's ancient People the <HI>Jews,</HI> are a moving Instance of this Kind, on whom <HI>Wrath came to the utmost, when they had filled up the Mea∣sure of their Iniquity;</HI> as also the <HI>Romans,</HI> who were the Instruments of executing upon them, the Judgments of Heaven. That powerful State which was so long the <HI>Wonder, Terror,</HI> and <HI>Envy</HI> of the World, which the most powerful Enemies could not subdue, fell a Sacrifice to their own <HI>Lusts</HI> and <HI>Corruptions,</HI> as all acquainted with their History, well know. And does not Destruction threaten the <HI>British Nation,</HI> and her <HI>American Colonies,</HI> from
<PB N="28" REF="007373_0028_102B8BB5619B7460"/>the same Quarter? Such Vices as now prevail, sap the very <HI>Foundation</HI> of a Society, exhaust its <HI>Riches,</HI> weaken its <HI>Power;</HI> destroy a Spirit of <HI>Industry, Frugality,</HI> and <HI>good</HI> Oeconomy; introduce <HI>Idleness</HI> and <HI>Effeminacy; Discontent with,</HI> and <HI>Contempt</HI> of <HI>Authority;</HI> which are the <HI>Bane</HI> of a People, and render them an <HI>easy Prey</HI> to their ambitious Neighbours. And do not these Things cry to Heaven, for Vengeance, and lay us open to the Displeasure of an angry God? <HI>Shall I not visit for these Things, saith the Lord? And shall not my Soul be avenged on such a Nation as this?</HI> Jer. v. 9. The <HI>Psalmist</HI> speaks of it, as the usual Method of divine Providence, <HI>to turn a fruitful Land into Barrenness. for the Wickedness of them that dwell therein,</HI> Psal. cvii, 34. 'Tis true, public Judgments are executed in a Way of Sovereignty, on some Nations <HI>sooner,</HI> and in a <HI>lesser Degree,</HI> as a <HI>Warning</HI> to Repentance; on others, who are more ripe for Vengeance, <HI>later,</HI> but in a more <HI>terrible Manner:</HI> However, national Sins persisted in, unreformed, and unrepented of, will sooner or later bring down the Judg∣ments of Heaven.—The Reason is plain. As to <HI>particular Persons,</HI> altho' Rewards and Punishments should be ever so promiscuous <HI>here,</HI> yet all will be rectified at the <HI>great Day;</HI> but <HI>Societies</HI> will be disbanded; and if ever they are punished as such, it must be in this World. And, indeed, the Experience of all Ages, has verified the Observation of the wise Man, <HI>Righteousness exalteth a Nation, but Sin is a Reproach to any People.</HI></P>
<P>IN this View, our Case looks <HI>dark;</HI> but blessed be God, not <HI>desperate. Sentence against our evil Deeds is not yet execu∣ted.</HI> Tho' God might in righteous Severity long before this, have cast us off and left us to all the <HI>Misery</HI> of a Peo∣ple, wholly abandoned by him, which we heard described in the former Part of the Day, yet he affords a Season of Repentance, and waits to be gracious. He seems, with an amazing Condescention, and Kindness, to say to us as to <HI>Ephraim</HI> of old, <Q>How shall I give thee up <HI>Ephraim?</HI> how shall I deliver thee <HI>Israel?</HI> How shall I make thee as <HI>Admah?</HI> How shall I set thee as <HI>Zeboim?</HI> Mine
<PB N="29" REF="007373_0029_102B8BB6FA401818"/>Heart is turned within me, my Repentings are kindled together.</Q> Our Danger from our <HI>Enemies,</HI> and especially from our <HI>Sins,</HI> is great; so is our Encouragement from the <HI>sovereign boundless Mercy</HI> of our God, and the many <HI>Tokens</HI> of his favourable Presence which yet remain with us. We may apply to ourselves the Words of the Prophet <HI>Jerem.</HI> li. 5. <Q>For <HI>Israel</HI> has not been forsaken, nor <HI>Judah</HI> of his God, of the Lord of Hosts, tho' the Land was filled with Sin against the holy one of <HI>Israel.</HI></Q></P>
<P>I TRUST there is yet Mercy in Store for us. God has in his sovereign Goodness, chosen the <HI>British Nation</HI> to be the <HI>Bulwark</HI> of the <HI>Reformation;</HI> to hold up a Standard against those <HI>Delusions, Superstitions,</HI> and <HI>Impostures,</HI> which the <HI>Church of Rome</HI> has been for above a thousand Years, spreading in the Christian Church, and distinguished it above all the <HI>Nations</HI> of the Earth, by the peculiar and constant Care of his Providence; by numberless <HI>signal Deliverances,</HI> and <HI>Salvations,</HI> which Time does not allow me to recount</P>
<P>AND I can't but esteem it a Token for Good, and Ground of great <HI>Encouragement,</HI> that, notwithstanding all our <HI>mourn∣ful Declensions,</HI> there are still among us, a <HI>Generation that fear God, whose righteous Souls are vexed from Day to Day, with the filthy Conversation of the Wicked;</HI> who are jealous for the Lord of Hosts, and plead his Cause against the Workers of Iniquity, who are labouring by their <HI>Prayers,</HI> by their <HI>Example</HI> and <HI>Influence,</HI> to reform a degenerate Age. How melancholly soever our Case is, it is not so bad as theirs, of whom God complains
<NOTE N="‖" PLACE="foot">Ezek. xxii. 30, 31.</NOTE>: <HI>And I sought for a Man among them, that should make up the Hedge, and stand in the Gap before me, for the Land, that I should not destroy it; but I found none: Therefore have I poured out my Indignation upon them: I have consumed them with the Fire of my Wrath; their own Way have I recompensed upon their Heads, saith the Lord God.</HI> We may indeed say with ano∣ther Prophet
<NOTE N="§" PLACE="foot">Isai. i. 9.</NOTE>, <HI>Except the Lord of Hosts had left unto us a</HI>
<PB N="30" REF="007373_0030_102B8BB98AB74940"/><HI>very small Remnant, we should have been as</HI> Sodom, <HI>and we should have been like unto</HI> Gomorrah. But blessed be God, such <HI>a Remnant</HI> is left, who have an Interest at the Throne of Grace, and improve it in daily Supplications, not only for themselves, their Families, and the Church of God, but for the <HI>Land</HI> of their Nativity, that God would save it from deserved <HI>Ruin,</HI> and not come out against it, and destroy it with a <HI>Curse.</HI></P>
<P>HAVING thus, <HI>my Brethren,</HI> laid before you something of our Danger, from the <HI>Power,</HI> the <HI>Pride,</HI> and the <HI>Policy</HI> of our Enemies, the Greatness of our Sins, and at the same Time, what Grounds we have to hope, that we are not forsaken by God; but that there is yet Mercy in Store for us. It only remains, that I briefly point out our Duty in this <HI>important Season,</HI> which it becomes us to hear, with Hearts fully disposed to a ready and unfeigned <HI>Compliance:</HI> And I think it lies plain before us, and may be concisely summed up under the following Particulars.</P>
<P N="1">I. WE ought to humble ourselves; repent as in <HI>Dust and Ashes,</HI> before God, and return to him with all our Hearts, from whom we have so grievously revolted. The Voice of divine Providence to us, at this Time, may well be expressed in the Words of the Prophet
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Joel 11.12, 13, 14.</NOTE>, <HI>Therefore also now saith the Lord, Turn ye even to me, with all your Heart, and with fasting, and with weeping, and with mourning, and rent your Heart, and not your Garments, and turn unto the Lord your God, for he is gracious and merciful, slow to Anger, and of great Kindness, and repenteth him of the Evil. Who knoweth, if he will return, and repent, and leave a Blessing behind him, even a Meat-Offering, and a Drink-Offering, unto the Lord your God.</HI> 'Tis not enough that we speak of public Sins, as being Matter of Lamentation, and confess them in a <HI>formal Way,</HI> in our Prayers, on such an Occasion as this; but we should in our <HI>private,</HI> as well as <HI>public</HI> Addresses to the Throne of Grace, bring our Case before God, with <HI>broken Hearts,</HI> and <HI>contrite Spirits,</HI> saying with the great Reformer of <HI>Israel</HI> 
<NOTE N="§" PLACE="foot">Ezra IX. 7, 10, and 15.</NOTE>, <HI>O! our God,</HI>
<PB N="31" REF="007373_0031_102B8BBB73EE28B0"/><HI>we are ashamed, and blush to lift up our Faces to thee; for our Iniquities are increased over our Heads, and our Trespasses are grown up into the Heavens.</HI> The following Words we may adopt, with a little Variation: <HI>Since the Days of our Fathers have we been in a great Trespass, unto this Day, and for our Iniquities, we, our Kings, and our Priests,</HI> our Nobles and our Commons, <HI>may</HI> justly <HI>be delivered into the Hands of the King,</HI> who seeks our Ruin, <HI>to the Sword, to Captivity, to a Spoil, and to Confusion of Face.—And now, O our God! what shall we say after this; for we have forsaken thy Com∣mandments.—O Lord God of</HI> Israel, <HI>thou art righteous; for we remain yet escaped, as it is this Day, behold we are before thee in our Trespasses, and we cannot stand before thee, because of this.</HI></P>
<P>IN such a Day, <Q>Let the Priests, the Ministers of the Lord, and all his People weep, between the Porch and the Altar; and let them say, Spare thy People, O Lord, and give not thy Heritage to Reproach, that the Hea∣then should rule over them. Wherefore should they say among the People, where is their God? Then will the Lord be jealous for this Land, and pity this People.</Q></P>
<P N="2">II. We should labour after a thorough <HI>Reformation.</HI> Our Fastings, Humiliation, and Shews of Repentance, will signify Nothing without this. O! how much is a general thorough Reformation, to be desired! how vigorously should it be attempted, by all that have the Honour of God, and Interest of their Country at Heart! When our Land is sinking under the Load of <HI>public Guilt,</HI> and Iniqui∣ty is coming in upon us, like a <HI>Flood,</HI> shall we not lift up a <HI>Standard</HI> against it, and labour to <HI>prevent</HI> the <HI>Ruin</HI> we fear and deserve, by <HI>removing</HI> the <HI>Cause?</HI> Did but an holy Ardor, and Zeal for this <HI>noble Work,</HI> begin to kindle among every Order and Rank of Men, it would be a Token for Good; it would enliven our Hopes, and invigorate all our Attempts for the Protection and Defence of our Country. For how little soever we may think of it, our <HI>worst Enemies</HI> are those of our <HI>own House;</HI> our multiplied Transgressions, which expose us to the Angry Resentments of Heaven:
<PB N="32" REF="007373_0032_102B8BBD48428C38"/>And were <HI>these</HI> subdued, <HI>these</HI> that now rise up against us, and seek our Ruin, I doubt not would soon be made to flee before us.</P>
<P>How <HI>desirable</HI> a Prospect would it therefore afford, should all according to their various Stations and Capaci∣ties, <HI>cordially unite</HI> in this necessary Work.</P>
<P><HI>1st.</HI> THE <HI>civil Magistrates</HI> in the Land, are loudly called upon in such a Day, to exert the <HI>Authority</HI> God has put into their Hands, for the <HI>Suppression</HI> of Vice and Immo∣rality. They are appointed to execute Wrath on evil Doers
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Rom. xiii. 3.</NOTE>, and did they conscientiously put in <HI>Execution</HI> the many <HI>excellent Laws</HI> we have against Vice, and strike a Dread into presumptuous Sinners, by restraining their enor∣mous and scandalous Crimes, it would be of unspeak∣able <HI>Service</HI> to the <HI>public Interest;</HI> give Life and Vigour to all Attempts for a Reformation. When Men of <HI>superior Characters</HI> and <HI>Influence,</HI> appear against Sin, it puts it <HI>out of Countenance,</HI> and the Vicious are ashamed to show their Heads. They might do much towards putting a Stop to that Torrent of Iniquity, that threatens the Ruin of our Land. And surely they are not only by the <HI>sacred Solemni∣ty</HI> of their <HI>Oath,</HI> but by a Regard to the <HI>dying Cause</HI> of their <HI>Country,</HI> and as they would not have the Public Guilt crying against them at the last Day, bound to exert them∣selves at such a Season, and not bear the <HI>Sword of Justice</HI> in vain. And should they add to their Authority, the <HI>engaging Force</HI> of their superior <HI>Example,</HI> for the Encou∣ragement of Piety towards God; Justice and Charity, to∣wards Men; Sobriety, Frugality and Chastity,—who can say how far the <HI>kind Influence</HI> might extend?</P>
<P><HI>2dly,</HI> AND surely it concerns those of the <HI>sacred Order,</HI> of every Denomination, most heartily to engage in such a Design. 'Tis justly expected, that we should appear on the Lord's Side, against the Workers of Iniquity. Our <HI>Profession</HI> obliges us to give the <HI>Alarm</HI> of <HI>impending Judg∣ments;</HI> to shew to God's People, their Transgression and
<PB N="33" REF="007373_0033_102B8BBED4E04CA0"/>Sin, as the procuring Cause of all the Calamities we feel, or fear.—Methinks at such a Day, we should lay aside all Bigotry, and <HI>Party Disputes,</HI> about lesser Matters, and <HI>unite</HI> our Endeavours, to reform a degenerate Age. We may soon be <HI>Companions</HI> in suffering, and see all our <HI>Differences</HI> buried in one <HI>common Ruin.</HI> There has perhaps scarce ever been a Time, when Ministers were more loudly called upon, to unite their Activity and Diligence, in awakening a secure Generation from the Lethargy into which they are sunk, and exciting them to a speedy Re∣pentance and Reformation, as the <HI>necessary Means</HI> of saving a guilty Land. When we look around, and see how Iniquity abounds; how God is dishonoured; the Cause of our glorious Redeemer despised and ridiculed by some; slighted and disregarded by most; can we be <HI>unaffected</HI> with the mournful Scene? Shall we stand as <HI>unconcerned</HI> Spectators, of all the Profaneness and Security which is so visible and lamentable, in thoughtless Sinners? Of all the Hypocrisy, Formality and Apostacies among Pro∣fessors? Where is our <HI>Zeal</HI> for the LORD OF HOSTS? our Bowels of <HI>Compassion</HI> for <HI>perishing</HI> Sinners? our <HI>Concern</HI> for the <HI>sinking Interest</HI> of the Common-wealth? When the <HI>Ark of God</HI> is just ready to <HI>depart</HI> from us, and with it, all our Privileges, to be careless and unconcerned about <HI>re∣moving</HI> the <HI>Cause</HI> of the divine Displeasure, must be <HI>unpar∣donable</HI> Stupidity. We have every Thing to awaken our Zeal, and animate to Diligence in our great Work. Our Mouths may soon be stopped, and we called to seal our Testimony with our own Blood. What therefore we have to do for God, the <HI>Souls</HI> of our Hearers, and for our <HI>Country,</HI> we should do quickly, and <HI>with all our Might.</HI></P>
<P><HI>3dly,</HI> PARENTS and <HI>Governors</HI> of <HI>Families,</HI> should use their Authority and Influence, for the reforming a corrupt and wicked Generation. Upon a careful Enquiry, we shall find, that almost all the prevailing Corruptions of the Times, spring from the Want of proper Government, Discipline, and Instruction in Families, which are <HI>Nurseries</HI> where Youth are sormed for the Public, when they are
<PB N="34" REF="007373_0034_102B8BC1B79B9C68"/>most <HI>susceptible</HI> of any Impressions, and most like to <HI>retain</HI> them. Then the <HI>Foundation</HI> is most commonly laid for their being <HI>Blessings</HI> or <HI>Plagues,</HI> to the World.—It can't easily be expressed, how much the Welfare of Church and State depends on the <HI>proper Management</HI> of the rising Generation. The <HI>first</HI> Part of Education enters much <HI>farther</HI> into Life, has a <HI>greater Influence</HI> on the Whole of Persons <HI>future</HI> Conduct, than most imagine; and an <HI>Error here</HI> is often attended with a long Train of <HI>pernicious</HI> Consequences. <HI>Ungoverned Families,</HI> where Children and Servants are not instructed in the great Things of Religion, but trained up in <HI>Ignorance,</HI> and suffered to walk in the <HI>Ways of their own Heart,</HI> and in the <HI>Sight of their own Eyes,</HI> are the <HI>Bane</HI> of Societies, and do unknown Mischief in the World; and such should tremble to think, how much of the <HI>common Guilt</HI> will be found at their Door, and how deep a Share they will have in the <HI>Ruin</HI> of their Country, if, when their Sons and Daughters make themselvs vile, they don't restrain them. Would <HI>Parents</HI> and <HI>Masters</HI> conscientiously discharge their important Trust to their Children and Servants, open to them the <HI>great Truths</HI> of Christianity, and solemly impress them on their Con∣sciences, paint out the <HI>fatal Consequences</HI> of Sin; the <HI>Beauty</HI> of Holiness, the <HI>Excellency</HI> of a Life spent in serving God and their Generation; with affectionate Exhortations, Warnings and Entreaties, and prohibit them from such foolish Diversions, and extravagant Pleasures, as debauch their Minds, and spoil their Morals; innure them to Temperance, Sobriety, Industry and Frugality, enforcing all by an Example of Piety and Virtue; what <HI>happy Influence</HI> would it have, to produce the Reformation, that is so much wanted! What <HI>delightful</HI> Prospect would it afford, to behold a Generation rising up to serve God, to support his Cause, and hand down Religion to those that are yet unborn! Surely such as have any Regard for the Glory of God, the Welfare of their Posterity, or the Felicity of their Country, dare not live in the Neglect of so reasonable and necessary a Duty. In a Word, Persons
<PB N="35" REF="007373_0035_102B8BC346873BF0"/>of <HI>every</HI> Station, Character and Relation in Life, should think themselves concerned, to <HI>contribute</HI> all that lies in their Power, towards <HI>reforming</HI> this corrupt and licentious Age. And surely, if we feel <HI>any warm Zeal</HI> for the Honour of <HI>Religion,</HI> any <HI>due Affection</HI> for our dear <HI>Country,</HI> or any <HI>Compassion</HI> to those abandon'd Sinners, who are pulling down the Wrath of God on themselves and us, we shall be vigorous and active, in this laudable Design. I can't leave this Head, without adding my earnest Wish, that Men of Influence and public Spirit, would, according to the Example set them in their Mother Country, endea∣vour to set up in the several Parts of the Land, <HI>Societies for Reformation of Manners,</HI> founded on such a <HI>Plan,</HI> as that Persons of <HI>different</HI> Denominations might unite in them.</P>
<P N="3">III. WE ought to acknowledge our <HI>Dependance</HI> on God, and look to Heaven for Direction and Assistance, against our Enemies; with a deep Sense of the <HI>Insufficiency</HI> of human Wisdom and Strength, without divine Help. Nothing is more provoking to God, than for a People to cast off their Dependance upon him; overlook <HI>his Hand</HI> in all the signal Dispensations of his Providence, and act as tho' the <HI>Source</HI> of their Safety was wholly <HI>in themselves.</HI> Too much of this <HI>Spirit</HI> of <HI>Infidelity</HI> has evidently appeared in the <HI>British</HI> Nation, which I look upon as one of the darkest Symptoms upon us. It was Matter of Grief and Astonishment, to all that had any Sense of Religion left, to observe how very little Regard we showed to an <HI>over∣ruling Providence,</HI> by our public Conduct in the late War
<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">The Conduct of <HI>New-England,</HI> in taking <HI>Cape-Breton,</HI> must be excepted. See Mr. <HI>Prince</HI>'s excellent Sermon, on the Occasion.</NOTE>, how we seemed to ground all our Expectations on our <HI>own Wisdom</HI> and <HI>Power,</HI> and as it were, bid Defiance to God and Man. This mournful Observation is abundantly confirmed, by the ingenious and serious Author of a Pamphlet, entitled, <HI>Britain's Remembrancer:</HI> Having men∣tioned some such Passages in the <HI>public Prints,</HI> as these, <HI>viz.</HI> "Our Fleets are in high Spirits, <HI>&amp;c."</HI> <Q>We only
<PB N="36" REF="007373_0036_102B8BC588CF89F8"/>desire the Arm of Flesh may decide the Quarrel.</Q> <Q>Let <HI>England</HI> but take Care of her Fleets, and what has she to fear?</Q> In all which, says he, there is so far from any Appearance of a <HI>Sense</HI> of <HI>Dependance upon Heaven,</HI> that we seem rather desirous to stand by our <HI>own Strength,</HI> than be beholding to the God of Battles. And speaking of declaring War with <HI>Spain,</HI> he adds, <Q>I appeal to Thousands, who saw it declared, whether there appeared in the Behaviour and Conversation of the People of <HI>London,</HI> on that Occasion, the least Sense of Humanity for their Fellow-Creatures, that were like to perish in it, or the least Dependance on Heaven, for the Success of it; or whether the Spirit which reigned at that Time in <HI>England,</HI> was not a Spirit of Insolence, and Defiance both of God and Man.</Q> That an Account of one of the most <HI>remarkable</HI> Transactions in the whole War, in which there was such a Series of <HI>eminent Dangers,</HI> and <HI>signal Deliverances,</HI> should be wrote by a <HI>Clergyman</HI>
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Vide Anson</HI>'s Voyage, by his Chaplain.</NOTE>, with scarce the <HI>least Acknowledgement</HI> of the <HI>Hand</HI> of <HI>God,</HI> in any of them, shows what a Spirit of Impiety and Infi∣delity reigned in the Nation; and 'tis hard to say, whether the Stupidity, or Wickedness of such a Conduct, be the greater.—Who that has the least Acquaintance with ancient or modern History, but must observe, that the <HI>Rise</HI> and <HI>Fall</HI> of States and Empires, spring from <HI>unforeseen Causes,</HI> and turn on <HI>such Incidents,</HI> as the Sagacity of the wisest Politicians could not discover, nor the greatest human Power prevent! How constantly is the Observation of the wise Man verified
<NOTE N="§" PLACE="foot">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> i. 3 and 18.</NOTE>, <HI>The Race is not to the Swift, nor the</HI> Battle <HI>to the</HI> Strong. Vain Man thinks himself so very wise, his Schemes so well-concerted, so secretly laid, that nothing can defeat them; but, God says, <HI>He will destroy the Wisdom of the Wise, and bring to nothing the Un∣derstanding of the Prudent.</HI> Where is the Wise, the great Statesman and Politician? Where are all his fine Schemes?
<PB N="37" REF="007373_0037_102B8BC75B9CB1F0"/>Has not God <HI>made foolish, the Wisdom of this World?</HI> Does he not often suffer them to take such foolish and destruc∣tive Counsels, as tend to their own Ruin? He makes Diviners mad, turns the wise Men backward, and makes their Knowledge foolish
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Isai. xliv. 25.</NOTE> <HI>Ahitophel,</HI> was a great Politi∣cian; the Oracle of his Day; how confident were many, that his superior <HI>Sagacity,</HI> would have secured <HI>Success</HI> to <HI>Absolom</HI>'s Conspiracy; but how easily was it, by a Method altogether <HI>unexpected,</HI> turned into Foolishness.</P>
<P>WE may boast of our <HI>Strength,</HI> by Sea and Land; of our <HI>Valour</HI> and <HI>Wisdom;</HI> imagine our Schemes are so well contrived, that nothing will prevent their Success: Yet if God be not for us, our <HI>Strength</HI> will be but <HI>Weakness;</HI> our <HI>Wisdom,</HI> but <HI>Folly;</HI> and we shall fall an easy Prey to our ambitious Foes. 'Tis infinitely easy with God, to defeat the Devices of the deepest Policy. What Madness therefore and Folly, as well as great Wickedness, is it, to put our Confidence in an <HI>Arm</HI> of <HI>Flesh?</HI> And we should tremble at the Thoughts of it, when God has said, <HI>Cursed be he that putteth his Trust in Man, and maketh Flesh his Arm.</HI> And surely we shall be more <HI>inexcusable,</HI> than any Nation under Heaven, if we cast off our Dependance upon God, when he has repeatedly, in a most remarkable Manner, appeared for our Deliverance and Salvation. Let us labour therefore to feel in our selves, and to raise in others, a Disposition, humbly to acknowledge God, in all our public Concerns, at this <HI>critical Juncture,</HI> saying with the Prophet
<NOTE PLACE="foot" N="¶">Hosea xiv. 3.</NOTE>, ASHUR <HI>shall not save us; we will not ride upon Horses, neither will we say any more to the Work of our Hands, Ye are our Gods, for in thee the Fatherless findeth Mercy.</HI></P>
<P N="4">IV. WHILE our Eyes are to Heaven, for Direction and Assistance, we should <HI>vigorously exert</HI> ourselves in our own <HI>Defence,</HI> by all those <HI>Means</HI> that the Providence of God has put into our Power. To pretend to rely on the Al∣mighty for Protection, in Time of Danger, while we
<PB N="38" REF="007373_0038_102B8BC9AE3836E0"/>carelessly neglect those Methods of securing ourselves, which are pointed out in his Providence, is not to trust, but to mock and tempt him. When <HI>Jacob</HI> was in eminent Danger, from the Fury of his enraged Brother, he goes to God as his only Refuge; but at the same Time, con∣trives the most <HI>politic</HI> Method to divert, or to stand the Shock of his Wrath
<NOTE N="§" PLACE="foot">Gen. XXXII. 9.13.</NOTE>. DAVID went forth in the Name of the God of <HI>Israel,</HI> to meet the insulting <HI>Philistine,</HI> but did not go without the <HI>Instruments</HI> of <HI>Death,</HI> which he could best use; a <HI>Sling</HI> and a <HI>Stone</HI>
<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">1 Sam. xvii. 45, 49.</NOTE>. And why need I speak of <HI>Joshua, Gideon, Jephtha,</HI> and the Worthies of old, who did such Wonders by Faith; was it not in the Use of <HI>proper Means?</HI> They <HI>waxed valiant in Battle, and put to flight the Armies of the Aliens.</HI></P>
<P>WHEN God has appointed Means for our Safety, care∣lessly to neglect them, vainly imagining <HI>Deliverance</HI> will come in some <HI>miraculous</HI> Way, is not <HI>Faith,</HI> but <HI>Folly;</HI> not <HI>Confidence,</HI> but <HI>Madness.</HI> And who does not see, that the present <HI>Defenceless State</HI> of our Southern Provinces, is not the Effect of <HI>Trust</HI> and <HI>Dependance</HI> on God, but either of <HI>meer Sloth,</HI> or <HI>sordid Covetousness.</HI></P>
<P>WE shall not, I presume, pretend that our present Secu∣rity arises from our having so much a <HI>greater</HI> Sense of Religion; Disposition to acknowledge God, and depend upon him, than <HI>our Neighbours.</HI> Must we not rather con∣fess, it flows from the <HI>Want</HI> of a becoming Sensibility of the invaluable Privileges we enjoy, and of the Greatness of our Danger, tho' it be so near and apparent.—But I trust, after all that has been said, to open our Eyes and alarm our Fears, we shall not any longer fold our Hands together, and cry, <HI>A little more Sleep, and a little more Slum∣ber.</HI> 'Tis <HI>high Time</HI> to look about us, and vigorously fall upon every proper Method of Defence.</P>
<P><PB N="39" REF="007373_0039_102B8BCC33D6EB78"/>
WHAT a Pity, that at such a Time, there should be any <HI>Contention</HI> between our <HI>Governors,</HI> and respective <HI>Assemblies,</HI> but who should be <HI>most</HI> forward and zealous in the Service of their <HI>King</HI> and <HI>Country.</HI> All private and <HI>selfish</HI> Designs; all petty Disputes and Contentions, should be swallowed up in a <HI>disinterested</HI> View to, and Concern for, the public Good. Of what Importance is it, that our Representatives should have <HI>enlarged Views,</HI> of the public Interest, and a <HI>deep Sense,</HI> how much the Welfare of their Country, depends upon <HI>their Conduct,</HI> in this difficult Day.—Nothing can be plainer, than that a <HI>parsimonious</HI> Spirit, at such a Time, opens a Door to the most <HI>extravagant</HI> Expence. To do Things by <HI>Halves,</HI> is worse, than doing nothing at all. This we have learnt by fatal Experience. What £. 10,000 would have done, when we <HI>first</HI> had the Alarm, £. 100,000, 'tis probable, will not <HI>now</HI> effect; and 'tis constantly <HI>increasing</HI> on our Hands, thro' the Vigilance, Activity, and continual Pre∣parations of our Enemies. And should they by our Delays, and <HI>stingy</HI> Provisions for Defence, thro' Fear of putting the Country to Charges, make it the Seat of a long distressing War, there is no computing the Expence, and Number of Lives it may cost. <HI>War</HI> is, indeed, to be deprecated; both Conquerors, and Conquered, are sure to feel the sad Effects of it, more or less; and <HI>Peace</HI> is so great a Blessing, that it is to be <HI>pursued</HI> by all just and rational Methods. But the Way to have Peace in the present Case, is to make a speedy and vigorous Pre∣paration for War: Had this been done more seasonably, it might have prevented all we now fear. There seems but two possible Ways left, to avoid the War we are threatned with from <HI>France.</HI> The one, tamely to <HI>submit</HI> to their unrighteous Encroachments; quietly resign up our Possessions, and all our Privileges, into the Hands of a lawless Tyrant; and expose ourselves and Posterity, to the mad Zeal and Fury, of cruel persecuting Bigots.— The other is, to let them speedily know, that we have it in our Power to <HI>force</HI> them, to reasonable Terms, and
<PB N="40" REF="007373_0040_102B8BCDC33430C0"/><HI>oblige</HI> them to keep within their own Limits; and I need not say which, both Duty and Interest, lead us to take.</P>
<P>WERE the several Provinces thoroughly engaged, to take some speedy, vigorous Steps, for the Protection and Defence of the Land, it might strike such Dread into our Enemies, whose Insolence and Courage, arise chiefly from our Sloth and Stupidity, as might divert the Storm that is now gathering fast upon us. And methinks we have every Thing to awaken our <HI>Fears,</HI> and animate our <HI>Hopes.</HI> On the one Hand, there is Poverty, Slavery, Persecution and Death; on the other, a fruitful Country, pleasant Habitations, <HI>British</HI> Liberty, and what is dearer than all, undefiled Christianity. And do not let us put far away the evil Day. <HI>Delays</HI> may prove of the most fatal Con∣sequence; our Danger may be much <HI>nearer,</HI> and much <HI>greater</HI> than we imagine.</P>
<P>SHOULD the <HI>French,</HI> agreeable to their known Perfidy, before they declare War, send a Fleet, with a large Army of well-disciplined Troops, to lay waste, and destroy our Coasts; while the <HI>savage Natives,</HI> whose tender Mercies, are Cruelty, join them in falling on our <HI>Frontiers,</HI> what a a distressing Scene opens to our View? Our Sea-port <HI>Towns</HI> sack'd, and laid in Ashes!—Our Country ravaged! our <HI>Houses</HI> plundered!—The Voice of Lamentation and Woe heard in our Streets!—Our <HI>Men</HI> slaughtered!—Our <HI>Wives</HI> and <HI>Daughters</HI> delivered to the Lusts and Fury of a lawless Soldiery!—Our helpless <HI>Babes</HI> dashed against the Stones!—Men looking on the right Hand for Help, and on the Left there is none to deliver! Their Hearts failing them for Fear, while they hear the confused Noise of War; see Garments rolled in Blood, and the insulting Foe spreading Desolation and Ruin all around!—But I must stop:—The <HI>tragical</HI> Scene is too distressing, even in <HI>distant</HI> Prospect! And is there a <HI>emote Probability,</HI> is there <HI>appa∣rent Danger,</HI> of our being thrown into such universal Tumult and Confusion and shall we not <HI>exert</HI> ourselves, in making the most speedy and effectual Preparation against it? What Folly, what Madness; nay I may
<PB N="41" REF="007373_0041_102B8BCF4EB117D8"/>say, what <HI>Cruelty</HI> to ourselves and Posterity, is it, to run the Risk of having Desolation, Anguish and Despair, spread thro' the Land, by a sudden Invasion, while we are so shamefully unprepared, to make any proper Defence.</P>
<P>WE have every Thing to alarm, to rouse and animate us, in such a Day as this, when all that is valuable, all that is dear, lies at Stake. Shall we tamely suffer our delightful Possessions, to be taken from us?—become the Dupes and Slaves of a <HI>French</HI> Tyrant? What!—sacrifice our precious Liberty, our Property, and what is more, our Religion, to our Sloth? entail Misery, Slavery, and Ruin, on our Posterity, by our Indolence and Cowardice! God forbid! 'Tis high Time, to awake, to call up all the <HI>Briton</HI> in us, every Spark of <HI>English</HI> Valour; chearfully to offer our Purses, our Arms, and our Lives, to the Defence of our Country, our holy Religion, our excellent Constitution, and invaluable Liberties. For what is Life, without <HI>Liberty?</HI> without the Enjoyment of the glorious <HI>Gospel</HI> of Christ, depending on the <HI>Will</HI> of a <HI>Tyrant</HI> and exposed to all the <HI>Insults</HI> of persecuting <HI>Bigots?</HI> 'Tis not worth hav∣ing. A <HI>free-born Briton,</HI> should disdain the Life of a Slave;—better,—far better, bravely to <HI>sacrifice</HI> it to the Defence of our Religion and Country, than to <HI>survive</HI> the dismal Day, when these Regions of Light and Liberty, shall be overspread with Ignorance, Superstition, and Ty∣ranny. And had we but the <HI>Spirit</HI> of our <HI>brave Ancestors,</HI> who chearfully ventured their Lives, and resigned all the Comforts thereof, in an howling Wilderness, that they might hand down to us the inestimable Privileges we now enjoy: Were <HI>we,</HI> I say, animated with the same <HI>heroic</HI> Spirit, in the Defence of them; with the same ardent De∣sire of leaving them <HI>inviolate</HI> to our Posterity;—did but the <HI>noble Ardor</HI> kindle from Breast to Breast, I doubt not, by the Smiles of Heaven, we should soon make our Ene∣mies flee before us, and again sit quietly under our Vines and Fig-trees, and eat the Good of the Land. <HI>Which God of his infinite Mercy grant,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>AMEN.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

