<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-04-21</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Check for blanks. Checked for signatures. Checked for #s. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N08483">
<STC T="E">10849</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99001440</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="010849_0000_0F85232F88547240"/>
<PB REF="010849_0001_0F85232FAAF71988"/>
<HEAD>A CARD.</HEAD>
<P>MR. Axe and Mr. Hammer being <HI>solicited</HI> by a Num∣ber of their Brother Freeholders and Freemen of the City of New-York, to return their hearty Thanks to their good Friends, Mr. Hatchway and Mr. Bowline, have <HI>con∣sented,</HI>—and think proper to do it <HI>in this public Manner;</HI>—and to assure them, that the <HI>Leather-Aprons (a very respecta∣ble Body)</HI> are clearly of their Opinion, That it is TRADE, and not LAW supports our Families:—And honest <HI>Jolt</HI> the Cartman, says he never got Six-Pence for riding Law-Books, tho' he gets many Pounds from the Merchants,—So that with many Thanks for your sensible good Card—<HI>we</HI> all say, as <HI>you</HI> say,—</P>
<P>NO LAWYER IN THE ASSEMBLY.—</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Tradesman's-Hall,</HI> <DATE>29<HI>th February,</HI> 1768.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

