<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-05-15</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Check for blanks. Checked for signatures. Checked for #s. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Corrected 28 $-groups. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N30111">
<STC T="E">39991</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99005977</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="039991_0000_1015884763C889A8"/>
<PB REF="039991_0001_10158849E998E918"/>
<P>A DIALOGUE BETWEEN THOMAS SWEET-SCENTED, WILLIAM ORONOCO, Planters, both Men of good Understanding, and Justice LOVE-COUNTRY, who can speak for himself. RECOMMENDED To the Reading of the Planters.</P>
<P>By a sincere Lover of <HI>VIRGINIA.</HI></P>
<P><HI>WILLIAMSBURG:</HI> Printed by WILLIAM PARKS. M,DCC,XXXII.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="dialogue">
<PB N="3" REF="039991_0002_1015884B72655A18"/>
<HEAD>A DIALOGUE, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>HOW d'ye, how d'ye, Neighbour? Well, how goes the World?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am pretty well I thank you, only troubled a good deal in Mind.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why what's the Matter, Man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Matter! Matter enough: I have been at the Warehouse, to have some of my Tobacco inspected.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah! Well, pray how is it? I want sadly to know a little: How do you like these new Officers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my Troth, <HI>Tommas,</HI> I can't tell what to say to it; I am really nonplust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prithee tell me how it fared with you: Let me hear a little.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hear a little! You shall hear a great deal, if you go to that. Can any Body say, that it is not very hard upon a poor Man, to have Part of his Labour burnt by these Inspectors, because, forsooth they don't like our Tobacco? when at the same time, for aught I can see, they are no better Judges of it than any of us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis very hard indeed Neighbour: For my Part, I can't by any manner of Means approve this new Law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Approve it! No, who can? For they tell me, that if our Tobacco is not 800, they won't pay us for the Cask.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>How so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may depend upon what I tell you, and something worse: For, when I was at the Warehouse, Neighbour <HI>Seconds</HI> brought Two Hogsheads of Tobacco to be viewed, which, to please these Men, he had made above 800: But so it fell out, the Tobacco not
<PB N="4" REF="039991_0003_1015884E9E41C210"/>
having been well handled in the Curing, by pressing it hard to make it that Weight, it turn'd black, (as you know Tobacco will do that is not well lookt after;) and what do you think these unmerciful Officers said to him—Why truly, that it was such black Stuff, unless he would pick it, they must burn it all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, and so if our Tobacco is not 800, they won't pay us for the Cask; and if, to make it that Weight, it turns black under the Press, which, as you say, all Tobacco will do that is'nt well handled, they'll burn it, will they? Things are come to a fine Pass indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Burn it! Ay, up it goes in a Funk, unless you'll pick it; I must say for them, they'll suffer a poor Man to do That. But there's another Circumstance harder than what you've heard: If our Casks are not exactly of such a Gauge, be our Tobacco never so good, they won't pass it: What think you of that? This seems to me to exceed all the rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, there's nothing new in that, d'ye see: There has been for some Years a Law ord'ring us not to make our Hogsheads above such a Size.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed! Well that's what I never knew before: One of our Neighbours, sometime since, did say that's the Truth on't, that we must make them so and so, and luckily I did, but I never knew there was a Law for it; and till this Year, I am sure we never minded it; every Body made their Casks as big as they pleased.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>That can't be denied, but we—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>What then, this that I thought so very hard, is come to Nothing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not to be charged to this new Law, it being—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>It signifies Nothing to talk of it then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing, d'ye call it? I always thought we were obliged to con—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, I mean 'tis not material, not worth Noticing in this Case, in this new Law, where there are so many other Things that pinch us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>There I agree with you: I wish with all my Heart <HI>Will,</HI> I could but once understand what our Assembly meant by making such a Law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="5" REF="039991_0004_10158851115A90E0"/>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Find that out if you can: 'Twould puzzle a Philosopher, I believe; <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> they say he is a mighty Man for this Law, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Law; and I must confess I have heard other Gentlemen say so, particularly, that 'tis a good Law for the poor Planters; but, for my Life, I can't see in what.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>We have lost the Justice, he is turned out of the Road to a Plantation on the Left Hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am sorry for it, he is a right honest Man; and if we could have got him into Talk, would have told us all. However, let's stay here, perhaps he may come this Way anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then, as we were saying,—oh—Notwithstanding what so many Folks say, I can't discover One good Thing in the Law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Folks say! Why Man, tho' some Folks say as I told you, there are other Folks that say quite contrary: I am sure I have heard a great many Speeches against it at the Race-Grounds, and at the County-Courts, when the Courts were over, and Men were got together in the Ordinary, speaking their Thoughts freely, with∣out any Liking to it, nay, they have publickly curs'd it: And sure we can't all of us be mistaken.—Why, pray is it not a clear Case, don't we see our Tobacco burnt by the Humour of the In∣spectors? Who can bear such Usage?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Far and softly, <HI>Will:</HI> Don't fly into Passion; that avails nought, you know; for, bear it we must: What can we do? No∣thing but quietly submit:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Quietly submit! Hast thou lived to these Years to be so tame a Creature, as to cry out on such an Occasion, What can we do?—Yes, Yes, something might be done, if we could but con∣fide in one another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>As how, pray? What wou'd thy wise Head propose, ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>My wise Head! Why, my wife Head tells me, that there are a Power of People in some of the <HI>Upper Counties,</HI> and abun∣dance in the <HI>Northern Neck,</HI> that complain as heavily against this Law as we do; and certainly, 'tis as easy as 'tis to jump over a Fence-Rail, for us to get together, and think of something or other that might be done, to force—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="6" REF="039991_0005_10158853F3D7AEC8"/>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pretty Fellow indeed! To force! To force what? Art thou such an Oaf as to talk after this Rate? To force! Force your self headlong into Rebellion, be hanged, lose your Land, and ruin your Family, rather than submit to a Law, the Great Ones and the Rich Ones must submit to as well as we; a Law, whatever at present we may think of it, was undoubtedly designed by our Burgesses for the Good of the Country.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>But hark you <HI>Tom:</HI> What did you talk of Rebellion for, and all that? No, I ask your Pardon there, I did not mean That neither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not mean, No verily I believe thee: Though whatever you meant, would have signified but little; your Meaning woudn't have procured you a Pardon, woudn't have sav'd you from the Gallows: And I must needs say, all our Disturbances are owing to such Wiseacres as you. You pretend to fly in the Face of the Go∣vernment? I charge you on my Friendship to talk no more in this Strain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed <HI>Tom,</HI> I did not consider—But <HI>Tom,</HI> the Justice is coming.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay, Young Man, if he should hear what you have been talking of, I woudn't be in your Coat for—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray <HI>Tom,</HI> be pacified; and since you have declared your self my Friend, advise me seriously how to behave.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Behave! If you are really One of the impatient Crew, and can't wait the Event of this new Regulation, send your Grievances to the Assembly; they say they are to meet in <HI>May.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>In <HI>May!</HI> That's a good one indeed: In <HI>May!</HI> If we car∣ry our Tobacco to the Warehouse, Part of it will be burnt before <HI>May</HI> comes; and if we don't, by what I can learn, no Body will buy it of us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then you must be contented, that's all that I know, I am sure, I'm resolv'd to be so: I am as uneasy, it may be, as some others are, but not quite so fierce; for tho' I can't tell how, in what, nor when, I comfort my self with the Hopes that this Law will help us, that it was not made in vain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say no more, here's the Justice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="7" REF="039991_0006_101588562BC1F720"/>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Day to you, Neighbours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>The like to your Worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>The same to you; Sir,—Let me speak, <HI>Will.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do so then, since you are so fond on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>What News d'ye hear? All the Discourse now, I suppose, is about our new Law: Pray how goes Tobacco at the Warehouses?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go, Master! Some of it goes into the Fire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thrown into the Fire, say'st thou? I am very glad to hear it, exceedingly rejoiced.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>But why, Master, are you so glad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah, Master, why so rej—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be quiet, can't you. What makes you so glad, Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a certain Sign the Inspectors are honest Men, and do their Duty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Their Duty! 'Tis very hard upon us in the mean Time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>No such Thing, I promise you: In the first Place, don't you know good Tobacco as well as they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>To be sure we do.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>To be sure we do.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then why do you carry such Tobacco to them, that you know they must burn? But however, since I have happened with you, and we are entred upon the Subject, if you are willing to be informed, and are resolved to govern your selves accordingly, be patient, speak one at a Time, and you'll both of you be made easy, never fear.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>We shall do as you desire, Sir, and think our selves much obliged to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>We want, may it please your Worship, to hear what may be said on the Side of this same Law, and what Good it will do us poor Planters; for we are strangely pestered with odd Notions about it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>I don't wonder at it; the best Things are the most liable to be abused: Though it astonishes me, that so plain a Law as this is, should have so many Enemies. A Law, not only the best that ever was made for the Country, for our Trade in general, but the best for the poor Planters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="8" REF="039991_0007_1015885803CE0790"/>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Worship said, for the poor Planters?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>I did so; and that You may comprehend me the bet∣ter, tell me the Parts of it You dislike, and I'll explain their Mean∣ing to You.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dislike!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dislike! Dislike! Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay, tell me what you grumble at.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Grumble at!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Burning, <HI>Tom.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Grumble at! Why, Sir, don't they burn our Tobacco; and is not that enough to make any Man grumble?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>I own they do burn Tobacco, and this Year they'll burn a great deal of Tobacco; for a worse Year for Tobacco we have not had these 20 Years: But what then? If they burn Yours, they'll as readily burn mine, and some of every Man's they'll burn, if we don't sort it carefully before we carry it to them. And now let me ask you a Question, answer me honestly? Is the Tobacco the In∣spectors burn, fit for any thing else? Can either of you say, 'tis fit for any Market? If not, then such Trash ought to be destroy'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Master, since you have put it so very home to us, we must own, the Tobacco they burn, is not good for much; but then, as bad as it is, we always got something for it, and so, I don't doubt, we should this Year, were we at Liberty; which, we confess, has been a very indefferent Year for Tobacco.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Therefore pray consider: The Accounts we have had for several Years past, from every Port in <HI>Great-Britain</HI> our Tobacco is carry'd to, are full of Complaints, that we make more than all <HI>Europe</HI> can consume, and a great Part of it such Trash, as no Pur∣chaser will meddle with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>If this be true, Why then, Master, don't they stint us?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stint you! It has been tried, and found ineffectual: And no wonder; for tho' it lessen'd the Quantity, it did not mend the Quality; there was Trash still in Proportion to clog the Markets; and so there would be, reduce the Number of Plants as low as you please: Let us be restrained never so much, we find Ways to make it up, and you own you can fell all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="9" REF="039991_0008_10158859A2761520"/>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do: But Burning, Master! That's the terrible Article.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a Bit; 'tis no such terrible Thing. Isn't the Coun∣try almost ruined? And let me tell you, this very Year our Ruin had been compleated, had not this excellent Law interposed, which destroys all bad Tobacco, and suffers none but good to be exported to the Markets in <HI>Europe.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>But spare me, Sir: What have we, who sell our Tobacco in the Country, to do with the Markets Abroad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you don't send any Home, you must know all of it goes Home; and that a great many of us ship our Tobacco on our own Venture to the Markets: Thousands of Hogsheads are every Year consigned upon Freight to the Merchants in <HI>London, Glascow, Bristol,</HI> and other <HI>Ports:</HI> And can you be such a Simpleton, as not to consider, that the better the Markets are in <HI>Europe,</HI> the more Money you'll sell your Tobacco for here: Or, that when all Trash is destroyed, and our Staple gets a Reputation, the Price for it will advance, and in all Likelihood the Consumption of it increase.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>There seems to be some Sense in that, Master; the better the Commodity, the better it will sell, to be sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast hit it, <HI>Will:</HI> The Lowness of the Markets, I have been long since convinced, is not altogether occasion'd by the Quantity: Therefore, if under the Direction of this Law, we lessen the Quantity, and mend the Quality, by destroying the Trash, we drive the right Nail.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you in Earnest conceit so, Master?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>No less, my Word for it: If, when your Tobacco is well cull'd, you get as much for 800 that is Clean and Neat, as you could do before this Law for 1200 Tag-rag and Bob-tail, what In∣jury or Injustice pray will this Law do you? The naked Truth, <HI>Tom,</HI> is this, <HI>Bad Tobacco destroyed, stamps a Value upon the re∣maining Good,</HI> which will for ever be depreciated by a Mixture.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>I grant it, Sir; but I fear we must wait some Time to see all this come to pass.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you were to wait, you would be no Loser at the Long Run; but there is no Room for such Fears: Have but Pa∣tience, and this very Year you'll see it come to pass. Send 2000
<PB N="10" REF="039991_0009_1015885D8B217CC0"/>
Weight of Tobacco to the Warehouse, if the Inspectors pass but 1200 of it, I will engage to give you more, in Money or Goods, for the 1200, than you could sell the 2000 for.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Engage to give us more! Will you so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, tho' I am no Dealer, only to shew you what you may do.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>But, Sir, after we have been at the Trouble, and perhaps some Expence, in carrying our Tobacco to the Inspectors, that they should have Authority to burn it, That is what galls us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pretty Business indeed! Don't both of you boast that you know good Tobacco as well as they? Is it not, therefore, un∣reasonable to complain of what you may prevent, by carefully Sorting of it before you carry it to them? And then, the devious and designing Men would not have that Handle for Clamour and Noise, nor would it be so much in their Power to raise foolish Sto∣ries against the Law, because they see Tobacco burnt, that a right honest Man, tender of the Welfare of his Country, would not of∣fer to Sale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>What your Worship says is very right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Man with half an Eye might see it: 'Tis your Im∣patience that spoils all: You eagerly catch up every idle Story that artful Men, for private Interest, propagate among you; and then you impute them to the Law: When, lack-a-day, the Sense and Meaning of the Law is no way concerned; all your Uneasiness arise from their wicked Insinuations. Let me tell you, 'tis much easier to raise a Dust than to lay it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis but too true, I have seen enough of that, Master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, you begin to be convinc'd, do you? Let us then next reflect upon the great Advantage of these Inspectors Notes, which they give you for your Tobacco after they have pass'd it; Notes full as good as so much ready Money, the same as so much Cash, and as such will be received in Payment at any Store, for what Goods you want: Your Tobacco you may parcel out, into as many of them as you please, so as to be able to pay this Man 50 Pounds of Tobacco, another 100, and another 200; in short, make Payment of any Debt: And thus, according to the Price of
<PB N="11" REF="039991_0010_1015885FDA9CF530"/>
Tobacco, these Notes will answer 10, 20, 30, or 40 Shillings in Money, in any Part of the Neck you live in:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>We were told that we were to have Notes, but never dreamt of this good Accompt they are like to turn to; that Thing of Burn∣ing was always uppermost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did'st thou never read the Law?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Have you, Neighbour?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>No truly, I can't say I have.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has it been read to you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thought as much; clever Fellows indeed! you have been finding Fault with a Law you never read, never heard read, a Law you know nothing of, but from the Reports of lawless Mouths, who meant, by what they said, to impose upon you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am inclined to think what your Worship has told us is the Truth, I must acknowledge the Imposition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Imposition with a Witness. But as I was saying, by Virtue of these Inspectors Notes, I dare to promise you Goods much cheaper than hitherto you have had them: So that by this Law, you'll not only get more Money for your Tobacco, but you'll pay less for your Goods.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah Master, that's rare News indeed: But how, Sir, how is that to be?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Every Man must say, that knows any thing of your way of Dealing in these Upper parts of the Country, nay, the Store∣keepers will own it, that they were always obliged to be very sharp in the Sale of their Goods, on the Score of the Badness of the Tobac∣co they were generally paid in, and the Risque they run of being Losers by it at Home; and therefore they valued their Goods, rai∣sing the <HI>per Cent.</HI> upon them, not from the prime Cost, but by the Quality of the Tobacco: Insomuch, that when you have had the Name of selling your Tobacco for 10, 12, 15 Shillings per Hundred, in Reality you had not above 4, 5, or 6 Shillings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>What have we been thus used?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="12" REF="039991_0011_10158861620CA108"/>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, marry have you: I have known in a scarce Year, one of these Gentlemen give 3l. 2s. 6d. per Hundred for Tobac∣co, in Goods, the first Cost of which Goods was not above 20<HI>s.</HI> if so much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>If so, we have paid through the Nose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes; but it was with Tobacco not fit to be put there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Sir, the Season is far advanced, and I don't hear that any Price is set upon Inspected Tobacco, or, that many Goods are in the Stores.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Ships are very late in this Year, they came out late; those that failed the first, have had long Passages; they are but just arrived, and few Goods are yet imported: But assure your selves, in a little Time the Face of Affairs will be much changed for the better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>We should rejoice to see it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rest satisfied: <HI>Rome</HI> was not built in a Day: Laws are never made to oppress People, but to relieve them: And this very Law against which there is so much Cavil, is calculated to redress all our Grievances in Trade. The Clamours that oppose it, only shew how corrupt Men are, nothing else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed!—Well, but Master, woudn't a Stint do all these fine Things as well; and then, mayhaps, the Country would be easy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Stint, Noodle! <HI>Tom.</HI> you are enough to provoke me: Are we not now under a Stint? And let me tell you, the most in∣dulgent Stint that could be propos'd for us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's that, Sir! Clear that same Indulgence, if you please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>It wants no Clearing, it speaks its self: But if I must tell you my Story over again, and beat into your Head by Repe∣tition, you shall have it. You remember, before this Law, we were limited by an Act of Assembly to 6000 Plants per Taxable, and some were for reducing us lower, to a less Number; but did that, or will such a Method, remedy the Mischiefs the Country lay under?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can't say it did.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="13" REF="039991_0012_1015886450E7AAD0"/>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say it did! No, it would not do: And therefore I tell you again, we must mend our Staple, as well as lesson the Quan∣tity. But answer me faithfully, Did you make more Tobacco un∣der a Stint, than what, by this Law, in a favourable Year, you may get pass'd by the Inspectors? If you did, then this Law les∣sons the Quantity, and mends the Quality: If you did not, you have no Reason to complain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can't say any thing to it one Way nor t'other; but by your Leave, Sir, under the Stint Law, I could sell all that I made, and that I can't do now: There's the Grievance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>For my Part, I must think, if any Law may be called grievous, 'tis that which cuts us short in the Management of our own Land.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, but Sir, where's the Difference between cutting a Man short in his Labour, and in the Fruit of his Labour; these Laws considered together, the Stint appears the more favourable of the Two, for by That I reap some Advantage from all my Labour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you were the only Person concerned in making of Tobacco, and carried on the whole Trade by your self, it would then be cruel, not to say unjust, to restrain you either Way; be∣cause, the Consequence of your Management would advantage no other Man, neither would it injure any other; but when the Public is taken into the Account, 'tis quite another Argument; and as the whole Country is engaged in the same Trade, every Man in the Country will be more or less affected by the Contrivances of unfair Dealers. This was the Reason why the Assembly, the Guar∣dians of our Trade and Property, entred into these Measures, to prevent, if possible, in this general Commerce, all Fraud and De∣ceit, by making every Man honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is what our Assembly meant, it is Sir? In troth, I think they're honest Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>But let me answer the Bounce you made of Advantage from all your Labour, by which, you declare the Stint the more favourable Law: Don't you know, that the Reward of your La∣bour depends upon the Profit you make at the Winding up of the Bottom? For Instance, suppose now you had 100 Bushels of Wheat
<PB N="14" REF="039991_0013_10158867C1CCF7D0"/>
in the Ear, in several Stacks in your Yard, which you might sell for 2 Shillings the Bushel; and that by the Accident of Fire, half of it was destroyed. Now, only suppose the like Misfortune had befallen every Man in the Country, and that the Price of Wheat by this Casualty advanced, as no Doubt it would, and you could sell the remaining 50 Bushels at 4 Shillings; what's become of the Produce of all your Labour, as you term it? Have you any Rea∣son on the Account of Interest to bewail Burning?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I think not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Case is the same in Tobacco, with this Difference, Tobacco is made better by Part of it (the Trash) being destroied; and for that one Reason, will fetch a better Price: So that, to the extraordinary Labour you are at, in making more Tobacco than you are allow'd to sell, be pleased to place the Advantage you will reap by mending the Quality; and rest assured you'll be well paid for your Pains.</P>
<P>What, perhaps you are resolved not to be convinced.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, we are not obstinate; but you must needs think, we have been strangely prepossest. For, notwithstanding 'tis so very plain, to shew you the Roguery of some that shall be nameless, 'twas confidently buzzed about, as if, by this Law, the Rich in∣tended to ruin the Poor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>None but the worst of Villains could suggest such a Re∣flection: No such Thing, upon my Honour: Consider the Persons concerned in making this Law; Are they not all of them Gentle∣men of Probity and great Integrity? And have they not, by this very Act of theirs, sufficiently testified their Regard for the Public, and their tender Concern for the poor Planters?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, for my Part, I am resolved never to quarrel for the future with what I don't understand: And whenever they din any idle Reports against Laws in my Ears, that are beyond my Capaci∣ty, if your Worship will give me Leave, I'll wait on your Worship with them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do so and welcome, either of you: Don't suffer your selves to be debauched by ne'er a He that wears a Head: 'Tis the Duty of every Magistrate, as the Laws are the Peoples Direction
<PB N="15" REF="039991_0014_1015886A406A9140"/>
in moral Actions, to give them all the Light they can, into the In∣tent and Meaning of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>We thank you, Master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Have you done with Objections?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Tommas</HI> has said nothing, Sir, about the Charge of the Warehouses, and the Inspectors Salaries.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>What of them, pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, it may be, this is a Rout about Nothing too: But the Thing <HI>Will.</HI> means, is the Charge the Country is put to on those Two Accounts, the Houses, and Officers Salaries.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Country put to! Why the Whole is defray'd out of the Money paid by the Shippers, for Passing their Tobacco.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>But we poor Men don't ship any Tobacco.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you are not concerned in it one Way nor t'other; it rests upon the Merchants. But, if Charges and Expences are drawn in to make the Cry the louder, let what follows make a thankful Impression upon your Minds, to the Assembly; who, by this Law, have released us from the Tax we paid, under the Stint-Law, to Tellers, for Counting our Plants; from the One Shilling per Hogshead we paid to Rolling-houses; and from the Expence of Receivers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>These Things were nothing to us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you did not pay them, they did who purchased your Tobacco; and if they are relieved from these Charges, and are to be paid by the Captains of the Ships, 4<HI>s.</HI> per Hogshead, for the Trouble and Expence of Shipping their Tobacco themselves, can't they for this Reason afford to give you the better Price?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cry-mercy: But, Sir, the Shipping of the Tobbacco occa∣sions great Murmurings; they say the Country is not able to do it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Willing Minds would go a great Way towards it: In the Lower Parts of the Country, where the Rivers are broad, and the Navigation difficult, they may not be able; but towards the Heads of the Rivers it might be done: But this Complaint is No∣thing; for, if the Publick are not in a Condition to comply with That Clause of the Law, they may depend upon Relief, when the Assembly meet; who, without any Question, will make such Al∣terations
<PB N="16" REF="039991_0015_1015886BC482DC88"/>
and Amendments, as they find, in the Execution of it, are wanting, to make all Parties concerned in it, easy. And we shall deserve to be branded for the maddest People on the Face of the whole Earth, not to acquiesce; but by malicious and ignorant ran∣dom Judgments, endeavour to defeat such good Purposes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>These Hopes, Master, as much a Convert as I am to <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, do administer more Comfort; for, who can be discontented, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> knows what the Assembly aim'd at by this Law, and that they'll leave no Stone unturned, to secure to us the good Things contained in it; most especially, more Money for our Tobacco, and less for our Goods; that we mayn't pay away so much as we receive.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>There are one or two Particulars more I must trouble your Worship with, that I have heard discoursed of, as Grievances.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, let me hear them; make Dispatch; it grows late,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why one is, That tho' they are at no Charge for Rolling-Houses, they say they are strangely hamper'd, having no Place to lay the Goods in, they import: Indeed this is no Concern of ours who buy our Goods in the Country. Then they cry, that many of them had Wharfs and Landing Places, which are become useless.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>As to convenient Places for lodging their Goods, Are not the former Storehouses still in Being, where they may put their Goods? No Man that imports Goods, is destitute of Friends that live on the River, where so many Wharfs and Landing Places, you say, are be∣come useless, but he may have the Benefit of the most commodious in Situation near his Dwelling, to lodge his Goods, since the Cap∣tains of the Ships are so obliging to put them or. Shore where-ever they are desired. As to their Uselesness on other Accounts, 'tis of no Weight; if it doth deprive some People of any Profit they were for∣merly to them, 'tis a private Stake, and must be given up to the Good of the Publick. This is all you have to say. I presume?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, Master, we thank you; we had been sadly on't, if we had not had the good Fortune to meet with your Worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Since you esteem it so, I am glad, for your Sakes, that we were so fortunate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay, Master, 'tis very lucky for Neighbour <HI>Will.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hush, <HI>Tom,</HI> Hush.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="17" REF="039991_0016_1015886E310894F0"/>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why for <HI>Will,</HI> more than for your self?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing in the universal World, only <HI>Tommas,</HI> now your Worship has made him light-heel'd, now your Worship has made it out that 'tis a good Law for the poor Planters, has a Mind to be jocose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Upon my Conscience 'tis a good Law for every Body: I have not told you half the good Things contained in it; I have confined my self, for your better Information, to the Trade in the Country; when alas, if I was to launch out, into the Effects of it Abroad, 'tis impossible to say when I should have done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed, Sir!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed, Sir!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are obliged to your Worship, for this seasonable In∣struction: We shall expect to find what your Worship has told us▪ and in the mean Time, shall do our Endeavours to reconcile our Neighbours to so beneficial a Law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do so: But before we part, since we have conversed <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> much on this Subject, and I have taken so much Pains <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> I can't think of leaving you without a Word or two of <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> which, on all Occasions, remember to put in Practice. <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> become honest Men, minding only your own Business: <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> honour the King, and meddle not with those that are <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Noise and Violence: Submit your selves to every Law: <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Race-grounds, those Schools of Gaming and Drunkenness <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> go near the County-Courts, unless Business calls you thither <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> when it doth, return Home as soon as it is done: Make <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> your principal Employment, this coming Summer, to look well to your Crops, especially your Tobacco, which ought to be tended with the same Care that Annuals are in a Garden: And, since you are indulged the Privilege of making as much Tobacco as you can, make it as good as you can. The Inspectors don't take Pleasure in burning of Tobacco; 'tis what the Law requires of them, and they are under the Obligation of an Oath, a very great Penalty, to destroy all that is bad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="18" REF="039991_0017_10158870671606F8"/>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>But, Master, out of Spite and Malice they may burn ones Tobacco, and I don't see how we can help it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prove that, and you have your Remedy against them; and you may be assured, such a One wou'd be turned out of his Office, with Infamy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>But then, they may be more nice in Transfer-Tobacco, on Account of the Penalty, if, upon a second View, 'tis not found good; and most of That belongs to poor Planters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Inspectors are bound by Oath, to take Care of the Goodness of the Crop-Tobacco, as well as the Transfer; and, I don't question, they perform their Duty in both: But the Cause why the Transfer-Tobacco is more found Fault with, is, Many more are concerned in That than the Other; and, as 'tis generally carried to the Warehouse in Parcels, People think it hard to see so much of each Parcel rejected, as is often done, and as this Year it deserves: But, at the same Time, they should consider, that the Crop-Tobacco undergoes as strict an Examination, and has as much in Proportion, condemned to the Fire. The Truth is, The great Noise that's made, about the Strictness used in Transfer-Tobacco, proceeds from a malicious Insinuation, as if the Inspectors only re∣garded their own Interest, lest the Transfer-Tobacco should be re∣fused, and turned upon their Hands by the Publick Creditors, if found faulty; but I can see no manner of Reason to apprehend any ill Consequence to any Planter, from this Observation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>If we are under no Hardship from hence, I must say, No Man living, and dealing in Tobacco, has any Fault to find with this Law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Justice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, let me end with you: And, if under this Regu∣lation, we send Home more good Tobacco than can be consumed, fear not, my Lads, with this Method we may expect a Stint; there is no other Way to recover our Trade, which, This Year, had it not been for This Law, would have demolish'd us all. God be with you. Farewel.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="19" REF="039991_0018_1015887237C88C50"/>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Night, Sir: We are much obliged to you.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Huzza! God bless the King, the Governor, Council, and House of Burgesses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis high Time for us to part too: Good by to you, <HI>Will.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will.</SPEAKER>
<P>Adieu: The Justice is a good Man; he gave us very good Advice: But I must go to see a Race sometimes, for all that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, Well: Good Night to you.</P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

