<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet TYPE="text/css" href="http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE><DATE>yyyy-mm-dd</DATE><RESPSTMT><NAME>[name of reviewer]</NAME><RESP>MURP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM></CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>

<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K021000.000">
<STC T="C">T001752</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3314251799</BIBNO>
<VID SET="ECLL">0779900100</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<P><PB REF="1"/>
THE BANISHMENT OF CICERO.</P>
<P>A TRAGEDY.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1>
<P><PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
THE BANISHMENT OF CICERO.</P>
<P>A TRAGEDY.</P>
<P>By RICHARD CUMBERLAND, Es{que} Te, te, Patria, testor, et vos penates patriique dii, me vestra∣rum sedum templorumque causa, me propter salutem meo∣rum civium, quae mihi semper fuit mea carior vita, dimica∣tionem caedemque fugisse.</P>
<P>CIC.</P>
<P>LONDON: Printed for J. WALTER, at Homer's-Head, Charing-Cross. 1761.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="3" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>DRAMATIS PERSONAE.</HEAD>
<P><TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL>L. CALPHURNIUS PISO,</CELL>
<CELL ROWS="2">CONSULS.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>AULUS GABINIUS,</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>P. CLODIUS, TRIBUNE.</CELL>
<CELL></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>M. T. CICERO.</CELL>
<CELL></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>POMP. ATTICUS.</CELL>
<CELL></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>CAIUS PISO FRUGI.</CELL>
<CELL></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>TERENTIA.</CELL>
<CELL></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>TULLIA.</CELL>
<CELL></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>CLODIA</CELL>
<CELL></CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
<P>SCENE, ROME.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>THE BANISHMENT OF CICERO.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1">
<HEAD>ACT I.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1">
<HEAD>SCENE I.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS,</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>Enters alone.</STAGE>
<L>ROMANS, you have your wish; at length you've found</L>
<L>A Tribune; one, who knows your brutal lust</L>
<L>For civil slaughter, and will sate its rage</L>
<L>On the first Spirits of imperial Rome.</L>
<L>I saw you, as you rent your throats for Clodius,</L>
<L>How vulture-like you turn'd aloft in air</L>
<L>Your carrion beaks, and snuft the winds for prey:</L>
<L>And ye shall have it; to the lips in blood,</L>
<L>Patrician blood, I'll steep you; till the days</L>
<L>Of Gracchus shall look white compar'd to mine,</L>
<L>Now Aulus—</L>
<STAGE>Enter A. Gabinius, Consul.</STAGE>
</SP>
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Happiness and length of days</L>
<L>Wait on our Tribune, and my noble Friend!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why how now, Consul, these are terms of office,</L>
<L>And savour of the Fasces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pass on there.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Lictors, &amp;c.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now, my Friend, how looks the day abroad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>To you clear and propitious; to your foes,</L>
<L>And that old scoffing pedant Cicero,</L>
<L>Louring and mournful, as the garb he wears.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say'st thou the garb?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, he hath put on black;</L>
<L>Know you not that? Caius, and all the rest;</L>
<L>The whole Tribe mourns; Terentia too—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well;</L>
<L>'Tis as I wisht it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your new law condemns him,</L>
<L>Which interdicts the elemental uses,</L>
<L>To whomsoever shall have put to death</L>
<L>A Citizen untried.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="7" REF="6"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not the law,</L>
<L>But he himself by this unmanly act</L>
<L>That doth himself condemn: Weak, shallow coward!</L>
<L>I would have had his ruin my own work;</L>
<L>But he runs on my toils, as if he meant</L>
<L>To be my rival in his own destruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hear thou this, Catiline! and ye that bled</L>
<L>At the proud Consul's bidding!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Gabinius,</L>
<L>In my revenge the dead themselves shall join;</L>
<L>And by the quick'ning powers of vengeance rous'd,</L>
<L>The ashes of your brave friend Catiline</L>
<L>Shall leap and burst their urn.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was my Friend,</L>
<L>My brave, unhappy, much-lamented Friend;</L>
<L>With pride I own it: Oh! were this the day,</L>
<L>When, with my foot on yon proud Pleader's neck,</L>
<L>I might proclaim it in the Senate's face,</L>
<L>Up to the beard of Cato.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft you now;</L>
<L>I hold the Senate as our Friends, Gabinius.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang 'em, dull herd, they're each man's friends by turns,</L>
<L>The latest speaker ever has their voices.</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="7"/>
Yon alking gownsman with his bleared eyes,</L>
<L>By dealing forth his own applause amongst them,</L>
<L>And his stale cant of Danger to the State,</L>
<L>Had almost wrought his hearers to the pitch</L>
<L>Of driving Publius Clodius forth from Rome,</L>
<L>The Enemy' of his Country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah! Where met they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I' the Fane of Concord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fane of Concord say'st thou?</L>
<L>I tell thee, Aulus, in that very spot,</L>
<L>Which now they call of Concord, but which soon</L>
<L>Shall prove the scene of civil desolation;</L>
<L>I will make fat the dogs of Rome with slaughter,</L>
<L>E're I will move one foot from out these walls</L>
<L>At their audacious bidding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fear it not;</L>
<L>Their tumult had the life but of a moment;</L>
<L>When strait they fell to prayers and abject tears,</L>
<L>Which I with scorn repuls'd; whereat enrag'd,</L>
<L>Uprose the Tribune Ninnius, and mov'd</L>
<L>That that august Assembly should adopt</L>
<L>The same dark weeds which Marcus Tullius wore,</L>
<L>And dignify his sorrows with their own.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Senate mourn for Cicero? For Cicero</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="8"/>
Have I then toil'd? and have I sow'd my gold</L>
<L>In each base palm, (O wavering worthless Senate)</L>
<L>For him to reap the harvest of my hopes?</L>
<L>My curses on the name!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why rave you thus?</L>
<L>And what am I? hath not my edict power</L>
<L>To shake the Senate from their feeble votes?</L>
<L>And it hath done it; from the Rostrum's height</L>
<L>I have denounc'd my war upon their heads:</L>
<L>I've silenc'd Lucius Lamia's saucy tongue;</L>
<L>Two hundred miles from Rome the exile wanders:</L>
<L>And what more aweful is there in the name</L>
<L>Of Cicero, than Lamia? O my Publius,</L>
<L>Leave we to prey upon the wretched limbs,</L>
<L>And at the head and vital source of all,</L>
<L>Strike; there direct one bold decisive blow,</L>
<L>And live at large hereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Greatly said!</L>
<L>Thy Friendship's warm and animating spirit,</L>
<L>Breath'd on my ripening projects, calls 'em forth</L>
<L>To full-grown life, in the same fruitful period</L>
<L>At once conceiv'd and born; and therefore, Aulus,</L>
<L>Thou shalt receive a fruitful recompence;</L>
<L>Not bare Cilicia; but a richer lot,</L>
<L>Syria, the wealthiest province of the state,</L>
<L>Shall crown thy fortune, shall repair the breach</L>
<L><PB N="10" REF="9"/>
Which thy bold waste has made, and shut out Ruin,</L>
<L>That else might fasten on thy naked state,</L>
<L>And pull thee down to shame.—Of this enough,</L>
<L>This saucy Tribune Ninnius.—'Tis well;</L>
<L>'Tis well. O Memory register that deed!</L>
<L>Yet what of that? Contemptuous silence quell'd</L>
<L>The vain light thought, and the rash project fell</L>
<L>With its first mover.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Couldst thou think it, friend,</L>
<L>That many of the first esteemed note,</L>
<L>Curio, Hortensius, and the old stoic Cato,</L>
<L>Aided the hateful motion? Weak indeed</L>
<L>His single voice; but, spreading as it roll'd,</L>
<L>It came upon us like the gathering thunder,</L>
<L>And the low murmur swell'd into a storm.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they so rank? And hath old Cato then</L>
<L>Forgot his rugged nature, and become</L>
<L>Fawning and smooth? To Marcus Tullius smooth?</L>
<L>Oh! I could burst with spleen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Clodius, no:</L>
<L>Cato is still severe, is still himself;</L>
<L>Rough and unshaven in his squalid garb,</L>
<L>He told us he had long in anguish mourn'd,</L>
<L>Not in a private but the public cause;</L>
<L>Not for the wrong of one, but wrong of all,</L>
<L>Of Liberty, of Virtue, and of Rome.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="11" REF="10"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, I sleep o'er Cato's drowsy theme:</L>
<L>He is the Senate's drone, and dreams of Liberty,</L>
<L>When Rome's vast Empire is set up to sale,</L>
<L>And portion'd out to each ambitious bidder</L>
<L>In marketable lots.—But now proceed;</L>
<L>Give me more names; these many I have wrote</L>
<L>Deep in the vengeful tablets of my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then in the front and foremost page of all</L>
<L>Print deep in everlasting characters,</L>
<L>The hated name of Milo; his alone,</L>
<L>When every other eye was red with tears,</L>
<L>His only burnt with hot and scalding rage;</L>
<L>He hates thee, Clodius; and when all were loud</L>
<L>For mourning, he with a disdainful air</L>
<L>Throwing his mantle by, in public view</L>
<L>Shew'd them his mailed corselet, bid 'em mark it;</L>
<L>For 'twas a Roman's dress; their sable scarves,</L>
<L>Them, as he said, he left to puling maids</L>
<L>And sedentary widows.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Gabinius,</L>
<L>Let me not hear it; in the world there lives not</L>
<L>One, whom my soul holds in such perfect hate</L>
<L>As that same Milo. How it is I know not,</L>
<L>But by the Gods he awes my very blood;</L>
<L>Therefore no more of him.—What said my Caesar?</L>
<L>Tell me how look'd the rising Sun of Rome?</L>
</SP>
<PB N="12" REF="11"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, know you not that Caesar's new command</L>
<L>Forbids his entrance into Rome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true:</L>
<L>But Pompey—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! who shall attempt to read</L>
<L>In Pompey's face the movements of his heart?</L>
<L>The same calm artificial look of state,</L>
<L>His half-clos'd eyes in self-attention wrapt</L>
<L>Serve him alike to mask unseemly joy,</L>
<L>Or hide the pangs of envy and revenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, yonder your old collegue Piso comes—</L>
<L>But name Hypocrisy and he appears;</L>
<L>How like his Grandsire's monument he looks?</L>
<L>He wears the dress of holy Numa's days,</L>
<L>The brow and beard of Zeno; trace him home,</L>
<L>You'll find his house the school of vice and lust,</L>
<L>The foulest sink of Epicurus' stye</L>
<L>And him the rankest swine of all the herd.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2">
<HEAD>SCENE II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>CLODIUS, GABINIUS, PISO, <HI>attended by several Grecians, and others.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, by the soul of Socrates, I swear</L>
<STAGE>(Aside to his attendants.</STAGE>
<L>They do me wrong, who say I sought this load</L>
<L><PB N="13" REF="12"/>
Of care and envy: I, a weak old man,</L>
<L>What other taste of joy have I, alas!</L>
<L>Save only with a few learn'd friends about me,</L>
<L>To measure out my last low dregs of life</L>
<L>In peace, and creep into a silent grave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most learn'd and noble Piso, fairly met.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome, thrice-worthy Collegue!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome both:</L>
<L>Shame of my old eyes that I saw you not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bear with me, Brother, if I'm bold to tell you</L>
<L>You've done me wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Name it, and be redrest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too studious of your ease, and seek</L>
<L>To shift the burthen, you was bound to share,</L>
<L>Upon the weaker shoulders: From the Senate</L>
<L>Wherefore this morning absent? whilst I bear</L>
<L>The sweat and labour of the day, at home</L>
<L>You sit, wrapt up in calm philosophy,</L>
<L>And moralize at leisure: 'Tis not well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me your pardon, when my Country made me</L>
<L>Their Consul, did they make me young withal,</L>
<L>Active and vigorous, like thee, Gabinius?</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="13"/>
Or take me as they found me, an old man</L>
<L>Worn out with age and study? Let 'em then</L>
<L>Look for no other than an old man's service,</L>
<L>My counsel and my pray'rs; them they shall have.</L>
<L>I told you t'would be thus.</L>
<STAGE>(To his Attendants.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence are these strangers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of Athens.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Learn'd no doubt.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>As Greece e'er bred.</L>
<L>Apollodorus, prithee call to mind</L>
<L>The lines which Athenaeus (him, I mean</L>
<L>The Epigrammatist) writes in the praise</L>
<L>Of the wise Sect of Stoics, the sound school,</L>
<L>And true definers of the Sovereign Good;</L>
<L>Speak low, such are not for the public ear.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>How this old specious rascal cheats the world!</L>
<L>Yon fellow is his parasite, his pimp;</L>
<L>I read it on his forehead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>And did Clodia</L>
<L>Deliver this herself to you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>APOLLODORUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Herself,</L>
<L>With her own gracious lips.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="15" REF="14"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods, Gods! I thank you:</L>
<L>As soon as I can quit me of her brother,</L>
<L>With my best speed I'll seek her: Soft you now;</L>
<L>Was there nought else?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>APOLLODORUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, more; the fatted quails,</L>
<L>And the red mullet for your mistress Lesbia.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>—Give me your pardon, grave and reverend Sir,</L>
<L>If I break in upon your better thoughts,</L>
<L>And beg your patient ear: You're not to learn</L>
<L>What public, bold, and undisguis'd affront</L>
<L>I have of late endur'd; endur'd from one,</L>
<L>A public railer; whom nor birth, nor fortune,</L>
<L>Manhood, nor merit, have made great and noble,</L>
<L>But rancour, pride, and swoln conceit, conspire</L>
<L>To render hateful.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis to Marcus Cicero</L>
<L>Your preface points; and I must needs confess</L>
<L>He is too bitter, and too sharp in speech;</L>
<L>That error set aside, I hold him clear</L>
<L>Of every other stain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, good man,</L>
<L>With what dim eyes you see him! As for me,</L>
<L>'Tis known how I have liv'd; and I must own</L>
<L>In heat of youth, and wantonness of spirit,</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="15"/>
I have done much to justify reproach:</L>
<L>But when he makes your gravity his jest,</L>
<L>Your wisdom and severity of manners</L>
<L>His table-scandal, every honest man</L>
<L>Cries out upon the wrong; and I who love,</L>
<L>Altho' I practise not your virtues, burn</L>
<L>For vengeance on the crime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>When vice is honour,</L>
<L>I glory in reproach:—But wherefore this,</L>
<L>And whither would you lead? You say I'm wrong'd</L>
<L>Of Marcus Cicero; be his the shame,</L>
<L>Who did the wrong; I know not to revenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>If private wrongs are nothing, yet your duty</L>
<L>To your lov'd Country, and the natural hatred,</L>
<L>Which each free Roman bears to slavery,</L>
<L>Bid you stand up and show yourself a man.</L>
<L>You talk of Pompey's greatness, and you tremble</L>
<L>At the fear'd name of Caesar. Mighty Gods!</L>
<L>The tongue of this vain pedant plagues the state;</L>
<L>Ay, and enslaves you worse than their ambition,</L>
<L>Tho' it look up to Empire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, no more.</L>
<L>If you are with us, thus with wide-stretch'd arms,</L>
<L>As Brother should greet Brother, we embrace you:</L>
<L>If not, be plain, tell us you hold not with us,</L>
<L>And we will on without you.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="17" REF="16"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis enough;</L>
<L>Piso, I know thy heart, and thou know'st mine;</L>
<L>Like cunning gamesters we have plied each other</L>
<L>With strained art, and run thro' every feint;</L>
<L>Now let us draw the undecided stake:</L>
<L>Take you your title of philosopher,</L>
<L>Barren unenvied lot: Let me depart</L>
<L>With the rich spoils of Macedon, which, Jove!</L>
<L>Thou know'st, I would have pour'd into his lap,</L>
<L>Who dar'd to own himself my friend.—Farewell.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet hear me, Clodius; what you take in hand</L>
<L>Demands mature and calm deliberation;</L>
<L>For trust me, 'tis no slight and trivial matter,</L>
<L>But bold and big with danger: Sleeps he then?</L>
<L>And hath the thunder of his eloquence</L>
<L>Forgot to roll? Or is it all as easy,</L>
<L>To buy the life of the first man of Rome,</L>
<L>As 'tis to traffick for the lowest slave?</L>
<L>When he was Consul, all men worship'd him;</L>
<L>He was the God of Rome: Not so you say,</L>
<L>"The Tyrant rather."—Give me proof of that,</L>
<L>Let it outweigh the public voice, and make</L>
<L>The flatt'ring Senate liars; and by Heaven!</L>
<L>Had I and Marcus Cicero together</L>
<L>Laid in one womb, been foster'd at one breast,</L>
<L>Indignant I would shake him from my heart,</L>
<L>And give him up to justice and to thee.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="18" REF="17"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if I give you not the proof you ask,</L>
<L>Renounce me, Gods!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Upon those terms we close;</L>
<L>At present strong occasions draw me hence;</L>
<L>To-night if you can relish such coarse fare</L>
<L>As my poor board affords, we will talk farther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'll be your thankful guests: Farewell.</L>
<STAGE>(Exit Piso.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3">
<HEAD>SCENE III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>CLODIUS, GABINIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, he's my own! How quick the old fox doubled!</L>
<L>Why, what a world is this! Behold that man,</L>
<L>The noblest born in Rome; wealthy and old,</L>
<L>And seeming virtuous; yet a province buys him:</L>
<L>And shall a peasant of Arpinum check</L>
<L>The course of my success, and soar a pitch</L>
<L>Of virtue, which our Nobles cannot reach?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say'st thou, our Nobles? Why they are his vassals,</L>
<L>And he ambitious sits among the clouds,</L>
<L>Like a strange meteor that appalls the world;</L>
<L><PB N="19" REF="18"/>
Whilst we the sons of earth look up aghast</L>
<L>And deprecate his wrath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so, Gabinius,</L>
<L>High as he is, this arm shall reach him yet,</L>
<L>And crush him in his pride; the bubble broke</L>
<L>All men will mock its emptiness; and thus</L>
<L>When flamy comets vex our frighted sphere,</L>
<L>Tho' now the nations melt with awful fear,</L>
<L>From the dread omen fatal ills presage,</L>
<L>Dire plague and famine, and war's wasting rage;</L>
<L>In time some brighter genius may arise,</L>
<L>And banish signs and omens from the skies,</L>
<L>Expound the comet's nature and its cause,</L>
<L>Assign its periods and prescribe its laws;</L>
<L>Whilst man grown wise, with his discoveries fraught,</L>
<L>Shall wonder how he needed to be taught.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>END OF THE FIRST ACT.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2">
<PB N="20" REF="19"/>
<HEAD>ACT II.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1">
<HEAD>SCENE I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>An Apartment in</HI> CICERO'S <HI>Palace.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>TULLIA, FRUGI.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>ALONE; unguarded; to the house of Clodia,</L>
<L>The sister of my father's deadliest foe?</L>
<L>She tempts you to your ruin: This late hour</L>
<L>Appointed for your meeting; her pretence</L>
<L>To reconcile her brother to our house,</L>
<L>Each circumstance about it breathes contrivance,</L>
<L>And meditated mischief. Do not go:</L>
<L>Trust her not, Caius; ah! she is a woman,</L>
<L>The wiliest of her sex.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can I do?</L>
<L>A sinking man will catch at slender holds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sinking man?—Was ever friend like thee?</L>
<L>In his full tide of pow'r my father stood,</L>
<L>Like some tall rock, around whose worship'd sides</L>
<L>The climbing surges hung, by prosperous gales</L>
<L>Driv'n gladly on; but when the veering wind</L>
<L>And fickle current chang'd, the ebbing waves</L>
<L>Roll'd back and left him bare. Why then alone</L>
<L>Dost thou, unlike the false ones of the world,</L>
<L><PB N="21" REF="20"/>
Embrace a falling fabrick, whose vast ruin</L>
<L>Shall bury thee, and dash thy youthful hopes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>And, tell me, hast thou never, O my Tullia,</L>
<L>Ask'd of thy heart that question? Never yet</L>
<L>Bid it resolve thee, why with anxious zeal</L>
<L>For Marcus Cicero, I have stak'd my hopes</L>
<L>An uninvited friend, and drawn the rage</L>
<L>Of the whole Clodian faction on my head?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, I know not. Whither would you lead me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then if thou know'st not why I have done this,</L>
<L>It is because my Tullia's charms outweigh,</L>
<L>Great as it is, the virtue of her father;</L>
<L>Because it is in love to do and suffer,</L>
<L>More than the warmest sense of friendship dare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take care; I'd not conceive a less'ning thought</L>
<L>Of Frugi's friendship—interested friendship?—</L>
<L>An interested service?—How that sounds!</L>
<L>Oh! how it loses the great name of virtue,</L>
<L>And the sweet praise that gratitude bestows</L>
<L>On clear intent, and pure beneficence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her father speaks within her: How she awes me?</L>
<L>Fir'd with thy just reproof, I could explore</L>
<L>The farthest regions of th' untravell'd earth,</L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="21"/>
Beyond the sound of thy great father's fame,</L>
<L>And arm the barbarous nations in his cause,</L>
<L>If that would gain thy love. But this is raving,</L>
<L>And Clodia's hour is come; farewell! awhile,</L>
<L>If it be possible, I will forget</L>
<L>How much I love thee, Tullia.</L>
<STAGE>(Exit Frugi.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he gone?</L>
<L>For ever gone? O stay; return, my Caius.</L>
<STAGE>FRUGI <HI>Returns.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold thy Caius—that alluring voice</L>
<L>Has music in't of such a heav'nly sort,</L>
<L>As might awake attention in the grave,</L>
<L>And harmonize the drowsy ear of death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah! spare my blushes; spare a doating maid,</L>
<L>Nor scorn the easy conquest of my heart,</L>
<L>Which fixt on thee, and with thy virtues charm'd,</L>
<L>Bursts its confinement and that modest guard,</L>
<L>Which prudent virgins plant upon their lips;</L>
<L>And do not think it weak and slightly pois'd,</L>
<L>For each vain blast of flattery to o'erturn;</L>
<L>Nor charge the softness you alone inspire,</L>
<L>To female frailty and defective nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, thou art all that's elegant and fair,</L>
<L>And perfect upon earth; and Caius happy</L>
<L><PB N="23" REF="22"/>
Beyond whatever gratitude express'd,</L>
<L>Or fancy drew, when glowing raptures catch</L>
<L>The poet's breast, and set the soul on fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why must I only answer thee with sighs?</L>
<L>What is it hangs thus heavy on my heart,</L>
<L>And weighs it down, when it should spring with joy?</L>
<L>Alas! 'tis conscience; 'tis the pride of honour;</L>
<L>'Tis the severe condition of my fate,</L>
<L>Which makes it ruin to be lov'd by Tullia,</L>
<L>And warns me to suppress the guilty flame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure virtue will not be renounc'd of Heav'n:</L>
<L>The Gods are just; thy father must not perish.</L>
<L>Clodia, I come. Fate holds her balance forth,</L>
<L>That wavers doubtful betwixt death and life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah! do not rush upon assur'd destruction;</L>
<L>Perhaps that life, which you so rashly venture,</L>
<L>Tullia may hold far dearer than her own.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let me stay, till Clodius finds me here,</L>
<L>And fate arrests me in my Tullia's arms.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O horror! how, and what shall I resolve?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>The pity, that now springs in Clodia's heart,</L>
<L>If scorn'd, will turn to unrelenting rage,</L>
<L>And burst in ruin on thy father's head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="24" REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>How soon that name recalls me to myself!</L>
<L>Fly, Caius, fly; e're love revokes the doom,</L>
<L>And drives out nature from my vanquish'd heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Tullia, take, for thou hast won my soul!</L>
<L>Now I'm o'erpaid for all that fate can do.</L>
<STAGE>(Embracing her,</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah! look not, speak not: I relapse apace.</L>
<L>Let me not turn a parricide; away!</L>
<L>If I recall thee, come not back. Adieu!</L>
<L>While I have strength to speak the word, adieu!</L>
<STAGE>(Exit Frugi.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA,</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>Alone.</STAGE>
<L>What have I done, and whither is he gone?</L>
<L>To Clodia.—Ah! I fear that is to death:</L>
<L>For she perhaps hath laid this midnight plot,</L>
<L>To seize my unsuspecting Frugi's life;</L>
<L>Perhaps, (ah! that were worse) to seize his heart;</L>
<L>For she is mistress of a thousand charms.</L>
<L>O Love, thou wear'st a smiling Cupid's face,</L>
<L>Till we fond virgins take thee in our arms;</L>
<L>There warm'd, thou grow'st into an ugly fiend,</L>
<L>And strik'st a thousand daggers in our hearts.</L>
<STAGE>(Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2">
<HEAD>SCENE II.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>A Street in</HI> ROME.</STAGE>
<STAGE>CLODIUS <HI>and</HI> GABINIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now thou shalt feel me, Rome. Come on, my friend;</L>
<L>Loud as the orgies of the God of wine,</L>
<L><PB N="25" REF="24"/>
Let our bold revels wake the sleeping night,</L>
<L>And rock the throne of Jove. I tread on air;</L>
<L>My mounting spirits lift me from the earth,</L>
<L>Gay dancing pleasures play around my heart,</L>
<L>And the full Bacchus revels in my veins.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent Piso! O most potent Consul!</L>
<L>Divine philosopher! why, what a lecture</L>
<L>Hath yon old thirsty stoic read us, Clodius,</L>
<L>In the Symposia? Gods! with what a throat</L>
<L>He quaft the rich Falernian, till the fumes</L>
<L>Wrapp'd round the giddy roof, and breath'd a gale</L>
<L>Mix'd with Sabean odors; all the while</L>
<L>A female band of Grecian dancers trod</L>
<L>Their wanton measures to the melting sound</L>
<L>Of breathing flutes, that caught the ravish'd soul,</L>
<L>And sooth'd it into harmony and love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never did lust and luxury assume</L>
<L>So sanctified a form; by the great Gods!</L>
<L>Methinks your collegue, Aulus, hath a swallow</L>
<L>As deep as Erebus; he is a man</L>
<L>Fit to sit down at a celestial banquet,</L>
<L>And pledge the Gods in nectar.—But behold!</L>
<L>Yon sober orb hath turn'd her back on night,</L>
<L>And leans tow'rds morning;—the choice minutes fly,</L>
<L>My soul is up in arms and pants for action:</L>
<L>Oh! for some master-deed of glorious mischief;</L>
<L>Something, I know not what, but full of wonder,</L>
<L><PB N="26" REF="25"/>
Lofty and bold, of the true Clodian stamp;</L>
<L>A deed to add new terror to my name,</L>
<L>Silence the cavils of proud prying gownsmen,</L>
<L>And fright the world from its dull dream of virtue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed; let's up together to mount Palatine;</L>
<L>Fire Cicero's palace; pull the dreaming dotard</L>
<L>By the long lazy neck, from the stale arms</L>
<L>Of shrill Terentia; force his pale-fac'd daughter</L>
<L>Before his eyes; then send her weeping back</L>
<L>To her beloved Caius; bid him take her</L>
<L>Fresh from her wrongs to his fond foolish bosom,</L>
<L>And glean the sordid refuse of our joys.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah! that were well; a great and apt revenge</L>
<L>Is my soul's health.—Yet stay—It dawns upon me,</L>
<L>A bold, sublime, and unattempted deed:</L>
<L>By Heaven! the glorious face of danger charms me,</L>
<L>And my soul rushes ardent to embrace it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is it, speak; oh! how I burn to hear it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there be thunder, and a Heaven, and Gods,</L>
<L>They must revenge; befall that as it may:</L>
<L>I think not with the vulgar; let Heaven strike,</L>
<L>So shall I perish by no earthly hand;</L>
<L>But if the light'ning sleep, farewell these horrors,</L>
<L>Hell is a dream, Religion is a jest,</L>
<L>And nothing real, but this world we live in.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="27" REF="26"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why are you rapt? let me partake your thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>My purse, my mistress, and my best of means</L>
<L>Freely partake; in danger and in fame</L>
<L>I brook no rival, and admit no friend:</L>
<L>All else is open to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take, O Clodius,</L>
<L>Take the full glory of thine own attempt,</L>
<L>Give me the merit only to have known it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honest and brave, I know thee; yet, my friend,</L>
<L>Were this place where we stand a desart waste,</L>
<L>No living creature but thyself to hear me,</L>
<L>And yon pale conscious planet o'er our heads,</L>
<L>I would not tell it in the ears of night,</L>
<L>Lest things inanimate should take a voice</L>
<L>And blazon it to the world: farewell, farewell!</L>
<STAGE>(Exit Clodius.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fortune and fame go with thee, crown thy wishes,</L>
<L>And bring thee back in safety to thy friend.</L>
<STAGE>(Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3">
<HEAD>SCENE III.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>An Apartment in</HI> CLODIA<HI>'s House.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>FRUGI, <HI>and an Attendant of</HI> CLODIA<HI>'s.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thro' what blind entries lies the Cave of Guilt!</L>
<L><PB N="28" REF="27"/>
Say, whither wouldst thou lead me, thou dark guide?</L>
<L>I'll on no further.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTENDANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>What! do you shrink, my Lord,</L>
<L>And from a harmless woman? from a fair one?</L>
<L>Fie, fie, for shame! how these unmanly fears</L>
<L>Belie that noble presence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, proceed.</L>
<L>It is my Tullia's cause, the cause of Love.</L>
<STAGE>(Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4">
<HEAD>SCENE IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>An inner Apartment in</HI> CLODIA<HI>'s House.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm here—so mighty is the force of gold.</L>
<L>Gold is the key that opes the bower of Love,</L>
<L>The Sybil branch that charms Hell's centinel;</L>
<L>Our passport to Elysium—</L>
<STAGE>FRUGI, <HI>enters unseen by</HI> PISO.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah! a man?</L>
<L>Amazement, Piso!—Can I trust my eyes?</L>
<L>Honour forgive me, if I turn a listener;</L>
<L>All means are lawful to detect a villain.</L>
<STAGE>(Steps aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now inspire me, Wine, thou friend to Love!</L>
<L>My gold has done its part; complete the work,</L>
<L>And be my God for ever.—Yet what hope,</L>
<L>What hope for age? Curse on this wrinkled front,</L>
<L><PB N="29" REF="28"/>
Bow'd back, slow pulse, weak hams, and slack'ned nerves!</L>
<L>Cursed be Nature rather, trebly curst!</L>
<L>Who keeps not equal pace in our decay,</L>
<L>But pays us for the daily waste she makes</L>
<L>Of this poor body's strength, by throwing on</L>
<L>Fresh fuel to the unabating lusts,</L>
<L>And stirs the hell within us.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5">
<HEAD>SCENE V.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> CLODIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where, where is he?</L>
<L>Thus let me fly to him.—Hah! who art thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not know me, Clodia? Your old faithful slave,</L>
<L>That throwing thus his age and cares aside,</L>
<L>Runs to thy arms with a young lover's ardor,</L>
<L>To claim thy transports, and return their warmth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Off, monster, off! nor blast me with thy touch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can this mean? yet, yet, you know me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes, I know thee, (cursed be the mark!)</L>
<L>I thought to have flush'd an Eagle in my toils,</L>
<L>And find a filthy Raven in his place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seems I come unwelcome then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="30" REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do,</L>
<L>Most fatally; and I would curse thee for it,</L>
<L>But that thou carriest every plague about thee,</L>
<L>That I could wish, or Hell itself inflict:</L>
<L>Who brought you here? At this late hour how dar'd you</L>
<L>To come unask'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unask'd, perfidious woman!</L>
<L>With your own lips you spoke, repeated welcomes;</L>
<L>The slave that brought 'em swore it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like a slave</L>
<L>He lied; or if I did, my mind is chang'd,</L>
<L>And as 'twas then my pleasure you should come,</L>
<L>'Tis now my will that you depart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more?—</L>
<L>Thus do you treat me, thus spurn from your doors,</L>
<L>Like a base lacquey, the first man in Rome?</L>
<L>But have a care, the trodden worm will turn;</L>
<L>And I have found thee, proud insatiate woman:</L>
<L>You have your private, cull'd, and midnight sparks,</L>
<L>Ready at hand against the hot fire takes you,</L>
<L>The hirelings of your lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blaspheming villain!</L>
<L>Oh! that the noble youth were here! I tell thee,</L>
<L>Pale, tott'ring coward! he would thrust that tongue,</L>
<L><PB N="31" REF="30"/>
That lying tongue, down thy base scurrilous throat.</L>
<L>Away, old hypocrite! you dare as well</L>
<L>With those blear blister'd eyes of thine look up</L>
<L>In the broad face of the meridian sun,</L>
<L>When he drinks up the Tyber, as abide</L>
<L>The terror of his frown.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would he were here!</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> FRUGI.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold, you have your wish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods! Gods! I thank ye.</L>
<L>Thrice welcome, my deliverer; what blest star</L>
<L>Led you unseen to save me? Now you see him;</L>
<L>Now you behold the slave, the midnight hireling;</L>
<L>Hah! looks he like a hireling, like a slave?</L>
<L>Down on your knees, your old weak trembling knees,</L>
<L>And wet his feet with supplicating tears.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, Clodia, peace: Young Lord, I joy to see you;</L>
<L>I came a suppliant to this lady's brother,</L>
<L>For our friend Cicero, and, how I know not,</L>
<L>Whether I spake too warm in his behalf,</L>
<L>Or whether my rude manners gave offence;</L>
<L>But I, alas! unwittingly have drawn</L>
<L>Displeasure from the fair.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! good man;</L>
<L><PB N="32" REF="31"/>
If I may boast an interest in her thoughts,</L>
<L>All shall be well; we'll all be reconcil'd;</L>
<L>I too have hopes of pardon from your favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>What pardon can the noble Frugi need?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! my offence is heinous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What intends he?</L>
<L>Where will this end?</L>
<STAGE>(Aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fear not, but speak it boldly;</L>
<L>It cannot be too great for my forgiveness.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>First then the names of slave, and midnight hireling,</L>
<L>Which you bestow'd on me unseen, I take,</L>
<L>And wear them as my own.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm dumb with wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>For I have ta'en the office of a slave,</L>
<L>And been a spy upon you; turn'd a list'ner</L>
<L>To your most grave soliloquy, am witness</L>
<L>To this fair lady's most unkind disdain,</L>
<L>And your most patient bearing; am possest</L>
<L>Of your whole heart, and know you what you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>What am I, speak Sir!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="33" REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me, my Lord;</L>
<L>I'll tell you what you should be; honest, grave,</L>
<L>And sober; Consul you should be, and noble</L>
<L>As your birth speaks you; in one word,—a Roman!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hear you that, Sir? O how thou charm'st me, Caius!</L>
<L>My soul drinks love and wisdom from thy lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Consul I am, and will be, and as Consul</L>
<L>Command you from my presence; hence, avoid!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weak man, I will not, you mistake your office;</L>
<L>Your Fasces and your Lictors pass not here</L>
<L>Within a lady's chamber; your great title</L>
<L>Is here your shame not safe-guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>This to me?</L>
<L>Honour enough for thee to draw thy blood</L>
<L>At humble distance from the same great fount,</L>
<L>With which these veins are fill'd, audacious boy!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Boast not your birth, lest your great father's tomb</L>
<L>Utter a voice against you; sheath your sword,</L>
<L>And hide one weakness more: I'll not betray you;</L>
<L>Live still a lie; hypocrisy in you</L>
<L>Stands in some rank of merit, and in time</L>
<L>By feigning virtue, may you learn to have it!</L>
</SP>
<PB N="34" REF="33"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PISO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by the Gods!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more; O shame, shame, shame!</L>
<L>Is this to be a Consul? Go to Cicero,</L>
<L>Ponder the annals of his glorious aera;</L>
<L>Go to his sober couch, and learn of him</L>
<L>To watch and labour in thy country's service,</L>
<L>And be the guardian of expiring freedom.</L>
<STAGE>(Exit Piso.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6">
<HEAD>SCENE VI.</HEAD>
<STAGE>CLODIA, FRUGI.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Frugi, what a happy chance was this!</L>
<L>Andromeda ne'er blest wing'd Perseus more</L>
<L>Than I do thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest rather be the cause,</L>
<L>And this auspicious hour that brought me here!</L>
<L>I pause for your commands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah! why so guarded?</L>
<L>You speak not before witnesses, but speak</L>
<L>To one alone, too much alas! your friend.</L>
<L>Say'st thou, commands?—O tell me first my power</L>
<L>E're I command. Wilt thou not understand?</L>
<L>Hast thou not, yes, I know thou hast, the art</L>
<L>To read a lady's wishes in her eyes?</L>
<L>If then thou hast the art, and had'st been kind,</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="34"/>
Thou should'st have let thy wishes marshal mine,</L>
<L>Have importun'd me to my own desires,</L>
<L>And kneeling beg'd the joys yourself bestow'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>How wide you speak! Where's Cicero in this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah! Cicero?—my everlasting hatred</L>
<L>Pursue and overtake him! Nature feels not</L>
<L>Such horror at approaching dissolution,</L>
<L>As I to hear your lips pronounce his name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell! I have my answer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Caius, stay.</L>
<L>You are his friend, and would do much to save him;</L>
<L>I yet will treat with you on terms of peace</L>
<L>And reconcilement; say, what would'st thou do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would I do? As much as friend dare do;</L>
<L>And more than all your malice could invent,</L>
<L>Great as it is, to task me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O ingrateful!</L>
<L>My malice?—But I'll put you to the proof.</L>
<L>Now, Frugi, now you shall see Clodia's malice,</L>
<L>How very hard a task-mistress she is:</L>
<L>If you love Cicero, love him alone;</L>
<L>Renounce the daughter to preserve the father;</L>
<L>Abandon Tullia.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="36" REF="35"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Abandon Tullia;</L>
<L>And come, O come to these protecting arms:</L>
<L>With twice her ardor if they meet thee not,</L>
<L>With twice her fondness if they close not on thee,</L>
<L>Take her, my happy rival, take again,</L>
<L>And cast me off to wretchedness and shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can I do this and live?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What! am I scorn'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your offers are, tho' bitterest death ensued</L>
<L>On the refusal.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what else will follow?</L>
<L>Your fates are in my keeping; Clodius' hand.</L>
<L>Hangs o'er you, and but waits my nod to strike.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know with Clodius how great your power;</L>
<L>And know the damning price you bought it at:</L>
<L>But boast it not; blush, rather blush to death,</L>
<L>And deprecate the vengeance of the Gods.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I'll not blush, nor ask the Gods forgiveness,</L>
<L>But glory rather that I've found the means</L>
<L>With these despised charms to blast thee yet,</L>
<L><PB N="37" REF="36"/>
And triumph o'er thy peace. Go to your Tullia:</L>
<L>The sun must soon go down upon your loves,</L>
<L>And night at last will bring on my revenge.</L>
<L>Then, when thou see'st the lofty palace flaming,</L>
<L>Thy mistress seiz'd by the dishevell'd locks,</L>
<L>Screaming and yelling in the spoiler's arms;</L>
<L>Thyself bound down, mad'ning with fruitless rage,</L>
<L>Then, then, remember me, then know 'tis I,</L>
<L>It is my Genius that directs thy fate,</L>
<L>And learn too late to reverence Clodia's charms.</L>
<STAGE>(Exit Clodia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Horror go with thee! what a look was there?</L>
<L>How all the savage purpose of her soul</L>
<L>Spoke in her eyes? A sad alternative</L>
<L>Is offered to my choice.—To die with Tullia,</L>
<L>Or, (which is worse than death) to live with Clodia.</L>
<L>If true to Tullia, and my heart I prove,</L>
<L>I fall the victim here of slighted love;</L>
<L>If Clodia wins me to her loose desires,</L>
<L>Behold the fond forsaken maid expires!</L>
<L>Life on thy terms, O Clodia, I disdain;</L>
<L>The death of Honour is exempt from pain.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>END OF THE SECOND ACT.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3">
<PB N="38" REF="37"/>
<HEAD>ACT III.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1">
<HEAD>SCENE I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>CLODIUS, GABINIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>YET further, Aulus—let these walls not listen,</L>
<L>Nor the pale prying spirits, that unseen</L>
<L>Course up and down beneath the shadowy moon,</L>
<L>Hover about me: rather let me stand</L>
<L>With night and desolation all around,</L>
<L>While in thy listful ear I drop my words,</L>
<L>More lightly than the vernal dew descends</L>
<L>On the soft lap of Hybla.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spare your preface,</L>
<L>And to the purpose, Clodius.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know then first,</L>
<L>Caesar—the God, whom we poor mortals worship,</L>
<L>Hath a kind wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kind wife?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know her kind.</L>
<L>Nay, never stare and stagger with amaze,</L>
<L>'T has been the lot of many a better man.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="39" REF="38"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ye Gods! the great Triumvir?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Gabinius!</L>
<L>Like a bold bird of prey, I have dislodg'd</L>
<L>This tame domestic fowl from off his nest,</L>
<L>And rifled all his brood of nuptial joys.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now thank the Gods! for if Pompeia's false,</L>
<L>There's not one true in Rome; brave men shall flourish,</L>
<L>Posterity shall bless us; no man's wife</L>
<L>Censure her neighbour; money-hoarding knaves</L>
<L>Bequeath their usuries to the spendthrift's son,</L>
<L>And no house want an heir. But say, my Clodius,</L>
<L>Tell me, dear youth, how, when, and where you met.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay, there my story rises into wonder;</L>
<L>There, there, Gabinius, I am more than Clodius;</L>
<L>What man yet never dar'd, yet never saw,</L>
<L>These eyes beheld undaunted. Know, last night,</L>
<L>My Genius (call it good or evil) led me</L>
<L>Without the city walls to seek Pompeia:</L>
<L>She then was busied in those sacred rites,</L>
<L>Which the sex pay to the mysterious Goddess,</L>
<L>Whom they call Good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was a bar betwixt you,</L>
<L>As high as is mount Athos.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="40" REF="39"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Gabinius,</L>
<L>It is a bar to men of common souls,</L>
<L>Whom base tradition awes, and holy tales</L>
<L>Told by the dreaming nurse; but you and I,</L>
<L>And spirits cast in our ambitious mould,</L>
<L>Will leap such petty bars, and boldly scorn</L>
<L>Religion's weak enclosure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>You're my witness</L>
<L>I dare do much; but this—forbid it, Gods!</L>
<L>It chills my blood. Oh! if thou hast profan'd</L>
<L>These unreveal'd solemnities, farewell;</L>
<L>If there be wrath in Heaven, expect it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I,</L>
<L>I have done this and live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang the Heav'ns o'er us?</L>
<L>Have those eyes speculation, and that heart</L>
<L>Motion and sense of life?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whole and untouch'd</L>
<L>I mock the wrath of Jove. Do you avoid me?</L>
<L>Survey me well; where has the light'ning pierc'd?</L>
<L>Wast thou the friend of Catiline? Like children,</L>
<L>Who talk of goblins, till they think they see 'em,</L>
<L>Ye draw your Gods with thunder in their hands,</L>
<L>Till your own fancies fright you. What, d'ye think,</L>
<L><PB N="41" REF="40"/>
If there be Gods, will their immortal natures</L>
<L>Take thought of such a sorry thing as Clodius,</L>
<L>And taint the peace of their celestial dwellings</L>
<L>With earthly occupations? No, Gabinius,</L>
<L>Serene they sit above this noisy world,</L>
<L>And yield the reins to chance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, my friend,</L>
<L>My wishes, not my reason, are convinc'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>There then abide, and never seek to know,</L>
<L>What known will leave thee hopeless. But no more,</L>
<L>I should have told thee under what disguise</L>
<L>I enter'd; how betray'd; and with what art</L>
<L>I 'scap'd; but that thy inauspicious looks</L>
<L>Have chill'd the pregnant functions of my brain,</L>
<L>And strangled the brave story in its birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>There in oblivious silence let it lie,</L>
<L>Lest Rumor's ever-open ears should hear it,</L>
<L>And all her thousand mouths proclaim the deed.</L>
<L>How would your foes exult? The Sacred College,</L>
<L>How would they rise against you? What dire ills</L>
<L>Would the prophetic Figulus denounce?</L>
<L>How would the Praetors punish? Above all</L>
<L>Think you hear Cicero declaim against you,</L>
<L>With all the energy of voice and action,</L>
<L>And tears and words; that give the thing they speak,</L>
<L>And realize description: All around</L>
<L><PB N="42" REF="41"/>
The list'ning Senate hang upon his lips;</L>
<L>Whilst you, as Catiline did once, with shame</L>
<L>And blushes cover'd underneath his lash</L>
<L>Sit like a chidden school-boy; or, contending,</L>
<L>After faint struggle, you are borne along</L>
<L>Down the strong torrent of his eloquence,</L>
<L>Like the light trash that rides upon the flood,</L>
<L>When the Alps pour their deluge on the plains.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet, yet, I am before you: Come, my friend,</L>
<L>And I will lead you up to glorious action;</L>
<L>The garish sun is set, this night concludes;</L>
<L>To-morrow, I or Cicero am nothing.</L>
<STAGE>(Exeunt▪</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2">
<HEAD>SCENE II.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>An Apartment in</HI> CICERO'S <HI>Palace.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>TULLIA, FRUGI.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why do you meet me thus with alter'd looks?</L>
<L>Your full heart labours with unvented sorrow,</L>
<L>And in the silent language of the eyes</L>
<L>Tells me, I never shall know comfort more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot speak to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do' you shun me, Caius?</L>
<L>Ah! that cold look has froze me into horror.</L>
<L>Am I grown stale? has this poor form of mine</L>
<L><PB N="43" REF="42"/>
Lost all its little merit? have these tears</L>
<L>Quite, quite effac'd the roses of my cheeks?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heav'n be my witness, how thou wrong'st my love!</L>
<L>No, thou'rt more welcome to my sight, and fairer,</L>
<L>Than yon all-blessed sun; more dear thou art</L>
<L>To this sad breast, than are the vital drops</L>
<L>That fall in tender pity from my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! had you known the visions of last night—</L>
<L>Under how many dismal shapes of horror</L>
<L>Did that dear image haunt my sleepless eyes!</L>
<L>Methought I saw thee lie an out-stretch'd corse,</L>
<L>Stuck full of wounds and welt'ring in thy blood;</L>
<L>Strait I beheld the traitress Clodia take</L>
<L>A secret dagger from her cursed bosom</L>
<L>Dripping with blood, and smile upon the point:</L>
<L>Then at a thought the scene of blood was shifted,</L>
<L>And all was revelry, and all was love;</L>
<L>I saw my Frugi lying in her arms,</L>
<L>Gazing with lifted eyes upon her face;</L>
<L>Aloud I call'd thee; thou with feeble tone</L>
<L>Coldly replied, "Alas! unhappy Tullia!"</L>
<L>And sunk again into her arms.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more;</L>
<L>My blood runs back with horror at the thought:</L>
<L>While thus I strain thee to my throbbing bosom,</L>
<L>Blest as I am, and honour'd in thy love,</L>
<L><PB N="44" REF="43"/>
At this dear moment my presaging heart,</L>
<L>Quailing and sinking with unusual softness,</L>
<L>Feels all the pangs that parting souls endure,</L>
<L>When rigid Fate exacts her stern demands,</L>
<L>And Nature bids a last farewell to life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are thy thoughts? O tell me whence they rise,</L>
<L>What is it shakes thy noble nature thus?</L>
<L>Ah! now I see, I read it in thy looks;</L>
<L>It must be so; destruction is complete,</L>
<L>And my great father falls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rome is no more;</L>
<L>Dire Clodius reeking with a mother's blood,</L>
<L>Plants the last wound in her expiring breast.</L>
<L>Peace, Science, Virtue, mutual Faith and Freedom,</L>
<L>Each Art, and every Grace is on the wing;</L>
<L>Before 'em flies the day, and at their back</L>
<L>Hellish Corruption sows the land with death,</L>
<L>Making a void more hideous and more dark</L>
<L>Than central Night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father, O my father!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I came this instant from the godlike man.</L>
<L>Silent long time the musing patriot sate,</L>
<L>His big heart lab'ring with contending cares;</L>
<L>While from his eyes the sacred pity fell,</L>
<L><PB N="45" REF="44"/>
Like Heav'n's blest dew upon a thankless soil,</L>
<L>And all the Father of his Country mourn'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah! what does he resolve?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>To leave this city,</L>
<L>To leave Terentia, and thy weeping self,</L>
<L>A voluntary Exile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah! an Exile?</L>
<L>It must not, can not be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! my Tullia,</L>
<L>Not built on fear, or Passion's slippery base,</L>
<L>His cool mature resolves are fix'd as Fate.</L>
<L>I heard the final sentence pass his lips;</L>
<L>To-morrow sees him turn his back on Rome,</L>
<L>Self-doom'd, to search for some more friendly shore,</L>
<L>There to abide till better days succeed,</L>
<L>And Rome deserves his presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave his Country,</L>
<L>Forsake his friends, forsake his houshold Gods,</L>
<L>And tear asunder each dear natural tie</L>
<L>That wraps about his heart? Heav'n will forbid it,</L>
<L>His bitterest foes will kneel to hold him back,</L>
<L>The very walls of Rome will rise against him,</L>
<L>And meeting close their great preserver in.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="46" REF="45"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! thou know'st not what a world thou liv'st in.</L>
<L>Dwells there in this base city one so bold,</L>
<L>Who dares to own himself the friend of Virtue?</L>
<L>The Public Body is diseas'd and foul,</L>
<L>Rotten at heart, and ripe for dissolution;</L>
<L>Our Magistrates are slaves, our Nobles beggars,</L>
<L>Our Courts of Justice made a public mart,</L>
<L>Where black Corruption holds her damning traffic</L>
<L>In the broad eye of day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then what am I?</L>
<L>Where can the fatherless look out for pity?</L>
<L>Ah! where can friendless Virtue hide her head?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never, while these fond arms have strength to move,</L>
<L>Or this poor bleeding heart has sense to beat,</L>
<L>Shall that dear head be left without a shelter.</L>
<L>Come, Clodius; come, Gabinius; to your swords</L>
<L>My willing breast I offer; spare my Tullia,</L>
<L>My dying lips shall bless you for the stroke,</L>
<L>And call its torture mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, my Caius!</L>
<L>Blest Hymen joys not in unequal bands.</L>
<L>O had I known thee in those happier days,</L>
<L>When Fortune smil'd upon my father's house,</L>
<L>Without a blush I should have told my love,</L>
<L>And thou with honour claim'd me for thy wife.</L>
<L><PB N="47" REF="46"/>
But now, instead of pow'r, and fame, and wealth,</L>
<L>To bring thee want and ruin for my portion,</L>
<L>Honour forbids it, and my heart that loves thee,</L>
<L>Scorns to be such a debtor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dearest maid,</L>
<L>Dearer in all thy wrongs, than if thou cam'st</L>
<L>Deck'd in the splendor of thy fullest fortune,</L>
<L>My soul almost rejoices in thy sorrows:</L>
<L>Ambition else had shar'd my thoughts with thee,</L>
<L>And Interest stol'n some portion of my love;</L>
<L>But now Adversity's refining fire</L>
<L>Melts down the base alloy of earthly passions,</L>
<L>And purifies the temper of the heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more; I must not hear that flatt'ring tongue;</L>
<L>My father now demands my duty—leave me.</L>
<L>Still are you here?—Farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgive me, Tullia,</L>
<L>I cannot leave thee. O I could unfold</L>
<L>A tale of horror.—The grim night comes on,</L>
<L>And the dark ministers of Hell are busy:</L>
<L>Let me not leave thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>If my hour is come,</L>
<L>And ruin hangs o'er this devoted head,</L>
<L>Make from the fall; live thou to think on me,</L>
<L>And grace my memory with a noble sorrow;</L>
<L><PB N="48" REF="47"/>
If I had lov'd thee less, we had not parted;</L>
<L>Now take my last embrace: Break, break, my heart!</L>
<L>Farewell, (alas! and must I say) for ever?</L>
<STAGE>(Exit Tullia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hast thou left me? Yet I will be near thee,</L>
<L>Glide after thee with still and ghost-like steps,</L>
<L>Haunt the lov'd spot, and hover o'er my treasure.</L>
<STAGE>(Exit Frugi.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3">
<HEAD>SCENE III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>An inner Apartment.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO,</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>is discovered alone.</STAGE>
<L>And what is Rome? There's breathing space enough</L>
<L>Without the walls of Rome; then Rome farewell:</L>
<L>I've said it; and my heart performs its office</L>
<L>As steadily as ever: But, O Nature,</L>
<L>With what voice shall I say, Farewell, Terentia,</L>
<L>Tullia, farewell? how heavily that sounds!</L>
<L>There, there's the pang: And yet there lies beyond it,</L>
<L>Something too horrible for thought—to page</L>
<L>Ambitious Caesar's heels, to lick the dust</L>
<L>Of Pompey's hall, and cringe for sordid life.</L>
<L>O death to Honour! Come thou, Clodius, rather,</L>
<L>And rip this breast: Yet on these slavish terms</L>
<L>Live all in Rome; be exile then my choice!</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> ATTICUS.</STAGE>
<L>Hah! by my soul's best hopes, my Atticus!</L>
<L>Blest be the guiding hand of Heav'n that brought thee,</L>
<L>From peaceful climes, and philosophic scenes,</L>
<L><PB N="49" REF="48"/>
Safe thro' a boist'rous and discordant world</L>
<L>To this storm-beaten hut.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still are you here?</L>
<L>Up, up, my friend, and disappoint these traitors:</L>
<L>Break from the toils just ready to enclose you,</L>
<L>And follow Virtue in her flight from Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, art thou come to chide me, my Pomponius?</L>
<L>But do it freely; it becomes thy friendship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot flatter; I am wean'd from Rome,</L>
<L>And Roman arts; I think that Caesar's oaths</L>
<L>Are empty words; and would not build my faith</L>
<L>On Pompey's promises, which drop as fast</L>
<L>From his oil'd lips, as flakes of snow from clouds;</L>
<L>And, oh! the sorrow, melt away as soon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both are ambitious, faithless both, and cruel;</L>
<L>Yet Caesar's bold oppression irks me less,</L>
<L>Than Pompey's pliant falshood. 'Twas this morn</L>
<L>I sought him on mount Alba, (do I live</L>
<L>To own it?) waited like a needy client</L>
<L>In his proud hall, whilst he escap'd unseen</L>
<L>Like a detected criminal, and left me</L>
<L>To think on faith, and ponder o'er my wrongs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is the ancient Roman spirit fled?</L>
<L><PB N="50" REF="49"/>
What are these mighty men, but as you make 'em?</L>
<L>Like a blind doating mother you have nurs'd</L>
<L>Growing Oppression, with the milk of Freedom,</L>
<L>Which now ingrateful, factious and adult,</L>
<L>Spurns at the breast it fed on: Hapless Rome,</L>
<L>Like a tame jade, hath giv'n her patient back</L>
<L>To each aspiring rider, and now spent</L>
<L>And giddy with the course of their ambition,</L>
<L>Sinks with her weight, and bleeds at every stroke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can no more: These hands, that once already</L>
<L>Have giv'n their country life, now want a shield</L>
<L>To fence themselves from ruin. O Pomponius,</L>
<L>Thé inevitable day comes on apace,</L>
<L>When this tyrannic league shall burst asunder;</L>
<L>And yon cemented friends, like ravening dogs,</L>
<L>Contending for their prey, drag different ways</L>
<L>The mangled remnant of expiring Freedom,</L>
<L>And drench the world in blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then make from Rome;</L>
<L>Seek out a shelter e're the night comes on,</L>
<L>And the wild uproar of the storm begins;</L>
<L>Call up the injur'd shade of great Metellus;</L>
<L>Hear him repeat his last departing words,</L>
<L>And let him point the road to glorious exile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more; it is resolv'd; thus, my Pomponius,</L>
<L><PB N="51" REF="50"/>
I banish Rome; behold! indignant thus</L>
<L>I cast behind me every tender thought</L>
<L>Of this degenerate country; never more</L>
<L>Shall these sad eyes behold th' all-glorious Sun</L>
<L>Rise on her guilty domes, till bath'd in tears,</L>
<L>Her proud head with repentant ashes strow'd,</L>
<L>This base unnatural Daughter lowly comes</L>
<L>To call her Father to his native home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come then, my friend, and in some distant land,</L>
<L>Where Freedom and the liberal Graces dwell,</L>
<L>We'll make ourselves a home, and call it Rome;</L>
<L>And fear not, Marcus, but the same bright Sun</L>
<L>That crowns the lofty Capitol, shall stoop</L>
<L>His gracious head with beams of orient gold</L>
<L>To kiss our humble dwelling; there together,</L>
<L>As Scipio and his Laelius idly pac'd</L>
<L>The shores of soft Laurentum, we will walk</L>
<L>The vacant beach, and as the thronging waves,</L>
<L>Like morning clients, bow their curled heads</L>
<L>To kiss our feet, we'll spurn the flatterers from us,</L>
<L>And blush to think we ever were ambitious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>O happy friend! thy calm and temperate mind,</L>
<L>With Attic wisdom fraught, can look with scorn</L>
<L>On base Ambition and its empty joys;</L>
<L>But all in vain, I struggle to get free,</L>
<L>The guilty world still hangs about my heart;</L>
<L><PB N="52" REF="51"/>
The pageantry of office, the loud shouts</L>
<L>Of the throng'd Forum, and the frequent Senate</L>
<L>With one voice, hailing me their Country's Father,</L>
<L>Still echo in my ears; bear with my weakness,</L>
<L>Rome yet sits heavy here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>O happier state!</L>
<L>To follow Nature in her simple haunts;</L>
<L>With early steps to climb the shaggy sides</L>
<L>Of some hoar cliff, and meet the dewy breath</L>
<L>Of Morning, issuing from the flow'ry vale:</L>
<L>Or soft reclining on the mossy turf,</L>
<L>In solemn musings rapt, or sacred song,</L>
<L>Careless to lie, and as the dimpling brook</L>
<L>Steals gently by, with motionless regard</L>
<L>To eye the floating mirror; while as fast</L>
<L>Down Meditation's smooth and silent tide,</L>
<L>In easy lapse your tuneful moments flow,</L>
<L>Clear and untroubled as the passing stream.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ho! Terentia; come, thou best of women;</L>
<L>And thou, my dearest Tullia, come. Behold,</L>
<L>My daughter and my wife! now judge me, Atticus,</L>
<L>And tell me if these sorrows are unseemly.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4">
<HEAD>SCENE IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE>CICERO, ATTICUS, TERENTIA, TULLIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I own them just.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="53" REF="52"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me embrace you both:</L>
<L>O Clodius, thou hast conquer'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still on Clodius?</L>
<L>Come to your peaceful bed; the night is dang'rous;</L>
<L>Strange screamings up and down the streets are heard,</L>
<L>Our Lares fall untouch'd, and your Minerva,</L>
<L>Chief of the tutélar Deities, dissolves</L>
<L>In drops of blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods, I obey your omens!</L>
<L>Come, lead me to the altar, my Terentia,</L>
<L>And let me see these prodigies; farewell,</L>
<L>Ye much-lov'd walls, ye shall not long survive</L>
<L>Your master's fall: no more of sleep within you:</L>
<L>Ye are my witness, 'tis not the first time</L>
<L>That I have watch'd for this ingrateful country.</L>
<L>O Friend, when I am gone, protect my wife,</L>
<L>And be a father to my helpless daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you forsake me, Tullius? On my knees</L>
<L>I beg you stay: Your friends are great and many;</L>
<L>Your hopes yet fresh and smiling, while the faction</L>
<L>And their cause drōp; murder not then your fame,</L>
<L>Abandon not your friends, your wife, your country,</L>
<L>But live our glory, and your foes confusion.</L>
<STAGE>(Terentia and Tullia kneel to him.</STAGE>
</SP>
<PB N="54" REF="53"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou too kneel, thou weeping, speechless maid?</L>
<STAGE>(To Tullia.</STAGE>
<L>Rise, rise, ye pow'rful pleaders! in your hands</L>
<L>I rest my cause. When I am gone from Rome,</L>
<L>And Envy that now tears me from her side,</L>
<L>Sated with vengeance, sleeps; arise you then,</L>
<L>And in the melting accents of distress</L>
<L>Tell my sad story, till at length you see</L>
<L>The soft infection stealing on your hearers,</L>
<L>And pitying Rome restores me to your arms.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>END OF THE THIRD ACT.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4">
<PB N="55" REF="54"/>
<HEAD>ACT IV.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1">
<HEAD>SCENE I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>A View of Mount</HI> PALATINE <HI>and</HI> CICERO<HI>'s Palace.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>CLODIUS, <HI>attended with Soldiers,</HI> &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>PEACE, and hear all! by Heav'n ye glad me well;</L>
<L>Thus drest in flames ye look as Romans should.</L>
<L>Is there amongst you one who loves reveng<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</L>
<L>Behold I bear a torch to light him to it.</L>
<L>Is there amongst you one who hates a tyrant?</L>
<L>Your Tribune tells you Cicero's a tyrant.</L>
<L>Then crush him, and be free; and in the spot,</L>
<L>Where you proud palace stands, I'll raise a shrine</L>
<L>To Liberty in memory of your fame.</L>
<L>You know your parts: Now, Romans, to your work.</L>
<STAGE>(Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2">
<HEAD>SCENE II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>TULLIA <HI>is dragged along by</HI> GABINIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O save me, save me—Monster, let me go,</L>
<L>Or I will rend Heav'n's concave with my cries;</L>
<L>Guardians of Virtue, hear me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease your clamour:</L>
<L>Virtue in Rome? You spend your breath in vain.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="56" REF="55"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you no pity? Romans, will you see</L>
<L>The daughter of your once lov'd Consul dragg'd</L>
<L>To horrid violation? Traitors! villains!</L>
<L>Where now, O Frugi; where art thou, my Caius?</L>
<STAGE>(Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3">
<HEAD>SCENE III.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Various Ornaments belonging to</HI> CICERO<HI>'s Palace, are borne across by</HI> CLODIUS' <HI>Soldiers. A Cry of Mercy is heard, and several Domestics are forced across the Stage.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>CLODIUS <HI>is discovered, they kneeling to him.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercy? away. The red plague seize you all!</L>
<L>Accurst and wither'd be the hand that spares you;</L>
<L>An universal curse involve mankind!</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> CLODIA.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, why rave you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cicero is fled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah! is he fled? 'tis well; it aids my project;</L>
<L>But what of Frugi?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He too is escap'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confusion to my hopes! And Tullia with him.</L>
<L>How have you slept to let 'em thus escape you?</L>
</SP>
<PB N="57" REF="56"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tullia is seiz'd; Gabinius bore her off,</L>
<L>Her father with Terentia, as it seems,</L>
<L>Fled to the Capitol.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forsook his daughter?</L>
<L>'Tis strange! and Frugi too (O gallant lover!)</L>
<L>Saw bold Gabinius seize his captive fair one,</L>
<L>And meanly turn'd his back upon her cries:</L>
<L>Perdition seize the coward! O my Publius!</L>
<L>Fly to the Capitol; from his asylum</L>
<L>Drag the pale fugitive, and never sheath</L>
<L>Thy manly sword, till you can say to Clodia,</L>
<L>"'Tis done: he lives no more."</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>My guide! my mistress!</L>
<L>I go thy ready minister of Death.</L>
<L>Farewell; you are obey'd, and he is nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! only worthy of thy Sister's love,</L>
<L>These arms shall welcome my returning hero,</L>
<L>With ecstasies that Nature dares not own,</L>
<L>And only Lovers feel.</L>
<STAGE>(Exit Clodius.</STAGE>
<L>No more of that—</L>
<L>Reflection touch not there.—</L>
<STAGE>A Noise is heard, as of the fall of a Building.</STAGE>
<L>Heav'ns, what a fall!</L>
<L>Behold the blazing trophy of Revenge!</L>
<L>Hail, glorious ruin, 'midst unnumber'd pangs,</L>
<L>There is some consolation in these horrors.</L>
<L><PB N="58" REF="57"/>
Yet Frugi lives—and Clodius' sword again</L>
<L>May quit its prey unflesh'd.—Prevent it then:</L>
<L>Secure my victim by a second blow—</L>
<L>Hah! by my hopes, Volumnius is at hand,</L>
<L>He's bold, and apt, and made for midnight uses—</L>
<L>Thus doubly arm'd, I come, ingrateful man!</L>
<L>With all the warm fond wishes of a bride</L>
<L>To meet thee, my belov'd! enjoy thy pangs,</L>
<L>And in thy blood consummate my revenge.</L>
<STAGE>(Exit Clodia.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4">
<HEAD>SCENE IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>The Portico of the Capitol.</HI> FRUGI <HI>and</HI> TULLIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here we are safe; Murder and Violation</L>
<L>Far off avoid these consecrated walls,</L>
<L>Aw'd by the present God. Weep then no more,</L>
<L>Look up and know thy Frugi: The dire image</L>
<L>Of the accurst Gabinius haunts thee yet,</L>
<L>And when I strain you in my faithful arms,</L>
<L>You start and cry, "Off, off! and force me not!"</L>
<L>So the poor deer, that 'scapes the hunter's toils,</L>
<L>Trembling and panting with tumultuous fears</L>
<L>Looks all around her, starts at every breeze,</L>
<L>And with her lov'd companion by her side</L>
<L>In her safe haunt, still thinks herself pursued.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O born to save and to possess my heart!</L>
<L>At length I wake to Reason and to thee;</L>
<L>Thy well-lov'd form, like the all-glorious Sun</L>
<L><PB N="59" REF="58"/>
After a gloom of horror dawns upon me,</L>
<L>And day breaks in on my benighted soul.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>But tell me, Tullia, if thy fears have left</L>
<L>So much remembrance with thee, what strange chance</L>
<L>Staid thee behind, thus helpless and alone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soon as the tumult of the night began,</L>
<L>And Clodius enter'd with his savage crew,</L>
<L>Thro' all the house I heard a dreadful voice</L>
<L>Calling aloud on thee: Our houshold slaves</L>
<L>Wild and unarm'd ran shrieking up and down:</L>
<L>My father fled; with weak and tott'ring steps</L>
<L>I follow'd; when anon the uproar ceas'd.</L>
<L>Whereat, methought, a faint and dying voice</L>
<L>Cried, "Frugi is no more."—At that I stopt;</L>
<L>Rooted with fear and motionless I stood.</L>
<L>Again it murmur'd—"Caius is no more"—</L>
<L>When all at once, unknowing what I did,</L>
<L>I plung'd into the flames, thro' ev'ry room</L>
<L>Pursu'd the flying voice; while all around</L>
<L>The blazing roof burst o'er my desperate head,</L>
<L>And the fierce spoilers toss'd their flaming brands:</L>
<L>'Twas here Gabinius—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! break off thy story.</L>
<L>Good Heav'n! hadst thou the heart to rush thro' flames</L>
<L>And men, more fierce than flames, for Frugi's sake,</L>
<L>When thy fond fancy heard his dying groans?</L>
<L><PB N="60" REF="59"/>
O wond'rous effort of transcendent love!</L>
<L>How hast thou by this all-exceeding act,</L>
<L>Stript my last service of its little merit,</L>
<L>And made my love a bankrupt!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Caius,</L>
<L>Thus may I keep thee ever in my debt:</L>
<L>But ah! I tremble for thee, my Preserver,</L>
<L>To think the wretch that seiz'd me is a Consul.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wou'd he had met the death! blush, Greatness, blush,</L>
<L>Rage on, ye flames, and bury Rome in ruins,</L>
<L>For Lust and Murder have usurp'd dominion,</L>
<L>And Virtue's cries are sent to Heav'n against thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, Frugi, peace: The all-disposing God,</L>
<L>Who from this Capitol, his earthly throne,</L>
<L>Surveys all Rome, and sees and knows our wrongs,</L>
<L>Just to our cause, in his own chosen time</L>
<L>Vengeful will launch his unexpected bolt,</L>
<L>And crush 'em in the fulness of their crimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Methinks a voice, like the complaintive sound</L>
<L>Of distant waters, thro' the vaulted isles</L>
<L>Deep-murmuring strikes mine ear.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my father's.</L>
<L>Here in the presence of protector Jove</L>
<L>Secure he vents the anguish of his heart,</L>
<L><PB N="61" REF="60"/>
And bids farewell to Rome. With silent steps</L>
<L>And reverential awe, let us approach</L>
<L>The venerable man; when Virtue mourns,</L>
<L>The Gods are present and partake its sorrows.</L>
<STAGE>(Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5">
<HEAD>SCENE V.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>The inner Part of the Capitol.</HI> CICERO, TERENTIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Author of Life, behold and help thy Creature!</L>
<L>Is Reason giv'n us, yet its use denied?</L>
<L>So were thy gift our torment. Freely then,</L>
<L>Oh! let me ask, by what law dost thou govern?</L>
<L>By Justice—as becomes a gracious Father?</L>
<L>Or by wild will—as suits a lawless King?</L>
<L>Not so besure. Then let the guilty tremble;</L>
<L>Virtue is safe from harm. So I myself</L>
<L>Guilty pronounce; else wherefore thus undone?</L>
<L>Does Conscience, that just Judge, confirm my sentence?</L>
<L>There I am clear. My faults are then not mine,</L>
<L>But Nature's; against which no verdict lies:</L>
<L>Have the Gods less forbearance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou methinks,</L>
<L>My Tullius, hast too much. Can Reason heal</L>
<L>Wrongs, great as ours? No; 'tis Revenge must cure 'em.</L>
<L>Would I could breathe my woman's soul into thee!</L>
<L>Ills, that make thee despair, embolden me.</L>
<L>Yon palace, which now blazes to its base,</L>
<L>Feels not so fierce a flame as rages here.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="62" REF="61"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>But this, perhaps, is best; and Heav'n may lay</L>
<L>Her rod on Virtue's head, to teach mankind</L>
<L>That retribution lies beyond the Grave,</L>
<L>And stretch their prospect to another Life.</L>
<L>Need Heav'n to prove its mercy then be cruel?</L>
<L>Can good ends spring from none but evil means?</L>
<L>O Jove! in justice if thou art not seen,</L>
<L>Where shall we seek thee? I am lost in doubt:</L>
<L>This only melancholy truth I know,</L>
<L>That Clodius triumphs, and that I'm undone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>All is not lost; go forth: The name of Cicero,</L>
<L>That magic word, shall raise all Rome about you;</L>
<L>Meet Ruin in mid-way, and beat it back</L>
<L>On him that sent it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vain, presumptuous hope!</L>
<L>Save only my integrity, Terentia,</L>
<L>What in this world have these despoilers left me?</L>
<L>With thee I soon must part, and what sad fortune</L>
<L>Attends my absent daughter, Heaven alone,</L>
<L>And the dread Agents of Heav'n's vengeance know;</L>
<L>My Friends—but wherefore name I friends? They drop'd</L>
<L>With the first blast that shook me.</L>
<STAGE>(Frugi and Tullia enter.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6">
<HEAD>SCENE VI.</HEAD>
<STAGE>FRUGI, TULLIA, CICERO <HI>and</HI> TERENTIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, Despairer,</L>
<L><PB N="63" REF="62"/>
Yet, yet, we are not quite renounc'd of Heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Tullia, O my daughter, do I live</L>
<L>Once more to see and bless thee, e're we part?</L>
<L>How did I lose thee in this night's confusion?</L>
<L>And how, when Death and Violation scour</L>
<L>Th' affrighted city, arm'd with all Hell's flames,</L>
<L>Hast thou, defenceless maid, escap'd unhurt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold the guardian of my life and honour!</L>
<L>Dragg'd by the hands of the accurst Gabinius</L>
<L>Half-dead and sinking with my fears he found me,</L>
<L>Like my preserving Angel, he redeem'd me,</L>
<L>Snatch'd me from death and ruin, brought me to thee,</L>
<L>And gave me second life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>All-gracious Powers!</L>
<L>If when ye rain'd your sorrows on my head,</L>
<L>Unknowing of your provident designs,</L>
<L>And to the period of my sufferings blind,</L>
<L>Murmuring I took my fate, impute it not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that I dar'd to speak! but Tullia's looks</L>
<L>Awe, while they charm, and while they prompt, forbid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Rome! O Country! once the patriot soil</L>
<L>Of Freedom; parent once of god-like Virtues,</L>
<L>Mistress of Arts and Empire! now, alas!</L>
<L>The dying victim of unnatural Faction,</L>
<L><PB N="64" REF="63"/>
And stage of rank Corruption! Yet I'll hope,</L>
<L>Fall'n as thou art, yet I'll not deem thee lost,</L>
<L>While thou can'st boast one son of genuine worth,</L>
<L>Noble, as this dear Youth: Thou see'st, my Frugi,</L>
<L>How Rome rewards my services; yet, oh!</L>
<L>Let not the memory of my wrongs extinguish</L>
<L>That spark divine, which animates the soul,</L>
<L>And lights the path of glory; but where I,</L>
<L>Torn from my Country's side, now drop the work</L>
<L>Unfinish'd, thou with fresher nerves succeed</L>
<L>To the brave toil, and fill the mighty plan</L>
<L>With Freedom, such as our great Fathers gave it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my soul burns within me! O my guide,</L>
<L>Model my young ambition; teach me how</L>
<L>I may deserve to die in this great cause,</L>
<L>And leave a name immortal as thy own.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>By one firm faithful even course of honour;</L>
<L>By standing forth alone, not Caesar's follower,</L>
<L>Not Pompey's slave, but Rome's and Virtue's friend:</L>
<L>Sworn to no party; 'midst corruption pure;</L>
<L>Scorning all titles, dignities, and wealth,</L>
<L>When weigh'd against Integrity; rememb'ring</L>
<L>That Patriot is the highest name on earth.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> ATTICUS.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hail, Friend! or rather let me greet thee, Exile!</L>
<L>For from this night, I'll own no other name:</L>
<L><PB N="65" REF="64"/>
Roman? no more on't; Scythian call me rather;</L>
<L>For we have chang'd conditions: Social Virtue</L>
<L>Is fled beyond the mountains; nothing now</L>
<L>Is truly barbarous, but within these walls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there aught new abroad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can be new,</L>
<L>When I have seen mount Palatine? what strange,</L>
<L>When I have heard the Father of his Country</L>
<L>Revil'd, insulted, banish'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Came you thence,</L>
<L>From yonder pile of ruin?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis no more:</L>
<L>These eyes beheld it level with the dust;</L>
<L>The mansion of my friend, the social seat</L>
<L>Of polish'd manners, gay convivial wit,</L>
<L>And hospitable ease. Alas! the days,</L>
<L>The nights, that we have known! Bear with me, Marcus,</L>
<L>But my remembrance gave such life and being</L>
<L>To the sad scene, so knit and wove together</L>
<L>Things living with inanimate; methought</L>
<L>'Twas thou, my friend, that fell; struck with the sight,</L>
<L>I follow'd the false impulse of my heart,</L>
<L>And on the senseless ashes dropt a tear.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I look'd not for this show of tenderness,</L>
<L><PB N="66" REF="65"/>
And thank thee for it from my heart, my Atticus:</L>
<L>But tears are catching, and these eyes are apt</L>
<L>To every soft infection. You have said,</L>
<L>When you would wean my thoughts from Rome, "Content</L>
<L>"Depends not upon place;" Why then farewell</L>
<L>Ye scenes of past delights, exil'd from you</L>
<L>With Freedom and with Virtue for my guides,</L>
<L>Indifferent where to fix, I'll range the world,</L>
<L>And Rome shall follow me where'er I go.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arise, set forth, cast not a look behind,</L>
<L>But seize the present Now; on every side,</L>
<L>Around, above, beneath you, all is Treason;</L>
<L>Our streets, our houses, nay, our very temples,</L>
<L>Daily she haunts; ev'n here you are not safe;</L>
<L>On Jove's own Capitol her ensigns float,</L>
<L>And bid defiance to the bolts of Heav'n.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me the Statue—"Stand thou there; Minerva,</L>
<L>"Goddess ador'd! my last departing pledge</L>
<L>"To after-ages; prop the falling state,</L>
<L>"And be to Rome what Cicero is no more."—</L>
<L>Now, friends, have with you; bear with me this once,</L>
<L>I'll task your friendship but a few short hours,</L>
<L>And quit you then for ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Break, break, Heart!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confusion light on the whole race of Clodius!</L>
<L>Must we be torn asunder?</L>
</SP>
<PB N="67" REF="66"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spare, O spare me!</L>
<L>The cruel moment comes full fraught with woe</L>
<L>Sufficient for itself. Now Frugi, Atticus,</L>
<L>Dear Youth, and best approved Friend, bestir you;</L>
<L>South of the Capitol take you your course,</L>
<L>And fetch a wider compass; from mount Aventine</L>
<L>Summon young Curio to the Capuan gate:</L>
<L>Thou eastward to the Caelian hill, my Atticus,</L>
<L>Call up Hortensius, raise Servilius Rufus,</L>
<L>Lentulus and Caelius; but let Milo sleep;</L>
<L>His heady zeal will know no bounds, and stain</L>
<L>The civil tenour of my cause with blood.</L>
<L>Do this, and meet me both at Vesta's Temple;</L>
<L>There I must render up to her protection</L>
<L>This well-beloved charge. Pass on; that way</L>
<L>Is private.—Hah! and am I fall'n so low?</L>
<L>I, that so often have been borne along</L>
<L>In triumph thro' these gates.—Mark this, young Man,</L>
<L>And learn the vanity of Human Greatness.</L>
<STAGE>(Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="7">
<HEAD>SCENE VII.</HEAD>
<STAGE>The Entrance of the Capitol.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis He; (may lightning catch and blast his speed!)</L>
<L>'Tis Frugi; muffled as he is, I know him:</L>
<L>Just where the moon-beam smites athwart the portal</L>
<L>My eye o'er-took him; (would my sword had so!)</L>
<L>What can be done? Singly attempt a faction;</L>
<L><PB N="68" REF="67"/>
And rush on certain death? My band all broke,</L>
<L>Buried in wine and plunder: Then the place—</L>
<L>Jove's own peculiar Temple; who if aught</L>
<L>Can stir him, now must put forth all the God,</L>
<L>Or lose his name Capitoline. No more:</L>
<L>Away, vain fears; ye strangers to my heart!</L>
<L>Alone, without a friend, save this good sword,</L>
<L>And the great ruling Fate that moves within me,</L>
<L>Against all Law, and Right, and Men, and Gods,</L>
<L>Thus I advance to conquest, or to death.</L>
<STAGE>(Enters the Capitol.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="8">
<HEAD>SCENE VIII.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>enters alone.</STAGE>
<L>It must be by his blood: The word is past</L>
<L>'Twixt me and Death, and he expects his victim.</L>
<L>My love I tender'd, he disdain'd my love,</L>
<L>And chose my vengeance; vengeance let him have!</L>
<L>Is this hard dealing, Gods? In common life,</L>
<L>Things noxious and abhorr'd we freely kill,</L>
<L>But what we love we spare; my heart then asks</L>
<L>Must Frugi die? Ah! rather must he live;</L>
<L>For Tullia live? while this despised form,</L>
<L>To which the proudest knees in Rome have bent,</L>
<L>Whilst Heav'n was left unworship'd, shall abide</L>
<L>The killing taunts of an insulting Rival,</L>
<L>And waste itself with Envy. Come, Volumnius;</L>
<L>Come Clodius! rather let your keen swords meet</L>
<L>And hack each other, in the dying heart</L>
<L>Of this dear scornful youth. My Soul is tost</L>
<L><PB N="69" REF="68"/>
Upon a sea of blood, whose stormy channel</L>
<L>My lab'ring bark must pass, e're it can reach</L>
<L>That land of Peace, to which its Hopes are bound.</L>
<STAGE>CLODIUS <HI>comes out of the Temple.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah! who art thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>A woman, and a bold one;</L>
<L>That shrinks not to receive thee to her arms,</L>
<L>Fresh from thy crimes, and purpled o'er with blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hail, Mistress of my Soul; 'tis done: Revenge</L>
<L>Hath had her fill, and Frugi is no more.</L>
<L>Warm from the living fountain of his heart,</L>
<L>Behold how, like a young and blushing maid,</L>
<L>My pale steel, flecker'd with the ruddy drops,</L>
<L>Weeps for the deed 't has done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me the dagger:</L>
<L>And is this then the haughty high-born blood,</L>
<L>That flush'd with conscious pride upon his cheek,</L>
<L>When deaf to Love's soft pray'rs he spurn'd me from him,</L>
<L>And chid me with an insolence of Virtue?</L>
<L>Now, Clodius, where's the body?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drench'd in blood</L>
<L>On the cold pavement, and defac'd with wounds,</L>
<L>There, where it fell it lies. Alone I enter'd;</L>
<L>I listen'd; all was silence; save the sound</L>
<L><PB N="70" REF="69"/>
Of feet light treading on the echoing floor;</L>
<L>Near and more near he came; I cow'ring low</L>
<L>Crept behind Pompey's statue; till at once,</L>
<L>Quick as a lion from his watch, upon him</L>
<L>I sprung, and thrust my weapon to his heart;</L>
<L>He started, fell, and died without a groan.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>But where was Cicero?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where fled I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is enough; my vengeance is complete.</L>
<L>Drag forth the body.—Yet I'll view those eyes</L>
<L>Seated in death; Clodius hath marr'd their lustre,</L>
<L>And I may gaze unharm'd.</L>
<STAGE>(Clodius drags the Body sorth.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What have I done?</L>
<L>Volumnius?—aim'd my dagger at my foe,</L>
<L>And struck a Sister's heart. Where shall I vent</L>
<L>My curses? on the living or the dead?</L>
<L>On him, myself, or Frugi? Hence, away!</L>
<L>Thou hateful minister.</L>
<STAGE>(Throws away his Dagger.</STAGE>
<L>Oh! I am mock'd</L>
<L>Of Heaven, and made the veriest fool of Nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was this well done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, by Heav'n I swear—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>And dar'st thou swear</L>
<L><PB N="71" REF="70"/>
By Heav'n, when Hell itself is in thy heart?</L>
<L>I bad thee strike a bold and open foe;</L>
<L>Thou basely murder'st an unguarded friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do I deserve this of thee? Think, O think!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis thought that makes me mad. Ah! wretched me!</L>
<L>Doom'd to be wrong'd and scorn'd by those I lov'd.</L>
<L>For thee, ingrateful, have I stab'd my fame?</L>
<L>For thee endur'd the hiss of public scorn,</L>
<L>And stifled Nature's cries? Was it for thee,</L>
<L>That thou might'st revel in my widow'd arms,</L>
<L>I plung'd my soul in blood; a Husband's blood?</L>
<L>And is not this enough? must he too perish,</L>
<L>That guiltless youth, who troubled not the fount</L>
<L>Of thy delights, but drank at humble distance</L>
<L>The leavings of thy joys.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I own I wish'd</L>
<L>To hold entire possession of thy soul:</L>
<L>But 'twas in vain; I saw unnumber'd rivals,</L>
<L>And yet with-held Revenge. Think you I knew not,</L>
<L>When with that fatal steel you arm'd my hand,</L>
<L>And bad me bury it in Frugi's heart;</L>
<L>Think you I knew not then that desperate Love,</L>
<L>And frantic Disappointment doom'd his death?</L>
<L>Yes, Clodia, yes: And therefore 'twas I flew,</L>
<L>Prompt to fulfil thy vengeance and my own,</L>
<L>Nor staid the shifting of a woman's will:</L>
<L>Twice he hath 'scap'd me, yet again I'll meet him,</L>
<L><PB N="72" REF="71"/>
And then redeem my error.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never, never.</L>
<L>Had'st thou at first obey'd and murder'd Caius,</L>
<L>I must have hated him who shed his blood,</L>
<L>But not as now despis'd: Henceforth he lives.</L>
<L>My next revenge a surer hand shall act,</L>
<L>And in a juster cause.—Alas! Volumnius;</L>
<L>Thou never slighted'st me, as Caius did;</L>
<L>Thou wast not harsh, ungrateful, as this Brother,</L>
<L>But ever apt and gentle to' my wishes;</L>
<L>I did not think to have grac'd thee with a tear,</L>
<L>But thy sad fate demands it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there's truth,</L>
<L>Or honesty in man, I knew him not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I know thee. Oh! that my breath could give</L>
<L>Motion and utterance to these pale cold lips,</L>
<L>And put a tongue into each gaping wound;</L>
<L>That from as many several mouths at once,</L>
<L>As thou to him in jealousy gave strokes,</L>
<L>I might proclaim thee lyar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hear me, Clodia—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I'll not hear: Cry to the roaring winds,</L>
<L>When they unseat the everlasting rocks,</L>
<L>And lift the wild waves to the vaulted Heav'n,</L>
<L>And thou shalt find an audience from the storm,</L>
<L><PB N="73" REF="72"/>
But me for ever deaf.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then to the winds</L>
<L>I will complain, for they shall hear my wrongs,</L>
<L>And bear 'em on their charitable wings</L>
<L>To every shore they visit. Luckless man!</L>
<L>O thou, by ill-designing Nature cast</L>
<L>In the same mould with Frugi; what dark errand</L>
<L>Brought thee to this dire place? Ah! why conceal'd you</L>
<L>That ill-star'd head? and thou, malicious Planet,</L>
<L>Why wouldst not lend thy light?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not Frugi's form,</L>
<L>Not this dark hour, nor ill-designing Nature,</L>
<L>But the sole crime of being lov'd by Clodia,</L>
<L>Brought thee to this sad end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Injurious woman,</L>
<L>Wou'd that men's thoughts were graven on their hearts!</L>
<L>So should these hands of mine to thy confusion</L>
<L>Pluck out the bleeding witness of my truth,</L>
<L>And die upon the proof.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bare to my eye,</L>
<L>As is thy face, thy guilty bosom lies;</L>
<L>And there in staring characters I read</L>
<L>Murder and Jealousy; infernal names!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murder and Jealousy? O Clodia, Clodia,</L>
<L>Talk'st thou of murder, thou, whose soul is dy'd</L>
<L>Deeper than are these hands which did thy work?</L>
<L>Talk'st thou of Jealousy?—Who doom'd to death</L>
<L>The guiltless Frugi for his faith to Tullia?</L>
<L><PB N="74" REF="73"/>
Who arm'd my hand this fatal night with flames</L>
<L>'Gainst Cicero's palace? Who inspir'd Gabinius</L>
<L>To seize thy shrieking rival? Who but thou</L>
<L>And that unhappy man, thy guilty minion,</L>
<L>Mixt the dire dose which brave Metellus drank,</L>
<L>And shed a Husband's blood? This thou hast done;</L>
<L>Then talk no more of Jealousy and Murder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take up your sword; lo! where the deathful weapon</L>
<L>Lies at the side of him it basely slew;</L>
<L>Behold my ready bosom; plunge it here.</L>
<L>A curse is fallen on our guilty Loves;</L>
<L>And I am weary of the world and thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, you've done me wrong; yet shall my hand</L>
<L>Not spill your blood: But if you're bent on death,</L>
<L>Behold I leave you that; when life is irksome,</L>
<L>'Tis all the remedy I know for sorrow.</L>
<STAGE>(Exit Clodius.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be so. My Soul approves the counsel.</L>
<STAGE>(Takes up the dagger.</STAGE>
<L>Now, Frugi, since the over-ruling will</L>
<L>Of Fate denies me to repay thy scorn;</L>
<L>'Tis well this way is left me to avoid it.</L>
<L>Farewell, poor murder'd Corse! What, do thy wounds</L>
<L>Open afresh, and answer me in blood?</L>
<L>Thus to the Manes of my murder'd Honour</L>
<L>I make libation; to the vengeful Sisters,</L>
<L>Who with scorch'd feet travel the burning soil,</L>
<L>Where Phlegethon his fiery torrent rolls,</L>
<L>These Harbingers I send: Open, firm Earth,</L>
<L>And give 'em passage to announce my coming.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>END OF THE FOURTH ACT.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5">
<PB N="75" REF="74"/>
<HEAD>ACT V.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1">
<HEAD>SCENE I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>The</HI> TEMPLE <HI>of</HI> VESTA.</STAGE>
<STAGE>CICERO, TERENTIA, TULLIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>LIFE of the World! First Principle and last!</L>
<L>All-powerful Element! Hail Vesta, hail!</L>
<L>To thy protecting Altars I bequeath</L>
<L>This Pledge; oh! may thine ever-wakeful fires</L>
<L>Catch and consume the wretch, that dares attempt</L>
<L>This hospitable shrine. Now hold, my heart!</L>
<L>Terentia, come forward; time is short,</L>
<L>Yet I have much to say—my wife, my wife!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that thus folded in each others arms,</L>
<L>Here, as we've liv'd, together we might fall!</L>
<L>Or parting hence in social exile join'd,</L>
<L>Set forth, and take our fates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Might that be so,</L>
<L>Ruin would lose its name; Exile its terrors,</L>
<L>And Clodius reap no triumph from my fall.</L>
<L>But Heaven that gave a blessing to our bed,</L>
<L>Stampt the great Law of Nature on my heart,</L>
<L>And bound me to it by the sacred ties</L>
<L>Of fatherly affection; can I then</L>
<L><PB N="76" REF="75"/>
Wed my poor Tullia to disgrace and sorrow,</L>
<L>And to my Boy bequeath the bitter portion</L>
<L>Of Exile, and hereditary ruin?</L>
<L>Rather, just Gods! if so ye deem it fit,</L>
<L>Let me atone for all; on me be pour'd</L>
<L>Your whole collected vengeance, and repay me</L>
<L>For these dire wrongs, this undeserv'd affliction,</L>
<L>An hundred fold, as heav'nly bounty should,</L>
<L>In blessings on my children.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my father,</L>
<L>When thou art gone, and the great mound is broke</L>
<L>Which stood betwixt us and a stormy world,</L>
<L>And threw the black and beating surges from us,</L>
<L>Th' exasperated torrent rolling back,</L>
<L>Whelming upon us thro' the fatal breach,</L>
<L>Shall burst resistless o'er our feeble banks,</L>
<L>And pour a deluge of destruction round.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Daughter, I've look'd into the hearts of men,</L>
<L>And trac'd the shifting passions, as they turn</L>
<L>To opposite extremes; there I have mark'd,</L>
<L>When Envy keeps the throne, 'tis Hell within us:</L>
<L>Soon as the guilty passion is allay'd,</L>
<L>The green and morbid colour of our souls</L>
<L>Is chang'd to virgin white; a gentle breeze</L>
<L>Of pity springs within us; with fond sorrow</L>
<L>Upon our prostrate rival we look down,</L>
<L>And mourn our own success.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="77" REF="76"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Clodius relent?—</L>
<L>Gabinius feel the gentle touch of pity?—</L>
<L>Bid the sun blanch the raven's jetty plume,</L>
<L>Tho' Nature steep'd it in her darkest dye,</L>
<L>And it shall sooner take a dove-like hue,</L>
<L>Than their fell hearts remorse. What fence so high</L>
<L>To bound their vast ambition? What so sacred</L>
<L>To stem their impious fury? Why this night</L>
<L>May they not force us hence? Alas, what help?</L>
<L>Our cries will then not reach thee; thou'lt hold on</L>
<L>Thy solitary course, and fondly think us</L>
<L>In this asylum safe. What chance that he,</L>
<L>Who mocks the Goddess, should revere her Temple?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nature, that made you pow'rless, made herself</L>
<L>Your fond Protectress; set a guard about you</L>
<L>Of winning charms, and bid you walk secure</L>
<L>Amidst a warring world; then fear not Clodius;</L>
<L>Fierce tho' he be, he cannot quite st<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ike off</L>
<L>The seal that Heav'n hath set upon its work,</L>
<L>And cease to be a man.—Now, Atticus,</L>
<L>Comes Curio with you?</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> ATTICUS.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>At the Capuan Gate</L>
<L>He waits your coming: All the City wakes;</L>
<L>Pale staring forms course up and down the streets,</L>
<L>Half-dead with fear and wonder; naked some,</L>
<L><PB N="78" REF="77"/>
As if the Gaul was at their doors; all weep</L>
<L>And smite their breasts, and call upon your name:</L>
<L>Amongst the rest, I met your freedman Tiro;</L>
<L>Horrid and wan he look'd, and bath'd in tears;</L>
<L>With thick and falt'ring speech he question'd me</L>
<L>Of his dear Lord. What follows is the worst—</L>
<L>Young Frugi, as 'tis said, by Clodius' hand,</L>
<L>Was in the Capitol most basely murder'd;</L>
<L>And lies in public view a lifeless Corse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbid it Heav'n!</L>
<STAGE>(Tullia falls into her mother's arms.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! my child, my child!</L>
<L>Keen Anguish wrings her heart. She faints; she dies.</L>
<L>Help, help, your daughter dies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would Heav'n I might!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my prophetic Soul! Thy story, Atticus,</L>
<L>Hath murder'd my poor Tullia; hapless Love,</L>
<L>Thy Victim she expires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will not be;</L>
<L>My officious heart yet beats, and feeble Grief</L>
<L>Slowly puts out the stubborn lamp of Life.</L>
<L>What have I done? Usurp'd a Father's right,</L>
<L>And giv'n my soul away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Severe, O Gods!</L>
<L><PB N="79" REF="78"/>
To me and to my House, hath been thy doom.</L>
<L>Such evils from conceal'd affections spring.</L>
<L>Why, O my daughter—? but I'll not reproach thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shame stopt my voice; Honour, and conscious Pride,</L>
<L>That scorn'd to meet on less than equal terms,</L>
<L>And hope of happier days: While Frugi liv'd</L>
<L>Thy sorrows kept possession of my heart,</L>
<L>And Love receded from the stronger guest;</L>
<L>Now his dear image rises to my view</L>
<L>So piteously array'd, with such a train</L>
<L>Of tender thoughts assails this shatter'd frame,</L>
<L>That Reason quits her fort, and flies before,</L>
<L>To the last verge of phrenzy and despair.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Frugi, O my Son! for by that name</L>
<L>Henceforth I'll call thee ever, what dire fate</L>
<L>Hangs o'er the fortunes and the friends of Cicero?</L>
<L>What curse shall I invoke? Where'er I turn,</L>
<L>Full in my view that hated monster stands,</L>
<L>Thwarts every hope, and murders every joy.</L>
<L>O friend, hast thou no comfort to bestow?</L>
<L>Revoke the cruel tale: Saidst thou the Capitol?</L>
<L>It cannot be—we parted thence together:</L>
<L>With hasty strides I saw him shape his course</L>
<L>Strait to the Caelian mount.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true he lives,</L>
<L>And I renounce my fears. Shame on his tongue,</L>
<L>Who told you this false tale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="80" REF="79"/>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas your-own Tiro.</L>
<L>Why will you thus provoke the fatal truth?</L>
<L>Lost in the wild disorder of the night,</L>
<L>As thro the city streets he sought you out,</L>
<L>Chance led him to the Capitol: At once</L>
<L>The well-known form of Clodia struck his view;</L>
<L>Before the Temple's porch aloft she stood;</L>
<L>Musing and sad she seem'd. When soon, behold!</L>
<L>With loud recoil the sacred doors flew back;</L>
<L>Forth rush'd a ghastly form, and wav'd a sword</L>
<L>Dripping with blood; when with a voice that shook</L>
<L>The vaulted dome, and spoke him very Clodius,</L>
<L>"'Tis done (he cried) vengeance has had her fill,</L>
<L>"And Frugi is no more." At that dire word,</L>
<L>Tiro affrighted, shrunk, and fled unseen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! 'tis apparent all; 'tis Truth as clear</L>
<L>As Oracle e're spoke. Now who shall comfort me?</L>
<L>Now who shall reason him to Life again,</L>
<L>Or me to Peace? will you, or you, attempt it?</L>
<L>Ah! no; ye both despair. Then give me way,</L>
<L>And since ye cannot bring to me my Caius,</L>
<L>I'll fly to him.—</L>
<STAGE>(Frugi enters.</STAGE>
<L>Nay, if your tombs can't hold you,</L>
<L>But you must rise with all your wounds about you,</L>
<L>And stalk abroad in common with the Living,</L>
<L>The world's too narrow for us both: Down, down!</L>
<L>Or give us up your Graves.—Nay, now—'tis past.</L>
<STAGE>(Frugi catches her in his arms.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="81" REF="80"/>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why do you bend such fearful eyes on me?</L>
<L>Speak he that can, and tell me whence this horror!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Joyful Surprize, not Horror, wraps us thus,</L>
<L>To see thee living, whom Report had murder'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who then hath done this deed?</L>
<STAGE>(Looking on Tullia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast, my son.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>So is my guilt, my blessing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, unhand me.</L>
<L>I knew him and his errand: I can die</L>
<L>In spite of you; Death's thousand doors are open,</L>
<L>And this rebellious Spirit will break prison,</L>
<L>To make itself an entrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lead her forth.</L>
<L>She's thine, if Heav'n restore her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, good Heaven,</L>
<L>Or calm her senses, or extinguish mine.</L>
<STAGE>(Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2">
<HEAD>SCENE II.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>A Street in</HI> ROME.</STAGE>
<STAGE>CLODIUS, GABINIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gabinius, welcome. Wherefore droops my friend?</L>
<L><PB N="82" REF="81"/>
What, foil'd at your late revel? You have ta'en</L>
<L>Too full a meal of Tullia's maiden fruit,</L>
<L>And the pall'd appetite now turns aside</L>
<L>With loathing and aversion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Clodius, no;</L>
<L>She's lost; perdition light on him that stole her!</L>
<L>Sure some curst Demon hovers in the air,</L>
<L>And showers down mischief on this fatal night.</L>
<L>She's vanish'd, gone, untasted, unenjoy'd,</L>
<L>Snatch'd like a dream from the deluded sight,</L>
<L>And left no trace behind, but Shame and Anguish,</L>
<L>And racking Disappointment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Curst mischance!</L>
<L>What villain tore her from you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! no more.</L>
<L>Thou hast thy sorrows, Clodius, I have mine.</L>
<L>Liberal of Ill, Fate hath bestow'd on each,</L>
<L>Griefs of their own, and not to thee the least.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are they? Speak. Dost pause? O fear me not.</L>
<L>Ills cannot come too sudden for the brave:</L>
<L>I live at war with Fate, and scorn to hold</L>
<L>My being in unmanly base dependence</L>
<L>Upon the wayward stars; but seize the present,</L>
<L>And bid defiance to the coming hour,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Clodia is dead.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="83" REF="82"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then I thank thee, Nature,</L>
<L>That when you made this frame of such frail stuff,</L>
<L>So sensible of harm, so ill array'd</L>
<L>To combat sharp Misfortune, yet you cas'd</L>
<L>My Heart in temper'd steel, and made it proof</L>
<L>Against the soft compunctious stroke of Pity,</L>
<L>Bidding it laugh at all that Fate can do.</L>
<L>Now, if thou can'st, relate the Tale of Death,</L>
<L>And keep no circumstance of horror back;</L>
<L>For 'tis a sound familiar to my ear,</L>
<L>And needs no softening to inure me to it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alone, and musing on my wayward Fate,</L>
<L>As tow'rds Mount Palatine I took my way</L>
<L>A short hour since, I met that wretched woman,</L>
<L>Whom you no more call Sister: Mad she seem'd,</L>
<L>Convulsion shook her frame; wild Horror glar'd</L>
<L>In her chang'd visage; eager was her speech,</L>
<L>And broke with frequent sighs: She bad me follow;</L>
<L>In silence I obey'd; she led me on.</L>
<L>Nor cast a look behind, till to the fount</L>
<L>Of Niobe we came.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know the place,</L>
<L>South of Mount Aventine it lies; the grove</L>
<L>Of spreading beeches, that embower the fount,</L>
<L>Was her most favour'd spot.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="84" REF="83"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>There first she stop'd:</L>
<L>When, turning short, she cried, (how shall I speak it?)</L>
<L>"Go, tell my savage, my incestuous Brother,</L>
<L>"That you have seen me mad. Hark! I am call'd—</L>
<L>"But take this secret with you e're we part,</L>
<L>"There is a Hell for Murder and for Incest:</L>
<L>"Metellus hath been with me, my late Lord,</L>
<L>"Whom I, inhuman! murder'd, to make room</L>
<L>"For this perfidious Brother, told me so;</L>
<L>"And I believe it spite of Epicurus."</L>
<L>Then turning from me, quick as thought she buried</L>
<L>This dagger in her breast: "Take it, she cried,</L>
<L>"To Clodius bear his last best present back,</L>
<L>"This weapon reeking with a Sister's blood;</L>
<L>"And tell him—" More she would have said, but Death</L>
<L>In everlasting silence seal'd her lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>(Taking and looking on the dagger.</STAGE>
<L>So!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not think too deeply: This sad story</L>
<L>Dwells in our bosoms only; wrapt in night</L>
<L>Her mute attendants bear her body home,</L>
<L>And weep her death, unknowing of the cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fate now, I know thy utmost. Take the dagger:</L>
<L>If, when I look upon those limbs in Death,</L>
<L>My Heart within me sinks, and coward Nature</L>
<L><PB N="85" REF="84"/>
Melts to unwilling tears; then strike it home</L>
<L>One saving stroke, prevent the gathering sigh,</L>
<L>And meet it e're it rises to my lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>May all the Gods confound me, if I spare you!</L>
<L>But now awhile retire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why retire?</L>
<L>What! Lover-like beneath some yew-tree's shade,</L>
<L>To stand with folded arms and drooping head,</L>
<L>Poring upon some moulder'd monument</L>
<L>By the pale moon? or holding sad discourse▪</L>
<L>With its inhabitant the Owl? Away!</L>
<L>No, I'll abroad; out-face the flaring day:</L>
<L>I never yet knew grief, but Wine cou'd cure it;</L>
<L>Wine is the Lethe of the Poet's Fable;</L>
<L>And, Clodia, there I'll bury thy remembrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, lay that thorn for ever to thy breast</L>
<L>To keep Revenge awake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Revenge? Ye Gods!</L>
<L>How flat is Life, unseason'd with Revenge?</L>
<L>If Glory gilds it not, how blank the page?</L>
<L>Had I in store myriads of dreaming years,</L>
<L>I'd set 'em all upon one desp'rate cast,</L>
<L>And mock at Cicero in the arms of Death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then take this dagger back, and on its blade,</L>
<L><PB N="86" REF="85"/>
With bloody characters empurpled o'er,</L>
<L>Read the last will of Clodia: Hah! what says it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou curst Remembrancer! 'twice aim'd in vain</L>
<L>At Caius Frugi's breast, now dy'd, alas!</L>
<L>In the life-blood of her, who sent thee to me,</L>
<L>Lie there, and make acquaintance with my Heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why not plant it, where it first was aim'd,</L>
<L>In Caius Frugi's breast? How my soul fires</L>
<L>At that detested name! O Clodius, Clodius,</L>
<L>This is the hour, if thou dar'st do a deed</L>
<L>To make thy name a terror, and appall</L>
<L>Ev'n Heav'n itself; this is th' important hour.</L>
<L>In Vesta's Fane assembles all the House</L>
<L>Of Cicero; a weak unguarded crew,</L>
<L>Fondly presuming on their sacred refuge,</L>
<L>And confident 'gainst all attempts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough.</L>
<L>Not all the Synod of the Gods can shake me.</L>
<L>Did I respect thee, Fauna, and thy rites,</L>
<L>Goddess, rever'd of women? Then, O Vesta,</L>
<L>In spite of thee and thy perennial fires,</L>
<L>Ev'n at thy altar's foot I'll seize my Victims;</L>
<L>While the chaste flame looks pale at my attempt,</L>
<L>And dimly lights me to my great revenge.</L>
<STAGE>(Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3">
<PB N="87" REF="86"/>
<HEAD>SCENE III.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Scene returns to the</HI> TEMPLE <HI>of</HI> VESTA.</STAGE>
<STAGE>CICERO, TERENTIA, TULLIA, ATTICUS, CAIUS FRUGI.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Urge me no more; 'tis fixt for Sicily:</L>
<L>The Justice of my Government, the Grace</L>
<L>I've ever shewn the Island, still are fresh</L>
<L>In all men's memories; if Gratitude</L>
<L>Yet dwells in human hearts, it must be there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ATTICUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fated to conquer and corrupt the world,</L>
<L>Victorious Rome in every soil and clime</L>
<L>Hath sow'd her fertile vices; Virtue ever</L>
<L>Bleeds at the side of Freedom: Greece alone,</L>
<L>Triumphant in her fall, hath with her arts</L>
<L>Made Captive her Despoiler, and remains</L>
<L>A land of refuge 'gainst oppressive wrong,</L>
<L>The Nurse of Science and the Seat of Peace.</L>
<L>Thither, my Friend, betake thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah! no more;</L>
<L>My heart I give amongst you; for my body,</L>
<L>Which Rome thus casts away, fall where it may,</L>
<L>It is a sorry thing, nor worth the purchase</L>
<L>Of so much soil as it will cover.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Athens</L>
<L>Has my voice; but, where'er you bend your flight,</L>
<L><PB N="88" REF="87"/>
Be still thyself, my Marcus; no retirement</L>
<L>Can hide a great man from the world, for Rome</L>
<L>Hath eyes in every sphere, and they will watch you,</L>
<L>Tho' buried deep within Sicilian shades,</L>
<L>As when you stood the foremost of mankind,</L>
<L>And sway'd the Fate of Empires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Terentia,</L>
<L>'Tis hard, but just withall; for mine's a Heart</L>
<L>Slightly made up by Nature, in whose compound.</L>
<L>Preside the soft and sensible Affections,</L>
<L>And bend to every pressure. But why speaks not</L>
<L>My dearest Tullia? has thy Caius yet</L>
<L>Allay'd the wild disorder of thy mind,</L>
<L>And sooth'd it into peace?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The storm is past;</L>
<L>Sorrows as deep, tho' calmer, now succeed;</L>
<L>My soul shuts out each soft and joyful sense,</L>
<L>Ev'n Love itself, to entertain thy wrongs.</L>
<L>For thee each morn e're Phoebus streaks the East,</L>
<L>With early Orisons I'll waken Heaven;</L>
<L>For thee each night shall find me on my knees;</L>
<L>No note of mirth, no ill-according joy,</L>
<L>Shall break the tenor of my pious task,</L>
<L>Till the wish'd hour, when wearied Fate relents,</L>
<L>And Heav'n recalls her exil'd Patriot home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be it your care to wean her from her griefs,</L>
<L><PB N="89" REF="88"/>
And lead her with a watchful hand thro' Life;</L>
<L>Yet at some times indulge her in her tears,</L>
<L>Nor grudge that tribute to a Father's name.</L>
<L>Now with Pomponius to the Capuan Gate</L>
<L>Depart: My bursting Heart must have its vent;</L>
<L>And trust me he's the best Philosopher,</L>
<L>Who keeps the moments of his weakness private.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet e're we part, before this awful shrine,</L>
<L>Here in the presence of the Guardian Goddess;</L>
<L>Let me conjure thee by the name of Father,</L>
<L>O crown my hopes, and consecrate my Love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why wilt thou urge us both to our destruction?</L>
<L>Ah! wherefore tempt this black ill-omen'd hour,</L>
<L>For Treason only fit, for Lust and Murder,</L>
<L>And magic Incantations. This a time</L>
<L>To ask a blessing in? hence must we date</L>
<L>Our inauspicious nuptials? here commence</L>
<L>Our dark unhallow'd course? Forbid it, Heav'n!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be wise, be virtuous, and defy the Stars.</L>
<L>Come near me both.—Here o'er this holy flame,</L>
<L>I join your hands, an emblem of your hearts:</L>
<L>Henceforth be one.—Like this perennial fire,</L>
<L>So be your Loves aspiring, ardent, pure,</L>
<L>Perpetual; ceasing not till this expires.</L>
<STAGE>The Flame is seen to sink gradually, and at length goes out. They stand amazed at the Omen, when suddenly a great Noise is heard without.</STAGE>
</SP>
<PB N="90" REF="89"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FRUGI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hark! they assault the Temple; we're beset;</L>
<L>Clodius is at our doors: Impious attempt!</L>
<STAGE>(Atticus and Frugi go out.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Heav'n and Earth! where run you, Caius, Husband?</L>
<L>Help, help, they murder my dear, dear, defender.</L>
<STAGE><HI>A clashing of swords.</HI> FRUGI <HI>retreats fighting, and falls at</HI> TULLIA<HI>'s feet.</HI> CLODIUS <HI>and</HI> GABINIUS <HI>enter with Followers:</HI> CLODIUS <HI>advances to</HI> CICERO.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>So; you are found.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hangs the roof o'er thee yet?</L>
<L>Gods! Gods! why sleep ye? wherefore rise ye not</L>
<L>Ye violated Fires? in our defence</L>
<L>Why blaze not forth your Altars, and avenge</L>
<L>This Sacrilege?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I despise thee too?</L>
<L>Rail on thou credulous and shallow Pedant,</L>
<L>Till thy Gods hear thee, or till I relent.</L>
<L>But know to thy confusion, not the Winds,</L>
<L>That sweep the Scythian desart, are more deaf,</L>
<L>Than are thy fancied Deities; nor Rocks,</L>
<L>That shake those Winds from off their icy sides,</L>
<L>More hard, or more unfeeling than my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villain profest and shameless!</L>
</SP>
<PB N="91" REF="90"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Time is short;</L>
<L>Pomponius is escap'd; Caius yet breathes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, was my sword too short? this dagger then</L>
<L>Shall piece it out, and find his Heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away!</L>
<L>Thou'st done thy work too well, inhuman wretch!</L>
<L>The sternest murderers will turn aside,</L>
<L>Nor dare to look upon the deed they've done;</L>
<L>Thou only tak'st a cool delight in blood,</L>
<L>Can'st reason and descant upon thy trade,</L>
<L>And, butcher-like, deface and carve the slain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drag 'em asunder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>That ye shall not do;</L>
<L>Thus will I screen his poor remains of Life.</L>
<L>Now, now, transfix us both; the Wife and Husband;</L>
<L>The living and the dying; 'tis enough,</L>
<L>So I can hold off Death one moment from him,</L>
<L>And meet it in its passage to his Heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then take thy wish.</L>
<STAGE>(Offers to kill her.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah! stop thy desperate hand.</L>
<L>Let this alone; behold! a Father kneels.</L>
<L>O Clodius, thou hast brought me to the Earth;</L>
<L><PB N="92" REF="91"/>
Enjoy my shame, but spare my daughter's life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah! this is vengeance. Let me view thee well:</L>
<L>Kneel'st thou, proud Spirit? Wou'd all Rome were here</L>
<L>Spectators of my triumph! Come what may,</L>
<L>I've liv'd enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hoa! Catiline, where art thou?</L>
<L>Burst from thy sleep of Death; this is a sight</L>
<L>To weigh against Elysium.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise for shame;</L>
<L>Rise and defy 'em; their insulting mockery</L>
<L>Is sharper than their swords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>What have I done?</L>
<L>O coward Nature! is there no way left</L>
<L>To save a Child, but by a Father's shame?</L>
<L>Each drop of blood about me that is Roman;</L>
<L>Rebels against this weakness: But remember,</L>
<L>When you report this deed, report withal</L>
<L>That he who kneel'd to save a Daughter's life,</L>
<L>Disdain'd to ask his own.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who asks for life,</L>
<L>When this dear youth expires? Death grows upon him;</L>
<L>Nor needs your daggers to ensure his victim.</L>
<L>How piteously his eyes are fix'd on me!</L>
<L>Convulsion shakes each joint; he cannot utter,</L>
<L><PB N="93" REF="92"/>
Yet his lips move most speakingly. Where are ye?</L>
<L>Ye talk'd of daggers; who will plant one here?</L>
<L>Or must I linger till distraction ends me,</L>
<L>And on this pavement dash my desperate brains?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GABINIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>That groan's his last. My vengeance asks no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>This consolation comes too late for thee,</L>
<L>Unhappy Clodia: Yet it glads me well.</L>
<L>Hence with these women to the Public Court,</L>
<L>And there in full assembly urge their crimes;</L>
<L>Be it my task to cast this Exile forth,</L>
<L>And execute the Doom my Country past.</L>
<STAGE>(Guards seize Terentia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unhallow'd villains! loose your brutal hold.</L>
<L>O my Terentia; how this wrings my Heart!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TERENTIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fear not, my Marcus; we shall meet again;</L>
<L>If not, I will not shame thee at my Death,</L>
<L>But suffer as a Roman Matron should.</L>
<STAGE>(They force her off.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Guards take away</HI> FRUGI<HI>'s body, and force</HI> TULLIA <HI>away.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where do you drag me? We must part, my Caius;</L>
<L>Relentless monsters, can ye view that face</L>
<L>And pay no reverence? Howsoe'er ye treat</L>
<L>The living, do no violence to the dead.</L>
<L>These are my nuptial joys.—Alas, my Father!</L>
<L>And dost thou weep? O agonizing sight!</L>
<L>Come, let me go—for evermore farewel!</L>
<STAGE>(Exit.</STAGE>
<PB N="94" REF="93"/>
<STAGE>CICERO, CLODIUS, <HI>and</HI> GUARDS.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, my Tormentor, can'st thou aught invent</L>
<L>Deeper and keener than the pangs I feel;</L>
<L>Or is thy vengeance wearied?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have liv'd</L>
<L>To laugh at thee, and all thy patriot schemes,</L>
<L>To see thy Palace dust, thyself an Exile,</L>
<L>A prostrate Beggar bending to the earth;</L>
<L>Thy House of all its borrow'd splendor strip'd,</L>
<L>And to its first obscurity reduc'd:</L>
<L>Henceforth I think not of thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not think of me?</L>
<L>Dream on, till Vengeance wake thee, till thy Conscience</L>
<L>Bloated and swell'd, from Pleasure's guilty feast</L>
<L>Starts up aghast, turns suddenly upon thee,</L>
<L>And stings thee to the Heart; and mark me, Traitor,</L>
<L>In the great scale and order of Creation</L>
<L>All have their parts; but your's are servile uses,</L>
<L>Monsters of Vice; yet in the hand of Heaven</L>
<L>Ye minister to Good, and are the instruments</L>
<L>To tent the hollow-hearted, and distinguish</L>
<L>Between the similar back-sliding hypocrite,</L>
<L>And the long-suffering single-hearted man:</L>
<L>When you have done your work, you're thrown aside,</L>
<L>As such base tools should be.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="95" REF="94"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Base do you call me?</L>
<L>O thou more wretched than the basest Beggar!</L>
<L>For he unquestion'd breathes the liberal air,</L>
<L>Drinks health and pleasure at the running fount;</L>
<L>'Gainst thee the elements are shut, the Earth</L>
<L>Our common parent disavows thee, thee,</L>
<L>Thy Country's out-cast, and the sport of Nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CICERO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blush thou, for having made me what I am.</L>
<L>I sav'd my Country; thou hast driven me from it.</L>
<L>All good men bless me; thee all ill ones serve.</L>
<L>Thus by the larger portion of mankind</L>
<L>I'm banish'd; thou condemned by the best:</L>
<L>Farewell; Posterity decide betwixt us!</L>
<STAGE>(Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLODIUS</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>Remains.</STAGE>
<L>His words go thro' my soul; my cause is weak,</L>
<L>And my good Genius fails me: Must I own</L>
<L>There is a dignity, a grace in Virtue,</L>
<L>Which Vice in all its pomp can never reach?</L>
<L>With all the ensigns of his power about him,</L>
<L>I saw, and sigh'd not at the Consul's greatness:</L>
<L>Now he appears so awful in distress,</L>
<L>That I most envy when I most oppress.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>
