<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet TYPE="text/css" href="http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE><DATE>yyyy-mm-dd</DATE><RESPSTMT><NAME>[name of reviewer]</NAME><RESP>MURP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM></CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>

<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="K024209.000">
<STC T="C">T008579</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3310780733</BIBNO>
<VID SET="ecll">0227100400</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE ROMAN FATHER, A TRAGEDY.</P>
<P>[Price One Shilling and Six-pence.]</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<P>THE ROMAN FATHER, A TRAGEDY.</P>
<P>As it is Acted at the THEATRE ROYAL in <HI>Drury-Lane,</HI> By His MAJESTY's Servants.</P>
<P>By Mr. <HI>W. WHITEHEAD.</HI></P>
<Q><L>— Utcunque ferent ea facta Minores,</L>
<L>Vincet Amor Patriae, Laudumque immensa Cupido!
<BIBL><HI>VIRG.</HI></BIBL></L></Q>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI> Printed for R. DODSLEY at <HI>Tully</HI>'s-head, <HI>Pall-mall;</HI> and sold by M. COOPER in <HI>Pater-noster-Row.</HI></P>
<P><ABBR>MDCCL.</ABBR></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="3"/>
<P>TO The HONOURABLE <HI>THOMAS VILLIERS,</HI></P>
<P>One of the LORDS COMMISSIONERS for executing the Office of Lord High Admiral of <HI>Great Britain,</HI></P>
<P>The following TRAGEDY is in∣scribed by</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>His most obliged, and most obedient humble Servant, W. WHITEHEAD.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="advertisement">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>ADVERTISEMENT.</HEAD>
<P>I Think it necessary to acquaint the Public, that I should never have thought of writing a Play on the following Subject, if I had not first read the just∣ly celebrated <HI>Horace</HI> of Mr. <HI>Corneille,</HI> and admired his Management of some Parts of the Story. They will find me tracing him very closely (with some few Alte∣rations) in the latter End of the Third Act, and in the Beginning of the Fourth. In the other Acts I am hardly conscious to myself of having borrowed even a Thought from him; tho' I might have been proud to have translated whole Scenes, if my Plan and Cha∣racters would have admitted of it.</P>
<P>I must beg leave to add, that I was induced, for the Sake of the Action, to put several Speeches at the latter End of the Play into the Mouth of <HI>Publius,</HI> which more properly belong to the Father. The Reader will accordingly find them restored here to their first Situation.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>PROLOGUE.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Spoken by Mr. BARRY.</BYLINE>
<LG>
<L><HI>BRITONS,</HI> To-night in native Pomp we come,</L>
<L>True Heroes all, from virtuous ancient <HI>Rome;</HI></L>
<L>In those far distant Times when <HI>Romans</HI> knew</L>
<L>The Sweets of guarded Liberty, like You;</L>
<L>And, safe from Ills which Force or Faction brings,</L>
<L>Saw Freedom reign beneath the Smile of Kings.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Yet from such Times, and such plain Chiefs as these,</L>
<L>What can we frame a polish'd Age to please?</L>
<L>Say, can you listen to the artless Woes</L>
<L>Of an old Tale, which every School-boy knows?</L>
<L>Where to your Hearts alone the Scenes apply,</L>
<L>No Merit their's but pure Simplicity.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Our Bard has play'd a most adventurous Part,</L>
<L>And turn'd upon himself the Critic's Art:</L>
<L>Stripp'd each luxuriant Plume from Fancy's Wings,</L>
<L>And torn up Similies like vulgar Things.</L>
<L>Nay even each Moral, <HI>Sentimental,</HI> Stroke,</L>
<L>Where not the Character but Poet spoke,</L>
<L>He lopp'd, as foreign to his chaste Design;</L>
<L>Nor spar'd an useless tho' a golden Line.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>These are his Arts; if these cannot atone</L>
<L>For all those nameless Errors yet unknown,</L>
<L>If shanning Faults which nobler Bards commit,</L>
<L>He wants their Force to strike th' attentive Pit,</L>
<L>Be just and tell him so; he asks Advice,</L>
<L>Willing to learn, and would not ask it twice.</L>
<L>Your kind Applause may bid him write—beware!</L>
<L>Or kinder Censure teach him to forbear.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>PERSONS Represented.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>MEN.</HEAD>
<ITEM>TULLUS HOSTILIUS, King of <HI>Rome,</HI> Mr. <HI>Sowdon.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>HORATIUS, A <HI>Roman</HI> Senator, Mr. <HI>Garrick.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>PUBLIUS HORATIUS, His Son, Mr. <HI>Barry.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>VALERIUS, A young <HI>Patrician,</HI> Mr. <HI>King.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>WOMEN.</HEAD>
<ITEM>HORATIA, Daughter to HO∣RATIUS, Mrs <HI>Pritchard</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>VALERIA, Sister to VALE∣RIUS, Mrs. <HI>Ward.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Citizens, Guards, and Attendants.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>The Music composed by Dr. BOYCE.</P>
<P>The vocal Parts performed</P>
<P>By Mr. BEARD, Miss NORRIS, Miss COLE, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>SCENE <HI>Rome.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="drama">
<PB REF="7"/>
<HEAD>THE ROMAN FATHER, A TRAGEDY.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. I.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>A Room in</HI> HORATIUS<HI>'S House.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>A Soldier crosses the Stage,</HI> HORATIA <HI>following.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>TAY Soldier.—As you parted from my Father,</L>
<L>Something I overheard of near Concern,</L>
<L>But all imperfectly. Said you not <HI>Alba</HI></L>
<L>Was on the Brink of Fate, and <HI>Rome</HI> determin'd</L>
<L>This Day to crush her haughty Rival's Power,</L>
<L>Or perish in th' Attempt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SOLDIER.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas so resolv'd</L>
<L>This Morning, Lady, ere I left the Camp.</L>
<L>Our Heroes are tir'd out with ling'ring War,</L>
<L>And half-unmeaning Fights.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="2" REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! I hop'd</L>
<L>The kind Remorse which touch'd the kindred States,</L>
<L>And made their Swords fall lightly on the Breasts</L>
<L>Of Foes they could not hate, might have produc'd</L>
<L>A milder Resolution!—Then this Day</L>
<L>Is fix'd for Death or Conquest?—
<STAGE><HI>He bows.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>—To me Death</L>
<L>Whoever conquers!—I detain you Sir;</L>
<L>Commend me to my Brothers, say, I wish—</L>
<L>But wherefore should I wish; the Gods will crown</L>
<L>Their Virtues with the just Success they merit.</L>
<L>—Yet let me ask you, Sir—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SOLDIER.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Duty, Lady,</L>
<L>Commands me hence; ere this they have engag'd;</L>
<L>And Conquest's self would lose its Charms to me,</L>
<L>Should I not share the Danger.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>As the Soldier goes out, enter</HI> VALERIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA. [<HI>looking first on the Soldier and then on</HI> HORATIA]</SPEAKER>
<L>My dear HORATIA, wherefore wilt thou court</L>
<L>The Means to be unhappy, still enquiring</L>
<L>Still to be more undone? I heard it too;</L>
<L>And flew to find thee, ere the fatal News</L>
<L>Had hurt thy quiet, that thou might'st have learnt it</L>
<L>From a Friend's Tongue, and dress'd in gentler Terms.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O I am lost, VALERIA, lost to Virtue.</L>
<L>Ev'n while my Country's Fate, the Fate of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Hangs on the Conqueror's sword, this Breast can feel</L>
<L>A softer Passion, and divide its Cares.</L>
<L><HI>Alba</HI> to me is <HI>Rome.</HI> Would'st thou believe it,</L>
<L>I would have sent by him thou saw'st departing</L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="9"/>Kind Wishes to my Brothers, but my Tongue</L>
<L>Denied its Office, and this Rebel Heart</L>
<L>Ev'n dreaded their Success. O CURIATIUS,</L>
<L>Why art thou there, or why an Enemy!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbear this self-reproach, he is thy Husband,</L>
<L>And who can blame thy Fears? if Fortune make him</L>
<L>Awhile thy Country's Foe, she cannot cancel</L>
<L>Vows register'd above. What though the Priest</L>
<L>Had not confirm'd it at the sacred Altar;</L>
<L>Yet were your Hearts united, and that Union</L>
<L>Approv'd by each consenting Parent's Choice.</L>
<L>Your Brothers lov'd him as a Friend, a Brother;</L>
<L>And all the Ties of Kindred pleaded for him;</L>
<L>And still must plead, whate'er our Heroes teach us</L>
<L>Of Patriot-strength: Our Country may demand</L>
<L>We should be wretched, and we must obey;</L>
<L>But never can require us not to feel</L>
<L>That we are miserable, Nature there</L>
<L>Will give the Lie to Virtue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>True; yet sure</L>
<L>A <HI>Roman</HI> Virgin should be more than Woman.</L>
<L>Are we not early taught to mock at Pain,</L>
<L>And look on Danger with undaunted Eyes?</L>
<L>But what are Dangers? what the ghastliest Form</L>
<L>Of Death itself?—O were I only bid</L>
<L>To rush into the <HI>Tiber</HI>'s foaming Wave</L>
<L>Swollen with uncommon Floods, or from the Height</L>
<L>Of yon <HI>Tarpeian</HI> Rock, whose giddy Steep</L>
<L>Has turn'd me pale with Horror at the Sight,</L>
<L>I'd think the Task were nothing; but to bear</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="10"/>These strange Vicissitudes of torturing Pain,</L>
<L>To fear, to doubt, and to despair as I do?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why despair? have we so idly learned</L>
<L>The noblest Lessons of our Infant Days,</L>
<L>Our Trust above? Does there not still remain</L>
<L>The Wretch's last Retreat, the Gods, HORATIA?</L>
<L>'Tis from their awful Wills our Evils spring,</L>
<L>And at their Altars may we find Relief.</L>
<L>Say, shall we thither?—look not thus dejected,</L>
<L>But answer me. A Confidence in them,</L>
<L>Even in this Crisis of thy Fate, will calm</L>
<L>Thy troubled Soul, and fill thy Breast with Hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Talk not of Hope; the Wretch on yonder Plain</L>
<L>Who hears the Victor's Threats, and sees his Sword</L>
<L>Impending o'er him, feels no surer Fate,</L>
<L>Tho' less delay'd than mine.—What shou'd I hope?</L>
<L>That <HI>Alba</HI> conquer?—Curst be every Thought</L>
<L>Which looks that Way, the Shrieks of captive Matrons</L>
<L>Sound in my Ears!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbear, forbear, HORATIA;</L>
<L>Nor fright me with the Thought. <HI>Rome</HI> cannot fall.</L>
<L>Think of the glorious Battles she has fought;</L>
<L>Has she once fail'd, tho' oft expos'd to Danger;</L>
<L>And has not her immortal Founder promis'd</L>
<L>That she should rise the Mistress of the World?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if <HI>Rome</HI> conquers, then HORATIA dies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why wilt thou form vain Images of Horror,</L>
<L>Industrious to be wretched? Is it then</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="11"/>Become impossible that <HI>Rome</HI> should triumph,</L>
<L>And CURIATIUS live? He must, he shall;</L>
<L>Protecting Gods shall spread their Shields around him,</L>
<L>And Love shall combat in HORATIA'S Cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Think'st thou so meanly of him?— No, VALERIA,</L>
<L>His Soul's too great to give me such a Trial;</L>
<L>Or could it ever come, I think, myself,</L>
<L>Thus lost in Love, thus abject as I am,</L>
<L>I should despise the Slave who dar'd survive</L>
<L>His Country's Ruin. Ye immortal Powers!</L>
<L>I love his Fame too well, his spotless Honour,</L>
<L>At least I hope I do, to wish him mine</L>
<L>On any Terms which he must blush to own.</L>
<L>—What means that Shout?— might we not ask, VALERIA?</L>
<L>Didst thou not wish me to the Temple?—Come,</L>
<L>I will attend thee thither; the kind Gods</L>
<L>Perhaps may ease this throbbing Heart, and spread</L>
<L>At least a temporary Calm within.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, HORATIA, 'tis not to the Temple</L>
<L>That thou would'st fly; the Shout alone alarms thee.</L>
<L>But do not thus anticipate thy Fate;</L>
<L>Why should'st thou learn each Chance of varying War,</L>
<L>Which takes a thousand Turns, and shifts the Scene</L>
<L>From Bad to Good, as Fortune smiles or frowns?</L>
<L>Stay but an Hour perhaps, and thou shalt know</L>
<L>The whole at once.—I'll send—I'll fly myself</L>
<L>To ease thy Doubts, and bring thee News of Joy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Again, and nearer too—I must attend thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="6" REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hark! 'tis thy Father's Voice, he comes to cheer thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> HORATIUS, <HI>and</HI> VALERIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS. <HI>[entering]</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>News from the Camp my Child!—
<STAGE>[<HI>seeing</HI> VALERIA]</STAGE></L>
<L>Save you, sweet Maid!</L>
<L>Your Brother brings the Tidings, for alas</L>
<L>I am no Warrior now; my useless Age</L>
<L>Far from the Paths of Honour loiters here</L>
<L>In sluggish Inactivity at home.</L>
<L>Yet I remember—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'll forgive us, Sir,</L>
<L>If with Impatience we expect the Tidings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had forgot; the Thoughts of what I was</L>
<L>Engross'd my whole Attention.—Pray, young Soldier,</L>
<L>Relate it for me; you beheld the Scene,</L>
<L>And can report it justly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentle Lady,</L>
<L>The Scene was piteous, tho' its end be Peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace? O my flutt'ring Heart! by what kind Means?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twere tedious, Lady, and unnecessary</L>
<L>To paint the Disposition of the Field;</L>
<L>Suffice it we were arm'd, and Front to Front</L>
<L>The adverse Legions heard the Trumpet's Sound:</L>
<L>But vain was the Alarm, for motionless</L>
<L>And wrapt in Thought they stood, the kindred Ranks</L>
<L>Had caught each others Eyes, nor dar'd to lift</L>
<L>The fault'ring Spear against the Breast they lov'd.</L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="13"/>Again th' Alarm was given, and now they seem'd</L>
<L>Preparing to engage, when once again</L>
<L>They hung their drooping Heads, and inward mourn'd.</L>
<L>Then nearer drew, and at the third Alarm</L>
<L>Casting their Swords and useless Shields aside</L>
<L>Rush'd to each others Arms.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas so, just so,</L>
<L>(Tho' I was then a Child, yet I have heard</L>
<L>My Mother weeping oft relate the Story)</L>
<L>Soft Pity touch'd the Breasts of mighty Chiefs</L>
<L><HI>Romans</HI> and <HI>Sabines,</HI> when the Matrons rush'd</L>
<L>Between their meeting Armies, and oppos'd</L>
<L>Their helpless Infants, and their heaving Breasts</L>
<L>To their advancing Swords, and bade them there</L>
<L>Sheath all their Vengeance.—But I interrupt you,—</L>
<L>Proceed, VALERIUS, they would hear th' Event.</L>
<L>—And yet methinks the <HI>Albans</HI>—pray go on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our King HOSTILIUS from a rising Mound</L>
<L>Beheld the tender Interview, and join'd.</L>
<L>His friendly Tears with theirs; then swift advanc'd</L>
<L>Ev'n to the thickest Press, and cried, My Friends,</L>
<L>If thus we love, why are we Enemies?</L>
<L>Shall stern Ambition, Rivalship of Power,</L>
<L>Subdue the soft Humanity within us?</L>
<L>Are we not join'd by every Tie of Kindred,</L>
<L>And can we find no Method to compose</L>
<L>These Jars of Honour, these nice Principles</L>
<L>Of Virtue, which infest the noble Mind?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>There spoke his Country's Father! this transcends</L>
<L>The Flight of Earth-born Kings, whose low Ambition</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="14"/>But tends to lay the Face of Nature waste,</L>
<L>And blast Creation!—how was it receiv'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>As he himself could wish, with eager Transport.</L>
<L>In short, the <HI>Roman</HI> and the <HI>Alban</HI> Chiefs</L>
<L>In Council have determin'd, that since Glory</L>
<L>Must have her Victims, and each rival State</L>
<L>Aspiring to Dominion scorns to yield,</L>
<L>From either Army shall be chose three Champions</L>
<L>To fight the Cause alone, and whate'er State</L>
<L>Shall prove superior, there acknowledg'd Power</L>
<L>Shall fix th' imperial Seat, and both unite</L>
<L>Beneath one common Head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kind Heaven, I thank thee!</L>
<L>Blest be the friendly Grief that touch'd their Souls!</L>
<L>Blest be HOSTILIUS for the generous Counsel!</L>
<L>Blest be the meeting Chiefs! and blest the Tongue,</L>
<L>Which brings the gentle Tidings!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, HORATIA,</L>
<L>Your idle Fears are o'er.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet one remains.</L>
<L>Who are the Champions, are they yet elected?</L>
<L>Has <HI>Rome</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>—The <HI>Roman</HI> Chiefs now meet in Council,</L>
<L>And ask the Presence of the Sage HORATIUS.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS. <HI>[after having seem'd some time in Thought]</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Yet still methinks, I like not this, to trust</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="15"/>The <HI>Roman</HI> Cause to such a slender Hazard—</L>
<L>Three Combatants!—'tis dangerous—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA. <HI>[in a Fright]</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>My Father!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I might perhaps prevent it—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not, Sir,</L>
<L>Oppose the kind Decree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rest satisfied,</L>
<L>Sweet Lady, 'tis so solemnly agreed to,</L>
<L>Not even HORATIUS'S Advice can shake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet 'twere well to end these civil Broils:</L>
<L>The neighb'ring States might take Advantage of them.</L>
<L>—Would I were young again! how glorious</L>
<L>Were Death in such a Cause!—and yet, who knows,</L>
<L>Some of my Boys may be selected for it—</L>
<L>Perhaps may conquer—grant me that, kind Gods,</L>
<L>And close my Eyes in Transport!—Come, VALERIUS,</L>
<L>I'll but dispatch some necessary Orders,</L>
<L>And strait attend thee.—Daughter, if thou lovest</L>
<L>Thy Brothers, let thy Prayers be pour'd to Heaven,</L>
<L>That one at least may share the glorious Task!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> cannot trust her Cause to worthier Hands.</L>
<L>They bade me greet you, Lady;
<STAGE>[<HI>To</HI> HORATIA]</STAGE></L>
<L>Well, VALERIA,</L>
<L>This is your Home I find; your lovely Friend</L>
<L>And you, I doubt not, have indulg'd strange Fears,</L>
<L>And run o'er all the horrid Scenes of War.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="10" REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tho' we are Women, Brother, we are <HI>Romans,</HI></L>
<L>Not to be scared with Shadows, tho' not Proof</L>
<L>'Gainst all Alarms, when real Danger threatens.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA. <HI>[with some Hesitation.]</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>My Brothers, gentle Sir, you said were well,</L>
<L>Saw you their noble Friends the CURIATII?</L>
<L>The Truce perhaps permitted it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Lady,</L>
<L>I left them jocund in your Brothers Tent,</L>
<L>Like Friends, whom envious Storms a-while had parted,</L>
<L>Joying to meet again.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sent they no Message?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>None, Fair-one, but such general Salutations,</L>
<L>As Friends would bring unbid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Said CAIUS nothing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>CAIUS?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay, CAIUS,—did he mention me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas slightly, if he did, and 'scapes me now—</L>
<L>O yes, I do remember, when your Brother</L>
<L>Ask'd him in Jest, if he had ought to send,</L>
<L>A Sigh's soft Wastage, or the tender Token</L>
<L>Of Tresses breeded to fantastic Forms</L>
<L>To sooth a love-sick Maid, (your Pardon, Lady,)</L>
<L>He smil'd, and cry'd, Glory's the Soldier's Mistress.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="11" REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you'll excuse me—something of Importance—</L>
<L>My Father may have Business—O VALERIA
<STAGE><HI>Aside to</HI> VA∣LERIA.</STAGE></L>
<L>Talk to thy Brother, know the fatal Truth</L>
<L>I dread to hear, and let me learn to die,</L>
<L>If CURIATIUS has indeed forgot me.
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>She seems disorder'd!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has she not just Cause?</L>
<L>Can you administer the baneful Potion,</L>
<L>And wonder at th' Effect?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>You talk in Riddles!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>They're Riddles, Brother, which your Heart unfolds,</L>
<L>Tho' you affect Surprize. Was CURIATIUS</L>
<L>Indeed so cold? poor, shallow Artifice,</L>
<L>The Trick of hopeless Love! I saw it plainly.</L>
<L>Yet what could you propose? An Hour's Uneasiness</L>
<L>To poor HORATIA; for be sure by that Time</L>
<L>She sees him, and your deep-wrought Schemes are Air.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What could I do? this Peace has ruin'd me;</L>
<L>While War continued, I had Gleams of Hope,</L>
<L>Some lucky Chance might rid me of my Rival,</L>
<L>And Time efface his Image in her Breast.</L>
<L>But now—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, now you must resolve to follow</L>
<L>Th' Advice I gave you first, and root this Passion</L>
<L>Entirely from your Heart; for know she doats,</L>
<L>Ev'n to Distraction doats on CURIATIUS;</L>
<L><PB N="12" REF="18"/>And every Fear she felt, while Danger threaten'd,</L>
<L>Will now endear him more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cruel VALERIA,</L>
<L>You triumph in my Pain!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>By Heaven I do not,</L>
<L>I only would extirpate every Thought</L>
<L>Which gives you Pain, nor leave one foolish Wish</L>
<L>For Hope to dally with. When Friends are mad,</L>
<L>'Tis most unkind to humour their Distraction;</L>
<L>Harsh Means are necessary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet we first</L>
<L>Should try the gentler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did I not? ye Powers!</L>
<L>Did I not sooth your Griefs, indulge your Fondness,</L>
<L>While the least Prospect of Success remain'd?</L>
<L>Did I not press you still to urge your Suit,</L>
<L>Intreat you daily to declare your Passion,</L>
<L>Seek out unnumber'd Opportunities,</L>
<L>And lay the Follies of my Sex before you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, thou know'st, VALERIA, Woman's Heart</L>
<L>Was never won by Tales of bleeding Love:</L>
<L>'Tis by Degrees the sly Enchanter works</L>
<L>Assuming Friendship's Name, and fits the Soul</L>
<L>For soft Impressions, ere the fault'ring Tongue,</L>
<L>And guilty-blushing Cheek, with many a Glance</L>
<L>Shot inadvertent, tells the secret Flame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="13" REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, these are Arts for those who love at leisure;</L>
<L>You had no Time for tedious Stratagem;</L>
<L>A dang'rous Rival prest, and has succeeded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I own my Error—yet once more assist me—</L>
<L>Nay, turn not from me; by my Soul I mean not</L>
<L>To interrupt their Loves—Yet should some Accident,</L>
<L>'Tis not impossible, divide their Hearts,</L>
<L>I might perhaps have Hope: Therefore 'till Marriage</L>
<L>Cuts off all Commerce, and confirms me wretched,</L>
<L>Be it thy Task, my Sister, with fond Stories,</L>
<L>Such as our Ties of Blood may countenance,</L>
<L>To paint thy Brother's Worth, his Power in Arms,</L>
<L>His Favour with the King, but most of all</L>
<L>That certain Tenderness of Soul which steals</L>
<L>All Womens hearts, then mention many a Fair,</L>
<L>No matter whom, that sighs to call you Sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, well, away— Yet tell me, ere you go,</L>
<L>How did this Lover talk of his HORATIA?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why will you mention the ungrateful Subject?</L>
<L>Think what you've heard me breathe a thousand Times</L>
<L>When my whole Soul dissolv'd in Tenderness;</L>
<L>'Twas Rapture all; what Lovers only feel,</L>
<L>Or can express when felt. He had been here,</L>
<L>But sudden Orders from their Camp detain'd him.</L>
<L>Farewel, HORATIUS waits me—but remember,</L>
<L>My Life, nay more than Life, depends on you.
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="14" REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poor Youth! he knows not how I feel his Anguish,</L>
<L>Yet dare not seem to pity what I feel.</L>
<L>How shall I act betwixt this Friend and Brother?</L>
<L>Should she suspect his Passion, she may doubt</L>
<L>My Friendship too; and yet to tell it her</L>
<L>Were to betray his Cause. No, let my Heart</L>
<L>With the same blameless Caution still proceed,</L>
<L>To each inclining most as most distrest,</L>
<L>Be just to both, and leave to Heaven the rest!
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB N="15" REF="21"/>
<HEAD>ACT II.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Scene continues.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> HORATIA <HI>and</HI> VALERIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>ALAS, how easily do we admit</L>
<L>The Thing we wish were true! yet sure, VALERIA,</L>
<L>This seeming Negligence of CURIATIUS</L>
<L>Betrays a secret Coldness at the Heart.</L>
<L>May not long Absence, or the Charms of War</L>
<L>Have damp'd, at least, if not effac'd his Passion?</L>
<L>I know not what to think.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Think, my HORATIA,</L>
<L>That you're a Lover, and have learn'd the Art</L>
<L>To raise vain Scruples, and torment yourself</L>
<L>With every distant Hint of fancied Ill.</L>
<L>Your CURIATIUS still remains the same.</L>
<L>My Brother idly trifled with your Passion,</L>
<L>Or might perhaps unheedingly relate</L>
<L>What you too nearly feel. But see, your Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="16" REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>He seems transported; sure some happy News</L>
<L>Has brought him back thus early: O my Heart!</L>
<L>I long, yet dread to ask him; speak, VALERIA.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> HORATIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>You're soon return'd, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Return'd, VALERIA!</L>
<L>My Life, my Youth's return'd, I tread in Air.</L>
<L>—I cannot speak; my Joy's too great for Utterance.</L>
<L>—O I cou'd weep!—my Sons, my Sons are chosen</L>
<L>Their Country's Combatants, not one, but all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Brothers said you, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>All three, my Child,</L>
<L>All three are Champions in the Cause of <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
<L>O happy State of Fathers! thus to feel</L>
<L>New Warmth revive, and springing Life renew'd</L>
<L>Even on the Margin of the Grave!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Time</L>
<L>Of Combat, is it fix'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Day, this Hour</L>
<L>Perhaps decides our Doom.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>And is it known</L>
<L>With whom they must engage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not yet, VALERIA;</L>
<L>But with Impatience we expect each Moment</L>
<L><PB N="17" REF="23"/>The Resolutions of the <HI>Alban</HI> Senate.</L>
<L>And soon may they arrive, that ere we quit</L>
<L>Yon hostile Field, the Chiefs who dared oppose</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI>'s rising Glories, may with Shame confess</L>
<L>The Gods protect the Empire they have rais'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Where are thy Smiles, HORATIA? whence proceeds</L>
<L>This sullen Silence, when my thronging Joys</L>
<L>Want Words to speak them? Prithee, talk of Empire,</L>
<L>Talk of those Darlings of my Soul thy Brothers.</L>
<L>Call them whate'er wild Fancy can suggest,</L>
<L>Their Country's Pride, the Boast of future Times,</L>
<L>The dear Defence, the guardian Gods of <HI>Rome!</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>By Heaven thou stand'st unmov'd, nor feels thy Breast</L>
<L>The Charms of Glory, the exstatic Warmth</L>
<L>Which beams new Life, and lifts us nearer Heaven!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gracious Father, with Surprize and Transport</L>
<L>I heard the Tidings, as becomes your Daughter.</L>
<L>And like your Daughter, were our Sex allow'd</L>
<L>The noble Privilege which Man usurps,</L>
<L>Could die with Pleasure in my Country's Cause.</L>
<L>But yet permit a Sister's Weakness, Sir,</L>
<L>To feel the Pangs of Nature, and to dread</L>
<L>The Fate of those she loves, however glorious.</L>
<L>And sure they cannot all survive a Conflict</L>
<L>So desperate as this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Survive! by Heaven</L>
<L>I could not hope that they should all survive.</L>
<L>No, let them fall; if from their glorious Deaths</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI>'s Freedom spring, I shall be nobly paid</L>
<L>For every sharpest Pang the Parent feels.</L>
<L>Had I a thousand Sons, in such a Cause</L>
<L><PB N="18" REF="24"/>I could behold them bleeding at my Feet,</L>
<L>And thank the Gods with Tears!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> PUBLIUS HORATIUS</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Father!
<STAGE><HI>Offering to kneel.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence!</L>
<L>Kneel not to me—stand off; and let me view</L>
<L>At Distance, and with reverential Awe,</L>
<L>The Champion of my Country!—O, my Boy,</L>
<L>That I should live to this—my Soul's too full;</L>
<L>Let this and this speak for me.—Bless thee, bless thee!</L>
<STAGE><HI>Embracing him.</HI></STAGE>
<L>But wherefore art thou absent from the Camp?</L>
<L>Where are thy Brothers? has the <HI>Alban</HI> State</L>
<L>Determin'd? is the Time of Combat fix'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Think not, my Lord, that filial Reverence,</L>
<L>However due, had drawn me from the Field,</L>
<L>Where nobler Duty calls: a Patriot's Soul,</L>
<L>Can feel no humbler Ties, nor knows the Voice</L>
<L>Of Kindred, when his Country claims his Aid.</L>
<L>It was the King's Command I should attend you,</L>
<L>Else had I staid 'till Wreaths immortal grac'd</L>
<L>My Brows, and made thee proud indeed to see</L>
<L>Beneath thy Roof, and bending for thy Blessing,</L>
<L>Not thine, HORATIUS, but the Son of <HI>Rome!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>O virtuous Pride!—'tis Bliss too exquisite</L>
<L>For human Sense! —thus, let me answer thee.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Embracing him again.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Where are my other Boys?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="19" REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>They only wait</L>
<L>'Till <HI>Alba</HI>'s loit'ring Chiefs declare her Champions,</L>
<L>Our future Victims, Sir, and with the News</L>
<L>Will greet their Father's Ear.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall not need,</L>
<L>Myself will to the Field. Come, let us haste;</L>
<L>My old Blood boils, and my tumultuous Spirits</L>
<L>Pant for the Onset. O for one short Hour</L>
<L>Of vigorous Youth, that I might share the Toil</L>
<L>Now with my Boys, and be the next my last!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Brother!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My HORATIA! ere the Dews</L>
<L>Of Evening fall thou shalt with Transport own me;</L>
<L>Shalt hold thy Country's Saviour in thy Arms,</L>
<L>Or bathe his honest Bier with Tears of Joy.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thy Lover greets thee, and complains of Absence</L>
<L>With many a Sigh, and many a longing Look</L>
<L>Sent tow'rd the Towers of <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Methinks, a Lover</L>
<L>Might take th'Advantage of the Truce, and bear</L>
<L>His kind Complaints himself, not trust his Vows</L>
<L>To other Tongues, or be oblig'd to tell</L>
<L>The passing Winds his Passion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Dearest Sister,</L>
<L>He with Impatience waits the lucky Moment</L>
<L>That may with Honour bear him to your Arms.</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="26"/>Didst thou but hear how tenderly he talks,</L>
<L>How blames the dull Delay of <HI>Alban</HI> Councils,</L>
<L>And chices the ling'ring Minutes as they pass,</L>
<L>'Till Fate determines, and the tedious Chiefs</L>
<L>Permit his Absence, thou woud'st pity him.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But soon, my Sister, soon shall every Bar</L>
<L>Which thwarts thy Happiness be far away.</L>
<L>We are no longer Enemies to <HI>Alba,</HI></L>
<L>This Day unites us, and to-morrow's Sun</L>
<L>May hear thy Vows, and make my Friend my Brother.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS. [<HI>Having talked apart with</HI> VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis truly <HI>Roman.</HI>—Here's a Maid, HORATIA,</L>
<L>Laments her Brother lost the glorious Proof</L>
<L>Of dying for his Country.—Come, my Son,</L>
<L>Her Softness will infect thee, prithee, leave her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA. <HI>[Looking first on her Father, and then tenderly on her Brother.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not 'till my Soul has pour'd its Wishes for him.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Hear me, dread God of War, protect and save him!</L>
<STAGE><HI>Kneeling.</HI></STAGE>
<L>For thee, and thy immortal <HI>Rome</HI> he fights!</L>
<L>Dash the proud Spear from every hostile Hand</L>
<L>That dares oppose him; may each <HI>Alban</HI> Chief</L>
<L>Fly from his Presence, or his Vengeance feel!</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And when in Triumph he returns to <HI>Rome,</HI>
<STAGE><HI>Rising.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Hail him, ye Maids, with grateful Songs of Praise,</L>
<L>And scatter all the blooming Spring before him.</L>
<L>Curs'd be the envious Brow that smiles not then,</L>
<L>Curs'd be the Wretch that wears one Mark of Sorrow,</L>
<L>Or flies not thus with open Arms to greet him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> TULLUS HOSTILIUS, VALERIUS, <HI>and Guards.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King, my Lord, approaches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="21" REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Sir,</L>
<L>Whence comes this Condescension?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS HOSTILIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good old Man;</L>
<L>Could I have found a nobler Messenger,</L>
<L>I would have spared myself th' ungrateful Task</L>
<L>Of this Day's Embassy, for much I fear</L>
<L>My News will want a Welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mighty King!</L>
<L>Forgive an old Man's Warmth—They have not sure</L>
<L>Made choice of other Combatants.—My Sons,</L>
<L>Must they not fight for <HI>Rome?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS HOSTILIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too sure they must.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I am blest!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS HOSTILIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>But that they must engage</L>
<L>Will hurt thee most, when thou shalt know with whom.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I care not whom.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS HOSTILIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suppose your nearest Friends</L>
<L>The <HI>Curiatii</HI> were the <HI>Alban</HI> Choice,</L>
<L>Could you bear that? Could you, young Man, support</L>
<L>A Conflict there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could perform my Duty,</L>
<L>Great Sir, tho' even a Brother should oppose me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="22" REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS HOSTILIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a <HI>Roman!</HI> Let thy King embrace thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>And let thy Father catch thee from his Arms.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS HOSTILIUS. [<HI>To</HI> PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know then that Trial must be thine. The <HI>Albans</HI></L>
<L>With Envy saw one Family produce</L>
<L>Three Chiefs, to whom their Country dared entrust</L>
<L>The <HI>Roman</HI> Cause, and scorn'd to be outdone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I am lost indeed; was it for this,</L>
<L>For this, I pray'd!
<STAGE><HI>Swoons.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Sister!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My HORATIA!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>O scolish Girl, to shame thy Father thus!</L>
<L>Here, bear her in.<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot"><HI>HORATIA</HI> is carried in, <HI>VALERIUS</HI> and <HI>VALERIA</HI> follow.</NOTE>—I am concern'd, my Sovereign,</L>
<L>That even the meanest Part of me should blast</L>
<L>With impious Grief a Cause of so much Glory.</L>
<L>But let the Virtue of my Boy excuse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS HOSTILIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>It does most amply. She has Cause for Sorrow.</L>
<L>The Shock was sudden, and might well alarm</L>
<L>A firmer Bosom. The weak Sex demand</L>
<L>Our Pity, not our Anger; their soft Breasts</L>
<L>Are nearer touch'd, and more expos'd to Sorrows</L>
<L>Than Man's experter Sense. Nor let us blame</L>
<L>That Tenderness which smooths our rougher Natures,</L>
<L><PB N="23" REF="29"/>And softens all the Joys of social Life.</L>
<L>We leave her to her Tears. For you, young Soldier,</L>
<L>You must prepare for Combat. Some few Hours</L>
<L>Are all that are allow'd you. But I charge you</L>
<L>Try well your Heart, and strengthen every Thought</L>
<L>Of Patriot in you. Think how dreadful 'tis</L>
<L>To plant a Dagger in the Breast you love;</L>
<L>To spurn the Ties of Nature, and forget</L>
<L>In one short Hour whole Years of virtuous Friendship.</L>
<L>Think well on that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do, my gracious Sovereign;</L>
<L>And think the more I dare subdue Affection</L>
<L>The more my Glory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS HOSTILIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>True; but yet consider,</L>
<L>Is it an easy Task to change Affections?</L>
<L>In the dread Onset can your meeting Eyes</L>
<L>Forget their usual Intercourse, and wear</L>
<L>At once the Frown of War, and stern Defiance?</L>
<L>Will not each Look recall the fond Remembrance</L>
<L>Of Childhood past, when the whole open Soul</L>
<L>Breath'd cordial Love, and plighted many a Vow</L>
<L>Of tend'rest import? Think on that, young Soldier,</L>
<L>And tell me if thy Breast be still unmov'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Think not, O King, howe'er resolv'd on Combat,</L>
<L>I sit so loosely to the Bonds of Nature,</L>
<L>As not to feel their Force. I feel it strongly.</L>
<L>I love the <HI>Curiatii,</HI> and would serve them</L>
<L>At Life's Expence: But here a nobler Cause</L>
<L>Demands my Sword: For all Connections else,</L>
<L>All private Duties are subordinate</L>
<L><PB N="24" REF="30"/>To what we owe the Public. Partial Ties</L>
<L>Of Son, and Father, Husband, Friend, or Brother,</L>
<L>Owe their Enjoyments to the public Safety,</L>
<L>And without that were vain.—Nor need we, Sir,</L>
<L>Cast off Humanity, and to be Heroes</L>
<L>Cease to be Men. As in our earliest Days,</L>
<L>While yet we learn'd the Exercise of War,</L>
<L>We strove together, not as Enemies,</L>
<L>Yet conscious each of his peculiar Worth,</L>
<L>And scorning each to yield; so will we now</L>
<L>Engage with ardent not with hostile Minds,</L>
<L>Not fired with Rage, but emulous of Fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS HOSTILIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I dare trust thee; go, and teach thy Brothers</L>
<L>To think like thee, and Conquest is your own.</L>
<L>This is true Courage, not the brutal Force</L>
<L>Of vulgar Heroes, but the firm Resolve</L>
<L>Of Virtue, and of Reason. He who thinks</L>
<L>Without their Aid to shine in Deeds of Arms,</L>
<L>Builds on a sandy Basis his Renown;</L>
<L>A Dream, a Vapour, or an Ague Fit</L>
<L>May make a Coward of him.—Come, HORATIUS,</L>
<L>Thy other Sons shall meet thee at the Camp,</L>
<L>For now I do bethink me 'tis not fit</L>
<L>They should behold their Sister thus alarm'd.</L>
<L>Haste, Soldier, and detain them.
<STAGE><HI>To one of the Guards.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Sir,</L>
<L>We'll follow on the instant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS HOSTILIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Farewel.</L>
<L>When next we meet, 'tis <HI>Rome</HI> and Liberty!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit with Guaras.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB N="25" REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, let me arm thee for the glorious Toil.</L>
<L>I have a Sword whose Light'ning oft has blaz'd</L>
<L>Dreadfully fatal on my Country's Foes;</L>
<L>Whose temper'd Edge has cleft their haughty Crests,</L>
<L>And stain'd with Life-blood many a reeking Plain.</L>
<L>This shalt thou bear; myself will gird it on,</L>
<L>And lead thee forth to Death or Victory.
<STAGE><HI>Going.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>— And yet, my PUBLIUS, shall I own a Weakness;</L>
<L>Tho' I detest the Cause from whence they spring,</L>
<L>I feel thy Sister's Sorrows like a Father.</L>
<L>She was my Soul's delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>And may remain so.</L>
<L>This sudden Shock has but alarm'd her Virtue,</L>
<L>Not quite subdued its Force. At least, my Father,</L>
<L>Time's lenient Hand will teach her to endure</L>
<L>The ills of Chance, and Reason conquer Love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should we not see her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no means, my Lord;</L>
<L>You heard the King's Command about my Brothers,</L>
<L>And we have Hearts as tender sure as they.</L>
<L>Might I advise, you should confine her closely,</L>
<L>Lest she infect the Matrons with her Grief,</L>
<L>And bring a Stain we should not wish to fix</L>
<L>On the <HI>Horatian</HI> Name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be so.</L>
<L>We'll think no more of her. 'Tis Glory calls,</L>
<L>And humbler Passions beat Alarms in vain.
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>As</HI> HORATIUS <HI>goes off,</HI> HORATIA <HI>enters at another Door.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB N="26" REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is my Brother?—O my dearest PUBLIUS,</L>
<L>If e'er you lov'd HORATIA, ever felt</L>
<L>That Tenderness which you have seem'd to feel,</L>
<L>O hear her now!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would'st thou, my HORATIA?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what I would—I'm on the Rack,</L>
<L>Despair and Madness tear my lab'ring Soul.</L>
<L>—And yet, my Brother, sure you might relieve me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, by what means? By Heaven, I'd die to do it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>You might decline the Combat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not</L>
<L>Expect it from thee. Prithee look more kindly.</L>
<L>—And yet, is the Request so very hard?</L>
<L>I only ask thee not to plunge thy Sword</L>
<L>Into the Breast thou lov'st, not kill thy Friend,</L>
<L>Is that so hard?—I might have said thy Brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What canst thou mean? Beware, beware, HORATIA.</L>
<L>Thou know'st I dearly love thee, nay thou know'st</L>
<L>I love the Man with whom I must engage.</L>
<L>Yet hast thou faintly read thy Brother's Soul,</L>
<L>If thou can'st think Entreaties have the Power,</L>
<L>Tho' urg'd with all the Tenderness of Tears,</L>
<L>To shake his settled Purpose: They may make</L>
<L><PB N="27" REF="33"/>My Task more hard, and my Soul bleed within me,</L>
<L>But cannot touch my Virtue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not Virtue</L>
<L>Which contradicts our Nature, 'tis the Rage</L>
<L>Of over-weening Pride. Has <HI>Rome</HI> no Champions</L>
<L>She could oppose but you? Are there not thousands</L>
<L>As warm in Glory, and as tried in Arms,</L>
<L>Who might without a Crime aspire to Conquest,</L>
<L>Or die with honest Fame?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, away;</L>
<L>Talk to thy Lover thus. But 'tis not CAIUS</L>
<L>Thou would'st have infamous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O kill me not</L>
<L>With such unkind Reproaches. Yes, I own</L>
<L>I love him, more—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Than a chaste <HI>Roman</HI> Maid</L>
<L>Should dare confess.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should dare! What means my Brother?</L>
<L>I had my Father's Sanction on my Love,</L>
<L>And Duty taught me first to feel it's Power.</L>
<L>—Should dare confess!—is that the dreadful Crime?</L>
<L>Alas but spare him, spare thy Friend, HORATIUS,</L>
<L>And I will cast him from my Breast for ever.</L>
<L>Will that oblige thee?—only let him die</L>
<L>By other Hands, and I will learn to hate him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why wilt thou talk thus madly? Love him still:</L>
<L>And if we fall the Victims of our Country</L>
<L>(Which Heaven avert!) wed, and enjoy him freely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="28" REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O never, never. What, my Country's Bane!</L>
<L>The Murderer of my Brothers! may the Gods</L>
<L>First tear me, blast me, scatter me on Winds,</L>
<L>And pour out each unheard-of Vengeance on me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not torment thyself thus idly—Go,</L>
<L>Compose thyself, and be again my Sister.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Re-enter</HI> HORATIUS <HI>[with the Sword]</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Sword in <HI>Veii</HI>'s Field—What dost thou here?</L>
<L>Leave him I charge thee, Girl—Come come, my PUBLIUS,</L>
<L>Let's haste where Duty calls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, to the Field?</L>
<L>He must not, shall not go; here will I hang—</L>
<L>O if you have not quite cast off Affection,</L>
<L>If you detest not your distracted Sister—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shame of thy Race, why dost thou hang upon him?</L>
<L>Would'st thou entail eternal Infamy</L>
<L>On him, on me, on all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I would not.</L>
<L>I know I ask Impossibilities;</L>
<L>Yet pity me, my Father!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pity thee?</L>
<L>Begone, fond Wretch, nor urge my Temper thus.</L>
<L>By Heaven I love thee as a Brother ought.</L>
<L>Then hear my last Resolve; if Fate, averse</L>
<L>To <HI>Rome,</HI> and us, determine my Destruction,</L>
<L>I charge thee wed thy Lover; he will then</L>
<L><PB N="29" REF="35"/>Deserve thee nobly. Or if kinder Gods</L>
<L>Propitious hear the Prayers of suppliant <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>And he should fall by me, I then expect</L>
<L>No weak Upbraidings for a Lover's Death,</L>
<L>But such Returns as shall become thy Birth,</L>
<L>A Sister's Thanks for having sav'd her Country.
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet stay—Yet hear me, PUBLIUS—But one Word—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let go thy hold, rash Girl, thou'l't tempt thy Father</L>
<L>To do an Outrage might perhaps distract him.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, forgive me, Sir—I'm very wretched,</L>
<L>Indeed I am—Yet I will strive to stop</L>
<L>This swelling Grief, and bear it like your Daughter.</L>
<L>Do but forgive me, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do, I do—</L>
<L>Go in, my Child, the Gods may find a Way</L>
<L>To make thee happy yet. But on thy Duty,</L>
<L>Whate'er Reports may reach, or Fears alarm thee,</L>
<L>I charge thee come not to the Field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not,</L>
<L>If you command it, Sir. But will you then,</L>
<L>As far as cruel Honor may permit,</L>
<L>Remember that your poor HORATIA'S Life</L>
<L>Hangs on this dreadful Contest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lead her in.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> HORATIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB N="30" REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS. <HI>[Looking after her.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Spite of my boasted Strength, her Griefs unman me.</L>
<L>—But let her from my Thoughts. The Patriot's Breast</L>
<L>No Hopes, no Fears, but for his Country knows,</L>
<L>And in her Danger loses private Woes.
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER><HI>The END of the</HI> Second Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB N="31" REF="37"/>
<HEAD>ACT III.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Scene continues.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>VALERIUS <HI>and</HI> VALERIA <HI>meeting.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>NOW, my VALERIA, where's the charming she</L>
<L>That calls me to her? with a Lover's Haste</L>
<L>I fly to execute the dear Command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not the Lover, but the Friend she wants,</L>
<L>If thou dar'st own that Name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Friend, my Sister!</L>
<L>There's more than Friendship in a Lover's Breast,</L>
<L>More warm, more tender is the Flame he feels —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, these Raptures suit not her Distress,</L>
<L>She seeks th' indulgent Friend, whose sober Sense</L>
<L>Free from the Mists of Passion might direct</L>
<L>Her jarring Thoughts, and plead her doubtful Cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I that Friend? O did she turn her Thought</L>
<L>On me for that kind Office?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="32" REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, VALERIUS.</L>
<L>She chose you out to be her Advocate</L>
<L>To CURIATIUS; 'tis the only Hope</L>
<L>She now dares cherish; her relentless Brother</L>
<L>With Scorn rejects her Tears, her Father flies her,</L>
<L>And only you remain to sooth her Cares,</L>
<L>And save her ere she sinks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her Advocate</L>
<L>To CURIATIUS!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis to him she sends you,</L>
<L>To urge her Suit, and win him from the Field.</L>
<L>But come; her Sorrows will more strongly plead</L>
<L>Than all my Grief can utter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>To my Rival!</L>
<L>To CURIATIUS plead her Cause, and teach</L>
<L>My Tongue a Lesson which my Heart abhors!</L>
<L>Impossible! VALERIA, prithee say</L>
<L>Thou saw'st me not; the Business of the Camp</L>
<L>Confin'd me there; Farewel.
<STAGE><HI>Going.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What means my Brother?</L>
<L>You cannot leave her now; for shame turn back;</L>
<L>Is this the Virtue of a <HI>Roman</HI> Youth?</L>
<L>O by these Tears!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>They flow in vain, VALERIA:</L>
<L>Nay, and thou knowest they do. O Earth and Heaven!</L>
<L><PB N="33" REF="39"/>This Combat was the Means my happier Stars</L>
<L>Found out, to save me on the Brink of Ruin;</L>
<L>And can I plead against it, turn Assassin</L>
<L>On my own Life?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet thou can'st murder her</L>
<L>Thou dost pretend to love; away, Deceiver;</L>
<L>I'll seek some worthier Messenger to plead</L>
<L>In Beauty's Cause; but first inform HORATIA,</L>
<L>How much VALERIUS is the Friend she thought him.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Going.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Heav'ns! stay, Sister; 'tis an arduous Task.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know the Task is hard, and thought I knew</L>
<L>Thy Virtue too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must, I will obey thee.</L>
<L>Lead on.—Yet, prithee, for a Moment leave me,</L>
<L>'Till I can recollect my scatter'd Thoughts,</L>
<L>And dare to be unhappy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My VALERIUS!</L>
<L>I fly to tell her you but wait her Pleasure.
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I will undertake this hateful Office;</L>
<L>It never can succeed. — Yet at this Instant</L>
<L>It may be dangerous, while the People melt</L>
<L>With fond Compassion.—No, it cannot be;</L>
<L>His Resolution's fix'd, and virtuous Pride</L>
<L>Forbids an Alteration. To attempt it</L>
<L>Makes her my Friend, and may afford hereafter</L>
<L><PB N="34" REF="40"/>A thousand tender Hours to move my Suit.</L>
<L>That Hope determines all.
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD><HI>SCENE,</HI> Another Apartment.</HEAD>
<STAGE>HORATIA <HI>and</HI> VALERIA. HORATIA <HI>with a Scarf in her Hand.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Where is thy Brother? Wherefore stays he thus?</L>
<L>Did you conjure him, did he say he'd come?</L>
<L>I have no Brothers now, and fly to him</L>
<L>As my last Refuge. Did he seem averse</L>
<L>To thy Intreaties? Are all Brothers so!</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Alas, thou told'st me he spake kindly to thee;</L>
<L>'Tis me, 'tis me he shuns; I am the Wretch</L>
<L>Whom Virtue dares not make Acquaintance with.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Yet fly to him again, intreat him hither,</L>
<L>Tell him for thy Sake to have Pity on me,</L>
<L>Thou art no Enemy to <HI>Rome,</HI> thou hast</L>
<L>No <HI>Alban</HI> Husband to claim half thy Tears,</L>
<L>And make Humanity a Crime.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dear Maid,</L>
<L>Restrain your Sorrows, I've already told you</L>
<L>My Brother will with Transport execute</L>
<L>Whatever you command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O wherefore then</L>
<L>Is he away? each Moment now is precious,</L>
<L>If lost, 'tis lost for ever, and if gain'd,</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="41"/>Long Scenes of lasting Peace, and smiling Years</L>
<L>Of Happiness unhop'd-for wait upon it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will again go seek him; pray be calm;</L>
<L>Success is thine if it depends on him.
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Success! alas, perhaps ev'n now too late</L>
<L>I labour to preserve him; the dread Arm</L>
<L>Of Vengeance is already stretch'd against him,</L>
<L>And he must fall. Yet let me strive to save him.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Yes, thou dear Pledge, design'd for happier Hours,</L>
<STAGE><HI>To the Scarf.</HI></STAGE>
<L>The Gift of nuptial Love, thou shalt at least</L>
<L>Essay thy Power.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Oft as I fram'd the Web,</L>
<L>He fate beside me, and would say in Sport,</L>
<L>This Present, which thy Love designs for me,</L>
<L>Shall be the future Bond of Peace betwixt us.</L>
<L>By this we'll swear a lasting Love, by this,</L>
<L>Thro' the sweet Round of all our Days to come,</L>
<L>Ask what thou wilt, and CURIATIUS grants it.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>O I shall try thee nearly now, dear Youth;</L>
<L>Glory and I are Rivals for thy Heart,</L>
<L>And one must conquer.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> VALERIUS <HI>and</HI> VALERIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save you, gracious Lady;</L>
<L>On the first Message which my Sister sent me</L>
<L>I had been here, but was oblig'd by Office,</L>
<L>Ere to their Champions each resign'd her Charge,</L>
<L>To ratify the League 'twixt <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Alba.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="36" REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they engag'd then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, not yet engag'd;</L>
<L>Soft Pity for a while suspends the Onset;</L>
<L>The Sight of near Relations, arm'd in Fight</L>
<L>Against each other, touch'd the Gazers Hearts;</L>
<L>And Senators on each Side have propos'd</L>
<L>To change the Combatants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Blessings on them!</L>
<L>Think you they will succeed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Chiefs themselves</L>
<L>Are resolute to fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Insatiate Virtue!</L>
<L>I must not to the Field; I am confin'd</L>
<L>A Prisoner here; or sure these Tears would move</L>
<L>Their flinty Breasts.—Is CURIATIUS too</L>
<L>Resolv'd on Death?—O Sir, forgive a Maid,</L>
<L>Who dares in spite of Modesty confess</L>
<L>Too soft a Passion. Will you pardon me,</L>
<L>If I intreat you to the Field again</L>
<L>An humble Suitor from the veriest Wretch,</L>
<L>That ever knew Distress.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dear Lady speak;</L>
<L>What would you I should do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O bear this to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS,</SPEAKER>
<L>To whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="37" REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>To CURIATIUS bear this Scarf;</L>
<L>And tell him if he ever truly lov'd;</L>
<L>If all the Vows he breath'd were not false Lures</L>
<L>To catch th' unwary Mind,—and sure they were not!</L>
<L>O tell him now he may with Honour cease</L>
<L>To urge his cruel Right; the Senators</L>
<L>Of <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Alba</HI> will approve such Mildness.</L>
<L>Tell him his Wife, if he will own that Name,</L>
<L>Intreats him from the Field; his lost HORATIA</L>
<L>Begs on her trembling Knees he would not tempt</L>
<L>A certain Fate, and murder her he loves.</L>
<L>Tell him if he consents, she fondly swears</L>
<L>By every God the varying World adores,</L>
<L>By this dear Pledge of vow'd Affection swears,</L>
<L>To know no Brothers and no Sire but him;</L>
<L>With him, if Honour's harsh Commands require it,</L>
<L>She'll wander forth, and seek some distant Home,</L>
<L>Nor ever think of <HI>Rome</HI> or <HI>Alba</HI> more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, well, he will; do not torment thyself.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA. <HI>[Catching hold of the Scarf, which she looked upon attentively while</HI> Valeria <HI>spoke.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Look here, VALERIA, where my Needle's Art</L>
<L>Has drawn a <HI>Sabine</HI> Virgin, drown'd in Tears</L>
<L>For her lost Country, and forsaken Friends;</L>
<L>While by her Side the youthful Ravisher</L>
<L>Looks ardent Love, and charms her Griefs away.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I am that Maid distress'd, divided so</L>
<L>'Twixt Love and Duty.—But why rave I thus!</L>
<L>Haste, haste, to CURIATIUS; and yet stay,</L>
<L>Sure I had something more to say to him;</L>
<L>I know not what it was.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="38" REF="44"/>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could I, sweet Lady,</L>
<L>But paint your Grief with half the Force I feel it,</L>
<L>I need but tell it him, and he must yield.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be so. Stay, stay, besure you tell him,</L>
<L>If he rejects my Suit, no Power on Earth</L>
<L>Shall force me to his Arms; I will devise—</L>
<L>I'll die and be reveng'd!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, my Brother;</L>
<L>But oh for Pity, do your Office justly;
<STAGE><HI>Aside to</HI> VALERIUS.</STAGE></L>
<L>Let not your Passion blind your Reason now,</L>
<L>But urge her Cause with Ardor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my Soul</L>
<L>I will VALERIA; her Distress alarms me;</L>
<L>And I have now no Interest but hers.
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, dearest Maid, indulge not thus your Sorrows:</L>
<L>Hope smiles again, and the sad Prospect clears.</L>
<L>Who knows th'Effect your Message may produce;</L>
<L>The milder Senators ere this perhaps</L>
<L>Have mov'd your Lover's Mind; and if he doubts,</L>
<L>He's yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's gone.—I had a thousand Things;</L>
<L>And yet I'm glad he's gone. Think you, VALERIA,</L>
<L>Your Brother will delay? they may engage</L>
<L>Before he reaches them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Field's so near,</L>
<L>That a few Minutes bring him to the Place:</L>
<L>And 'tis not probable the Senators</L>
<L>So soon should yield a Cause of so much Justice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="39" REF="45"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, they should have thought on that before,</L>
<L>'Tis now too late. The Lion when he's rous'd</L>
<L>Must have his Prey, whose Den we might have past</L>
<L>In Safety while he slept. To draw the Sword,</L>
<L>And fire the youthful Warrior's Breast to Arms</L>
<L>With aweful Visions of immortal Fame,</L>
<L>And then to bid him sheath it, and forget</L>
<L>He ever hop'd for Conquest and Renown;</L>
<L>Vain, vain Attempt!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet when that just Attempt</L>
<L>Is seconded by Love, and Beauty's Tears</L>
<L>Lend their soft Aid to melt the Hero down;</L>
<L>What may we not expect?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My dear VALERIA,</L>
<L>Fain wou'd I hope I had the Power to move him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have, you must; Success is yours already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet should I succeed, the hard-gain'd Strife</L>
<L>May chance to rob me of my future Peace.</L>
<L>He may not always with the Eyes of Love</L>
<L>Look on that Fondness which has stab'd his Fame.</L>
<L>He may regret too late the Sacrifice</L>
<L>He made to Love, and a fond Woman's Weakness;</L>
<L>And think the milder Joys of social Life</L>
<L>But ill repay him for the mighty Loss</L>
<L>Of Patriot-reputation!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray forbear,</L>
<L>And search not thus into eventful Time</L>
<L><PB N="40" REF="46"/>For Ills to come. This fatal Temper, Friend,</L>
<L>Alive to feel, and curious to explore</L>
<L>Each distant Object of refin'd Distress,</L>
<L>Shuts out all Means of Happiness, nor leaves it</L>
<L>In Fortune's Power to save you from Destruction.</L>
<L>Like some distemper'd Wretch, your wayward Mind</L>
<L>Rejects all Nourishment, or turns to Gall</L>
<L>The very Balm that should relieve its Anguish.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>He will admire thy Love, which could perswade him</L>
<L>To give up Glory for the milder Triumph</L>
<L>Of heart-felt Ease and soft Humanity.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fain would hope so. Yet we hear not of him.</L>
<L>Your Brother, much I fear, has sued in vain.</L>
<L>Could we not send to urge his slow Express?</L>
<L>This dread Uncertainty! I long to know</L>
<L>My Life or Death at once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Wings of Love</L>
<L>Cannot fly faster than my Brother's Zeal</L>
<L>Will bear him for your Service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I believe it,</L>
<L>Yet doubt it too. My sickly Mind unites</L>
<L>Strange Contradictions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I to the Walls?</L>
<L>I may from thence with Ease survey the Field,</L>
<L>And can dispatch a Messenger each Moment</L>
<L>To tell thee all goes well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My best VALERIA!</L>
<L>Fly then. I know thy Heart is there already▪</L>
<L><PB N="41" REF="47"/>Thou art a <HI>Roman</HI> Maid, and tho' thy Friendship</L>
<L>Detains thee here with one who scarce deserves</L>
<L>That sacred Name, art anxious for thy Country.</L>
<L>But yet for Charity think kindly of me;</L>
<L>For thou shalt find by the Event, VALERIA,</L>
<L>I am a <HI>Roman</HI> too, however wretched.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> VALERIA.</STAGE>
<L>Am I a <HI>Roman</HI> then? Ye Powers, I dare not</L>
<L>Resolve the fatal Question I propose.</L>
<L>If dying would suffice, I were a <HI>Roman;</HI></L>
<L>But to stand up against this Storm of Passions</L>
<L>Transcends a Woman's Weakness. Hark, what Noise!—</L>
<L>'Tis News from CURIATIUS; Love, I thank thee!</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter a Servant.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Well, does he yield? distract me not with Silence;</L>
<L>Say in one Word.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SERVANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Father—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of him?</L>
<L>Would he not let him yield? O cruel Father!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SERVANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, he's here—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SERVANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Borne by his Attendants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What mean'st thou?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>HORATIUS <HI>is led in by his Servants.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lead me yet a little onward;</L>
<L>I shall recover straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="42" REF="48"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gracious Sire!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lend me thy Arm, HORATIA.—So—my Child,</L>
<L>Be not surpriz'd; an old Man must expect</L>
<L>These little Shocks of Nature, they are Hints</L>
<L>To warn us of our End.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>How are you, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better, much better. My frail Body could not</L>
<L>Support the swelling Tumult of my Soul.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Accident I hope alarm'd you, Sir,</L>
<L>My Brothers—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, go to the Field again,</L>
<L>You CAUTUS and VINDICIUS; and observe</L>
<L>Each Circumstance; I shall be glad to hear</L>
<L>The manner of the Fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they engag'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are, HORATIA; but first let me thank thee
<STAGE><HI>During this Speech a Ser∣vant gives a Paper to</HI> HORATIA.</STAGE></L>
<L>For staying from the Field; I would have seen</L>
<L>The Fight myself, but this unlucky Illness</L>
<L>Has forc'd me to retire. Where is thy Friend?</L>
<L>What Paper's that? Why dost thou tremble so?</L>
<L>Here let me open it.—From CURIATIUS!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O keep me not in this Suspence, my Father;</L>
<L>Relieve me from the Rack.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="43" REF="49"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He tells thee here,</L>
<L>He dare not do an Action that would make him</L>
<L>Unworthy of thy Love, and therefore—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dies!</L>
<L>Well, I am satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see by this</L>
<L>Thou hast endeavour'd to persuade thy Lover</L>
<L>To quit the Combat. Could'st thou think, HORATIA,</L>
<L>He'd sacrifice his Country to a Woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what I thought; he proves too plainly</L>
<L>Whate'er it was, I was deceiv'd in him</L>
<L>Whom I applied to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not think so, Daughter;</L>
<L>Could he with Honour have declin'd the Fight,</L>
<L>I should myself have join'd in thy Request,</L>
<L>And forc'd him from the Field. But think, my Child,</L>
<L>Had he consented, and had <HI>Alba</HI>'s Cause,</L>
<L>Supported by another Arm, been baffled,</L>
<L>What then could'st thou expect? Would he not curse</L>
<L>His foolish Love, and hate thee for thy Fondness?</L>
<L>Nay think, perhaps, 'twas Artifice in thee</L>
<L>To aggrandize thy Race, and lift their Fame</L>
<L>Triumphant o'er his Ruin and his Country's.</L>
<L>Think well on that, and Reason must convince thee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE><HI>Wildly.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Alas, had Reason ever yet the Power</L>
<L>To talk down Grief, or bid the tortur'd Wretch</L>
<L>Not feel his Anguish? 'tis impossible.</L>
<L><PB N="44" REF="50"/>Could Reason govern, I should now rejoice</L>
<L>They were engag'd, and count the tedious Moments</L>
<L>'Till Conquest smil'd, and <HI>Rome</HI> again was free.</L>
<L>Could Reason govern, I should beg of Heaven</L>
<L>To guide my Brother's Sword, and plunge it deep</L>
<L>Ev'n in the Bosom of the Man I love.</L>
<L>I should forget he ever won my Soul;</L>
<L>Forget 'twas your Command that bade me love him;</L>
<L>Nay fly perhaps to yon detested Field,</L>
<L>And spurn with Scorn his mangled Carcase from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why wilt thou talk thus? Prithee be more calm:</L>
<L>I can forgive thy Tears, they flow from Nature,</L>
<L>And could have gladly wish'd the <HI>Alban</HI> State</L>
<L>Had found us other Enemies to vanquish.</L>
<L>But Heaven has will'd it, and Heaven's Will be done!</L>
<L>The glorious Expectation of Success</L>
<L>Buoys up my Soul, nor lets a Thought intrude</L>
<L>To dash my promis'd Joys.—What steady Valour</L>
<L>Beam'd from their Eyes! Just so, if Fancy's Power</L>
<L>May form Conjecture from his After-age,</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI>'s Founder must have look'd, when warm in Youth</L>
<L>And flush'd with future Conquest forth he march'd</L>
<L>Against proud <HI>Acron,</HI> with whose bleeding Spoils</L>
<L>He grac'd the Altar of <HI>Feretrian Jove.</HI></L>
<L>—Methinks I feel recover'd; I might venture</L>
<L>Forth to the Field again. What ho! VOLSCINIUS,</L>
<L>Attend me to the Camp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My dearest Father,</L>
<L>Let me intreat you stay; the Tumult there</L>
<L>Will discompose you, and a quick Relapse</L>
<L><PB N="45" REF="51"/>May prove most dangerous. I'll restrain my Tears,</L>
<L>If they offend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I'll be advis'd.</L>
<L>'Twere now too late, ere this they must have conquer'd.</L>
<L>—And here's the happy Messenger of Glory!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> VALERIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>All's lost, all's ruin'd, Freedom is no more!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dost thou say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>That <HI>Rome</HI>'s subdued by <HI>Alba.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot be; where are my Sons? all dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>PUBLIUS is still alive, the other Two</L>
<L>Have paid the fatal Debt they owed their Country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>PUBLIUS alive? you must mistake, VALERIA;</L>
<L>He knows his Duty better.</L>
<L>He must be dead, or <HI>Rome</HI> victorious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thousands as well as I beheld the Combat;</L>
<L>After his Brother's Deaths he stood alone,</L>
<L>And acted Wonders against three Assailants;</L>
<L>'Till forc'd at last to save himself by Flight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>By Flight? and did the Soldiers let him pass?</L>
<L>O I am ill again!—the Coward Villain!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Throwing himself into his Chair.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB N="46" REF="52"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, my Brothers!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weep not for them, Girl;</L>
<L>They've died a Death which Kings themselves might envy,</L>
<L>And whilst they liv'd they saw their Country free.</L>
<L>O had I perish'd with them! But for him</L>
<L>Whose impious Flight dishonours all his Race,</L>
<L>Tears a fond Father's Heart, and tamely barters</L>
<L>For poor precarious Life his Country's Glory,</L>
<L>Weep, weep for him, and let me join my Tears!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What could he do, my Lord, when three oppos'd him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He might have died!—O Villain, Villain, Villain!</L>
<L>—And he shall die; this Arm shall sacrifice</L>
<L>The Life he dared preserve with Infamy.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Endeavouring to rise.</HI></STAGE>
<L>What means this Weakness? 'tis untimely now,</L>
<L>When I should punish an ungrateful Boy.</L>
<L>Was this his boasted Virtue which could charm</L>
<L>His cheated Sovereign, and brought Tears of Joy</L>
<L>To my old Eyes?—so young a Hypocrite!</L>
<L>O Shame, Shame, Shame!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have patience Sir, all <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Beheld his Valour, and approv'd his Flight</L>
<L>Against such Opposition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tell not me,</L>
<L>What's <HI>Rome</HI> to me? <HI>Rome</HI> may excuse her Traitor;</L>
<L>But I'm the Guardian of my House's Honour,</L>
<L><PB N="47" REF="53"/>And I will punish. Pray ye lead me forth,</L>
<L>I would have Air. But grant me Strength, kind Gods,</L>
<L>To do this Act of Justice, and I'll own,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Whate'er 'gainst <HI>Rome</HI> your awful Wills decree,</L>
<L>Ye still are just, and merciful to me!
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt.</HI></STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER><HI>The END of the</HI> Third Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB N="48" REF="54"/>
<HEAD>ACT IV.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>A Room in</HI> HORATIUS<HI>'S House.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> HORATIUS, VALERIA <HI>following.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>AWAY, away,—I feel my strength renew'd,</L>
<L>And I will hunt the Villain thro' the World;</L>
<L>No Desarts shall conceal, nor Darkness hide him.</L>
<L>He is well skill'd in Flight, but he shall find</L>
<L>'Tis not so easy to elude the Vengeance</L>
<L>Of a wrong'd Father's Arm, as to escape</L>
<L>His Adversary's Sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Restrain your Rage</L>
<L>But for a Moment Sir; when you shall hear</L>
<L>The whole unravel'd, you will find he's innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>And see my Brother comes,</L>
<L>He may perhaps relate—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="49" REF="55"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not hear him;</L>
<L>I will not listen to my Shame again.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> VALERIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come with kind condolance from the King</L>
<L>To sooth a Father's Grief, and to express—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I've heard it all; I pray you spare my Blushes.</L>
<L>I want not Consolation, 'tis enough</L>
<L>They perish'd for their Country. But the third—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, he indeed may well supply their Loss,</L>
<L>And calls for all your Fondness.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>All my Vengeance;</L>
<L>And he shall have it, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What means my Lord?</L>
<L>Are you alone displeas'd with what he has done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis I alone, I find, must punish it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Punish, my Lord? What Fault has he committed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why will you double my Confusion thus?</L>
<L>Is Flight no Fault?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>In such a Cause as his</L>
<L>'Twas glorious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="50" REF="56"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Glorious! O rare Sophistry,</L>
<L>To find a Way through Infamy to Glory!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I scarce can trust my Senses!—Infamy!</L>
<L>What, was it infamous to save his Country?</L>
<L>Is Art a Crime? Is it the Name of Flight</L>
<L>We can't forgive, though its ador'd Effect</L>
<L>Restor'd us all to Freedom, Fame, and Empire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Fame, what Freedom, who has saved his Country?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Son, my Lord, has done it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, when, where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't possible? Did you not say you knew?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I care not what I knew; O tell me all,</L>
<L>Is <HI>Rome</HI> still free? has <HI>Alba?</HI> has my Son?</L>
<L>Tell me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Son, my Lord, has slain her Champions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, PUBLIUS?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>O let me clasp thee to me—</L>
<L>Were there not three remaining?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, there were;</L>
<L>But wounded all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="51" REF="57"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Sister here had told us</L>
<L>That <HI>Rome</HI> was vanquish'd, that my Son was fled—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>And he did fly, but 'twas that Flight preserv'd us.</L>
<L>All <HI>Rome</HI> as well as she has been deceiv'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me again embrace thee.—Come, relate it.</L>
<L>Did I not say, VALERIA, that my Boy</L>
<L>Must needs be dead, or <HI>Rome</HI> victorious?</L>
<L>I long to hear the Manner.—Well, VALERIUS.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your other Sons, my Lord, had paid the Debt</L>
<L>They owed to <HI>Rome,</HI> and he alone remain'd</L>
<L>'Gainst three Opponents, whose united Strength,</L>
<L>Tho' wounded each, and robb'd of half their Force,</L>
<L>Was still too great for his. Awhile he stood</L>
<L>Their fierce Assaults, and then pretended Flight</L>
<L>Only to tire his wounded Adversaries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pretended Flight, and this succeeded, ha!</L>
<L>O glorious Boy!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas better still, my Lord;</L>
<L>For all pursued, but not with equal Speed.</L>
<L>Each eager for the Conquest press'd to reach him,</L>
<L>Nor did the first 'till 'twas too late perceive</L>
<L>His fainter Brothers panting far behind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He took them singly then? an easy Conquest,</L>
<L>'Twas Boy's Play only.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="52" REF="58"/>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never did I see</L>
<L>Such universal Joy, as when the last</L>
<L>Sunk on the Ground beneath HORATIUS' Sword;</L>
<L>Who seem'd awhile to parley as a Friend,</L>
<L>And would have given him Life, but <HI>Caius</HI> scorn'd it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caius!</HI> O poor HORATIA!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, I charge thee.</L>
<L>Go, dress thy Face in Smiles, and bid thy Friend</L>
<L>Wake to new Transports; let Ambition fire her;</L>
<L>What is a Lover lost? There's not a Youth</L>
<L>In <HI>Rome</HI> but will adore her; Kings will seek</L>
<L>For her Alliance now, and mightiest Chiefs</L>
<L>Be honour'd by her Smiles. Will they not, Youth?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> VALERIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most sure, my Lord, this Day has added Worth</L>
<L>To her, whose Merit was before unequall'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>How could I doubt his Virtue!—Mighty Gods,</L>
<L>This is true Glory, to preserve his Country,</L>
<L>And bid by one brave Act th' <HI>Horatian</HI> Name</L>
<L>In Fame's eternal Volumes be enroll'd.</L>
<L>Methinks already I behold his Triumph.</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> gazes on him like a second Founder,</L>
<L>The wond'ring Eye of Childhood views with Awe</L>
<L>The new Divinity, and trembling Age</L>
<L>Crowds eager on to bless him ere it dies!</L>
<L>Ere long, perhaps, they will raise Altars to him,</L>
<L>And even with Hymns and Sacrifice adore</L>
<L><PB N="53" REF="59"/>The Virtue I suspected!—Gracious Heav'n!</L>
<L>Where is he? Let me fly, and at his Feet</L>
<L>Forget the Father, and implore a Pardon</L>
<L>For such Injustice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may soon, my Lord,</L>
<L>In his Embraces lose the fond Remembrance</L>
<L>Of your mistaken Rage. The King ere this</L>
<L>Has from the Field dispatch'd him; he but stay'd</L>
<L>'Till he could send him home with some slight Honours</L>
<L>Of scatter'd Wreaths, and grateful Songs of Praise.</L>
<L>For 'till to-morrow he postpones the Pomp</L>
<L>Of solemn Thanks, and Sacrifice to Heaven</L>
<L>For Liberty restor'd. But hark! that Shout,</L>
<L>Which sounds from far, and seems the mingled Voice</L>
<L>Of Thousands, speaks him onward on his Way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my Heart dances!—Yet I blush to meet him.</L>
<L>But I will on. Come, come HORATIA, leave
<STAGE><HI>Calling at the Door.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Thy Sorrow far behind, and let us fly</L>
<L>With open Arms to greet our common Glory.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> HORATIUS.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> HORATIA <HI>and</HI> VALERIA, <HI>to</HI> VALERIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I will go; this Father's hard Command</L>
<L>Shall be obey'd, and I will meet the Conqueror;</L>
<L>But not in Smiles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>O go not, gentle Lady;</L>
<L>Might I advise —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="54" REF="60"/>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Griefs are yet too fresh,</L>
<L>And may offend him; do not, my HORATIA.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed 'twere better to avoid his Presence,</L>
<L>It will revive your Sorrows, and recall —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, when I saw you last I was a Woman,</L>
<L>The Fool of Nature, a fond Prey to Grief,</L>
<L>Made up of Sighs and Tears. But now, my Soul</L>
<L>Disdains the very Thought of what I was;</L>
<L>'Tis grown too callous to be mov'd with Toys.</L>
<L>Observe me well; am I not nobly chang'd?</L>
<L>Flow my sad Eyes, or heaves my Breast one Groan?</L>
<L>No, for I doubt no longer. 'Tis not Grief,</L>
<L>'Tis Resolution now, and fix'd Despair.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My dear HORATIA, you strike Terrors thro' me;</L>
<L>What dreadful Purpose hast thou form'd? O speak!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Talk gently to her.—Hear me yet, sweet Lady;</L>
<L>You must not go; whatever you resolve</L>
<L>There is a Sight will pierce you to the Soul.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Sight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, I should be glad to hide it;</L>
<L>But it is—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="55" REF="61"/>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Brother wears in Triumph</L>
<L>The very Scarf I bore to CURIATIUS.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE><HI>Wildly.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Ye Gods, I thank ye! 'tis with Joy I hear it.</L>
<L>If I should falter now, that Sight would rouze</L>
<L>My drooping Rage, and swell the Tempest louder.</L>
<L>— But soft; they may prevent me; my wild Passion</L>
<L>Betrays my Purpose.—I'll dissemble with them.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>She sits down.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>She softens now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>How do you, my HORATIA?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, my Friend, 'tis Madness which I utter—</L>
<L>Since you persuade me then, I will not go,</L>
<L>But leave me to myself; I would sit here,</L>
<L>Alone in silent Sadness pour my Tears,</L>
<L>And meditate on my unheard-of Woes.</L>
<STAGE>VALERIUS <HI>to</HI> VALERIA.</STAGE>
<L>'Twere well to humour this. But may she not</L>
<L>If left alone do Outrage on herself?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have prevented that; she has not near her</L>
<L>One Instrument of Death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Retire we then.</L>
<L>But oh not far, for now I feel my Soul</L>
<L>Still more perplex'd with Love. Who knows, VALERIA,</L>
<L><PB N="56" REF="62"/>But, when this Storm of Grief has blown its Fill,</L>
<L>She may grow calm, and listen to my Vows.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> VALERIUS <HI>and</HI> VALERIA.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>After a short Silence</HI> HORATIA <HI>rises, and comes forward.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, they are gone; and now be firm my Soul!</L>
<L>This Way I can elude their Search. The Heart,</L>
<L>Which doats like mine, must break to be at Ease.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Just now I thought, had CURIATIUS lived,</L>
<L>I could have driven him from my Breast for ever.</L>
<L>But Death has cancell'd all my Wrongs at once.</L>
<L>—They were not Wrongs; 'twas Virtue which undid us,</L>
<L>And Virtue shall unite us in the Grave.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I heard them say, as they departed hence,</L>
<L>That they had robb'd me of all Means of Death.</L>
<L>Vain Thought; they knew not half HORATIA'S Purpose.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Be resolute, my Brother, let no weak</L>
<L>Unmanly Fondness mingle with thy Virtue,</L>
<L>And I will touch thee nearly. O come on,</L>
<L>'Tis thou alone can'st give HORATIA Peace.
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="57" REF="63" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>SCENE II. <HI>A Street of</HI> Rome.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>CHORUS of Youths and Virgins singing and scat∣tering Branches of Oak, Flowers,</HI> &amp;c. <HI>Then enters</HI> HORATIUS <HI>leaning on the Arm of</HI> PUBLIUS HO∣RATIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CHORUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus, for Freedom nobly won,</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> her hasty Tribute pours;</L>
<L>And on one victorious Son</L>
<L>Half exhausts her blooming Stores.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A YOUTH.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scatter here the Laurel Crown,</L>
<L>Emblem of immortal Praise!</L>
<L>Wond'rous Youth! to thy Renown</L>
<L>Future Times shall Altars raise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A VIRGIN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scatter here the Myrtle Wreath,</L>
<L>Tho' the bloodless Victor's Due;</L>
<L>Grateful Thousands sav'd from Death</L>
<L>Shall devote that Wreath to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A YOUTH.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scatter here the Oaken Bough;</L>
<L>Ev'n for one averted Fate</L>
<L>We that Civic Meed bestow—</L>
<L>He sav'd all, who sav'd the State.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="58" REF="64"/>
<SPEAKER>CHORUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus for Freedom, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou do'st forgive me then, my dearest Boy,</L>
<L>I cannot tell thee half my Exstacy.</L>
<L>The Day which gave thee first to my glad Hopes</L>
<L>Was Misery to this—I'm mad with Transport!</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Why are ye silent there? again renew</L>
<L>Your Songs of Praise, and in a louder Strain</L>
<L>Pour forth your Joy, and tell the list'ning Spheres</L>
<L>That <HI>Rome</HI> is freed by <HI>my</HI> HORATIUS' Hand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, my Friends.—You must permit me, Sir,</L>
<L>To contradict you here. Not but my Soul,</L>
<L>Like yours, is open to the Charms of Praise:</L>
<L>There is no Joy beyond it, when the Mind</L>
<L>Of him who hears it can with honest Pride</L>
<L>Confess it just, and listen to its Music.</L>
<L>But now the Toils I have sustain'd require</L>
<L>Their Interval of Rest, and every Sense</L>
<L>Is deaf to Pleasure.—Let me leave you, Friends;</L>
<L>We're near our Home, and would be private now:</L>
<L>To-morrow we'll expect your kind Attendance</L>
<L>To share our Joys, and waft our Thanks to Heaven.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>As they are going off</HI> HORATIA <HI>rushes in.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is this mighty Chief?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Daughter's Voice!</L>
<L>I bade her come; she has forgot her Sorrows,</L>
<L>And is again my Child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the Hero</L>
<L><PB N="59" REF="65"/>That tramples Nature's Ties, and nobly soars</L>
<L>Above the Dictates of Humanity?</L>
<L>Let me observe him well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What means my Sister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Sister! I disclaim the impious Title;</L>
<L>Base and inhuman! Give me back my Husband,</L>
<L>My Life, my Soul, my murdered CURIATIUS!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He perish'd for his Country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Gods,</L>
<L>Was't not enough that thou had'st murdered him,</L>
<L>But thou must triumph in thy Guilt, and wear</L>
<L>His bleeding Spoils?—O let me tear them from thee,</L>
<L>Drink the dear Drops that issued from his Wounds,</L>
<L>More dear to me than the whole Tide that swells</L>
<L>With impious Pride a hostile Brother's Heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I awake, or is it all Illusion!</L>
<L>Was it for this thou cam'st?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>HORATIA, hear me.</L>
<L>Yet I am calm, and can forgive thy Folly;</L>
<L>Would I could call it by no harsher Name.</L>
<L>But do not tempt me farther.—Go, my Sister,</L>
<L>Go hide thee from the World, nor let a <HI>Roman</HI></L>
<L>Know with what Insolence thou dar'st avow</L>
<L>Thy Infamy, or what is more my Shame</L>
<L>How tamely I forgave it.—Go, HORATIA.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="60" REF="66"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not go.—What, have I touch'd thee then?</L>
<L>And can'st thou feel?—O think not thou shalt lose</L>
<L>Thy share of Anguish. I'll pursue thee still,</L>
<L>Urge thee all Day with thy unnatural Crimes,</L>
<L>Tear, harrow up thy Breast: and then at Night</L>
<L>I'll be the Fury that shall haunt thy Dreams;</L>
<L>Wake thee with Shrieks, and place before thy Sight</L>
<L>Thy mangled Friends in all their Pomp of Horror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with her; 'tis womanish Complaining.</L>
<L>Think'st thou such Trifles can alarm the Man</L>
<L>Whose noblest Passion is his Country's Love?</L>
<L>—Let it be thine, and learn to bear Affliction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Curse on my Country's Love, the Trick ye teach us</L>
<L>To make us Slaves beneath the Mask of Virtue;</L>
<L>To rob us of each soft endearing Sense,</L>
<L>And violate the first, great Law within us.</L>
<L>I scorn the impious Passion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have a Care;</L>
<L>Thou'st touch'd a String which may awake my Ven∣geance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE><HI>Aside.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Then it shall do it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, if thou dar'st prophane</L>
<L>That sacred Tie which winds about my Heart,</L>
<L>By Heaven I swear, by the great Gods who rule</L>
<L>The Fate of Empires, 'tis not this fond Weakness</L>
<L><PB N="61" REF="67"/>Which hangs upon me, and retards my Justice,</L>
<L>Nor even thy Sex, which shall protect thee from me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Clapping his Hand on his Sword.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drag her away—thou'lt make me curse thee, Girl—</L>
<L>Indeed she's mad.
<STAGE><HI>To</HI> PUBLIUS.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand off, I am not mad—</L>
<L>Nay, draw thy Sword; I do defy thee, Murderer,</L>
<L>Barbarian, <HI>Roman!</HI>—Mad; the Name of <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Makes Madmen of you all; my Curses on it.</L>
<L>I do detest its impious Policy.</L>
<L>Rise, rise ye States (O that my Voice could fire</L>
<L>Your tardy Wrath!) confound its selfish Greatness,</L>
<L>Rase it's proud Walls, and lay its Towers in Ashes!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll bear no more—
<STAGE><HI>Drawing his Sword.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Distraction!—Force her off—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA. <HI>[Struggling.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Could I but prove the <HI>Helen</HI> to destroy</L>
<L>This curs'd unsocial State, I'd die with Transport:</L>
<L>Gaze on the spreading Fires—'till the last Pile</L>
<L>Sunk in the Blaze—then mingle with its Ruins.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt not live to that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Assist me, Friends—</L>
<L>Drag—tear her off.—O PUBLIUS—O my Son—</L>
<L>Spare, spare a Father!
<STAGE><HI>They force her off.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="62" REF="68"/>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS. <HI>[After a Pause.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Let her avoid me then.—My whole Soul's mov'd,</L>
<L>And <HI>Rome</HI>'s immortal Genius stirs within me!</L>
<L>Yes, ye dread Powers, whose everlasting Fires</L>
<L>Blaze on our Altars, and whose sacred Shields</L>
<L>From Heaven descending guard imperial <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>I feel, I feel your Wrongs—for you I fought,</L>
<L>For you I bear the Sword.—Lead on my Friends.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS. <HI>[Looking at him as he goes out.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How dreadful, yet how lovely is his Virtue!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Going after him.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> VALERIUS <HI>and two or three Servants.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE><HI>Stopping</HI> HORATIUS.</STAGE>
<L>Saw you your Daughter, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, VALERIUS,</L>
<L>I yet stand trembling on the Brink of Fate,</L>
<L>And scarce can think the dreadful Moment past.</L>
<L>She has been here, and with such impious Outrage</L>
<L>Assail'd her Brother, that our utmost Force</L>
<L>Scarce sav'd her from his Sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He could not sure</L>
<L>Attempt her Life!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>And could you bear</L>
<L>That Sight, my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="63" REF="69"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>VALERIUS, ask me not</L>
<L>What I could bear. I feel the Torment still.</L>
<L>And dread to think what Mischiefs had ensued</L>
<L>Had I like him been warm'd and deaf to Nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>But she is safe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, from the Sword she is;</L>
<L>But mad as the <HI>Cumaean</HI> Maid she raves,</L>
<L>And pours incessant Curses on her Country.</L>
<L>Misguided Girl!</L>
<L>But I can bear my Fate; the Hand of Heaven</L>
<L>Chastises thus my Insolence of Joy,</L>
<L>I were too happy else!—Yet Art perhaps</L>
<L>May give her Ease, your Sister will attend her.</L>
<L>I must not see her now; PUBLIUS will think</L>
<L>That I neglect him; every Pang I feel</L>
<L>Affronts his Virtue, and each idle Doubt</L>
<L>Is Treason to the State his Arm has saved.</L>
<L>O my divided Heart!
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>PUBLIUS will think!</L>
<L>Then 'tis in <HI>Rome,</HI> it seems, become a Crime</L>
<L>Ev'n for the softer Sex to let their Anguish</L>
<L>Transport their Souls beyond the Bounds of Reason.</L>
<L>Our Heroes would new-mold Humanity;</L>
<L>And tie down Madness to the pedant Rules</L>
<L>Of dull Discretion.—Dar'd attempt her Life!</L>
<L>Let me not think on that. I will avoid him,</L>
<L>'Till I am calm again.—Go some of you</L>
<L>This Way, some that, and search my Sister out.</L>
<L><PB N="64" REF="70"/>Say, If I meet her not, I shall return</L>
<L>And wait her here.—This Violence of Grief</L>
<L>Cannot last long and such a Heart as hers</L>
<L>So form'd for Passion, so accessible</L>
<L>To tender Pains, may learn once more to prove</L>
<L>The pleasing Transports of reviving Love.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER><HI>The END of the Fourth</HI> ACT.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB N="65" REF="71"/>
<HEAD>ACT V.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE I.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>The Street.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> VALERIA <HI>and a Servant.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA. <HI>[in Disorder.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>REgard not me.—Did you not say, my Brother</L>
<L>Was here? Where is he?—Yet I know not why</L>
<L>I wish him here, but that my bursting Heart</L>
<L>May vent its Griefs, and find a Refuge for them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SERVANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, my Lord approaches.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> VALERIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O VALERIUS,</L>
<L>HORATIA, poor HORATIA'S lost for ever;</L>
<L>Her unrelenting Brother—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dearest Sister,</L>
<L>Compose your Fears. She has escap'd his Rage.</L>
<L>But now I saw her Father, and his Care</L>
<L>Has sav'd her from the Blow, and begs your Aid</L>
<L>To sooth her tortur'd Mind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="66" REF="72"/>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What says my Brother?</L>
<L>How sav'd? alas, too sure she dies this Moment.</L>
<L>She had no Father there; these Eyes beheld</L>
<L>The fatal Stroke, and these sad Arms receiv'd her.</L>
<L>Nor had I left her now but to obey</L>
<L>Her own Command, and by Intreaties force</L>
<L>Her cruel Brother to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS. <HI>[With Amazement.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>When was this?</L>
<L>Where was it?—Say, VALERIA—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I left you</L>
<L>To seek some diff'rent Way our hapless Charge,</L>
<L>Led by the Noise from Street to Street I ran,</L>
<L>And came at last where through the gather'd Crowd</L>
<L>I saw but could not reach her. Wild she seem'd,</L>
<L>Struggling with all that would oppose her Passage,</L>
<L>And trying every Method to provoke</L>
<L>Her Brother's Fury: With dire Blasphemies,</L>
<L>Which shock'd my trembling Soul, her Tongue profan'd</L>
<L>Each awful Name, and not a God escap'd</L>
<L>Her imprecating Rage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, well, enough;</L>
<L>But come to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ilent awhile he stood,</L>
<L>As the dead Calm before the Thunder rolls,</L>
<L>Nor answer'd to her Rage: Then, rous'd at once,</L>
<L>As if some Inspiration touch'd his Soul,</L>
<L>His Bosom heav'd, he rais'd his Eyes to Heav'n,</L>
<L>Then burst in Tears, and whilst he wept he drove</L>
<L><PB N="67" REF="73"/>The Poiniard to her Heart, and thus, he cried,</L>
<L>Thus perish all the Enemies of <HI>Rome!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou seem'st to plead his Cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, my Brother,</L>
<L>I speak but what I saw.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where was her Father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not, but some Chance, they said, detain'd him;</L>
<L>He scarce had left the Crowd, and thought her safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scarce left the Crowd, and thought her safe?—O Gods,</L>
<L>'Twas I, 'twas I detain'd him; in that Moment</L>
<L>The horrid Deed was done.—Where are they now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope with her. She fear'd some fatal Violence,</L>
<L>And therefore beg'd me to intreat them to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>And have you seen them? Are they Friends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no,</L>
<L>I found them high in Wrath: The poor old Man</L>
<L>Torn with contending Passions threaten'd oft</L>
<L>Destruction on his Son, who with Disdain</L>
<L>Laid bare his Breast, and bade him strike the Blow.</L>
<L>The Patriot then took Place, and he would wish</L>
<L>He never had a Daughter. My Approach</L>
<L>Alarm'd them both; but PUBLIUS soon resum'd</L>
<L>His wonted Firmness, bade her Father go</L>
<L>And mingle Tears with hers, he would not see her,</L>
<L><PB N="68" REF="74"/>Nor dared pollute his Conquests with her Presence.</L>
<L>Hast thou no Heart, the Father cried, and look'd</L>
<L>Unutterable Sorrow; at which Sight</L>
<L>He yielded, and obey'd. I left them then</L>
<L>To seek you out.—My Brother, you regard not</L>
<L>What I have said.—You hear me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>VALERIA,</L>
<L>Revenge is busy here. Yes, thou proud Chief,</L>
<L>In spite of all the Glories which surround thee,</L>
<L>I yet may crush thy Pride!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will not kill him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kill him, VALERIA!—'Tis no common Death</L>
<L>Which he shall die: I will have noble Vengeance.</L>
<L>The Thought delights my Soul!
<STAGE><HI>Going.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What Thought, my Brother?</L>
<L>Nay tell me, or you go not.—Stay at least</L>
<L>'Till you hear more.—I feel HORATIA'S Wrongs</L>
<L>As strong as you.—
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> VALERIUS.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>He's gone, Tho' my Heart bleeds</L>
<L>For my poor dying Friend, I must pursue him.</L>
<L>His fatal Rashness may distress her more,</L>
<L>And bring fresh Sorrows on an aged Sire</L>
<L>Oppress'd too much already.
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI></STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<PB N="69" REF="75"/>
<HEAD>SCENE the last.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>A Room in</HI> HORATIUS<HI>'S House.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>HORATIA <HI>on a Couch, and Attendants.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease, cease your cruel Aid, ye shall not save me.</L>
<L>My utmost Wish is Death, and I will have it.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> HORATIUS <HI>and</HI> PUBLIUS.</STAGE>
<L>Yet, let me thank you for this little Life</L>
<L>Your Art prolongs, 'till I have made my Peace,</L>
<L>And ask'd Forgiveness here,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Child, my Child!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What means this Tenderness?—I thought to see you</L>
<L>Inflamed with Rage against a worthless Wretch,</L>
<L>Who has dishonour'd your illustrious Race,</L>
<L>And stain'd its brightest Fame. In Pity look not</L>
<L>Thus kindly on me. O behold me, Sir,</L>
<L>With that stern Aspect my wrong'd Brother wears,</L>
<L>And I may then support this dreadful Parting:</L>
<L>For I have injur'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou has not, Girl;</L>
<L>I said, 'twas Madness; but he would not hear me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O wrong him not, his Act was noble Justice.</L>
<L>I forc'd him to the Deed: For know, my Father,</L>
<L>It was not Madness, but the firm Result</L>
<L>Of settled Reason, and deliberate Thought.</L>
<L><PB N="70" REF="76"/>I was resolved on Death, and witness Heaven,</L>
<L>I'd not have died by any Hand but his</L>
<L>For the whole round of Fame his Worth shall boast</L>
<L>Thro' future Ages. Nought but this, my Father,</L>
<L>Could reconcile us; I forgive him now</L>
<L>The Death of CURIATIUS; this last Blow</L>
<L>Has cancell'd that, and he's once more my Brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hast thou said? Were't thou so bent on Death?</L>
<L>Was all thy Rage dissembled?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>All, my Father,</L>
<L>All but my Love was false; what that inspired</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>utter'd freely, and still hate the Cause</L>
<L>Which has undone us, tho' I know 'twas Virtue,</L>
<L>But for the rest, the Curses which I pour'd</L>
<L>On Heav'n-defended <HI>Rome,</HI> were merely Lure</L>
<L>To tempt his Rage, and perfect my Destruction.</L>
<L>Heav'n! with what Transport I beheld him mov'd,</L>
<L>How my Heart leap'd to meet the welcome Point,</L>
<L>And leave its Sorrows there!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unkind HORATIA!</L>
<L>Had'st thou no Pity on thy Father's Age?</L>
<L>Could'st thou to ease thy Griefs abandon his,</L>
<L>And leave him Childless.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Childless? gracious Powers,</L>
<L>Can he be Childless from whose happy Loins</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI>'s great Deliverer spring, and still survives</L>
<L>To bless and cherish him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="71" REF="77"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He does indeed,</L>
<L>And I'm asham'd to think how I neglect him.—</L>
<L>Forgive me, Boy; she has unman'd my Virtue.</L>
<L>Yet can I see her thus, and not remember</L>
<L>Her thousand little tender Arts, which sooth'd</L>
<L>The Cares of Age, and led me gently through</L>
<L>The Evening of my Days?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forget them, Sir,</L>
<L>They all are nothing now; this last dire Act</L>
<L>May justly shut me from your Breast for ever.</L>
<L>Turn, turn to him; there blooms the kind Support</L>
<L>Of your remaining Life. What tho' he bends</L>
<L>His stern Regards on me, who have deserv'd them?</L>
<L>He is by Nature gentle, mild, and loving,</L>
<L>Will greatly pity your deserted State,</L>
<L>And pay a double Duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore then</L>
<L>Would'st thou provoke his Rage, and make me look</L>
<L>With Horror on him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis on me, not him,</L>
<L>That thou should'st look with Horror; 'twas my Act,</L>
<L>Not his.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>O foolish Nature, how it struggles here</L>
<L>Against the force of Reason!—Save me, Boy,</L>
<L>From the dire Conflict: when I look this way,
<STAGE><HI>To his Son.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>'Tis Reason's Triumph; Justice sanctifies</L>
<L>Paternal Love, and Glory crowns the whole.</L>
<L><PB N="72" REF="78"/>But when I turn to her, I feel my Strength</L>
<L>Again relapse, and scarce can bless the Hand</L>
<L>Which sav'd my Country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, there's nought remains,</L>
<L>But thus to rid you of the only Clog,
<STAGE><HI>Tearing off her Bandages.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Which keeps Affection from its proper Sphere,</L>
<L>And shackles Coward Virtue.—But forgive me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Sister, stay; I charge thee live, HORATIA.</L>
<L>O thou hast planted Daggers here!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Brother!</L>
<L>Can you forgive me too? then I am happy.</L>
<L>I dared not hope for that. Ye gentle Ghosts</L>
<L>That rove Elysium, hear the sacred Sound!</L>
<L>My Father and my Brother both forgive me!</L>
<L>I have again their Sanction on my Love.</L>
<L>O let me hasten to those happier Climes</L>
<L>Where unmolested we may share our Joys,</L>
<L>Nor <HI>Rome,</HI> nor <HI>Alba,</HI> shall disturb us more!</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> VALERIA.
<STAGE><HI>In a Fright.</HI></STAGE></STAGE>
<L>O Sir, O my HORATIA—yet thou livest,</L>
<L>And may'st recover all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What mean you, Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>All <HI>Rome,</HI> my Lord, has ta'en th' Alarm, and Crowds</L>
<L>Of Citizens enrag'd are posting hither</L>
<L>To call for Justice on HORATIUS' Head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="73" REF="79"/>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>For thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Heavens! why Numbers of them</L>
<L>Beheld his Provocation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>True they did;</L>
<L>But my unhappy Brother—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas he loved HORATIA, and her Loss</L>
<L>Has urg'd him to this Frenzy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of him?</L>
<L>Does he arraign my Son?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>He leads the Crowd,</L>
<L>And, as he pleases, sways their giddy Minds:</L>
<L>Paints the dire Tale in all its Pomp of Sadness,</L>
<L>And wakes Compassion by each varied Art</L>
<L>Of winning Eloquence. Around the King</L>
<L>They press in thousands; his Authority,</L>
<L>Tho' aided with strict Promises of Justice,</L>
<L>Can scarcely calm their agitated Minds.</L>
<L>—But she shall live, and all be well again.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Turning tenderly toward</HI> HORATIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O no, it cannot be—detested Parricide!</L>
<L>Could'st thou not die without the added Guilt</L>
<L>Of murdering all thy Race?—O Sir—O Brother!</L>
<L><PB N="74" REF="80"/>Can ye behold me now, and not recall</L>
<L>Your kind Forgiveness?—Can ye—will ye?—Speak!</L>
<L>—But do not curse me, Sir!</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>—Yet why, my Father,</L>
<L>Why stand you thus amaz'd? The Laws are yours;</L>
<L>What Right can they pretend, ungrateful Men?</L>
<L>Has not a <HI>Roman</HI> Father Power to take</L>
<L>The Lives of all his Children?—He but acted</L>
<L>By your Command—O take the Deed on you!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Sister stay, and you, my Father, hear me.</L>
<L>I'll end this Strife, and die since they require it.</L>
<L>Heaven knows how willingly!</L>
<L>But let not Ignominy stain my Wreaths,</L>
<L>Let me not fall a public Spectacle</L>
<L>Dragg'd like a Criminal to Justice. No,</L>
<L>My Father, save me from that dreadful Scene,</L>
<L>Assume the generous Right the Laws allow you,</L>
<L>And take this forfeit Life with Honour from me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Offering him his Sword.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, and it shall be so. Yes, yes, my Children,</L>
<L>We'll die together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA. <HI>[Rising from the Couch.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>O forbear, forbear!—</L>
<L>Was this Pang wanting to compleat my Fate!</L>
<L>In Pity to yourselves, to the dear Honour</L>
<L>Of your unspotted Names!—O blind old Man</L>
<L>Darest thou lift up thy sacrilegious Hand</L>
<L>Against the Chief, the God that saved thy Country.</L>
<STAGE><HI>A Noise without.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Alas they're here—help me, I die—O now</L>
<L>My Father, now exert thy utmost Force</L>
<L><PB N="75" REF="81"/>With them, and shew thyself indeed a <HI>Roman;</HI></L>
<L>Not with thy Sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1st CITIZEN. <HI>[Without.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We must not be denied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2d CITIZEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will have Justice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>We demand HORATIUS.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I could live!—it will not be—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Daughter!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Regard not me —There, there employ thy Power.</L>
<L>'Tis my last Prayer—VALERIA, I adjure thee</L>
<L>By the just Gods, proclaim him innocent—</L>
<L>They'll think my Father partial—O remember</L>
<L>Remember, dear VALERIA—Brother—Father!
<STAGE><HI>Dies.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's gone, she's dead!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Fate has done it's worst.</L>
<L>Where are these Citizens?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>VALERIA,</L>
<L>PUBLIUS, look there—look yonder—what a Sight!</L>
<L>Is it for this we wish for Length of Days!—</L>
<L>O my poor bleeding Boys, how much I envy</L>
<L>Your happier Lot!
<STAGE><HI>Noise without.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> TULLUS, VALERIUS, <HI>and</HI> CITIZENS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>See! Fellow Citizens, see where she lies</L>
<L>The bleeding Victim—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="76" REF="82"/>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stop, unmanner'd Youth!</L>
<L>Think'st thou we know not wherefore we are here?—</L>
<L>Seest thou yon drooping Sire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS. <HI>[Turning hastily towards them.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Permit them, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can he mean? Some other time, HORATIUS.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no, this Instant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1st CITIZEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>He seems eager for it.</L>
<L>He sides with us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, be it so. I know not</L>
<L>What he intends; but if he meets my Wishes,</L>
<L>His strong unlabour'd Eloquence of Grief</L>
<L>May move them more than Reason's subtlest Force.</L>
<L>What would ye, <HI>Romans?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are come, dread Sir,</L>
<L>In the behalf of murdered Innocence</L>
<L>Murdered by him, the Man—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose conquering Arm</L>
<L>Has saved you all from Ruin. O Shame, Shame!</L>
<L>Has <HI>Rome</HI> no Gratitude? Do ye not blush</L>
<L>To think whom your insatiate Rage pursues?</L>
<L>Down, down, and worship him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1st CITIZEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does he plead for him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="77" REF="83"/>
<SPEAKER>2d CITIZEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does he forgive his Daughter's Death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He does.</L>
<L>And glories in it, glories in the Thought</L>
<L>That there's one <HI>Roman</HI> left who dares be grateful.</L>
<L>If you are wrong'd, then what am I? Must I</L>
<L>Be taught my Duty by th' affected Tears</L>
<L>Of Strangers to my Blood? Had I been wrong'd</L>
<L>I know a Father's Right, and had not ask'd</L>
<L>This ready talking Sir to bellow for me,</L>
<L>And mouth my Wrongs in <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Friends, Countrymen,</L>
<L>Regard him not, his Griefs have hurt his Reason.</L>
<L>'Tis true that PUBLIUS has preserv'd his Country;</L>
<L>But must one glorious Act exalt him quite</L>
<L>Beyond all Laws, and give a boundless Scope</L>
<L>To his o'erweening Cruelty? ere long</L>
<L>He'll claim a privilege to murder all</L>
<L>Who dare oppose his Will; and when his Sword</L>
<L>Has spread with mangled Carcases your Streets,</L>
<L>He'll tell you 'twas that Sword which saved his Country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Injurious Youth: That Sword which saved his Country</L>
<L>Was never drawn but in his Country's Service.</L>
<L>Some of you must remember, you I'm sure</L>
<L>SERVILIUS you were there, and must remember</L>
<L>With what dire Curses this unhappy Girl—</L>
<L>I will not call her mine—pursu'd us all,</L>
<L>And dar'd insult the Majesty of <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="78" REF="84"/>
<SPEAKER>1st CITIZEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes we all remember.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas for that,</L>
<L>For that he kill'd her; 'twas not him she injur'd,</L>
<L>'Twas in your Cause he kill'd her, not his own;</L>
<L>And must he die for that? if 'tis a Crime</L>
<L>To vindicate your Honour, he indeed</L>
<L>Has been most guilty; 'twas for that he Fought,</L>
<L>For that he kill'd his Friends the <HI>Curiatii;</HI></L>
<L>If that's a Crime, O let him die for that,</L>
<L>Not for his Justice on a guilty Girl,</L>
<L>And he shall fall contented.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Guilty Girl?</L>
<L>How guilty? Madness has a Privilege</L>
<L>To talk unpunish'd, and was ne'er till now</L>
<L>Arraign'd severely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mad? She was not mad;</L>
<L>Believe me, Friends, she own'd it ere she died,</L>
<L>Confess'd she did it to provoke his Vengeance</L>
<L>Deliberately guilty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Citizens,</L>
<L>Friends, Countrymen, regard not what he says.</L>
<L>Stop, stop your Ears, nor hear a frantic Father</L>
<L>Thus plead against his Child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He does belie me,</L>
<L>What Child have I?—Alas, I have but One,</L>
<L>And him ye would tear from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All CITIZENS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hear him, hear him!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="79" REF="85"/>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, let me speak. Think'st thou, ungenerous Youth,</L>
<L>To hurt my Quiet?—I am hurt beyond</L>
<L>Thy Power to harm me. Death's extremest Tortures</L>
<L>Were Happiness to what I feel.—Yet know</L>
<L>My injur'd Honour bids me live, nay more,</L>
<L>It bids me even descend to plead for Life.</L>
<L>—But wherefore waste I Words. 'Tis not to him</L>
<L>But you, my Countrymen, to you I speak,</L>
<L>He lov'd the Maid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CITIZENS.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, loved her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fondly loved her,</L>
<L>And under Show of public Justice screens</L>
<L>A private Passion, and a mean Revenge.</L>
<STAGE>VALERIUS <HI>seems confounded and goes to his Sister.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Think ye I loved her not? high Heaven's my Witness</L>
<L>How tenderly I loved her, and the Pangs</L>
<L>I feel this Moment, could you see my Heart,</L>
<L>Would prove too plainly I am still her Father.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>You'll say I love him too. I glory in it.</L>
<L>But 'tis not for myself, my Dregs of Life</L>
<L>Will soon be spent, 'tis for my Country's Service</L>
<L>I would preserve her Champion. 'Tis not me</L>
<L>Whom you should pity, 'tis yourselves, your Wives,</L>
<L>Your tender little Ones;—for most of you</L>
<L>Are Fathers too.—O think, the Time may come,</L>
<L>When you again shall want his Sword, and find</L>
<L>Perhaps an hostile Ear as deaf to Mercy</L>
<L>As I have found—But I forget myself,</L>
<L>You are all <HI>Romans,</HI> and what you decree</L>
<L>However hard is just.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="80" REF="86"/>
<SPEAKER>1st CITIZEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall be saved.</L>
<L>VALERIUS has misled us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save him, save him!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank you, Friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VALERIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What mean ye, would ye save</L>
<L>A Murderer from Death?—I'll not be held,
<STAGE><HI>To his Sister.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>It was no Crime to love her, I will speak.</L>
<L>—If Justice moves you not, yet dread th' Event.</L>
<L>Fear ye not Heaven and the avenging Gods</L>
<L>Who gave him up to Shame, and urg'd him on</L>
<L>To stain his Conquests with a Sister's Blood.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, away; is he the first whose Arm</L>
<L>Was stained with Kindred Blood? and dar'st thou talk</L>
<L>In <HI>Rome</HI> thus idly? What's our Founder then,</L>
<L>If he's a Murderer? Heaven approved the Death</L>
<L>Of <HI>Remus,</HI> as deliberate as this.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, enough!</L>
<L>With Reverence speak we of those mighty Names</L>
<L>Which stand enroll'd above. All Acts of Blood</L>
<L>Must not be deem'd as Murders. 'Tis the Intent</L>
<L>And not the Action constitutes the Crime.</L>
<L>My Friends, and Fellow Citizens, I praise</L>
<L>That Zeal for Justice in you, which permits not</L>
<L>The Blaze of Fame, or Gratitude itself</L>
<L><PB N="81" REF="87"/>For Actions which might move inferior Minds,</L>
<L>To blind or weaken its determin'd Force.</L>
<L>Tho' here perchance it err. Behold this Youth</L>
<L>So late your Glory, with what conscious Shame</L>
<L>He sees himself reduced for one rash Act,</L>
<L>The Crime of Virtue, to solicit here</L>
<L>A Life which he contemns. He loved the Maid</L>
<L>With a fond Brother's Love; and had he felt</L>
<L>No nobler Passion, she had still survived.</L>
<L>That other Passion was his Love of you.</L>
<L>Say, shall he die for that? For 'tis to you</L>
<L>He makes his last Appeal.</L>
<L>Or grant it were a Crime, the worst of Crimes,</L>
<L>You might with Ardor seize the happy Power</L>
<L>Which Fortune now allows you. Could you else</L>
<L>Have rais'd your Gratitude to his Desert?</L>
<L>Fate seems to have found out this only Means</L>
<L>By which you could reward him. Life for Life</L>
<L>You may return him now, for Freedom, Freedom.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1st CITIZEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>We did declare him free, but this VALERIUS</L>
<L>Would interrupt our Will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2d CITIZEN.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> glories in him!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or turn this Way, if yet a Doubt remains.</L>
<L>Behold that virtuous Father, who could boast</L>
<L>This very Morn a numerous Progeny,</L>
<L>The dear Supports of his declining Age.</L>
<L>Then read the sad Reverse with pitying Eyes,</L>
<L>And tell your conscious Hearts they fell for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="82" REF="88"/>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am o'erpaid by that, nor claim I ought</L>
<L>On their Accounts; for by high Heaven I swear</L>
<L>I'd rather see him added to the Heap</L>
<L>Than <HI>Rome</HI> enslaved.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1st CITIZEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>O excellent HORATIUS.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2d CITIZEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>O worthy Father!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3d CITIZEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were he ten Times guilty,</L>
<L>The Son of such a Sire might pass unpunish'd,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I pronounce him free. And now, HORATIUS,</L>
<L>The Evening of thy stormy Day at last</L>
<L>Shall close in Peace. Here, take him to thy Breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HORATIUS.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Son, my Conqueror!—'Twas a fatal Stroke,</L>
<L>But shall not wound our Peace. This kind Embrace</L>
<L>Shall spread a sweet Oblivion o'er our Sorrows:</L>
<L>Of if in After-times, tho' 'tis not long</L>
<L>That I shall trouble you, some sad Remembrance</L>
<L>Should steal a Sigh, and peevish Age forget</L>
<L>Its Resolution, only boldly say</L>
<L>Thou saved'st the State, and I'll intreat Forgiveness.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TULLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VALERIUS too must be your Friend again.</L>
<L>But that we leave to Time. The present Hour</L>
<L>Must be employ'd to expiate his Offence.</L>
<L>Be that thy Care, HORATIUS; that the Gods</L>
<L>May bless To-morrow's Rites, and gracious hear</L>
<L>Our Hymns of Praise for Liberty restor'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="83" REF="89"/>
<L>Learn hence, ye <HI>Romans,</HI> on how sure a Base</L>
<L>The Patriot builds his Happiness; no Stroke,</L>
<L>No keenest, deadliest, Shaft of adverse Fate</L>
<L>Can make his generous Bosom quite despair,</L>
<L>But that alone by which his Country falls.</L>
<L>Grief may to Grief in endless Round succeed,</L>
<L>And Nature suffer when our Children bleed:</L>
<L>Yet still superior must that Hero prove,</L>
<L>Whose first, best Passion is his COUNTRY's LOVE.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<HEAD>EPILOGUE, spoken by Mrs. <HI>Pritchard.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>LADIES, by me our courteous Author sends</L>
<L>His Compliments to all his Female Friends:</L>
<L>And thanks them from his Soul for every bright</L>
<L>Indulgent Tear, which they have shed To-night.</L>
<L>Sorrow in Virtue's Cause proclaims a <HI>MIND,</HI></L>
<L>And gives to Beauty Graces more refin'd.</L>
<L>O who could bear the loveliest Form of Art,</L>
<L>A Cherub's Face, without a feeling Heart!</L>
<L>'Tis there alone, whatever Charms we boast,</L>
<L>Tho' Men may flatter, and tho' Men will toast,</L>
<L>'Tis there alone they find the Joy sincere,</L>
<L>The Wife, the Parent, and the Friend are there.</L>
<L>All else, the veriest Rakes themselves must own,</L>
<L>Are but the paltry Play-things of the Town;</L>
<L><PB N="84" REF="90"/>The painted Clouds, which glittering tempt the Chace,</L>
<L>Then melt in Air, and mock the vain Embrace.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Well then; the private Virtues, 'tis confest,</L>
<L>Are the soft Inmates of the Female Breast.</L>
<L>But then, they fill so full that crouded Space,</L>
<L>That the p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or Public seldom finds a Place.</L>
<L>And I suspect there's many a Fair-one here,</L>
<L>Who pour'd her Sorrows on <HI>HORATIA</HI>'S Bier,</L>
<L>That still retains so much of Flesh and Blood,</L>
<L>She'd fairly hang the Brother, if she could.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Why, Ladies, to be sure, if that be all,</L>
<L>At your Tribunal he must stand or fall.</L>
<L>Whate'er his Country, or his Sire decreed,</L>
<L>You are his Judges now, and he must plead.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Like other Culprit Youths, he wanted Grace;</L>
<L>But could have no Self-interest in the Case.</L>
<L>Had she been Wife, or Mistress, or a Friend,</L>
<L>It might have answered some convenient End:</L>
<L>But a mere Sister, whom he lov'd—to take</L>
<L>Her Life away,—and for his Country's Sake!</L>
<L>Faith, Ladies, you may pardon him; indeed</L>
<L>There's very little Fear the Crime should spread.</L>
<L>True Patriots are but rare among the Men,</L>
<L>And really might be useful, now and then.</L>
<L>Then do not check, by your Disapprobation,</L>
<L>A Spirit which once rul'd the <HI>British</HI> Nation,</L>
<L>And still might rule—would you but set the Fashion.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER><HI>The END.</HI></TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>
