<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet TYPE="text/css" href="http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE><DATE>yyyy-mm-dd</DATE><RESPSTMT><NAME>[name of reviewer]</NAME><RESP>MURP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM></CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>

<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K030930.000">
<STC T="C">T022235</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3316563715</BIBNO>
<VID SET="ECLL">1135502100</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1>
<P><PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
APOLOGY FOR THE MINOR.</P>
<P>IN A LETTER TO The Rev. Mr BAINE.</P>
<P>To which is added, The ORIGINAL EPILOGUE.</P>
<P>By SAMUEL FOOTE, Es{que}</P>
<P>EDINBURGH: Printed for J. WOOD; and sold by him at his Shop below the Tron Church.</P>
<P>MDCCLXXI.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1>
<P><PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
Entered in Stationer's-Hall, according to Act of Parliament; and whoever reprints the same will be prosecuted according to Law.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>TO The REV. MR BAIN.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>REVEREND SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>I HAVE not troubled the public with a∣ny reply to the Sermon you addressed to me; not, as you fondly imagine, because your arguments were unanswerable, but because I really did not think they deserved an answer.</P>
<P>The utility of the MINOR has been felt and acknowledged by all orders and degrees of men in the country where it was first produced, with an exception indeed to those subjects who were unhappily tainted with the principles that dra∣matic piece was intended to combat. To reason with those who professedly give up the use and exercise of their reason, would be <HI>non aliter quam si des operam ut cum ratione insanires.</HI></P>
<P>Had you, Sir, enjoyed your supposed supe∣riority
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
in silence, or been satisfied with the pri∣vate congratulatory bleatings of the unfortunate flock you fodder, I should not have made a single attempt to sully your triumph: but as you have thought fit, in the public papers, to celebrate, with a degree of wanton insolence, not very consistent with the pretended piety of your principles, and the humility of your pro∣fession, a victory, which, like the great Tom Thumb, you have attained, not by vanquish∣ing your foes, but in finding no foes to van∣quish; it becomes necessary to let you see, that, with the town of Geneva, you owe your strength to your weakness; and that you have been hi∣therto spared, not from the want of arms or courage, but from a real principle of com∣passion.</P>
<P>The greater part of your Sermon, consist∣ing of self-evident principles, sustained by hack∣neyed quotations, badly arranged and ill ex∣pressed, I shall give you all the credit that the communication of such tritical truths deserves.</P>
<P>In the conclusion, indeed, or your precious morsel of eloquence, you make an application of these principles to the Comedy in question; but as all you say there, has been said before, and much better, I take the liberty of submit∣ting to the public the <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Wrote by the Rev. Mr. M—d—n.</NOTE> Objections originally made to the MINOR, by one of the sounders of the methodistical sect, with my answers; both
<PB N="5" REF="5"/>
which were published immediately after the first exhibition of the MINOR.</P>
<P>As the pamphlets themselves are too bulky for the room of a letter, I have satisfied myself with an extract, which contains the substance of each; and, for the more distinctness, shall state the Objections as they occur, with my Answers to each immediately following.</P>
<P>The Objections have for title: <Q>“CHRISTIAN and CRITICAL Remarks on a <HI>Droll</HI> or <HI>Inter∣lude,</HI> called the MINOR, <HI>said to be acted by authority.”</HI></Q></P>
<P>To this title, I give for answer, That the MINOR is not a Droll or Interlude. A Droll, if it is the same as the Interlude, was a part of the entertainment amongst the Greeks, and was performed by the chorus. In our theatres it is the dance, and at Tottenham-Court it is the ballad, or musical entertainment, which fills up the space between the different parts of the performance: but a Droll is generally supposed to be a kind of theatrical, not a dra∣matic entertainment, distinguished by the name of <HI>Farce,</HI> and is a sort of hodge-podge, where the mangled limbs of probability, common sense, and decency, are served up to gratify the voracious cravings of the most depraved ap∣petites. But a Comedy is an exact representa∣tion of the peculiar manners of that people a∣mong whom it happens to be performed; a faithful imitation of absurdities and follies,
<PB N="6" REF="6"/>
made for the correction of individuals, and an example to the community: so that it is not the extent, but the object of the piece, that deter∣mines the title. A poem of one act may be an excellent comedy, and a play of five a most ex∣ecrable farce; and I hope, that the characters in the MINOR are not strained above the mo∣desty of nature, nor their employment unsuit∣able to their rank, or inconsistent with their situation.</P>
<P><HI>Observ.]</HI> Mr Foote has shot a bow's length beyond any of his competitors, in debauching, if possible, and debasing the stage; by doing that which nobody else in these kingdoms ever had the confidence to attempt; by the intro∣duction of real and living characters into his pieces. That this was the original method of comedy nobody can deny; but the sensible A∣thenians found the ill consequence of it. So∣crates, that divine philosopher, (if we may call him divine, who was almost a heathen through the unhappy prejudice of education), was al∣lowed to be the first man for wisdom and vir∣tue, not only in Greece, famous for great men; but in the whole world: yet this man, when he was in his highest reputation, when the prin∣cipal youth of Athens were under his tuition; and his advice was taken in the most important and difficult affairs; this very man, at this very time, could not with all his glory get the better of the ridicule of Aristophanes; who, in a co∣medy called <HI>the Clouds,</HI> made a jest of him with such success, that though the people of Athens
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
idolized Socrates next to their gods, they run after this burlesque foppery night after night; and some of the best writers have dated the fall of the greatest pagan philosopher that ever lived, from the first exhibition of this contemp∣tible farce, which, however it might appear in acting, is such a poor piece of writing, that it is very little superior to the MINOR.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.]</HI> In this charge you are, Sir, at once erroneous and unjust: You err in your notions of the nature of the ancient comedy, and are unjust in attributing its revival to me, when, at the same time, that honour is solely due to the reverend gentleman whose advocate you are. But for the better determining this question, let us consider where the specific difference lyes, between the ancient, middle, and modern co∣medy.</P>
<P>The ancient comedy was a representation of real persons and facts; in the middle comedy, the persons were real, and the facts feigned; in the modern, both the persons and the facts were fictitious. Now, Sir, though in the MINOR you may call some of the characters real, yet you must, at least, allow the fable to be an in∣vention; that piece, therefore, wants just half its construction to be ranked in the order of an∣cient comedies. But let us, on the other hand, consider the claims of your Hero for a niche near Thespis in the temple of Apollo; and for this purpose we will examine one of his pieces, at which I was a spectator. The piece is pretty
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
well known, and after the manner of Aristo∣phanes and Plautus we will distinguish it from the principal incident, by the name of <HI>Mutton,</HI> a comedy <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">See the Epilogue to the MINOR, annexed.</NOTE>. As an introduction to this enter∣tainment, we were told by the chorus or pro∣logue, that the persons were then living, that the dialogue really happened between them, and that the catastrophe of the leg of mutton and turnips, was a literal fact. In this composition you fee, Sir, we have at once every member of the ancient comedy. The method of declaim∣ing or conveying it, too, was precisely after the Greek in recitative; and tho' we had not the accompaniment of the <HI>tibiae dextrae</HI> and <HI>sini∣strae,</HI> yet a melodious nasal twang, produced by an orchestra of old women, who surrounded the actor, amply supplied that deficiency. To this when I add, that, after the manner of Thespis, the piece was exhibited in a cart upon a common, not a single doubt can, I think, remain. <HI>Dicitur et plaustris vexisse poemata Thespis.</HI> Perhaps the critics may object to the divine machinery of this piece, as believing the leg of mutton might have been produced with propriety enough by natural means. <HI>Nec Deus intersit nisi dignus vindice nodus.</HI> But as the mo∣del of the mutton was produced previous to the existence of Aristotle or Horace, it would be ab∣surd, in a professed imitator of that model, to be directed by their rules. From this disquisition, then, Sir, and the earnest inclination your reve∣rend friend always shows to display his abilities in a
<PB N="9" REF="9"/>
cart, even though it be with a criminal to Ty∣burn, I think we may venture, without any impeachment of our understanding, to pro∣nounce him the real restorer of the ancient Thespian cart-comedy.</P>
<P>You affirm, with an intrepidity which, con∣sidering your ignorance in dramatic produc∣tions, is a little astonishing, that Mr Foote, amongst the moderns, is the only man who has produced real characters upon the stage.—What think you of a countryman of ours, one Shakespeare? In travelling through his page, did you never meet with a boorish, illiterate, trifling, tedious country Justice called <HI>Shallow?</HI> Have you never heard that this man's real name was <HI>Lucy?</HI> and that his inflexible severity to our author, for a venial slip in his youth, pro∣cured him a seat in the temple of folly, con∣demned to everlasting fame?</P>
<P>Your next anathema is thundered out against one Aristophanes, a certain Greek comic poet, whose disciple you pronounce me to be; and to the unbounded licence of whose execrable farces, produced and fostered by the corruption and depravity of the age, the untimely death of Socrates was owing. As to any resemblance you think you may have discovered between my little piece and the works of that great ma∣ster, I am too much flattered with the compa∣rison to think of pointing out your mistake; I leave that task to my enemies: But from what quarter did you collect the rest of your mate∣rials?
<PB N="10" REF="10"/>
you must have either lost your historical knowledge, or have suck'd from some muddy gutter the impure stream with which you pol∣lute the brightest period the world ever saw. This was the aera when the Attic genius tri∣umphed; when its liberty was pure and virtu∣ous; when a citizen could have gone from a conference with Socrates, to an oration from Demosthenes, and have closed his evening with the Electra of Sophocles, the Phaedra of Euri∣pides, the moral scenes of Menander, or the sprightly comic muse of Aristophanes. Then flourished Plato, Xenophon, Aristotle, Isocrates, Thu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ydides, and Eschylus, men born to en∣lighten the human mind, and diffuse the glory of their country to latest posterity. No, Sir, the sacrifice of Socrates was reserved for the age of bigotry and abject slavery, when Ly∣sander had changed the constitution of Athens, from a Democracy to an Aristocracy, when the thirty rulers had established an absolute ty∣ranny. The <HI>Clouds</HI> was exhibited in the eighth year of the Peloponnesian war, at least twenty-six years before the death of Socrates. Could a little slight harmless raillery, at what, per∣haps, were soibles in the character of that great man, have excited such an inflammation in the minds of the multitude? it must have been at the time when Socrates was upon the spot, in the very theatre where he had been drawn, to make a discovery of his own imperfections, with a declared resolution to amend them. But the real truth is, Sir, Socrates fell for the very fact which you charge as a crime upon
<PB N="11" REF="11"/>
Aristophanes; for his free, spirited, and per∣sonal invectives against Critias, one of the thir∣ty rulers. The resentment of that tyrant, joined by the hatred the public bore Socrates, for ha∣ving been the instructor, the preceptor of that very Critias, were the unhappy, only instru∣ments, that, before his time, closed the eyes of that first of philosophers, whose not being a Christian I do not, like you, impute to the vice of his education; for let that have been as it would, there seems to be an almost insuperable obstacle to his ever joining in one communion with us, viz. that he died in the 95th olym∣piad, just 399 years before Christ was born.</P>
<P><HI>Rem.]</HI> Whether the paultry reflection cast upon a preacher of God's word, in the name of <HI>Squintum,</HI> be equitable, I leave to the world; nay, even to Mr Foote himself: for if the ac∣cidental unhappiness of a provincial dialect is not a proper subject for ridicule, how much less are the errors of nature in matters of bo∣dily defect?</P>
<P><HI>Ans.]</HI> Provincial dialects are not the proper objects of comedy; <HI>and if not dialects,</HI> surely much less natural infirmities. Granted.</P>
<P>But if men, with these infirmities, will attempt things which those very infirmities have render∣ed them incapable of properly executing, it is their own fault, if the source that should ac∣quire them compassion, degenerates into a foun∣tain of ridicule. My Lord Lanesborough's gout
<PB N="12" REF="12"/>
would have hardly found a place in Mr Pope's page, if it had not hobbled a minuet at court; nor should Mr <HI>Squintum</HI> have shown the whites of his eyes at the Hay-market, if he had con∣fined his circumspection to the tap-room of the Bell at Gloucester; or, after his admission to the ministry, modestly submitted to the decent duties of a country cure: but if, in despite of art and nature, not content with depreciating every individual of his own order; with a coun∣tenance, not only inexpressive, but ludicrous; a dialect, not only provincial, but barbarous; a deportment, not only aukward, but savage; he will produce himself to the whole public, and there deliver doctrines equally heretical and absurd, in a language at once inelegant and ungrammatical, he must expect to have his pre∣tensions to oratory derided, his sincerity su∣spected, and the truth of his mission denied.</P>
<P><HI>Observ]</HI> I do not rightly know what is meant by enthusiasm: if people mean by enthusiasm, that the Methodists pretend to the extraordi∣nary operation of working miracles, or speaking with tongues, they are no enthusiasts, for they never laid claim to any such thing. But if they only mean, that enthusiasm is a strong persua∣sion of the mind, that we are guided in an ex∣traordinary manner by immediate impulses and impressions of the spirit of God; then, perhaps, they may not injure them.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.]</HI> Are you really puzzled for the precise meaning of the word Enthusiasm? Why, then,
<PB N="13" REF="13"/>
I will give it to you; but take this by the way, that the term was never applied by me to the leader of the Methodists, but to his deluded disciples only; for the very essence of an enthu∣siast is, that though mistaken, he is sincere; though erroneous, he is in earnest.</P>
<P>Enthusiasm, in divinity, is a kind of a reli∣gious phrensy, that mistakes the dictates of an inflamed imagination, the vapours of a troubled brain, for the operation of a divine possession, the effects of an immediate inspiration: nor is it material, that the enthusiast should think himself the person inspired; if his distempered judgment bestows the same attribute on any other individual, his delusion is the same.</P>
<P><HI>Observ.]</HI> The stage is of Pagan origin.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.]</HI> So is sculpture, painting, and not only all the elegant, but most of the useful arts.</P>
<P><HI>Observ.]</HI> The stage was invented for the ho∣nour and worship of daemons.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.]</HI> If by their daemons you mean as they did their gods, you are right enough.</P>
<P>And where could they better employ it? To these people you would surely permit some re∣ligious worship; but you will insist that they ought all to have been Christians; though dead before Christ came into the world.</P>
<P><PB N="14" REF="14"/>
<HI>Observ.]</HI> Pagans, who had no regard to virtue, abominated theatres, as seminaries of vice.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.]</HI> Who were these Pagans? And when and where did they live?</P>
<P><HI>Observ.]</HI> The diversions of the stage, though at first encouraged, were afterwards discounte∣nanced by the Greeks and Romans.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.]</HI> Just the contrary is true; and plays were in such estimation in Greece, that the ex∣hibition of the tragedies of Sophocles alone, cost the Athenian state more than the whole Peloponnesian war; and the profession of the stage was at that time so far from contemptible, that even their ambassadors were selected from the body of the players. They were not indeed in equal repute at Rome, for the same reason, that in the decline of the empire, the practice of the bar fell into disgrace, because the pro∣fessors of both became mercenaries: but still the dramatic authors had a Scipio, a Laelius, a Maecenas, an Augustus, for their patrons; and to sum up all these names in one, the actors had a Cicero for their friend. The Romans were so far from ever discountenancing dra∣matic performances, that one of the fathers you have quoted, St Augustine, observes, that 436 years after Christ, the theatres began to be closed in the great towns of Italy, owing to the incursions of the Goths and Vandals, <HI>Nisi forte hinc sine tempora mala quia per omnes civitates cadunt theatra.</HI> And Cassiodorus, who wrote
<PB N="15" REF="15"/>
in 520, almost a hundred years after St Austin, mentions, in several of his letters, that the theatres were still open at Rome; so that; in all probability, the playhouses were not totally shut till the sack of Rome by Totila; then, indeed, when the wives and children of the Patricians were compelled to beg their bread at the doors of their own palaces, plays, players, arts, sciences, and even the Roman name, sunk in one universal ruin.</P>
<P>In conjunction with Collier, and the other virulent declaimers against the stage, you seem to lay infinite stress on the authorities of those fathers who have condemned it, without once considering where they lived, and when they wrote. Clemens wrote in 192, Chrysostom in 354, St Augustin in 436, all of them in Italy, when their followers were few, and those too newly converted. Feasts, instituted in honour of the Heathen gods, were undoubtedly not only very indecent, but very dangerous sights for Christian converts; they might have revi∣ved an affection for their ancient rites. But what is all this to us? we have not the same danger to apprehend. I never heard that Mr Garrick sacrificed to Pan, or Mr Rich danced a jigg in honour of Cybele. The prohibition of the Roman theatres to the primitive Chri∣stians, has no more relation to our playhouses, than to a horse-race at Barnet, or a ball upon my Lord Mayor's day.</P>
<P><PB N="16" REF="16"/>
<HI>Observ.]</HI> Mr <HI>Squintum</HI> has preached chastity, justice, and honesty; temperance, sobriety, and loyalty; and that with such success, that if there should be a rebellion in England to-morrow, which God of his infinite mercy forbid, he does not doubt but that twenty thousand of his flock, fraught with these principles, would rise with one hand and one heart, to repel the invaders of their king and country.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.]</HI> You seem to think, Sir, that the loyal∣ty of your favourite pastor should screen his ignorance, and shelter his imposition. I did not, indeed, at first conceive, of what conse∣quence to the public your friend's political creed would be, till you yourself have given me a most alarming reason. Twenty thousand men are, it seems, ready to take the field, whenever their spiritual guide shall give the word of command I am very sorry, Sir, that any such power should be lodged in other hands, than where the constitution has thought proper to place it, but more especially in <HI>such</HI> hands. The Asiatic impostor subjugated almost all the East, with less than half that number of men; but, as I suppose this declaration will be canvassed in another place, and, if true, its consequences properly guarded against, I shall refer it to their consideration, to whom it more immediately belongs. But pray, Sir, who a∣mongst you are the Antinomians? Are the doctrines of that sect the tenets of the taber∣nacle? In vain are human laws instituted to guard the lives and properties of individuals,
<PB N="17" REF="17"/>
if a religion be tolerated which makes it a merit to deprive them of both. The greater crime you commit, the greater glory you give to God; the virtue of the blood of Christ being render∣ed meritorious in proportion to the greatness of the offence it is to expia<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e. This very opi∣nion I received, as the found sense of the go∣spel, in the village I now write from.</P>
<P><HI>Observ.]</HI> What wealth has Mr <HI>Squintum</HI> a∣massed?</P>
<P><HI>Ans.]</HI> He is, I believe, too cunning to let any body into that secret: but from your com∣putation of males fit to carry arms, who are listed in his service, and the price they are well known to pay for admittance, even into the gallery of his theatre, I should suppose his an∣nual income must double that of the Primate's. To this may be added private benefactions, and occasional contributions. The proportion of this that he allows to the poor, who, but him∣self, can discover? Some specious ostentatious acts of it (for it is a prostitution of the word to call it Charity) are the mere tricks of his trade, the baits, the springes.</P>
<P><HI>Observ.]</HI> Foote, in his MINOR, has put ex∣pressions into the mouth of Mrs Cole, a bawd, fit only to be uttered by the devil.</P>
<P><HI>Ans.]</HI> Why, they do come from the mouth of a being very little better than the devil; but
<PB N="18" REF="18"/>
for those she or her teachers are answerable, not your humble servant; these are <HI>her</HI> words, not <HI>mine.</HI> Would you have a mirror reflect beauty from deformity? I do my duty, if the copy is a faithful transcript of the original; and of that the public are judges. The plain points to be determined are these: Is there such a character in nature as Mrs Cole? That grant∣ed, is that character a proper object for the stage? Why, if a detection of the most consum∣mate hypocrisy, and guarding the most inno∣cent and unsuspecting part of the creation from the crafts and subtleties of the most artful and designing, be of use to society, no object so proper; but then the words, <HI>providence, rege∣neration, grace, new-birth,</HI> should they be spoken upon a theatre? why not?</P>
<P>Though the abuse of these words may (as it is intended it should) cast an odium on the character that misapplies them; yet surely no dishonour is reflected on the words themselves, or the ideas they represent. Does any man con∣demn Ben Johnson for giving his hypocritical saints, Tribulation and Ananias, the language of the scripture, though employed in a work diametrically opposite to the sense and spirit of the scripture? But to ridicule what is said in a church?—and why not▪ if what is said there deserves ridicule? Is it a crime to pick a pocket at church? Its being a church is an additional reason why a man should not have done it; but it is no argument why he should not be pu∣nished for doing it.</P>
<P><PB N="19" REF="19"/>
But if words, which are the mere arbitrary marks of things, are by any use so consecrated, as never to be produced but in a particular ser∣vice, what apology can you make for your prin∣cipal, whose conversation is an eternal prosti∣tution both of words and things? If profane∣ness consists in idly mentioning the Supreme Being, what offender must he be, that makes him a principal agent in the most trifling, common occurrences? If he is bit by fleas, he is buffeted by Satan: if he has the good for∣tune to catch them, God will subdue his ene∣mies under his feet.</P>
<P><HI>[To the</HI> REMARKS <HI>are added some Verses, which</HI> Mr Foote <HI>has thus taken notice of.]</HI></P>
<P><HI>Ans.]</HI> I shall not animadvert upon the pretty copy of verses with which you have closed your pamphlet: though, for decency's sake, if you are a minister of the church of Christ, I hope you are not impious enough to chant such compositions in your places of worship, by the way of giving glory to God. There is a place, you say, where saints shall enjoy</P>
<Q><L>Eternal rest, an active, blissful state,</L>
<L>Joy, ever new, transporting, ever great.</L></Q>
<P>I hope, Sir, in this paradise of your own manufacture, you will allow your saints, after their active rest, a sup of dry drink, and let them just take a waking nap, by way of a little
<PB N="20" REF="20"/>
fatiguing refreshment. The Climax too in your next line is extremely happy; Joys not only transporting, but great: but this is a trifle to what occurs in the progress of your poem; you there make a conveyance to your disciples of certain seats you pretend to have in the realms above, and you promise them not only a good neighbourhood of patriarchs, apostles, and martyrs, but that the Tottenham teacher him∣self shall certainly settle amongst them. This puts me in mind of what happened at a certain place, in summing up the evidence against a libeller of the revolution: <Q>“The prisoner has dared, gentlemen, to vilify even the revolu∣tion, gentlemen; a measure, gentlemen, vi∣sibly begun, conducted, and completed, by the peculiar interposition of divine Provi∣dence; and not only that, gentlemen, but confirmed by act of parliament.”</Q></P>
<P>Your two next lines, and the last I shall meddle with, are,</P>
<Q><L>In lofty strains, which angels cannot sing,</L>
<L>There saints shall praise their Priest and heavenly King.</L></Q>
<P>And why can't the angels sing the strains? What, perhaps they are of your own composing? Otherwise, we are told, that to sing praises, was one great purpose of their creation. But I for∣get, these are your own angels too; nay, it's but reasonable you should people your paradise. Fye upon you; are you not ashamed to cajole
<PB N="21" REF="21"/>
a parcel of ignorant mechanics into a belief, that by chanting such inexplicable nonsense they are performing a sacrifice of praise agree∣able to the great Author of their being!</P>
<P>It is asserted, and with truth, that at the ex∣hibition of the MINOR in this town, when Mr Foote was called upon by the public to give them the Epilogue, he apologi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed for the omis∣sion by the application of a law of Solon's to the recent death of the Tottenham-Court preacher;</P>
<Q>De mortuis nil nisi bonum.</Q>
<P>But this was rather a condescension to the ge∣neral prejudice of mankind, than to any con∣viction of the propriety of the law.</P>
<P>If the examples of bad men are to be point∣ed out as matter of caution to the rest of their fellow-creatures, it can, by the constitution of these countries, be only done after their death: for, during their lives, their characters, how∣ever infamous, are guarded by the laws against libels. And indeed, the contrary practice pre∣vailed amongst the Romans. To prove this, I need only cite their custom of appointing public orators at the funeral of their principal citizens. The orator frequently assumed the person of the deceased. A passage, which occurred at the
<PB N="22" REF="22"/>
death of an avaritious Emperor, cannot be for∣got, when a sum was voted by the Senate for his funeral. <HI>Give me,</HI> says the Monarch's re∣presentative, <HI>the money; and, if you please, throw my body into the Tyber.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="23"/>
<HEAD>THE EPILOGUE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>AND what becomes of your poor servant Shift?</L>
<L>Your father talks of lending me a lift;</L>
<L>A great man's promise when his turn is serv'd!</L>
<L>Capons on promises would soon be starv'd!</L>
<L>No, on myself alone I'll now rely;</L>
<L>Gad, I've a thriving traffic in my eye.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Near the mad mansions of Moorfields I'll bawl,</L>
<L>Friends, fathers, mothers, sisters, sons and all</L>
<L>Shut up your shops, and listen to my call.</L>
<L>With labour, toil, all second means dispense,</L>
<L>And live a rent-charge upon Providence.</L>
<L>Prick up your ears; a story now I'll tell,</L>
<L>Which once a widow and her child befell,</L>
<L>I knew the mother and her daughter well.</L>
<L>Poor, it is true, they were, but never wanted,</L>
<L>For whatsoe'er they ask'd was always granted.</L>
<L>One fatal day the matron's truth was try'd:</L>
<L>She wanted meat, and drink, and fairly cry'd.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Child.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mother, you cry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mother.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, Child! I've got no bread.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Child.</SPEAKER>
<P>What matters that? why, Providence an't dead.</P>
</SP>
<LG>
<L>With reason good this truth the child might say,</L>
<L>For there came in at noon that very day,</L>
<L>Bread, greens, potatoes, and a leg of mutton,</L>
<L>A better sure a table ne<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er was put on.</L>
<L>Ay, that might be, ye cry, with those poor souls,</L>
<L>But we ne'er had a rasher for the coals:</L>
<L><PB N="24" REF="24"/>
And d'ye deserve it? how d'ye spend your days?</L>
<L>On pastimes, prodigality, and plays.</L>
<L>Let's go see FOOTE! Ah FOOTE's a precious limb!</L>
<L>Old Nick will soon a football make of him.</L>
<L>For foremost rows in side boxes you shove:</L>
<L>Think you to meet with side-boxes above,</L>
<L>Where giggling girls and powder d'fops may sit?</L>
<L>No you will <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ll be cramm'd into the pit,</L>
<L>And crowd the house for Satan's benefit.</L>
<L>Oh! what, you snivel? Well, do so no more:</L>
<L>Drop, to attone, your money at the door,</L>
<L>And, if I please,—I'll give it to the poor.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>
