<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet TYPE="text/css" href="http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE><DATE>yyyy-mm-dd</DATE><RESPSTMT><NAME>[name of reviewer]</NAME><RESP>MURP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM></CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>

<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K035866.000">
<STC T="C">T032968</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3319817470</BIBNO>
<VID>0430600600</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE
PARALEL:
OR,
PERSECUTION
OF
PROTESTANTS
The Shortest Way to prevent the
Growth of Popery
IN
IRELAND.</P>
<P><HI>DƲBLIN:</HI>
Printed in the Year 1705.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE
QUEEN.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>MADAM,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>YOur Majesty's most Loyal, Dutiful, and always
Faithful Subjects, the Protestant Dissenters in
Ireland, could never so well demonstrate either
their profound Duty to your Person, and Regard to your
Repose, or their own most heavy Pressure of Mind under
the melancholly Consideration of being incapacitated for your
Majesty's Service by any Method, as by the Dutiful Si∣lence
and Entire Submission they have always shown to your
Government, and the Laws.</P>
<P><PB REF="3"/>
They have no more been Clamarous with their Complaints,
than disobedient in their Practice, although under the ter∣rible,
and Pardon them, <HI>Madam,</HI> if they think, undeserv'd
Mortification, of being joined with your Majesty's Capital
Enemies, the <HI>Irish</HI> Papists; and enacted against in a Bill
for the Publick Security of this Kingdom.</P>
<P>As nothing could have been more desireable to them than
to see Your Majesty's Crown and Government secur'd by an
intire suppressing Popery in this Nation, so nothing could
have been more agreeable to them than to hear of a Bill de∣pending
in your Majesty's most Honourable Privy Council,
presented by your Faithful and Dutiful Commons of <HI>Ireland,</HI>
for the more effectual Security of Your Majesty, and this
Nation, by preventing the Growth of Popery.</P>
<P>And, <HI>Madam,</HI> as it must needs be the remotest thing in
the World from their Thoughts, that they could be any way
concern'd in such a Bill, other than to reap in Common,
with the rest of your Majesty's Loyal Subjects, the Securities
and Advantages of it; so nothing could be more surprizing,
as well as afflicting, than to find themselves rank'd with those
People, whom, they presume, your Majesty is well assur'd
they have always been earnest to oppose; and at the Ex∣pence
of their Blood and Fortunes have assisted your Maje∣stys
Royal Predecessors against upon all Occasions.</P>
<P>It cannot be that your Majesty's Protestant Dissenting
Subjects of <HI>Ireland</HI> can be guilty of any thing to entitle them
to such severe Mortifications, since tho' they have the Ʋn∣happiness
to differ in some Opinions from your Majety's Sen∣timents,
and the Established Church; yet as they value
themselves upon the Testimonies graciously given them by
your Majesty's Ancestors of their steady and unshaken Loy∣alty
to the Crown of <HI>England,</HI> and your Majesty's Royal
Family, so they humbly presume to appeal to their Profes∣sions
of Faith, in Matters of Religion, as well as to
<PB REF="4"/>
their Constant Practice, to determine whether they have
always adhered to Principles equally Orthodox in Doctrine,
and equally contrary to, and inconsistent with, the Errors
and Absurdities of the Church of <HI>Rome.</HI></P>
<P>As Your Majesty's Royal Resolution to protect the Pro∣testant
Interest without Distinction is known to the World,
so your equal Conduct to all your Subjects gives an universal
Satisfaction, that your Royal Judgment knows perfectly to
execute by the most proper Methods what your Goodness hath
first determined to be reasonable; and as this is the Joy of
all your People, so <HI>Madam,</HI> your Protestant Dissenting Sub∣jects
in <HI>Ireland</HI> are too sensible of the Blessing, and know
too well both their Duty and Interest, to do any thing to
forfeit their Share in it.</P>
<P>Nor can they doubt, but as Your Majesty's equal Regard
to all your Subjects is your Glory, so it will be their Ad∣vantage
always, enclining your Majesty to hear, and re∣dress
the Pressures and Complaints of any Part of your Go∣vernment,
crush'd by the Weight of Another; and humbly
laying themselves and their Case at Your Royal Feet, they
willingly wait the time when God shall move Your Royal
Heart to that Goodness and Tenderness which the true Mo∣ther
extended to the Child when the Dreadful Arm was
stretcht out to divide it.</P>
<P>In the Confidence of this, they heartily pray for Your
Majesty's unvalluable Life and Prosperity, and earnestly
wish and desire the whole Body of Protestants in these Na∣tions,
for the Security of their Interests, and of Your Ma∣jesty's
Government, would obey the Glorious Invitation to
Peace and Ʋnion, which Your Majesty has so often made to
all your Subjects, by which we might all joyn in your Ser∣vice
to the Glory of the Protestant Religion, the entire
Satisfaction of Your Majesty, and the Peace and Prosperity
of these unhappy divided Nations.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1>
<PB N="1" REF="5"/>
<HEAD>THE
PARALLEL, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<P>THOSE Gentlemen who wrote with so much vigor in the Case
of Occasional Conformity, had most effectually clench'd their
Arguments, and overthrown all the Pretences of the Diffenters
against an Occasional Bill, could they, as they undertook,
ha' made it out, That <HI>in all wise Nations it has been the Practice to Exclude
all such as are not of the national Church from any share in the Administration
of Publick Affairs.</HI></P>
<P>But as the good or bad Effects of Exclusive Laws may be most clearly dis∣covered
in Cases where the Seasons, Methods, Persons, Interests and Cir∣cumstances,
run in the most exact Parallel, I shall beg leave to pass by th'
exploded Arguments, drawn from the Practise of Nations abroad, for
excluding from the Management of Publick Affairs all who are not of their
National Church, and bring up a Precedent near home in the Kingdom of
<HI>Ireland,</HI> where the resemblance of a Bill against Occasional Conformity, in
its charitable Expedients and flourishing Consequences, may teach those who
desire the like in <HI>England</HI> to look over among their Neighbours and see the
Consequences of it upon the Dissenters.</P>
<P>'Tis very probable the Gentlemen concern'd in that Project for <HI>Ireland,</HI>
would never have push'd at it if they had not thought at the same time
something equivalent in <HI>England</HI> would have past; for they would not
have been so accessary to discovering the real Design, they would not
have been willing the cloven Foot should have been seen so soon.</P>
<P><HI>Ʋnhappy</HI> Ireland! Thou art always bound to be ruin'd to save thy
Neighbours; How was thy Massacre in Forty-one a flaming Beacon to Il∣luminate
the World, and tell <HI>England</HI> what was coming upon her! Giv∣ing
her timely notice to take care of her self, and leading the way to her
safety with the Blood of 200000 innocent betray'd Protestants.</P>
<P>In our last unhappy Popish Reign how was this Kingdom swallowed up
with Tyranny, and made a Sacrifice to <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Romish</HI> Politicks; en∣tirely
devour'd and over run by the Arbitrary Methods of that Time?
How was Tyranny and Popery Hand in Hand Introduc'd, and the Laws
and Liberties of Protestants trod under Foot, <HI>as a fair Introduction to the
same Method putting forward in</HI> England, but not so easily brought to pass,
and consequently as a fair Notice to the <HI>English</HI> People to fortifie them∣selves
against that Flood of Destruction which they had seen overflow
their Unfortunate Neighbours.</P>
<P><PB N="2" REF="6"/>
Now thou art set a third time as a Mark, a Buoy on the cover'd Rock,
a Notice of concealed Mischiefs, a warning Piece to all the Protestant World,
but particularly as a Plan of a Design laid for the Destruction both of the
Liberties, Civil Rights and Religious Privileges of thy Protestant Dissen∣ting
Nighbours.</P>
<P>In all Cases; and on all Occasions, when the Ruin and Destruction of
<HI>England</HI> has been design'd, <HI>Ireland</HI> has <HI>thus gone before her;</HI> some that are
wiser in Politicks than I can pretend to, give this for a Reason, That the
Protestant Interest being weaker in this Kingdom than in that, the en∣croaching
Party has not been oblig'd to such Cautions, and such nice Mea∣sures
here as they have there, and the Project has been sooner ripe; but
they have been very happily defeated in their grand Design, by their own
Forwardness in that part of it, the first Execution in that Case opening the
Scene so early, that Nation has always been allarum'd from hence, and
found occasion to remember the old Rule in the Accidence, <HI>Faelix quem
Facient, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>And thus in the fatal Instances given, <HI>England</HI> always took warning
from her Sister <HI>Ireland;</HI> in 1641, when the bloody Papists Massacred so ma∣ny
thousand Protestants in <HI>Ireland,</HI> it immediately allarm'd the whole <HI>Eng∣lish</HI>
Nation, and told then in Characters too plain not to be read by the
meanest Understanding, what <HI>English</HI> Men were to expect from the Pre∣dominacy
of the same Party, and consequently that it was high time to
Arm against the Encroachments of Popery at home, to prevent the same
Destruction they had seen happen to their Neighbours here in <HI>Ireland.</HI></P>
<P>In 1688, when the Methods of Arbitrary Power, and the Popish De∣signs
went on so fast in <HI>Ireland,</HI> that the whole Kingdom appeared in a
manner subjugated to the Power of the Princes Will, and prepared to be
either Papists or Slaves, or both. The forward Ruin of their Liberties,
and the visible Destruction of the Protestant Religion in <HI>Ireland, like the
Drum to the Battail,</HI> awakned the <HI>English</HI> Nation to their own Delive∣rance,
and rouz'd them to consider, That the only Reason why they were
not reduced to the same Condition with their unhappy Neighbours was, be∣cause
the Enemies Power was not yet arrived to a pitch of Capacity; and
that the Design was the same, tho' the End was remoter there, as their
Work had more difficulty.</P>
<P>The Third Article is now before us, <HI>equally Ruinous</HI> in its Consequences
and <HI>equally Exemplar;</HI> and in this they keep still to the former Method,
That we are always Ruin'd a step before <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>'Tis confest the Contrivers of these Religious Disturbances managed their
Matters so as to have the blow struck in both Kingdoms at the same Time,
and so have prevented the Mischief in one Place being a Warning to the
other: But Providence that has ever watch'd over the Protestant Interest
broke the Snare, and unravel'd all this knot of Misery, and still poor <HI>Ire∣land</HI>
is the Beacon to warn us, the Allarm to rouze us, and the Example
from which to beware.</P>
<P>'Tis therefore worth some Remark here, that the specious Pretences
made in both Kingdoms to cover and conceal the real Design, have been
equally contriv'd, tho' not equally successful. In <HI>Ireland</HI> a Clause to ruin
the Protestant Dissenters, and in Effect the Protestant Interest, by discou∣raging
and discontenting a great part of the Protestants in that Kingdom,
comes introduc'd under the Title of <HI>an Act to prevent the Growth of Po∣pery.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="3" REF="7"/>
'Tis not material to Enquire by whose Application or secret Manage∣ment
this Mischief was accomplish'd; nor is it the Design of this Paper
to make Personal Reflections.</P>
<P>But it cannot but be observ'd, that it seems something hard, and very
unkind, that the Dissenters in <HI>Ireland,</HI> who were known to be one of the
chief Bulwarks in that Kingdom against Popery, and who were in general
a People who at the Price of their Blood defended themselves to the last
Extremity, and kept a footing in <HI>Ireland</HI> till Relief could come from <HI>Eng∣land,</HI>
should by the Artifice, and for the private Ends of a Party, who
have not yet told us what they drive at, be rank'd in the same Class with the
Introducers <HI>of that Popery</HI> they laid down their Lives to oppose, and be
coupled with the most dangerous Enemies of the Kingdom.</P>
<P>At best it savours of a most scandalous Ingratitude, That the very Peo∣ple
who drank deepest of the Popish Fury, and that were the most vigor∣ous
to shew both their Zeal and their Courage, in opposing Tyranny and
Popery, and on the Foot of whose Forwardness and Valour, the Church
of <HI>Ireland</HI> recovered her self from the low Condition Popery had reduc'd
her to, should now be requited with so injurious a Treatment as to be
link'd with those very Papists they fought against, and be Enacted against
under the Head of <HI>preventing the Growth of Popery.</HI></P>
<P>At the same time that this Bill was passing in <HI>Ireland,</HI> great Boasts were
made by some People, of a Bill on foot in <HI>England,</HI> for the further en∣forcing
the Test Act by preventing the <HI>Occasional Conformity</HI> of Dis∣senters.</P>
<P>The Advocates for this Bill have had a great deal of trouble to defend
it from some Scandals thrown upon it by other Pens, As that it was a
Breach of <HI>To<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eration,</HI> a Design of <HI>Persecution,</HI> and an Encroachment on
Civil as well as Religious <HI>Right.</HI> Whether it has been clear'd of these
Charges is not the business of this Paper; and yet if my Opinion were to
be ask'd in this Case, I believe I should say, that both Persecution and
Encroachments on Civil Liberties, was actually expected by some that
built their Hopes on the Success of this Bill.</P>
<P>Why some Gentlemen took care to put out of the Preamble to the second
Bill the Declaration against Persecution, is a Mystery I wont undertake to
explain; but that it afforded various Speculations to us without Doors is
as certain, as that after it was so left out, some People began to les∣sen
their Diligence in Exploding Persecuting Principles.</P>
<P>The Language of those Gentlemen without Doors, who at first were
only for restraining a vicious Practice as they call'd it, was
soon alter'd,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Cassandra. Sachevrel.</NOTE> and the Pulpit and the Press throng'd with In∣vectives
at the Dissenters.</P>
<P>Ishall not direct the World to judge of one thing by another, but where
Parallels are drawn very exact, what shall we say when two Things are
acted at the same Time, by the same Persons, in the same Methods, and
the Subject exactly the same, who shall doubt the sameness of the De¦sign.</P>
<P>Never let our New Association Men talk any more of Dissenters
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Now As∣sociation<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></NOTE>Associating, the Associations are against them, what else are
such unusual Methods, such forgetting of Services, such making Laws a∣gainst
the Innocent, such branding them with odious Characters.</P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="8"/>
What can any Man expect when the peaceable part of the Nation
are called<NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg">Suchevrel's <HI>Oxford Sermon.</HI></NOTE> Bloody, those that spent their Blood against Po∣pery
Enacted against to <HI>prevent the Growth of Popery;</HI> they that
stood to the Defence of their Country when some of them that
applauded this Law ran away and deserted it, made uncapable and thought
unfit to be trusted with the Civil Administration in that Country they so
bravely defended.</P>
<P>What can the largest Charity think is in the bottom of all this, when
we see a Party in Travel with a monstrous Birth? In <HI>England</HI> the Tole∣ration
Act to be kept inviolable, yet severe Penalties to be inflicted on Dis∣senters.
In <HI>Ireland,</HI> to prevent the growth of Popery, the Diffenters must
be treated as Men most dangerous and suspected, notwithstanding their
Zeal for the Protestant Interest, so conspicuous in the defence of that Coun∣try.
When Men strain their Reason to reconcile such Contradictions,
we may expect the Birth will disclose something which at present they
would be loath to own as legitimate. No Men strech their Reason and
act beyond the common Rate of Creatures but on extraordinary Occasion;
such preposterous Dealings as these would not have been practis'd with
any People in the World, if there were not a Figure, <HI>A Meosis</HI> in it, some∣thing
more Intended than is Express'd.</P>
<P>It cannot be that the Dissenters in <HI>Ireland,</HI> who of all the People of
that Nation ventur'd with the greatest Obstinacy and Resolution to defend
their Country, and the Protestant Religion against Popery, can be con∣cern'd
in a Bill <HI>to prevent the Growth of Popery;</HI> such Contradictions must be
big with some other Birth; there must be some Plot against the Dissenters
<HI>as such,</HI> and the hedging them into an Act for <HI>preventing the Growth of Po∣pery,</HI>
must be either a meer Indignity put upon them to render them O∣dious
and Contemptible to the World, or a Fraud, a Concealment to blind
the Eyes of the Dissenters that it might pass without their Notice, since
no one could imagine it could be possible an Act to <HI>prevent the Growth of
Popery</HI> could have any thing in it that could affect the Dissenters, than
whom none were more violent against Popery on all Occasions, or more
ready to expose themselves for the defence of their Country and the Pro∣testant
Religion.</P>
<P>But however unkind or mysterious this Matter is, so it appears; and in
order to lay open the Case, s as to let the World judge of it, and to make
out the Hardships, which with submission to our Superiors, we think the
Dissenters in <HI>Ireland</HI> lye under, 'tis necessary,</P>
<P>1. To enter into the Particulars, examine the Fact, and see what it is
that is done to the Dissenters in <HI>Ireland,</HI> with the Manner and Circum∣stances.</P>
<P>2.
Enquire into the Behaviour of the Dissenters in <HI>Ireland,</HI> and see what
they have done to deserve such Treatment, and what Reason they had
to expect better.</P>
<P>3. Examine whether the present Usuage has not been against the
real Design of the Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI> and what has been done by them
to shew their concern at it, or their forwardness to give them an Equi∣valent.</P>
<P>4.
Examine what natural Consequences may be expected from such a
Treatment of the Dissenters, and what the Detriment to the whole
Nation.</P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="9"/>
1. As to the Matter of Fact, the short Abridgment of it is as follows.</P>
<P>The Protestants in <HI>Ireland</HI> had many Years laboured under the Encroach∣ments
of the Papists, they had been once most horridly Massacred to the
number of 200000, and the rest Plundred and driven from their Settle∣ments
and Possessions in the Year 1641.</P>
<P>In the last War they ran a Fate equal to the first, <HI>the Massacre except∣ed,</HI>
and <HI>as will be farther observed,</HI> in these Extremities, the little City of
<HI>Derry</HI> was the only place of Refuge for the Protestants, and a Sanctuary
which the Papists could never drive them out of with all their Force, and
where they found such resistance as gave all the World reason <HI>to know,</HI> that
the aversion between the Dissenters and the Papists was as constant as
great, and as irreconcilable as possible, and served to encrease the Won∣der,
That the Dissenters should, of all People in the World, be look'd upon
as Persons in the same Class <HI>with the Papists,</HI> and Enacted against in a Bill
prevent <HI>the Growth of Popery.</HI></P>
<P>In order to secure the Protestants from the like Erruptions of Popery,
several Bills had been offered in Parliament, to prevent the growth and
encrease of that Power that had been so dangerous, and had struck twice
at the Root of their Liberty and Religion.</P>
<P>But it had been the Misfortune of this Country to have such Bills, thro'
one unhappy Accident or other, always to miscarry, either at home among
themselves, or at the <HI>English</HI> Court, where the Native <HI>Irish</HI> always culti∣vated
such an Interest as was too hard for the Protestants, and has been
a means to deprive them of the blessing of such Bills.</P>
<P>The late Glorious King <HI>William,</HI> who, at the hazard of his Royal Per∣son,
was the special Instrument of their second redemption from the pre∣prevailing
Power of the <HI>Irish,</HI> had such a peculiar Love for this Kingdom,
as the Triumph of his own immediate Conduct and Valour, that he al∣ways
studied its Welfare, and was ready to give Ear to any Proposal for
its advantage.</P>
<P>But as that Prince, who had upon his Thought the universal good of
Mankind, had no sooner recovered one Kingdom from Destruction but
he had another upon his Hands; (his whole Reign being embarrass'd
with the perpetual Cares of serving Ungrateful Nations,) so the Prote∣stants
found the Settlement of Affairs in <HI>Ireland</HI> so perplex'd, and the Re∣assumation
of Grants ready to bring a new Difficulty on the Stage; and in
all this time they found no opportunity to offer at the Settlement and Se∣curity
of their Interest and Religion, as they expected and desir'd.</P>
<P>But when they saw the Disorders pretty well over, and the loss of their
glorious Benefactor so happily supply'd, by the Accession of her present
Majesty Queen <HI>Anne.</HI></P>
<P>When to their great Comfort and Satisfaction, they saw the early Care
her Majesty took of all her Protestant Subjects, her Zeal for the Protestant
Religion, and the powerful Assistance she prepared to give it in all parts of
<HI>Europe</HI> where she saw it oppress'd.</P>
<P>When they saw themselves bless'd with such a Lord Lieutenant, who by
'reason of his great Possessions among them, <HI>besides the Native Inclination,</HI>
his Grace the Duke of <HI>Ormond, always discovered to acts of Generosity,</HI>
had powerful Obligations of Care and Respect upon him for the Kingdom
of <HI>Ireland</HI> in Particular; such a Governor as the People of <HI>Ireland</HI> always
lov'd and long'd for, and than whom, none ever was, or could be sent thi∣ther
<PB N="6" REF="10"/>
more Enclin'd or better prepared to Improve all her Majesty's gra∣cious
Intentions of Good to the Kingdom, in the highest manner her Ma∣jesty
could desire or the People expect.</P>
<P>This, of all the critical Junctures that ever happen'd to this Kingdom,
seem'd <HI>the happy opportunity,</HI> put into their Hands by a special Providence,
to obtain the Settlement and Security of the Protestant Religion, which
they and their Ancestors had spent so much Blood and Treasure to pro∣cure,
and the want of which had been attended with so many fatal Con∣sequences.</P>
<P>In
order to this, among the several Bills presented by the Parliament to
his Grace the Lieutenant, in the second Year of his Government, to be by
him transmitted to <HI>London,</HI> and to be passed in the Council there, <HI>accord∣ing
to the Settlement,</HI> there was one particular Bill, Entituled, <HI>An Act to
prevent the Growth of Popery.</HI></P>
<P>That the greater solemnity might add to the Value of it, and that it
might appear of what Consequence the Parliament of <HI>Ireland</HI> thought this
Act, the Speaker, attended by the whole House, waited on the Lord Lieu∣tenant
of <HI>Ireland</HI> to present this Bill, and in a particular manner recom∣mended
it to his Care; at the same time acquainting his Grace, that
the House had sufficient Grounds to believe the <HI>Irish</HI> Papists had rais'd a
Sum of Money in the Kingdom, to manage their Sollicitations against this
Bill, in order to prevent its return out of <HI>England.</HI></P>
<P>His Grace, to his Glory may it be remember'd, had that Care of the
Protestant Religion, that Concern for the good of <HI>Ireland,</HI> and that spe∣cial
Regard for the Recommendation of the Parliament, that sending the
Bill to <HI>England,</HI> and backing it with his powerful and hearty Sollicitations
at the Court of <HI>England,</HI> he prevented the Papists; and notwithstanding
the opposition they made, obtained the Bill to be approv'd, and returned
to the unspeakable Joy, and no less Surprize of the whole Body of Pro∣testants
in the Kingdom.</P>
<P>But this Joy was exceedingly lessen'd, when upon the reading the Bill
they found to their Amazement, among the Clauses for security of
the Protestants and weakening the Power of Popery, a Clause put in to
oblige all the Protestant Dissenters in <HI>Ireland,</HI> that have any Place, Of∣fice,
or Power from the Government, to conform to the Church of <HI>Ire∣land,</HI>
and receive the Sacrament after the usage thereof, or else to be Dis∣abled
or Incapacitated for the Service of their Country.</P>
<P>The Protestants of the Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI> who tho' they were zealous
for the Establish'd Church, were yet sensible of the Power of the Papists,
and how useful on all Occasions the Protestant Dissenters had been in help∣ing
them to oppose Popery, were extremely concern'd at this; they
remember'd their Power, tho' united, had been twice too weak to resist
the Papists, and that therefore it was a most unhappy piece of unseason∣able
Policy, to weaken the Church by depriving them of the Assistance of
so great a Body of Protestants, or at least disobliging them.</P>
<P>They foresaw that this Clause would endanger the loss of the Bill, since
it would engage the Dissenters with all their Interest to oppose it, as the
Papists they were sure already would do.</P>
<P>They foresaw this Clause would allarm the Dissenters, and make them
judge their faithful Services in the Siege of <HI>London-Derry,</HI> at <HI>Inniskilling</HI>
and other places ill rewarded, and break that Harmony which with so
<PB N="7" REF="11"/>
much Charity and Tenderness had been reciprocally maintained between
Conformists and Dissenters in <HI>Ireland.</HI></P>
<P>In Consideration of these things, almost all People were under great
Concern, and not a few thought it very unkind to the Dissenters, and a
Requital of their faithful Services at the Siege of <HI>London-Derry,</HI> at <HI>Innis∣killing,</HI>
and other places, in a manner very unsuitable to their Merits.</P>
<P>I choose to mention here the Concern the Conforming Protestants were
in at this Clause, not only to testifie their Zeal for the Bill of security a∣gainst
Popery, which they were afraid by this Clause would be lost, but
also to witness for them, as they had no hand in, nor any Design to bring
such a thing upon the Dissenters, so the Church of <HI>Ireland</HI> has on many
Occasions express'd, and at all times for above twenty Years past practis'd,
all the Charity and Easiness to the dissenting Protestants that can be de∣sired
among Christians; agreeing in all Capital Points of Religion, and
particularly embark'd in one and the same bottom of Interest and publick
Safety.</P>
<P>When this Bill came to be Read in the House, it met with particular
opposition from the Papists, who were heard by their Council, and who
pleaded the Articles of <HI>Limerick,</HI> &amp;c. and charged the Protestants with
breach of Faith and Capitulations.</P>
<P>The Clause against the Dissenters was oppos'd by several worthy Mem∣bers
of the Protestant Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI> and a great many Learned
Speeches were made on that Head.</P>
<P>And not to presume to publish a Relation of what was said by any par∣ticular
Member, I am inform'd that near one hundred Gentlemen, all of
the Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI> spoke with a great deal of Tenderness and Con∣cern
for the Dissenters as too hardly dealt with, and too much affected with
this Clause.</P>
<P>The Dissenters in the House were observ'd to make little or no opposi∣tion
in this Case, but as the old Earl of <HI>Strafford,</HI> when being Attainted
in Parliament, the King refusing to sign the Attainder, he gave his own
consent to have his Head cut off to fix the Peace between his Majesty and
his People; they choose rather to acquiesce with an Unhappiness laid on
them, and suffer all the ill they saw coming upon them, than let
such a Bill drop in the House, which they knew to be so much wanted
against Popery, and which was of such a vast Benefit to the security
of the Protestant Interest in general, and the publick Quiet and Safety of
the Kingdom.</P>
<P>Thus they sacrific'd themselves and their Brethren for the publick Good
of their Country, and were passive in their own Prejudices that the Bill
might not be lost.</P>
<P>The Gentlemen, on the other side, on no Consideration desir'd to
put these Hardships on the Dissenters, but saw themselves oblig'd
to pass this Clause, or lose all the Advantages which were accruing
to them by the other, so gave at last an unwilling Assent to the Bill,
publickly declaring their Resolution <HI>To do something which should make
the Dissenters as easie as they are in</HI> England; and accordingly it
was Resolv'd, <HI>Nemine Contradicente,</HI> the very next Day, that Heads
of a Bill should be brought in to give the Dissenters the same
Tolleration they enjoy in <HI>England;</HI> but the Sessions was so near
a Conclussion that there was not time for that Bill to be brought
in: And thus the Bill pass'd, and the Dissenters are thereby ob∣lig'd
<PB N="8" REF="12"/>
to conform to the Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI> or to quit all the Service of
their Country, and be turned out of every place of Trust or Profit in the
Nation.</P>
<P>This is a short Abstract of the Fact as it now lies before us, the Conse∣quences
of this Act of Parliament, so far as it affects the Dissenters in the
Kingdom of <HI>Ireland,</HI> may be guest at from the following, Account of the
proceedings upon this Act in the North parts, and particularly in the City
of <HI>London-Derry.</HI></P>
<P>The Province of <HI>Ʋlster,</HI> as is well known to all those who are acquaint∣ed
with <HI>Ireland,</HI> is chiefly Inhabited by <HI>English</HI> and <HI>Scots,</HI> and above two
Thirds of them by computation are Protestant Dissenters.</P>
<P>How they have always behav'd themselves, both in Peace and War,
both to their Enemies and to their Neighbours, both to the Government
and for the Government, will be considered in an Article by it self.</P>
<P>How they have now been Treated, with respect to this Act, comes un∣der
this Head, and will appear by the surprizing Proceedings with the
Magistrates of <HI>London-Derry,</HI> and other places in <HI>Ʋlster.</HI></P>
<P>In this Transaction its observable, how readily the very Essence of a
Party, Humour, Spleen and Forwardness, may be disfused into the Minds
of Men, since notwithstanding the Tenderness and Consideration of the
Enactors, yet the Execution has not been managed with the same Spirit.</P>
<P>By this Act they have put out most of the Justices of the Peace in the
Province of <HI>Ʋlster,</HI> for we do not hear of above one or two that have
Qualified themselves and for want of Gentlemen that are qualified, have
been oblig'd to fill up the Commission of the Peace with Clergy-men;
where by the way it may be noted, That the Phanaticks in <HI>New England</HI>
are not the only People who make their Priests Magistrates, and have the
Law and the Gospel under the management of the same Hand.</P>
<P>It was thought strange, that in those Counties they should be under Ec∣clesiastical
Magistrates, and the Men of the Gown have both the Word of
the Lord and the Sword <HI>of the State,</HI> instead of that of the <HI>Spirit</HI> to man∣age,
and so in <HI>Ireland</HI> it might be thought as strange, that the antient In∣habitants,
who spent their Fortunes, and hazarded their Lives in Defence
of the whole Protestant Interest, are now not thought worthy to Govern
what they so gallantly defended; but as People not fit to be trusted
with that in Peace which they saved in War, are laid by with Contempt,
and their places not being to be filled up with Men of equal Worth and
equal Figure, in part supplied with Youths, Strangers, new Comers, and
Clergy-men; Men of little Estates, and consequently having not so much
Obligation on them to be concerned for the Good of the place; Persons
that have little, if any thing, to recommend them to the Dignity of Ma∣gistrates
but their going to Church, with neither Fortunes, Interest or
Qualification.</P>
<P>How far the Government is concern'd, how far the Safety of the City,
how far the Service of her Majesty is advanc'd in this way of Proceedings,
Time, and the Consequences of Things, must determine, and avoiding any
Reflections on the probability, 'tis left to the publick Consideration.</P>
<P>And since 'tis natural for all Persons, and even a Turk, that sees a Nation
or a Party punish'd, exploded and unqualified by a Law would be ready to en∣quire
what Crime they have been Guilty of, what Offence they have commit∣ted
that should move the Government to throw them by as useless Persons,
dismiss them as People not fit to be trusted and employ'd, it obliges us to fall
<PB N="9" REF="13"/>
in with the same Enquiry, and so go on with the second Head of this
Argument, <HI>viz.</HI></P>
<P>2. Enquire into the Behaviour of the Dissenters, and see what they
have done to deserve such a Treatment, and what reason they have to
expect a better.</P>
<P>And because it is the Custom of all the Dissenters Enemies in <HI>England,</HI>
who seek for Matter to charge them with, to go back to the Years of 41
to 48 and 60, and to rake into the Follies and Misfortunes of former Ages
to seek for Arguments to brand the present, <HI>a certain sign</HI> the modern
Behaviour of the Dissenters does not furnish sufficient Matter of
blame to justifie their present Treatment; yet in the Case of the
Dissenters in <HI>Ireland,</HI> we are as willing as they to go back to those Times,
and should be pleased to join Issue with them in searching out for the Re∣bellions,
the Associations, the Factions, and the Disturbances the Dissen∣ters
in <HI>Ireland</HI> ever raised against their Prince.</P>
<P>It was one of the Objections against the late Earl of <HI>Strafford</HI> at his
Tryal, That he proposed the Army in <HI>Ireland</HI> to come over hither to the
Assistance of his Majesty, as People of whose Fidelity he was sure of, and
several Regiments of them did afterwards come over, and fought for the
King at the Battail at <HI>Nantwich,</HI> among whom were several Dissenters, and
where General <HI>Monk,</HI> then but a Captain, was taken Prisoner, who was
afterwards Instrumental in the Restoring the King.</P>
<P>In all the Civil Wars here in <HI>Ireland,</HI> we find none of these Peo∣ple
up in Arms for the Parliament, but we find them zealously es∣pousing
the King's Quarrel, and contending with the <HI>Sectaries,</HI> as they
themselves call'd them, who opposed the King here.</P>
<P>And as no Testimony of the good Deeds of a Person, or a Party, can
come with such unexceptioned Authority as what has the concurring
Testimony of their Enemies, we refer the Reader for the Particulars
to the famous <HI>Milton,</HI> whose Pen must needs obtain Credit of our high
Gentlemen since he Quarrels with the very Men they would quarrel with,
and falls in with the fury of the Times, to expose those they would have
exposed.</P>
<P>The Misfortune is, he Exposes the Presbyterians, Rails at and Accuses
them of that as a Crime, the not doing which is the very Crime these Gen∣tlemen
would brand them for now.</P>
<P>Our Modern Authors would set a Mark on the Dissenters for fighting a∣gainst,
Dethroning and Murthering their King, Subverting the Constituti∣on,
and overthrowing the Government, here we find Mr. <HI>Milton</HI> exposing
and defaming the Protestant Dissenters of <HI>Ʋlster,</HI> for not joining with his
Party in those things, but fighting for their King, and endeavouring to pre∣vent
the very things for which these People are accused, and endeavour∣ing
to restore the Monarchy in the Son which they would not help to sup∣press
in the Father.</P>
<P>To make out this, the Reader is referred to the particular Authors
and their Writings, which are in every Library of any Value to be
seen, the brevity of this Tract not allowing us to quote these things at
large.</P>
<P>But we cannot omit to quote here the Representation of the Presbytery
at <HI>Belfast,</HI> dated <HI>Feb.</HI> 15. 1649. wherein the Dissenters of the North of
<PB N="10" REF="14"/>
<HI>Ireland,</HI> declare their detestation of all the Proceedings in <HI>England;</HI> see
<HI>Milton</HI>'s Works, Fol. 566, 567.</P>
<P>“What of late have been, and now are, the insolence and presump∣tuous
Practises of the Sectaries in <HI>England,</HI> is not unknown to the
World.”</P>
<P>“Moreover it is more than manifest, that they seek not the Vindication
but the Extirpation of the Laws and Liberties, as appears by their
seizing the Person of the King, their violent Surprizing, Imprisoning and
Secluding many of the most worthy Members of the Honourable House
of Commons: neither hath their Fury staid here, but without all Rule
or Example, being but private Men, they have proceeded to the Tryal
of the King, against both the Interest, Protestation and Publick Decla∣rations
of both Kingdoms, and with cruel Hands have put him to Death,
an act so horrible as no History Divine or Humane hath laid a precedent
of the like.”</P>
<P>“These and many other their destable Insolencies, may abundantly
convince any unbyass'd Judgment, that the present practises of the Sect∣aries
and their Abettors, do directly overturn the Laws and Liberties of
the Kingdom, root out lawful and supreme Magistracy, the just Pri∣viledges
whereof we have sworn to maintain, and Introduce a fearful
Confusion and lawless Anarchy.”</P>
<P>And in the subsequent Paragraphs as follows, Fol. 562.</P>
<P>“When we consider these things, we cannot but declare and manifest
our utter Dislike and Detestation of all such unwarrantable Practises,
directly subverting our Religion, Laws and Liberties.”</P>
<P>We farther refer the Readers for the Treatment these Dissenters met with
in Print from their Brethren of <HI>England</HI> then in Power, to Mr. <HI>Milton</HI>'s
Observations on the Representation in the same Collection, in Fol. 553,
554, 555, where he treats them with the scandalous Terms of <HI>Egregious
Liars and Impostures, blockish Presbyters;</HI> and goes on to justifie the putting
the King to Death, all the way upbraiding them with Ignorance and Se∣paration.</P>
<P>This
Testimony sufficiently clears the Dissenters in <HI>Ireland</HI> from being
concerned in any of the Councils of those Days, and the Histories of those
Times which all People are left to peruse, are sufficient to prove how the
Northern Protestants, being most of them Dissenters, were the most effe∣ctual
Barriers of the Royal Interest at that time, and when all the rest of
the Country was over-run with Popery, Blood and Desolation; were left
as a Sanctuary to which the Duke of <HI>Ormond</HI> and the Royal Party retreat∣ed,
that they endured all the Miseries of a long War, and defended
themselves with the same Vigor and Obstinacy as they did in the City of
<HI>Derry</HI> in the late Time, till they were reduced by absolute Force and the
Current of the Times, being conquer'd and oppress'd by the prevailing Par∣ty
under <HI>Oliver Cromwel,</HI> together with all the rest of the Kingdom.</P>
<P>But as these things are so well known to all the World, as not to require
that we should repeat them, it remains to examine what Sense the Royal
Family had of their Behavionr in those Times, and what greater Testimo∣ny
can be desired than is naturally deduc'd from the Bounty of King <HI>Charles</HI>
<PB N="11" REF="15"/>
the Second after his Restoration, in the Grant whereof it will appear
and to which for a proof of this the Reader is referr'd, that for the good
Services rendred by the Protestant Dissenters of <HI>Ʋlster</HI> to his Royal Father,
and afterwards to himself; and in regard to the great Sufferings they
had undergone in the time of the Wars, the King grants the Sum of 800<HI>l.</HI>
Sterling <HI>per Annum</HI> for the support of the Dissenting Ministers in the said
Provinces.</P>
<P>This Grant was made soon after the Restoration, the Money was con∣stantly
paid out of the Revenue of <HI>Ireland</HI> all the Reign of King <HI>Charles</HI>
the Second, and was continued till the Revolution, and the Interruption
of the last War; it was afterwards renewed by King <HI>William</HI> of glorious
Memory, was augmented by the late Queen <HI>Mary</HI>'s special Bounty to 1200<HI>l.
per Annum,</HI> and was lately, <HI>viz.</HI> in the second Year of her present Majesty re∣trench'd
by the Parliaments Authority, not upon any failure of Duty
charg'd on the Protestant Dissenters, or any Branch of the Queens Esteem;
but among other Grants and Pensions, which in Consideration of the im∣poverish'd
State of the Kingdom, the pressure of the present War, and the
great Exigencies of the State, the Commons thought fit to suspend for a
Season.</P>
<P>This may serve for a short Representation of the Behaviour of the Pro∣testants,
Dissenters in <HI>Ireland,</HI> and to clear them from all that Reproach
with which their Brethren in <HI>England</HI> seem to be loaden, and consequently
serves to make it out, that there could not be the same Reasons why such
Provisionary Laws should be made against them, since People always Loy∣al,
rewarded and acknowledged as such by our Kings, and who have suf∣fered
so deeply for it, cannot without an inexcusable breach both in Cha∣rity
and good Manners, be supposed to give any cause of Jealousie, or to
make it necessary for us to couple them with Papists in our Acts of Se∣curity.</P>
<P>I refer for the Proof of these Matters to the Testimony of <HI>Milton</HI> afore∣said,
their profest Enemy, who in his Observations on their unchristian
Representation as he calls it, falls on them in these Terms, <HI>Milton</HI>'s
Works, Fol. 551.</P>
<P>“Nay, while we are writing these things, and foretelling all Men the
Rebellion which was even then design'd by these unhallow'd Priests, at
the same time when with their Lips they are disclaiming all Sedition,
News is brought, and too true, that the <HI>Scotch</HI> Inhabitants of that Pro∣vince
are actually Revolted, and have not only besieged in <HI>London-Derry</HI>
those Forces which were to have fought against <HI>Ormond,</HI> but have
in a manner began open War against the Parliament, and all this by the
Incitement and Illusions of that unchristian Synagogue the Presby∣tery
at <HI>Belfast.</HI>”</P>
<P>As this is sufficient to declare their Behaviour in those Days, so we have
no less Authority to prove their hearty Union with the Church of <HI>Ire∣land,</HI>
i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> defence of the Protestant Religion in the late War, and their Ten∣derness
of, and Charity to the Ministers of the Church, when oppress'd by
the Papists; and for this we refer to that known and unexceptionable Hi∣story,
call'd, <HI>The State of the Protestants in</HI> Ireland <HI>under the late King</HI>
James <HI>his Government;</HI> written by the learned Dr. <HI>King,</HI> Bishop of <HI>Derry,</HI>
and now Lord Archbishop of <HI>Dublin;</HI> wherein his Lordship with an un∣exampled
<PB N="12" REF="16"/>
Generosity, telling us of the Reasons of the Clergy of <HI>Ireland</HI>
abandoning the Country and their Cures in many places, has these
Words,</P>
<P>“I do confess that there was no reason to complain of the People's
backwardness to maintain the Clergy, on the contrary they contributed
to the utmost of their Power, and made no distinction of Sects; many
Dissenters Contributing liberally to this good End, which ought to be
remembred to their Honour”. Archbishop <HI>King</HI>'s State of <HI>Ireland,</HI> page 231.</P>
<P>It cannot be denied but that this is an Authentick Certificate of their
Charity to the Church, as the other of their Loyalty to their King, and
how it has been <HI>remembred to their Honour,</HI> is left to all impartial Judg∣ments,
who please to give themselves the trouble to review the Conse∣quences
of the Bill lately past; by which they have rank'd their Charita∣ble
Brethren amongst their worst Enemies, and chain'd them to a Compul∣sion
as a means <HI>to prevent the Growth of Popery.</HI></P>
<P>And being brought by this Article to the late War, after the Confession
of so eminent a Branch of the Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI> with respect to their
Charity, it is fit a little to examine their Behaviour in the late Seige of <HI>Derry,</HI>
and the several Actions at <HI>Inniskilling.</HI></P>
<P>To make out this: Was this Paper confin'd to <HI>Ireland,</HI> and were we writ∣ing
to none but our own Country-men, it were easie to appeal to the know∣ledge
of thousands yet alive, in whose Memory it must yet be very fresh,
with what undistinguish'd Charity and Alacrity the Dissenters join'd with
their Brethren of the Church, in the mutual defence of Religion and Li∣berty,
how they went Hand in Hand into the Field, and Hand in Hand
to the Grave, fighting for one another, and their dear Families and Re∣ligion.</P>
<P>What tho' they have not the Arrogance to enter upon any distinguish∣ing
Circumstances, in which they might go beyond their Brethren, yet
since the Church themselves will not assume a pretence to have out-gone
them, we hope their Modesty in that Case cannot tend to their Prejudice.</P>
<P>We therefore avoid so ungrateful a strife as it must be, to find out and
fix the Particulars in which one Party excell'd another; 'tis enough to both
their Honour, that they strove to out-do themselves and one another, as
they plainly did all the rest of the Kingdom in Acts of Gallantry and Cou∣rage,
in a free open handed contributing to one anothers Wants, and sup∣plying
all People concern'd in the defence of the Nation, and in the Per∣sonal
Bravery in the defence of the place.</P>
<P>Nor are we afraid to enter into a List of the Numbers of the People of
either sort slain in that Siege; if they are two Dissenters to one Church∣man,
they cannot take it ill that we do not boast of it.</P>
<P>The several Magistrates of the City of <HI>Derry,</HI> now turned out of Com∣mission
by this Act, as not safe to be trusted, are too Modest to furnish us
with an Account how much Money each of them expended in Provisions,
Stores, and Charity for the defence of the Town; and the Editor of this
is forc'd to boast for them, without Reflections on any, that some of
them have disburst greater Sums than many of their Successors are in Con∣dition
to spare, if there should be the like occasion.</P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="17"/>
The Testimony given by Authority to their Behaviour, in the defence
of their Country, and the Protestant Religion, is an unquestion'd Proof of
the just Claim they have to the Title of Loyal, Faithful and Valiant Sub∣jects,
and is a perfect Contradiction to the Notion of obtaining Security a∣gainst
them as against Papists, and coupling them with the known Enemies
of the Nation.</P>
<P>The late Queen <HI>Mary,</HI> a Name both Nations have an equal Veneration
for, and which we cannot name without a Sigh, had so true a Sense on her
Mind, of the Courage and Fidelity of the Dissenters in <HI>Derry,</HI> that she
gave them a Mark of her Royal Favour in Money, to be employ'd to
rebuild their Market House, and to erect a new Meeting-house in that
City.</P>
<P>Nor let us do Injustice to the Church and Gentry, or Clergy of the
Church of <HI>Ireland;</HI> 'tis most certain it never enter'd into the Hearts of the
Conforming Protestants of this Kingdom, to impose these Hardships upon
their Brethren, much less did they imagine to have it included in their Bill
to prevent the Growth of Popery.</P>
<P>Nothing so hard, nothing so ungrateful could enter into the Hearts of
the Church in this Kingdom, who could not but remember what the Dis∣senters
had done to deserve, and from whence they might expect better
Usage.</P>
<P>They could not but have it fresh in their Memories, how they had re∣lieved
their Clergy in distress, harboured their banish'd, diverted the Forces
of the Enemy, and defended the remnant of the Kingdom against Popery.</P>
<P>They could not forget the Slaughter made of the <HI>Irish</HI> Army under the
Walls of <HI>Derry,</HI> and how that bold stand, made by such a handful of Men,
aw'd the Enemy, encourag'd Friends, and made way for the Conquests of
King <HI>William,</HI> by securing to him all the North of <HI>Ireland;</HI> by which means
he had leisure to March directly to the <HI>Boyn,</HI> and there put the whole For∣tune
of <HI>Ireland</HI> upon one decisive Battel; and by beating the <HI>Irish</HI> there de∣livered
this Nation, which he could not have done had the Province of
<HI>Ʋlster</HI> been at his back possess'd by his Enemies, who would have cut off
his Provisions, and exceedingly straitned his Quarters.</P>
<P>'Twould be endless to reckon up all the brave Actions done in this War
by the Dissenters, own'd by the King himself, acknowledg'd by the
Archbishop of <HI>Dublin,</HI> rewarded by the Queen, and consider'd by
the Parliament.</P>
<P>From all these things I cannot but be of the Opinion, the Dissenters in
<HI>Ireland</HI> had a great deal of reason to expect better Treatment, and had
indeed a just Claim to the same brotherly Charity they shew'd to the
Church.</P>
<P>And here they cannot but lament in themselves the evil of the Times,
when they should meet with such usage after all their Services done, and
Duty express'd, that contrary to the true Sentiments of the Church of <HI>Ire∣land,</HI>
after an Acknowledgment of one of the Primates of the Clergy, that
it ought to be remember'd to their Honour, it should at last be remember'd
to their Infamy, and the Dissenters be counted with the number of the
Nations Enemies, and included in a Law for the general Security.</P>
<P>And it cannot but be observ'd here, the Earl of <HI>N.......</HI> could not
be ignorant of the acknowledgment made by the Archbishop, in the
Case of the Dissenters Kindness to the Clergy, which it was his Graces
Opinion, ought to be remember'd with Honour, since his Imprimatur
<PB N="14" REF="18"/>
being to that Book, his Lordship could not but have perused the Book,
unless we should advance a Notion too mean for a Man of his Capacity
and Prudentials, <HI>viz.</HI> That his Lordship put his Imprimatur to it, not
having read it over, and so Licens'd he knew not what.</P>
<P>We come now to the Third General Head, <HI>viz.</HI></P>
<P>To examine the Effects this ill Step upon the Dissenters may have, with
the particular Circumstances that aggravate it several ways, and as we go,
to make some needful Remarks: As,</P>
<P>1. How full of Vicissitudes are Humane Things, Times Turn-about,
Men and Parties change Principles, <HI>Nos &amp; mutamur in illis.</HI> The Lord
Bishop of <HI>Derry,</HI> a Man of Temper and Moderation, being well treated by
the Dissenters, recommends it <HI>To be remember'd to their Honour;</HI> but my
Lord Archbishop of <HI>Dublin</HI> grown quite a new Man, flying in the Face of
all their Merit, and embracing Principles which are destructive of the
Rights and Liberties of the very People they Rule, prompts with all pos∣sible
Zeal a Persecution Spirit, to the Ruin and Injury of those very Peo∣ple
of whom, by the E... of <HI>N.......</HI>'s leave, he had said all those
things before.</P>
<P>2. Here we cannot but observe, how change of things will change Clergy∣men,
and other Men too, make moderate Bishops turn violent Archbishops,
make Men forget when the Storm's over the Vows they made in the time
of its violence.</P>
<P>Some have had ill Nature enough to compare this with the Practises of
some of the <HI>English</HI> Clergy, who in the same times of Trouble in <HI>England,</HI>
promised to come to a Temper with the Dissenters, in order to draw them
off from closing with King <HI>James,</HI> and the extraordinary advantages he of∣fer'd
them, and have since been pleased to forget very much of that Tem∣per,
and pursue the same Dissenters with ill Language, persecuting Laws,
and the like.</P>
<P>'Tis unhappy for the Dissenters however, that this unchristian Spirit
should be convey'd into this Nation, where all liv'd in Peace and U∣nion,
and began to cultivate the happy Fruits of Charity and good
Neighbourhood.</P>
<P>'Tis presum'd the Church of <HI>Ireland</HI> had nothing of this in their
Thoughts, and are not pleased with it now they have it, as they cannot
but see that it is the beginning of intestine Strife, and a Bone of Conten∣tion,
Emulation and unchristian Discord among us, dividing us into Par∣ties,
sowring and dissatisfying thousands of Protestants, as good Subjects,
as Loyal to the Queen, as faithful to her Interest, and without vanity as
able to render her Service as any her Majesty has in these Parts.</P>
<P>And tho' we are assur'd nothing will be able to extort from the Dissen∣ters
any thing, either in Word or Action, Undutiful or Disrespectful to
her Majesty or her Government; yet 'tis no breach of Duty to observe,
that it is a great discouragement to the Trade and Prosperity of this King∣dom,
as it will occasion many wealthy Families to abandon their Country
where they are used so ill, and will at least not invite other Families to
settle here in their room, where they are sure to be treated with Jealousie
and Disrespect.</P>
<P>It cannot but be allow'd by any Persons who have the least knowledge
of publick Matters, that to drive the People away from any Country is so
<PB N="15" REF="19"/>
far to impoverish that Country; and of all Methods of Goverment it is
the most Impolitick, since the Wealth of a Nation depends upon the Mul∣titude
of its Inhabitants. But of all Countries in <HI>Europe,</HI> this distress'd
Kingdom, that has twice now, in the space of sixty Years, been in a
manner Depopulated by most bloody and inhumane Wars, two Wars that
have been more particularly destructive to the Inhabitants than may be ex∣pected
to happen in like Cases, and which have destroyed such incredible
numbers, that 'tis a wonderful thing to see there should be People left to
cultivate and manage the Earth; the least of these Wars having, by the
judgment of moderate Computators, kill'd, or driven beyond the Seas,
above 400000 of the Inhabitants of this Kingdom.</P>
<P>We shall not presume to foretel, or enter into reasons, why great num∣bers
of the Inhabitants in this Kingdom will remove Themselves and Ef∣fects,
upon the melancholly prospect of Persecution, and the discourage∣ment
received by this Treatment.</P>
<P>But it cannot but be allow'd, that to make them uneasie in their Con∣sciences,
or deprive them of the Honours and Trust which ever since the
fettling of this Kingdom they have enjoy'd in common with their Bre∣thren
of the Church, will be far from inviting other Families to come thi∣ther
and settle, and so keep them as thin of People as the War has left
them.</P>
<P>The advantage this will be to <HI>Scotland,</HI> whither the Dissenters in these
Parts must of course retreat, and where they talk very big of erecting and
improving the <HI>English</HI> Manufacture: as it is a Subject which affords many
Speculations, so it can be no trespass upon Reason to say, we believe the
Gentlemen who contriv'd this Law, would not like it the better for its be∣ing
a means of Enriching or Encouraging the <HI>Scots..</HI></P>
<P>Asto the Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI> tho' the Dissenters are as we think unkind∣ly
treated, we cannot but acquit them, <HI>as a Body,</HI> of being any way
guilty of this thing, and crave leave to lay this Greviance where it real∣ly
lies.</P>
<P>First, By the Church of <HI>Ireland</HI> we mean, the Protestant Nobility, Gentry
and common People, Inhabitants of this Kingdom conforming to the Church.</P>
<P>And these being unconcern'd, appear'd, as has been already noted, in
a great surprize; it was perfectly a strange thing to them when they found
their Bill come back clog'd with such a Clause as was unwelcome to them
both; and had not the Dissenters in the House acquiesced, for the publick
Good, had endanger'd the loss of their Bill.</P>
<P>If any Man will suggest, That it was sollicited privately by the Clergy of
the Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI> they must at the same time sly in the Face of the
Lord Archbishop of <HI>Dublin,</HI> and charge all the Clergy of <HI>Ireland</HI> with very
much Ingratitude to treat those Men so ill, who by the confession of the
said Archbishop deserv'd to have their Charity and Kindness to their Bre∣thren
<HI>remembred to their Honour.</HI></P>
<P>It can therefore lye no where but among the Enemies of the Dissenters,
who for the gratification of their private Malice, or for the carrying on of
some private Design, have misrepresented them at the Court of <HI>Eng∣land,</HI>
and causing all their Submissions and past Services to be forgotten,
prevailed to have them treated as Enemies and dangerous Persons, to that
Government which they had so often and so faithfully defended.</P>
<P>If the E... of <HI>N.....</HI> had been pleased to remember his Imprimatur
to the Book of his Grace of <HI>Dublin,</HI> as in Honour most M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n think he was
<PB N="16" REF="20"/>
bound he would certainly have made a generous Representation of the
Dissenters Case to the <HI>English</HI> Court.</P>
<P>And we hope we cannot be guilty of presumption in saying, that who∣ever
they were-that promoted this Clause, and whatsoever their Reasons
might be, they cannot pretend that in it they pursued her Majesty's true
Interest, or indeed her own genuine or glorious Design, which appears
from her own Royal Mouth to be the Good, the Peace and Prosperity
of all her Protestant Subjects, since to oppress a Party of them, and persecute
them for their Religion, at a time when her Majesty has declar'd her
Royal Intentions to the contrary, can never be agreeable to her Majesty's
Pleasure, nor could ever have been obtain'd without some Misrepresenta∣tion
of her Majesty's Loyal and Faithful Subjects.</P>
<P>Farther, 'tis our Opinion that the Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI> as before describ'd,
cannot be the Agents of this ill Treatment, because 'tis apparent the Sense
both of what the Dissenters have done and suffer'd, for the security and
preservation of that Church, would have given all its moderate Members
such Satisfaction, and made them so easy with the Dissenters, and the Dis∣senters
with them, that the Peace and Union which her Majesty has so
earnestly recommended to her Subjects in <HI>England,</HI> seem'd to be arrived to
a perfection in <HI>Ireland.</HI></P>
<P>To the Papists in particular there appear'd no difference, Protestants were
always treated alike as Enemies, and always heartily concerned themselves
for one another in their mutual Defence.</P>
<P>'Tis no vanity to say, the Church-men could 'not have defended them∣selves
against the Papists without the Dissenters; and we need appeal to
no body but themselves for the truth of it; we need ask none but the
Church-men, whether the Dissenters did not both in their Persons and
Purses heartily join with them, and if they should be so disingenuous as to
deny it, the Papists themselves would confess it for them.</P>
<P>The Dissenters assisting them, and relieving them, both Clergy and
Laity, in their flight and distress is fairly and honourably own'd by the
Church, and by one of the most eminent of their Dignified Clergy, his
Grace the Lord Archbishop of <HI>Dublin,</HI> as has been already noted.</P>
<P>Nor can we forbear to mention, to the Honour of the Church of <HI>Ire∣land,</HI>
that they have been so sensible of this, and so far from expressing
any heat, or breach of Charity, so far from inclining to a persecuting
Temper, or from envying, or molesting the Dissenters in their Conscien∣tious
Liberties, that they have enjoy'd a perfect and entire Liberty, tho
without any Toleration by a Law, and this Liberty, to the Honour of the
Church of <HI>Ireland</HI> Protestants, was found free from all those Heart-burn∣ings,
Insultings, Lampoons and Reproaches, which their Neighbours have
been treated with on that account; they liv'd together in Charity, good
Neighbourhood, and settled friendly Correspondence.</P>
<P>And as the Church of <HI>Ireland</HI> of their meer Inclination gave to the Dis∣senters
an undisturb'd Liberty of Conscience, so on the other hand the Dis∣senters
manifested their entire confidence in the Christian Temper and Mo∣deration
of the Church, and never sollicited the obligation of a Law to the
Toleration of their Religious Worship; they knew they had oblig'd the
Church to the highth, and always frankly join'd Hearts and Hands to
defend them, and as they found no ungrateful Usage they fear'd
none; and thus they lived together in full Confidence of one another, and
as they never expected this act, so we firmly believe it was the re∣motest
<PB N="17" REF="21"/>
thing in the World from their Thought to put any such thing upon
the Publick as the joyning the Dissenters with the Nation's Enemies, and
ranking them with those they ought to be afraid of.</P>
<P>If any Man should ask now what will be the Effect of all this Hardship
and ill Usage, <HI>which is the Fourth Head,</HI> the Author of this answers, there
cannot be Place in the Compass of these Sheets to enumerate all the unhap∣py
Consequences of this Matter; nor may it be fit to suggest what we ought
to fear on this Account. But as far as may consist with Reason, we answer
1. Negatively.</P>
<P>Nothing Tumultuous, nothing Disobedient or Undutiful to her Majesty,
whose Inclination we have abundant Reason to know, is entirely set to
promote the Peace of all her Dominions, and the general Union of all her
People. We should not presume to quote the Address from the Prebyterian
Ministers of the North of <HI>Ireland,</HI> and how they boast to her Majesty in
these Words, <HI>According to our known Principles of Loyalty,</HI> were it not known
to her Majesty, and even to the Dissenters Enemies that nothing has ever
been able to shake their Fidelity to the <HI>English</HI> Crown; and that their
Principles have never been Tainted with Disobedience or Disaffection,
either to the Persons or Government of our Protestant Princes.</P>
<P>Therefore as the worst of the Dissenters Enemies cannot suggest any thing
Undutiful of them, with the least Shadow of Reason; so they will be ef∣fectually
disappointed in their Expectations, that any Hardships put upon
the Dissenters, of what sort, or by what Means, Contrivance, or Procure∣ment
soever, will drive them, either by Word or Action, to express the least
Disrespect to her Majesty's Person or Government, much less to show any
Undutiful Disturbing, or factious Resentment.</P>
<P>Nor can the Appeal made to all the World in the Publication of these
Sheets, in Behalf of the Dissenters, signifie any such thing, being no
other than a setting the Case in a true Light; that, if possible, the Eyes
of the Nation's Representatives or Governours being open'd, they may
become Advocates for them, and humble Petitioners with them to her
Majesty, to repeal that Part of this Act that treats them in such a manner,
that they may no longer, <HI>without any Desert of their own,</HI> lie under so hea∣vy
a Burthen, as being misrepresented to their Prince, and being counted
Dangerous to that State they so zealously and ardently fought for, and en∣gag'd
their Lives and Fortunes to save.</P>
<P>2. <HI>Not Peace and Ʋnion.</HI> For as such a Law cannot but Sower and
Discompose the Parties, and make One side always regret the Wrong they
think done them; so on the other Hand, it rouzes the Evil Spirit of Ma∣lice
and Envy in those, who had before no Inclination to insult their Bre∣thren.
The Lord <HI>Falkland,</HI> in his Speech to the Parliament, tells them, that
the Church had destroy'd Union under Pretence of Uniformity. <HI>Rush. Coll.</HI>
Vol. 2. Fol. 1342. 'Tis plain, that there was no Strife of Parties before,
but <HI>Peace</HI> and <HI>Ʋnion</HI> were their Pleasure and their Boast.</P>
<P>If any shall attempt to tell us what a Learned Author advanc'd in <HI>Eng∣land,</HI>
that this would establish Peace and Union, it must be referr'd to the
Example of the North of <HI>Ireland,</HI> where this Law is likely to fill a peaceable
Nation with all the Constant, but Fatal Attendants of contending Parties,
to the Breach of that Union, Peace, Charity, and Temper which
reign'd in the Hearts of all her Majesty's Subjects, of what Perswasion
foever.</P>
<P><PB N="18" REF="22"/>
Certainly Oppression of Consciences, or Deprivation of Benefits for
the Sake of Conscience, can never be a means of uniting Parties. '<HI>Tis im∣possible</HI>
any Party can be easy to see known Loyalty of Principles suspect∣ed,
unbroken Duty and untainted Affection treated with Doubts, and
enacted against as dangerous.</P>
<P>Either the Dissenting Protestants of <HI>Ireland</HI> are dangerous to the Go∣vernment,
there is something to befear'd from-them, or the Act would be
preposterous, and there can be no Reason assign'd for the making it; and
joyning them with the Enemies of the Nation would be barbarous and un∣christian.
But the worst Enemy they have cannot charge them with One
Action, either in Memory or in History, in Modern or in Antient Time,
that can make them so much as look like Men dangerous to the Govern∣ment,
or from whom something is to be fear'd. <HI>Ergo</HI></P>
<P>If then this Act has divided those Protestants into Parties who were
united before, has fill'd them with Heats, Animosities and Repinings at
one another that were in perfect Peace before, will any Man say we are in
the wrong in saying among the Effects of this Bill negatively Not <HI>Peace</HI>
and <HI>Ʋnlon.</HI></P>
<P>Discontenting any one sort of People to please another, suppressing one
Part to raise another, setting one Party above another; these can ne∣ver
be made use of as Arguments to prove that Peace will be the Effect;
and above all it is plain it will never bring it to pass.</P>
<P>Peace and Union are the Native Produce of easy Laws, Plenty, and
Prosperity; People are apt to be pleased when they are easy, when they
enjoy their Rights, and when an Equality of the Government fways all
Parties; but if there is a Byass in the ruling Powers against or for one
Party more than another, 'tis natural for the oppress'd Party to envy or re∣pine
at the other. It breeds ill Blood, it boils in the Breast of the Party, and
'tis impossible it should be otherwise; and therefore 'tis not to be expect∣ed
that any of the Consequences of this Act can be Peace and Union.</P>
<P>3. <HI>Not the Increase of Trade.</HI> This is apparent, for that the People of
all Governments trade freest when they are easy. Trade always declines
in Governments where the People are not easy; and any one might see
it in <HI>London,</HI> during a certain time when a particular Bill was on-foot in
the House; Stocks, Publick Credit and Actions of Companies always rose
and fell as that Bill did or did not go forward in the House: What Joy in
Trade, what Rise of Stocks, what a Flux of Credit was in that Nation at
the Demise of that Bill!</P>
<P>We have indeed no Banks, <HI>East India</HI> Companies, or Publick Stocks
in <HI>Ireland</HI> to feel the sensible Injury done to Trade; but if any Man will
ask whether the Dissenters, who are some of the principle Traders in that
Kingdom, will launch out the farther, and embark the more heartily in
Trade for being Dishonour'd, Disfranchis'd, Disheartned and Supprest; it
is a Question that needs very little Answer, and what the meancst Un∣decrstanding
in the World would give a Negative to with little or no He∣sitation.</P>
<P>Can
it be, that the Dissenters should wish well to that Country, where
notwithstanding their constant steady Loyalty, their universal En∣gaging
in its Defence, the Expence of their Blood and Estates in opposing
Popery, they should be now suspected as dangerous to its Welfare, turn'd
out of all Honours, Trusts or Profits in the Neighbourhood, and look'd
upon as Persons unsafe to be trusted in any Publick Employment. Such
<PB N="19" REF="23"/>
Treatment can never be attractive of the Affections and the Love of the
Dissenters; they cannot study the Prosperity of a Country where they are
us'd with so much ungrateful Distinction.</P>
<P>If then their Affections to the Place may justly be chang'd by unkind
Treatment, the Transposing themselves, their Stocks and Families into o∣ther
Parts is a Consequence we may say more to afterwards; but the Trade
following the Traders by Consequence the Country will sink in its People,
Wealth, and Trade.</P>
<P>There are more Negatives which might be insisted on here, when we
are enquiring into the Consequences of this Act; as</P>
<P>4. <HI>No Reputation to the Church of Ireland,</HI> to Persecute those People of
whom the Arch-Bishop of <HI>Dublin</HI> has recorded in Print, that their Kindness
and Charity to her Clergy in their Flight and Distress deserves to be re∣member'd
to their Honour. Ingratitude can be no Reputation either to
a Party or Church, any more than to a single Person; and though the
Protestant Dissenters of <HI>Ireland</HI> do acquit the Church <HI>as such</HI> of contriving
this Hardship, yet the Scandal will for ever lie on the Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI>
so far as they dip their Hands in the unhappy <HI>if rigorous</HI> Execution
of it.</P>
<P>Nor will this ever tend to the Reputation of the Govern—- of <HI>Ire∣land.</HI>—To
say they were impos'd upon any where is to say nothing; for
though 'tis not a Man's Fault that he is impos'd upon, 'tis a Disreputation
to him to be impos'd on: And the farther those Arguments are true which
acquit the Gentry and the Church of <HI>Ireland</HI> of designing this Mischief to
the Protestant Dissenters, the farther this Disreputation of their Conduct
will appear.</P>
<P>If they had no Hand in the Contrivance of this Clause, if it was sent
back with that Clause incerted without the Privity or Knowledge of any
of the Governing Party in this Kingdom, either in Church or State, this
may acquit them of Ingratitude to the Dissenters, but it can never acquit
them of being impos'd upon somewhere: And if they had furnish'd
themselves with Courage and Honour enough to have represented back
the Services, the Fidelity and Loyalty of the Dissenters, and their Debt
of Kindness and Charity to them; if all this had been laid before her
Majesty, we cannot doubt but such Orders would have been given by her
Majesty's Gracious Direction as are suitable to that Tenderness she has al∣ways
express'd to her People in General, and as we know to be the Innate
and Heredirary Quality of our Sovereign.</P>
<P>Nay had our Clergy represented to the Right Honourable the E... of
<HI>N.</HI> then Secretary of State, and through whose Hands this Law, with this
unhappy additional Clause must pass, had they represented to his Lordsnip
the Kindness, Charity and Goodness which the Dissenters shew'd to their
persecuted Brethren, rccorded, as is noted, by the Arch-Bishop of <HI>Duhlin;</HI> had
they reminded him that his Lordship's <HI>Imprimatur</HI> is to the Book, and that
himself pass'd it into the World; that his Lordship has thereby own'd to
all the World that <HI>it ought to be remember'd of the Dissenters to their Ho∣nour,</HI>
that they reliev'd the Clergy of the Church in their Suffering with∣out
Distinction—-had his Lordship been referr'd back to this Testimon<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
under his own Hand, he is a Gentleman of too much Justice and Honour
ever to have forwarded such a Bill, without humbly laying it before her
Majesty, that to his Knowledge they deserv'd better Treatment.</P>
<P><PB N="20" REF="24"/>
It can therefore never be reckon'd up to the Honour and Reputation of
the G.....t or Clergy in <HI>Ireland,</HI> that they should represent the Case
to the Court of <HI>England,</HI> use their Interest to obtain such a Remission
as, in Gratitude for Service done, and Love express'd, they ow'd to
the Dissenters. And all we can say for them on that Head, is
the great Concern they were in for the Loss of the Needful Security a∣gainst
Popery, together with Resolutions to make the Dissenters some fu∣ture
Amends, which may something extenuate the thing.</P>
<P>5. Another Negative may be thus express'd. This will certainly be no
Encouragement to the Dissenters to joyn with their Brethren in their mu∣tual
Defence the next time the Papists shall please to take Arms, and at∣tempt
their Throats.</P>
<P>Not but that perhaps they may be Fools enough, as they always were, to stand
in the Gap, and 'tis plain they have actually sav'd the Church of <HI>Ireland</HI> from
Ruin; but it cannot be that they have any Arguments to move them to
it from this Bill. If they had no other Inducements, they could never be
thought to be mov'd to it from this Law.</P>
<P>If ever the Papists in <HI>Ireland</HI> should rebel and commence a new Massa∣cre,
as 'tis known they have good Will enough to do, and the Protestants
of the Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI> taking Arms to defend themselves, should say
to the Dissenters, Come <HI>help the Lord against the Mighty;</HI> and the Dissen∣ters
should say, “No, Gentlemen, we are not fit to be trusted, we were
not fit to be Mayors or Justices; Custom-house or Excise Officers, Aldermen
or Common-Councilmen for Fear of the Growth of Popery, pray take
Care of it your selves; we were not to be trusted with Commissions in
your Army, or your Country <HI>Militia,</HI> pray fight by your selves; we
were not to be intrusted in your Stores, pray be your own Gunners;
we'll have no Hand in it; you are able no doubt to beat the <HI>Irish</HI> with∣ont
us, pray don't trouble us about it, 'tis none of our Business, you
took it out of our Hands by Act of Parliament.</P>
<P>We are content to appeal to all the World whether such an Answer as
this would not be <HI>Lex Talionis,</HI> would not be fair and just in the Dissen∣ters;
and whether indeed, all things consider'd, they ought not to act thus,
and answer thus, if ever the Case came to the Crisis, and they should be
tried as they have been already—- Would not all the World call them
Fools, to do any thing again that merits <HI>to be remember'd to their Honour</HI>—If
this be the Church's Method of <HI>remembring Favours,</HI> if this be their
<HI>Returns of Gratitude,</HI> let them fight for them next time that dare trust
their Temper.</P>
<P>And here, with Submission, there appears some Inconsistency in the ve∣ry
Act it self; and the Consequences of this Bill still as to Negatives will
be really,</P>
<P>6. No preventing the Growth of Popery. Will any Man in the World
tell us, that <HI>To divide Protestants is a way to prevent the further Growth of
Popery.</HI> This is like sinking the Ship to drown the Rats—like Cutting
off the Foot to cure the Corns. To divide Protestants is to weaken them,
or else our Saviour was a false Prophet; and can weakening the Protestant
Interest be a way to prevent the Growth of Popery?</P>
<P>This would merit some Satyr if the Case was not really too sad and se∣rious
to bear a Banter. If these are Church of <HI>Ireland</HI> Politicks, for Shame
Gentlemen never reproach the Native <HI>Irish</HI> for winking when they shoot,
for never Marks-men took such Aim as this. 'Tis such a <HI>Tale of a Tub</HI> the
<PB N="21" REF="25"/>
very <HI>Irish</HI> themselves must of Necessity laugh at it; and where
as we have been told they were in Hopes this Clause would break the Bill,
divide the House, and so the Bill be lost, we are of Opinion they ought
to have acquiesc'd and forwarded the passiug the Bill for the Sake of this
Clause; for what could be of more Service to the Popish Interest in that
Kingdom than to see the Protestants thus divided, persecuting, distrusting
and disobliging one another—To see that Party suppress'd, trampl'd
on and dissatisfied who were always the dead Weight against Popery, from
whom they received the most Power and Shot, and by whom they were
always worst handled—This certainly ought to have comforted them,
made them hope for a Restoration of their Affairs with more Proba∣billity
than ever, and might be thought a sufficient Satisfaction to them
for all the other Disappointments of that Bill.</P>
<P>How can it but be an inexpressible Satisfaction and Pleasure to the <HI>Irish</HI>
Papists, who wish all the <HI>English</HI> Protestants out of the Kingdom, to see a
great many of the richest and most trading Inhabitants draw in their Ef∣fects,
remit their Money to other Places, follow it with their Fa∣milies;
and a Law made by their Fellow Protestants, which making them
uneasy is the Occasion of it all.</P>
<P>If it be answer'd, the Church Party are strong enough to take Care of
the <HI>Irish</HI> without the Dissenters, this opens the Door to a very unhappy
Argument against them, <HI>Then what need of the Act;</HI> if there was no Occa∣sion
for it, <HI>Why was it made?</HI> And this would cause the Church of <HI>Ireland</HI>
to run the Risque of being charg'd with some special Malice, to make a
Law so grievous to their Brethren, so unkind, and so otherwise ill circum∣stanc'd,
without any manner of Occasion for it; wherefore we choose to
dismiss that Answer as a vain Pretence, and bring it to matter of Truth.</P>
<P>That there is Occasion in the Kingdom of <HI>Ireland</HI> to prevent the Growth
of Popery.</P>
<P>That the united Force of all the Protestants in <HI>Ireland</HI> is necessary to
discourage and keep it down, and all little enough.</P>
<P>And if so, then 'tis a great Encouragement to the Growth of Popery
to divide and disunite the Protestants; and consequently, the Act disagrees
with it self, it pulls down in one part what it builds up in another; the
Whole is inconsistent with the Parts, and incoherent with the Title.</P>
<P>'Tis time to have done with the Negatives. The Affirmative Conse∣quences
of this matter are many, and time may make them appear to be
more than yet they seem to be; some of them have been toucht in their
Contraries.</P>
<P>1. Persecution for Conscience Sake, which whatever may have been pre∣tended,
has been in all Ages allow'd to be contrary to the Principles of
the Christian Religion, and is Publickly disown'd and disapprov'd by the
Church of <HI>England,</HI> which is allow'd to be the Parent and Nursing Mother
of the Church of <HI>Ireland.</HI> To persecute for the Sake of a Conscientious
Difference, as it has no Scriptural Authority so it has no Humane Autho∣rity
to give it any Colour of a Law, or to make it agreeable to the Minds
of Men—- And therefore when we call it Persecution, we find none of
the Church pretend to justify the Article of Persecution as lawful; but they
would come off here by proving, that this is not Persecution; because, say
they, we allow you the Liberty of all Religious Worship your own Way.</P>
<P>The Answer to this is so unhappily plain, that sad and most pitiful
Shifts are made to evade it.</P>
<P><PB N="22" REF="26"/>
Persecution, if we understand it right, is punishing any Person or Peo∣ple
for not complying with, or conforming to, some Particular of Divine
Worship, or some Article of Religion which that Power that persecutes
demands a Conformity to.</P>
<P>Now if those Gentlemen, who will not have these things go under the
Title of Persecution, will tell us that to turn all the Dissenters out of
Places of Honour, Trust and Profit for not complying with the Sacrament,
is not punishing them for not complying with some Particular of Divine
Worship, they will come to a Necessity of proving One of these Two
things.</P>
<P>1. That inflicting Penalties is no Punishment. Or,
2. That the Sacrament is no Particular of Divine Worship, or no Re∣ligious
Act.</P>
<P>Any Man would be glad to see either of these Two points so answer'd,
as that this Cause might be clear'd from the Scandal, and the Church of
<HI>Ireland</HI> be acquitted from practicing that Persecution which her Principle
disowns.</P>
<P>2. The second Consequence, which any wise Man may foresee must
follow this Matter is <HI>Division</HI>—The Effects of that capacious Word are
too many and too long, to be describ'd.</P>
<P>Divisions have too long afflicted these unhappy Nations to leave us in
any Degree Strangers to their ill Consequences. The Queen's Majesty, in
all her late most Excellent Speeches to her Parliament, has given us true
Ideas of the fatal Effect of Divisions, and Breaches in the Union of a Na∣tion;
and sufficiently warn'd all her Subjects, were they a People capable
of Warning, against all the Circumstances that lead to such an Evil.</P>
<P>The Union of Protestants in <HI>Ireland,</HI> till now, was very remarkable;
some hints have been given of it in this Tract, and much more might
be said on that pleasant Subject; but the Discontents that begin already
to show their ill Aspects, and cloud and eclipse the Beauty and Lustre of
that Light, how many, how numberless are they! and what a black Pro∣spect
have we still of those behind!</P>
<P>To divide the Protestant Interest is to weaken it, to weaken that is to
strengthen its contrary, Popery; and what can be a more fatal Blow to
the general Good of that Nation.</P>
<P>Capt. <HI>Lawrence,</HI> a Learned and a Sensible Gentleman, who wrote of,
and very well understood the Interest of <HI>Ireland,</HI> has this very apt Notion
of the Interest of <HI>Ireland;</HI> and with that we shall end this Discourse.</P>
<P>“But that which would, above all other Expedients, tend to the
strengthning the <HI>English</HI> Interest in <HI>Ireland,</HI> would be to endeavour a
right Understanding and charitable Union between all sober pious Pro∣testants
in matters of Religion, the Want of which increaseth ground∣lefs
Jealousies of each other, and strengthneth the Confidence of the
common Enemy of the Protestant Interest, that they are easily run down,
as in the Massacre 1641. when at first they declar'd their Design was a∣gainst
the Puritannical Party, then against the <HI>English,</HI> not the <HI>Scots:</HI> But I
suppose I need not inform you how soon all Protestants became equal Ob∣jects
of their Fury and barbarous Cruelty. <HI>Law. Int. Ireland.</HI> pag. 99”</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1>
<PB N="23" REF="27"/>
<HEAD>CONCLUSION
To the Church of Ireland.</HEAD>
<OPENER>Gentlemen,</OPENER>
<P>YOUR Protestant Brethren, the Dissenters of this Kingdom, tho' not
personally acquainted with the Publication of these Sheets, are
here represented your humble Suppliants for the Testimonies of Loyalty
and Peaceable Behaviour, due from you in Justice to Truth, and Honour to
your selves.</P>
<P>These Innocents allied to you in Blood, united to you in one Faith,
Doctrine, and Redeemer, often your Companions in Sufferings for the
same Religion, the same Liberty, and the same Country; your Fellows in
Arms for the Defence of this Kingdom, and Sharers with you in the Joy
of the same Conquests; your Partners in the many Blessings of the Revo∣lution,
and interested with you in the Favour and mighty Protection of
the same Defender King <HI>William,</HI> always thought they should, with mutual
Satisfaction, enioy with you their Share of the immortal Blessings of Peace,
purchas'd under the Valour and Conduct of that Prince, by the joint
Concurrence of the Protestant Power, undistinguish'd as to Party, Profes∣sion,
or Opinion.</P>
<P>'Tis with insinite Regret they see the Endeavours of their Ene∣mies
to render them suspected to you, too successful; and those Laws,
which were introduced for the Security of this Nation, pointed at them
in Company with the Capital Enemies of <HI>Ireland.</HI> They cannot believe
the Church of <HI>Ireland as such</HI> could entertain a Thought so destructive to
the general Welfare, as the loading the Dissenters with Crimes, which, by
God's Grace, they never were, or will be guilty of; or be so unkind as to e∣nact
against them as Criminal, while under the authentick Testimonies of
Loyalty and Good Services done to your whole Body, as well as the Go∣vernment,
they have an Acknowledgment of their extraordinary Zeal
for the Safety of both.</P>
<P>They are therefore rather enclined to suppose they shall meet with Ease
and Redress of this Burthen from your Hands, than that you will show
your selves so much as enclin'd to lay any Hardship upon them; and the
Design of these Sheets is but in an humble Manner to expostulate with
you on their Behalf, that from the Sence of their Merit, their past Servi∣ces
and known Loyalty, you would become humble Intercessors with them,
and for them, to their Sovereign, that such part of this Pressure as, your
own Justice and Honour shall dictate to you they have not deserv'd, may
be taken off; and that the Church may not lie under the Reflection of ha∣ving
enjoy'd the Advantage of their Sufferings and Faithful Services, with∣out
suitable Returns to the People, who have, by your own Acknowledg∣ment,
merited to be remember'd by you to their Honour.</P>
<P>Next, and immediately after the Arguments in this Case, drawn from
the Principles of Charity, Neighbourhood, Christian-love, and the Sence
of Merit, known in some Countries by the Name of Common Gratitude,
the Author of these Sheets humbly desires, in the Name of the whole Body
<PB N="24" REF="28"/>
of the Dissenters in <HI>Ireland,</HI> that all those Gentlemen of the Church of
<HI>Ireland,</HI> who may be enclined to acquiese in the Hardships put upon their
Dissenting Brethren would be pleas'd to consider</P>
<P>1. <HI>Their own Interests.</HI> And 1. Whether upon the Emergency of any fu∣ture
Insolence, Rebellion, or Insurrection of the Native <HI>Irish,</HI> whether
back'd by Foreign Alliance, or not, they are able of themselves, without
the Assistance of these dangerous Protestants, call'd Dissenters, to oppose,
sight, conquer, and reduce the said Native <HI>Irish.</HI></P>
<P>2. Whether if it be true that the Native <HI>Irish</HI> and Papists, by com∣mon
Calculation are Eight to One against the <HI>Brittish</HI> and Protestants in
that Kingdom, speaking inclusively of all sorts of Dissenters: The said
<HI>Irish, &amp;c.</HI> would not be above Sixteen to One, in Case all sorrs of Dissen∣ters
are excluded from every Part of the Defence, and laid by either as
Neuters, or as Enemies.</P>
<P>3. Whether, allow the <HI>Irish</HI> to be worse Cowards and Scoundrels than
ever they yet appeared, whether they think it possible to fight them with
the Inequality of One to Sixteen.</P>
<P>2. <HI>Justice.</HI> Whether it be reasonable to expect the Dissenters, who, in
time of Peace, and without Provocation, are enacted against as dangerous
Enemies, and not thought fit to be trusted with Posts of Profit, should be
concern'd in Case of Rebellion and War to accept of Places of Hazards,
and embark in the Defence of those People who treated them so un∣kindly.</P>
<P>3.
Past Actions. Whether ever the Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI> when oppress'd
or insulted by the <HI>Irish,</HI> were able to defend themselves against them, with∣out
the Help of their Dissenting Brethren?</P>
<P>4. Whether they found them backward in such time of Distress to ven∣ture
their Fortunes and Blood for the general Preservation? And whether
by right of War they have not an equal Claim to the Privileges of that
Peace they help'd to obtain.</P>
<P>If we might be allow'd here to expostulate with the Church of <HI>Ireland,</HI>
it should be to ask them, Gentlemen, do you think the Papists are likely
ever to renounce their old Principles of Hatred against the <HI>English,</HI> as a
Nation; or that upon every Opportunity they should not be very forward
to put in Practice the former Rage against the Protestant Interest in ge∣neral;
whether, when they find an Occasion to put this in Practice, either
by Insurrection, General Massacre, or any other publick or private Me∣thod,
they will distinguish Church Protestants from Dissenting Prote∣stants.</P>
<P>We
desire, with all Modesty and possible Respect, to ask whether you
do not seem to express a greater Confidence in the Dissenters on one Hand,
than is consistent with the Distrust and Diffidence on the other Hand,
which must be suppos'd to make it rational, that they should be enacted a∣gainst
in the same Law with Papists and Enemies to the Government; and
whether you do not seem hereby to own, that we are more Loyal to the
Government, and True to the Protestant Interest than your selves, in that
you venture to put the highest Indignity, Reproach and Affront upon us,
and thereby presume we are by no ill Treatment to be provoked so much
as to stand Neuter when your Defence requires our Assistance, much less
that you should think, weshall on any Terms be brought to joyn with the
Papists in your Destruction.</P>
<P><PB N="25" REF="29"/>
We would be glad you would reconcile these two palpable Contradicti∣ons;
and would willingly know, whether, if after all this Treatment,
the next time the Papists of this Kingdom shall think fit to insult you, and
the Dissenters fall in, and with the Hazards of their Lives, Estates, and
all that is dear to them, defend you, whether you will not blush at this
Bill, and enter your Acknowledgment upon Record, as it is already, that
these Things ought to be remembred to their Honour?</P>
<P>It cannot be defended by the Rules of Charity, Christian-Love, and
Good Neighbourhood, any more than it can from the Rules of Justice
or Policy, that the Dissenters should be thus treated; since they,
especially those of them who now inhabit the Northern Parts of the King∣dom,
came to you as Fellow-Planters and Settlers of Collonies, in the
Beginning of the Peopling this Nation by the <HI>Brittish</HI> Protestants; and
consequently, have equal Right of Liberty and Settlement as your selves;
or else came hither as Auxiliaries, as indeed they have ever since prov'd,
and as your Assistants against your Enemies; and have thereby obtain'd a
Right of Settlement and Liberty by Treaties and Capitulations, which
ought not to be violated or invaded.</P>
<P>Upon all these Considerations, and many more, of which they save to
themselves the Liberty of reminding you, as Occasion requires, they desire
to lay before you calmly and sedately; and in all Tenderness and Charity
the Hardship, and, as they think, Injustice of thos Gentlemen, who think
they merit such severe Treatment.</P>
<P>They humbly appeal to your certain Knowledge in their constant Beha∣viour,
and in the Truth of every Article insisted on in this Book: And the
Author of this Tract is not afraid to take upon him the Demonstration of
all the Particulars; and to recommend them, in Bealf of the Dissenters, to
the Gentlemen of the Church, as their Fellows, in all possible degrees of
Right to the Peace of this Nation; and most earnestly to desire their
serious Considerations of the Indignities, Injuries and Oppressions they al∣ready
suffer, and are likely yet farther to suffer on this Account.</P>
<P>And thus they are your humble Petitioners, that from a Sence of Justice,
Gratitude, and Christian Charity, as you know the Dissenters innocent of
any thing to merit being treated severely, from a Sence of Interest, Pru∣dence,
and Civil Polity, as there is more than ordinary Occasion of a sirm
Union among all Protestants for the mutual Defence of themselves and the
Nation; and as you would encourage the Dissenters, and expect of them
to assist you in Case of any future Dangers from the Publick Enemy, and
from a Sence of the Christian Obligation of Charity and Forbearance,
which in all Cases declares against Coertion or Punishments in Cases of
Conscieuce, and from many other Reasons, as well Civil as Religious, too
long to be here enumerated, <HI>You would be pleased</HI> to become humble Inter∣cessors
with her Majesty, and the Parliament of this Kingdom, for the Re∣peal
of that part of the Clause, and Remission of that part of this Act,
which they have just Reason to complain is grievous to them, as Protestant
Dissenters; and against the Honourable Remembrance of their former Loy∣alty
and Services; and that they may no longer be reckoned among the
Nations Enemies, and enacted against as People dangerous and suspected,
at least till by some disloyal or disaffected Behaviour, which they trust will
never be found on them, they shall have done fomething to forseit the
Title of, as well as the Protection, which all Governments think due to,
faithful and peaceable Subjects.</P>
<P><PB N="26" REF="30"/>
Thus you will effectually secure this Kingdom against the Growth of
Popery, by firmly uniting the Hearts and Hands of all her Majesty's Pro∣testant
Subjects, in the vigorous Defence both of her Person and Govern∣ment;
and in that blessed Peace and Union, which her Majesty has, on all
Occasions, declared to be her pious Desire, and has so often recommended
to all her Subjects.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>
