<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet TYPE="text/css" href="http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE><DATE>yyyy-mm-dd</DATE><RESPSTMT><NAME>[name of reviewer]</NAME><RESP>MURP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM></CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>

<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K049437.000">
<STC T="C">T055487</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3304778123</BIBNO>
<VID>0533301800</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>Reflections
ON THE
<HI>Prohibition Act:</HI>
WHEREIN
The Necessity, Usefulness and
Value of that LAW, are Evinced
and Demonstrated.</P>
<P>In ANSWER to a
Letter <HI>on that</HI> Subject,
From a Gentleman concern'd in
TRADE▪</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed in the Year, MDCCVIII.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1>
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>REFLECTIONS
ON THE
Prohibition Act.</HEAD>
<OPENER>London, <DATE>Jan. 10. 1707-08.</DATE>
<SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>BY yours of the first Instant, you require
my Opinion about the <HI>Prohibition Act,</HI>
in Terms manifestly indicating your
Fear and Concern least we should be deprived
of it. I know not what Reasons you may have
for such Apprehensions; and perhaps You and
I never differ'd more then in the Matter of the
present Subject; about which I shall honestly
and plainly give you my Thoughts, and handle
the Point with that Freedom and Sincerity
which the Weight of the Subject deserves, be∣ing
under no Restriction that I know of to the
contrary. To which Purpose I shall lay down
the Two following Positions.</P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="3"/>
I. That the Act of Parliament prohibiting
the Use of the Manufactured Silks, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> of <HI>In∣dia,
China,</HI> and <HI>Persia,</HI> in this Nation, is one
of the happiest and best Laws we enjoy, re∣lating
to Trade.</P>
<P>II. That we are not in any Danger of losing
it; that is to say, that it is not like to be Re∣pealed;
but on the contrary, will stand firm
and unshaken to future Ages, notwithstanding
the Designs and Attempts of all its Adver∣saries.</P>
<P>1.
That the <HI>Prohibition Act</HI> is one of the
happiest and best Laws we enjoy relating to
Trade.</P>
<P>To prove this, there is nothing further Ne∣cessary
then to consider the Circumstance and
Condition of the <HI>English</HI> Manufactures for the
Space of six or seven Years before and after
that Law took Place, and fairly to compare
them together; by which the Necessity, as
well as the Usefulness of that seasonable Act,
will evidently appear, to all unbiased and un∣prejudiced
Persons.</P>
<P>The Places where these Manufactures, <HI>before
the late Inundation of</HI> India <HI>Goods,</HI> more espe∣cially
flourished, were <HI>London, Canterbury</HI> and
<HI>Norwich;</HI> together with the Counties of <HI>Essex,
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
Suffolk, Norfolk, Hartford</HI> and <HI>Cambridge,</HI> whose
Employment chiefly consisted in making <HI>Yarn</HI>
for <HI>London</HI> and <HI>Norwich.</HI></P>
<P>As to <HI>London,</HI> the Manufactures were almost
lost by the coming in of <HI>East India</HI> Goods, for
divers Years before the obtaining of the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rohi∣bition;</HI>
the Tradesman generally undone, whole
Streets uninhabited, many of our best Artists
left the Kingdom; some went to <HI>Holland,</HI> some
to <HI>Ireland,</HI> others to <HI>Scotland.</HI> Those that re∣main'd
were not half employ'd; the rest redu∣ced
to the greatest Extremities, of whom many
begged their Bread, and were forced to be main∣tain'd
by their Parishes.</P>
<P>And if it fared thus with <HI>London,</HI> it could
not be much better with <HI>Norwich,</HI> whose Nu∣merous
Families had nothing to depend on, but
their own Manufactures, which those of <HI>India</HI>
so directly oppose: No wonder therefore if the
former sunk, whilst the other prevail'd, and
less wonder still, they should so heartily join
with the Manufacturers of <HI>London</HI> to seek Re∣lief
<HI>where it was only to be had.</HI></P>
<P>As for <HI>Canterbury,</HI> the Misery of the People
at the Time I speak of, was scarce to be cre∣dited,
their Manufacture was intirely lost and
given up, the Manufacturers fled from their
Habitations in such Multitudes, that at the
Time the <HI>Prohibition Act</HI> passed, that famous
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
City was reduced from <HI>near a Thousand, to
about Fifty Looms.</HI></P>
<P>The Counties before-mention'd, depending
chiefly upon <HI>London</HI> and <HI>Norwich,</HI> for buying
up their <HI>Yarn,</HI> bore an equal Share in the Com∣mon
Calamity, were left without Employment,
some turning themselves to new Ways of get∣ting
their Bread, others seeking for it in Foreign
Countries, leaving their Wives and Children to
the Parishes; by which Means we were not only
strip'd of the Profitable Labour of many thou∣sand
Hands, <HI>the least of which is of more Value
to this Nation than all the Manufactured Silks of</HI>
India, China <HI>and</HI> Persia, but were forced to con∣vey
both our <HI>Art and our Hands</HI> to Foreign
Countries, unhappily teaching them to fight us
at our own Weapons, and to be Masters of <HI>all
our Mystery, and all our Trade at the<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame Time.</HI>
And of what Consequence this might have been
to <HI>Great Britain,</HI> woful Experience would be∣fore
this have taught us all, had not the Legi∣slative
Power intervened, and prevented <HI>us by
this happy, seasonable and useful Act.</HI></P>
<P>Let us now take a View of the present State
and Condition of Trade in the Places and Coun∣ties
aforemention'd, that were thus Sunk, De∣serted
and Depopulated by these <HI>Indian Manu∣factures.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="7" REF="6"/>
And tho' it must be own'd that the Space of
<HI>Eighteen Months</HI> given by the Act to the Deal∣ers
in those Commodities, to dispose of the va<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t
Quantities of them which were then in the Na∣tion,
together with the Influence of the Com∣panies,
and the Bent of all Sorts and Degrees of
People towards these Goods, did necessarily
suspend for some Time the Design and Influence
of this Law; yet, God be thanked, the Time
is now come, when all Men that do not shut
their Eyes, both see and feel the Benefit and
Advantage of it. It cannot be expected that any
Thing in the World can restore the Manufa∣ctures
of <HI>Great Britain</HI> to their full Advantage
and Height, so long as the War continues; and
we must be all content to submit to the Common
Inconveniencies, till Peace be restored to <HI>Europe.</HI>
But as far as our present Circumstances will ad∣mit,
this seasonable Act has relieved us; and I
dare adventure to say, effectually too, as plainly
appears in the following Instances.</P>
<P>In <HI>London,</HI> the Maker has a Market for his
Goods, Artists and Work-men <HI>are return'd from
the Places of their Dispersion, and find a full Em∣ployment
for all their Hands; the empty Streets
and Houses are again Inhabited,</HI> and higher
Rents paid for them than before. <HI>Several New
Species</HI> of Manufactures set up, and every Day
<HI>increasing and improving upon our Hands;</HI> a great
Part of which are Exported to our Neighbours,
and as much in Vogue with them as they are in
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
Fashion with us: And I doubt not, but the
Export of these Goods will be much higher yet,
if we continue the general Use and Fashion of
them at Home; for it must always be noted,
<HI>That Fashions generally reach as far as the Hon∣our
and Reputation of a Nation Influenceth,</HI> of
which we have too pregnant an Instance in a
Neighbouring Country.</P>
<P><HI>Norwich</HI> gets up again apace; they have a
Market for their Goods, and Employment for
their Hands, and their Circumstance being the
same, it fares with them just as it does with
<HI>London. They fell,</HI> and Thanks be to God and
our Legislators, <HI>they are risen together.</HI></P>
<P>The Case must needs be the same also with
Respect to the several Counties, whose Employ∣ment
depends upon <HI>London</HI> and <HI>Norwich,</HI> as
before was noted; so that there needs nothing
more to be Remarked in Relation to them, then
that <HI>their Affairs are Restored and Retrieved in
an exact Proportion to that of those Two great
Marts.</HI></P>
<P>As for <HI>Canterbury,</HI> the Influence of this Act
is more visibly seen there, than in any Place in
the Nation. <HI>That City was even become Deso∣late;
they are now return'd to their Homes,</HI> as
as before they left them, <HI>in Shoals and Compa∣<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</HI>
Their Houses and their Bellies are full.
They rather want Hands then Work; <HI>and
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
there is at this Day neither Complaint nor Decay
amongst them for lack of Employment.</HI></P>
<P>We ought now to consider this Law as it
Effects the Nation in general, <HI>in its Merchan∣dizes,
Manufactures and Lands.</HI> But I must be
very short in these Particulars. And I think I
need take Notice of the <HI>Turky</HI> and <HI>Italian</HI> Mer∣chants
only, under the first Head; who like all
other Exporters, <HI>cannot possibly carry their Trade
farther than the Vend of their Imports will Sup∣port.</HI>
And I take <HI>it to be Demonstration that
these Gentlemen must long since have laid down
the greatest Part of their Business, if this Law
had not interven'd.</HI> Our Silken Manufacture at
Home was both supplanted and supplied by <HI>In∣dian</HI>
Goods. Upon which Account we could
have no Demand or Occasion for Raw Silks
from <HI>Turky</HI> and <HI>Italy,</HI> and setting that Commo∣dity
aside, there are no other Effects in those
Countries, sufficient to carry on a Valuable
Trade, that can be disposed of in <HI>Great Britain.</HI>
So that we are intirely indebted to this Act for
the most, both of our Exports and Imports,
to and from those Places; the Advantage and
Profit of which redounds to the Manufacturer as
well as to the Merchant; so that we are at
once beholding to this Law, under the present
Head of our Consideration, for the Circulation
of our Money, the Preservation of onr Com∣merce,
and the Employment of our People.
But there are other Advantages that attend this
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
Act, which the People of <HI>Leeds, Halifax, Wake∣field,
Beedal,</HI> and other Places in <HI>Yorkshire</HI> par∣take
of; where New Manufactures are set up
for <HI>Tar<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> great Quantities of which are sent
every Week to <HI>London</HI> and <HI>Norwich,</HI> and are
there Manufactured. Many other Places like∣wise
in <HI>Great Britain</HI> have begun other Manu∣factures,
which are like to prove more or less
Profitable, according to the Skill of the Di∣rectors;
all Hands here find Work. There is
no want in these Places of publick Work-Houses
for the Willing Labourer of any Sex,
Age or Condition.</P>
<P>It would be wasting of Time to shew that
that this Law is of great Advantage to the
Landed Men of the Nation. I am perswaded
there is not one Gentleman of an Estate in it,
that is not throughly convinced of the Truth of
the Assertion. But that nothing may pass <HI>Gra∣tis
dictum,</HI> let it only be consider'd, That this
Island can neither increase nor support its
Riches, but by Trade and Commerce. This is
the Life and Blood of the Nation, which as
from the Heart, disperseth and communicates
Vigour and Influence to the Whole, and every
Branch and Member of it. And so far as this
Law has retriev'd, reviv'd and improv'd our
Manufactures, so far as it has enabled us to con∣tinue
and increase our Profitable Exports, and
the Produce of them; so far as it has recalled
our Exiles, and strengthen'd our Hands, <HI>so far
<PB N="11" REF="10"/>
it has advantaged our Lands,</HI> increased our
Rents, and enabled the Tenants to pay both
the QUEEN and the Landlord. I hope
there is now enough said, and nothing said but
Matter of Fact, to support and establish my first
Position concerning the Usefulness and Value
of this happy Law; and there is nothing left
under this Head, but to return our just Ac∣knowledgments
to those Worthy Patriots, who
received so kindly <HI>the Application of the Distres∣sed;</HI>
apprehended so clearly <HI>the Cause of their
Misery;</HI> relieved so seasonably <HI>a sinking People,</HI>
and establish'd so firmly <HI>this glorious Law.</HI> May
the Blessings of Heaven attend them and their
Posterity, and be as lasting as the happy Effects
of this Act.</P>
<P>It is time now to establish the second Positi∣on.
And the very repeating of it, will I hope
make the Task easie enough. It runs thus.</P>
<P>2. We are not in any Danger of losing this
Act, that is to say, it is not like to be Re∣peal'd:
But on the contrary, will stand firm
and unshaken to future Ages, notwithstanding
the Designs and Attempts of its Adversaries.</P>
<P>I. And first I think this Act will stand by
reason of its own intrinsick Worth and Value.</P>
<P>II. Because its Enemies are few.</P>
<P><PB N="12" REF="11"/>
III. Because they who shall attempt to Repeal
it, may find the Task more Difficult then they
are aware of.</P>
<P>IV. Because of the Misery and Desolation the
Repealing it would occasion.</P>
<P>1. As to the first Reason why the Act should
stand, I need not say any Thing here; the
whole foregoing Discourse, being a Demonstra∣tion
of its Worth, Value and Usefulness to this
Nation.</P>
<P>2. And as to the second Reason, unless the
Ladies be reckon'd in the Number, I believe
the Assertion is actually and literally true. <HI>Few
doubtless they are, if compared with the Number
or Value of those for whose sake the Bill was
Enacted;</HI> I speak Politically, for by the latter,
<HI>I mean not only the Manufactures, but the whole
Nation.</HI> After all, I am more at a loss to know
who <HI>are Enemies to this Law,</HI> then in concern
for their Numbers. I know the Cause of Fear,
were it freely own'd, can proceed from nothing
but <HI>the Strength and Influence of the Companies.</HI>
But I must crave leave to say, that People may
fear where no Fear is, and fancy they are in
Danger, when no body designs to hurt them;
and excepting some Rumors about the Town,
perhaps industriously spread Abroad, to try the
Temper of the People; I have good reason to
believe <HI>this to be the true State of the Matter.</HI>
<PB N="13" REF="12"/>
The <HI>East-India</HI> Companies are made up of the
Wealthiest Merchants and Gentry of the Nati∣on,
who have large Estates, and great Stakes in
the Government: I hope most of them, I am
sure some of them, have the Welfare and Pros∣perity
of their Country more at Heart than to
to Wish, much less to Endeavour <HI>the Repealing
to this Act;</HI> and it is my real Opinion, that
there is no such Design on Foot, <HI>I cannot think
so hardly</HI> of these Gentlemen, and there can be
no Danger from any other Quarter. But sup∣posing,
not allowing the worst of the Case, I
must still add,</P>
<P>3. Even the united Company it self, Strong
and Potent as it is, might, and I hope would
miscarry in the Attempt. The Matter in con∣test
would then be, <HI>Whether the Nation should
sink that the Company might rise? Whether the
Staple Manufactures of</HI> Great Britain <HI>should be
once more destroyed, to exalt the tempting Excesses
of</HI> India, China <HI>and</HI> Persia? <HI>Whether our best Ar∣tists
should make a Second Experiment to Instruct
our Neighbours in our Mis<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ries and Improve∣ments,
that we may strave more Luxuriously in</HI>
Indian-<HI>Habits? Whether we should Empty our
selves of our Numbers and Strength to make more
room for prohibited Goods? And whether the
whole must be Impoverish'd to Enrich a few?</HI> If
these Things can be digested, such an Attempt
might possibly prevail. But in the mean time,
I think we are safe enough; and I think we are
<PB N="14" REF="13"/>
so, <HI>because we are safe in the Honour and Justice
of our Legislators.</HI> Those that made this Law
have Power to preserve it; and the Value of it
is too precious to part with for such Gugaws as
we must have in Exchange for it; especially
when by loosing it, we intail upon the Nation
such <HI>a deluge of Miseries</HI> as are hinted above.
Not that all the Misfortunes that would come
upon us are there enumerated; there are others
yet behind that would effectually do our Busi∣ness,
and render us as compleatly miserable as
our Grand Enemy could wish, and our own
Folly deserve. Of these I will only mention
Three, as so many standing Arguments for my
Fourth Reason why this Act will not be Re∣pealed,
<HI>viz.</HI> Because of the Misery and Desola∣tion
it would occasion.</P>
<P>4. These Three Misfortunes are the carrying
out of all our Bullion. The suddenness of the
Blow; and the probable Consequences of it.</P>
<P>It cannot be denyed that the present Trade to
<HI>India,</HI> under all its Restrictions, <HI>requires an Ex∣port
of Bullion much greater, not only than the
Nation can spare, but indeed than it possesseth.</HI>
Now if this Act were Repealed, it must be in
favour of the Companies, and on purpose to en∣large
their Trade and Dealing with those Coun∣tries.
This must of course require a greater Ex∣port
of Bullion, which as our Case stands, can
be no otherwise supplied <HI>but from the Coin;</HI>
<PB N="15" REF="14"/>
which single Point considered, is of the last
Consequence to this Nation, and needs no Ap∣plication.
I suppose every Body will readily
grant, That the Companies Traded to <HI>India</HI>
much higher for the Seven Years preceding the
Act, than in the Seven Years that followed it;
the Consequence of which necessarily was, <HI>That
in the former Seven Years they carried out seve∣ral
Hundred Thousand Pounds</HI> per Annum <HI>in
Bullion, more than in the latter:</HI> Which Sum,
whatever it be, is saved to us purely by force
of this Act.</P>
<P>The suddenness of the Blow is a stuning Ar∣ticle.
The Manufacturers Livelyhood was not
heretofore snatched from them at one Stroke,
as it would be in this Case; they were enured
to Want, and learned to Starve by degrees; but
by R<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pealing this Act, <HI>Poverty would come upon
them like an armed Man;</HI> suddenly, inevitably,
<HI>and there would be none to help:</HI> And what Per∣plexity,
what Misery, what Desolation; nay,
what Agitations and Convulsions all this might
occasion, is much fitter for private Reflection,
than publick Representation. I love not to
mention <HI>the beginnings of such Woes,</HI> and tremble
to think <HI>now they would End.</HI></P>
<P>Since therefore there is so much Good alrea∣dy
procured by this Law, and so much more to
be expected; since such Misery must needs at∣tend
the Repeal of it, and perhaps more than is
<PB N="16" REF="15"/>
fit to be suggested. Why should it be Ima∣gined,
much less Credited, That the Thing can
be effected, or ever will be attempted? 'Tis too
hard and injurious a Thought <HI>upon the Compa∣nies;</HI>
and 'tis a dishonourable and unworthy Re∣flection
<HI>upon the Government.</HI> It will not, it
never can be; 'tis raving and phrensie to sup∣pose
it, because it would be madness, and a ju∣dicial
Desertion to Design it; 'tis putting an
End to the War <HI>the shortest Way.</HI> In short, 'tis
French Slavery, and Wooden Shooes all over.
I will only add, That <HI>so long as we are Blest
with our present Constitution, and a Brittish Par∣liament;
so long I verily believe, this Act will
stand firm and unshaken;</HI> that is, I hope and
trust, so long as the Sun and Moon endureth.</P>
<P>Thus I have done with the main part of your
Letter; there is nothing now behind but to
Consider the Four Arguments, for the setting
aside this Bill, which you say you find so often
in some Peoples Mouths. In Truth, <HI>these Ar∣guments</HI>
as you are pleased to call them, are not
only fo <HI>Weak, but so Provoking,</HI> that I scarce
know with what Language to treat them; but
because you request it, I will set them down,
and endeavour to Expose them as they well de∣ferve.</P>
<P><HI>Object.</HI>
1. It seems, the Exports of our Wool∣len
Manufactures are lessened since this Act
was made.</P>
<P><PB N="17" REF="16"/>
2. Our Imports of Wrought Silk from our
<HI>European</HI> Neighbours are increased.</P>
<P>3. By Repealing this Act, it is not design∣ed
to take away the Employment of the Peo∣ple,
but only to change the <HI>Prohibition</HI> into
an Imposition.</P>
<P>4. The Necessities of the Nation require
this to be done, to raise a FUND for the
WAR.</P>
<P>1. The first of these Arguments is deceit∣fully
laid down, and would conclude no∣thing,
supposing it to be true. To convince
you of this, I would only desire you to con∣sider
what Part of our Manufactures are less
Exported then heretofore. If this be affirm∣ed
of our Fine Manufactures made of Wool,
and Silk and Wool, <HI>it is a Mistake in Fact;</HI>
for there never was a Time when so many of
these, which directly oppose the <HI>Indian</HI> Goods,
were Exported to <HI>HOLLAND, HAM∣BURGH</HI>
and <HI>PORTUGAL,</HI> as of late
Years. And there is a plain Reason for the
Encrease of these Exports, to wit, the small
Quantity of prohibited Manufactures brought
into <HI>GREAT BRITAIN,</HI> since that Act
commenced: For since that Time, our own
Fine Manufactures have supplied their Place
both at Home and Abroad. And if it be af∣firmed
<PB N="18" REF="17"/>
in respect only of our Courser Wool∣lens;
all it will conclude is, that we suffer
much in this Article, for want of TRADE
with the <HI>Spanish</HI> Dominions, which no body
will deny: But then this Misfortune is not
to be imputed to the <HI>Prohibition Act,</HI> but to
the House of <HI>BOƲRBON</HI>'s seizing of, and
hindring our TRADE to those Countries.</P>
<P>2. As to the second Argument, 'tis wholly
deny'd. Men may affirm what they please.
But I insist upon it, and the Dealers in Fo∣reign
Silks know it to be true; That from
the Year One Thousand Six Hundred and
Sixty there never was so little of this Manu∣facture
imported into <HI>GREAT BRITAIN,</HI>
as within these Six Years last past; and a
great Part even of this too, is run in upon
us by the Smugler and unfair Trader, with∣out
paying the Customs. The <HI>Brittish</HI> Ma∣nufacturer
pays in our own Markets, Ten or
Fifteen Pound <HI>Per Cent.</HI> more for Raw Silk
than the <HI>Dutch</HI> do, by reason the latter are
allowed to draw back the Customs. But this
Mischief cannot be imputed to any Deficien∣cy
in the <HI>Prohibition Act,</HI> but to the want of
due Care in paying the Customs upon the
Imports of these Goods back again, and the
Practises of the unfair Dealer.</P>
<P><PB N="19" REF="18"/>
3. The third Argument is both Deceitful
and False, by pretending to insinuate, that a
high Duty upon <HI>Indian</HI> Goods would secure
the Manufacture at Home. It is something
strange that the Manufacturer should be secu∣red
by that which destroys the Manufacture,
and that a Weaver in <HI>Spittle-fields</HI> should thrive
the better, because <HI>Indian</HI> Silks are Sold the
Dearer. Alass it is not the Rate or Price,
but the Quantity of these Goods that effects
the Profit of the Importer, and the Ruin of
the Manufacturer. And is it possible, that <HI>an
Imposition</HI> can prevent great Quantities from
coming in? It is not pretended, on the con∣trary,
an Imposition is laid on purpose that
they might be brought in. <HI>Nothing can keep
them out but a Prohibition; and nothing can
let them in but an Imposition.</HI> Besides, Expe∣rience
has taught us, that a high Duty is a
Bait to some Men, that never fails to tempt
them to defraud the Government, and preju∣dice
the Manufacturer and fair Dealer. And
indeed the Fraud is but too Practicable, by
pretending to Export them, and then running
them in again; so that whatever Price is paid
by the Buyer for the Goods that have fairly
paid the High Duty; to be sure these that
are Run may be afforded Cheap enough, en∣tirely
to destroy the Poor Remnant of <HI>Brittish</HI>
Manufacture, the other would leave us. Be∣sides,
were these Commodities, such as could
<PB N="20" REF="19"/>
not easily be Run, and did they come from
Countries that took off Proportionable Quan∣tities
of our own Produce in Exchange for
them; it were yet to be consider'd what Duty
ought to be laid on them, to bring them up∣on
a Level with our own Manufactures; for
this must be done before the Manufacture at
Home can be secured. Now the Value of the
Labour of the People of <HI>India</HI> bearing no
greater Proportion to ours, then One does to
Six; it follow, that to effect this Secu∣rity,
no less Imposition can be laid on <HI>East-India</HI>
Goods than Five Hundred Pound <HI>per
Cent.</HI> as was done in the CASE of the <HI>East-India</HI>
Sugars, to secure the Produce of our
<HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rican</HI> Colonies, which had the designed
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ect, and amounted to a Prohibition; for
since the Passing of that ACT, none of those
Sugars have been consumed in <HI>Great Britain.</HI>
I do not say, were this Imposition laid on,
that the <HI>Brittish</HI> Manufactures could be Se∣cure;
and it is plain, no Imposition can make
them so; for such is the Fondnesse <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>f all Sorts
of People for these Goods, that vast Quanti∣ties
of them would go off, let the Price be
what it will. Nor does it at all concern the
Manufacturer, at what Rate these Goods are
Sold, it being the Quantity, and the Opposi∣<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion,
and not the Price that destroys us. And
this Destruction of our Manufactures would
still be more certain, by the Running of the
<PB N="21" REF="20"/>
Goods, and the Practise of Smuglers and un∣fair
Dealers, as before was noted.</P>
<P>4. The fourth Argument is a Home one
indeed; and if it be true, which God forbid,
'tis the best News the <HI>French</HI> King ever heard
since his Head was crown'd, and the worst
that ever befel this Nation. But pray, Sir,
who are the Men that are so Bold as to assert,
<HI>That the Necessities of the Nation require this to
be done, to raise a Fund for the War?</HI> That is
to say, that we are so Exhausted, that a Year∣ly
Fund of 100000 <HI>l.</HI> cannot be found out
without Repealing this Act. I cannot forbear
to think that such Notions as these, and so stu∣diously
advanced, have a very evil Tendency
in them, and are meant to dispirit and discou∣rage
the People, to make them weary and dis∣satisfied
with the Just and Necessary Measures
we are ingaged in, and the Managers of the
War; to Expose the Nakedness of the Land to
its Enemies, and to Weaken both the Hearts
and Han<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> of its Friends. <HI>Ways and Means
are Parliamentary Affairs;</HI> and it is fit the Me∣thods
of raising Money should be left to those
whose Province it is to supply Her Majesty's
Just Occasions, and to take Care of the Subject.
But if any Regard is to be had to the Asserti∣on
above, it would render these Two Things
Incompatible; for if no Money can be raised
without Repealing the <HI>Prohibition Act, either
the Money must be wanted, or the Nation must be
<PB N="22" REF="21"/>
ruined;</HI> by either of which Accidents, the
Common Cause is given up. This is the <HI>Di∣lemma</HI>
these Gentlemen would bring us into;
because this is the Condition they would have
it believed we are in. I have not Patience to
dwell any longer on this Subject; but hope I
may say with good Assurance that this War
may and will be carry'd on, and I hope effe∣ctually
too, without running any great Risque
to the Nation; much more without exposing
our Selves and Posterity to utter Ruine, to
Establish a Fund for One Hundred Thousand
Pounds <HI>per Annum.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><HI>I am Sir,</HI>
Your Humble Servant.</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>
