<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet TYPE="text/css" href="http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE><DATE>yyyy-mm-dd</DATE><RESPSTMT><NAME>[name of reviewer]</NAME><RESP>MURP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM></CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>

<EEBO>
<IDG S="auto" R="OX" ID="K054680.004">
<STC T="C">T063190_pt4</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3306640142</BIBNO>
<VID>0853400104</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>ANECDOTES
OF
PAINTING in ENGLAND;
With some Account of the principal Artists;
And incidental NOTES on other ARTS;
Collected by the late
Mr. GEORGE VERTUE;
And now digested and published from his original MSS.
By Mr. HORACE WALPOLE.</P>
<P>To which is added
The HISTORY of
The MODERN TASTE in GARDENING.</P>
<Q>The Glory of <HI>Lebanon</HI> shall come unto thee, the Fir-Tree, the Pine-Tree,
and the Box together, to beautify the Place of my Sanctuary, and I
will make the Place of my Feet glorious.</Q>
<BIBL>Isaiah, LX. 13.</BIBL>
<P>VOLUME the FOURTH and last.</P>
<P>STRAWBERRY-HILL:
PRINTED by THOMAS KIRGATE, MDCCLXXI.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO HIS GRACE
CHARLES,
Duke of Richmond, Lenox and Aubigny.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>MY LORD,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>IT is not to court protection to this work; it is
not to celebrate your Grace's virtues and abili∣ties,
which want no panegyric; it is to indulge the
sentiments of respect and esteem, that I take the
liberty of prefixing your name to this volume, the
former parts of these Anecdotes having been inscribed
to a Lady, now dead, to whom I had great obli∣gations.
The publications of my press have been
appropriated to Gratitude and Friendship, not to
<PB N="iv" REF="3"/>
Flattery. Your Grace's singular Encouragement of
Arts, a virtue inherited with others from your noble
Father, intitle you to this Address; and allow me
to say, my Lord, it is a proof of your Judgment
and Taste, that in your countenance of talents there
is but one instance of partiality—I mean, your Fa∣vour
to,</P>
<CLOSER><SALUTE>MY LORD,</SALUTE>
Your Grace's
most faithful and obedient
humble Servant,
<SIGNED>HORACE WALPOLE.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="advertisement">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>ADVERTISEMENT.</HEAD>
<P>THIS last volume has been long written, and even printed.
The publication, though a debt to the purchasers of the
preceding volumes, was delayed from motives of tender∣ness.
The author, who could not resolve, like most biographers,
to dispense universal panegyric, especially on many incompetent ar∣tists,
was still unwilling to utter even gentle censures, which might
wound the affections, or offend the prejudices of those related to the
persons whom truth forbad him to commend beyond their merits.
He hopes, that as his opinion is no standard, it will pass for mis∣taken
judgment with such as shall be displeased with his criticisms.
If his encomiums seem too lavish to others, the public will at least
know that they are bestowed sincerely. He would not have hesi∣tated
to publish his remarks sooner, if he had not been averse to
exaggeration.</P>
<P>The work is carried as far as the author intended to go, though
he is sensible he could continue it with more satisfaction to himself,
as the arts, at least those of painting and architecture, are emerging
from the wretched state in which they lay at the accession of George
the first. To architecture, taste and vigour were given by lord Bur∣lington
and Kent—They have successors worthy of the tone they
gave; if, as refinement generally verges to extreme contrarieties,
Kent's ponderosity does not degenerate into filligraine—But the mo∣dern
<PB N="vi" REF="5"/>
Pantheon, uniting grandeur and lightness, simplicity and orna∣ment,
seems to have marked the medium, where taste must stop.
The architect who shall endeavour to refine on Mr. Wyat, will per∣haps
give date to the age of embroidery. Virgil, Longinus and
Vitruvius afford no rules, no examples, of scattering finery.</P>
<P>This delicate redundance of ornament growing into our architec∣ture
might perhaps be checked, if our artists would study the sub∣lime
dreams of Piranesi, who seems to have conceived visions of
Rome beyond what it boasted even in the meridian of its splendor.
Savage as Salvator Rosa, fierce as Michael Angelo, and exuberant
as Rubens, he has imagined scenes that would startle geometry, and
exhaust the Indies to realize. He piles palaces on bridges, and tem∣ples
on palaces, and scales Heaven with mountains of edifices. Yet
what taste in his boldness! what grandeur in his wildness! what la∣bour
and thought both in his rashness and details! Architecture, in∣deed,
has in a manner two sexes; its masculine dignity can only
exert it muscles in public works and at public expence: its softer
beauties come better within the compass of private residence and
enjoyment.</P>
<P>How painting has rekindled from its embers, the works of many
living artists demonstrate. The prints after the works of sir Joshua
Reynolds have spread his fame to Italy, where they have not at pre∣sent
a single painter that can pretend to rival an imagination so fertile,
that the attitudes of his portraits are as<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Sir J. Reynolds has been accused of plagiarism for having borrowed atti∣tudes from ancient masters. Not only candour but criticism must deny the <HI>force</HI> of the charge. When a single posture is imitated from an historic picture and applied to a portrait in a different dress and with new attributes, This is not plagiarism, but quotation: and a quotation from a great author, with a novel application of the sense, has always been allowed to be an instance of parts and taste; and may have more merit than the original. When the sons of Ja∣cob imposed on their father by a false coat of Joseph, saying, “Know now whether This be thy son's coat or not,” they only asked a deceitful question—but that interrogation became wit, when Richard 1st. on the pope reclaiming a bishop whom the king had taken prisoner in battle, sent him the prelate's coat of mail, and in the words of scripture asked his holiness, whether THAT was the coat of his son or not? Is not there humour and satire in sir Joshua's reduc∣ing Holbein's swaggering and colossal haughtiness of Henry 8th. to the boyish jollity of master Crewe?—One prophecy I will vent<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re to make; sir Joshua is not a plagiary, but will beget a thousand. The exuberance of his invention will be the grammar of future painters of portrait.</NOTE> various as those of history.
<PB N="vii" REF="6"/>
In what age were paternal despair and the horrors of death pro∣nounced
with more expressive accents than in his picture of count
Ugolino? When was infantine loveliness, or embrio-passions, touched
with sweeter truth than in his portraits of miss Price and the baby
Jupiter? What frankness of nature in Mr. Gainsborough's land∣scapes;
which may entitle them to rank in the noblest collections!
What genuine humour in Zaffanii's comic scenes; which do not,
like the works of Dutch and Flemish painters, invite laughter to di∣vert
itself with the nastiest indelicacy of boors!</P>
<P>Such topics would please a pen that delights to do justice to its
country—but the author has forbidden himself to treat of living
professors. Posterity appreciates impartially the works of the dead.
To posterity he leaves the continuation of these volumes; and recom∣mends
<PB N="viii" REF="7"/>
to the lovers of arts the industry of Mr. Vertue, who pre∣served
notices of all his cotemporaries, as he had collected of past
ages, and thence gave birth to this work. In that supplement will
not be forgotten the wonderful progress in miniature of lady Lucan,
who has arrived at copying the most exquisite works of Isaac and
Peter Oliver, Hoskins and Cooper, with a genius that almost depre∣ciates
those masters, when we consider that they spent their lives in
attaining perfection; and who, soaring above their modest timidity,
has transferred the vigour of Raphael to her copies in water-colours.
There will be recorded the living etchings of Mr. H. Bunbury, the
second Hogarth, and first imitator who ever fully equalled his origi∣nal;
and who, like Hogarth, has more humour when he invents,
than when he illustrates<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">For instance, in his prints to Tristram Shandy.</NOTE>—probably because genius can draw from
the sources of nature with more spirit than from the ideas of another.
Has any painter ever executed a scene, a character of Shakespear,
that approached to the prototype so near as Shakespeare himself at∣tained
to nature? Yet is there a pencil in a living hand as capable of
pronouncing the passions as our unequalled poet; a pencil not only
inspired by his insight into nature, but by the graces and taste of
Grecian artists—but it is not fair to excite the curiosity of the public,
when both the rank and bashful merit of the possessor, and a too rare
exertion of superior talents, confine the proofs to a narrow circle.
Whoever has seen the drawings, and basreliefs, designed and execut∣ed
by lady Diana Beauclerc, is sensible that these imperfect encomi∣ums
are far short of the excellence of her works. Her portrait of
the duchess of Devonshire, in several hands, confirms the truth of
<PB N="ix" REF="8"/>
part of these assertions. The nymph-like simplicity of the figure is
equal to what a Grecian statuary would have formed for a dryad or
goddess of a river. Bartolozzi's print of her two daughters after the
drawing of the same lady, is another specimen of her singular genius
and taste. The gay and sportive innocence of the younger daughter,
and the demure application of the elder, are as characteristically con∣trasted
as Milton's Allegro and Penseroso.</P>
<P>Little is said here but historically of the art of gardening. Mr.
Mason in his first beautiful canto on that subject has shown that
Spenser and Addison ought not to have been omitted in the list of
our authors who were not blind to the graces of natural taste. The
public must wish with the author of this work, that Mr. Mason
would compleat his poem, and leave this essay as unnecessary as it
is imperfect.</P>
<P>The historic compositions offered for St. Paul's by some of our first
artists seemed to disclose a vision of future improvement—a period
the more to be wished, as the wound given to painting through the
sides of the Romish religion menaces the arts as well as idolatry—
unless the methodists, whose rigour seems to soften and adopt the
artifices of the catholics, [for our itinerant mountebanks already are
fond of being <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ainted in mezzotinto, as well as their St. Bridge<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s and
Teresas] should borrow the paraphernalia of enthusiasm now waning
in Italy, and superadd the witchery of painting to that of music.
Whitfield's temples encircled with glory may convert rustics, who
have never heard of his or Ignatius Loyola's peregrinations. If en∣thusiasm
is to revive, and tabernacles to rise as convents are demo∣lished,
may we not hope at least to see them painted? Le Sueur's
<PB N="x" REF="9"/>
cloyster at Paris makes some little amends for the imprisonment of
the Carthusians. The absurdity of the legend of the reviving canon
is lost in the amazing art of the painter; and the last scene of St.
Bruno expiring, in which are expressed all the stages of devotion
from the youngest mind impressed with fear to the composed resigna∣tion
of the prior, is perhaps inferior to no single picture of the great∣est
master. If Raphael died young, so did Le Sueur; the former
had seen the antique, the latter only prints from Raphael: yet in the
Chartreuse, what airs of heads! what harmony of colouring! what
aerial perspective! How Grecian the simplicity of architecture and
drapery! How diversified a single quadrangle, though the life of a
hermit be the only subject, and devotion the only pathetic! In short,
till we have other pictures than portraits, and painting has ampler
fields to range in than private apartments, it is in vain to expect the
art should recover its genuine lustre. Statuary has still less encou∣ragement.
Sepulchral decorations are almost disused; and though
the rage for portraits is at its highest tide both in pictures and prints,
busts and statues are never demanded. We seem to wish no longer
duration to the monuments of our expence, than the inhabitants of
Peru and Russia, where edifices are calculated to last but to the next
earthquake or conflagration.</P>
<CLOSER><DATE>October 1, 1780.</DATE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="toc">
<PB REF="10"/>
<HEAD>CONTENTS
OF THE
FOURTH VOLUME.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>CHAP. I.</HEAD>
<ITEM>PAINTERS in the Reign of King <HI>George I.</HI> p. 1.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>CHAP. II.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Architects and other Artists in the Reign of <HI>George I.</HI> p. 41.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>CHAP. III.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Painters in the Reign of <HI>George II.</HI> p. 51.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>CHAP. IV.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Account of William Hogarth, and Catalogue of his Prints, p. 68.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>CHAP. V.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Painters in Enamel and Miniature, Statuaries and Medallists, in the
Reign of <HI>George II.</HI> p. 90.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>CHAP. VI.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Architects in the Reign of <HI>George II.</HI> p. 104.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>CHAP. VII.</HEAD>
<ITEM>History of modern Gardening, p. 117.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="11"/>
<HEAD>ANECDOTES of PAINTING, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. I.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Painters in the Reign of King GEORGE I.</HEAD>
<P>WE are now arrived at the period, in which the arts were
sunk to the lowest ebb in Britain. From the stiffness in∣troduced
by Holbein and the Flemish masters, who not
only laboured under the timidity of the new art, but who saw no∣thing
but the starch and unpliant habits of the times, we were fallen
into a loose, and, if I may use the word, a <HI>dissolute</HI> kind of painting,
which was not less barbarous than the opposite extreme, and yet had
not the merit of representing even the dresses of the age. Sir God∣frey
Kneller still lived, but only in name, which he prostituted by
suffering the most wretched daubings of hired substitutes to pass for
his works, while at most he gave himself the trouble of taking the
likeness of the person who sat to him. His bold and free manner
was the sole admiration of his successors, who thought they had
caught his style, when they neglected drawing, probability, and
finishing. Kneller had exaggerated the curls of full-bottomed wigs
and the tiaras of ribbands, lace and hair, till he had struck out a
graceful kind of unnatural grandeur; but the succeeding modes
were still less favourable to picturesque imagination. The habits of
<PB N="2" REF="12"/>
the time were shrunk to awkward coats and waistcoats for the men;
and for the women, to tight-laced gowns, round hoops, and half a
dozen squeezed plaits of linen, to which dangled behind two un∣meaning
pendants, called lappets, not half covering their strait∣drawn
hair. Dahl, Dagar, Richardson, Jervas, and others, rebuffed
with such barbarous forms, and not possessing genius enough to de∣viate
from what they saw into graceful variations, cloathed all their
personages with a loose drapery and airy mantles, which not only
were not, but could not be the dress of any age or nation, so little
were they adapted to cover the limbs, to exhibit any form, or to ad∣here
to the person, which they scarce enveloped, and from which
they must fall on the least motion. As those casual lappings and
flowing streamers were imitated from nothing, they seldom have any
folds or chiaro 'scuro; anatomy and colouring being equally forgot∣ten.
Linen, from what oeconomy I know not, is seldom allowed
in those portraits, even to the ladies, who lean carelesly on a bank,
and play with a parrot they do not look at, under a tranquillity which
ill accords with their seeming situation, the slightness of their vest∣ment
and the lankness of their hair having the appearance of their
being just risen from the bath, and of having found none of their
cloaths to put on, but a loose gown. Architecture was perverted to
meer house-building, where it retained not a little of Vanbrugh; and
if employed on churches, produced at best but corrupt and tawdry
imitations of sir Christopher Wren. Statuary still less deserved the
name of an art.</P>
<P>The new monarch was void of taste, and not likely at an advanced
age to encourage the embellishment of a country, to which he had
little partiality, and with the face of which he had few opportunities
<PB REF="13"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>Louis Laquerre.</P>
</FIGURE>
<FIGURE>
</FIGURE>
<FIGURE>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="3" REF="14"/>
of getting acquainted; though had he been better known, he must
have grown the delight of it, possessing all that plain good-homour∣ed
simplicity and social integrity, which peculiarly distinguished <HI>the
honest English private gentleman.</HI> Like those patriots, it was more na∣tural
to George the first to be content with, or even partial to what∣ever
he found established, than to seek for improvement and foreign
ornament. But the arts, when neglected, always degenerate. En∣couragement
must keep them up, or a genius revivify them. Nei∣ther
happened under the first of the house of Brunswic. I shall be as
brief as I can in my account of so ungrateful a period, for though
the elder Dahl and and Richardson and a very few more had merit in
some particulars, I cannot help again advertising my readers, that no
reign, since the arts have been in any esteem, produced fewer works,
that will deserve the attention of posterity. As the reign too was of
no long duration, most of the artists had lived under the predecessors
of George the first, or flourished under his son, where several will be
ranked with more propriety. Of the former class was
<Q>LOUIS LAGUERRE,</Q>
the assistant and imitator of Verrio, with whose name his will be pre∣served
when their united labours shall be no more, both being im∣mortalized
by that unpropitious line of Pope,
<Q>Where sprawl the saints of Verrio and Laguerre.</Q>
The same redundancy of history and fable is displayed in the works
of both; and it is but justice to say that their performances were at
least in as good a taste as the edifices they were appointed to adorn.</P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="15"/>
Laguerre's father was a Catalan, who settled in France, and be∣came
master of the menagerie at Versailles. The son being born at
Paris in 1663, Louis the fourteenth did him the honour of being his
godfather, and gave him his own name. At first he was placed in
the Jesuit's college, but having a hesitation in his speech, and dis∣covering
much inclination to drawing, the good fathers advised his
parents to breed him to a profession that might be of use to himself,
since he was not likely to prove serviceable to them. He however
brought away learning enough to assist him afterwards in his alle∣goric
and historic works. He then studied in the royal academy of
painting, and for a short time under Le Brun. In 1683 he came to
England with one Ricard, a painter of architecture, and both were
employed by Verrio. Laguerre painted for him most part of the
large picture in St. Bartholomew's hospital, and succeeding so well
when little above twenty, he rose into much business, executing great
numbers of cielings, halls and staircases, particularly at lord Exe∣ter's
at Burleigh, the staircase at old Devonshire-house in Piccadilly,
the staircase and salon at Buckingham-house, the staircase at Pet∣worth,
many of the apartments at Burleigh on the hill where the
walls are covered with his Caesars, some things at Marlborough-house
in St. James's park, and, which is his best work, the salon at
Blenheim. King William gave him lodgings at Hampton-court,
where he painted the labours of Hercules in chiaro scuro; and be∣ing
appointed to repair those valuable pictures, the triumphs of
Julius Caesar by Andrea Montegna, he had the judgment to imitate
the style of the original, instead of new cloathing them in vermilion
and ultramarine; a fate that befel Raphael even from the pencil of
Carlo Maratti.</P>
<P><PB N="5" REF="16"/>
Laguerre was at first chosen unanimously by the commissioners for
rebuilding St. Paul's to decorate the inside of the cupola, but was set
aside by the prevailing interest of Thornhill, a preference not ravished
from him by superior merit. Sir Godfrey Kneller was more just to
him<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Vide life of Kneller in the preceding volume.</NOTE>, though from pique to Thornhill, and employed him to paint
the staircase of his house at Witton, where Laguerre distinguished
himself beyond his common performances. On the union of Eng∣land
and Scotland he was ordered by queen Anne to make designs
for a set of tapestry on that occasion, in which were to be introduced
the portraits of her majesty and the principal ministers; but though
he gave the drawings, the work went no farther. A few pictures he
painted besides, and made designs for engravers. In 1711 he was
a director of an academy of painting erected in London, and was
likely to be chosen governor on the resignation of Kneller, but was
again baffled by his competitor Thornhill. In truth he was, says
Vertue, a modest unintriguing man, and as his father-in-law<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">A founder of iron balustrades.</NOTE> John
Tijou said, God had made him a painter, and there left him. The
ever-grateful and humble Vertue commends him highly, and ac∣knowledges
instructions received from him; the source, I doubt, of
some of his encomiums. At a tavern in Drury-lane, where was held
a club of virtuosi, he painted in chiaro scuro round the room a Bac∣chanalian
procession, and made them a present of his labour. Ver∣tue
thinks that sir James Thornhill was indebted to him for his
knowledge of historic painting on cielings, &amp;c. and says he was
<PB N="6" REF="17"/>
imitated by<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Lanscroon was another assistant of Verrio and Laguerre, on his first arrival from Flanders. He died poor in 1737, leaving a son of his profession.</NOTE> others, as one<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">Riario painted a staircase at lord Carpenter's.</NOTE> Riario, Johnson, Brown, and several,
whose names are perished as well as that gawdy style.</P>
<P>Laguerre towards his latter end grew dropsical and inactive, and
going to see the Island Princess at Drury-lane, which was acted for
the benefit of his son, then newly entered to sing on the stage, he
was seized with a stroke of apoplexy, and dying before the play be∣gan,
April 20, 1721, he was buried in the church-yard of St. Mar∣tin's
in the Fields.</P>
<P>John Laguerre the son had talents for painting, but wanted appli∣cation,
preferring the stage to more laborious studies. After quit∣ting
that profession, I think he painted scenes, and published a set
of prints of Hob in the well, which had a great sale, but he died at
last in indigent circumstances in March, 1748.
<Q>MICHAEL DAHL</Q>
was born at Stockholm, and received some instructions from Ern∣straen
Klocke, and esteemed artist in that country and painter to the
crown, who in the early part of his life had been in England. At
the age of 22 Dahl was brought over by Mr. Pouters, a merchant,
who five years afterwards introduced Boit from the same country.
After a year's residence here, Dahl continued his travels in search of
improvement, staid about a year at Paris, and bestowed about three
more on the principal cities in Italy. At Rome he painted the por∣trait
of P. F. Garroli, a sculptor and architect, under whom Gibbs
<PB REF="18"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>MICHAEL DAHL</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="7" REF="19"/>
studied for some time. But it was more flattering to Dahl to be em∣ployed
by one that had been his sovereign, the famous queen Chris∣tina.
As he worked on her picture, she asked what he intended she
should hold in her hand? He replied, a fan. Her majesty, whose
ejaculations were rarely delicate, vented a very gross one, and added,
“a fan! give me a lion; that is fitter for the queen of Sweden.” I
repeat this, without any intention of approving it. It was a pedan∣tic
affectation of spirit in a woman who had quitted a crown to ram∣ble
over Europe in a motley kind of masculine masquerade, assum∣ing
a right of assassinating her galants, as if tyranny as well as the
priesthood were an indelible character, and throwing herself for pro∣tection
into the bosom of a church she laughed at, for the comforta∣ble
enjoyment of talking indecently with learned men, and of living
so with any other men. Contemptible in her ambition by abandon∣ing
the happiest opportunity of performing great and good actions,
to hunt for venal praises from those parasites the litterati, she attain∣ed,
or deserved to attain, that sole renown which necessarily accom∣panies
great crimes or great follies in persons of superior rank. Her
letters discover no genius or parts, and do not even wear that now
trite mantle of the learned, the affectation of philosophy. Her wo∣manish
passions and anger display themselves without reserve, and
she is ever mistaking herself for a queen, after having done every
thing she could to relinquish and disgrace the character.</P>
<P>Dahl returned to England in 1688, where he found sir Godfrey
Kneller rising to the head of the profession, and where he had yet
merit enough to distinguish himself as no mean competitor. His co∣louring
was good, and attempting nothing beyond portraits, he has
certainly left many valuable pictures, especially as he did not neglect
<PB N="8" REF="20"/>
every thing but the head like Kneller, and drew the rest of the figure
much better than Richardson. Some of Dahl's works are worthy of
Riley. The large equestrian picture of his sovereign Charles the
eleventh at Windsor has much merit, and in the gallery of admirals
at Hampton-court he suffers but little from the superiority of sir
Godfrey. In my mother's picture at Houghton there is great grace,
though it was not his most common excellence. At Petworth are
several whole lengths of ladies by him extremely well coloured. The
more universal talents of Kneller and his assuming presumption car∣ried
away the croud from the modest and silent Dahl, yet they seem
to have been amicable rivals, sir Godfrey having drawn his portrait.
He did another of himself, but Vertue owns that sir Godfrey's de∣served
the preference for likeness, grace, and colouring. Queen
Anne sat to him, and prince George was much his patron.</P>
<P>Virtuous and esteemed, easy in his circumstances and fortunate in
his health, Dahl reached the long term of eighty seven years, and
dying October 20, 1743, was buried in St. James's church. He
left two daughters, and about three years before lost his only son,
who was a very inferior painter, called the younger Dahl, but of
whose life I find no particulars among Vertue's collections.
<Q>PETER ANGELIS</Q>
worked in a very different style from the two preceding painters, ex∣ecuting
nothing but conversations and landscapes with small figures,
which he was fond of enriching with representations of fruit and fish.
His manner was a mixture of Teniers and Watteau, with more
grace than the former, more nature than the latter. His pencil was
<PB N="9" REF="21"/>
easy, bright, and flowing, but his colouring too faint and nerveless.
He afterwards adopted the habits of Rubens and Vandyck, more
picturesque indeed, but not so proper to improve his productions in
what their chief beauty consisted, familiar life. He was born at
Dunkirk in 1685, and visiting Flanders and Germany in the course
of his studies, made the longest stay at Dusseldorpe, enchanted with
the treasures of painting in that city. He came to England about
the year 1712, and soon became a favourite painter; but towards
the year 1730 he set out for Italy, where he spent three years. At
Rome his pictures pleased extremely, but being of a reserved temper
and not ostentatious of his merit, he disgusted several by the reluct∣ance
with which he exhibited his works: his studious and sober tem∣per
inclining him more to the pursuit of his art, than to the advan∣tage
of his fortune. Yet his attention to the latter prevented his
return to England as he intended, for stopping at Rennes in Bre∣tagne,
a rich and parliamentary town, he was so immediately over∣whelmed
with employment there, that he settled in that city, and
died there in a short time, in the year 1734, when he was not above
forty-nine years of age. Hyssing painted his picture while he was in
England.
<Q>ANTONY RUSSEL</Q>
is recorded by Vertue, as one of Riley's school, [consequently a
painter of portraits] as were Murray and Richardson, though he
owns with less success and less merit: nor does he mention any other
facts relating to him, except that he died in July 1743, aged above
fourscore. I should not be sollicitous to preserve such dates, but
<PB N="10" REF="22"/>
that they may sometimes ascertain the hands by which pictures have
been painted—and yet I have lived long enough since the first vo∣lumes
of this work were printed, to see many pieces ascribed to Hol∣bein
and Vandyck in auctions, though bearing dates notoriously
posterior to the deaths of those masters: such notices as these often
helping more men to cheat than to distinguish.
<Q>LUKE CRADOCK,</Q>
who died early in this reign, was a painter of birds and animals, in
which walk he attained much merit by the bent and force of his own
genius, having been so little initiated even in the grammar of his
profession, that he was sent from Somerton near Ilchester in Somerset∣shire,
where he was born, to be apprentice to a house-painter in Lon∣don,
with whom he served his time. Yet there, without instructions,
and with few opportunities of studying nature in the very part of the
creation which his talents led him to represent, he became, if not a
great master, a faithful imitator of the inferior class of beings. His
birds in particular are strongly and richly coloured, and were much
sought as ornaments over doors and chimney-pieces. I have seen
some pieces of his hand painted with a freedom and fire that intitled
them to more distinction. He worked in general by the day and for
dealers who retailed his works, possessing that conscious dignity of
talents that scorned dependence, and made him hate to be employed
by men whose birth and fortune confined his fancy and restrained his
freedom. Vertue records a proof of his merit which I fear will enter
into the panegyrics of few modern painters—he says he saw several
of Cradock's pictures rise quickly after his death to three and four
<PB N="11" REF="23"/>
times the price that he had received for them living. He died in
1717, and was buried at St. Mary's, Whitechapel.
<Q>PETER CASTEELS</Q>
was, like Cradock, though inferior in merit, a painter of fowls, but
more commonly of flowers, yet neither with the boldness and relievo
of a master, nor with the finished accuracy that in so many Flemish
painters almost atones for want of genius. He was born at Antwerp
in 1684, and in 1708 came over with his<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">So Vertue. I suppose he means brother-in-law.</NOTE> brother Peter Tillemans.
In 1716 he made a short journey to his native city, but returned soon.
In 1726 he published twelve plates of birds and fowl which he had
designed and etched himself, and did a few other things in the same
way. In 1735 he retired to Tooting, to design for callico-printers:
and lastly, the manufacture being removed thither, to Richmond,
where he died of a lingering illness May 16, 1749.
<Q>—DAGAR,</Q>
the son of a French painter, and himself born in France, came young
into England and rose to great business, though upon a very slender
stock of merit. He was violently afflicted with the gout and stone,
and died in May 1723, at the age of Fifty-four. He left a son
whom he bred to his own profession.
<PB N="12" REF="24"/>
<Q>CHARLES JERVAS.</Q>
No painter of so much eminence as Jervas, is taken so little notice
of by Vertue in his memorandums, who neither specifies the family,
birth or death of this artist. The latter, as well as I remember,
happened at his<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">He had another house at Hampton.</NOTE> house in Cleveland-court, in 1739, or 1740. One
would think Vertue foresaw how little curiosity posterity would feel
to know more of a man who has bequeathed them such wretched
daubings. Yet, between the badness of the age's taste, the dearth
of good masters, and a fashionable reputation, Jervas sat at the top
of his profession; and his own vanity thought no encomium dispro∣portionate
to his merit. Yet was he defective in drawing, colour∣ing,
composition, and even in that most necessary, and perhaps most
easy talent of a portrait-painter, likeness. In general, his pictures
are a light flimsy kind of fan-painting as large as the life. Yet I
have seen a few of his works highly coloured; and it is certain that
his copies of Carlo Maratti, whom most he studied and imitated,
were extremely just, and scarce inferior to the originals. It is a well-known
story of him, that having succeeded happily in copying [he
thought, in surpassing] a picture of Titian, he looked first at the
one, then at the other, and then with parental complacency cried,
“Poor little Tit! how he would stare!”</P>
<P>But what will recommend the name of Jervas to inquisitive pos∣terity
was his intimacy with Pope, whom he instructed to draw and
paint, whom therefore these anecdotes are proud to boast of and
<PB N="13" REF="25"/>
enroll<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">See his letters to Jervas, and a short copy of verses on a fan designed by himself on the story of Cephalus and Procris. There is a small edition of the Essay on Man with a frontispiece likewise of his design.</NOTE> among our artists, and who has enshrined<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">See Pope's epistle to Jervas with Dryden's translation of Fresnoy's Art of Painting.</NOTE> the feeble ta∣lents
of the painter in the lucid amber of his glowing lines. The re∣peated
name of lady<NOTE N="‡" PLACE="foot">Elizabeth countess of Bridgwater, one of the beautiful daughters of the great duke of Marlborough.</NOTE> Bridgwater in that epistle was not the sole
effect of chance, of the lady's charms, or of the conveniency of her
name to the measure of the verse. Jervas had ventured to look on
that fair one with more than a painter's eyes; so entirely did the
lovely form possess his imagination, that many a homely dame was
delighted to find her picture resemble lady Bridgwater. Yet neither
his presumption nor his passion could extinguish his self-love. One
day, as she was sitting to him, he ran over the beauties of her face
with rapture—“but, said he, I cannot help telling your ladyship
that you have not a handsome ear.” “No! said lady Bridgwater;
pray, Mr. Jervas, what is a handsome ear?” He turned aside his
cap, and showed her his own.</P>
<P>What little more I have to say of him, is chiefly scattered amongst
the notes of Vertue. He was born in Ireland, and for a year studied
under sir Godfrey Kneller. Norris, frame-maker and keeper of the
pictures to king William and queen Anne, was his first patron, and
permitted him to copy what he pleased in the royal collection. At
Hampton-court he copied the cartoons in little, and sold them to
Dr. George Clarke of Oxford, who became his protector and fur∣nished
<PB N="14" REF="26" MS="y"/>
him with money to visit Paris and Italy. At the former he
lent two of his cartoons to Audran, who engraved them, but died
before he could begin the rest. At Rome he applied himself to learn
to draw, for though thirty years old, he said he had begun at the
wrong end, and had only studied colouring. The friendship of Pope,
and the patronage of other men of genius and rank, extended a re∣putation
built on such slight foundations: to which not a little con∣tributed,
we may suppose, the Tatler, No. VIII, April 18, 1709,
who calls him <HI>the last great painter that Italy has sent us.</HI> To this
incense a window worth 20,000 <HI>l.</HI> added the solid, and made him her
husband. In 1738 he again travelled to Italy for his health, but
survived that journey only a short time.</P>
<P>He translated and published a new edition of Don Quixote. His
collection of drawings and Roman fayence, called<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">There is a large and fine collection of this ware at the late sir Andrew Fountain's at Narford in Norfolk.</NOTE> Raphael's earth∣en-ware,
and a fine cabinet of ivory carvings by Fiamingo, were
sold, the drawings in April 1741, and the rest after the death of
his wife.</P>
<P>It will easily be conceived by those who know any thing of the
state of painting in this country of late years, that this work pretends
to no more than specifying the professors of most vogue. Portrait-painting
has increased to so exuberant a degree in this age, that it
would be difficult even to compute the number of limners that have
appeared within the century. Consequently it is almost as necessary
that the representations of men should perish and quit the scene to
their successors, as it is that the human race should give place to ris∣ing
<PB REF="27"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>JONATHAN RICHARDSON.</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="15" REF="28"/>
generations. And indeed the mortality is almost as rapid. Por∣traits
that cost twenty, thirty, sixty guineas, and that proudly take
possession of the drawing-room, give way in the next generation to
those of the new-married couple, descending into the parlour, where
they are slightly mentioned as <HI>my father's and mother's pictures.</HI> When
they become <HI>my grandfather and grandmother,</HI> they mount to the two
pair of stairs; and then, unless dispatched to the mansion-house in
the country, or crouded into the house-keeper's room, they perish
among the lumber of garrets, or flutter into rags before a broker's
shop at the Seven Dials. Such already has been the fate of some of
those deathless beauties, who Pope promised his friend should
<Q>Bloom in his colours for a thousand years:</Q>
and such, I doubt, will be the precipitate catastrophe of the works
of many more who babble of Titian and Vandyck, yet only imitate
Giordano, whose hasty and rapacious pencil deservedly acquired him
the disgraceful title of <HI>Luca fa presto.</HI>
<Q>JONATHAN RICHARDSON</Q>
was undoubtedly one of the best English painters of a head, that had
appeared in this country. There is strength, roundness, and bold∣ness
in his colouring; but his men want dignity, and his women
grace. The good sense of the nation is characterised in his portraits.
You see he lived in an age when neither enthusiasm nor servility were
predominant. Yet with a pencil so firm, possessed of a numerous
and excellent collection of drawings, full of the theory, and pro∣found
in reflections on his art, he drew nothing well below the head,
and was void of imagination. His attitudes, draperies, and back∣grounds
<PB N="16" REF="29" MS="y"/>
are totally insipid and unmeaning; so ill did he apply to his
own practice the sagacious rules and hints he bestowed on others.
Though he wrote with fire and judgment, his paintings owed little
to either. No man dived deeper into the inexhaustible stores of Ra∣phael,
or was more smitten with the native lustre of Vandyck. Yet
though capable of tasting the elevation of the one and the elegance
of the other, he could never contrive to see with their eyes, when he
was to copy nature himself. One wonders that he could comment
their works so well, and imitate them so little.</P>
<P>Richardson was born about the year 1665, and against his incli∣nation
was placed by his<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">His own father died when he was five years old.</NOTE> father-in-law apprentice to a scrivener,
with whom he lived six years, when obtaining his freedom by the
death of his master, he followed the bent of his disposition, and at
twenty years old became the disciple of Riley; with whom he lived
four years, whose neice he married, and of whose manner he acquired
enough to maintain a solid and lasting reputation, even during the
lives of Kneller and Dahl, and to remain at the head of the profes∣sion
when they went off the stage. He quitted business himself some
years before his death; but his temperance and virtue contributed to
protract his life to a great length in the full enjoyment of his under∣standing,
and in the felicity of domestic friendship. He had had a
paralytic stroke that affected his arm, yet never disabled him from
his customary walks and exercise. He had been in St. James's park,
and died suddenly at his house in Queen-square on his return home,
May 28, 1745, when he had passed the eightieth year of his age.
He left a son and four daughters, one of whom was married to his
disciple Mr. Hudson, and another to Mr. Grigson, an attorney.
<PB N="17" REF="30"/>
The taste and learning of the son, and the harmony in which he
lived with his father, are visible in the joint works they composed.
The father in 1719 published two discourses; 1. An Essay on the
whole Art of Criticism as it relates to Painting; 2. An Argument
in Behalf of the<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">He tells us, that being in search of a proper term for this science, Mr. Prior proposed to name it <HI>connoissance;</HI> but that word has not obtained possession as <HI>connoisseur</HI> has.</NOTE> Science of a Connoisseur; bound in one volume
octavo. In 1722 came forth An Account of some of the Statues,
Bas-reliefs, Drawings and Pictures, in Italy, &amp;c. with Remarks by
Mr. Richardson, Sen. and Jun. The son made the journey; and
from his notes, letters, and observations, they both at his return
compiled this valuable work. As the father was a formal man, with
a slow, but loud and sonorous voice, and, in truth, with some af∣fectation
in his manner; and as there is much singularity in his style
and expression, those peculiarities, for they were scarce foibles, struck
superficial readers, and between the laughers and the envious, the
book was much ridiculed. Yet both this and the former are full of
matter, good sense and instruction: and the very quaintness of some
expressions, and their laboured novelty, show the difficulty the au∣thor
had to convey meer visible ideas through the medium of lan∣guage.
Those works remind one of Cibber's inimitable treatise on
the stage: when an author writes on his own profession, feels it pro∣foundly,
and is sensible his readers do not, he is not only excusable,
but meritorious, for illuminating the subject by new metaphors or
bolder figures than ordinary. He is the coxcomb that sneers, not he
that instructs in appropriated diction.</P>
<P><PB N="18" REF="31"/>
If these authors were censured, when conversant within their own
circle, it was not to be expected that they would be treated with
milder indulgence, when they ventured into a sister region. In 1734
they published a very thick octavo, containing explanatory notes and
remarks on Milton's Paradise lost, with the life of the author, and a
discourse on the poem. Again were the good sense, the judicious
criticisms, and the sentiments that broke forth in this work, forgot∣ten
in the singularities that distinguish it. The father having said in
apology for being little conversant in classic litterature, that he had
looked into them through his son, Hogarth, whom a quibble could
furnish with wit, drew the father peeping through the nether end of
a telescope, with which his son was perforated, at a Virgil aloft on a
shelf. Yet how forcibly Richardson entered into the spirit of his
author appears from his comprehensive expression, that <HI>Milton was
an ancient born two thousand years after his time.</HI> Richardson, how∣ever,
was as incapable of reaching the sublime or harmonious in
poetry as he was in painting, though so capable of illustrating both.
Some specimens of verse, that he has given us here and there in his
works, excite no curiosity for more, though he informs us in his
Milton, that if painting was his wife, poetry had been his secret
concubine. It is remarkable that another commentator of Milton
has made the same confession;
<Q><L>—sunt &amp; mihi carmina, me quoque dicunt</L>
<L>Vatem pastores—</L></Q>
says Dr. Bentley. Neither the doctor nor the painter add, <HI>sed non ego
credulus illis,</HI> though all their readers are ready to supply it for both.</P>
<P><PB N="19" REF="32"/>
Besides his pictures and commentaries, we have a few etchings by
his hand, particularly two or three of Milton, and his own head.</P>
<P>The sale of his collection of drawings, in February 1747, lasted
eighteen days, and produced about 2060 <HI>l.</HI> his pictures about <HI>700l.</HI>
Hudson, his son-in-law, bought many of the drawings.
<Q>—GRISONI</Q>
was the son of a painter at Florence, whence Mr. Talman brought
him over in 1715. He painted history, landscape, and sometimes
portrait; but his business declining, he sold his pictures by auction,
in 1728, and returned to his own country with a wife whom he had
married here of the name of St. John.
<Q>WILLIAM AIKMAN</Q>
was born in Scotland, and educated under sir John Medina. He
came young to London, travelled to Italy, and visited Turkey, and
returned through London to Scotland, where he was patronized by
John duke of Argyle the general, and many of the nobility. After
two or three years he settled in London, and met with no less encou∣ragement—but
falling into a long and languishing distemper, his
physicians advised him to try his native air, but he died at his house
in Leicester-fields, in June, 1731, aged fifty. His body, by his
own desire, was carried to and interred in Scotland. Vertue com∣mends
his portrait of Gay for the great likeness, and quotes the fol∣lowing
lines, addressed to Aikman on one of his performances, by
S. Boyse;
<PB N="20" REF="33"/>
<Q><L>As Nature blushing and astonished eyed</L>
<L>Young Aikman's draught, surpriz'd the goddess cried,</L>
<L>Where didst thou form, rash youth, the bold design</L>
<L>To teach thy labours to resemble mine?</L>
<L>So soft thy colours, yet so just thy stroke.</L>
<L>That undetermin'd on thy work I look.</L>
<L>To crown thy art cou'dst thou but language join,</L>
<L>The form had spoke, and call'd the conquest thine.</L></Q>
<Q>JOHN ALEXANDER,</Q>
of the same country with the preceding, was son of a clergyman, and
I think descended from their boasted Jamisone. He travelled to
Italy, and in 1718 etched some plates after Raphael. In 1721 was
printed a letter to a friend at Edinburgh, describing a staircase paint∣ed
at the castle of Gordon with the rape of Proserpine by this Mr.
Alexander.
<Q>Sir JAMES THORNHILL,</Q>
a man of much note in his time, who succeeded Verrio and was the
rival of Laguerre in the decorations of our palaces and public build∣ings,
was born at Weymouth in Dorsetshire, was knighted by George
the First, and was elected to represent his native town in parliament.
His chief works were, the dome of St. Paul's, an apartment at
Hampton-court, the altar-piece of the chapel of All Souls at Oxford,
another for<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The altar-piece at Weymouth was engraved by a young man, his scholar, whom he set up in that business.</NOTE> Weymouth of which he made them a present, the hall
<PB REF="34"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>S<SUP>R</SUP>. JAMES THORNHILL.</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="21" REF="35"/>
at Blenheim, the chapel at lord Oxford's at Wimpole in Cambridge∣shire,
the salon and other things for Mr. Styles at More-park, Hert∣fordshire,
and the great hall at Greenwich hospital. Yet high as his
reputation was, and laborious as his works, he was far from being
generously rewarded for some of them, and for others he found it diffi∣cult
to obtain the stipulated prices. His demands were contested at
Greenwich, and though La Fosse received <HI>2000l.</HI> for his work at Mon∣tagu-house
and was allowed <HI>500l.</HI> for his diet besides, sir James could
obtain but <HI>40s.</HI> a yard square for the cupola of St. Paul's, and I think
no more for Greenwich. When the affairs of the South-sea company
were made up, Thornhill, who had painted their stair-case and a lit∣tle
hall by order of Mr. Knight their cashier, demanded <HI>1500l.</HI> but
the directors learning that he had been paid but <HI>25s.</HI> a yard for the
hall at Blenheim, they would allow no more. He had a longer con∣test
with Mr. Styles, who had agreed to give him <HI>3500l.</HI> but not
being satisfied with the execution, a law-suit was commenced, and
Dahl, Richardson, and others, were appointed to inspect the work.
They appeared in court, bearing testimony to the merit of the per∣formance;
Mr. Styles was condemned to pay the money, and by
their arbitration <HI>500l.</HI> more, for decorations about the house and for
Thornhill's acting as surveyor of the building. This suit occasion∣ing
enquiries into matters of the like nature, it appeared that <HI>300l.</HI>
a year had been allowed to the surveyor of Blenheim, besides travel∣ing
charges: <HI>200l.</HI> a year to others; and that Gibbs received but
<HI>550l.</HI> for building St. Martin's church.</P>
<P><PB N="22" REF="36"/>
By the favour of that general Mecaenas<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">It was by the influence of the same patron that sir James was employed to paint the princess's apartment at Hampton-court. The duke of Shrewsbury, lord chamberlain, intended it should be executed by Sebastian Ricci, but the earl, then first commissioner of the treasury, preferring his own countryman, told the duke, that if Ricci painted it, he would not pay him.</NOTE>, the earl of Halifax, sir
James was allowed to copy the cartoons at Hampton-court, on which
he employed three years. He executed a smaller set, of one fourth
part of the dimensions. Having been very accurate in noticing the
defects, and the additions by Cooke who repaired them, and in ex∣amining
the parts turned in to fit them to the places; and having
made copious studies of the heads, hands, and feet, he intended to
publish an exact account of the whole, for the use of students: but
this work has never appeared. In 1724 he opened an academy for
drawing at his house in Covent-garden, and had before proposed to
lord Halifax to obtain the foundation of a royal academy at the up∣per
end of the Mews, with apartments for the professors, which by
an estimate he had made would have cost but <HI>3139l.</HI> for sir James
dabbled in architecture, and stirred up much envy in that profession
by announcing a design of taking it up, as he had before by think∣ing
of applying himself to painting portraits.</P>
<P>Afflicted with the gout and his legs swelling, he set out for his seat
at Thornhill near Weymouth, where four days after his arrival he
expired in his chair, May 4, 1734, aged fifty-seven, leaving one
son named James, whom he had procured to be appointed serjeant-painter
and painter to the navy; and one daughter, married to that
original and unequalled genius, Hogarth.</P>
<P><PB N="23" REF="37"/>
Sir James's collection, among which were a few capital pictures of
the great masters, was sold in the following year; and with them his
two sets of the cartoons, the smaller for seventy-five guineas, the
larger for only <HI>200l.</HI> a price we ought in justice to suppose was ow∣ing
to the few bidders who had spaces in their houses large enough
to receive them. They were purchased by the duke of Bedford, and
are in the gallery at Bedford-house in Bloomsbury-square. In the
same collection were drawings by one Andrea, a disciple of Thorn∣hill,
who died about the same time at Paris.
<Q>ROBERT BROWN</Q>
was a disciple of Thornhill, and worked under him on the cupola of
St. Paul's. Setting up for himself, he was much employed in deco∣rating
several churches in the city, being admired for his skill in
painting crimson curtains, apostles, and stories out of the New Test∣ament.
He painted the altar-piece of St. Andrew Undershaft, and
the spaces between the gothic arches in chiaro scuro. In the parish
church of St. Botolph, Aldgate, he painted the transfiguration for
the altar; in St. Andrews, Holborn, the figures of St. Andrew and
St. John, and two histories on the sides of the organ. In the chapel
of St. John at the end of Bedford-row, he painted St. John the Bap∣tist
and St. John the Evangelist, and even two signs that were much
admired, that for the Paul's head tavern in Cateaton-street, and the
Baptist's head at the corner of Aldermanbury. Correggio's sign of
the muleteer is mentioned by all his biographers. Brown, I doubt,
was no Correggio.
<PB N="24" REF="38"/>
<Q>—BELLUCCI,</Q>
an Italian painter of history, arrived here in 1716, from the court of
the elector Palatine. In 1722 he finished a cieling at Buckingham-house,
for which the duchess paid him <HI>500l.</HI> He was also employed
on the chapel of Canons, that large and costly palace of the duke of
Chandos, which by a fate as transient as its founder's, barely sur∣vived
him, being pulled down as soon as he was dead; and, as if in
mockery of sublunary grandeur, the scite and materials were pur∣chased
by Hallet the cabinet-maker. Though Pope was too grateful
to mean a satire on Canons, while he recorded all its ostentatious
want of taste, and too sincere to have denied it, if he had meant it,
he might without blame have moralized on the event in an epistle
purely ethic, had he lived to behold its fall and change of masters.</P>
<P>Bellucci executed some other works which Vertue does not specify;
but being afflicted with the gout, quitted this country, leaving a
nephew, who went to Ireland, and made a fortune by painting por∣traits
there.
<Q>BALTHAZAR DENNER,</Q>
of Hamburgh, one of those laborious artists, whose works surprise
rather than please, and who could not be so excellent if they had not
more patience than genius, came hither upon encouragement from
the king, who had seen of his works at Hanover and promised to sit
to him, but Denner succeding ill in the pictures of two of the fa∣vourite
German ladies, he lost the footing he had expected at court:
<PB N="25" REF="39"/>
his fame however rose very high on his exhibiting the head of an old
woman, that he brought over with him, about sixteen inches high
and thirteen wide, in which the grain of the skin, the hairs, the
down, the glassy humour of the eyes, were represented with the most
exact minuteness. It gained him more applause than custom, for a
man could not execute many works who employed so much time to
finish them. Nor did he even find a purchaser here; but the em∣peror
bought the picture for six hundred ducats. At Hamburgh he
began a companion to it, an old man, which he brought over and
finished here in 1726, and sold like the former. He painted himself,
his wife and children, with the same circumstantial detail, and a half-length
of himself, which was in the possession of one Swarts, a painter,
totally unknown to me. He resolved however, says Vertue, to quit
this painful practice and turn to a bolder and less finished style; but
whether he did or not is uncertain. He left England in 1728. The
portrait of John Frederic Weickman of Hamburgh, painted by
Denner, is said to be in the Bodleian library at Oxford.
<Q>—FERG,</Q>
of Vienna, was a charming painter, who had composed a manner
of his own, from various Flemish painters, though resembling Po∣lenburgh
most in the enamelled softness and mellowness of his colour∣ing:
but his figures are greatly superior; every part of them is suf∣ficiently
finished, every action expressive. He painted small land∣scapes,
fairs, and rural meetings, with the most agreable truth; his
horses and cattle are not inferior to Wouvermans, and his buildings
and distances seem to owe their perspective softness to the intervening
<PB N="26" REF="40"/>
air, not to the pencil. More faithful to nature, than Denner, he
knew how to omit exactness, when the result of the whole demands
a less precision in parts. This pleasing artist passed twenty years
here, but little known, and always indigent. Unhappy in his do∣mestic,
he was sometimes in prison, and never at ease at home, the
consequence of which was dissipation. He died suddenly in the street
one night, as he was returning from some friends, about the year 1737,
having not attained his fiftieth year. He left four children.
<Q>THOMAS GIBSON,</Q>
a man of a most amiable character, says Vertue, had for some time
great business, but an ill state of health for some years interrupted
his application, and about 1730 he disposed of his pictures privately
amongst his friends. He not long after removed to Oxford, and I
believe practised again in London. He died April 28, 1751, aged
about seventy-one. Vertue speaks highly of his integrity and mo∣desty,
and says he offended his cotemporary artists by forbearing
to raise his prices; and adds, what was not surprising in such con∣genial
goodness, that of all the profession Gibson was his most sin∣cere
friend.
<Q>—HILL</Q>
was born in 1661, and learned to draw of the engraver Faithorne.
He painted many portraits, and died at Mitcham in 1734.
<PB REF="41"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>P. MONAMY.</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="27" REF="42"/>
<Q>P. MONAMY,</Q>
a good painter of sea-pieces, was born in Jersey, and certainly from
his circumstances or the views of his family had little reason to ex∣pect
the fame he afterwards acquired, having received his first rudi∣ments
of drawing from a sign and house painter on London-bridge.
But when nature gives real talents, they break forth in the homeliest
school. The shallow waves that rolled under his window taught
young Monamy what his master could not teach him, and fitted him
to imitate the turbulence of the ocean. In painter's-hall is a large
piece by him, painted in 1726. He died at his house in Westmin∣ster
the beginning of 1749.
<Q>JAMES VAN HUYSUM,</Q>
brother of John, that exquisite painter of fruit and flowers, came
over in 1721, and would have been thought a great master in that
way, if his brother had never appeared. Old Baptist had more free∣dom
than John Huysum, but no man ever yet approached to the
finishing and roundness of the latter. James lived a year or two
with sir Robert Walpole at Chelsea, and copied many pieces of Mi∣chael
Angelo Caravaggio, Claud Lorrain, Gaspar, and other mas∣ters,
which are now over the doors and chimnies in the attic story at
Houghton; but his drunken dissolute conduct occasioned his being
dismissed.
<PB N="28" REF="43"/>
<Q>JAMES MAUBERT</Q>
distinguished himself by copying all the portraits he could meet with
of English poets, some of which he painted in small ovals. Dryden,
Wycherley, Congreve, Pope, and some others, he painted from the
life. He died at the end of 1746. Vertue says he mightily adorned
his pictures with flowers, honey-suckles, &amp;c.
<Q>—PESNE,</Q>
a Parisian, who had studied at Rome, and been painter to the king
of Prussia, grandfather of the present king. He came hither in
1724, and drew some of the royal family, but in the gawdy style
of his own country, which did not at that time succeed here.
<Q>JOHN STEVENS,</Q>
a landscape-painter, who chiefly imitated Vandiest, painted small
pictures, but was mostly employed for pieces over doors and chim∣nies.
He died in 1722.
<Q>JOHN SMIBERT,</Q>
of Edinburgh, was born about 1684, and served his time with a
common house-painter; but eager to handle a pencil in a more ele∣vated
style, he came to London, where however for subsistence he
was forced to content himself at first with working for coach-painters.
<PB N="29" REF="44"/>
It was a little rise to be employed in copying for dealers, and from
thence he obtained admittance into the academy. His efforts and
ardour at last carried him to Italy, where he spent three years in
copying portraits of Raphael, Titian, Vandyck, and Rubens, and
improved enough to meet with much business at his return. When
his industry and abilities had thus surmounted the asperities of his
fortune, he was tempted against the persuasion of his friends to em∣bark
in the uncertain but amusing scheme of the famous dean Berke∣ley,
afterwards bishop of Cloyne, whose benevolent heart was then
warmly set on the erection of an universal college of science and arts
in Bermudas, for the instruction of heathen children in christian du∣ties
and civil knowledge. Smibert, a silent and modest man, who
abhorred the finesse of some of his profession, was enchanted with a
plan that he thought promised him tranquility and honest subsistence
in a healthful Elysian climate<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">One may conceive too how a man so devoted to his art must have been animated, when the dean's enthusiasm and eloquence painted to his imagination a new theatre of prospects, rich, warm and glowing with scenery, which no pencil had yet made cheap and common by a sameness of thinking and imagina∣tion. As our disputes and politics have travelled to America, is it not probable that poetry and painting too will revive amidst those extensive tracts as they in∣crease in opulence and empire, and where the stores of nature are so various, so magnificent, and so new?</NOTE>, and in spite of remonstrances en∣gaged
with the dean, whose zeal had ranged the favour of the court
on his side. The king's death dispelled the vision. Smibert how∣ever,
who had set sail, found it convenient or had resolution enough
to proceed, but settled at Boston in New England, where he suc∣ceeded
<PB N="30" REF="45"/>
to his wish, and married a woman with a considerable for∣tune,
whom he left a widow with two children in March 1751. A
panegyric on him, written there, was printed here in the Courant,
1730. Vertue, in whose notes I find these particulars, mentions
another painter of the same country, one Alexander Nesbitt of
Leith, born in 1682, but without recording any circumstances re∣lative
to him.
<Q>—TREVETT</Q>
was a painter of architecture and master of the company of painter-stainers,
to whose hall he presented one of his works. He painted
several views both of the inside and outside of St. Pauls, intending
to have them engraved, for which purpose Vertue worked on them
some time; but the design was never compleated. He began too a
large view of London, on several sheets, from the steeple of St.
Mary Overy, but died in 1723.
<Q>HENRY TRENCH</Q>
was a cotemporary of Kent, and gained a prize in the academy of
St. Luke at Rome, at the same time. Trench was born in Ireland,
but studied many years in Italy, and for some time under Gioseppe
Chiari. Returning to England, he professed painting history, but
not finding encouragement, went back to Italy and studied two years
more. He came over for the last time in 1725, but died the next
year, and was buried at Paddington.
<PB REF="46"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>PETER TILLEMANS.</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="31" REF="47"/>
<Q>PETER TILLEMANS</Q>
not only distinguished himself above most of his competitors, but
which is far more to his honour, has left works that sustain them∣selves
even in<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">His view of Chatsworth hangs among several fine pictures at Devonshire-house, and is not disgraced by them.</NOTE> capital collections. He was<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">His father was a diamond-cutter.</NOTE> born at Antwerp,
and made himself a painter, though he studied under very indifferent
masters. In 1708 he was brought to England, with his brother-in-law
Casteels, by one Turner, a dealer in pictures; and employed by
him in copying Bourgognon and other masters, in which he succeeded
admirably, particularly Teniers, of whom he preserved all the free∣dom
and spirit. He generally painted landscapes with small figures,
sea-ports and views; but when he came to be known, he was pa∣tronized
by several men of quality; and drew views of their seats,
huntings, races, and horses in perfection. In this way he was much
employed both in the west and north of England, and in Wales, and
drew many prospects for the intended history of Northamptonshire by
Mr. Bridges. He had the honour of instructing the late lord Byron,
who did great credit to his master, as may be seen by several of his
lordship's drawings at his beautiful and venerable seat at Newstede∣abbey
in Northamptonshire, and where Tillemans himself must have
improved amidst so many fine pictures of animals and huntings.
There are two long prints of horses and hunting designed and etched
by him, and dedicated to his patrons the duke of Devonshire and
<PB N="32" REF="48"/>
lord Byron. With Joseph Goupy he was prevailed upon to paint a
set of scenes for the opera, which were much admired. After la∣bouring
many years under an asthma, for which he chiefly resided at
Richmond, he died at Norton in Suffolk December 5, 1734, at about
the fiftieth year of his age.
<Q>JOHN VANDREBANK,</Q>
a painter much in fashion in the reigns of the two last kings, is said
by Vertue to be an Englishman (though by his name at least of fo∣reign
extraction) and to have attained his skill without any assistance
from study abroad. Had he not been careless and extravagant, says
my author, he might have made a greater figure than almost any
painter this nation had produced; so bold and free was his pencil and
so masterly his drawing. He died of a consumption when he was
not above forty-five, in Hollis-street, Cavendish-square, December
23, 1739. John Vandrebank gave the designs of a set of plates for
Don Quixote. He had a brother of the same profession; and a
cousin, called
<Q>SAMUEL BARKER,</Q>
whom he instructed in the art, but who having a talent for painting
fruit and flowers, imitated Baptist, and would probably have made
a good master, but died young in 1727.
<PB N="33" REF="49"/>
<Q>PETER VAN BLEECK,</Q>
came into England in 1723, and was reckoned a good painter of
portraits. There is a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ine mezzotinto, done in the following reign,
from a picture which he painted of those excellent comedians, John∣son
and Griffin, in the characters of Ananias and Tribulation, in the
Alchymist. I have mentioned Johnson in this work before, as the
most natural actor I ever saw. Griffin's eye and tone were a little
too comic, and betrayed his inward mirth, though his muscles were
strictly steady. Mr. Weston is not inferior to Johnson in the firm∣ness
of his countenance, though less universal, as Johnson was
equally great in some tragic characters. In bishop Gardiner he sup∣ported
the insolent dignity of a persecutor; and compleatly a priest,
shifted it in an instant to the fawning insincerity of a slave, as soon
as Henry frowned. This was indeed history, when Shakespeare
wrote it, and Johnson represented it. When we read it in fictitious
harangues and wordy declamation, it is a tale told by a pedant to a
school-boy. Vanbleeck died July 20, 1764.
<Q>H. VANDERMIJN,</Q>
another Dutch painter, came over recommended by lord Cadogan
the general, and in his manner carried to excess the laborious minute∣ness
of his countrymen; faithfully imitating the details of lace, em∣broidery,
fringes, and even the threads of stockings. Yet even this
accuracy in artificial trifles, which is often praised by the people as
<HI>natural,</HI> nor the protection of the court, could establish his reputa∣tion
<PB N="34" REF="50"/>
as a good master; though perhaps the time he wasted on his
works, in which at least he was the reverse of his slatternly contempo∣raries,
prevented his enriching himself as they did. In history he is
said to have had greater merit. He was more fortunate in receiving
<HI>500l.</HI> for repairing the paintings at Burleigh. The prince of
Orange sat to him, and he succeeded so well in the likeness, that
the late prince of Wales not only sent for him to draw his picture,
but prevailed on his sister the princess of Orange to draw Vander∣mijn's;
for her royal highness, as well as princess Caroline, both
honoured the art by their performances in crayons. This singular
distinction was not the only one Vandermijn received; George the
first, and the late king and queen, then prince and princess, answer∣ed
for his son, a hopeful lad, who was lost at the age of sixteen, by
the breaking of the ice as he was scating at Marybone, at the end of
the greast frost in 1740. Vandermijn had a sister called Agatha,
who came over with him, and painted fruit, flowers, and dead fowls.
I do not find in what year he died.
<Q>ENOCH ZEEMAN.</Q>
Vertue has preserved few anecdotes of this painter, whom I remem∣ber
in much business. His father and three brothers followed the
same profession; one of them in water-colours; but Enoch was most
in fashion. At nineteen he painted his own portrait in the finical
manner of Denner, and executed the heads of an old man and wo∣man
in the same style afterwards. He died suddenly in 1744, leav∣ing
a son, called Paul, who followed the same profession. Isaac
<PB REF="51"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>ENOCH SEEMAN.</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB REF="52"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>WATTEAU</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="35" REF="53"/>
Zeeman, brother of Enoch, died April 4, 1751, leaving also a son
who was a painter.
<Q>WATTEAU.</Q>
England has very slender pretensions to this original and engaging
painter; he having come hither only to consult Dr. Meade, for
whom he painted two pictures, that were sold in the doctor's col∣lection.
The genius of Watteau resembled that of his countryman
D'urfè; the one drew and the other wrote of imaginary nymphs and
swains, and described a kind of impossible pastoral, a rural life led
by those opposites of rural simplicity, people of fashion and rank.
Watteau's shepherdesses, nay, his very sheep, are coquet; yet he
avoided the glare and clinquant of his countrymen; and though he
fell short of the dignified grace of the Italians, there is an easy air
in his figures, and that more familiar species of the graceful, which
we call genteel. His nymphs are as much below the forbidding ma∣jesty
of goddesses, as they are above the hoyden awkwardness of
country-girls. In his halts and marches of armies, the careless slouch
of his soldiers still retain the air of a nation that aspires to be agrea∣ble
as well as victorious.</P>
<P>But there is one fault of Watteau, for which till lately I could
never account. His trees appear as unnatural to our eyes, as his
figures must do to a real peasant who had never stirred beyond his
village. In my late journies to Paris the cause of this grievous ab∣surdity
was apparent to me, though nothing can excuse it. Wat∣teau's
trees are copied from those of the Tuilleries and villas near
Paris; a strange scene to study nature in! There I saw the originals
of those tufts of plumes and fans, and trimmed-up groves, that nod
<PB N="36" REF="54"/>
to one another like the scenes of an opera. Fantastic people! who
range and fashion their trees, and teach them to hold up their heads,
as a dancing-master would, if he expected Orpheus should return
to play a minuet to them.
<Q>ROBERT WOODCOCK,</Q>
of a gentleman's family, became a painter by genius and inclination.
He had a place under the government, which he quitted to devote
himself to his art, which he practiced solely on sea-pieces. He drew
in that way from his childhood, and studied the technical part of
ships with so much attention, that he could cut out a ship with all
the masts and rigging to the utmost exactness. In 1723 he began to
practice in oil, and in two years copied above forty pictures of Van∣develde.
With so good a foundation he openly professed the art,
and his improvements were so rapid that the duke of Chandos gave
him thirty guineas for one of his pieces. Nor was his talent for mu∣sic
less remarkable. He both played on the hautboy and composed,
and some of his compositions in several parts were published. But
these promising abilities were cut off e'er they had reached their
maturity, by that enemy of the ingenious and sedentary, the gout.
He died April 10, 1728, in the thirty-seventh year of his age, and
was buried at Chelsea.
<Q>ISAAC WHOOD</Q>
painted portraits in oil, and in black-lead on vellom, chiefly profiles.
He was patronized by Worthesley duke of Bedford, and has left
<PB N="37" REF="55"/>
several of his works at Woburn-abbey. He died in Bloomsbury∣square,
February 24, 1752, aged sixty-three. He was remarkable
for his humour, and happy application of passages in Hudibras.
<Q>—VOGELSANG,</Q>
of what country I know not, was a landscape-painter, who went to
Ireland, where he had good business; but leaving it to go to Scot∣land,
was not equally successful, and returned to London. These
are all the traces I find of him in Vertue's notes.
<Q>—ZURICH,</Q>
of Dresden, was son of a jeweller, who bred him to his own busi∣ness,
but giving him some instructions in drawing too, the young
man preferred the latter, and applied himself to miniature and enam∣elling.
He studied in the academy of Berlin, and came to Eng∣land
about 1715, where he met with encouragement, though now
forgotten, and obscured by his countryman that second Petitot,
Zincke, whom I shall mention in the next reign. Zurich died about
Christmas 1735, in the fiftieth year of his age, and was buried near
the Lutheran church in the Savoy, leaving a son about twelve years
old. Frederic Peterson was an enameller about the same time, and
died in 1729.
<PB N="38" REF="56"/>
<Q>CHRISTIAN RICHTER,</Q>
son of a silversmith at Stockholm, came over in 1702 and practiced
in oil, chiefly studying the works of Dahl, from which he learned a
strong manner of colouring, and which he transplanted into his
miniatures, for which he is best known. In the latter part of his
life he applied to enamelling, but died, before he had made great
proficience in that branch, in November, 1732, at about the age of
fifty. He had several brothers, artists, one a medallist at Vienna,
and another at Venice, a painter of views. Richter was member of
a club with Dahl and several gentlemen, whose heads his brother
modelled by the life, and from thence made medals in silver. I
mention this as it may explain to collectors the origine of those me∣dals,
when they are met with. Sir William Rich, Grey Neville,
and others, were of the club, and I think some foreign gentlemen.
<Q>JACQUES ANTOINE ARLAUD</Q>
was born at Geneva, May 18, 1668, and was designed for the
church, but poverty obliged him to turn painter. At the age of
twenty he quitted Geneva, worked at Dijon, and from thence re∣paired
to Paris, where, succeeding in miniature, he was approved
of by the academy and countenanced by the king. The regent ad∣mired
him still more—I am almost afraid to repeat what follows, so
much exaggeration seems to have been mixed with the account.
Having copied a Leda, my author says from a basrelief of Michael
Angelo, I rather suppose it was the famous Leda of Correggio de∣stroyed
<PB REF="57"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>JAMES ANTHONY ARLAUD</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="39" REF="58"/>
by the bigotry of the regent's son, all Paris was struck with
the performance. The due de la Force gave twelve thousand livres
for it, but the duke being a sufferer by the Mississipi [probably be∣fore
the picture was paid for] restored it to Arlaud, with 4000 li∣vres
for the time he had enjoyed it. In 1721 Arlaud brought this
chef d'oeuvre to London, but would not sell it—but sold a copy of
it, says the same author, for six hundred pounds sterling. This fact
is quite incredible. The painter was at least so much admired, that
he received many presents of medals, which are still in the library of
Geneva. But poor Leda was again condemned to be the victim of
devotion—in 1738 Arlaud himself destroyed her in a fit of piety, yet
still with so much parental fondness, that he cut her to pieces ana∣tomically.
This happened at Geneva. Mons. de Champeau, then
resident there from France, obtained the head and one foot of the dis∣sected;
a lady got an arm. The comte de Lautrec, then at Geneva,
and not quite so scrupulous, rated Arlaud for demolishing so fine a
work. The painter died May 25, 1743. These particularities are
extracted from the poems of Mons. de Bar, printed at Amsterdam in
3 volumes, 1750. In the third volume is an ode on the Leda in
question. Vertue speaks incidentally of the noise this picture made in
London, but says nothing of the extravagant price of the copy. The
duchess of Montagu has a head of her father when young, and ano∣ther
of her grandfather the great duke of Marlborough, both in wa∣ter-colours
by Arlaud. The celebrated count Hamilton wrote a little
poem to him on his portrait of the pretender's sister. <HI>See his works,
vol. 4, p.</HI> 279.
<PB N="40" REF="59"/>
<Q>Mrs. HOADLEY,</Q>
whose maiden name was Sarah Curtis, was disciple of Mrs. Beal,
and a paintress of portraits by profession, when she was so happy as
to become the wife of that great and good man, Dr. Hoadley, af∣terwards
bishop of Winchester. From that time she only practiced
the art for her amusement; though if we may judge of her talents
by the print from her portrait of Whiston, the art lost as much as
she gained—but ostentation was below the simplicity of character
that enobled that excellent family. She died in 1743. In the libra∣ry
at Chatsworth, in a collection of poems is one addressed by a lady
to Mrs. Sarah Hoadley, on her excellent painting.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="60"/>
<HEAD>ANECDOTES of PAINTING, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. II.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Architects and other Artists, in the Reign of George I.</HEAD>
<P>THE stages of no art have been more distinctly marked than
those of architecture in Britain. It is not probable that our
masters the Romans ever taught us more than the construction of
arches. Those, imposed on clusters of disproportioned pillars, com∣posed
the whole grammar of our Saxon ancestors. Churches and
castles were the only buildings, I should suppose, they erected of
stone. As no taste was bestowed on the former, no beauty was
sought in the latter. Masses to resist, and uncouth towers for keep∣ing
watch, were all the conveniencies they demanded. As even
luxury was not secure but in a church, succeeding refinements were
solely laid out on religious fabrics, till by degrees was perfected the
bold scenery of Gothic architecture, with all its airy embroidery and
pensile vaults. Holbein, as I have shown, checked that false, yet
venerable style, and first attempted to sober it to classic measures;
but not having gone far enough, his imitators, without his taste,
compounded a mungrel species, that had no boldness, no lightness,
and no system. This lasted till Inigo Jones, like his countryman
<PB N="42" REF="61"/>
and cotemporary Milton, dis<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>losed the beauties of ancient Greece,
and established simplicity, harmony, and proportion. That school
however was too chaste to flourish long. Sir Christopher Wren lived
to see it almost expire before him; and after a mixture of French
and Dutch ugliness had expelled truth, without erecting any certain
style in its stead, Vanbrugh with his ponderous and unmeaning
masses overwhelmed architecture in meer masonry. Will posterity
believe that such piles were erected in the very period when St. Paul's
was finishing?</P>
<P>Vanbrugh's immediate successors had no taste, yet some of them
did not forget that there was such a science as regular architecture.
Still there was a Mr. Archer, the groom-porter, who built Hethrop,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">St. Philip's church at Birmingham, Cliefden-house, and a house at Roe∣hampton, (which as a specimen of his wretched taste may be seen in the Vitru∣vius Britannicus) were other works of the same person; but the chef d'oeuvre of his absurdity was the church of St. John with four belfrys in Westminster.</NOTE>
and a temple at Wrest; and one Wakefield, who gave the design of
Helmsley; each of whom seemed to think that Vanbrugh had deli∣vered
the art from shackles, and that they might build whatever
seemed good in their own eyes. Yet before I mention the struggles
made by the art to resume its just empire, there was a disciple of Sir
Christopher Wren that ought not to be forgotten; his name was
<Q>NICHOLAS HAWKSMOOR.</Q>
At eighteen he became the scholar of Wren, under whom during his
life, and on his own account after his master's death, he was con∣cerned
<PB N="43" REF="62"/>
in erecting many public edifices. So early as Charles's reign
he was supervisor of the palace at Winchester, and under the same
eminent architect assisted in conducting the works at St. Paul's to
their conclusion. He was deputy-surveyor at the building Chel∣sea-college,
and clerk of the works at Greenwich, and was conti∣nued
in the same post by king William, queen Anne, and George
the first, at Kensington, Whitehall, and St. James's; and under
the latter prince was first surveyor of all the new churches and of
Westminster-abbey from the death of Sir Christopher, and designed
several of the temples that were erected in pursuance of the sta∣tute
of queen Anne for raising fifty new churches; their names are,
St. Mary Woolnoth, in Lombard-street; Christ-church, Spital-fields;
St. George, Middlesex; St. Anne, Limehouse; and St. George,
Bloomsbury; the steeple of which is a master-stroke of absurdity,
consisting of an obelisk, crowned with the statue of king George the
First, and hugged by the royal supporters. A lion, an unicorn, and
a king on such an eminence are very surprising:
<Q><L>The things, we know, are neither rich nor rare,</L>
<L>But wonder how the devil they got there.</L></Q>
He also rebuilt some part of All-Souls college<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Dr. Clarke, member for Oxford, and benefactor to that university, built three sides of the square called Peckwater at Christ-church, and the church of All Saints in the high street there.</NOTE>, Oxford, the two
towers over the gate of which are copies of his own steeple of St.
Anne, Limehouse. At Blenheim and Castle-Howard he was asso∣ciated
with Vanbrugh, at the latter of which he was employed in
erecting the magnificent mausoleum there when he died. He built
<PB N="44" REF="63"/>
several considerable houses for various persons, particularly Easton
Neston in Northamptonshire; restored a defect in the minster of
Beverley, by a machine of his own invention<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Of that machine by which he serewed up the fabric with extraordinary art, there was a print published.</NOTE>; repaired in a judi∣cious
manner the west end of Westminster-abbey; and gave a de∣sign
for the Ratcliffe library at Oxford. His knowledge in every
science connected with his art is much commended, and his character
remains unblemished. He died March 25, 1736, aged near seventy.
The above particulars are taken from an account of him given in
the public papers, and supposed by Vertue to be drawn up by his
son-in-law Mr. Blackerby. Many of the encomiums I omit, because
this is intended as an impartial register of, not as a panegyric on,
our artists. When I have erred on either side, in commending or
blaming, I offer but my own judgment, which is authority to no∣body
else, and ought to be canvassed or set right by abler decisions.
Hawksmoor deviated a little from the lessons and practice of his
master, and certainly did not improve on them; but the most dis∣stinguished
architect was
<Q>JAMES GIBBS,</Q>
who without deviating from established rules, proved what has been
seen in other arts, that meer mechanic knowledge may avoid faults,
without furnishing beauties; that grace does not depend on rules;
and that taste is not to be learnt. Virgil and Statius used the same
number of feet in their verses; and Gibbs knew the proportions of
<PB REF="64"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>JAMES GIBBS.</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="45" REF="65"/>
the five orders as well as Inigo; yet the Banquetting-house is a stand∣ard,
and no man talks of one edifice of Gibbs. In all is wanting
that harmonious simplicity that speaks a genius—and that is often
not remarked till it has been approved of by one. It is that grace
and that truth, so much meditated, and delivered at once with such
correctness and ease in the works of the ancients, which good sense
admires and consecrates, because it corresponds with nature. Their
small temples and statues, like their writings, charm every age by
their symmetry and graces and the just measure of what is necessary;
while pyramids and the ruins of Persepolis, only make the vulgar
stare at their gigantic and clumsy grandeur. Gibbs, like Vanbrugh,
had no aversion to ponderosity, but not being endued with much in∣vention,
was only regularly heavy. His praise was fidelity to rules;
his failing, want of grace.</P>
<P>He was born at Aberdeen in 1683, and studied his art in Italy.
About the year 1720 he became the architect most in vogue, and
the next year gave the design of St. Martin's church, which was
finished in five years, and cost thirty-two thousand pounds. His like∣wise
was St. Mary's in the Strand, one of the fifty new churches, a
monument of the piety more than of the taste of the nation. The
new church at Derby was another of his works; so was the new
building at King's college, Cambridge, and the senate-house there,
the latter of which was not so bad as to justify erecting the middle
building in a style very dissonant. The Ratcliffe library<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">At the opening the library, Gibbs was complimented by the university with the degree of master of arts.</NOTE> is more
exceptionable, and seems to have sunk into the ground; or, as
Sarah Duchess of Marlborough said of another building, it looks as
<PB N="46" REF="66"/>
if it was making a curtsy. Gibbs, though he knew little of Gothic
architecture, was more fortunate in the quadrangle of All Souls,
which has blundered into a picturesque scenery not void of grandeur,
especially if seen through the gate that leads from the schools. The
assemblage of buildings in that quarter, though no single one is
beautiful, always struck me with singular pleasure, as it conveys
such a vision of large edifices, unbroken by private houses, as the
mind is apt to entertain of renowned cities that exist no longer.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">It is the same kind of visionary enchantment that strikes in the gardens at Stowe. Though some of the buildings, particularly those of Vanbrugh and Gibbs, are far from beautiful, yet the rich landscapes occasioned by the multi∣plicity of temples and obelisks, and the various pictures that present themselves as we shift our situation, occasion surprize and pleasure, sometimes recalling Albano's landscapes to our mind, and oftener to our fancy the idolatrous and luxurious vales of Daphne and Tempe. It is just to add that the improvements made by lord Temple have profited of the present perfect style of architecture and gardening. The temple of Concord and Victory presiding over so noble a valley, the great arch designed by Mr. T. Pitt, and the smaller in honour of princess Amelie, disclosing a wonderfully beautiful perspective over the Elysian fields to the Palladian bridge, and up to the castle on the hill, are monuments of taste, and scenes, that I much question if Tempe or Daphne exhibited.</NOTE></P>
<P>In 1728 Gibbs published a large folio of his own designs, which I
think will confirm the character I have given of his works. His
arched windows, his rustic-laced windows, his barbarous buildings
for gardens, his cumbrous chimney-pieces, and vases without grace,
are striking proofs of his want of taste. He got 1500 <HI>l.</HI> by this pub∣lication,
and sold the plates afterwards for 400 <HI>l.</HI> more. His repu∣tation
was however established, and the following compliment, pre∣served
<PB N="47" REF="67"/>
by Vertue, on his monument of Prior in Westminster-abbey,
shows that he did not want fond admirers:
<Q><L>While Gibbs displays his elegant design,</L>
<L>And Rysbrack's art does in the sculpture shine,</L>
<L>With due composure and proportion just</L>
<L>Adding new lustre to the finish'd bust,</L>
<L>Each artist here perpetuates his name,</L>
<L>And shares with Prior an immortal fame. T. W.</L></Q>
There are three prints of Gibbs, one from a picture of Huyssing, and
another from one of Schryder, a Swiss, who was afterwards painter
to the king of Sweden, and the third from Hogarth. Gibbs was
afflicted with the gravel and stone and went to Spa in 1749, but did
not die till August 5, 1754. He bequeathed an hundred pounds to
St. Bartholomew's hospital, of which he was architect and governor,
the same to the Foundling hospital, and his library and prints to the
Ratcliffe library at Oxford, besides charities, and legacies to his re∣lations
and friends.
<Q>COLIN CAMPBELL,</Q>
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> countryman of Gibbs, had fewer faults, but not more imagination.
He published three large folios under the title of Vitruvius Britan∣nicus,
containing many of his own designs, with plans of other ar∣chitects;
but he did not forsee with how much more justice that title
would be worn by succeeding volumes to be added to his works.
One has already been given. The best of Campbell's designs, are
Wanstead, the Rolls, and Mereworth in Kent: the latter avowedly
copied from Palladio. Campbell was surveyor of the works at
Greenwich hospital, and died in 1734.
<PB N="48" REF="68" MS="y"/>
<Q>JOHN JAMES,</Q>
of whom I find no mention in Vertue's notes, was, as I am inform∣ed,
considerably employed in the works at Greenwich; where he
settled. He built the church there, and the house for sir Gregory
Page at Blackheath, the idea of which was taken from Houghton.
James likewise built the church of St. George Hanover-square, the
body of the church at Twickenham, and that of St. Luke, Middle∣sex,
which has a fluted obelisk for its steeple. He translated from
the French some books on gardening.
<Q>—CARPENTIERE,</Q>
or Charpentiere, a statuary much employed by the duke of Chandos
at Canons, was for some years principal assistant to Van Ost, an ar∣tist
of whom I have found no memorials, and afterwards set up for
himself. Towards the end of his life, he kept a manufacture of
leaden statues in Piccadilly, and died in 1737, aged above sixty.
<Q>CHARLES CHRISTIAN REISEN,</Q>
the celebrated engraver of seals, was son of Christian Reisen of
Drontheim in Norway<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The father, on his voyage to England, had been driven by a storm to Scotland, and worked at Aberdeen for one Melvin, a goldsmith, for two years before he came to London, where he arrived on the second day of the great fire in September, 1666. Here he first began to engrave seals, having been only a goldsmith before. Afterwards he was confined in the Tower for four years on suspicion of engraving dies for coining, but was discharged without a trial.</NOTE>, who had followed the same profession, and
<PB REF="69"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>CHARLES CHRISTIAN REISEN.</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="49" REF="70"/>
who with one Stykes were the first artists of that kind who had dis∣tinguished
themselves in England. The father died here leaving a
widow and a numerous family, the eldest of which was Charles
Christian, who though scarce twenty had made so rapid a progress un∣der
his father's instructions, that he became the support of the family,
and in a few years equalled any modern that had attempted the art of
intaglia. He was born in the parish of St. Clement's Danes, and on
account of his extraction was recommended to prince George, but
being little versed in the language of his family, does not appear to
have been particularly encouraged by his royal highness. The force
of his genius however attracted the notice of such a patron as genius
deserved, and always found at that time, Robert earl of Oxford,
whose munificence and recommendation soon placed Christian (by
which name he is best known) on the basis of fortune and fame. In
the library and museum of that noble collector he found all the helps
that a very deficient education had deprived him of; there he learned
to see with Grecian and Roman eyes, and to produce heads after
the antique worthy of his models; for though greatly employed on
cutting arms and crests, and such tasteless fantasies, his excellence
lay in imitating the heroes and empresses of antiquity. I do not find
that he ever attempted cameo. The magic of those works, in
which by the help of glasses we discover all the beauties of statuary
and drawing, and even the science of anatomy, has been restricted to
an age that was ignorant of microscopic glasses; a problem hitherto
<PB N="50" REF="71"/>
unresolved to satisfaction. Christian's fame spread beyond the con∣fines
of our island, and he received frequent commissions from Den∣mark,
Germany, and France. Christian, as his fortune and taste
improved, made a collection himself of medals, prints, drawings
and books; and was chosen director of the academy under sir God∣frey
Kneller. On the trial of bishop Atterbury, on a question relat∣ing
to the impression of a seal, he was thought the best judge, and
was examined accordingly. Vertue represents him as a man of a
jovial and free, and even sarcastic temper and of much humour, an
instance of which was, that being illiterate, but conversing with men
of various countries, he had composed a dialect so droll and divert∣ing,
that it grew into a kind of use among his acquaintance, and he
threatened to publish a dictionary of it. His countenance harmo∣nized
with his humour, and Christian's mazard was a constant joke;
a circumstance not worth mentioning, no more than the lines it occa∣sioned,
but as they fell from the pen of that engaging writer, Mr.
Prior. Sir James Thornhill having drawn an extempore profile of
Christian, the poet added this distich,
<Q><L>This, drawn by candle-light and hazard,</L>
<L>Was meant to show Charles Christian's mazard.</L></Q>
This great artist lived chiefly in the neighbourhood of Covent-garden,
so long the residence of most of our professors in virtù. He died there
of the gout, December 15, 1725, when he had not passed the forty-sixth
year of his age, and was buried in the church-yard on the north
side next to the steps. He appointed his friend sir James Thornhill
one of his executors, and dying a batchelor left the bulk of his for∣tune
to a maiden sister who had constantly lived with him, and a por∣tion
to his brother John.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="72"/>
<HEAD>ANECDOTES of PAINTING, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. III.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Painters in the Reign of King GEORGE II.</HEAD>
<P>IT is with complacency I enter upon a more shining period in the
history of arts, upon a new aera; for though painting made but
feeble efforts towards advancement, yet it was in the reign of George
the Second that architecture revived in antique purity; and that an
art unknown to every age and climate not only started into being,
but advanced with master-steps to vigorous perfection, I mean, the
art of gardening, or as I should chuse to call it, <HI>the art of creat∣ing
landscape.</HI> Rysbrack and Roubiliac redeemed statuary from re∣proach,
and engraving began to demand better painters, whose works
it might imitate. The king, it is true, had little propensity to re∣fined
pleasures; but queen Caroline was ever ready to reward merit,
and wished to have their reign illustrated by monuments of genius.
She enshrined Newton, Boyle, and Locke: she employed Kent,
and sat to Zincke. Pope might have enjoyed her favour, and Swift
had it at first, till insolent under the mask of independence, and not
content without domineering over her politics, she abandoned him
<PB N="52" REF="73"/>
to his ill-humour, and to the vexation of that misguided and disap∣pointed
ambition, that perverted and preyed on his excellent genius.</P>
<P>To have an exact view of so long a reign as that of George the
Second, it must be remembered that many of the artists already re∣corded
lived past the beginning of it, and were principal performers.
Thus the style that had predominated both in painting and architec∣ture
in the two preceding reigns, still existed during the first years of
the late king, and may be considered as the remains of the schools of
Dahl and sir Godfrey Kneller, and of sir Christopher Wren. Rich∣ardson
and Jervas, Gibbs and Campbell, were still at the head of
their respective professions. Each art improved, before the old pro∣fessors
left the stage. Vanloo introduced a better style of draperies,
which by the help of Vanaken became common to and indeed the
same in the works of almost all our painters; and Leoni, by pub∣lishing
and imitating Palladio, disencumbered architecture from some
of the weight with which it had been overloaded. Kent, lord Bur∣lington,
and lord Pembroke, though the two first were no foes to
heavy ornaments, restored every other grace to that imposing science,
and left the art in possession of all its rights—yet still Mr. Adam and
Mr. Chambers were wanting to give it perfect delicacy. The reign
was not closed, when sir Joshua Reynolds ransomed portrait-painting
from insipidity, and would have excelled the greatest masters in that
branch, if his colouring were as lasting, as his taste and imagination
are inexhaustible—but I mean not to speak of living masters,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">This is the reason why no account is given here of that able master Mr. Scott, painter of sea-pieces, who ought to make a principal figure in this reign.</NOTE> and
<PB N="53" REF="74" MS="y"/>
must therefore omit some of the ornaments of that reign. Those I
shall first recapitulate were not the most meritorious.
<Q>HANS HUYSSING,</Q>
born at Stockholm, came over in 1700, and lived many years with
Dahl, whose manner he imitated and retained. He drew the three
eldest princesses, daughters of the king, in the robes they wore at
the coronation.
<Q>CHARLES COLLINS</Q>
painted all sorts of fowl and game. He drew a piece with a hare
and birds and his own portrait in a hat. He died in 1744.
<Q>—COOPER</Q>
imitated Michael Angelo di Caravaggio in painting fruit and flowers.
He died towards the end of 1743.
<Q>BARTHOLOMEW DANDRIDGE,</Q>
son of a house-painter, had great business from his felecity in taking
a likeness. He sometimes painted small conversations, but died in
the vigour of his age.
<PB N="54" REF="75"/>
<Q>—DAMINI,</Q>
an Italian painter of history, was scholar of Pelegrini. He returned
to his own country in 1730, in company with Mr. Hussey, whose
genius for drawing was thought equal to very great masters.
<Q>JEREMIAH DAVISON</Q>
was born in England, of Scots parents. He chiefly studied sir
Peter Lely, and with the assistance of Vanaken, excelled in paint∣ing
sattins. Having got acquainted with the duke of Athol at a
lodge of free-masons, he painted his grace's picture and presented it
to the society. The duke sat to him again with his duchess, and pa∣tronized
and carried him into Scotland, where, as well as in London,
he had great business. He died the latter end of 1745, aged about
fifty.
<Q>JOHN ELLIS,</Q>
born in 1701, was at fifteen placed with sir James Thornhill, and
afterwards was a short time with Schmutz; but he chiefly imitated
Vandrebank, to whose house and business he succeeded; and by the
favour of the duke of Montagu, great master of the wardrobe, pur∣chased
Vandrebank's place of tapestry-weaver to the crown, as by
the interest of sir Robert Walpole, for whom he bought pictures, he
was appointed master-keeper of the lions in the Tower. In these
easy circumstances he was not very assiduous in his profession.
<PB REF="76"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>PHILIP MERCIER.</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="55" REF="77"/>
<Q>PHILIP MERCIER,</Q>
of French extraction, but born at Berlin, studied there in the acade∣my
and under monsieur Pesne. After visiting France and Italy he
went to Hanover, where he drew prince Frederic's picture, which
he brought to England, and when his royal highness came over,
Mercier was appointed his painter, became a favourite and was ta∣ken
into his service and houshold; and by the prince's order drew
several of the royal family, particularly the three eldest princesses,
which pictures were published in mezzotinto. After nine years, he
lost the favour of the prince of Wales, and was dismissed from his
service. At first he talked of quitting his profession, retired into the
country, and bought a small estate; but soon returned and took a
house in Covent-garden, painting portraits and pictures of familiar
life in a genteel style of his own, and with a little of Watteau, in
whose manner there is an etching of Mercier and his wife and two
of their children. There is another print of his daughter. Children
too and their sports he painted for prints. From London he went to
York, and met with encouragement, and for a short time to Portu∣gal
and Ireland; and died July 18, 1760, aged seventy-one.
<Q>JOSEPH FRANCIS NOLLIKINS,</Q>
of Antwerp, son of a painter who had long resided in England, but
who had settled and died at Roan. The son came over young, and
studied under Tillemans, and afterwards copied Watteau and Paulo
Panini. He painted landscape, figures, and conversations, and par∣ticularly
<PB N="56" REF="78"/>
the amusements of children. He was much employed by
lord Cobham at Stowe, and by the late earl of Tilney. He died in
St. Anne's parish, January 21, 1748, aged forty-two, and left a
wife and a numerous young family. Slater painted in the same kind
with Nollikins, and executed cielings and works in fresco at Stowe
and at the earl of Westmorland's at Mereworth in Kent.
<Q>—ROBINSON,</Q>
a young painter from Bath, had been educated under Vandrebank,
but marrying a wife with 4 or <HI>5000l.</HI> and taking the house in Cleve∣land-court
in which Jervas had lived, he suddenly came into great
business, though his colouring was faint and feeble. He affected to
dress all his pictures in Vandyck's habits; a fantastic fashion with
which the age was pleased in other painters too, and which, could
they be taken for the works of that great man, would only serve to
perplex posterity. Vanaken assisted to give some credit to the delu∣sion.
Robinson died when he was not above thirty, in 1745.
<Q>ANDREA SOLDI,</Q>
of Florence, arrived in 1735, being then about the age of thirty-three.
He had been to visit the Holy Land, and at Aleppo having
drawn the pictures of some English merchants, they gave him recom∣mendations
to their countrymen. For some time he had much busi∣ness,
and painted both portraits and history, but outlived his income
and fell into misfortunes.
<PB N="57" REF="79" MS="y"/>
<Q>CHEVALIER RUSCA,</Q>
a Milanese, came over in 1738, and painted a few pictures here in
a gawdy fluttering style, but with some merit. I think he staid here
but a very few years.
<Q>STEPHEN SLAUGHTER</Q>
Succeeded Mr. Walton as supervisor of the king's pictures, and had
been for some time in Ireland, where he painted several portraits.
He had a sister that excelled in imitating bronzes and basreliefs to
the highest degree of deception. He died at Kensington, whither he
had retired, May 15, 1765. He was succeeded in his office of sur∣veyor
and keeper of the pictures by Mr. George Knapton, painter in
crayons.
<Q>JAMES WORSDALE</Q>
would have been little known, had he been distinguished by no talents
but his pencil. He was apprentice to sir Godfrey Kneller, but mar∣rying
his wife's neice without their consent, was dismissed by his mas∣ter.
On the reputation however of that education, by his singing,
excellent mimickry and facetious spirit, he gained many patrons and
business, and was appointed master-painter to the board of ordnance.
He<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Vide Victor's Companion to the Playhouse.</NOTE> published several small pieces, songs, &amp;c. besides the following
dramatic performances:</P>
<P><PB N="58" REF="80"/>
1. A Cure for a Scold, a ballad opera, taken from Shakespeare's
Taming of a Shrew.</P>
<P>2. The Assembly, a farce, in which Mr. Worsdale himself played
the part of lady Pentweezle admirably well.</P>
<P>3. The Queen of Spain.</P>
<P>4. The extravagant Justice.</P>
<P>He died June 13, 1767, and was buried at St. Paul's Covent-gar∣den,
with this epitaph composed by himself,
<Q><L>Eager to get, but not to keep the pelf,</L>
<L>A friend to all mankind, except himself.</L></Q>
<Q>RANELAGH BARRETT</Q>
was a noted copyist, who being countenanced by sir Robert Walpole,
copied several of his collection, and others of the duke of Devonshire
and Dr. Meade. He was indefatigable, and executed a vast number
of works. He succeeded greatly in copying Rubens. He died in
1768, and his pictures were sold by auction in December of that year.
<Q>JOHN WOOTTON,</Q>
a scholar of Wyck, was a very capital master in the branch of his
profession to which he principally devoted himself, and by which he
was peculiarly qualified to please in this country; I mean, by paint∣ing
horses and dogs, which he both drew and coloured with con∣summate
skill, fire and truth. He was first distinguished by frequent∣ing
Newmarket and drawing race-horses. The prints from his hunt∣ing-pieces
<PB N="59" REF="81"/>
are well known. He afterwards applied to landscape,
approached towards Gaspar Poussin, and sometimes imitated happily
the glow of Claud Lorrain. In his latter pieces the leafage of his
trees, from the failure of his eyes, is hard and too distinctly marked.
He died in January, 1765, at his house in Cavendish-square, which
he built, and had painted with much taste and judgment. His prices
were high; for a single horse he has been paid 40 guineas; and 20,
when smaller than life. His collection was sold before his death, on
his quitting business; his drawings and prints January 21, 1761,
and his pictures the 12th and 13th of March following.
<Q>GIACOMO AMICONI,</Q>
a Venetian painter of history, came to England in 1729, when he
was about forty years of age. He had studied under Bellucci in the
Palatine court, and had been some years in the elector of Bavaria's
service. His manner was a still fainter imitation of that nerveless
master Sebastian Ricci, and as void of the glow of life as the Nea∣politan
Solimeni: so little attention do the modern Venetian painters
pay to Titian, Tintoret, and Paul Veronese, even in Venice. Ami∣coni's
women are meer chalk, as if he had only painted from ladies
who paint themselves. Nor was this his worse defect; his figures are
so entirely without expression, that his historical compositions seem
to represent a set of actors in a tragedy, ranged in attitudes against
the curtain draws up. His Marc Antonys are as free from passion
as his Scipios. Yet novelty was propitious to Amiconi, and for a
few years he had great business. He was employed to paint a stair∣case
at lord Tankerville's in St. James's-square [now destroyed.] It
<PB N="60" REF="82"/>
represented stories of Achilles, Telemachus and Tiresias. When he
was to be paid, he produced bills of workmen for scaffolding, &amp;c.
amounting to ninety pounds, and asked no more; content, he said,
with the opportunity of showing what he could do. The peer gave
him <HI>200l.</HI> more. Amiconi then was employed on the staircase at
Powis-house in Great Ormond-street, which he decorated with the
story of Holofernes, but with the additional fault of bestowing Roman
dresses on the personages. His next work was a picture of Shake∣speare
and the muses over the orchestra of the new theatre in Covent-garden.
But as portraiture is the one thing necessary to a painter in
this country, he was obliged to betake himself to that employment,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">For a whole length he was paid sixty guineas.</NOTE>
much against his inclination; yet the English never perhaps were
less in the wrong in insisting that a painter of history should turn
limner; the barrenness of Amiconi's imagination being more suited
to the inactive tameness of a portrait than to groupes and expression.
The duke of Lorrain, afterwards emperor, was then at London and
sat to him. He drew the queen and the three eldest princesses, and
prints were taken from his pictures, which he generally endeavoured
to emblematicize by genii and Cupids. In 1736 he made a journey
to Paris with the celebrated singer Farinelli and returned with him
in the October following. His portrait of Farinelli was engraved.
He then engaged with Wagner, an engraver, in a scheme of
prints from Canalletti's views of Venice, and having married an
Italian singer, returned to his own country in 1739, having acquired
here about <HI>5000l.</HI> At last he settled in Spain, was appointed painter
to the king, and died at Madrid, September 1752. Brunetti, an
<PB N="61" REF="83"/>
Italian, who had arrived before Amiconi, and was a painter of ar∣chitecture
and ornaments, assisted the latter at lord Tankerville's and
other places, and painted scenes for the opera. He etched some
plates of grotesque ornaments, but left England for want of business.
<Q>JAMES SEYMOUR,</Q>
was thought even superior to Wootton in drawing a horse, but was
too idle to apply himself to his profession, and never attained any
higher excellence. He was the only son of Mr. James Seymour, a
banker and great virtuoso, who drew well himself and had been in∣timate
with Faithorne, Lely, Simon, and sir Christopher Wren, and
died at the age of eighty-one, in 1739: the son in 1752, aged fifty.
<Q>JOHN BAPTIST VANLOO,</Q>
brother of Carlo Vanloo, a painter in great esteem at Paris, studied
in the academy at Rome, and became painter to the king of Sar∣dinia,
in whose court he made a considerable fortune, but lost it all
in the Mississipi, going to Paris in the year of that bubble. He was
countenanced by the regent, and appointed one of the king's painters,
though inferior in merit to his brother. At Paris he had the honour
of drawing the portrait of king Stanislas. In 1737 he came to Eng∣land
with his son, when he was about the age of fifty-five. His first
works here were the portraits of Colley Cibber and Owen Mac Swin∣ney,
whose long silver-grey hairs were extremely picturesque and
contributed to give the new painter reputation. Mac Swinney was
a remarkable person<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">See more of him in Cibber's apology for his own life.</NOTE>, of much humour, and had been formerly a
<PB N="62" REF="84"/>
manager of the operas, but for several years had resided at Venice.
He had been concerned in a publication of prints from Vandyck,
ten whole lengths of which were engraved by Van Gunst. He after∣wards
engaged in procuring a set of emblematic pictures, exhibiting
the most shining actions of English heroes, statesmen, and patriots.
These were painted by the best masters then in Italy, and pompous
prints made from them; but with indifferent success, the stories
being so ill told, that it is extremely difficult to decypher to what
individual so many tombs, edifices and allegories belong in each re∣spective
piece. Several of these paintings are in the possession of his
grace the duke of Richmond.</P>
<P>Vanloo soon bore away the chief business of London from every
other painter. His likenesses were very strong, but not favourable,
and his heads coloured with force. He executed very little of the
rest of his pictures, the draperies of which were supplied by Vana∣ken,
and Vanloo's own disciples Eccardt and Root. However, Van∣loo
certainly introduced a better style; his pictures were thoroughly
finished, natural, and no part neglected. He was laborious, and
demanded five sittings from each person. But he soon left the palm
to be again contended for by his rivals. He laboured under a com∣plication
of distempers, and being advised to try the air of his own
country, Provence, he retired thither in October 1742, and died
there in April 1746.
<Q>JOSEPH VANAKEN.</Q>
As in England almost every body's picture is painted, so almost
every painter's works were painted by Vanaken. He was born at
<PB N="63" REF="85"/>
Antwerp, and excelling in sattins, velvets, lace, embroidery, &amp;c.
he was employed by several considerable painters here to draw the
attitudes and dress the figures in their pictures; which makes it very
difficult to distinguish the works of the several performers. Hogarth
drew the supposed funeral of Vanaken, attended by the painters he
worked for, discovering every mark of grief and despair. He died
of a fever July 4, 1749, aged about fifty. He left a brother, who
followed the same business.</P>
<P>There was another of the same sirname, Arnold Vanaken, who
painted small figures, landscapes, conversations, and published a set
of prints of fishes, or the wonders of the deep. Arnold had a brother
who painted in the same way, and scraped mezzotintos.
<Q>CLERMONT,</Q>
a Frenchman, was many years in England, painted in grotesque,
foliages with birds and monkies, and executed several cielings and
ornaments of buildings in gardens; particularly a gallery for Fre∣deric
prince of Wales, at Kew; two temples in the duke of Marl∣borough's
island near Windsor, called from his grotesques, Monkey-island;
the cieling of lord Radnor's gallery, and of my Gothic library,
at Twickenham; the sides of lord Strafford's eating-room in St.
James's-square, from Raphael's loggie in the Vatican; and a cieling
for lord Northumberland at Sion. Clermont returned to his own
country in 1754.
<PB N="64" REF="86" MS="y"/>
<Q>CANALLETTI,</Q>
the well-known painter of views of Venice, came to England in
1746, when he was about the age of fifty, by persuasion of his coun∣tryman
Amiconi, and encouraged by the multitudes of pictures he
had sold to or sent over to the English. He was then in good cir∣cumstances,
and it was said came to vest his money in our stocks.
I think he did not stay here above two years. I have a perspective
by him of the inside of King's-college chapel.
<Q>—JOLI,</Q>
I think a Venetian, was in England in this reign, and painted ruins
with historic figures, in the manner of Paolo Panini. At Joli's
house I saw one of those pictures, in which were assembled as many
blunders and improprieties as could be well contained in that com∣pass.
The subject was Alexander adorning the tomb of Achilles—
on a grave-stone was inscribed, Hic Jacet M. Achille, P. P.
<HI>i. e.</HI> pater patriae. The Christian Latin, the Roman M. for Marcus,
the Pater Patriae, and the Italian termination to Achilles, all this
confusion of ignorance, made the picture a real curiosity.
<Q>GEORGE LAMBERT.</Q>
In a country so profusely beautified with the amaenities of nature, it
is extraordinary that we have produced so few good painters of land∣scape.
As our poets warm their imaginations with sunny hills, or
<PB REF="87"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>GEORGE LAMBERT.</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="65" REF="88"/>
sigh after grottoes and cooling breezes, our painters draw rocks and
precipices and castellated mountains, because Virgil gasped for breath
at Naples, and Salvator wandered amidst Alps and Apennines.
Our ever verdant lawns, rich vales, fields of haycocks, and hop∣grounds,
are neglected as homely and familiar objects. The latter,
which I never saw painted, are very picturesque, particularly in the
season of gathering, when some tendrils are ambitiously climbing,
and others dangling in natural festoons; while poles, despoiled of
their garlands, are erected into easy pyramids that contrast with the
taper and upright columns. In Kent such scenes are often backed
by sand-hills that enliven the green, and the gatherers dispersed
among the narrow alleys enliven the picture, and give it various
distances.</P>
<P><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">There is a print by Smith of one John Lambert, Es{que} painting an historic piece, from a portrait done by himself: I do not know whether he was related to George Lambert.</NOTE> Lambert, who was instructed by Hassel and at first imitated
Wootton, was a very good master in the Italian style, and followed
the manner of Gaspar, but with more richness in his compositions.
His trees were in a great taste, and grouped nobly. He painted
many admirable scenes for the playhouse, where he had room to
display his genius; and, in concert with Scott, executed six large
pictures of their settlements for the East-India company, which are
placed at their house in Leadenhall-street. He died Feb. 1, 1765.
He did a few landscapes in crayons.
<PB N="66" REF="89"/>
<Q>THOMAS WORLIDGE</Q>
for the greater part of his life painted portraits in miniature: he af∣terwards
with worse success performed them in oil; but at last ac∣quired
reputation and money by etchings in the manner of Rem∣brandt,
proved to be a very easy task by the numbers of men who
have counterfeited that master so as to deceive all those who did not
know his works by heart. Worlidge's imitations and his heads in
black-lead have grown astonishingly into fashion. His best piece is the
whole length of sir John Astley, copied from Rembrandt: his print
of the theatre at Oxford and the act there, and his statue of lady Pom∣fret's
Cicero, are very poor performances. His last work was a book
of gems from the antique. He died Sept. 23, 1766, at Hammer∣smith,
though latterly he resided chiefly at Bath. The following
compliment to his wife, on seeing her copy a landscape in needle∣work,
was printed in the Public Advertiser;
<Q><L>At Worlidge's as late I saw</L>
<L>A female artist sketch and draw,</L>
<L>Now take a crayon, now a pencil,</L>
<L>Now thread a needle, strange utensil!</L>
<L>I hardly could believe my eyes</L>
<L>To see hills, houses, steeples rise;</L>
<L>While crewel o'er the canvass drawn</L>
<L>Became a river or a lawn.</L>
<L>Thought I—it was not said thro' malice,</L>
<L>That Worlidge was oblig'd to Pallas;</L></Q>
<PB REF="90"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>THOMAS WORLIDGE</P>
</FIGURE>
<Q><PB N="67" REF="91"/>
<L>For sure such art can be display'd</L>
<L>By none except the blue-ey'd maid!</L>
<L>To him the prude is tender-hearted—</L>
<L>The paintress from her easel started—</L>
<L>“Oh! sir, your servant—pray sit down:</L>
<L>My husband's charm'd you're come to town.”—</L>
<L>For wou'd you think it?—on my life,</L>
<L>'Twas all the while the artist's wife.</L></Q>
I chose to insert these lines, not only in justice to the lady celebrated,
but to take notice that the female art it records, has of late placed
itself with dignity by the side of painting, and actually maintains a
rank among the works of genius. Miss Gray was the first who dis∣tinguished
herself by so bold an emulation of painting. She was
taught by a Mr. Taylor, but greatly excelled him, as appears by
their works at lord Spencer's at Wimbledon. His represents an old
woman selling fruit to a Flemish woman, after Snyder: hers a very
large picture of three recruiting-officers and a peasant, whole lengths—in
each, the figures are as large as life, but in hers whole lengths.
This gentlewoman has been followed by a very great mistress of the
art, Caroline countess of Ailesbury, who has not only surpassed seve∣ral
good pictures that she has copied, but works with such rapidity
and intelligence, that it is almost more curious to see her pictures in
their progress, than after they are finished. Besides several other
works, she has done a picture of fowls, a water-dog and a heron,
from Oudry, and an old woman spinning, whole length, from Ve∣lasco,
that have greater force than the originals. As some of these
masterly performances have appeared in our public exhibitions, I
venture to appeal to that public, whether justice or partiality dictated
this encomium.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="92"/>
<HEAD>ANECDOTES OF PAINTING, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. IV.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Painters in the Reign of King GEORGE II.</HEAD>
<Q>WILLIAM HOGARTH.</Q>
<P>HAVING dispatched the herd of our painters in oil, I reserved
to a class by himself that great and original genius, Hogarth;
considering him rather as a writer of comedy with a pencil, than as
a painter. If catching the manners and follies of an age <HI>living as
they rise,</HI> if general satire on vices and ridicules, familiarized by
strokes of nature, and heightened by wit, and the whole animated
by proper and just expressions of the passions, be comedy, Hogarth
composed comedies as much as Moliere: in his marriage alamode
there is even an intrigue carried on throughout the piece. He is
more true to character than Congreve; each personage is distinct
from the rest, acts in his sphere, and cannot be confounded with
any other of the dramatis personae. The alderman's footboy, in the
last print of the set I have mentioned, is an ignorant rustic; and if
wit is struck out from the characters in which it is not expected, it is
from their acting conformably to their situation and from the mode
<PB REF="93"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>WILLIAM HOGARTH.</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="69" REF="94"/>
of their passions, not from their having the wit of fine gentlemen.
Thus there is wit in the figure of the alderman, who when his
daughter is expiring in the agonies of poison, wears a face of solli∣citude,
but it is to save her gold ring, which he is drawing gently
from her finger. The thought is parallel to Moliere's, where the
miser puts out one of the candles as he is talking. Moliere, inimita∣ble
as he has proved, brought a rude theatre to perfection. Hogarth
had no model to follow and improve upon. He created his art;
and used colours instead of language. His place is between the Ita∣lians,
whom we may consider as epic poets and tragedians, and the
Flemish painters, who are as writers of farce and editors of bur∣lesque
nature.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">When they attempt humour, it is by making a drunkard vomit; they take evacuations for jokes, and when they make us sick, think they make us laugh. A boor hugging a frightful frow is a frequent incident even in the works of Teniers. If there were painters in the Alps, I suppose they would exhibit Mars and Venus with a conjunction of swelled throats. I cannot deny myself the pleasure of observing that we actually possess a painter, who finishing as ex∣quisitely as the Flemish, is a true master of comic nature. Need I say his name is Zaffanii?</NOTE> They are the Tom Browns of the mob. Hogarth
resembles Butler, but his subjects are more universal, and amidst all
his pleasantry, he observes the true end of comedy, reformation;
there is always a moral to his pictures. Sometimes he rose to tra∣gedy,
not in the catastrophe of kings and heroes, but in marking
how vice conducts insensibly and incidentally to misery and shame.
He warns against encouraging cruelty and idleness in young minds,
and discerns how the different vices of the great and the vulgar lead
<PB N="70" REF="95"/>
by various paths to the same unhappiness. The fine lady in Mar∣riage
Alamode, and Tom Nero in the Four Stages of Cruelty, termi∣nate
their story in blood—she occasions the murder of her husband,
he assassinates his mistress. How delicate and superior too is his satire,
when he intimates in the College of Physicians and Surgeons that pre∣side
at a dissection, how the legal habitude of viewing shocking
scenes hardens the human mind, and renders it unfeeling. The pre∣sident
maintains the dignity of insensibility over an executed corpse,
and considers it but as the object of a lecture. In the print of the
Sleeping Judges, this habitual indifference only excites our laughter.</P>
<P>It is to Hogarth's honour that in so many scenes of satire or ridi∣cule,
it is obvious that ill-nature did not guide his pencil. His end
is always reformation, and his reproofs general. Except in the print
of the Times, and the two portraits of Mr. Wilkes and Mr. Churchill
that followed, no man amidst such a profusion of characteristic faces,
ever pretended to discover or charge him with the caricatura of a
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">If he indulged his spirit of ridicule in personalities, it never proceeded be∣yond sketches and drawings; his prints touched the folly, but spared the person. Early he drew a noted miser, one of the sheriffs, trying a mastiff that had robbed his kitchen, but the magistrate's son went to his house and cut the picture to pieces.</NOTE> real person; except of such notorious characters as Chartres and
mother Needham, and a very few more, who are acting officially and
suitably to their professions. As he must have observed so carefully
the operation of the passions on the countenance, it is even wonder∣ful
that he never, though without intention, delivered the very fea∣tures
of any identical person. It is at the same time a proof of his
<PB N="71" REF="96"/>
intimate intuition into nature: but had he been too severe, the hu∣manity
of endeavouring to root out cruelty to animals would atone
for many satires. It is another proof that he drew all his stores from
nature and the force of his own genius, and was indebted neither to
models nor books for his style, thoughts or hints, that he never suc∣ceeded
when he designed for the works of other men. I do not
speak of his early performances at the time that he was engaged by
booksellers, and rose not above those they generally employ; but in
his maturer age, when he had invented his art, and gave a few de∣signs
for some great authors, as Cervantes, Gulliver, and even Hu∣dibras,
his compositions were tame, spiritless, void of humour, and
never reach the merits of the books they were designed to illustrate.
He could not bend his talents to think after any body else. He could
think like a great genius rather than after one. I have a sketch in
oil that he gave me, which he intended to engrave. It was done at
the time that the House of Commons appointed a committee to en∣quire
into the cruelties exercised on prisoners in the Fleet to extort
money from them. The scene is the committee; on the table are
the instruments of torture. A prisoner in rags half starved appears
before them; the poor man has a good countenance that adds to the
interest. On the other hand is the inhuman goaler. It is the very
figure that Salvator Rosa would have drawn for Iago in the moment
of detection. Villany, fear, and conscience are mixed in yellow
and livid on his countenance, his lips are contracted by tremor, his
face advances as eager to lie, his legs step back as thinking to make
his escape; one hand is thrust precipitately into his bosom, the fin∣gers
of the other are catching uncertainly at his button-holes. If this
<PB N="72" REF="97"/>
was a portrait, it is the most speaking that ever was drawn; if it
was not, it is still finer.</P>
<P>It is seldom that his figures do not express the character he intend∣ed
to give them. When they wanted an illustration that colours
could not bestow, collateral circumstances, full of wit, supply notes.
The nobleman in Marriage Alamode has a great air—the coronet on
his crutches, and his pedigree issuing out of the bowels of William
the Conqueror, add his character. In the breakfast the old steward
reflects for the spectator. Sometimes a short label is an epigram,
and is never introduced without improving the subject. Unfortu∣nately
some circumstances, that were temporary, will be lost to poste∣rity,
the fate of all comic authors; and if ever an author wanted a
commentary that none of his beauties might be lost, it is Hogarth—not
from being obscure, [for he never was that but in two or three
of his first prints where transient national follies, as lotteries, free∣masonry,
and the South-sea were his topics] but for the use of fo∣reigners,
and from a multiplicity of little incidents, not essential to,
but always heightening the principal action. Such is the spider's-web
extended over the poor's box in a parish-church; the blunders
in architecture in the nobleman's seat seen through the window, in
the first print of Marriage Alamode; and a thousand in the Strollers
dressing in a Barn, which for wit and imagination, without any other
end, I think the best of all his works: as for useful and deep satire,
that on the Methodists is the most sublime. The scenes of Bedlam
and the gaming-house, are inimitable representations of our serious
follies or unavoidable woes; and the concern shown by the lord-mayor
when the companion of his childhood is brought before him
<PB N="73" REF="98"/>
as a criminal, is a touching picture, and big with humane admoni∣tion
and reflection.</P>
<P>Another instance of this author's genius is his not condescending
to explain his moral lessons by the trite poverty of allegory. If he
had an emblematic thought, he expressed it with wit, rather than by
a symbol. Such is that of the whore's setting fire to the world in the
Rake's Progress. Once indeed he descended to use an allegoric per∣sonage,
and was not happy in it: in one of his election prints Bri∣tannia's
chariot breaks down, while the coachman and footman are
playing at cards on the box. Sometimes too, to please his vulgar
customers, he stooped to low images and national satire, as in the
two prints of France and England, and that of the Gates of Calais.
The last indeed has great merit, though the caricatura is carried
to excess. In all these the painter's purpose was to make his
countrymen observe the ease and affluence of a free government, op∣posed
to the wants and woes of slaves. In Beer-street the English
butcher tossing a Frenchman in the air with one hand, is absolute
hyperbole; and what is worse, was an afterthought, not being in
the first edition. The Gin-alley is much superior, horridly fine, but
disgusting.</P>
<P>His Bartholomew-fair is full of humour; the March to Finchley,
of nature: the Enraged Musician tends to farce. The Four Parts of
the Day, except the last, are inferior to few of his works. The
Sleeping Congregation, the Lecture on the Vacuum, the Laughing
Audience, the Consultation of Physicians as a coat of arms, and the
Cockpit, are perfect in their several kinds. The prints of Industry
and Idleness have more merit in the intention than execution.</P>
<P><PB N="74" REF="99"/>
Towards his latter end he now and then repeated himself, but
seldomer than most great authors who executed so much.</P>
<P>It may appear singular that of an author whom I call comic, and
who is so celebrated for his humour, I should speak in general in so
serious a style; but it would be suppressing the merits of his heart
to consider him only as a promoter of laughter. I think I have
shown that his views were more generous and extensive. Mirth co∣loured
his pictures, but benevolence designed them. He smiled like
Socrates, that men might not be offended at his lectures, and might
learn to laugh at their own follies. When his topics were harmless,
all his touches were marked with pleasantry, and fun. He never
laughed like Rabelais at nonsense that he imposed for wit; but like
Swift combined incidents that divert one from their unexpected en∣counter,
and illustrate the tale he means to tell. Such are the hens
roosting on the upright waves in the scene of the Strollers, and the
devils drinking porter on the altar. The manners or <HI>costume</HI> are
more than observed in every one of his works. The very furniture
of his rooms describe the characters of the persons to whom they
belong; a lesson that might be of use to comic authors. It was re∣served
to Hogarth to write a scene of furniture. The rake's levee-room,
the nobleman's dining-room, the apartments of the husband
and wife in Marriage Alamode, the alderman's parlour, the poet's
bechamber, and many others, are the history of the manners of
the age.</P>
<P>But perhaps too much has been said of this great genius as an
author, it is time to speak of him as a painter, and to mention the
circumstances of his life, in both which I shall be more brief. His
works are his history; as a painter, he had but slender merit.</P>
<P><PB N="75" REF="100"/>
He was born in the parish of St. Bartholomew, London, the son
of a low tradesman, who bound him to a mean engraver of arms on
plate; but before his time was expired he felt the impulse of genius,
and felt it directed him to painting, though little apprized at that
time of the mode nature had intended he should pursue. His ap∣prenticeship
was no sooner expired, than he entered into the academy
in St. Martin's-lane, and studied drawing from the life, in which
he never attained to great excellence. It was character, the passions,
the soul, that his genius was given him to copy. In colouring he
proved no greater a master: his force lay in expression, not in tints
and chiaro scuro. At first he worked for booksellers, and designed
and engraved plates for several books; and, which is extraordinary,
no symptom of genius dawned in those plates. His Hudibras was
the first of his works that marked him as a man above the common;
yet what made him then noticed, now surprizes us to find so little
humour in an undertaking so congenial to his talents. On the suc∣cess
however of those plates he commenced painter, a painter of por∣traits;
the most ill-suited employment imaginable to a man whose
turn certainly was not flattery, nor his talent adapted to look on
vanity without a sneer. Yet his facility in catching a likeness, and
the method he chose of painting families and conversations in small,
then a novelty, drew him prodigious business for some time. It did
not last, either from his applying to the real bent of his disposition,
or from his customers apprehending that a satirist was too formidable
a confessor for the devoteès of self-love. He had already dropped a
few of his smaller prints on some reigning follies, but as the dates
are wanting on most of them, I cannot ascertain which, though those
on the South-sea and Rabbit-woman prove that he had early disco∣vered
<PB N="76" REF="101"/>
his talent for ridicule, though he did not then think of build∣ing
his reputation or fortune on its powers.</P>
<P>His Midnight Modern Conversation was the first work that showed
his command of character: but it was the Harlot's Progress, pub∣lished
in 1729 or 1730 that established his fame. The pictures were
scarce finished and no sooner exhibited to the public, and the sub∣scription
opened, than above twelve hundred names were entered on
his book. The familiarity of the subject, and the propriety of the
execution, made it tasted by all ranks of people. Every engraver
set himself to copy it, and thousands of imitations were dispersed all
over the kingdom. It was made into a pantomime, and performed
on the stage. The Rake's Progress, perhaps superior, had not so
much succe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, from want of novelty; nor indeed is the print of the
arrest equal in merit to the others.</P>
<P>The curtain was now drawn aside, and his genius stood displayed in
its full lustre. From time to time he continued to give those works that
should be immortal, if the nature of his art will allow it. Even the
receipts for his subscriptions had wit in them. Many of his plates he
engraved himself, and often expunged faces etched by his assistants
when they had not done justice to his ideas.</P>
<P>Not content with shining in a path untrodden before, he was am∣bitious
of distinguishing himself as a painter of history. But not
only his colouring and drawing rendered him unequal to the task;
the genius that had entered so feelingly into the calamities and crimes
of familiar life, deserted him in a walk that called for dignity and
grace. The burlesque turn of his mind mixed itself with the most
serious subjects. In his Danae the old nurse tries a coin of the
golden shower with her teeth, to see if it is true gold: the Pool of
<PB N="77" REF="102"/>
Bethesda a servant of a rich ulcerated lady beats back a poor man
that sought the same celestial remedy. Both circumstances are justly
thought, but rather too ludicrous. It is a much more capital fault
that Danae herself is a meer nymph of Drury. He seems to have
conceived no higher idea of beauty.</P>
<P>So little had he eyes to his own deficiencies, that he believed he
had discovered the principle of grace. With the enthusiasm of a
discoverer he cried, Eureka! This was his famous line of beauty,
the ground-work of his Analysis, a book that has many sensible hints
and observations, but that did not carry the conviction nor meet the
universal acquiescence he expected. As he treated his contemporaries
with scorn, they triumphed over this publication, and imitated him
to expose him. Many wretched burlesque prints came out to ridicule
his system. There was a better answer to it in one of the two prints
that he gave to illustrate his hypothesis. In the ball had he confined
himself to such outlines as compose awkwardness and deformity, he
would have proved half his assertion—but he has added two samples
of grace in a young lord and lady, that are strikingly stiff and affect∣ed.
They are a Bath beau and a country beauty.</P>
<P>But this was the failing of a visionary. He fell afterwards into a
grosser mistake. From a contempt of the ignorant virtuosi of the
age, and from indignation at the impudent tricks of picture-dealers,
whom he saw continually recommending and vending vile copies to
bubble-collectors, and from having never studied, indeed having
seen, few good pictures of the great Italian masters, he persuaded
himself that the praises bestowed on those glorious works were no∣thing
but the effects of prejudice. He talked this language till he
believed it; and having heard it often asserted, as is true, that time
<PB N="78" REF="103"/>
gives a mellowness to colours and improves them, he not only de∣nied
the proposition, but maintained that pictures only grew black
and worse by age, not distinguishing between the degrees in which
the proposition might be true or false. He went farther: he deter∣mined
to rival the ancients—and unfortunately chose one of the finest
pictures in England as the object of his competition. This was the
celebrated Sigismonda of sir Luke Schaub, now in the possession of
the duke of Newcastle, said to be painted by Correggio, probably
by Furino, but no matter by whom. It is impossible to see the pic∣ture
or read Dryden's inimitable tale, and not feel that the same soul
animated both. After many essays Hogarth at last produced <HI>his</HI>
Sigismonda—but no more like Sigismonda, than I to Hercules. Not
to mention the wretchedness of the colouring, it was the representa∣tion
of a maudlin strumpet just turned out of keeping, and with eyes
red with rage and usquebaugh, tearing off the ornaments her keeper
had given her. To add to the disgust raised by such vulgar expres∣sion,
her fingers were bloodied by her lover's heart that lay before
her like that of a sheep's for her dinner. None of the sober grief,
no dignity of suppressed anguish, no involuntary tear, no settled
meditation on the fate she meant to meet, no amorous warmth
turned holy by despair; in short all was wanting that should have
been there, all was there that such a story would have banished from
a mind capable of conceiving such complicated woe; woe so sternly
felt and yet so tenderly. Hogarth's performance was more ridicu∣lous
than any thing he had ever ridiculed. He set the price of <HI>400l.</HI>
on it, and had it returned on his hands by the person for whom it
was painted. He took subscriptions for a plate of it, but had the
<PB N="79" REF="104"/>
sense at last to suppress it. I make no more apology for this account
than for the encomiums I have bestowed on him. Both are dictated
by truth, and are the history of a great man's excellencies and errors.
Milton, it is said, preferred his Paradise Regained to his immortal
poem.</P>
<P>The last memorable event of our artist's life was his quarrel with
Mr. Wilkes, in which if Mr. Hogarth did not commence direct
hostilities on the latter, he at least obliquely gave the first offence by
an attack on the friends and party of that gentleman. This conduct
was the more surprizing, as he had all his life avoided dipping his
pencil in political contests, and had early refused a very lucrative
offer that was made to engage him in a set of prints against the head
of a court-party. Without entering into the merits of the cause, I
shall only state the fact. In September 1762, Mr. Hogarth pub∣lished
his print of the Times. It was answered by Mr. Wilkes in a
severe North-Briton. On this the painter exhibited the caricatura of
the writer. Mr. Churchill, the poet, then engaged in the war, and
wrote his epistle to Hogarth, not the brightest of his works, and in
which the severest strokes fell on a defect that the painter had neither
caused nor could amend—his age; and which however was neither
remarkable nor decrepit; much less had it impaired his talents, as
appeared by his having composed but six months before one of his
most capital works, the satire on the Methodists. In revenge for
this epistle, Hogarth caricaturaed Churchill under the form of a
canonical bear, with a club and a pot of porter—et vitulâ tu dignus
&amp; hic—never did two angry men of their abilities throw mud with
less dexterity.</P>
<P><PB N="80" REF="105"/>
Mr. Hogarth, in the year 1730, married the only daughter of
sir James Thornhill, by whom he had no children. He died of
a dropsy in his breast, at his house in Leicester-fields, October 26,
1764.</P>
<P>He sold about twenty-four of his principal pictures by auction in
1745. Mr. Vincent Bourne addressed a copy of Latin hendecasylla∣bles
to him on his chief pictures; and Roquetti, the enameller,
published a French explanation, though a superficial one, of many
of his prints, which, it was said, he had drawn up for the use of
marshal Belleisle, then a prisoner in England.</P>
<P>As I am possessed of the most compleat collection of his prints
that I believe exists, I shall for the use of collectors give a catalogue
of them. Most them were assembled by Mr. Arthur Pond, and
some of them probably are now no where else to be found. I have
added every other print that I could discover to have been designed
or engraved by him. He had kept no suite himself, and had for∣gotten
several in which he had been concerned. He gave me what
few sketches had not been forced from him by his friends, particu∣larly
the Committee above-mentioned, and the first thoughts for In∣dustry
and Idleness.</P>
<DIV3>
<PB N="81" REF="106"/>
<HEAD>Catalogue of Mr. HOGARTH's Prints.</HEAD>
<DIV4 N="1">
<HEAD>CLASS 1. MISCELLANEOUS.</HEAD>
<P>1. His own cypher, with his name under it at length; a plate he
used for his books.</P>
<P>2. His own head in a cap, oval frame, a pug dog, and a pallet
with the line of beauty, &amp;c. inscribed Guglielmus Hogarth. Se ipse
pinxit &amp; sculpsit, 1749. A square print.</P>
<P>3. His own portrait, sitting and painting the mufe of comedy.
Head profile, in a cap. The Analysis of Beauty on the floor. W.
Hogarth serjeant-painter to his majesty. The face engraved by
W. Hogarth, 1758.</P>
<P>4. The same; the face retouched, but not so like as in the pre∣ceding.
Comedy also has the face and mask marked with black,
and inscribed, Comedy, 1764. No other inscription but his name,
William Hogarth.</P>
<P>5. An angel holding a palm in the left hand. A shop-bill.</P>
<P>6. Music introduced to Apollo by Minerva. 1727. Frontispiece
to some book, music, or ticket for a concert.</P>
<P>7. Minerva sitting and holding the arms of Holland, four Cupids
round her. Done for the books of John Holland, herald-painter.</P>
<P>8. Christ and his disciples; persons at a distance carried to an
hospital. In as much as ye have done it unto one of the least of
these my brethren, ye have done it unto me. St. Matt. xxv. ver. 40.
W. Hogarth inv. C. Grignion sculp. Ticket for a charity.</P>
<P><PB N="82" REF="107"/>
9. Seven small prints for Apuleius's Golden Ass. W. Hogarth
inv. &amp; sculp. On some, W. Hogarth fec.</P>
<P>15. Gulliver presented to the queen of Babilary. W. Hogarth inv.
Ger. Vandergucht sculp. It is the frontispiece to the Travels of
Capt. John Gulliver.</P>
<P>16. Five small prints for the translation of Cassandra. W. Ho∣garth
inv. &amp; sculp.</P>
<P>20. Six larger for Don Quixote. W. Hogarth inv. &amp; sculp.</P>
<P>26. Two small for Milton. W. Hogarth inv. &amp; sc.</P>
<P>28. Frontispiece to Terrae-filius. W. Hogarth fec.</P>
<P>29. Frontispiece to Tom Thumb. W. Hogarth inv. Ger. Van∣dergucht
sc. There is some humour in this print.</P>
<P>30. Frontispiece to the Humours of Oxford. W. Hogarth inv.
Ger Vandergucht sc.</P>
<P>31. Judith and Holofernes. Per vulnera servor, morte tuâ vivens.
W. Hogarth inv. Ger. Vandergucht sc. A frontispiece.</P>
<P>32. Perfeus, and Medusa dead, and Pegasus. Frontispiece to the
books of the entertainment of Perfeus and Andromeda. W. H. fec.</P>
<P>33. A monk leading an ass with a Scotch man and woman on it.
Head-piece to the Jacobite's Journal. Though this was done in 1748,
I place it here among his indifferent prints.</P>
<P>34. Eleven prints to Aubrey de la Motray's Travels. His name
to each.</P>
</DIV4>
<DIV4 N="2">
<HEAD>CLASS 2. PORTRAITS.</HEAD>
<P>1. The right hon. Frances lady Byron. Whole length, mezzo∣tinto.
W. Hogarth pinx. J. Faber fec. 1736.</P>
<P><PB N="83" REF="108"/>
2. The right hon. Gustavus lord viscount Boyne, &amp;c. &amp;c. Whole
length, mezzotinto. W. Hogarth pinx. Andrew Miller fecit. A
very bad print, done in Ireland.</P>
<P>3. Martin Folkes: half length: engraved. Mine is a proof
and has no inscription.</P>
<P>4. Sarah Malcolm, executed in 1732 for murdering her mistress
and two other women; drawn in Newgate. W. Hogarth (ad
vivum) pinxit &amp; sculpsit. This woman put on red to sit to him for
her picture two days before her execution. I have the original.</P>
<P>5. Simon lord Lovat, drawn from the life and etched in aqua∣fortis
by William Hogarth, 1746.</P>
<P>6. Mr. Pine, in the manner of Rembrandt. Mezzotinto, by
Mc. Ardell.</P>
<P>7. Captain Thomas Coram, who obtained the charter for the
Foundling-hospital. Mezzotinto, ditto.</P>
<P>8. Jacobus Gibbs, architectus. W. Hogarth delin. J. Mc. Ar∣dell
fec. partly mezzotinto, parly graved.</P>
<P>9. Daniel Lock, es{que} mezzotinto; Wm. Hogarth pinx. J. Mc.
Ardell fecit.</P>
<P>10. Benjamin Hoadley, bishop of Winchester. W. Hogarth pinx.
B. Baron sculp.</P>
<P>11. Thomas Herring, archbishop of Canterbury. W. Hogarth p.
B. Baron sculp.</P>
<P>12. Mr. Garrick, in the character of Richard III. Painted by
Wm. Hogarth; engraved by Wm. Hogarth and C. Grignion.</P>
<P>13. T. Morell, S. T. P. S. S. A. W. Hogarth delin. James
Basire sculp.</P>
<P><PB N="84" REF="109"/>
14. Henry Fielding, aetatis 48. W. Hogarth del. James Basire
sculp.</P>
<P>15. John Wilkes, esq. Drawn from the life and etched in aqua∣fortis
by Wm. Hogarth.</P>
<P>16. The Bruiser C. Churchill in the character of a Russian Her∣cules,
&amp;c. A Dutch dog pissing on the Epistle to Hogarth: a pal∣let,
the North-Britons and a begging-box to collect subscriptions for
them. Designed and engraved by W. Hogarth.</P>
<P>17. The same; but over the pallet lies a political print, in
which the painter is correcting Churchill and Wilkes in the charac∣ters
of a bear and monkey. Other satirical emblems behind.</P>
</DIV4>
<DIV4 N="3">
<HEAD>CLASS 3. COMIC and SERIOUS PRINTS.</HEAD>
<P>1. A burlesque on Kent's altar-piece at St. Clement's, with notes.
It represents angels very ill drawn, playing on various instruments.
I never saw but my proof which is on blue paper.</P>
<P>2. A midnight modern conversation.</P>
<P>3. Twelve prints for Hudibras, the large set.</P>
<P>4. The small set, containing seventeen prints with Butler's head.</P>
<P>5. A woman swearing a child to a grave citizen, with twelve
English verses. W. Hogarth pinx. J. Sympson, jun. sculp. A
very bad print.</P>
<P>6. Mary Tofts, the rabbit-woman of Godalmin, in labour. No
name to it.</P>
<P>7. The Lilliputians giving a clyster to Gulliver. A Lilliputian
painter's name to it. Hogarth sculp.</P>
<P><PB N="85" REF="110"/>
8. An emblematic print on the South-sea. Persons riding on
wooden horses. The devil cutting Fortune into collops. A man
broken on the wheel, &amp;c. W. Hogarth inv. &amp; sc.</P>
<P>9. A masquerade. There is much wit in this print. Invented
for the use of ladies and gentlemen by the ingenious Mr. H—r.
(Heidegger.)</P>
<P>10. Another, smaller, on masquerades and operas. Burlington∣gate,
as in the following. W. Hogarth inv. &amp; sculp.</P>
<P>11. The gate of Burlington-house. Pope white-washing it, and
bespattering the duke of Chandos's coach. A satire on Pope's epis∣tle
on taste. No name.</P>
<P>12. The Lottery. Emblematic, and not good. W. Hogarth inv.
&amp; sculp.</P>
<P>13. Taste in high Life. A beau and a fashionable old lady.
Painted by Mr. Hogarth. This was probably not published by
himself.</P>
<P>14. Booth, Wilks and Cibber contriving a pantomime. A satire
on farces. No name.</P>
<P>15. Charmers of the Age. A satire on stage-dancers. A sketch.
No name. The two last very scarce.</P>
<P>16. Henry VIII. and Anne Boleyn. Hogarth design. &amp; sculp.
Very indifferent.</P>
<P>17. The Mystery of Masonry brought to Light by the Gormogons.
Stolen from Coypel's Don Quixote. W. Hogarth inv. &amp; sc.</P>
<P>18. Sancho starved at Dinner by his Physician. W. Hogarth inv.
&amp; sculp.</P>
<P><PB N="86" REF="111"/>
19. Boys peeping at Nature. The subscription-ticket to the Har∣lot's
Progress.</P>
<P>20. The Harlot's Progress, in six plates.</P>
<P>21. The Rake's Progress, in eight plates.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The Rake's Progress was pirated by Boitard on one very large sheet of pa∣per, containing the several scenes represented by Mr. Hogarth. It came out about a fortnight before the genuine set, but was soon forgotten. However this gave occasion to Hogarth to apply for an act of parliament to secure the property of prints. He applied to Mr. Huggins, who took for his model the statute of queen Anne in favour of literary property. The act passed; but some years after appeared to be too loosely drawn, for on a cause founded on it, which came be∣fore lord Hardwick in chancery, he determined that no assignee, claiming under an assignment from the original inventor, could take any benefit by it. Hogarth immediately after the passing the act, published a small print with emblematic devices, and an inscription expressing his gratitude to the three branches of the legislature. This plate he afterwards made to serve for a receipt for subscriptions to the election-prints. Vide N<SUP>o</SUP> 54 of this class.</NOTE></P>
<P>22. The fourth plate of the same, with variations.</P>
<P>23. Two prints of Before and After.</P>
<P>24. The sleeping Congregation.</P>
<P>25. Bartholomew-fair.</P>
<P>26. A festoon with a mask, a roll of paper, a pallet and a laurel.
Subscription-ticket for Garrick in Richard the Third.</P>
<P>27. The poor Poet.</P>
<P>28. The Lecture. Datur vacuum.</P>
<P>29. The laughing Audience.</P>
<P><PB N="87" REF="112"/>
30. Consultation of Physicians. Arms of the undertakers.</P>
<P>31. Rehearsal of an Oratorio. Singing men and boys.</P>
<P>32. The four Parts of the Day.</P>
<P>33. Strolling Actresses dressing in a Barn.</P>
<P>34. The Search-Night. W. Hogarth inv. A very bad print,
and I believe an imposition.</P>
<P>35. The enraged Musician.</P>
<P>36. Characters and caricaturas, to show that Leonardo da Vinci
exaggerated the latter. The subscription-ticket to Marriage a la
Mode.</P>
<P>37. Marriage a la Mode, in six prints.</P>
<P>38. The Pool of Bethesda, from the picture he painted for St.
Bartholomew's hospital, in which parish he was born. Engraved by
Ravenet.</P>
<P>39. A stage-coach. An election-procession in the yard.</P>
<P>40. Industry and Idleness, in twelve plates.</P>
<P>41. An auction of pictures, duplicates of the same pictures. This
was a ticket to admit persons to bid for his works at his auction.</P>
<P>42. The Gates of Calais. His own head sketching the view. He
was arrested as he was making the drawing, but set at liberty when
his purpose was known.</P>
<P>43. A stand of various arms, bagpipes, &amp;c. The subscription-ticket
for the March to Finchley.</P>
<P>44. The March to Finchley; dedicated to the king of Prussia, in
resentment for the late king's sending for the picture to St. James's
and returning it without any other notice.</P>
<P>45. Beer-street; two of them with variations; and Gin-lane.</P>
<P><PB N="88" REF="113"/>
46. The Stages of Cruelty, in four prints.</P>
<P>47. Paul before Felix, designed and scratched in the true Dutch
taste by W. Hogarth. This is a satire on Dutch pictures.</P>
<P>48. Paul before Felix, from the original painting in Lincoln's-inn
hall painted by W. Hogarth. There is much less dignity in this
than wit in the preceding.</P>
<P>49. The same, as first designed, but the wife of Felix was after∣wards
omitted, because St. Paul's hand was very improperly placed
before her.</P>
<P>50. Columbus breaking the egg. The subscription-ticket to his
Analysis.</P>
<P>51. The two prints to the Analysis.</P>
<P>52. France and England, two plates.</P>
<P>53. Two plates to Tristram Shandy.</P>
<P>54. Crowns, mitres, maces, &amp;c. The Subscription-ticket to the
Election.</P>
<P>55. Four prints of an election.</P>
<P>56. The sleeping Judges.</P>
<P>57. The Cockpit.</P>
<P>58. Frontispiece to the Farmer's Return from London.</P>
<P>59. The Wigs and Head-dresses at the Coronation of George III.</P>
<P>60. Credulity, Superstition and Fanaticism. Satire on the Me∣thodists.</P>
<P>61. Frontispiece to Kirby's Perspective. Satire on false per∣spective.</P>
<P>62. Frontispiece to Brook Taylor's Perspective. With an attempt
at a new order.</P>
<P><PB N="89" REF="114"/>
63. Frontispiece and tailpiece to the catalogue of pictures exhibited
in 1761.</P>
<P>64. Time blackening a picture. Subscription-ticket for his Sigis∣monda.
This and the preceding tailpiece are satires on connoisseurs.</P>
<P>65. The Times.</P>
<P>66. Tailpiece to his works. Another satire on dealers in dark
pictures.</P>
<P>Hogarth, in his portrait-conversations, was imitated by Phillips,
a young man, who acquired great business. He was son of a painter
in oil, who died in 1741, aged about sixty. The son died much
younger.</P>
</DIV4>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="115"/>
<HEAD>ANECDOTES of PAINTING, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. V.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Painters in Enamel and Miniature in the Reign of
George II.</HEAD>
<DIV3>
<HEAD>JOHN STEPHEN LIOTARD,</HEAD>
<P>OF Geneva,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">He was born in 1702, and was designed for a merchant. He went to study at Paris in 1725, and in 1738 accompanied the marquis de Puisieux to Rome, who was going ambassador to Naples. At Rome he was taken notice of by the earls of Sandwich and Besborough, then lord Duncannon, who engaged Liotard to go with them on a voyage to Constantinople. <HI>See Museum Florent. vol.</HI> X, where lord Duncannon's name is spelt milord D'un Canon.</NOTE> came over in the last reign, and stayed two years.
He painted admirably well in miniature, and finely in enamel,
though he seldom practiced it. But he is best known by his works
in crayons. His likenesses were as exact as possible, and too like to
please those who sat to him; thus he had great business the first year,
and very little the second. Devoid of imagination, and one would
think of memory, he could render nothing but what he saw before
his eyes. Freckles, marks of the small-pox, every thing found its
place; not so much from fidelity, as because he could not conceive
the absence of any thing that appeared to him. Truth prevailed in
all his works, grace in very few or none. Nor was there any ease in
his outline; but the stiffness of a bust in all his portraits. Thence,
though more faithful to a likeness, his heads want air and the softness
of flesh, so conspicuous in Rosalba's pictures. Her bodies have a dif∣ferent
<PB REF="116"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>LIOTARD.</P>
<P>FREDERICK ZINCKE.</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="91" REF="117"/>
fault; she gave to men an effeminate protuberance about the
breasts; yet her pictures have much more genius. The earls of Har∣rington
and Besborough have some of his most capital works. At
Constantinople he became acquainted with the late lord Edgcumbe,
and sir Everard Fawkener, our ambassador, who persuaded him to
come to England. On his way he passed some time at Paris. In his
journey to the Levant he adopted the eastern habit, and wore it here
with a very long beard. It contributed much to the portraits of him∣self,
and some thought to draw customers; but he was really a painter
of uncommon merit. After his return, he married a young<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Maria Fargues, daughter of a merchant at Amsterdam</NOTE> wife,
and sacrificed his beard to Hymen. He came again to England in
1772, and brought a collection of pictures of different masters, which
he sold by auction; and some pieces of glass painted by himself with
surprising effect of light and shade, but a mere curiosity, as it was
necessary to darken the room before they could be seen to advantage;
he affixed too, as usual, extravagant prices to them. He staid here
about two years, as in his former journey. He has engraved some
Turkish portraits, one of the empress queen and the eldest arch-duch∣ess,
in Turkish habits, and the heads of the emperor and empress.
<Q>FREDERIC ZINCKE</Q>
was born at Dresden about 1684, and came to England in 1706,
where he studied under Boit, whom at length he not only surpassed,
but rivalled Petitot. I have a head of Cowley by him after sir Peter
Lely, which is allowed to excel any single work of that charming
enameller. The impassioned glow of sentiment, the eyes swimming
with youth and tenderness, and the natural fall of the long ringlets
<PB N="92" REF="118"/>
that flow round the unbuttoned collar, are rendered with the most
exquisite nature, and finished with elaborate care. For a great num∣ber
of years Mr. Zincke had as much business as he could execute;
and when at last he raised his price from twenty to thirty guineas, it
was occasioned by his desire of lessening his fatigue, for no man, so
superior in his profession, was less intoxicated with vanity. He was
particularly patronized by the late king and queen, and was appoint∣ed
cabinet-painter to the late prince of Wales. Her royal highness
princess Amelie has many portraits of the royal family by him of a
larger than his usual size. The late duke of Cumberland bought se∣veral
of his best works, particularly his beautiful copy of Dr. Meade's
queen of Scots by Isaac Oliver. He made a short visit to his own
country in 1737, and about 1746, his eyes failing, he retired from
business to South-Lambeth, with a second wife, by whom he had
three or four children. His first wife was a handsome woman, of
whom he had been very fond; there is a print of him and her: he
had a son by her, for whom he bought a place in the six clerks office,
and a daughter, who died a little before he retired to Lambeth. Af∣ter
his quitting business, madame Pompadour prevailed upon him to
copy in enamel a picture of the king of France, which she sent over
on purpose. Mr. Zincke died in March, 1767.
<Q>ROUQUET,</Q>
a Swiss of French extraction, was many years in England, and imi∣tated
Mr. Zincke in enamel with some success. He afterwards set∣tled
at Paris and improved considerably. He published a small tract
on the present state of the arts in England. I have mentioned his
explanation of Hogarth's prints.
<PB N="93" REF="119"/>
<Q>GROTH,</Q>
a German, painted in water-colours and enamel, but made no great
proficience.
<Q>BERNARD LENS,</Q>
of a family of artists, whom I have mentioned in the Catalogue of
Engravers, was an admirable painter in miniature. He painted
some portraits in that way, but his excellence was copying the works
of great masters, particularly Rubens and Vandyck, whose colour∣ing
he imitated exactly. He was painter to the crown by the title of
enameller, which was changed from limner, when Boit held the
office. Lens published some views and drawing-books, as he had
many scholars. He made two sales of his pictures, and died at
Knightsbridge, whither he had retired from business about 1741.
He had three sons, two that followed his profession, of whom one is
yet living.
<Q>JOSEPH GOUPY</Q>
was another fine painter in water-colours, but in a different style from
Lens. The latter stippled the faces, and finished highly; Goupy
imitated the boldness of strokes in oil. The latter too copied many
pictures of Italian masters, and excelled in imitating Salvator Rosa,
from whose works he engraved some prints. He had the honour
of teaching her royal highness the princess of Wales. His copies of
the cartoons were sold to the duke of Chandos for <HI>300l.</HI> but at the
<PB N="94" REF="120"/>
duke's sale produced not 17 guineas. If the painter had exacted, the
public had still less justice. Joseph died the latter end of 1747. He
had an uncle, born in France from whence the family sprung, who
came to England, and had already a brother here a fan-painter.
Louis, of whom I speak, painted portraits in oil, and afterwards
worked in fresco and crayons, and taught miniature. He had at∣tended
lord Burlington into Italy. There is a print of him by
George White. His nephew Joseph, and Bernard Lens were two of
our best miniature-painters, and their works worthy of any cabinet.
<Q>JAMES DEACON,</Q>
a gentleman of great talents for music and drawing, towards the
end of his life engaged professedly in the business, took Mr. Zincke's
house in Covent-garden, and painted portraits in miniature in a very
masterly manner; but had scarce embarked in the profession, when
he lost his life attending a cause at the Old Bailey, the day that
the goal-distemper destroyed the judge, the lord-mayor, and so
many of the audience, in May 1750.
<Q>—SPENCER</Q>
painted portraits in miniature, and lastly in enamel, with some
merit. He died October 30, 1763.</P>
<P><PB REF="121"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>MICHAEL RYSBRACK.</P>
</FIGURE></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3>
<PB N="95" REF="122"/>
<HEAD>STATUARIES.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">J. MICHAEL RYSBRACH,</HEAD>
<P>The best sculptor that has appeared in these islands since Le Soeur,
was born at Antwerp. His father was a landscape-painter, and had
been in England, but quitted it with Largilliere and went to Paris,
where he married, and returning to Brussels and Antwerp, died at
the latter in 1726, at the age of fourscore. Michael his son arrived
here in 1720, then about the age of twenty-six, and began with mo∣delling
small figures in clay, to show his skill. The earl of Notting∣ham
sat to him for his bust, in which the artist succeeded so well,
that he began to be employed in large works, particularly monu∣ments.
For some time he was engaged by Gibbs, who was sensible
of the young man's merit, but turned it to his own account, con∣tracting
for the figures with the persons who bespoke the tombs,
and gaining the chief benefit from the execution. Thus Gibbs re∣ceived
<HI>100l.</HI> a piece from lord Oxford for the statues on Prior's mo∣nument,
yet paid Rysbrach but <HI>35l.</HI> each. The statuary, though
no vain man, felt his own merit, and shook off his dependence on
the architect, as he became more known and more admired. Busi∣ness
crouded upon him, and for many years all great works were
committed to him; and his deep knowledge of his art and singular
industry gave general satisfaction. His models were thoroughly
<PB N="96" REF="123"/>
studied, and ably executed; and as a sculptor capable of furnishing
statues was now found, our taste in monuments improved, which
till Rysbrach's time had depended more on masonry and marbles
than statuary. Gothic tombs owed their chief grandeur to rich cano∣pies,
fretwork, and abundance of small niches and trifling figures.
Bishops in cumbent attitudes and cross-legged templars admitted no
grace, nor required any. In the reigns of queen Elizabeth and king
James I. a single figure reclining at length on the elbow in robes or
serjeant's gown, was commonly overwhelmed and surrounded with
diminutive pillars and obelisks of various marbles; and if particu∣larly
sumptuous, of alabaster gilt. Gibbs, in the duke of New∣castle's
monument in the abbey, seems to have had an eye to that
kind of tasteless expence. From the reign of Charles I. altar-tombs
or mural tablets with cherubims and flaming urns, generally satisfied
the piety of families. Bird indeed bestowed busts and basreliefs on
those he decorated, but sir Cloudesly Shovel's, and other monuments
by him, made men of taste dread such honours. Now and then
had appeared a ray of simplicity, as in sir Francis Vere's and cap∣tain
Hollis's tombs. The abilities of Rysbrach taught the age to
depend on statuary for its best ornaments, and though he was too
fond of pyramids for back-grounds, his figures are well disposed,
simple and great. We seem since to have advanced into scenery.
Mr. Nightingale's tomb, though finely thought and well executed,
is more theatric than sepulchral. The crouds and clusters of tombs
in the abbey has imposed hard conditions on our sculptors, who
have been reduced to couch obelisks in slanting windows, and rear
masses into the air, while St. Paul's remains naked of ornaments;
<PB N="97" REF="124"/>
though it had better remain so, than be subjected to the indiscrimi∣nate
expence of all who are willing to indulge their vanity.</P>
<P>Besides numbers more, Rysbrach executed the monument of sir
Isaac Newton and of the duke of Marlborough at Blenheim, and the
equestrian statue in bronze of king William at Bristol in 1733, for
which he received <HI>1800l.</HI> Scheemaker's model, which was rejected,
was however so well designed, that the city of Bristol made him a
present of <HI>50l.</HI> for his trouble. Rysbrach made also a great many
busts, and most of them very like, as of Mr. Pope, Gibbs, sir Ro∣bert
Walpole, the duke and duchess of Argyle, the duchess of Marl∣borough,
lord Bolingbroke, Wootton, Ben Johnson, Butler, Milton,
Cromwell, and himself; the statues of king George I. and of king
George II. at the Royal-Exchange; the heads in the hermitage at
Richmond, and those of the English worthies in the Elysian-fields
at Stowe.</P>
<P>This enjoyment of deserved fame was at length interrupted by the
appearance of Mr. Scheemaker's Shakespeare in Westminster-abbey,
which besides its merit, had the additional recommendation of Mr.
Kent's fashionable name. I shall say something hereafter on the de∣fects
of that design. It however hurt the vogue of Mr. Rysbrach,
who, though certainly not obscured, found his business decline, as
it was affected considerably afterwards by the competition of Mr.
Roubiliac; and no merit can chain the fickleness of fashion. Piqued
at Mr. Scheemaker's success, Rysbrach produced his three statues of
Palladio, Inigo Jones, and Fiamingo, and at last his chef d'oeuvre,
his Hercules; an exquisite summary of his skill, knowledge, and
judgment. This athletic statue, for which he borrowed the head of
<PB N="98" REF="125" MS="y"/>
the Farnesian god, was compiled from various parts and limbs of
seven or eight of the strongest and best made men in London, chiefly
the bruisers and boxers of the then flourishing amphitheatre for box∣ing,
the sculptor selecting the parts which were the most truly formed
in each. The arms were Broughton's, the breast a celebrated coach∣man's,
a bruiser, and the legs were those of Ellis the painter, a great
frequenter of that gymnasium. As the games of that Olympic aca∣demy
frequently terminated to its heroes at the gallows, it was soon
after suppressed by act of parliament, so that in reality Rysbrach's
Hercules is the monument of those gladiators. It was purchased by
Mr. Hoare, and is the principal ornament of the noble temple at
Stourhead, that beautiful assemblage of art, taste, and landscapes.</P>
<P>Mr. Rysbrach, who had by no means raised a fortune equal to
his deserts, before his death made a public sale of his remaining
works and models, to which he added a large collection of his own
historic drawings, conceived and executed in the true taste of the
great Italian masters. Another sale followed his death, which hap∣pened
January 8, 1770.</P>
<P>He had two brothers, Peter Andreas and G. Rysbrachs, who
painted fish, dead fowls and landscape, with considerable merit;
particularly the elder, who was born at Paris in 1690, and died here
of a consumption in 1648. In one of Michael's sales were some
pieces of history by a Louis Rysbrach; I do not know whether bro∣ther
or nephew of the statuary, probably the latter; Peter, the eld∣est
of all the brothers, had several children.</P>
<P>He had a scholar too, named Vander Hagen, who carved heads in
ivory.
<PB REF="126"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>LEWIS FRANCIS ROUBILIAC</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="99" REF="127"/>
<Q>L. F. ROUBILIAC,</Q>
born at Lyons in France, became a formidable rival to Rysbrach,
and latterly was more employed. He had little business till sir Ed∣ward
Walpole recommended him to execute half the busts at Tri∣nity-college,
Dublin; and by the same patron's interest he was em∣ployed
on the monument of the general, John duke of Argyle, in
Westminster-abbey, on which the statue of Eloquence is very mas∣terly
and graceful. His statue of Handel, in the garden at Vaux∣hall,
fixed Roubiliac's fame. Two of his principal works are the
monuments of the late duke and duchess of Montagu in Northamp∣tonshire,
well performed and magnificent, but wanting simplicity.
This able artist had a turn to poetry, and wrote satires in French verse.
He died January 11, 1762, and was buried in the parish of St.
Martin's, where he lived.
<Q>Signor GÜELPHI,</Q>
a scholar of Camillo Rusconi, was invited to England by lord Bur∣lington,
for whom he did many works in London and at Chiswick.
He was some time employed in repairing the antiques at lord Pom∣fret's
at Easton Neston, now at Oxford. His tomb of Mr. Craggs
in Westminster is graceful and simple, but shows that he was a
very indifferent sculptor. After a residence here of near twenty years
he returned to his native Bologna in 1734.
<PB N="100" REF="128"/>
<Q>L. DELVAUX</Q>
worked with Plumiere, and then with Bird. He went to Italy with
Scheemaker in August 1728, staid four or five years, and then re∣turned
to England; but settled at last at Brussels. There is a good
groupe by him at Stowe. For the late earl of Tilney he made a
statue of Hercules; and the figure of Time for the duke of Buck∣ingham's
monument in Westminster-abbey. The duchess's figure
was executed by Scheemaker.</P>
<P>A retainer of the art on a smaller scale was
<Q>JAMES FRANCIS VERSKOVIS,</Q>
an excellent carver in ivory, born in Flanders but settled at Rome,
where he was so much employed by English travellers, that he con∣cluded
he should make a fortune in England: he came over—and
starved. He executed whole figures in small and vases, with perfect
taste and judgment, and carved also in wood. He had a son, who
to the same arts added painting, but died young in 1749, before his
father. The latter did not survive above a year.</P>
<P>It would be injustice to omit the late Mr. Gosset, and his nephew
who has excelled his uncle, and carried the art of taking likenesses
in wax to surprizing perfection.
<PB REF="129"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>LAURENCE DELVAUX.</P>
</FIGURE></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3>
<PB N="101" REF="130"/>
<HEAD>MEDALLISTS.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">JOHN DASSIER,</HEAD>
<P>Though never in England, is certainly entitled to a place in this
catalogue. He was medallist to the republic of Geneva, and aspir∣ing
to be employed in the mint here, struck a series of the kings of
England, in a better style than our medals had been of late years.
Some of the heads indeed were not taken from true originals, but
the temples and monuments on the reverses were well designed and
executed. He published them by subscription in 1731, at six guineas
for 33 medals in copper, and fifteen in silver. His brother James
had been here three or four years before to endeavour to procure a
place in our mint for John, but none being vacant, sir Andrew
Fountaine, the celebrated virtuoso and patron of artists, and Mr.
Conduit, who had married sir Isaac Newton's neice, and who were
the persons then directing the mint, offered a pension of <HI>50l.</HI> a year
to Dassier till Mr. Croker should die; but he was not content with
the offer. James Antony Dassier, nephew of John, came over, and
on Croker's death in 1740, was next year appointed second engraver
to the mint, and returned to Geneva in 1745. The uncle had ex∣ecuted
a set of the reformers in smaller brass, and begun large me∣dals
of some of our great men then living; the nephew did several
more, which were sold in copper at seven shillings and sixpence each,
<PB N="102" REF="131"/>
and are very good performances, though inferior to the medals of
the popes by Hamerani, and more inferior to those of St. Urbain,
medallist to the last dukes of Lorrain. There is a beautiful and nu∣merous
suite of Roman history in small medals of bronze by the
younger Dassier.
<Q>J. CHRISTOPHER TANNER,</Q>
of Saxe Gotha, came to England about 1733, and had practiced
carving and graving for snuff-boxes, gun-locks, and in mother of
pearl. He was retained as a domestic in the family of the prince
of Wales, and by Mr. Conduit employed in the mint, where he
rose to be principal engraver on the death of Mr. Croker. He did
medals of the prince and princess of Orange and sir Isaac Newton,
and the large family medal of the late king and queen and all their
children.
<Q>LAURENCE NATTIER,</Q>
of Biberach in Suabia, was a good engraver of intaglias and medal∣list.
He struck a fine medal of sir Robert Walpole, the reverse of
which was copied from lord Leicester's statue of Cicero. He had
studied in Italy, and afterwards resided several years in England. In
1746 he went to Holland to make a medal of the prince of Orange,
as in 1743 he had been in Denmark with Marcus Touscher, painter,
architect and engraver, of Nuremberg, who arrived here from Italy
in 1741, and brought a high-finished drawing of the great duke's
<PB N="103" REF="132"/>
entrance into Florence, which he also executed with great labour
for the empress-queen, who however did not purchase it. The king
of Denmark bought the plate of the entry, and retained Touscher
in his service. Mr. Nattier published a well-known book on ancient
gems, and died of an asthma December 27, 1763, at St. Peters∣burgh,
whither he had been invited as principal engraver to the
empress.</P>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="133"/>
<HEAD>ANECDOTES of PAINTING, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VI.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">Architects in the Reign of George II.</HEAD>
<P>IT was in this reign that architecture resumed all her rights. Noble
publications of Palladio, Jones, and the antique, recalled her
to true principles and correct taste; she found men of genius to ex∣ecute
her rules, and patrons to countenance their labours. She found
more, and what Rome could not boast, men of the first rank who
contributed to embellish their country by buildings of their own design
in the purest style of antique composition. Before the glorious close
of a reign that carried our arms and victories beyond where Roman
eagles ever flew, ardour for the arts had led our travellers to explore
whatever beauties of Grecian or Latin taste still subsisted in provinces
once subjected to Rome; and the fine editions in consequence of
those researches have established the throne of architecture in Britain,
while itself languishes at Rome, wantons in tawdry imitations of the
French in other parts of Europe, and struggles in vain at Paris to
surmount their prepossession in favour of their own errors—for fickle
as we call that nation, their music and architecture prove how long
their ears and eyes can be constant to discord and disproportion.
<PB N="105" REF="134"/>
<Q>GIACOMO LEONI,</Q>
a Venetian, who had been architect to the elector Palatine, settled in
England, and published a fine edition of Palladio in 1742. He
was employed in building several houses, and died in 1746.
<Q>JOHN NICHOLAS SERVANDONI,</Q>
a celebrated architect, resided here some years, though having va∣rious
talents, he was best known in his own country as a painter.
He executed many scenes for the opera, and painted a staircase (in
conjunction with one Andrea) at Mr. Arundel's, the corner of Bur∣lington-street,
now Mr. Townshend's. He also gave the design of
the theatre of fireworks for the peace in 1746, soon after which he
returned to Paris. He was born at Florence May 2, 1695, studied
under Paolo Panini and Rossi, and was created a knight of the order
of Christ. His genius was particularly turned to theatric machinery,
of which he gave proofs at Dresden and Lisbon, and especially at
Paris, where he was received into the academy of painting and sculp∣ture,
and where he contrived magnificent serious pantomimes in the
grande sale des machines, besides fine decorations in several operas.
An account of those shows may be seen in the fifth volume of the
Dictionaire des Theatres. His capital work was the facade of St.
Sulpice, but the enormous masses of stone which he has heaped on
the tops of the towers, and which are considerable enough to disfi∣gure
the view of the city itself, destroy the result of so superb a
frontispiece.
<PB N="106" REF="135" MS="y"/>
<Q>THOMAS RIPLEY</Q>
was born in Yorkshire, and executed such considerable works that
he must not be omitted, though he wanted taste and fell under the
lash of lasting satire. Pope has twice mentioned him,
<Q><L>Who builds a bridge, that never drove a pile?</L>
<L>Should Ripley venture, all the world would smile.</L></Q>
And again,
<Q>And needs no rod but Ripley with a rule.</Q>
The truth is, politics and partiality concurred to help on these cen∣sures.
Ripley was employed by the minister, and had not the coun∣tenance
of lord Burlington, the patron of Pope. It is no less true,
that the admiralty is a most ugly edifice, and deservedly veiled by
Mr. Adam's handsome screen. Yet Ripley, in the mechanic part,
and in the disposition of apartments and conveniencies, was unluckily
superior to the earl himself. Lord Orford's at Houghton, of which
Campbell gave the original design, but which was much improved
by Ripley, and lord Walpole's at Woolterton, one of the best
houses of the size in England, will, as long as they remain, acquit
this artist of the charge of ignorance. I must mention a more barba∣rous
architect before I come to the luminaries of the science. This
was
<Q>BATTY LANGLEY,</Q>
who endeavoured to adapt Gothic architecture to Roman measures;
as sir Philip Sidney attempted to regulate English verse by Roman
<PB REF="136"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>HENRY HERBERT EARL OF PEMBROKE</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="107" REF="137"/>
feet. Langley went farther, and [for he never copied Gothic] <HI>in∣vented</HI>
five orders for that style. All that his books atchieved, has
been to teach carpenters to massacre that venerable species, and to
give occasion to those who know nothing of the matter, and who
mistake his clumsy efforts for real imitations, to censure the pro∣ductions
of our ancestors, whose bold and beautiful fabrics sir Chris∣topher
Wren viewed and reviewed with astonishment, and never
mentioned without esteem. Batty Langley published some other
works, particularly an useful one on the prices of work and mate∣rials
for building. He also invented an artificial stone, of which he
made figures. An art lately brought to great perfection.</P>
<DIV3>
<HEAD>HENRY HERBERT Earl of PEMBROKE.</HEAD>
<P>The soul of Inigo Jones, who had been patronized by his ancestors,
seemed still to hover over its favourite Wilton, and to have assisted
the muses of arts in the education of this noble person. The towers,
the chambers, the scenes which Holbein, Jones and Vandyck had
decorated, and which earl Thomas had enriched with the spoils of the
best ages, received the last touches of beauty from earl Henry's
hand. He removed all that obstructed the views to or from his pa∣lace,
and threw Palladio's theatric bridge over his river: the present
lord has crowned the summit of the hill with the equestrian statue of
Marcus Aurelius, and a handsome arch designed by Mr. Chambers.</P>
<P>No man had a purer taste in building than earl Henry, of which
he gave a few specimens, besides his works at Wilton. The new
lodge in Richmond-park, the countess of Suffolk's house at Marble-hill,
<PB N="108" REF="138"/>
Twickenham, the water-house in lord Orford's park at Hough∣ton,
are incontestable proofs of lord Pembroke's taste. It was more
than taste, it was passion for the utility and honour of his country
that engaged his lordship to promote and assiduously overlook the
construction of Westminster-bridge by the ingenious<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Charles Labelye died at Paris in the beginning of 1762. I know no par∣ticulars of his life: a monument he cannot want while the bridge exists.</NOTE> monsieur
Labelye, a man that deserves more notice than this slight encomium
can bestow.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3>
<HEAD>RICHARD BOYLE Earl of BURLINGTON.</HEAD>
<P>Never was protection and great wealth more generously and more
judiciously diffused than by this great person, who had every quality
of a genius and artist, except envy. Though his own designs were
more chaste and classic than Kent's, he entertained him in his house
till his death, and was more studious to extend his friend's fame
than his own. In these sheets I have mentioned many other instances
of the painters and artists he encouraged and rewarded. Nor was
his munificence confined to himself and his own houses and gardens.
He spent great sums in contributing to public works, and was known
to chuse that the expence should fall on himself, rather than that his
country should be deprived of some beautiful edifices. His enthu∣siasm
for the works of Inigo Jones was so active, that he repaired
the church of Covent-garden because it was the production of that
great master, and purchased a gateway at Beaufort-garden in Chelsea,
and transported the identical stones to Chiswick with religious attach∣ment.
<PB REF="139"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>RICHARD BOYLE EARL of BURLINGTON</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="109" REF="140"/>
With the same zeal for pure architecture he assisted Kent in
publishing the designs for Whitehall, and gave a beautiful edition of
the antique baths from the drawings of Palladio, whose papers he
procured with great cost. Besides his works on his own estate at
Lonsborough in Yorkshire, he new fronted his house in Piccadilly,
built by his<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">That lord Burlington being asked why he built his house so far out of town, replied, because he was determined to have no building beyond him. Little more than half a century has so inclosed Burlington-house with new streets, that it is now in the heart of that part of London.</NOTE> father, and added the grand colonade within the court.
As we have few samples of architecture more antique and imposing
than that colonade, I cannot help mentioning the effect it had on
myself. I had not only never seen it, but had never heard of it, at
least with any attention, when soon after my return from Italy, I
was invited to a ball at Burlington-house. As I passed under the
gate by night, it could not strike me. At day-break looking out of
the window to see the sun rise, I was surprised with the vision of the
<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">Campbell, in his Vitruvius Britannicus, assumes to himself the new front of Burlington-house and the gateway, but as he takes no credit for the colon∣ade, which is in a style very superior to his designs, we may safely conclude it was the earl's own.</NOTE> colonade that fronted me. It seemed one of those edifices in fairy∣tales
that are raised by genii in a night's time.</P>
<P>His lordship's house at Chiswick, the idea of which is borrowed
from a well-known villa of Palladio, is a model of taste, though not
without faults, some of which are occasioned by too strict adherence
to rules and symmetry. Such are too many correspondent doors in
<PB N="110" REF="141"/>
spaces so contracted; chimnies between windows, and which is
worse, windows between chimnies; and vestibules, however beauti∣ful,
yet too little secured from the damps of this climate. The
trusses that support the cieling of the corner drawing-room are be∣yond
measure massive, and the ground apartment is rather a diminu∣tive
catacomb, than a library in a northern latitude. Yet these
blemishes, and lord Hervey's wit, who said <HI>the house was too small
to inhabit, and too large to hang to one's watch,</HI> cannot depreciate the
taste that reigns in the whole. The larger court, dignified by pic∣turesque
cedars, and the classic scenery of the small court that unites
the old and new house, are more worth seeing than many fragments
of ancient grandeur, which our travellers visit under all the dangers
attendant on long voyages. The garden is in the Italian taste, but
divested of conceits, and far preferable to every style that reigned
till our late improvements. The buildings are heavy and not equal
to the purity of the house. The lavish quantity of urns and sculp∣ture
behind the garden-front should be retrenched.</P>
<P>Other works designed by lord Burlington, were, the dormitory at
Westminster-school, the assembly-room at York, lord Harrington's<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The octagon buildings at each end were afterwards added by Sheperd.</NOTE> at Petersham, the duke of Richmond's house at Whitehall, and ge∣neral
Wade's in Cork-street. Both the latter were ill-contrived and
inconvenient, but the latter has so beautiful a front, that lord Ches∣terfield
said, <HI>as the general could not live in it to his ease, he had better
take a house over against it and look at it.</HI> These are meer details re∣lating
<PB REF="142"/>
<FIGURE>
<P>WILLIAM KENT.</P>
</FIGURE>
<PB N="111" REF="143"/>
to this illustrious person's works.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Lord Burlington being consulted by the citizens for a proper person to carve the bas-relief in the pediment of the Mansion-house, his lordship replied, any body could do well enough for such a building.</NOTE> His genuine praise is bet∣ter
secured in Mr. Pope's epistle to him.</P>
<P>I ought not to omit that his countess, lady Dorothy Tufton, had
no less attachment to the arts than her lord. She drew in crayons,
and succeeded admirably in likenesses, but working with too much
rapidity, did not do justice to her genius. She had an uncommon
talent too for caricatura.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3>
<HEAD>WILLIAM KENT.</HEAD>
<P>Under the auspices of lord Burlington and lord Pembroke, archi∣tecture,
as I have said, recovered its genuine lustre. The former,
the Apollo of arts, found a proper priest in the person of Mr. Kent.
As I mean no panegyric on any man, beyond what he deserved, or
what to the best of my possibly erroneous judgment, I think he de∣served,
I shall speak with equal impartiality on the merits and faults
of Kent, the former of which exceedingly preponderated. He was
a painter, an architect, and the father of modern gardening. In the
first character, he was below mediocrity; in the second, he was a
restorer of the science; in the last, an original, and the inventor of
an art that realizes painting, and improves nature. Mahomet ima∣gined
an Elysium, but Kent created many.</P>
<P>He was born in Yorkshire, and put apprentice to a coach-painter,
but feeling the emotions of genius he left his master without leave,
and repaired to London; where he studied a little, and gave indica∣tions
<PB N="112" REF="144"/>
enough of abilities to excite a generous patronage in some gen∣tlemen
of his own county, who raised a contribution sufficient to
send him to Rome, whither he accompanied Mr. Talman in 1710.
In that capital of the arts he studied under cavalier Luti, and in the
academy gained the second prize of the second class; still without
suspecting that there was a sister art within his reach, more congenial
to his talents. Though his first resources were exhausted, he still
found friends. Another of his countrymen, sir John Wentworth,
allowed him <HI>40l.</HI> a year for seven years. But it was at Rome that
his better star brought him acquainted with lord Burlington, whose
sagacity discovered the rich vein of genius that had been hid from
the artist himself. On their return to England in 1719, lord Bur∣lington
gave him an apartment in his own house, and added all the
graces of favour and recommendation. By that noble person's in∣terest
Kent was employed in various works, both as a painter of history
and portrait; and yet it must be allowed that in each branch par∣tiality
must have operated strongly to make his lordship believe he
discovered any merit in his friend. His portraits bore little resem∣blance
to the persons that sat for them; and the colouring was worse,
more raw and undetermined than that of the most errant journeymen
to the profession. The whole lengths at Esher are standing evidences
of this assertion. In his cielings, Kent's drawing was as defective as
the colouring of his portraits, and as void of every merit. I have
mentioned Hogarth's parody, if I may call it so, of his picture at
St. Clement's. The hall at Wanstead is another proof of his inca∣pacity.
Sir Robert Walpole, who was persuaded to employ him at
Houghton, where he painted several cielings and the staircase, would
not permit him however to work in colours, which would have been
<PB N="113" REF="145"/>
still more disgraced by the presence of so many capital pictures, but
restrained him to chiaro scuro. If his faults are thence not so glar∣ing,
they are scarce less numerous. He painted a staircase in the
same way for lord Townshend at Rainham.</P>
<P>To compensate for his bad paintings, he had an excellent taste for
ornaments, and gave designs for most of the furniture at Houghton,
as he did for several other persons. Yet chaste as these ornaments
were, they were often unmeasurably ponderous. His chimney∣pieces,
though lighter than those of Inigo, whom he imitated, are
frequently heavy; and his constant introduction of pediments and
the members of architecture over doors, and within rooms, was dis∣proportioned
and cumbrous. Indeed I much question whether the
Romans admitted regular architecture <HI>within</HI> their houses. At least
the discoveries at Herculaneum testify, that a light and fantastic ar∣chitecture,
of a very Indian air, made a common decoration of pri∣vate
apartments. Kent's style however predominated authoritatively
during his life; and his oracle was so much consulted by all who
affected taste, that nothing was thought compleat without his assist∣ance.
He was not only consulted for furniture, as frames of pic∣tures,
glasses, tables, chairs, &amp;c. but for plate, for a barge, for
a cradle. And so impetuous was fashion, that two great ladies
prevailed on him to make designs for their birth-day gowns. The
one he dressed in a petticoat decorated with columns of the five
orders; the other like a bronze, in a copper-coloured sattin with
ornaments of gold. He was not more happy in other works in which
he misapplied his genius. The gilt rails to the hermitage at Rich∣mond,
were in truth but a trifling impropriety; but his celebrated
monument of Shakespeare in the abbey was preposterous. What an
<PB N="114" REF="146"/>
absurdity to place busts at the angles of a pedestal, and at the bot∣tom
of that pedestal! Whose choice the busts were I do not know,
but though queen Elizabeth's head might be intended to mark the
aera in which the poet flourished, why were Richard II. and Henry V.
selected? Are the pieces under the names of those princes two of
Shakespeare's most capital works? or what reason can be assigned
for giving them the preference?</P>
<P>As Kent's genius was not universal, he has succeeded as ill in
Gothic. The King's-bench at Westminster, and Mr. Pelham's house
at Esher, are proofs how little he conceived either the princples or
graces of that architecture. Yet he was sometimes sensible of its
beauties, and published a print of Wolsey's noble hall at Hampton∣court,
now crouded and half hidden by a theatre. Kent gave the
design for the ornaments of the chapel at the prince of Orange's wed∣ding,
of which he also made a print.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">His vignettes to the large edition of Pope's works are in a good taste.</NOTE></P>
<P>Such of the drawings as he designed for Gay's Fables, have some
truth and nature; but whoever would search for his faults, will find
an ample crop in a very favourite work of his, the prints for Spen∣cer's
Fairy Queen. As the drawings were exceedingly cried up by
his admirers, and disappointed the public in proportion, the blame
was thrown on the engraver, but so far unjustly, that though ill ex∣ecuted,
the wretchedness of drawing, the total ignorance of per∣spective,
the want of variety, the disproportion of the buildings,
and the awkwardness of the attitudes, could have been the faults of
the inventor only. There are figures issuing from cottages not so
high as their shoulders, castles in which the towers could not contain
<PB N="115" REF="147"/>
an infant, and knights who hold their spears as men do who are
lifting a load sideways. The landscapes are the only tolerable parts,
and yet the trees are seldom other than young beeches to which Kent
as a planter was accustomed.</P>
<P>But in architecture his taste was deservedly admired; and without
enumerating particulars, the staircase at lady Isabella Finch's in
Berkeley-square is as beautiful a piece of scenery, and considering
the space, of art, as can be imagined. The temple of Venus at
Stowe has simplicity and merit, and the great room at Mr. Pelham's
in Arlington-street, is as remarkable for magnificence. I do not
admire equally the room ornamented with marble and gilding at
Kensington. The staircase there is the least defective work of his
pencil; and his cielings in that palace from antique paintings, which
he first happily introduced, show that he was not too ridiculously
prejudiced in favour of his own historic compositions.</P>
<P>Of all his works, his favourite production was the earl of Leices∣ter's
house at Holkam in Norfolk. The great hall, with the flight
of steps at the upper end, in which he proposed to place a colossal
Jupiter, was a noble idea. How the designs of that house, which I
have seen an hundred times in Kent's original drawings, came to be
published under another name, and without the slightest mention of
the real architect, is beyond comprehension. The bridge, the tem∣ple,
the great gateway, all built, I believe, the two first certainly,
under Kent's own eye, are alike passed off as the works of another;
and yet no man need envy or deny him the glory of having oppressed
a triumphal arch with an Egyptian pyramid. Holkam has its faults,
but they are Kent's faults, and marked with all the peculiarities of
his style.</P>
<P><PB N="116" REF="148"/>
As I intend to consider him as the inventor of modern gardening
in a chapter by itself, I will conclude this account of him with the
few remaining circumstances of his life. By the patronage of the
queen, of the dukes of Grafton and Newcastle, and Mr. Pelham,
and by the interest of his constant friend, he was made master car∣penter,
architect, keeper of the pictures, and, after the death of
Jervas, principal painter to the crown; the whole, including a pen∣sion
of <HI>100l.</HI> a year which was given him for his works at Kensing∣ton,
producing <HI>600l.</HI> a year. In 1743 he had a disorder in his eyes
that was thought paralytic, but recovered. But in March 1748 he
had an inflammation both in his bowels and foot, which turned to a
general mortification, and put an end to his life at Burlington-house,
April 12, 1748, in the sixty-fourth year of his age. He was buried
in a very handsome manner in lord Burlington's vault at Chiswick.
His fortune, which with pictures and books, amounted to about ten
thousand pounds, he divided between his relations, and an actress
with whom he had long lived in particular friendship.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Henry Flitcroft was an artist much employed about this period. He built the church of St. Giles in the fields, the steeple of which too much resembled that of St. Martin. His too was the church of St. Olave, Southwark, reckoned the best of the new erections, but the tower was not finished from the deficience of the allotted-fund. Flitcroft is buried in the church-yard at Teddington, and against the church is a small tablet with a Latin inscription, which may be read from the road.</NOTE></P>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="149"/>
<HEAD>ANECDOTES of PAINTING, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VII.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">On modern Gardening.</HEAD>
<P>GARDENING was probably one of the first arts that succeeded
to that of building houses, and naturally attended property and
individual possession. Culinary, and afterwards medicinal herbs,
were the objects of every head of a family: it became convenient to
have them within reach, without seeking them at random in woods,
in meadows, and on mountains, as often as they were wanted.
When the earth ceased to furnish spontaneously all these primitive
luxuries, and culture became requisite, separate inclosures for rear∣ing
herbs grew expedient. Fruits were in the same predicament,
and those most in use or that demand attention, must have entered
into and extended the domestic inclosure. The good man Noah, we
are told, planted a vineyard, drank of the wine, and was drunken,
and every body knows the consequences. Thus we acquired kitchen-gardens,
orchards, and vineyards. I am apprized that the proto∣type
of all these sorts was the garden of Eden, but as that Paradise
was a good deal larger than any we read of afterwards, being in∣closed
by the rivers Pison, Gihon, Hiddekel, and Euphrates, as
<PB N="118" REF="150"/>
every tree that was pleasant to the sight and good for food grew in it,
and as two other trees were likewise found there, of which not a slip
or sucker remains, it does not belong to the present discussion. After
the fall no man living was suffered to enter into the garden; and the
poverty and necessities of our first ancestors, hardly allowed them time
<HI>to make improvements on their estates</HI> in imitation of it, supposing any
plan had been preserved. A cottage and a slip of ground for a cab∣bage
and a gooseberry-bush, such as we see by the side of a common,
were in all probability the earliest seats and gardens: a well and
bucket succeeded to the Pison and Euphrates. As settlements in∣creased,
the orchard and the vineyard followed; and the earliest
princes of tribes possessed just the necessaries of a modern farmer.</P>
<P>Matters, we may well believe, remained long in this situation;
and though the generality of mankind from their ideas from the im∣port
of words in their own age, we have no reason to think that for
many centuries the term <HI>garden</HI> implied more than a kitchen-garden
or orchard. When a Frenchman reads of the garden of Eden, I do
not doubt but he concludes it was something approaching to that of
Versailles, with clipt hedges, berceaus, and trellis-work. If his de∣votion
humbles him so far as to allow that, considering who designed
it, there might be a labyrinth full of Aesop's fables, yet he does not
conceive that four of the largest rivers in the world were half so
magnificent as an hundred fountains full of statues by Girardon. It
is thus that the word <HI>garden</HI> has at all times passed for whatever was
understood by that term in different countries. But that it meant no
more than a kitchen-garden or orchard for several centuries, is evi∣dent
from those few descriptions that are preserved of the most fa∣mous
gardens of antiquity.</P>
<P><PB N="119" REF="151"/>
That of Alcinous, in the Odyssey, is the most renowned in the
heroic times. Is there an admirer of Homer who can read his de∣scription
without rapture; or who does not form to his imagination
a scene of delights more picturesque than the landscapes of Tinian or
Juan Fernandez? Yet what was that boasted Paradise with which
the gods ordain'd
<Q>To grace Alcinous and his happy land? POPE.</Q>
Why, divested of harmonious Greek and bewitching poetry, it was
a small orchard and vineyard, with some beds of herbs and two
fountains that watered them, inclosed within a quickset hedge. The
whole compass of this pompous garden inclosed—four acres.
<Q><L>Four acres was th' allotted space of ground,</L>
<L>Fenc'd with a green inclosure all around.</L>
<L>The trees were apples, figs, pomgranates, pears, olives, and vines.</L>
<L>Tall thriving trees confess'd the fruitful mold;</L>
<L>The redning apple ripens into gold.</L>
<L>Here the blue fig with luscious juice o'erflows,</L>
<L>With deeper red the full pomegranate glows.</L>
<L>The branch here bends beneath the weighty pear,</L>
<L>And verdant olives flourish round the year.</L>
<L>Beds of all various herbs, for ever green,</L>
<L>In beauteous order terminate the scene.</L></Q></P>
<P>Alcinous's garden was planted by the poet, enriched by him with the
fairy gift of eternal summer, and no doubt an effort of imagination
surpassing any thing he had ever seen. As he has bestowed on the
same happy prince a palace with brazen walls and columns of silver,
<PB N="120" REF="152"/>
he certainly intended that the garden should be proportionably mag∣nificent.
We are sure therefore that as late as Homer's age, an in∣closure
of four acres, comprehending orchard, vineyard and kitchen-garden,
was a stretch of luxury the world at that time had never
beheld.</P>
<P>The hanging gardens of Babylon were a still greater prodigy. We
are not acquainted with their disposition or contents, but as they are
supposed to have been formed on terrasses and the walls of the palace,
whither soil was conveyed on purpose, we are very certain of what
they were not; I mean they must have been trifling, of no extent,
and a wanton instance of expence and labour. In other words, they
were what sumptuous gardens have been in all ages till the present,
unnatural, enriched by art, possibly with fountains, statues, balus∣trades,
and summer-houses, and were any thing but verdant and
rural.</P>
<P>From the days of Homer to those of Pliny, we have no traces to
lead our guess to what were the gardens of the intervening ages.
When Roman authors, whose climate instilled a wish for cool retreats,
speak of their enjoyments in that kind, they sigh for grottos, caves,
and the refreshing hollows of mountains, near irriguous and shady
founts; or boast of their porticos, walks of planes, canals, baths and
breezes from the sea. Their gardens are never mentioned as afford∣ing
shade and shelter from the rage of the dog-star. Pliny has
left us descriptions of two of his villas. As he used his Laurentine
villa for his winter-retreat, it is not surprising that the garden makes
no considerable part of the account. All he says of it is, that
the gestatio or place of exercise, which surrounded the garden (the
<PB N="121" REF="153"/>
latter consequently not being very large) was bounded by a hedge of
box, and where that was perished, with rosemary; that there was a
walk of vines, and that most of the trees were fig and mulberry, the
soil not being proper for any other sorts.</P>
<P>On his Tuscan villa he is more diffuse, the garden makes a con∣siderable
part of the description—and what was the principal beauty
of that pleasure-ground? Exactly what was the admiration of this
country about threescore years ago; box-trees cut into monsters,
animals, letters, and the names of the master and the artificer. In
an age when architecture displayed all its grandeur, all its purity,
and all its taste; when arose Vespasian's amphitheatre, the temple of
Peace, Trajan's forum, Domitian's baths, and Adrian's villa, the
ruins and vestiges of which still excite our astonishment and curiosity;
a Roman consul, a polished emperor's friend, and a man of elegant
litterature and taste, delighted in what the mob now scarce admire
in a college-garden. All the ingredients of Pliny's corresponded ex∣actly
with those laid out by London and Wise on Dutch principles.
He talks of slopes, terrasses, a wilderness, shrubs methodically trim∣med,
a marble bason,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The English gardens described by Hentzner in the reign of Elizabeth, are exact copies of those of Pliny. In that at Whitehall was a sun-dial and jet-d'eau, which on turning a cock spurted out water and sprinkled the spectators. In lord Burleigh's at Theobalds were obelisks, pyramids, and circular porticos, with cisterns of lead for bathing. At Hampton-court the garden walls were covered with rosemary, a custom, he says, very common in England. At Theobald's was a labyrinth also, an ingenuity I shall mention presently to have been frequent in that age.</NOTE> pipes spouting water, a cascade falling into
<PB N="122" REF="154"/>
the bason, bay-trees, alternately planted with planes, and a strait
walk, from whence issued others parted off by hedges of box, and
apple-trees, with obelisks placed between every two. There wants
nothing but the embroidery of a parterre, to make a garden in the
reign of Trajan serve for a description of one in that of king Wil∣liam.
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Dr. Plot, in his natural history of Oxfordshire, p. 380, seems to have been a great admirer of trees carved into the most heterogeneous forms, which he calls <HI>topiary works,</HI> and quotes one Laurembergius for saying that the English are as expert as most nations in that kind of sculpture; for which Hampton-court was particularly remarkable. The doctor then names other gardens that flourished with animals, and castles, formed arte topiariâ, and above all a wren's nest that was capacious enough to receive a man to sit on a seat made within it for that purpose.</NOTE> In one passage above Pliny seems to have conceived that na∣tural
irregularity might be a beauty; in opere urbanissimo, says he,
subita velut illati ruris imitatio. Something like a rural view was
contrived amidst so much polished composition. But the idea soon
vanished, lineal walks immediately enveloped the slight scene, and
names and inscriptions in box again succeeded to compensate for the
daring introduction of nature.</P>
<P>In the paintings found at Herculaneum are a few traces of gar∣dens,
as may be seen in the second volume of the prints. They are
small square inclosures formed by trellis-work, and espaliers,<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">At Warwick-castle is an ancient suit of arras, in which there is a garden exactly resembling these pictures of Herculaneum.</NOTE> and
regularly ornamented with vases, fountains and careatides, elegantly
symmetrical, and proper for the narrow spaces allotted to the garden
of a house in a capital city. From such I would not banish those
<PB N="123" REF="155"/>
playful waters that refresh a sultry mansion in town, nor the neat
trellis, which preserves it wooden verdure better than natural greens
exposed to dust. Those treillages in the gardens at Paris, particu∣larly
on the Boulevard, have a gay and delightful effect.—They
form light corridores, and transpicuous arbours through which the
sunbeams play and chequer the shade, set off the statues, vases and
flowers, that marry with their gaudy hotels, and suit the galant and
idle society who paint the walks between their parterres, and realize
the fantastic scenes of Watteau and Durfè.</P>
<P>From what I have said, it appears how naturally and insensibly the
idea of a kitchen-garden slid into that which has for so many ages
been peculiarly termed a garden, and by our ancestors in this coun∣try,
distinguished by the name of a pleasure-garden. A square piece
of ground was originally parted off in early ages for the use of the
family—to exclude cattle and ascertain the property it was separated
from the fields by a hedge. As pride and desire of privacy increased,
the inclosure was dignified by walls; and in climes where fruits were
not lavished by the ripening glow of nature and soil, fruit-trees were
assisted and sheltered from surrounding winds by the like expedient;
for the inundation of luxuries which have swelled into general neces∣sities,
have almost all taken their source from the simple fountain
of reason.</P>
<P>When the custom of making square gardens inclosed with walls
was thus established, to the exclusion of nature and<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">It was not uncommon, after the circumadjacent country had been shut out, to endeavour to recover it by raising large mounts of earth to peep over the walls of the garden.</NOTE> prospect,
<PB N="124" REF="156"/>
pomp and solitude combined to call for something that might enrich
and enliven the insipid and unanimated partition. Fountains, first
invented for use, which grandeur loves to disguise and throw out of
the question, received embellishments from costly marbles, and at
last to contradict utility, tossed their waste of waters into air in spout∣ing
columns. Art, in the hands of rude man, had at first been
made a succedaneum to nature; in the hands of ostentatious wealth,
it became the means of opposing nature; and the more it traversed
the march of the latter, the more nobility thought its power was de∣monstrated.
Canals measured by the line were introduced in lieu of
maeandring streams, and terrasses were hoisted aloft in opposition to
the facile slopes that imperceptibly unite the valley to the hill. Ba∣lustrades
defended these precipitate and dangerous elevations, and
flights of steps rejoined them to the subjacent flat from which the
terrass had been dug. Vases and sculpture were added to these un∣necessary
balconies, and statues furnished the lifeless spot with mimic
representations of the excluded sons of men. Thus difficulty and
expence were the constituent parts of those sumptuous and selfish
solitudes; and every improvement that was made, was but a step
farther from nature. The tricks of water-works to wet the unwary,
not to refresh the panting spectator, and parterres embroidered in
patterns like a petticoat, were but the childish endeavours of fashion
and novelty to reconcile greatness to what it had surfeited on. To
crown these impotent displays of false taste, the sheers were applied
to the lovely wildness of form with which nature has distinguished
each various species of tree and shrub. The venerable oak, the ro∣mantic
beech, the useful elm, even the aspiring circuit of the lime,
<PB N="125" REF="157"/>
the regular round of the chesnut, and the almost moulded orange-tree,
were corrected by such fantastic admirers of symmetry. The
compass and square were of more use in plantations than the nursery∣man.
The measured walk, the quincunx, and the etoile imposed
their unsatisfying sameness on every royal and noble garden. Trees
were headed, and their sides pared away; many French groves seem
green chests set upon poles. Seats of marble, arbours and summer-houses,
terminated every visto; and symmetry, even where the space
was too large to permit its being remarked at one view, was so es∣sential,
that, as Pope observed,
<Q><L>—each alley has a brother,</L>
<L>And half the garden just reflects the other.</L></Q>
Knots of flowers were more defensibly subjected to the same regu∣larity.
Leisure, as Milton expressed it,
in trim gardens took his pleasure.
In the garden of marshal de Biron at Paris, consisting of fourteen
acres, every walk is buttoned on each side by lines of flower-pots,
which succeed in their seasons. When I saw it, there were nine
thousand pots of Asters, or la Reine Marguerite.</P>
<P>We do not precisely know what our ancestors meant by a bower,
it was probably an arbour; sometimes it meant the whole frittered
inclosure, and in one instance it certainly included a labyrinth.
Rosamond's bower was indisputably of that kind, though whether
composed of walls or hedges we cannot determine. A square and a
round labyrinth were so capital ingredients of a garden formerly, that
in Du Cerceau's architecture, who lived in the time of Charles IX.
and Henry III. there is scarce a ground-plot without one of each.
<PB N="126" REF="158"/>
The enchantment of antique appellations has consecrated a pleasing
idea of a royal residence, of which we now regret the extinction.
Havering in the Bower, the jointure of many dowager queens, con∣veys
to us the notion of a romantic scene.</P>
<P>In Kip's views of the seats of our nobility and gentry, we see the
same tiresome and returning uniformity. Every house is approached
by two or three gardens, consisting perhaps of a gravel-walk and
two grass-plats, or borders of flowers. Each rises above the other
by two or three steps, and as many walls and terrasses; and so many
iron-gates, that we recollect those ancient romances, in which every
entrance was guarded by nymphs or dragons. At lady Orford's at
Piddletown in Dorfetshire, there was, when my brother married, a
double inclosure of thirteen gardens, each I suppose not an hundred
feet square, with an enfilade of correspondent gates; and before you
arrived at these, you passed a narrow gut between two stone terrasses,
that rose above your head, and which were crowned by a line of
pyramidal yews. A bowling-green was all the lawn admitted in
those times, a circular lake the extent of magnificence.</P>
<P>Yet though these and such preposterous inconveniencies prevailed
from age to age, good sense in this country had perceived the want
of something at once more grand and more natural. These reflect∣ions
and the bounds set to the waste made by royal spoilers, gave
origine to parks. They were contracted forests, and extended gar∣dens.
Hentzner says, that according to Rous of Warwick the first
park was that at Woodstock. If so, it might be the foundation of
a legend that Henry II. secured his mistress in a labyrinth: it was no
doubt more difficult to find her in a park than in a palace, when the
<PB N="127" REF="159"/>
intricacy of the woods and various lodges buried in covert might
conceal her actual habitation.</P>
<P>It is more extraordinary that having so along ago stumbled on the
principle of modern gardening, we should have persisted in retaining
its reverse, symmetrical and unnatural gardens. That parks were
rare in other countries, Hentzner, who travelled over great part of
Europe, leads us to suppose, by observing that they were common
in England. In France they retain the name, but nothing is more
different both in compass and disposition. Their parks are usually
square or oblong inclosures, regularly planted with walks of chesnuts
or limes, and generally every large town has one for its public recre∣ation.
They are exactly like Burton's court at Chelsea-college, and
rarely larger.</P>
<P>One man, one great man we had, on whom nor education nor
custom could impose their prejudices; who, <HI>on evil days though fallen,
and with darkness and solitude compassed round,</HI> judged that the mis∣taken
and fantastic ornaments he had seen in gardens, were unworthy
of the almighty hand that planted the delights of Paradise. He seems
with the prophetic eye of taste [as I have heard taste well defined]
to have conceived, to have foreseen modern gardening; as lord Ba∣con
announced the discoveries since made by experimental philoso∣phy.
The description of Eden is a warmer and more just picture of
the present style than Claud Lorrain could have painted from Hag∣ley
or Stourhead. The first lines I shall quote, exhibit Stourhead on
a more magnificent scale.
<Q><L>Thro' Eden went a river large,</L>
<L>Nor chang'd his course, but thro' the shaggy hill</L>
<L><PB N="128" REF="160"/>
Pass'd underneath ingulph'd, for God had thrown</L>
<L>That mountain as his garden-mound, high rais'd</L>
<L>Upon the rapid current—</L>
<L>Hagley seems pictured in what follows,
which thro' veins</L>
<L>Of porous earth with kindly thirst updrawn,</L>
<L>Rose a fresh fountain, and with many a rill</L>
<L>Water'd the garden—</L>
<L>What colouring, what freedom of pencil, what landscape in these
lines,</L>
<L>—from that saphire fount the crisped brooks,</L>
<L>Rolling on orient pearl and sands of gold,</L>
<L>With mazy error under pendent shades</L>
<L>Ran nectar, visiting each plant, and fed</L>
<L>Flow'rs worthy of Paradise, which not <HI>nice art</HI></L>
<L>In beds and curious knots, but <HI>nature</HI> boon</L>
<L>Pour'd forth profuse on hill and dale and plain,</L>
<L>Both where the morning sun first warmly smote</L>
<L>The <HI>open field,</HI> and where the unpierc'd shade</L>
<L>Imbrown'd the noon-tide bow'rs.—<HI>Thus was this place</HI></L>
<L>A happy rural seat of various view.</L></Q></P>
<P>Read this transporting description, paint to your mind the scenes
that follow, contrast them with the savage but respectable terror
with which the poet guards the bounds of his Paradise, fenced
<Q><L>—with the champain head</L>
<L>Of a steep wilderness, whose hairy sides</L>
<L>With thicket overgrown, grotesque and wild</L>
<L><PB N="129" REF="161"/>
Access denied; and over head upgrew</L>
<L>Insuperable height of loftiest shade,</L>
<L>Cedar and pine, and fir, and branching palm,</L>
<L>A sylvan scene, and as the ranks ascend,</L>
<L>Shade above shade, a woody theatre</L>
<L>Of stateliest view—</L></Q>
and then recollect that the author of this sublime vision had never
seen a glimpse of any thing like what he has imagined, that his fa∣vourite
ancients had dropped not a hint of such divine scenery, and
that the conceits in Italian gardens, and Theobalds and Nonsuch,
were the brightest originals that his memory could furnish. His in∣tellectual
eye saw a nobler plan, so little did he suffer by the loss of
sight. It sufficed him to have seen the materials with which he could
work. The vigour of a boundless imagination told him how a plan
might be disposed, that would embellish nature, and restore art to
its proper office, the just improvement or imitation of it.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Since the above was written, I have found Milton praised and sir William Temple censured, on the same foundations, in a poem called, The Rise and Progress of the present Taste in Planting, printed in in 1767.</NOTE></P>
<P>It is necessary that the concurrent testimony of the age should swear
to posterity that the description above-quoted was written above half
a century before the introduction of modern gardening, or our in∣credulous
descendents will defraud the poet of half his glory, by
being persuaded that he copied some garden or gardens he had seen—so
minutely do his ideas correspond with the present standard. But
what shall we say for that intervening half century who could read
that plan and never attempt to put it in execution?</P>
<P><PB N="130" REF="162"/>
Now let us turn to an admired writer, posterior to Milton, and see
how cold, how insipid, how tasteless is his account of what he pro∣nounced
a perfect garden. I speak not of his style, which it was
not necessary for him to animate with the colouring and glow of
poetry. It is his want of ideas, of imagination, of taste, that I
censure, when he dictated on a subject that is capable of all the
graces that a knowledge of beautiful nature can bestow. Sir Wil∣liam
Temple was an excellent man; Milton, a genius of the first
order.</P>
<P>We cannot wonder that sir William declares in favour of parterres,
fountains and statues, as necessary to break the sameness of large
grass-plats, which he thinks have an ill effect upon the eye, when he
acknowledges that he discovers fancy in the gardens of Alcinous.
Milton studied the ancients with equal enthusiasm, but no bigotry,
and had judgment to distinguish between the want of invention and
the beauties of poetry. Compare his Paradise with Homer's garden,
both ascribed to a celestial design. For sir William, it is just to ob∣serve,
that his ideas centured in a fruit-garden. He had the honour
of giving to his country many delicate fruits, and he thought of
little else than disposing them to the best advantage. Here is the
passage I proposed to quote; it is long, but I need not make an
apology to the reader for entertaining him with any other words in∣stead
of my own.</P>
<P>“The best figure of a garden is either a square or an oblong,” and
either upon a flat or a descent: they have all their beauties, but the
best I esteem an oblong upon a descent. The beauty, the air, the
view makes amends for the expence, which is very great in finishing
<PB N="131" REF="163"/>
and supporting the terras-walks, in levelling the parterres, and in
the stone-stairs that are necessary from one to the other.</P>
<P>“The perfectest figure of a garden I ever saw, either at home or
abroad, was that of Moor-park in Hertfordshire, when I knew it
about thirty years ago. It was made by the countess of Bedford,
esteemed among the greatest wits of her time, and celebrated by
doctor Donne; and with very great care, excellent contrivance and
much cost; but greater sums may be thrown away without effect or
honour, if there want sense in proportion to money, or <HI>if nature be
not followed,</HI> which I take to be the great rule in this, and perhaps
in every thing else, as far as the conduct not only of our lives, but
our governments.” [We shall see how <HI>natural</HI> that admired garden
was.]</P>
<P>“Because I take<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">This garden seems to have been made after the plan laid down by lord Ba∣con in his 46th essay, to which, that I may not multiply quotations, I will re∣fer the reader.</NOTE> the garden I have named to have been in all
kinds the most beautiful and perfect,” at least in the figure and dis∣position
that I have ever seen, I will describe it for a model to those
that meet with such a situation, and are above the regards of com∣mon
expence. It lies on the side of a hill, upon which the house
stands, but not very steep. The length of the house, where the best
rooms and of most use or pleasure are, lies upon the breadth of the
garden; the great parlour opens into the middle of a terras gravel-walk
that lies even with it, and which may lie, as I remember, about
three hundred paces long, and broad in proportion; the border set
with standard laurels and at large distances, which have the beauty
<PB N="132" REF="164"/>
of orange-trees out of flower and fruit. From this walk are three
descents by many stone steps, in the middle and at each end, into a
very large parterre. This is divided into quarters by gravel-walks,
and adorned with two fountains and eight statues in the several quar∣ters.
At the end of the terras-walk are two summer-houses, and the
sides of the parterre are ranged with two large cloisters open to the
garden, upon arches of stone, and ending with two other summer-houses
even with the cloisters, which are paved with stone, and design∣ed
for walks of shade, there being none other in the whole parterre.
Over these two cloisters are two terrasses covered with lead and fenced
with balusters; and the passage into these airy walks is out of the two
summer-houses at the end of the first terras-walk. The cloister facing
the south is covered with vines, and would have been proper for an
orange-house, and the other for myrtles or other more common
greens, and had, I doubt not, been cast for that purpose, if this
piece of gardening had been then in as much vogue as it is now.</P>
<P>“From the middle of this parterre is a descent by many steps
flying on each side of a grotto that lies between them,” covered with
lead and flat, into the lower garden, which is all fruit-trees ranged
about the several quarters of a wilderness which is very shady; the
walks here are all green, the grotto embellished with figures of shell∣rock-work,
fountains, and water-works. If the hill had not ended
with the lower garden, and the wall were not bounded by a common
way that goes through the park, they might have added a third
quarter of all greens; but this want is supplied by a garden on the
other side the house, which is all of that sort, very wild, shady, and
adorned with rough rock-work and fountains.</P>
<P><PB N="133" REF="165"/>
“This was Moor-park, when I was acquainted with it, and the
sweetest place, I think, that I have seen in my life, either before or
since, at home or abroad.”—</P>
<P>I will make no farther remarks on this description. Any man
might design and <HI>build</HI> as sweet a garden, who had been born in and
never stirred out of Holbourn. It was not peculiar to sir William
Temple to think in that manner. How many Frenchmen are there
who have seen <HI>our</HI> gardens, and still prefer <HI>natural</HI> flights of steps
and shady cloisters covered with lead! Le Nature, the architect of
the groves and grottoes at Versailles, came hither on a mission to
improve our taste. He planted St. James's and Greenwich parks—no
great monuments of his invention.</P>
<P>To do farther justice to sir William Temple, I must not omit
what he adds. “What I have said of the best forms of gardens, is
meant only of such as are in some sort regular; for there may be
other forms wholly irregular, that may, for aught I know, have
more beauty than any of the others; but they must owe it to some
extraordinary dispositions of nature in the seat, <HI>or some great race of
fancy or judgment in the contrivance,</HI> which may reduce many disa∣greeing
parts <HI>into some figure,</HI> which shall yet, upon the whole, be
very agreable. Something of this I have seen in some places, but
heard more of it from others, who have lived much among the Chi∣neses,
a people whose way of thinking seems to lie as wide of ours
in Europe, as their country does.—Their greatest reach of imagina∣tion
is employed in contriving figures, where the beauty shall be
great and strike the eye, but without any order or disposition of
parts, that shall be commonly or easily observed. And though we
<PB N="134" REF="166"/>
have hardly any notion of this sort of beauty, yet they have a parti∣cular
word to express it; and where they find it hit their eye at first
sight, they say the Sharawadgi is fine or is admirable, or any such
expression of esteem—but I should hardly advise any of these at∣tempts
in the figure of gardens among us, they are adventures of
too hard atchievement for any common hands; and though there
may be more honour if they succeed well, yet there is more disho∣nour
if they fail, and it is twenty to one they will; whereas in re∣gular
figures, it is hard to make any great and remarkable faults.”</P>
<P>Fortunately Kent and a few others were not quite so timid, or we
might still be going up and down stairs in the open air.</P>
<P>It is true, we have heard much lately, as sir william Temple did,
of irregularity and imitations of nature in the gardens or grounds of
the Chinese. The former is certainly true; they are as whimsically
irregular, as European gardens are formally uniform, and unvaried—but
with regard to nature, it seems as much avoided, as in the
squares and oblongs, and strait lines of our ancestors. An artificial
perpendicular rock starting out of a flat plain, and connected with
nothing, often pierced through in various places with oval hollows,
has no more pretension to be deemed natural than a lineal terrass or
a parterre. The late Mr. Joseph Spence, who had both taste and
zeal for the present style, was so persuaded of the Chinese emperor's
pleasure-ground being laid out on principles resembling ours, that he
translated and published, under the name of sir Harry Beaumont, a
particular account of that inclosure from the collection of the letters
of the Jesuits. I have looked it over, and except a determined irre∣gularity,
can find nothing in it that gives me any idea of attention
<PB N="135" REF="167"/>
being paid to nature. It is of vast circumference and contains 200
palaces, besides as many contiguous for the eunuchs, all gilt, paint∣ed
and varnished. There are raised hills from 20 to 60 feet high,
streams and lakes, and one of the latter five miles round. These
waters are passed by bridges—but even their bridges must not be
strait—they serpentize as much as the rivulets, and are sometimes so
long as to be furnished with resting places, and begin and end with
triumphal arches. Methinks a strait canal is as rational at least as a
maeandring bridge. The colonades undulate in the same manner.
In short, this pretty gaudy scene is the work of caprice and whim;
and when we reflect on their buildings, presents no image but that of
unsubstantial tawdriness. Nor is this all. Within this fantastic Pa∣radise
is a square town, each side a mile long. Here the eunuchs
of the court, to entertain his imperial majesty with the bustle and
business of the capital in which he resides, but which it is not of his
dignity ever to see, act merchants and all sorts of trades, and even
designedly exercise for his royal amusement every art of knavery that
is practiced under his auspicious government. Methinks this is the
childish solace and repose of grandeur, not a retirement from affairs
to the delights of rural life. Here too his majesty plays at agricul∣ture;
there is a quarter set apart for that purpose; the eunuchs sow,
reap, and carry in their harvest in the imperial presence; and his
majesty returns to Pekin persuaded that he has been in the country.</P>
<P>Having thus cleared my way by ascertaining what have been the
ideas on gardening in all ages, as far as we have materials to judge
by, it remains to show to what degree Mr. Kent invented the new
style, and what hints he had received to suggest and conduct his un∣dertaking.</P>
<P><PB N="136" REF="168"/>
We have seen what Moor-park was, when pronounced a standard.
But as no succeeding generation in an opulent and luxurious country
contents itself with the perfection established by its ancestors, more
perfect perfection was still sought; and improvements had gone on,
till London and Wise had stocked our gardens with giants, animals,
monsters,<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">On the piers of a garden-gate not far from Paris I observed two very coquet sphinxes. These lady monsters had straw hats gracefully smart on one side of their heads, and silken cloaks half veiling their necks; all executed in stone.</NOTE> coats of arms and mottoes in yew, box and holly. Ab∣surdity
could go no farther, and the tide turned. Bridgman, the
next fashionable designer of gardens, was far more chaste; and whe∣ther
from good sense, or that the nation had been struck and reform∣ed
by the admirable paper in the Guardian, N° 173, he banished
verdant sculpture, and did not even revert to the square precision of
the foregoing age. He enlarged his plans, disdained to make every
division tally to its opposite, and though he still adhered much to
strait walks with high clipped hedges, they were only his great lines;
the rest he diversified by wilderness, and with loose groves of oak,
though still within surrounding hedges. I have observed in the
garden<NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">The seat of the late sir Jeremy Sambroke. It had formerly belonged to lady More, mother-in-law of sir Thomas More, and had been tyrannically wrehched from her by Henry VIII. on the execution of sir Thomas, though not her son, and though her jointure from a former husband.</NOTE> at Gubbins in Hertfordshire many detached thoughts, that
strongly indicate the dawn of modern taste. As his reformation gain∣ed
footing, he ventured farther, and in the royal garden at Richmond
dared to introduce cultivated fields, and even morsels of a forest
<PB N="137" REF="169"/>
appearance, by the sides of those endless and tiresome walks, that
stretched out of one into another without intermission. But this was
not till other innovators had broke loose too from rigid symmetry.</P>
<P>But the capital stroke, the leading step to all that has followed,
was [I believe the first thought was Bridgman's] the destruction of
walls for boundaries, and the invention of fossès—an attempt then
deemed so astonishing, that the common people called them Ha!
Ha's! to express their surprize at finding a sudden and unperceived
check to their walk.</P>
<P>One of the first gardens planted in this simple though still formal
style, was my father's at Houghton. It was laid out by Mr. Eyre,
an imitator of Bridgman. It contains three-and-twenty acres, then
reckoned a considerable portion.</P>
<P>I call a sunk fence the leading step, for these reasons. No sooner
was this simple enchantment made, than levelling, mowing and roll∣ing,
followed. The contiguous ground of the park without the
sunk fence was to be harmonized with the lawn within; and the gar∣den
in its turn was to be set free from its prim regularity, that it
might assort with the wilder country without. The sunk fence as∣certained
the specific garden, but that it might not draw too obvious
a line of distinction between the neat and the rude, the contiguous
out-lying parts came to be included in a kind of general design: and
when nature was taken into the plan, under improvements, every
step that was made, pointed out new beauties and inspired new ideas.
At that moment appeared Kent, painter enough to taste the charms
of landscape, bold and opinionative enough to dare and to dictate,
and born with a genius to strike out a great system from the twilight
<PB N="138" REF="170"/>
of imperfect essays. He leaped the fence, and saw that all nature
was a garden. He felt the delicious contrast of hill and valley chang∣ing
imperceptibly into each other, tasted the beauty of the gentle
swell, or concave scoop, and remarked how loose groves crowned
an easy eminence with happy ornament, and while they called in the
distant view between their graceful stems, removed and extended
the perspective by delusive comparison.</P>
<P>Thus the pencil of his imagination bestowed all the arts of land∣scape
on the scenes he handled. The great principles on which he
worked were perspective, and light and shade. Groupes of trees
broke too uniform or too extensive a lawn; evergreens and woods
were opposed to the glare of the champain, and where the view was
less fortunate, or so much exposed as to be beheld at once, he blot∣ted
out some parts by thick shades, to divide it into variety, or to
make the richest scene more enchanting by reserving it to a farther
advance of the spectator's step. Thus, selecting favourite objects,
and veiling deformities by screens of plantation; sometimes allowing
the rudest waste to add its foil to the richest theatre, he realized the
compositions of the greatest masters in painting. Where objects
were wanting to animate his horizon, his taste as an architect could
bestow immediate termination. His buildings, his seats, his temples,
were more the works of his pencil than of his compasses. We owe
the restoration of Greece and the diffusion of architecture to his skill
in landscape.</P>
<P>But of all the beauties he added to the face of this beautiful coun∣try,
none surpassed his management of water. Adieu to canals, cir∣cular
basons, and cascades tumbling down marble steps, that last ab∣surd
<PB N="139" REF="171"/>
magnificence of Italian and French villas. The forced elevation
of cataracts was no more. The gentle stream was taught to ser∣pentize
seemingly at its pleasure, and where discontinued by dif∣ferent
levels, its course appeared to be concealed by thickets properly
interspersed, and glittered again at a distance where it might be sup∣posed
naturally to arrive. Its borders were smoothed, but preserved
their waving irregularity. A few trees scattered here and there on
its edges sprinkled the tame bank that accompanied its maeanders;
and when it disappeared among the hills, shades descending from the
heights leaned towards its progress, and framed the distant point of
light under which it was lost, as it turned aside to either hand of the
blue horizon.</P>
<P>Thus dealing in none but the colours of nature, and catching its
most favourable features, men saw a new creation opening before
their eyes. The living landscape was chastened or polished, not
transformed. Freedom was given to the forms of trees; they ex∣tended
their branches unrestricted, and where any eminent oak, or
master beech had escaped maiming and survived the forest, bush and
bramble was removed, and all its honours were restored to distin∣guish
and shade the plain. Where the united plumage of an ancient
wood extended wide its undulating canopy, and stood venerable in
its darkness, Kent thinned the foremost ranks, and left but so many
detached and scattered trees, as softened the approach of gloom and
blended a chequered light with the thus lengthened shadows of the
remaining columns.</P>
<P>Succeeding artists have added new master-strokes to these touches;
perhaps improved or brought to perfection some that I have named.
<PB N="140" REF="172"/>
The introduction of foreign trees and plants, which we owe princi∣pally
to Archibald duke of Argyle, contributed essentially to the
richness of colouring so peculiar to our modern landscape. The mix∣ture
of various greens, the contrast of forms between our forest-trees
and the northern and West-Indian firs and pines, are improvements
more recent than Kent, or but little known to him. The weeping-willow
and every florid shrub, each tree of delicate or bold leaf, are
new tints in the composition of our gardens. The last century was
certainly acquainted with many of those rare plants we now admire.
The Weymouth-pine has long been naturalized here; the patriarch
plant still exists at Longleat. The light and graceful acacia was
known as early; witness those ancient stems in the court of Bedford∣house
in Bloomsbury-square; and in the bishop of London's garden
at Fulham are many exotics of very ancient date. I doubt therefore
whether the difficulty of preserving them in a clime so foreign to their
nature did not convince our ancestors of their inutility in general,
unless the shapeliness of the lime and horse-chesnut which accorded
so well with established regularity, and which thence and from their
novelty grew in fashion, did not occasion the neglect of the more
curious plants.</P>
<P>But just as the encomiums are that I have bestowed on Kent's
discoveries, he was neither without assistance or faults. Mr. Pope
undoubtedly contributed to form his taste. The design of the prince
of Wales's garden at Carlton-house was evidently borrowed from
the poet's at Twickenham. There was a little of affected modesty
in the latter, when he said of all his works he was most proud of his
garden. And yet it was a singular effort of art and taste to impress
<PB N="141" REF="173"/>
so much variety and scenery on a spot of five acres. The passing
through the gloom from the grotto to the opening day, the retiring
and again assembling shades, the dusky groves, the larger lawn, and
the solemnity of the termination at the cypresses that lead up to his
mother's tomb, are managed with exquisite judgment; and though
lord Peterborough assisted him
<Q>To form his quincunx and to rank his vines,</Q>
those were not the most pleasing ingredients of his little perspective.</P>
<P>I do not know whether the disposition of the garden at Rousham,
laid out for general Dormer, and in my opinion the most engaging
of all Kent's works, was not planned on the model of Mr. Pope's, at
least in the opening and retiring shades of Venus's vale. The whole
is as elegant and antique as if the emperor Julian had selected the
most pleasing solitude about Daphne to enjoy a philosophic retirement.</P>
<P>That Kent's ideas were but rarely great, was in some measure
owing to the novelty of his art. It would have been difficult to have
transported the style of gardening at once from a few acres to tum∣bling
of forests: and though new fashions like new religions, [which
are new fashions] often lead men to the most opposite excesses, it
could not be the case in gardening, where the experiments would
have been so expensive. Yet it is true too that the features in Kent's
landscapes were seldom majestic. His clumps were puny, he aimed
at immediate effect, and planted not for futurity. One sees no large
woods sketched out by his direction. Nor are we yet entirely risen
above a too great frequency of small clumps, especially in the elbows
of serpentine rivers. How common to see three or four beeches, then
as many larches, a third knot of cypresses, and a revolution of all
<PB N="142" REF="174"/>
three! Kent's last designs were in a higher style, as his ideas opened
on success. The north terras at Claremont was much superior to the
rest of the garden.</P>
<P>A return of some particular thoughts was common to him with
other painters, and made his <HI>hand</HI> known. A small lake edged by
a winding bank with scattered trees that led to a seat at the head of
the pond, was common to Claremont, Esher, and others of his de∣signs.
At Esher,
<Q>Where Kent and nature vied for Pelham's love,</Q>
the prospects more than aided the painter's genius.—They marked
out the points where his art was necessary or not; but thence left
his judgment in possession of all its glory.</P>
<P>Having routed <HI>professed</HI> art, for the modern gardiner exerts his
talents to conceal his art, Kent, like other reformers, knew not how
to stop at the just limits. He had followed nature, and imitated her
so happily, that he began to think all her works were equally proper
for imitation. In Kensington-garden he planted dead trees, to give
a greater air of truth to the scene—but he was soon laughed out of
this excess. His ruling principle was, that <HI>nature abhors a strait line.</HI>—His
mimics, for every genius has his apes, seemed to think that
she could love nothing but what was crooked. Yet so many men of
taste of all ranks devoted themselves to the new improvements, that
it is surprizing how much beauty has been struck out, with how few
absurdities. Still in some lights the reformation seems to me to have
been pushed too far. Though an avenue crossing a park or sepa∣rating
a lawn, and intercepting views from the seat to which it leads,
<PB N="143" REF="175"/>
are capital faults, yet a great avenue<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Of this kind one of the most noble is that of Stanstead, the seat of the earl of Halifax, traversing an ancient wood for two miles and bounded by the sea. The very extensive lawns at that seat, richly inclosed by venerable beech woods, and chequered by single beeches of vast size, particularly when you stand in the portico of the temple and survey the landscape that wastes itself in rivers of broken sea, recall such exact pictures of Claud Lorrain, that it is difficult to conceive that he did not paint them from this very spot.</NOTE> cut through woods, perhaps
before entering a park, has a noble air, and
<Q><L>Like footmen running before coaches</L>
<L>To tell the inn what lord approaches,</L></Q>
announces the habitation of some man of distinction. In other places
the total banishment of all particular neatness immediately about
a house, which is frequently left gazing by itself in the middle of a
park, is a defect. Sheltered and even close walks in so very uncer∣tain
a climate as ours, are comforts ill exchanged for the few pic∣turesque
days that we enjoy: and whenever a family can purloin a
warm and even something of an old fashioned garden from the land∣scape
designed for them by the undertaker in fashion, without inter∣fering
with the picture, they will find satisfactions on those days that
do not invite strangers to come and see their improvements.</P>
<P>Fountains have with great reason been banished from gardens as
unnatural; but it surprizes me that they have not been allotted to
their proper positions, to cities, towns, and the courts of great
houses, as proper accompaniments to architecture, and as works of
grandeur in themselves. Their decorations admit the utmost inven∣tion,
and when the waters are thrown up to different stages, and
<PB N="144" REF="176"/>
tumble over their border, nothing has a more imposing or a more
refreshing sound. A palace demands its external graces and attri∣butes,
as much as a garden. Fountains and cypresses peculiarly be∣come
buildings, and no man can have been at Rome, and seen the
vast basons of marble dashed with perpetual cascades in the area of
St. Peter's, without retaining an idea of taste and splendor. Those
in the piazza Navona are as useful as sublimely conceived.</P>
<P>Grottoes in this climate are recesses only to be looked at tran∣siently.
When they are regularly composed within of symmetry and
architecture, as in Italy, they are only splendid improprieties. The
most judiciously, indeed most fortunately placed grotto, is that at
Stourhead, where the river bursts from the urn of its god, and passes
on its course through the cave.</P>
<P>But it is not my business to lay down rules for gardens, but to give
the history of them. A system of rules pushed to a great degree of
refinement, and collected from the best examples and practice, has
been lately given in a book intituled <HI>Observations on modern Gardening.</HI>
The work is very ingeniously and carefully executed, and in point
of utility rather exceeds than omits any necessary directions. The
author will excuse me if I think it a little excess, when he examines
that rude and unappropriated scene of Matlocke-bath, and criticizes
nature for having bestowed on the rapid river Derwent too many cas∣cades.
How can this censure be brought home to gardening? The
management of rocks is a province can fall to few directors of gar∣dens;
still in our distant provinces such a guide may be necessary.</P>
<P>The author divides his subject into gardens, parks, farms, and
ridings. I do not mean to find fault with this division. Directions
<PB N="145" REF="177"/>
are requisite to each kind, and each has its department at many of
the great scenes from whence he drew his observations. In the his∣toric
light, I distinguish them into the garden that connects itself
with a park, into the ornamented farm, and into the forest or savage
garden. Kent, as I have shown, invented or established the first
sort. Mr. Philip Southcote founded the second or ferme ornèe, of
which is a very just description in the author I have been quoting.
The third I think he has not enough distinguished. I mean that kind
of alpine scene, composed almost wholly of pines and firs, a few
birch, and such trees as assimilate with a savage and mountainous
country. Mr. Charles Hamilton, at Pain's-hill, in my opinion has
given a perfect example of this mode in the utmost boundary of his
garden. All is great and foreign and rude; the walks seem not de∣signed,
but cut through the wood of pines; and the style of the
whole is so grand, and conducted with so serious an air of wild and
uncultivated extent, that when you look down on this seeming forest,
you are amazed to find it contain a very few acres. In general, ex∣cept
as a screen to conceal some deformity, or as a shelter in winter,
I am not fond of total plantations of ever-greens. Firs in particular
from a very ungraceful summit, all broken into angles.</P>
<P>Sir Henry Englefield was one of the first improvers on the new
style, and selected with singular taste that chief beauty of all gardens,
prospect and fortunate points of view. We tire of all the painter's art
when it wants these finishing touches. The fairest scenes, that de∣pend
on themselves alone, weary when often seen. The Doric por∣tico,
the Palladian bridge, the Gothic ruin, the Chinese pagoda,
that surprize the stranger, soon lose their charms to their surfeited
<PB N="146" REF="178"/>
master. The lake that floats the valley is still more lifeless, and its
lord seldom enjoys his expence but when he shows it to a visitor.
But the ornament whose merit soonest fades, is the hermitage or
scene adapted to contemplation. It is almost comic to set aside a
quarter of one's garden to be melancholy in. Prospect, animated
prospect, is the theatre that will always be the most frequented.
Prospects formerly were sacrificed to convenience and warmth. Thus
Burleigh stands behind a hill, from the top of which it would com∣mand
Stamford. Our ancestors who resided the greatest part of the
year at their seats, as others did two years together or more, had an
eye to comfort first, before expence. Their vast mansions received
and harboured all the younger branches, the dowagers and ancient
maiden aunts of the families, and other families visited them for a
month together. The method of living is now totally changed, and
yet the same superb palaces are still created, becoming a pompous
solitude to the owner, and a transient entertainment to a few tra∣vellers.</P>
<P>If any incident abolishes or restrains the modern style of gardening,
it will be this circumstance of solitariness. The greater the scene,
the more distant it is probably from the capital; in the neighbour∣hood
of which land is too dear to admit considerable extent of pro∣perty.
Men tire of expence that is obvious to few spectators. Still
there is a more imminent danger that threatens the present, as it
has ever done, all taste. I mean the pursuit of variety. A modern
French writer has in a very affected phrase given a just account of
this, I will call it, distemper. He says, <HI>l'ennui du beau amene le
gout du singulier.</HI> The noble simplicity of the Augustan age was
<PB N="147" REF="179"/>
driven out by false taste. The gigantic, the puerile, the quaint,
and at last the barbarous, and the monkish, had each their successive
admirers. Music has been improved, till it is a science of tricks
and slight of hand: the sober greatness of Titian is lost, and paint∣ing
since Carlo Maratti, has little more relief than Indian paper.
Borromini twisted and curled architecture, as if it was subject to the
change of fashions like a head of hair. If we once lose sight of the
propriety of landscape in our gardens, we shall wander into all the
fantastic sharawadgis of the Chinese. We have discovered the point
of perfection. We have given the true model of gardening to the
world; let other countries mimic or corrupt our taste; but let it
reign here on its verdant throne, original by its elegant simplicity,
and proud of no other art than that of softening nature's harshnesses
and copying her graceful touch.</P>
<P>The ingenious author of the Observations on modern Gardening
is, I think, too rigid when he condemns some deceptions, because
they have been often used. If those deceptions, as a feigned steeple
of a distant church, or an unreal bridge to disguise the termination
of water, were intended only to surprise, they were indeed tricks that
would not bear repetition; but being intended to improve the land∣scape,
are no more to be condemned because common, than they
would be if employed by a painter in the composition of a picture.
Ought one man's garden to be deprived of a happy object, because
that object has been employed by another? The more we exact
novelty, the sooner our taste will be vitiated. Situations are every
where so various, that there never can be a sameness, while the dis∣position
of the ground is studied and followed, and every incident of
view turned to advantage.</P>
<P><PB N="148" REF="180"/>
In the mean time how rich, how gay, how picturesque the face of
the country! The demolition of walls laying open each improve∣ment,
every journey is made through a succession of pictures; and
even where taste is wanting in the spot improved, the general view is
embellished by variety. If no relapse to barbarism, formality, and
seclusion, is made, what landscapes will dignify every quarter of our
island, when the daily plantations that are making have attained
venerable maturity! A specimen of what our gardens will be, may
be seen at Petworth, where the portion of the park nearest the house
has been allotted to the modern style. It is a garden of oaks two
hundred years old. If there is a fault in so august a fragment of
improved nature, it is, that the size of the trees are out of all pro∣portion
to the shrubs and accompanyments. In truth, shrubs should
not only be reserved for particular spots and home delight, but are
passed their beauty in less than twenty years.</P>
<P>Enough has been done to establish such a school of landscape, as
cannot be found on the rest of the globe. If we have the seeds of a
Claud or a Gaspar amongst us, he must come forth. If wood, wa∣ter,
groves, vallies, glades, can inspire or poet or painter, this is
the country, this is the age to produce them. The flocks, the herds,
that now are admitted into, now graze on the borders of our culti∣vated
plains, are ready before the painter's eyes, and groupe them∣selves
to animate his picture. One misfortune in truth there is that
throws a difficulty on the artist. A principal beauty in our gardens
is the lawn and smoothness of turf: in a picture it becomes a dead
and uniform spot, incapable of chiaro scuro, and to be broken
insipidly by children, dogs, and other unmeaning <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igures.</P>
<P><PB N="149" REF="181"/>
Since we have been familiarized to the study of landscape, we hear
less of what delighted our sportsmen-ancestors, <HI>a fine open country.</HI>
Wiltshire, Dorsetshire, and such ocean-like extents were formerly
preferred to the rich blue prospects of Kent, to the Thames-watered
views in Berkshire, and to the magnificent scale of nature in York∣shire.
An open country is but a canvass on which a landscape might
be designed.</P>
<P>It was fortunate for the country and Mr. Kent, that he was suc∣ceeded
by a very able master; and did living artists come within my
plan, I should be glad to do justice to Mr. Brown; but he may be a
gainer, by being reserved for some abler pen.</P>
<P>In general it is probably true, that the possessor, if he has any taste,
must be the best designer of his own improvements. He sees his
situation in all seasons of the year, at all times of the day. He
knows where beauty will not clash with convenience, and observes in
his silent walks or accidental rides a thousand hints that must escape
a person who in a few days sketches out a pretty picture, but has not
had leisure to examine the details and relations of every part.</P>
<P>Truth, which after the opposition given to most revolutions, pre∣ponderates
at last, will probably not carry our style of garden into
general use on the continent. The expence is only suited to the opu∣lence
of a free country, where emulation reigns among many inde∣pendent
particulars. The keeping of our grounds is an obstacle, as
well as the cost of the first formation. A flat country, like Holland,
is incapable of landscape. In France and Italy the nobility do not
reside much, and make small expence at their villas. I should think
the little princes of Germany, who spare no profusion on their pa∣laces
<PB N="150" REF="182"/>
and country-houses, most likely to be our imitators; especially
as their country and climate bears in many parts resemblance to ours.
In France, and still less in Italy, they could with difficulty attain that
verdure which the humidity of our clime bestows as the ground-work
of our improvements. As great an obstacle in France is the em∣bargo
laid on the growth of their trees. As after a certain age,
when they would rise to bulk, they are liable to be marked by the
crown's surveyors as royal timber, it is a curiosity to see an old tree.
A landscape and a crown-surveyor are incompatible.</P>
<P>I have thus brought down to the conclusion of the last reign [the
period I had marked to this work] the history of our arts and artists,
from the earliest aera in which we can be said to have had either.
Though there have been only gleams of light and flashes of genius,
rather than progressive improvements, or flourishing schools; the
inequality and insufficience of the execution, have flowed more from
my own defects than from those of the subject. The merits of the
work, if it has any, are owing to the indefatigable industry of Mr.
Vertue, in amassing all possible materials. As my task is finished,
it will, I hope, at least excite others to collect and preserve notices
and anecdotes for some future continuator. The aera promises to
furnish a nobler harvest. Our exhibitions, and the institution of a
royal academy, excite emulation in the artists, diffuse their repu∣tation,
and recommend them to employment. The public examines
and reasons on their works, and spectators by degrees become judges.
Nor are persons of the first rank meer patrons. Lord Nuneham's
etchings are superior in boldness and freedom of stroke to any thing
we have seen from established artists. Gardening and architecture
<PB N="151" REF="183"/>
owe as much to the nobility and to men of fortune as to the profes∣sors.
I need but name general Conway's rustic bridge at Park-place,
of which every stone was placed by his own direction in one of the
most beautiful scenes in nature; and the theatric staircase designed
and just erected by Mr. Chute, at his seat of the Vine in Hampshire.
If a model is sought of the most perfect taste in architecture, where
grace softens dignity, and lightness attempers magnificence; where
proportion removes every part from peculiar observation, and deli∣cacy
of execution recalls every part to notice; where the position is
the most happy, and even the colour of the stone the most harmo∣nious;
the virtuoso should be directed to the new<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The old front, still extant, was erected by Thomas Wentworth late earl of Strafford; the new one was entirely designed by the present earl William himself.</NOTE> front of Went∣worth-castle:
the result of the same elegant judgment that had be∣fore
distributed so many beauties over that domain, and called from
wood, water, hills, prospects and buildings, a compendium of pic∣tursque
nature, improved by the chastity of art. Such an aera will
demand a better historian. With pleasure therefore I resign my pen;
presuming to recommend nothing to my successor, but to observe as
strict impartiality.</P>
<CLOSER><DATE>August 2, 1770.</DATE></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<PB REF="184"/>
<HEAD>ERRATA.</HEAD>
<P>Page 31, line 19, for, <HI>Northamptonshire,</HI> read, <HI>Nottinghamshire.</HI> P. 76, line
the last, insert, <HI>in,</HI> before <HI>the pool of Bethesda.</HI> P. 80, line 13, for, <HI>most them,</HI>
read, <HI>most of them.</HI> P. 83, line 17, for, <HI>parly,</HI> read <HI>partly.</HI> P. 90, line 3,
after <HI>Miniature,</HI> add, <HI>Statuaries and Medallists.</HI> P. 111, line 3, for, <HI>lady Doro∣thy
Tufton,</HI> read, <HI>lady Dorothy Saville.</HI> P. 112, l. 8, for, <HI>sir John Wentworth,</HI>
read, <HI>sir William Wentworth.</HI> P. 129, last line of the note, dele one of the
words <HI>in,</HI> before 1767.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="appendix">
<PB REF="185"/>
<HEAD>APPENDIX.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">PRINTS by or after HOGARTH,
Discovered since the Catalogue was finished.</HEAD>
<P>W. HOGARTH, engraver, with two figures and two cupids,
April 28, 1720.</P>
<P>People in a shop, under the king's arms: Mary and Ann Ho∣garth.
A shop-bill.</P>
<P>Small oval print for the Rape of the Lock.</P>
<P>An emblematic print representing agriculture and arts. Seems to
be a ticket for some society.</P>
<P>A coat of arms, with two slaves and trophies. Plate for books.</P>
<P>A foreign coat of arms, supporters a savage and angel. Ditto.</P>
<P>A grifon with a flag. A crest.</P>
<P>Another coat of arms, and two boys as terms.</P>
<P>A Turk's head. A shop-bill.</P>
<P>A small angel, almost the same as N<SUP>o</SUP> 5, class 1.</P>
<P>Another, almost the same as N<SUP>o</SUP> 8, class 1, but with a view of
the Foundling hospital.</P>
<P>Lord Aylmer's coat of arms.</P>
<P>Two ditto of the duchess of Kendal.</P>
<P><PB REF="186"/>
A shop-bill, representing trade and arms of Florence.</P>
<P>Five Muscovites. Small plate for a book of travels.</P>
<P>A ticket for the benefit of Milward, the tragedian.</P>
<P>A ticket for a burial.</P>
<P>The Pool of Bethesda; large, by Ravenet and Picot.</P>
<P>The good Samaritan; ditto, by Ravenet and Delatre.</P>
<P>Orator Henley christening a child. Mezzotinto.</P>
<P>Capt. Coram and the children of the Foundling hospital. A ticket.</P>
<P>The sleeping Judges, (as in N<SUP>o</SUP> 56, class 3, but) with heads after
L. da Vinci.</P>
<P>A large oval coat of arms, with terms of the four seasons.</P>
<P>Mr. Huggins, with a bust of Ariosto. Small round.</P>
<P>Twelve head-pieces for Beavers's Military Punishments of the An∣cients;
but scarce any copies have these plates.</P>
<P>Frontispiece to a pamphlet against the Hutchinsonians, never pub∣lished.
It represents a witch sitting on the moon, and watering on a
mountain, whence issue mice who are devouring sir Isaac Newton's
Optics: one mouse lies dead on Hutchinson's works, probably to im∣ply
being choaked. The conundrum signi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies, Front-is-piss.</P>
<P>Print of the weighing-house to Club's Physiognomy; a hu∣mourous
pamphlet in quarto, published in 1763, and dedicated to
Hogarth.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="index">
<PB REF="187"/>
<HEAD>INDEX
OF
NAMES OF ARTISTS
IN THIS VOLUME
Ranged according to the Times in which they lived.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>In the Reign of GEORGE I.</HEAD>
<ITEM>LOUIS laguerre, p, 3.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Lanscroon, 6.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Michael Dahl, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Peter Angelis, 8.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Antony Russel, 9.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Luke Cradock, 10.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Peter Casteels, 11.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Dagar, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Charles Jervas, 12.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Jonathan Richardson, 15.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Grisoni, 19.</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Aikman, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Alexander, 20.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir James Thornhill, 20.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Robert Brown, 23.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Bellucci, 24.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Balthazar Denner, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Ferg, 25.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thomas Gibson, 26.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Hill, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>P. Monamy, 27.</ITEM>
<ITEM>James Van Huysum, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>James Maubert, 28.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Pesne, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Stevens, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Smibert, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Trevett, 30.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Henry Trench, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB REF="188"/>
Peter 'Tillemans, 31:</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Vandrebank, 32.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Samuel Barker, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Peter Van Bleeck, 33.</ITEM>
<ITEM>H. Vandermijn, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Enoch Zeeman, 34.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Watteau, 35.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Robert Woodcock, 36.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Isaac Whood, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Vogelsang, 37.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Zurich, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Christian Richter, 38.</ITEM>
<ITEM>J. Antoine Arlaud, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mrs. Hoadley, 40.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>ARCHITECTS, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Nich. Hawksmoor, 42.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mr. Archer, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Wakefield, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>James Gibbs, 44.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Colin Campbell, 47.</ITEM>
<ITEM>John James, 48.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Carpentiere, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Christian Reisen, ib.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>GEORGE II.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Hans Huyssing, 53.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Charles Collins, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Cooper, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Barthol. Dandridge, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Damini, 54.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Jeremiah Davison, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Ellis, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Philip Mercier, 55.</ITEM>
<ITEM>J. Francis Nollikins, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Robinson, 56.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Andrea Soldi, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Chevalier Rusca, 57.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Stephen Slaughter, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>James Worsdale, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ranelagh Barrett, 58.</ITEM>
<ITEM>John Wootton, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Giacomo Amiconi, 59.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Brunetti, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>James Seymour, 61.</ITEM>
<ITEM>J. Baptist Vanloo, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Joseph Vanaken, 62.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Clermont, 63.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Canalletti, 64.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Joli, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>George Lambert, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thomas Worlidge, 66.</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Hogarth, 68.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>PAINTERS in ENAMEL and
MINATURE.</HEAD>
<ITEM>J. S. Liotard, 90.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Frederick Zincke, 91.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Rouquet, 92.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Groth, 93.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB REF="189"/>
Bernard Lens, 93.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Joseph Goupy, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>James Deacon, 94.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Spencer, ib.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>STATUARIES.</HEAD>
<ITEM>J. Michael Rysbrach, 95.</ITEM>
<ITEM>L. F. Roubiliac, 99.</ITEM>
<ITEM>—Güelphi, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>L. Delvaux, 100.</ITEM>
<ITEM>J. Francis Verskovis, ib.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>MEDALLISTS.</HEAD>
<ITEM>John Dassier, 101.</ITEM>
<ITEM>J. Christopher Tanner, 102.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Laurence Nattier, ib.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>ARCHITECTS.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Giacomo Leoni, 105.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thomas Ripley, 106.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Batty Langley, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>H. Earl of Pembroke, 107.</ITEM>
<ITEM>R. Earl of Burlington, 108.</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Kent, 111.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Henry Flitcroft, 116.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="index">
<PB REF="190"/>
<HEAD>INDEX
OF
NAMES OF ARTISTS
Ranged alphabetically.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>A.</HEAD>
<ITEM>AIKMAN, William, p. 19.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Alexander, John, 20.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Amiconi, Giacomo, 59.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Angelis, Peter, 8.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Archer, Mr. 42.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Arlaud, J. Antoine, 38.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>B.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Barker, Samuel, 32.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Barrett, Ranelagh, 58.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Bellucci,—, 24.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Brown, Robert, 23.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Brunetti,—, 59.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Burlington, Earl of, 108.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>C.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Campbell, Colin, 47.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Canalletti,—, 64.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Carpentiere,—, 48.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Casteels, Peter, 11.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Clermont,—, 63.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Collins, Charles, 53.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cooper,—, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cradock, Luke, 10.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>D.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Dagar,—, 11.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dahl, Michael, 6.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Damini,—, 54.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dandridge, Barth. 53.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dassier, John, 101.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Davison, Jeremiah, 54.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Deacon, James, 94.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Delvaux, L. 100.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Denner, Balthazar, 24.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<PB REF="191"/>
<HEAD>E.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Ellis, John, 54.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>F.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Ferg,—, 25.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Flitcroft, Henry, 116.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>G.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Gibbs, James, 44.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Gibson, Thomas, 26.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Goupy, Joseph, 93.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Grisoni,—, 19.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Groth, 93.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Guelphi,—, 99.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>H.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Hawksmoor, Nich. 42.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hill,—, 26.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hoadley, Mrs. 40.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hogarth, William, 68.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Huyssing, Hans, 53.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>J.</HEAD>
<ITEM>James, John, 48.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Jervas, Charles, 12.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Joli,—, 64.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>K.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Kent, William, 111.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>L.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Laguerre, Louis, 3.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lambert, George, 64.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Langley, Batty, 106.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lanscroon,—, 6.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lens, Bernard, 93.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Leoni, Giacomo, 105.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Liotard, J. S. 90.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>M.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Maubert, James, 28.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mercier, Philip, 55.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Monamy, P. 27.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>N.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Nattier, Laurence, 102.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Nollikins, J. Francis, 55.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>P.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Pembroke, Earl of, 107.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pesne,—, 28.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>R.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Reisen, Christian, 48.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Richardson, Jonathan, 15.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Richter, Christian, 38.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ripley, Thomas, 106.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Robinson,—, 56.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Roubiliac, L. F. 99.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB REF="192"/>
Rouquet,—, 92.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rusca, Chevalier, 57.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Russel, Antony, 9.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rysbrach, J. M. 95.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>S.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Seymour, James, 61.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Slaughter, Stephen, 57.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Smibert, John, 28.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Soldi, Andrea, 56.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Spencer,—, 94.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Stevens, John, 28.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>T.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Tanner, J. Christopher, 102.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thornhill, Sir James, 20.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Tillemans, Peter, 31.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Trench, Henry, 30.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Trevett,—, ib.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>V.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Vanaken, Joseph, 62.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Van Bleeck, P. 33.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vandermijn, H. ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vandrebank, John, 32.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Van Huysum, James, 27.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vanloo, J. Baptist, 61.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Verskovis, J. Francis, 100.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vogelsang,—, 37.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>W.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Wakefield,—, 42.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Watteau, 35.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Whood, Isaac, 36.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Woodcock, Robert, ib.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Wootton, John, 58.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Worlidge, Thomas, 66.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Worsdale, James, 57.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Z.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Zeeman, Enoch, 34.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Zincke, Frederick, 91.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Zurich,—, 37.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="193"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="194" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="195" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="196" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="197" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="198" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="199" MS="y"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>
