<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet TYPE="text/css" href="http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE><DATE>yyyy-mm-dd</DATE><RESPSTMT><NAME>[name of reviewer]</NAME><RESP>MURP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM></CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>

<EEBO>
<IDG S="auto" R="OX" ID="K056996.002">
<STC T="C">T066365_pt2</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3309241841</BIBNO>
<VID>0012900802</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
EXCURSION.</P>
<P>VOLUME THE SECOND.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="2"/>
<P>THE
EXCURSION.</P>
<P>IN TWO VOLUMES.</P>
<P>BY MRS. BROOKE;
AUTHOR of the History of Lady JULIA
MANDEVILLE, and of EMILY MONTAGUE.</P>
<P>VOL. II.</P>
<P>LONDON:
Printed for T. CADELL, in the STRAND.</P>
<P>MDCCLXXVII.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1>
<PB REF="3"/>
<P>THE EXCURSION.</P>
<P>BOOK V.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="book">
<PB N="3" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>THE EXCURSION.
BOOK V.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. I.</HEAD>
<P>IF Miss Villiers was elated with the sud∣den
return of her noble lover, a return
which she, with great appearance of proba∣bility,
attributed to the excess of his affec∣tion,
and his inability to live longer absent
from her; she was still more so on receiving
<PB N="4" REF="5"/>
from him the next morning a letter, in
which, after some general professions of the
most ardent passion, he intreated permission
to attend her in Berner's-street any evening
she would appoint, when he could have the
pleasure of entertaining her, without wit∣nesses,
on a subject of the utmost conse∣quence
to the future happiness of <HI>his</HI> life,
and, he flattered himself, of <HI>hers.</HI></P>
<P>She read the letter a thousand times; she
kissed the beloved name by which it was
subscribed: her heart beat with emotions
equally new and delightful.</P>
<P>She had <HI>hoped,</HI> but till this charming mo∣ment
she could not with any propriety be
said to have <HI>believcd,</HI> the reality of that hap∣piness
which now appeared to await her.</P>
<P>She sat down to write; it was the first
letter in which she had ever entered into so
interesting a subject: Lord Melvile was the
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>
first man she had ever suffered to speak to
her of love, the first man she had ever re∣garded
even with approbation.</P>
<P>She was embarrassed; she took up the
pen; she proceeded; she found the letter
too tender; her delicacy was alarmed; she
wrote another, she found it too cold.</P>
<P>Dissatisfied with every sentiment which
occurred, she determined on sending only a
card, to fix an evening when she might have
the pleasure of seeing him.</P>
<P>But, what evening? was the question;
and a question not easily answered.</P>
<P>Though she would have wished a conver∣sation
on which so much depended, in re∣spect
to her future days, to have taken place
immediately, yet modesty (for she was supe∣rior
to art), and that bashful timidity inse∣parable
from youth and sensibility like hers,
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
influenced her to postpone Lord Melvile's
proposed visit till Thursday.</P>
<P>She therefore wrote him, not an answer
to his letter, but a short card, inviting him
to tea, and, if he had no other engagement,
to supper, on Thursday evening.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. II.</HEAD>
<P>THE most perfect ignorance of the
world, and the most unsuspecting tem∣per
existing, will, in candid minds, but in
no other, apologize for Miss Villiers's ex∣treme
imprudence in inviting Lord Melvile
to a <HI>tete-a-tete</HI> supper; and that, in conse∣quence
of a declaration which was far from
being explicit as to its tendency.</P>
<P><PB N="7" REF="8"/>
The exuberance of her joy had once
more hurried her beyond the bounds of that
indispensable, that cardinal virtue, Discre∣tion;
a virtue without which all others lose
their exterior lustre, and which is the only
adequate guardian of female honour.</P>
<P>The world will judge, and it has a right
to judge, by probable appearances; and
though innocence may escape the snare it
has laid for itself in forming an indiscreet
appointment, yet reputation will be the in∣evitable
sacrifice.</P>
<P>The dignity and purity of Maria's mind
left her without an idea of danger from such
an interview; and even, if a doubt had
arisen, her unbounded esteem for, and con∣fidence
in, the object of her affection, would
have silenced it.</P>
<P><PB N="8" REF="9"/>
Convinced of the rectitude of Lord Mel∣vile's
intentions, the least shadow of suspi∣cion
would, in her own opinion, have ren∣dered
her unworthy his generous, his disin∣terested
tenderness.</P>
<P>Her imagination represented to her in the
liveliest colours his transport at placing the
woman he loved in a situation so worthy of
her.</P>
<P>She would have almost envied such ex∣cess
of felicity to any being but Lord Mel∣vile.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. III.</HEAD>
<P>HIS lordship saw the whole affair
through a medium extremely dif∣ferent.</P>
<P><PB N="9" REF="10"/>
Maria's invitation left him not a doubt of
success in his design; a design he had been
forming with great coolness and deliberation
ever since he left his father's seat in Yorkshire.</P>
<P>He therefore sat down, to consider how
he should regulate the future household,
and state the necessary expences, of our he∣roine,
whom from this moment he regarded
as a part of his equipage.</P>
<P>His marriage, the preliminaries of which
were settled, though he had not yet seen his
intended bride, and which was to be con∣cluded
soon after his father's return to town,
made it impossible for him to think of taking
her to Grosvenor-street.</P>
<P>It was therefore necessary she should have
a house, and an establishment of her own.</P>
<P><PB N="10" REF="11"/>
Naturally liberal in every part of his ex∣pence,
he was profuse, and with a strong
mixture of ostentation, in his pleasures.</P>
<P>As no man of the world marries with any
view but that of paying off the old debts of
his paternal estate, in order to be able to
contract new ones in his turn, a mistress is
an almost indispensable part of a matrimo∣nial
arrangement in high life; unless, which
is a plan attended with some hazard, affairs
of gallantry with women in high life should
be preferred.</P>
<P>The declared mistress of a man of his
rank ought to appear with eclat.</P>
<P>The <HI>declared</HI> mistress it was determined
she should be.</P>
<P>As vanity was the predominant passion of
his soul, he could not resist the triumph his
imagination promised him, in producing (as
<PB N="11" REF="12"/>
soon as decency after his marriage would
permit) so much beauty, as his property,
to the world.</P>
<P>Indeed, this was his most powerful motive
for making choice of our heroine, his in∣clination
being much stronger for Dorig∣non;
but Dorignon was not handsome
enough to do honour to his choice.</P>
<P>He had however another reason for the
preference he gave to Miss Villiers.</P>
<P>The vivacity of Dorignon's temper ren∣dered
her the most improper mistress
breathing for a man who intended to
marry.</P>
<P>There would have been no answering for
the manner in which she might have ex∣pressed
her irascible feelings, if she had met
her honourable rival in public.</P>
<P>Mais, a nos moutons.</P>
<P><PB N="12" REF="13"/>
The fortune of the destined Lady Mel∣vile,
and the consequent settlements to be
made by his father on himself, would ren∣der
his situation affluent, and justify a little
extraordinary expence in so important an
article as a mistress.</P>
<P>Miss Villiers's person, her air, her con∣versation,
her deportment, her <HI>tout ensem∣ble,</HI>
conveyed so strikingly the idea of a
woman of condition; she was so formed to
become an elegant style of life; her present
appearance (if we set aside her being in a
lodging) was so correspondent to that idea,
that he could not think of offering her com∣mon
terms.</P>
<P>Convinced, as he was determined to be,
that she was an adventurer, and that her
views corresponded with his own; yet he
felt a kind of respect, when with her, for
which he could not account.</P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="14"/>
It was not sufficient to make him desist
from his pursuit, but it determined him to
make such an ample provision for her as
should demonstrate to the world the gene∣rosity
of his disposition, and, at the same
time, give the oftensible goddess of his ido∣latry
that exterior splendor which aims at
confounding ranks and characters, and put∣ting
humble virtue out of countenance.</P>
<P>A dramatic writer, whose name I forget,
says, “Virtuous women walk on foot:”
which must not be understood to insinuate,
that only vicious women go in carriages;
and can certainly mean no more than this,
that, if a woman is not born to a coach, she
will never acquire one by her virtue.</P>
<P>From which premises we draw a conclu∣sion;
a conclusion which may not perhaps
be universally subscribed to, that a coach
is not, as some people suppose, a necessary
<PB N="14" REF="15"/>
concomitant of human happiness; since
heaven could never intend its creatures
should be less happy in proportion as they
deserved to be more so.</P>
<P>In other words, heaven could never or∣dain,
that poverty should be necessarily the
companion of virtue; or, that “Virtuous
women should walk on foot.”</P>
<P><HI>A propos,</HI> I have often wondered at the
various ideas annexed to this respectable
word, virtue; a word which in ancient
Rome meant public spirit; in modern Rome
means a taste in the fine arts; in England,
at least in the female vocabulary, means
chastity; and in France has little or no
meaning at all.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="15" REF="16"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. IV.</HEAD>
<P>THERE are lovers who would have
thought it a tedious interval between
the present hour and Thursday evening.</P>
<P>Not so Lord Melvile: the opera to-night,
and Bach's concert to-morrow—he did not
well know how to spare Thursday—if she
had luckily fixed on Friday, he had no en∣gagement.</P>
<P>Some true-born Englishman, some ge∣nuine
son of nature, who has not softened
his manners, and hardened his heart, by a
French education, may perhaps wonder at
the <HI>sang froid,</HI> and stoical deliberation, with
which Lord Melvile pursued a mistress,
whom he notwithstanding intended to sup∣port
at an extravagant expence.</P>
<P><PB N="16" REF="17"/>
He will be surprized that he should
coolly sit down and calculate this expence
with the precision of a clerk in a merchant's
counting-house; and be so methodically
discreet in an affair which seems founded in
indiscretion.</P>
<P>He will set no bounds to his astonishment
when he is told, that this young man, who
is not deficient either in understanding or
good-nature, chuses to incur the guilt of
seduction without even the excuse of passion
to alleviate his crime.</P>
<P>But a man of <HI>bon ton</HI> is a man of reason,
not of passion; he is invulnerable to the
shafts of beauty; and is vicious from prin∣ciple,
not inclination.</P>
<P>It is to the shrine of Vanity, not to that
of Love, his adoration is directed.</P>
<P><PB N="17" REF="18"/>
Not meerly a man of reason, he is a man
of snow: or, to express it better in the
beautiful lines of one of my fair country-women:</P>
<Q><L>“Cold as the snows of Rhodope descend,</L>
<L>And with the chilling waves of Hebrus blend;</L>
<L>So cold the heart where vanity presides,</L>
<L>And mean self-love the bosom-feelings guides<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The Bleeding Rock, a Legendary Tale; written in
the true spirit of poetry, by Miss Hannah More.</NOTE>.”</L></Q>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. V.</HEAD>
<P>A Moment, gentle reader, let us step to
Lady Blast's.</P>
<P>Ten dowagers obeyed her summons; the
merits of the cause were fully stated; and
after debates which might have done ho∣nour
<PB N="18" REF="19"/>
to the senatorial abilities of A—and
B—themselves; debates whence ministers
and patriots might equally have culled the
fairest flowers of elocution; Miss Villiers was
found guilty of having, by her indiscretion,
forfeited her title to be one of <HI>the world,</HI>
and was, in consequence, adjudged to be
degraded from the place she at present oc∣cupied
in the immaculate coterie into which
Lady Hardy had so kindly introduced her.</P>
<P>The dreadful sentence of banishment
from what these venerable matrons styled
<HI>good company,</HI> was denounced in form by
Lady Blast; who, after signifying the de∣cree
in writing to Miss Villiers's protectress,
Lady Hardy, proceeded to dissolve the as∣sembly.</P>
<P>The benevolent sisterhood, having hur∣ried
down their chocolate, dispersed differ∣ent
ways to publish the award of the court,
and, to do their <HI>possible,</HI> that from this in∣stant,
<HI>nobody should let Miss Villiers in.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="19" REF="20"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. VI.</HEAD>
<P>ABSORBED in her fairy dream, and
insensible to every object but Lord
Melvile, and her coronet, Maria walked
in air.</P>
<P>The crisis so ardently wished was at hand;
she was arrived at the smiling summit of
hope.</P>
<P>A thousand gay fantoms of happiness,
the delusive offspring of credulity and ex∣pectation,
chaced each other, in her imagi∣nation,
like the ever-varying tints of the
dawn.</P>
<P>The door opened: she started from her
reverie, on John's announcing Mr. Ham∣mond.</P>
<P><PB N="20" REF="21"/>
The amiable old man advanced; a new
source of pleasure opened on her mind; he
could only come to bring her an answer in
respect to her tragedy.</P>
<P>Certain of success in this interesting point,
she did not observe the traces of disappoint∣ment
on his countenance.</P>
<P>But his narrative, which we recommend
to the perusal of all young votaries of the
Dramatic Muse, will appear to most advan∣tage
in a separate Chapter.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VII.</HEAD>
<P>“IN obedience to your commands, ma∣dam,
I sent your tragedy to the
acting manager the very day I had the
honour of attending you before.”</P>
<P><PB N="21" REF="22"/>
“I accompanied the packet with a letter,
requesting him to read the play, which
was written by a friend for whose success
I was as anxious as I should be for my
own, with attention; and to give me his
decisive answer this morning; when I in∣tended
to have the pleasure of calling on
him to receive it.”</P>
<P>“I went accordingly at eleven, the hour
which I supposed would be most conve∣nient
to him.”</P>
<P>“As he loves to keep on good terms
with all authors of reputation who have
the complaisance not to write for the
theatre, as he has measures to keep with
me on account of some of my connexions,
and as he knows enough of my temper to
be assured it is not calculated for attend∣ance,
I was admitted the moment I sent
up my name.”</P>
<P><PB N="22" REF="23"/>
“I found him surrounded by a train of
anxious expectants, for some of whom I
felt the strongest compassion.”</P>
<P>“Amongst the rest I saw—but I forbear
his respectable name: an involuntary sigh
escaped me; I could scarce avoid ex∣claiming
aloud, Alas! to what is genius
reduced!”</P>
<P>“The train which composed this great
man's levee all retired on my entrance,
when the following conversation took
place; a conversation which will convince
you I over-rated my little interest, in sup∣posing
I could secure your tragedy a can∣did
reading.”</P>
<P>“My good sir, I am happy any thing
procures me the pleasure of seeing you—I
was talking of you only last week”—</P>
<P><PB N="23" REF="24"/>
“I am much obliged to you, sir, but the
business on which I attend you”—</P>
<P>“Why—a—um—true—this play of
your friend's—You look amazingly well,
my dear sir—In short—this play—I should
be charmed to oblige you—but we are so
terribly overstocked”—</P>
<P>“I am not to learn that you have many
applications, and therefore determined to
wait on you in time—You have read the
play, I take for granted”—</P>
<P>“Why—a—um—no—not absolutely
read it—Such a multiplicity of affairs—Just
skimmed the surface—I—a—Will
you take any chocolate, my dear
friend?”</P>
<P><PB N="24" REF="25"/>
“I have only this moment breakfasted,
sir—But to our play.”</P>
<P>“True—this play—the writing seems
not bad—something tender—something
like sentiment—but not an atom of the
<HI>vis comica.</HI>”</P>
<P>“In a tragedy, my good sir?”</P>
<P>“I beg pardon: I protest I had forgot—I
was thinking of Mr. What-d'ye-call-um's
comedy, which he left with me last
Tuesday.”</P>
<P>“But why tragedy? why not write co∣medy?
There are real sorrows enough in
life without going to seek them at the
theatre—Tragedy does not please as it
used to do, I assure you, sir.</P>
<P><PB N="25" REF="26"/>
“You see I scarce ever play tragedy
now? The public taste is quite changed
within these three or four years?”</P>
<P>“Yet Braganza”—</P>
<P>“A lucky hit, I confess—something well
in the last scene—But as I was saying,
sir—your friend's play—there are good
lines—But—the fable—the manners—the
conduct—people imagine—if authors
would be directed—but they are an in∣corrigible
race”—</P>
<P>“Ah! Mr. Hammond! we have no wri∣ters
now—there was a time—your Shakes∣peares
and old Bens—If your friend would
call on me, I could propose a piece for
him to <HI>alter,</HI> which perhaps”—</P>
<P><PB N="26" REF="27"/>
“My commission, sir, does not extend
beyond the tragedy in question; there∣fore
we will, if you please, return to
that.”</P>
<P>“Be so good, my dear sir, as to reach me
the gentleman's play: it lies under the
right-hand pillow of the sopha.”</P>
<P>“He took the play, which was still
in the cover in which I had sent it,
and it was easy to see had never been
opened.”</P>
<P>“He turned over the leaves with an air
of the most stoical inattention, and pro∣ceeded:”</P>
<P>“There is a kind of a—sort of a—smattering
of genius in this production,
<PB N="27" REF="28"/>
which convinces me the writer, with pro∣per
advice, might come to something in
time.”</P>
<P>“But these authors—and after all, what
do they do? They bring the meat indeed,
but who instructs them how to cook it?
Who points out the proper seasoning for
the dramatic ragoût? Who furnishes the
savoury ingredients to make the dish pa∣latable?
Who brings the Attic salt?—the
Cayenne pepper?—the—the—a—'Tis
amazing the pains I am forced to take
with these people, in order to give relish
to their insipid productions”—</P>
<P>“I have no doubt of all this, sir; but
the morning is wearing away.”</P>
<P>“You have many avocations, and I
would not take up your time; I have only
one word to add to what I have said: I
know we are too late for the present sea∣son;
<PB N="28" REF="29"/>
but you will oblige me infinitely if
you will make room for this piece in the
course of the next.”</P>
<P>“The next season, my dear sir!—why—a—it
is absolutely impossible—I have now
six-and-twenty new tragedies on my pro∣mise-list—besides,
I have not read it?—That
is—if—if—a—your friend will
send it me in July—if I approve it in
July, I will endeavour—let me see—what
year is this?—O, I remember—'tis se∣venty-five—Yes—if
I think it will do, I
will endeavour to bring it out in the win∣ter
of—the winter of—eighty-two.</P>
<P>“That is, if my partner—if Mr.—should
have made no engagement, un∣known
to me, for that year, which may
put it out of my power.”</P>
<P>“I wished him a good morning, madam;
and have brought back your tragedy.”</P>
<P><PB N="29" REF="30"/>
“I have related the conversation literally,
on which you are to make your own re∣flections:
whatever may be your future
determination, you will find me always
ready to execute your commands.”</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VIII.</HEAD>
<P>THE lively red in the cheek of Maria
went and returned a thousand times
in the course of this narration; her heart
beat thick with contrary passions; fear, a
faint ray of hope, uncertainty, disappoint∣ment,
indignation, took their turns; the
latter at length prevailed, and enabled her
to bear this unexpected stroke with becom∣ing
spirit.</P>
<P><PB N="30" REF="31"/>
She repressed the tear which was ready
to start, the tear of blended resentment and
distress.</P>
<P>She determined to make no further ap∣plication
to the theatres till she should glit∣ter
in the gay circle as Lady Melvile; and
the moment that event, which could not be
far distant, should take place, to make a pre∣sent
of her piece to the other house; let∣ting
the manager who had treated her so
contemptuously know, <HI>whose</HI> play it was he
had not condescended to read.</P>
<P>Elated with this idea, she thanked Mr.
Hammond for the unpleasing step he had
taken in the hope of serving her; and re∣placed
the unfortunate tragedy in her bu∣reau,
with an air of tranquillity which ef∣fectually
deceived him.</P>
<P><PB N="31" REF="32"/>
He was now convinced of what he had
before, from her apparent anxiety, a little
doubted, that fame was the only object she
had in view, and that no inconvenience
would arise from her waiting a more fa∣vourable
moment.</P>
<P>Perfectly at ease in this point, he pro∣ceeded
to give her his opinion on the gene∣ral
subject of writing for the theatre; a
pursuit in which her sex, her delicacy of
mind, her rectitude of heart, her honest
pride, and perhaps her genius, were all
strongly against her success.</P>
<P>He advised her to keep her piece—not
nine years, but till more liberal maxims of
government should take place in the impor∣tant
empire of the theatre; an empire on
the faithful administration of which de∣pended,
not only national taste, but in a
great degree national virtue.</P>
<P><PB N="32" REF="33"/>
“The incoherent jumble of words with∣out
ideas, which I have been repeating to
you, madam,” pursued he, “is, I am
told, the general answer to dramatic wri∣ters,
who are intended to be disgusted by
this unworthy treatment, which the ma∣nagers
honour with the name of policy,
from thinking of any future applica∣tions.”</P>
<P>“That vulgar, unenlightened, minds
should act with this wretched imitation
of craft (for even craft is here too re∣spectable
an appellation), I should natu∣rally
expect; but that a man of excellent
understanding, of the most distinguished
talents, the idol of the public; with as
much same as his most ardent wishes can
aspire to, and more riches than he knows
how to enjoy; should descend to such
contemptible arts, with no nobler a view
than that of robbing the Dramatic Muse,
<PB N="33" REF="34"/>
to whom he owes that fame and those
riches, of her little share of the reward, is
a truth almost too improbable to be be∣lieved.”</P>
<P>“Would it not have been wiser, as well
as more manly, to have said, in the clear∣est
and most unambiguous terms,”</P>
<P>“Sir, we have no occasion for new pieces
while there are only two English theatres
in a city so extensive and opulent as Lon∣don;
a city which, in the time of Eliza∣beth,
when the frequenters of the theatre
were not a tenth part of the present, sup∣ported
seventeen.”</P>
<P>“We will therefore never receive any
new production but when we are com∣pelled
to it by recommendations which
we dare not refuse: nor will I read the
tragedy you bring, lest its merit should
make me ashamed to reject it.”</P>
<P><PB N="34" REF="35"/>
“This would have been indeed the lan∣guage
of a thankless son of the drama;
the language of a man having no object
in view but his own emolument, and want∣ing
gratitude to that publick, and to that
beautiful art, to which he was so much
indebted; but it would have been the
language of a man, and a man possessed of
sufficient courage to avow his principle
of action.”</P>
<P>“Indulge me a moment longer. The
person, of whom I have been speaking,
deserves, in his profession, all the praise
we can bestow: he has thrown new lights
on the science of action, and has, per∣haps,
reached the summit of theatrical
perfection.”</P>
<P>“I say <HI>perhaps,</HI> because there is no limit∣ing
the powers of the human mind, or
saying where it will stop.”</P>
<P><PB N="35" REF="36"/>
“It is possible he may be excelled,
though that he may be equalled is rather
to be wished than expected, whenever (if
that time ever comes) his retiring shall
leave the field open to that emulation
which both his merit and his management
have contributed to extinguish.”</P>
<P>“I repeat, that, as an actor, the publick
have scarce more to wish than to see him
equalled; as an author, he is not devoid
of merit; as a manager, he has, I am
afraid, ever seen the dawn of excellence,
both in those who aspired to write for, or
to tread, the theatre, with a reluctant
eye; and has made it too much his ob∣ject,
if common sense, aided by impartial
observation,” is not deceived, “To blast
each rising literary blossom, and plant
thorns round the pillow of genius<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><P>Long after the above Chapter was written, but before it was committed to the press, this great theatri∣cal luminary disappeared from his orbit. As the writer honours his talents, though she disapproves his illiberal maxims of government, she has unaffected pleasure in predicting, that the various excellencies of his perfor∣mance will be remembered with delight, when the er∣rors of his management, though fatal to literature, shall be consigned to oblivion.</P>
<P>She wishes him a calm and honourable retreat under the shade of his own laurels: laurels which Candour will exult in twining round his brow, and proclaim to have been fairly won.</P>
<P>May she be here indulged in a wish, which she almost ventures to call a prediction, that the dramatic Muse may again raise her head; and new Shakespeares, new Sophocleses, new Garricks, arise, under the auspices of a manager who has sufficient genius to be above envy, and sufficient liberality of mind to be incapable of avarice?</P></NOTE>.”</P>
<P><PB N="36" REF="37"/>
On a favourite theme the garrulous old
man would have expatiated much longer,
had he not observed an air of impatience in
Miss Villiers, who was not inclined to attend
to reasoning, on a subject where both her
passions and her interest were so much con∣cerned.
He therefore took leave, and pro∣mised
to call on her again in a day or two.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="9" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="37" REF="38"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. IX.</HEAD>
<P>GRATEFUL as Miss Villiers really
was for Mr. Hammond's very friendly
interposition in favour of her tragedy, she
was not perfectly satisfied with his mode of
application.</P>
<P>He had depended too much on himself,
and on his supposed interest with the acting
manager.</P>
<P>He had, besides, even from his own ac∣count,
conversed with this gentleman in a
style far removed from the persuasive, and
not a little tending towards the dictatorial.</P>
<P>After all, the manager might not be so
much to blame.</P>
<P><PB N="38" REF="39"/>
Mr. Hammond had neglected adverting
to two circumstances, which appeared to her
of infinitely more importance to her success
than the protection of fifty peevish old fel∣lows
like himself.</P>
<P>The circumstances he had thus injudici∣ously
omitted to mention, would naturally
have had great weight with a man of ge∣nius,
who as such could not fail of being a
man of delicate and refined gallantry, and
a zealous partizan of female excellence.</P>
<P>He should have urged, that the piece in
question was the production of a woman
[he might, without the imputation of flat∣tery,
have added, of a young and amiable
woman, of family and unblemished charac∣ter],
and that the part of the heroine was
exquisitely adapted to display in full light
the brilliant powers of the actress who filled
the first characters at his theatre.</P>
<P>She had hinted both these particulars to
Mr. Hammond the first time he had at∣tended
<PB N="39" REF="40"/>
her on this business; but a sarcasti∣cal
smile of disapprobation had prevented
her entering further into the subject.</P>
<P>The truth is, he declined using those ar∣guments,
because he thought them both
extremely unfavourable to the cause.</P>
<P>She was not quite clear she had acted
wisely in consulting <HI>this</HI> Mr. Hammond; he
might be a very good kind of man, but
apparently ignorant of the world; nor did
she find that he was a man <HI>anybody knew.</HI></P>
<P>He was splenetic, fretful; and she could
not help believing, from the severe style in
which he spoke of theatrical direction in ge∣neral,
that he had, in the early part of his
life, been a candidate, and an unsuccessful
one, for the dramatic laurel.</P>
<P>In this, however, she was mistaken; as
she was in imagining she knew the world
<PB N="40" REF="41"/>
better than a man who had passed all his
life, and that life not a short one, in the first
company of which it is composed.</P>
<P>He had not indeed the honour of being
of a <HI>certain set;</HI> but there were coteries ra∣ther
more estimable, where his merit re∣ceived
the most flattering distinctions.</P>
<P>But to return to Miss Villiers.</P>
<P>She now wished ardently she had pur∣sued
her first plan, of writing to, or seeing,
the manager herself; she was certain she
should have succeeded better; nor should
she, in that case, have been without hopes
of prevailing on this great actor to perform
the character in her piece which she had
written on purpose for him.</P>
<P>It was however too late to take this step,
and therefore regret was folly.</P>
<P><PB N="41" REF="42"/>
She had judged ill in trusting this impor∣tant
affair to a stranger, but no matter—Lady
Melvile's play would undoubtedly be
<HI>received,</HI> though Miss Villiers's had not even
been <HI>read.</HI></P>
<P>She could not recollect this last humi∣liating
circumstance without feeling her re∣sentment
against the manager revive.</P>
<P>The blush of anger had not left her
cheek, when Lord Melvile, unexpectedly,
entered the room.</P>
<P>His Lordship, who had been riding in
Hyde Park, had there met the lovely Lady
B—, who had insisted so earnestly, before
twenty of the most fashionable people in
town, on his meeting her at Almack's on
Thursday evening, that he must have lost
all reputation as a gallant man had he re∣fused.</P>
<P><PB N="42" REF="43"/>
Not that he had the least inclination for
Lady B—, or she for him: on the contrary,
she was strongly suspected of giving the pre∣ference
to her Lord; but she was amazingly
<HI>the ton,</HI> and therefore to be distinguished
by her was of the utmost consequence.</P>
<P>What was to be done in this perplexing
situation? To have postponed an assigna∣tion,
would have been as great a solecism in
gallantry as to have refused Lady B—'s
challenge: to anticipate it, would have a
much better air.</P>
<P>He settled it with himself, to call on Miss
Villiers before he went home; to dissemble
a little impatience, and to prevail on her, if
possible, to change the time she had fixed
for their <HI>tete-a-tete,</HI> and permit him to sup
with her the approaching evening, after the
opera.</P>
<P><PB N="43" REF="44"/>
He addressed her with that persuasive
easy grace so natural to him on all occasions,
and so extremely useful on most, and found
very little difficulty in carrying his point.</P>
<P>Her present situation, setting her love
aside, made procrastination extremely incon∣venient
to her: she had failed in one of her
great pursuits; it was therefore indispensa∣bly
requisite she should be clearly informed
what she had to expect as to the other; and
an eclaircissement, though her modesty
would have deferred it, could not arrive too
soon.</P>
<P>Lord Melvile returned home to dress;
and Maria sent for Mrs. Merrick up stairs,
to order her supper.</P>
<P>She explained herself no farther than by
saying, she should have a friend to sup with
her, and desiring to have the table set out
with elegance.</P>
<P><PB N="44" REF="45"/>
Mrs. Merrick supposed the expected guest
to be Lady Hardy, who had more than once
supped with our heroine before; but had
too much respect for her young lady (so
she always called Miss Villiers) to ask the
question.</P>
<P>She withdrew, to make the necessary ar∣rangements
for the evening; and Miss Vil∣liers
retired to her dressing-room, to prepare
for the most important hour of her life;
an hour, on the events of which depended
the good or ill of her whole future days;
an hour, which was to decide whether she
was destined to be the most wretched, or
the most happy, of womankind.</P>
<P>Sanguine as she naturally was, the disap∣pointment
of the morning had a little abated
her presumption.</P>
<P><PB N="45" REF="46"/>
She had been, in idea, quite as certain of
success in the one point as in the other; and
yet she had failed.</P>
<P>But then—there was a very essential dif∣ference—
She was a stranger to the manager,
and it was therefore easy to mistake his cha∣racter
and turn of thinking.</P>
<P>She had supposed (and she might per∣haps,
if any manager had elevation of mind
sufficient to try the experiment, be justified
in this seemingly Utopian idea), that the di∣rector
of a theatre must at the same time taste
the most refined pleasure, and reap the most
permanent advantage, in encouraging ge∣nius
and gratifying the publick, by giving
pieces of superior excellence, without re∣gard
to any consideration but that excellence
itself.</P>
<P><PB N="46" REF="47"/>
On this supposition, after Mr. Ham∣mond's
very favourable judgement of her
tragedy, she had looked on it as certain it
would be received.</P>
<P>She had therefore only formed illusive ex∣pectations
by the commonest error in the
world; that of reasoning right on principles
which, unhappily, were wrong.</P>
<P>In respect to Lord Melvile the case was
very different; she was almost as well ac∣quainted
with his heart as with her own.</P>
<P>Could that countenance deceive—But
away with suspicion—Lord Melvile's mind
was as faultless as his form.</P>
<P>His soul was an emanation of the divini∣ty:
a lively image of the <HI>first good, first per∣fect,</HI>
and <HI>first fair.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="47" REF="48"/>
Besides, on this interesting occasion, her
own opinion, or rather her own heart, was
to direct her conduct.</P>
<P>Mr. Hammond, with his chilling, suspi∣cious,
superannuated policy, had, thank
heaven.! nothing to do in this affair.</P>
<P>Her hair-dresser interrupted this train of
reflections: he was desired to exert his ut∣most
skill; he obeyed, but she was far from
being satisfied: he had never dressed her so
well, yet never found it so impossible to
please.</P>
<P>His work finished, he observed, with a
very respectful bow, that her ladyship had
had the goodness to order her bill; he
should not have taken the liberty to remind
her of this, had he not been in great dis∣tress
to make up a payment the next morn∣ing.</P>
<P><PB N="48" REF="49"/>
Both her own temper, and the education
given her by Col. Dormer, had inspired her
with the laudable pride of disdaining to be
in debt.</P>
<P>She therefore paid him, however incon∣venient,
and found she had only twenty
pounds remaining.</P>
<P>She had still an hundred and twenty to
pay, the greater part of which she every
moment expected to be asked for.</P>
<P>She repented having been so precipitate
in calling in her bills.</P>
<P>Yet it was necessary to form some judge∣ment
of her situation in respect to money;
and who could have supposed her tragedy
would not have been received?</P>
<P><PB N="49" REF="50"/>
Alas! the ideal source of wealth, on
which she had so fondly relied, was no
more!</P>
<P>She did not dare to think—should Lord
Melvile deceive her—But it was a degree
of sacrilege even to suppose it possible—</P>
<P>At all events she determined on a truce
with care for the approaching evening.</P>
<P>So disinterested a lover deserved that she
should meet him drest in smiles.</P>
<P>The day past on; my reader will judge
of her anxiety.</P>
<P>She dined; that is, she sat down to table—she
drank tea—the hours past heavily
along.</P>
<P><PB N="50" REF="51"/>
She traversed her apartment, she changed
her seat a thousand times; she attempted to
read—the book might have been Greek—</P>
<P>Ten o'clock came; he had promised not
to stay the whole opera—the watchman went
the half hour—she had never known half
an hour so long—eleven—she looked pee∣vishly
at her watch—at a quarter past eleven,
Lord Melvile made his appearance—</P>
<P>A thousand apologies—the croud—his
carriage could not get up—he had met with
ladies in distress in the passage, and could
not refuse his assistance—Nothing was ever
so unlucky—She might judge what must
have been his impatience—</P>
<P>He presented her with a <HI>bouquet</HI> of roses
from his father's villa in Kent, praised her
dress, and told her all the little anecdotes
of the opera.</P>
<P><PB N="51" REF="52"/>
She talked too, as soon as that mixture
of anxiety and diffidence, which had taken
possession of her on Lord Melvile's entrance,
would give her leave.</P>
<P>She talked—good gods! how she talked!
Could he be otherwise than charmed!—she
talked of him.</P>
<P>She praised his dress; every thing he
wore was so exquisitely fancied.</P>
<P>He was in all so superior to other men!</P>
<P>She flattered, without herself perceiving
it, his taste, his understanding, his polite∣ness,
his knowledge of the world, his re∣fined
connoisseurship in the elegant arts.</P>
<P>He was enchanted—with the subject at
least.</P>
<P><PB N="52" REF="53"/>
He listened to her with the most gentle
complacency, found she had infinite wit,
though she had not yet said one word which
merited such an appellation; and applauded
himself for having once made a choice for
which he should not have occasion to blush.</P>
<P>He repaid her in kind the incense she so
liberally bestowed; the conversation was
consequently pretty dull, and, as it could
entertain only themselves, may be omitted
without any loss to the reader.</P>
<P>This mild, inoffensive chit-chat filled up
the interval, a very short one, between his
lordship's arrival, and the appearance of
supper.</P>
<P>They sat down; Lord Melvile ate ama∣zingly,
found every thing excellent, asked
if her cook was French, and was with dif∣ficulty
convinced of the contrary.</P>
<P><PB N="53" REF="54"/>
Mrs. Merrick had really this evening
surpassed herself; and she was by no means
unlettered in the fashionable science of good
eating.</P>
<P>Miss Villiers, inebriated with the pleasing
hope of finding Lord Melvile the man of
honour she had always believed him, and
happy at seeing him appear pleased with
her entertainment, forgot the important
crisis of her fate was arrived.</P>
<P>She forgot that her future life must pro∣bably
take its colour from the hour that
was on the wing; and found her anxiety,
before the supper was ended, give way to
modest confidence and convivial delight.</P>
<P>She recovered that chearful ease, that
something above serenity, which is so abso∣lutely
necessary to render our social mo∣ments
<PB N="54" REF="55"/>
pleasing; and gave way, by degrees,
to all the natural vivacity of her temper.</P>
<P>The bewitching melody of her voice; the
softness of her manner; that lovely femini∣ty
so conspicuously wanting in his Dorig∣non;
her sprightly sallies, chastised by de∣licacy
and good-breeding; commanded Lord
Melvile's admiration through all his <HI>sang
froid,</HI> and threw a new lustre round the at∣tractive
graces of her person.</P>
<P>Poisoned as his taste unhappily was by
the boundless licence of vicious conversa∣tion,
he yet found a thousand unexpected
charms in that of our heroine.</P>
<P>He even found her amusing, of which
till this moment he had not conceived the
remotest idea.</P>
<P>As his self-love was gratified to its ut∣most
extent by her very assiduous attention
<PB N="55" REF="56"/>
to please, by her smiles of undissembled af∣fection
(for she really loved him), it found
its account almost as much in her perfec∣tions
as in his own; and he therefore con∣templated
them with almost equal satisfac∣tion.</P>
<P>He had, he was convinced, nothing <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
fear from avowing his design, therefore why
not avow it? He even fancied she expected
a proposal of the kind which he intended
making.</P>
<P>Her tenderness for him was too evident
to be mistaken.</P>
<P>Yet, strange as it may seem to some of
our readers, that very tenderness, which
merited the utmost delicacy on his part;
her unaffected modesty; the elegance of
her manners; her apparent innocence
(whether real or assumed he was not at pre∣sent
able to determine); all together awed
<PB N="56" REF="57"/>
him into a temporary silence on the subject
which had occasioned his visit.</P>
<P>He talked of love, it is true; but it was
in such general terms as could not have
alarmed the most scrupulous, the most ap∣prehensive
virtue; in such terms as con∣firmed
Maria in the unhappy delusion which
had betrayed her into the imprudent part
she was unfortunately acting.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="10" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. X.</HEAD>
<P>THEY had supped, the conversation
was beginning to grow interesting.</P>
<P>Lord Melvile, after a thousand protesta∣tions
of the most sincere attachment, had
gone so far as to declare that the happiness
of his future life depended entirely on pas∣sing
it with her.</P>
<P><PB N="57" REF="58"/>
He had proceeded, in expressions which
were rather equivocal, to offer her <HI>carte
blanche</HI> in respect to settlements.</P>
<P>As her idea of the word settlement dif∣fered
very essentially from his lordship's,
she looked on their marriage as concluded,
and could with difficulty restrain the trans∣ports
of her heart.</P>
<P>She blushed, looked abashed, dropped a
tear of mixed tenderness and gratitude, and
was for some time unable to speak.</P>
<P>She at last assumed sufficient courage to
tell him, though with hesitation, that she
had the most lively sense of his lordship's
generosity and nobleness of sentiment; but
that she loved him for himself alone, and
was indifferent to every other considera∣tion.</P>
<P><PB N="58" REF="59"/>
As he looked on these as words of course,
which meant nothing, he pressed her to be
more explicit.</P>
<P>She was going to refer him to Col.
Dormer for an answer, when the door
opened, and a very genteel man, about
twenty-five, in regimentals, entered the
room, with an air of the most perfect ease
and unconcern, humming a part of one of
the favourite songs in Montezuma.</P>
<P>He stopped short, appeared confused,
looked round with astonishment, and, ad∣dressing
Maria with the most respectful air,
attempted to apologize for an intrusion
which he had not intended.</P>
<P>“Can you forgive me, madam? I found
the street-door open, and mistook it for
my own apartment, which is in the next
house.</P>
<P><PB N="59" REF="60"/>
“I am ashamed of my indiscretion, but
you have nothing to fear from it.”</P>
<P>He hurried down, after he had said this,
without waiting for an answer.</P>
<P>Neither Miss Villiers nor Lord Melvile
could speak; they were both petrified with
surprize.</P>
<P>His lordship's was, however, a surprize
mixed with uncertainty and chagrin.</P>
<P>He knew not how to give credit to the
stranger's story of mistaking the house; it
was very improbable, to say no more.</P>
<P>He might be a lover, and a favoured
one; or, at least, one who had been fa∣voured,
and was still in the list of her
friends.</P>
<P><PB N="60" REF="61"/>
His familiar manner of entering the
room, his unembarrassed address to Maria,
his retiring without waiting an answer, gave
Lord Melvile, who had been taught to
think ill of the human heart, suspicions still
more injurious to both.</P>
<P>He even fancied, and how creative is
fancy! that he had seen mutual glances of
intelligence.</P>
<P>He thought it more than possible he was
in danger of becoming a dupe to the most
infamous artifice; and that Maria, in her
seeming attachment to him, had been only
acting an assumed character, in order to de∣ceive.</P>
<P>His vanity combated, but could not con∣quer,
this very mortifying idea.</P>
<P>Unable to recover his good-humour, or
to resolve in what manner to take this ex∣traordinary
<PB N="61" REF="62"/>
adventure, he found it impossi∣ble,
and indeed he thought it impolitic, to
resume the conversation.</P>
<P>Miss Villiers, who was still more discon∣certed,
without having merited to be at all
so, had an air of perplexity and self-con∣demnation,
which added strength to Lord
Melvile's suspicions.</P>
<P>She was much more at a loss than his
lordship, how to behave in so uncommon a
conjuncture.</P>
<P>The confusion she felt on the stranger's
entering the room, gave her the first idea of
her own imprudence in allowing Lord Mel∣vile's
midnight visit.</P>
<P>The stranger's apology for his intrusion,
though apparently respectful, shewed too
plainly the light in which he regarded the
party.</P>
<P><PB N="62" REF="63"/>
She was alarmed, she was determined to
be more guarded for the future; she en∣treated
Lord Melvile to retire.</P>
<P>She was not without apprehension as to
the continuance of his esteem.</P>
<P>She dreaded losing his good opinion by
that very indiscretion of which her too great
anxiety to oblige him had been the sole
cause.</P>
<P>The delicacy inseparable from real affec∣tion
taught her to be the more careful of
her own honour because it was soon to be
his.</P>
<P>In short, without knowing well how to
develop her ideas, she found them crowd
upon her too fast for expression; nor in∣deed
were they such as she would have
chosen indiscriminately to communicate.</P>
<P><PB N="63" REF="64"/>
The continuity of the scene being broken
by this unexpected event, and both feeling
an embarrassment which made it very diffi∣cult
to recover the thread of their discourse;
each found a thousand plausible reasons for
separating, and deferring the subject, on
which they were just entering, to another
opportunity.</P>
<P>His lordship's politeness, however, and
that art which he had taken so much pains
to acquire, got so entirely the better of his
displeasure, that he left her without her en∣tertaining
the slightest suspicion that he at∣tributed
to her any share in this mysterious
adventure.</P>
<P>He was really extremely at a loss, as well
how to determine on this important point,
as how to form a just idea of her general
character.</P>
<P><PB N="64" REF="65"/>
He hesitated whether to pronounce her
the most artless, or the most designing, of
her sex.</P>
<P>As he very naturally, in which we wish
he had more imitators, looked on his father
as his firmest friend, and the person most
interested in his happiness, he with great
prudence resolved to suspend the present
negotiation till Lord Claremont's return to
town; to give his lordship, without disguise
or palliation, a circumstantial relation of the
whole transaction, so far as it had already
gone; and to ask his advice whether he
ought, in common discretion, to resume, or
to relinquish, his pursuit of our heroine.</P>
<P><PB REF="66"/>
THE EXCURSION.</P>
<P>BOOK VI.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="6" TYPE="book">
<PB N="67" REF="67"/>
<HEAD>THE EXCURSION.
BOOK VI.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. I.</HEAD>
<P>WHEN Miss Villiers rose in the morn∣ing,
she found Mrs. Merrick in her
dining-room waiting her coming, in order
to attend herself, as she sometimes did, dur∣ing
breakfast.</P>
<P><PB N="68" REF="68"/>
The grave air of this good woman
alarmed her; she enquired, with the utmost
kindness of manner, if she was well.</P>
<P>“Very well, I thank you, madam,
but”—</P>
<P>“But what, Mrs. Merrick? You gene∣rally
meet with smiles.”</P>
<P>“I am a little uneasy”—</P>
<P>“Is your uneasiness any thing I can re∣move?”</P>
<P>“Sure enough you can, my dear young
lady, for it is entirely on your account.”</P>
<P>After fifty apologies, and as many pro∣testations
that it was the first time in her life
she ever thought her in the wrong, she took
the liberty, which her long and faithful at∣tachment
<PB N="69" REF="69"/>
to the family of Miss Villiers ren∣dered
justifiable, of remonstrating gently on
the indiscreet party of the night before, and
its probable ill consequences to her reputa∣tion,
and of course to her happiness.</P>
<P>She placed the impropriety of this sup∣per
in so strong a light, that Maria, who
had the utmost indulgence for her, in order
to remove her anxiety, confessed to her, but
under the strictest injunctions of secrecy,
that she was in a very short time to be mar∣ried
to Lord Melvile.</P>
<P>She added, that Lord Melvile's motive
for this seemingly ill-timed visit, was to
consult her, without interruption, on the
necessary settlements to be made on this
interesting occasion; and that he chose the
evening as the most certain time to find her
without company.</P>
<P><PB N="70" REF="70"/>
She desired her to be under no apprehen∣sion
of her displeasure; assured her she did
not blame her, ignorant as she was of the
only circumstance which could render her
excusable, for thinking the party indis∣creet.</P>
<P>She however told her, she expected, after
such a proof of her unlimited confidence,
that, whatever visits she might in future have
occasion to receive from Lord Melvile, she
should rest satisfied with the propriety of
her conduct; which ever had been, and ever
should be, regulated by the most punctilious
rules of virtue and honour.</P>
<P>She proceeded to inform her, that she
should in a post or two, which was really
her intention, write to entreat Col. Dormer
to come to town, in order to arrange the
preliminaries of this marriage with Lord
Claremont.</P>
<P><PB N="71" REF="71"/>
Mrs. Merrick, who thought there was
no alliance to which her young lady had not
a right to pretend; who knew her incapa∣ble
of even the shadow of falsehood; and
who had, from his beauty to which women
are always partial, and his affability for
which all the world have the same prepos∣session,
a strong inclination to think highly
of Lord Melvile; was almost out of her
senses with pleasure, on receiving this unex∣pected
intelligence.</P>
<P>She made Miss Villiers a thousand con∣gratulatory
curtsies, wished her joy almost
as often, promised her the most inviolable
secrecy, and hastened down to communi∣cate
this good news, having first exacted a
solemn engagement that it should go no fur∣ther,
to her brother, a very honest trades∣man
in the neighbourhood, who happened
to be then in the house.</P>
<P><PB N="72" REF="72"/>
She looked on this as no breach of confi∣dence
in respect to Miss Villiers; because,
in the first place, it did not go out of the
family; and because, in the second, she
knew her brother to be an adept in the art
of keeping secrets, having been, in his
youth, for several years, the favourite do∣mestic
of one of the clerks in one of the
most important of the public offices.</P>
<P>She was a woman of honour, and would
not have betrayed her young lady for the
world; but she knew the secret was as safe
with her brother as with herself; for which
supposition every reader, who is not unrea∣sonable
indeed, will certainly give her
credit.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="73" REF="73"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. II.</HEAD>
<P>THE hours passed heavily on with our
heroine the next three days.</P>
<P>She heard nothing of Lord Melvile; and
would not venture to make a visit, lest he
should unluckily call during her absence.</P>
<P>As the moments of expectation are not
the pleasantest that can be conceived, she
determined, as she was sitting at breakfast
the fourth day, to go that evening to a rout,
for which she had received a card three
weeks before.</P>
<P>She resolved however not to play, be∣cause
she had scarce money sufficient for one
stake; but she could no longer support her
own society; and some sort of dissipation
<PB N="74" REF="74"/>
was become absolutely necessary to relieve
an anxiety rendered more exquisite by the
natural warmth and impatience of her tem∣per.</P>
<P>She was dressing for this purpose, when
her French milliner, who had just been at
Lady Blast's, where she had heard some
circumstances not too favourable to our he∣roine,
burst abruptly into the room, and,
with an air and manner to which Miss Vil∣liers
had not been accustomed, demanded
instant payment of her bill.</P>
<P>To pay her from the slender remains of
her own finances was impossible; not to pay
her was distraction.</P>
<P>In this tumult of her mind, hurried away
by honest pride and indignation, she took a
step which that very pride would at any
other moment have infallibly prevented.</P>
<P><PB N="75" REF="75"/>
She sat down, and wrote a note to Lady
Hardy, in which, after apologizing for tres∣passing
on her friendship, of which she had
already received so many striking proofs, she
entreated her ladyship, till she could order
a remittance from the country, to lend her
an hundred pounds, for which she had an
unexpected and immediate occasion.</P>
<P>She added, that, being perfectly ac∣quainted
with the nobleness of her lady∣ship's
sentiments, she knew she was laying
her under a distinguished obligation by
making a request which gave her an oppor∣tunity
of evincing the sincerity of her re∣gard,
and of those obliging offers of service
so often repeated.</P>
<P>She observed further, that this request
was the strongest mark she could give of her
esteem for her ladyship's amiable virtues;
and concluded by reminding her, that,
<PB N="76" REF="76"/>
amongst real friends, the greatest delicacy,
in points of this nature, consisted in having
no delicacy at all.</P>
<P>At the moment when Lady Hardy re∣ceived
this sentimental epistle, she was deli∣berating
with herself whether to support
Miss Villiers, and enter a caveat against
Lady Blast's whole proceeding; or abso∣lutely
to give up her acquaintance, and ac∣quiesce
in the sentence of the venerable
court of dowagers.</P>
<P>In other words, she was balancing in her
own mind the arguments for and against our
heroine's ever becoming Lady Melvile.</P>
<P>This letter removed every shadow of
doubt, and operated like magic in making
the unfavourable scale preponderate.</P>
<P>She called up Miss Villiers's new foot∣man,
who happened to be the bearer of the
<PB N="77" REF="77"/>
letter, and who, my reader may remember,
had been recommended by herself.</P>
<P>“Pray, Harry, is your lady out of her
senses!”</P>
<P>Harry bowed, and smiled.</P>
<P>“I should soon be in a fine way indeed,
if I was to lend my money to every little
adventurer”—</P>
<P>Harry looked grave—</P>
<P>“Do not be uneasy, Harry: I will get
you a better place, or perhaps take you
myself.</P>
<P>“In the mean time, you will extremely
oblige me, if you will tell me all you know
of this girl, by whom I have been shame∣fully
taken-in.”</P>
<P><PB N="78" REF="78"/>
A conversation ensued, in the course of
which Harry related the anecdote of the
supper, without subtracting the minutest
circumstance.</P>
<P>He finished his narrative by informing
her ladyship, that though he had no doubt
of Miss Villiers's having been kept by Lord
Melvile, yet he was inclined to believe the
affair was entirely over, and that his lord∣ship
had very prudently left her to make her
reflections on an adventure with which he
had had so much reason to be displeased.</P>
<P>He added, that he apprehended his lord∣ship
was jealous of the strange gentleman,
and very probably not without reason.</P>
<P>Just as Harry concluded his very accu∣rate
string of observations, Lady Blast was
announced.</P>
<P><PB N="79" REF="79"/>
She came to demand a categorical answer
to her letter containing Miss Villiers's sen∣tence,
and could not have arrived in a more
fortunate moment.</P>
<P>Lady Hardy ordered Harry to stay: the
history of our unfortunate heroine was re∣commenced,
with which Lady Blast was so
infinitely delighted, that she agreed to take
Harry, who she observed appeared to be a
very intelligent, honest, pretty, young fellow,
into her service, as soon as he could get his
<HI>congé;</HI> and to give him one third more
wages than he had agreed for with Miss
Villiers.</P>
<P>After a short consultation it was settled,
that Harry should return, and say he had
not found Lady Hardy at home.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="80" REF="80"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. III.</HEAD>
<P>THE long absence of the servant left
Miss Villiers without a doubt of
having succeeded in her application to her
<HI>friend.</HI></P>
<P>Harry at length appeared, and informed
her, that Lady Hardy was abroad, and was
not expected home till midnight.</P>
<P>Though her confidence in her <HI>friend</HI> was
not abated, yet her disappointment at this
information was extreme.</P>
<P>She asked Harry peevishly why, if Lady
Hardy was out, he had made so long a stay;
he made an impertinent answer; she told
him, with a haughty air, he was from that
moment discharged her service; he re∣turned
the reply valiant, “That he did
<PB N="81" REF="81"/>
not care how soon:” the bell was rung
for John, who was ordered to pay him the
little wages due, and to discharge him.</P>
<P>This extraordinary scene did not add to
the civility of the French milliner.</P>
<P>She renewed her solicitation in pretty
lively terms, and Miss Villiers was reduced
to the mortifying necessity of desiring her to
call for her money the next morning; to
which, with a good deal of murmuring, she
consented.</P>
<P>The next morning? And how was the
next morning to furnish her with the means
of keeping this indiscreet promise?</P>
<P>Lady Hardy—a thousand things might
happen—What thousand? Her uncle—but
could she procure it from her uncle the next
morning? Besides, whoever is acquainted
with the human heart, and remembers how
<PB N="82" REF="82"/>
she wrung from him his reluctant consent to
this journey, will know her uncle would be
indeed her last resource.</P>
<P>She was however convinced she should
get the money in time, though it was im∣possible
to divine how.</P>
<P>A thought started; this rout—she had
still twenty pounds remaining; she owed the
milliner fifty; thirty was not much to win—she
was determined to try—</P>
<P>This was a <HI>possible</HI> resource; she desired
no more; her sanguine temper elevated it
to a <HI>certain</HI> one.</P>
<P>She might even gain a much larger sum:
she might be enabled to pay all she owed:
she had seen people win a vast deal more at
guinea quadrille, at which she determined
to engage.</P>
<P><PB N="83" REF="83"/>
She drest, and went to Mrs. Harwood's
assembly.</P>
<P>The lady of the house, prepossessed by
the malevolent misrepresentations of Lady
Hardy and Lady Blast, the former of whom
had just been apologizing for having ever
introduced <HI>this little adventurer</HI> (so she
stiled her), to her acquaintance, received
her with a cold constrained civility, which
a mind less ardent than hers would have
seen in a moment.</P>
<P>Warm, unsuspecting, a little vain, and
justly conscious of having a right to those
unmeaning, yet agreeable, attentions which
constitute the bond of mixed society, she
had not an idea of their being omitted in
her regard; the omission therefore must
have been glaring indeed, if she had ob∣served
it.</P>
<P><PB N="84" REF="84"/>
Nor was Mrs. Harwood, who was a
woman of great good-nature, capable of
shocking any person who was her guest;
and, though she determined, in what she
supposed justice to herself, never to give
Miss Villiers another invitation, yet she hu∣manely
resolved to drop her acquaintance
in the quietest and most imperceptible man∣ner
possible.</P>
<P>As Maria passed through the apartments,
she saw several ladies at whose houses she
had visited with Lady Hardy; one or two
half returned her curtsy; but the greater
part looked full in her face, without be∣traying
the smallest consciousness of having
ever seen her before.</P>
<P>She was astonished how to account for
this general want of memory in the ladies,
when, turning her head, she observed Lady
Hardy and Lady Blast in close consultation,
<PB N="85" REF="85"/>
in a part of the room which she could not
avoid passing by, in order to enter the
next.</P>
<P>Lady Hardy held a paper in her hand,
which she was reading in a low voice to
Lady Blast, and which seemed to afford infi∣nite
entertainment to this amiable pair.</P>
<P>On approaching them, Miss Villiers, to
her great astonishment, discovered the paper,
which had so much amused them, to be her
own letter to Lady Hardy, requesting her to
lend her an hundred pounds.</P>
<P>She now, for the first time, saw Lady
Hardy in the light she merited; and, trem∣bling
with surprize and resentment, was
going to express her sense of this infamous
treatment with the spirit it deserved, when
both ladies turned full upon her, burst into
a loud laugh, and, brushing rudely by her,
retired into the inner apartment.</P>
<P><PB N="86" REF="86"/>
This insolence, in which nothing but the
most abandoned effrontery could have sup∣ported
them, was more than the lovely
victim of their malevolence could bear.</P>
<P>She had, however, the courage to re∣press
the almost starting tear, to struggle
with the rising passion which agitated her
whole frame, and to assume an appearance
of tranquillity which ill-suited the tumul∣tuous
emotions of her heart.</P>
<P>She felt the insult strongly, but she felt
it with dignity. She approached Mrs.
Harwood, and, with an air which was within
an atom of haughtiness, related the affront
she had received, and from whom.</P>
<P>She added, that she had entered Mrs.
Harwood's house, relying on that protection
from outrage which politeness and hospita∣lity
demanded, and to which both her birth
<PB N="87" REF="87"/>
and character gave her a right; that this
right had been violated by two persons
whose presence, after such behaviour, dis∣honoured
every circle in which they ap∣peared,
and that she must that moment
either give up her acquaintance or theirs.</P>
<P>Mrs. Harwood's heart was for our he∣roine;
but her fears enrolled her in the
contrary party.</P>
<P>She dreaded those envenomed tongues,
from which no innocence was secure; and
had the unpardonable weakness, instead of
supporting her own honour, which was
wounded by this shameful treatment of one
who, as her guest, had a right to her pro∣tection,
to tell Miss Villiers, though in the
softest terms possible, that she was mistress
of her own conduct, but not of hers.</P>
<P>Maria saw, and pitied, her pusillanimity;
and, without making any answer, retired
<PB N="88" REF="88"/>
with an air of majestic disdain, which almost
awed slander itself into silence.</P>
<P>She returned home, her heart swelling
with honest indignation.</P>
<P>She sat down; she reflected on the un∣merited
insult she had received, and on its
probable consequences; she saw her situa∣tion
in its true colours.</P>
<P>She had expended the money she brought
to town, she had incurred debts which she
knew not how to pay.</P>
<P>Even the wretched hope of relieving the
distress of the moment by play, a resource
equally infamous and uncertain, was at an
end.</P>
<P>She saw herself, she knew not why, driven
from the society in which she had lived
since her coming to town, and this in a
<PB N="89" REF="89"/>
manner the most humiliating that the
keenest malice could have contrived.</P>
<P>The French milliner, who had prest her
so rudely for money, was to call the next
morning.</P>
<P>She was unable to satisfy her; she had
every thing mortifying to expect from her
resentment on being disappointed.</P>
<P>She had to suffer, what was much worse,
the reproaches of her own heart, and the
painful consciousness of having broken her
word.</P>
<P>The tears, which she had hitherto re∣strained,
now forced their way, and gave
some relief to the agonizing sensations of
her soul.</P>
<P>The tide of blended passions, by degrees,
subsided; she saw the insult she had re∣ceived,
<PB N="90" REF="90"/>
and the persons who had offered it,
with the contempt they deserved.</P>
<P>Her pecuniary distress was of a more
alarming nature; but even there, if she
could gain a little time, she had still a va∣riety
of resources.</P>
<P>Her mind, recovering its natural tone,
became every moment more tranquil and
collected.</P>
<P>She ranged the whole expansive region
of indulgent fancy for subjects of consola∣tion;
nor did she range that expansive re∣gion
in vain.</P>
<P>The storm indeed was gathering round
her, but she saw it unappalled.</P>
<P>She had one of those happy warm imagi∣nations,
which through the impendent
<PB N="91" REF="91"/>
darkening cloud can pierce the gloom, and
discover the radiant blue sky behind.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. IV.</HEAD>
<P>MISS Villiers rose in the morning
with no little heart-ach at the re∣membrance
of her milliner's intended visit.</P>
<P>She had given her word to pay her; she
found it impossible to keep it.</P>
<P>She saw no immediate possibility of ful∣filling
her promise, except by borrowing
the money; but of whom?</P>
<P>Her <HI>friend,</HI> her only <HI>friend</HI> in town, had
not only refused, but cruelly insulted her
temporary distress.</P>
<P><PB N="92" REF="92"/>
She sat down to breakfast; the hour ap∣proached;
her terrors began to return.</P>
<P>A rap at the door made her start almost
from her seat.</P>
<P>Her heart sickened at the idea of seeing
this dreaded visitant.</P>
<P>John came up, and delivered her a letter,
which he told her was given him by a ser∣vant
who said it required no answer.</P>
<P>She took it, trembling with the appre∣hension
of other demands.</P>
<P>The writing of the superscription, and the
seal, were equally unknown to her.</P>
<P>There is no describing her surprize at
finding only a cover, without a single word,
enclosing a bank-note for 100<HI>l.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="93" REF="93"/>
Astonishment and joy rendered her mo∣tionless.</P>
<P>After a moment's pause, she fell on her
knees to thank the Omnipotent Disposer of
all for an event of which her feelings told
her her imprudence had rendered her un∣worthy.</P>
<P>She vowed, in the fervid ardour of her
gratitude, to merit, by her future conduct,
this apparent interposition of Providence in
her favour.</P>
<P>She resolved to dismiss her carriage, to
retrench her expence, to pay instantly every
demand she had incurred.</P>
<P>She almost resolved to return to the
happy roof she had so precipitately de∣serted.</P>
<P><PB N="94" REF="94"/>
She would have quite resolved it, had not
Lord Melvile's enchanting idea intervened.</P>
<P>It was, however, strange she had seen
nothing of him the two or three past days:
but a thousand causes unknown to her might
have prevented his calling.</P>
<P>His father might be returned, might fill
up all his time—She had every reason to
depend on the sincerity of his attachment.</P>
<P>But a truce to her reflections—Madame
Vipont came, was paid, and John dispatched
to discharge all her other bills.</P>
<P>This pleasing task compleated, she turned
her thoughts towards the unknown friend
who had been the instrument of heaven in
giving her this well-timed assistance—She
could not form a conjecture—</P>
<P><PB N="95" REF="95"/>
Was it not possible Lady Hardy might
have repented her unworthy behaviour, and
have sent the money?</P>
<P>It must be so—she knew so few persons—and
who else could have supposed she
wanted such assistance?</P>
<P>Yet, when she recollected the unfeeling
insolence of her behaviour, she found the
supposition impossible.</P>
<P>She was bewildering herself in vain, when
she received a card from Lord Claremont,
desiring to know at what hour that evening
he might have the pleasure of waiting on
her.</P>
<P>Lord Claremont!—Her joy was now
complete.</P>
<P><PB N="96" REF="96"/>
Every smiling vision of fancy returned.</P>
<P>The gloomy hour of adversity was past.</P>
<P>A brighter aera had commenced with this
happy dawn.</P>
<P>She was sorry Col. Dormer was not in
town.</P>
<P>Her resolutions of dismissing her carriage,
and retrenching her expence, were sus∣pended.</P>
<P>She sent for the frizeur, and prepared for
this important evening.</P>
<P>We will leave her for a moment to in∣dulge
her transports, and enquire what is
become of Lord Melvile.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="97" REF="97"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. V.</HEAD>
<P>ON returning home on Tuesday night
from his evening visit to Miss Villiers,
Lord Melvile was informed his father was
come to town, and had sent a message de∣siring
to see him, to breakfast, at ten the
next morning.</P>
<P>He had a strong inclination to have asked
the servant whether Mademoiselle Dorignon
was returned to town with Lord Claremont;
but he felt the weakness of being interested
in the question, and was ashamed to betray
that weakness even to his servant.</P>
<P>He knew she was not returned to Grosve∣nor-street;
the stillness of all around him
sufficiently announced her absence: he was
therefore not a little anxious to know how
she was disposed of.</P>
<P><PB N="98" REF="98"/>
He however suspended his curiosity till
the morning, when he attended Lord Clare∣mont
at the hour appointed.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VI.</HEAD>
<P>AFTER the breakfast was finished, and
the servants had retired, Lord Clare∣mont
entered on the intended subject of this
conference, the important business of Do∣rignon's
abdication.</P>
<P>“You cannot conceive, my dear Melvile,
how much I value myself on this nego∣tiation;
which, give me leave to say, re∣quired
fifty times more dexterity than a
treaty between two crowned heads.”</P>
<P>“Having first made Dorignon the confi∣dante
of your intended marriage, and con∣vinced
<PB N="99" REF="99"/>
her that she had nothing to expect
in future from your attachment, I car∣ried
my point, by flattering her with the
hope of marrying our West Indian.”</P>
<P>“This hope I am not clear she will not
be able to reduce to certainty; at least
if she steadily pursues the plan I have
taken the pains to trace out for her.”</P>
<P>“He is, you well know, just arrived
from one of the most uncivilized and bar∣barous
of our West India Islands, and
knows about as much of the world as a
country school-boy of thirteen.”</P>
<P>“I have regulated all Dorignon's future
measures by the exactest scales of sound
policy and knowledge of mankind.”</P>
<P>“These proposed measures are as much
calculated for her advantage as your
<PB N="100" REF="100"/>
safety, though the latter was undoubt∣edly
my first principle of action.”</P>
<P>“She is, by my intervention, secured in
a very liberal allowance from this young
man; and I have, unknown to him, pre∣sented
her, in your name, with three hun∣dred
guineas for her <HI>menus plaisirs.”</HI></P>
<P>“They are to go abroad immediately;
not to France, because there she is rather
too well known.”</P>
<P>“Not to Italy, because the Italian women
are as amusing, and ten thousand times
handsomer than herself.”</P>
<P>“But they are to make the tour of the
Northern courts, where the cards will be
almost played into her hands.”</P>
<P>“They set out for Vienna to-morrow;
and if the women there are not found
<PB N="101" REF="101"/>
sufficiently <HI>ennuieuse,</HI> she may possibly
proceed to St. Petersburg, in which case
I look on her business as done.”</P>
<P>“She desired to see you before she set
out; but on this request I thought it ne∣cessary
to put an absolute negative.”</P>
<P>“By the way, I am not very discreet in
mentioning this circumstance.”</P>
<P>(Lord Melvile sighed.)</P>
<P>“I see, Melvile, I was right in my pro∣hibition;
and, to prevent all possibility of
danger, I will not lose sight of you till
this happy pair have left London.”</P>
<P>“My chaise will be at the door in half
an hour, and it shall carry us to pay a
morning-visit to your intended bride, who
is about twenty miles from town, at her
father's villa in Surry.”</P>
<P><PB N="102" REF="102"/>
“Your lordship will, I am sure, give me
leave to dress.”</P>
<P>“By no means: we will only call <HI>en pas∣sant,</HI>
as if airing accidentally that way,
and make our visit of ceremony to-mor∣row.”</P>
<P>“Besides, give me leave to observe, that
your present <HI>deshabille</HI> is admirably fan∣cied,
and extremely becoming.”</P>
<P>“Without any compliment, my dear
Melvile, I know nobody who dresses so
uniformly well.”</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VII.</HEAD>
<P>THEY set out, and reached Mrs. Har∣ding's
villa about two.</P>
<P><PB N="103" REF="103"/>
The ladies, that is to say, Mrs. Harding,
and her daughter, the destined Lady Mel∣vile,
were in the dressing-room of the lat∣ter,
who was at her harpsichord when her
noble visitants arrived.</P>
<P>Lord Melvile entered the house with a
reluctance which he was scarce able to con∣ceal.</P>
<P>As he had heard nothing of his bride
from Lord Claremont, but that she was
rich, he had formed to himself an idea of
her the most unpleasing that can be con∣ceived.</P>
<P>His imagination had painted her in the
most disgusting colours; and he had only
reconciled himself to the marriage by con∣sidering
the absolute necessity of this step to
the emancipation of the family estate.</P>
<P><PB N="104" REF="104"/>
Full of the idea that the woman one mar∣ries
for money can have nothing but money
to recommend her, he had supposed her
ugly, awkward, foolish, ill-bred, ill-dressed,
uneducated; in short, a chemical compound
of every species of imperfection.</P>
<P>If she had possessed any uncommon ad∣vantages,
either personal or mental, Lord
Claremont would naturally have mentioned
(if he had not even exaggerated) these ad∣vantages.</P>
<P>Judge then of his astonishment at seeing,
in a <HI>deshabille</HI> as elegantly fancied as his
own, an extreme pretty little woman, per∣fectly
well made; a brunette, but of the
best style; unconstrained, <HI>degagée,</HI> with an
air of the world, and a manner as com∣pletely
French, as if she had never breathed
beneath any sky but that of Versailles.</P>
<P><PB N="105" REF="105"/>
She addressed him with the most perfect
ease, equally remote from English <HI>mauvaise
honte,</HI> and unweildy Asiatic self-importance.</P>
<P>Lord Melvile, from the information of
the harpsichord, thought it necessary to ask
her to sing, though he trembled at the idea
of her compliance.</P>
<P>Ten minutes sooner, his expectations
would have been circumscribed to,</P>
<Q>“Love's a gentle, generous passion:”</Q>
<P>They now rose as high as</P>
<Q>“Belle Iris.”</Q>
<P>But he was agreeably surprized with one
of Trajetta's most affecting airs, sung, in a
<HI>voce di camera</HI> indeed, but with a taste and
expression which would have satisfied the
master himself, had he been present.</P>
<P><PB N="106" REF="106"/>
The family pressed their noble visitants
to pass the remainder of the week at
Harding-Place; to which, having no objec∣tion
but what either of their valets de cham∣bre,
by going to town, could remove, they
willingly consented.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VIII.</HEAD>
<P>MISS Harding, who found her lover
extremely to her taste, laid herself
out to please, and she succeeded.</P>
<P>She was not long in discovering vanity to
be Lord Melvile's predominant passion, and
therefore on that side she made her attack.</P>
<P>She made this discovery with the greater
facility, as it was the side on which she was
herself most peculiarly vulnerable.</P>
<P><PB N="107" REF="107"/>
Without departing from what she owed
to herself, she behaved to him with that in∣sinuating,
yet almost imperceptible atten∣tion,
which supplies the place of every
other species of merit, where every other
species of merit is wanting.</P>
<P>This was however far from being the
case in the present instance.</P>
<P>She had, both from the gifts of nature
and those of education, an undoubted right
to please.</P>
<P>She had at least her share both of mental
and personal perfections.</P>
<P>She had an agreeable figure, an excellent
understanding, a thousand striking fashion∣able
accomplishments, and, above all, had
sacrificed largely to the Graces.</P>
<P><PB N="108" REF="108"/>
But the resistless enchantment by which
she proposed to bind Lord Melvile in silken
fetters, was not the power of her own at∣tractions,
but the lively sense she should ap∣pear
to have of his.</P>
<P>For her success in this attack on the heart
of Lord Melvile, there were many very im∣portant
reasons to be given, which we will
particularize in the next Chapter.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="9" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. IX.</HEAD>
<P>SETTING aside the <HI>agremens</HI> of his
intended bride, she could not have
found a more favourable interval in which
to seduce his inclinations.</P>
<P><PB N="109" REF="109"/>
He had lost Dorignon, and was piqued
at the equivocal conduct and supposed du∣plicity
of the lovely Maria.</P>
<P>Miss Harding had besides every external
advantage over her rivals which her father's
almost princely fortune could bestow.</P>
<P>It was not a French opera-girl, a woman
of abandoned character, supported by his
infatuation; it was not a little unknown ad∣venturer,
in a hired lodging, who now soli∣cited
his attention; but the heiress of im∣mense
wealth, whose attachment must there∣fore
necessarily be disinterested and sincere.</P>
<P>Her dress, her blaze of diamonds, her
apartment, her attendants, all spoke rather
an Asiatic queen than the daughter of an
English private gentleman.</P>
<P>The house was noble, and furnished with
all the splendour of Eastern magnificence.</P>
<P><PB N="110" REF="110"/>
The table was served in the most superb
style, and covered with every costly delicacy
of every land, and almost of every season;
with a profusion of blended French and
Oriental luxury.</P>
<P>Excellent music, amusing company, dan∣cing,
high play, the latter of which Lord
Melvile passionately loved, made the hours
pass away on rapid pinions.</P>
<P>But amongst all Miss Harding's auxilia∣ries
in her conquest of Lord Melvile, none
was more powerful in its effects than sur∣prize.</P>
<P>Lord Claremont, who knew the effect of
a <HI>coup de main,</HI> had intentionally bounded
his praises to the myriads Miss Harding was
to bring with her to her husband, without
hinting at her possessing one single attrac∣tive
quality besides.</P>
<P><PB N="111" REF="111"/>
The event justified this precaution.</P>
<P>Had Lord Melvile been told she was a
pretty woman, very accomplished, and that
she sung like an angel, he would have
found her a pretty woman, very accom∣plished,
and who sung like an angel; but
no more.</P>
<P>Contrasted with the unpleasing idea he
had formed of her in consequence of his fa∣ther's
affected silence on the subject, she
appeared to him almost a divinity.</P>
<P>His imagination was dazzled; he forgot
Miss Villiers, or remembered her only to
feel himself embarrassed by the recollection.</P>
<P>In short, this star of the East had, ere
four days had fully elapsed, by flattering
his self-love, and leading him through a
round of the most animated amusements,
<PB N="112" REF="112"/>
convinced him of the absurdity of his pro∣jected
arrangement with Miss Villiers, and
determined him to put a stop to the treaty.</P>
<P>“Why keep, and at a heavy expence, a
mistress who threatened, from her tiresome
affectation of sentiment, to be as <HI>ennuieuse</HI>
as a wife; when a wife was happily selected
for him by a father he wished to oblige,
who, besides bringing great riches into the
family, promised, from her talents and <HI>en∣joûement,</HI>
to be as amusing as a mistress?”</P>
<P>“Many a man of fashion had married the
woman he had kept: why not strike out
a different path, and keep the woman one
marries?”</P>
<P>“Keep one's wife! It would be droll—but
it would be new—And is there a
charm in human life equal to novelty?”</P>
<P><PB N="113" REF="113"/>
Thus reasoned Lord Melvile, as he was
dressing on Saturday morning.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="10" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. X.</HEAD>
<P>HE communicated this idea to Lord
Claremont, who came into the room
just as the arduous business of the toilet was
finished, and was beyond measure pleased
with a plan which promised many family
advantages.</P>
<P>Lord Melvile proceeded to inform his
indulgent parent of his situation in respect
to Miss Villiers, and of the offers he was
proceeding to make her, when the extraor∣dinary
adventure of the stranger threw a
damp on his beginning attachment.</P>
<P><PB N="114" REF="114"/>
He desired his lordship's opinion and as∣sistance
in respect to this lady, for whom he
now felt not the least shadow of inclination,
but who would have reason to think him a
man without the least sense of honour or of
gallantry, if he did not come to an explana∣tion
on a treaty which was in so advanced a
state.</P>
<P>Lord Claremont kindly undertook the
task of seeing our heroine, and of putting
an absolute period to this languid and un∣meaning
negotiation.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="11" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. XI.</HEAD>
<P>AFTER a consultation in what man∣ner
to conduct this delicate affair,
without wounding either humanity or <HI>bien∣seance,</HI>
<PB N="115" REF="115"/>
it was settled that Lord Melvile
should continue a few days longer at Har∣ding-Place,
where a masquerade was fixed
for the following Monday; and that Lord
Claremont should go immediately to town,
pay Miss Villiers a visit, and employ all his
knowledge of the human heart, as well to
discover her true character, as to lead her
gently to the point of breaking off this idle
connexion.</P>
<P>Lord Melvile begged his father to soften
the blow, as well by some act of generosity
like that he had shown to Dorignon, as by
every soothing art in the power of man to
employ.</P>
<P>He intreated his lordship to be particu∣larly
careful to avoid wounding the feelings
of her heart, if he found reason to think
her affection for him real.</P>
<P>Lord Claremont smiled rather sarcasti∣cally
at his son's apprehensions on this head,
<PB N="116" REF="116"/>
and ordered his carriage to be at the door
as soon as dinner should be ended.</P>
<P>He set off, pretending business of impor∣tance,
got to town in the evening without
being robbed, and in the morning sent the
card we have already recited to Miss Vil∣liers.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="12" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. XII.</HEAD>
<P>WE should have observed in the last
Chapter, that Lord Melvile, in the
course of his narration, had mentioned,
though very slightly, Sir Charles Watson's
admiration of our heroine, from which a ray
of light had darted on the mind of Lord
Claremont, who was too proud of his suc∣cess
in respect to Dorignon, to think any
design above the extent of his genius.</P>
<P><PB N="117" REF="117"/>
The idea of disposing advantageously of
two ladies who had composed a temporary
part of his family, was the most flattering
possible to Lord Claremont; and as he en∣tertained
not the least doubt that Lord Mel∣vile's
connexion with Miss Villiers had been
of the same intimate kind as that with Do∣rignon
(though Lord Melvile had assured
him of the contrary), he resolved on seeing
her Lady Watson, and in the mean time on
supporting her in the situation, whatever
that should be, in which his son, as he sup∣posed,
had already placed her.</P>
<P>As he had heard the story very imper∣fectly,
and under the disadvantage of conti∣nual
interruptions from the officious atten∣tion
of Mr. Harding, these conjectures
were very natural.</P>
<P>Under the full impression of these con∣jectures,
he prepared for his visit, and regu∣lated
his plan accordingly.</P>
<P><PB REF="118"/>
THE EXCURSION.</P>
<P>BOOK VII.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="7" TYPE="book">
<PB N="121" REF="119"/>
<HEAD>THE EXCURSION.</HEAD>
<HEAD>BOOK VII.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. I.</HEAD>
<P>MISS Villiers expected Lord Clare∣mont's
visit with an impatience which
will easily be imagined; but an impatience
mixed with the most alarming apprehen∣sions.</P>
<P><PB N="122" REF="120"/>
He might not see her with the same eyes
as his son; he might, on finding the dispro∣portion
of fortune so very great, think the
attachment imprudent, and insist on a sacri∣fice,
which, however painful to love, filial
duty might render indispensable.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. II.</HEAD>
<P>AT eight, on Sunday evening, Febru∣ary
the twenty-sixth (the reader must
have been very inattentive if he has not ob∣served
the precision of our chronology, a
point on which we pique ourselves as much
as Virgil on the geography of his immortal
poem), Lord Claremont entered Miss Vil∣liers's
apartment, and by the easy politeness
of his address, for he was one of the best∣bred
men in the world, dispelled in five mi∣nutes
<PB N="123" REF="121"/>
all the apprehensions to which she had
given way before his appearance.</P>
<P>His lordship was not only one of the best∣bred,
but one of the handsomest men in
town; and though considerably past fifty,
might have passed for about thirty-eight.</P>
<P>He had beyond most men, the happy art
of rendering himself agreeable to others,
by putting them in good humour with them∣selves.</P>
<P>He practised this art with so much suc∣cess
in his first half hour's conversation with
Miss Villiers, that she found herself inclined
to have as implicit a confidence in him, as
she could have had in Col. Dormer had he
been present.</P>
<P>When, by a series of the most delicate
and well-directed flattery, he had brought
her mind to the very state he wished, he
<PB N="124" REF="122"/>
proceeded to communicate, but by the gen∣tlest
gradations, the motives of his visit, and
his ideas in respect to her future conduct.</P>
<P>“Will you, madam, pardon the liberty
I take, when I tell you, you are the most
lovely woman I ever beheld?”</P>
<P>“You have every thing to expect from
such a profusion of charms, but you do
not appear to know the use of them; and
want a friend to conduct you through the
devious path of life.”</P>
<P>“In me behold that friend; command
my utmost services, and open your whole
heart to me without reserve.”</P>
<P>“Depend on my cares to place you in
the situation to which your beauty gives
you the best possible right to pretend;
but first tell me, with that amiable since∣rity
which is so visibly painted on your
<PB N="125" REF="123"/>
countenance, what is really the nature of
your present connexion with Lord Mel∣vile.”</P>
<P>The vivid crimson on the cheek of Maria,
who was equally charmed and embarrassed
by a conversation which seemed to lead to
all she wished; and the faltering of her
voice when she attempted, but in vain, to
make a reply, confirmed his lordship beyond
the possibility of a doubt in his very proba∣ble
conjecture in respect to their present in∣tercourse.</P>
<P>He therefore proceeded on that supposi∣tion,
and, willing to spare her confusion,
continued his harangue without waiting for
an answer.</P>
<P>After telling her he was sorry so tender
an intercourse should be so soon interrupted,
he informed her, that his son's intention had
been to have made a settlement on her for
<PB N="126" REF="124"/>
life, and to have continued her the mistress
of his heart, though family considerations
obliged him to give his hand to another.</P>
<P>He begged her to be assured of the sin∣cerity
of Lord Melvile's attachment, and of
the extreme difficulty he had found in con∣vincing
him of the imprudence of the step
into which his passion for her had almost
seduced him.</P>
<P>He added, that as Lord Melvile's mar∣riage
with Miss Harding, which was to take
place in a few days, would render the con∣tinuance
of their connexion highly impro∣per,
it was become absolutely necessary to
put an end to it, whatever regret such a sa∣crifice
might cause Lord Melvile.</P>
<P>That, thus circumstanced, and compelled
by the arguments of an indulgent father, to
relinquish the plan of life he had promised
himself such happiness in pursuing, Lord
<PB N="127" REF="125"/>
Melvile had employed himself, as the per∣son
dearest to him, to convey to her his
most passionate adieux, and to assure her
that no time should ever obliterate the re∣membrance
of her past condescension.</P>
<P>He stopped a moment, but observing she
seemed unable to reply, and imagining the
assiduity of a new lover the most effectual
consolation for the neglect of an old one, he
proceeded to inform her of the conquest she
had made of Sir Charles Watson.</P>
<P>He assured her, as his opinion, that this
young man, who knew much less of the
world than Lord Melvile, might even be
brought in time, if she played her cards
well, to change the rosy fetters of illicit
Love, for the more durable and more re∣spectable
ones of Hymen.</P>
<P>“I will to-morrow,” said his lordship,
give a supper, of which you shall be the
<PB N="128" REF="126"/>
heroine, and invite Sir Charles to be of
the party.”</P>
<P>“In the mean time,” added he, taking
out a pocket-book, and offering her a bank-note,
“Lord Melvile entreats you, madam,
as a grateful acknowledgement of that
amiable partiality he must for the future
unwillingly decline, to accept this note
for five hundred pounds, with which I
have the honour to present you in his
name.”</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. III.</HEAD>
<P>FROM the commencement of Lord
Claremont's harangue to the moment
of its very unexpected conclusion, Miss Vil∣liers
had kept the profoundest silence.</P>
<P><PB N="129" REF="127"/>
Deceived by its beginning, pleasure had
embarrassed her the first ten minutes; asto∣nishment
had next taken its turn, and had
been succeeded by a degree of indignation
which had almost suspended all her mental
faculties.</P>
<P>Her excess of resentment and surprize,
from the instant when Lord Claremont
mentioned his son's intended marriage, had
rendered her incapable of expressing what
she felt at a discourse so very humiliating.</P>
<P>Petrified by the disappointment of all her
dearest hopes, this offer, so alarming to her
pride, and so totally destructive of every idea
that Lord Melvile loved her with honour,
first arroused her to a perfect sense of her
situation.</P>
<P>Though wounded to the soul, and torn
by contending passions, she had the fortitude
<PB N="130" REF="128"/>
to command all the tumultuous feelings of
her breast.</P>
<P>Her mind, supported by its own native
consciousness of worth, rose in proportion
to the insult received.</P>
<P>She had acquired one very important ad∣vantage
from this extraordinary conversa∣tion,
and she felt it the moment her powers
of reasoning returned, the advantage of
being clearly informed as to the nature of
Lord Melvile's designs.</P>
<P>She could now be no longer the pre∣sumptuous
dupe of her own easy credulity,
or of Lord Melvile's equivocal addresses.</P>
<P>Lord Claremont's degrading offer, like
the sudden rush of the tempestuous North
wind, had dissipated the too flattering fa∣brick
of hope, the air-built fabrick raised by
delusive imagination.</P>
<P><PB N="131" REF="129"/>
Adieu! the pleasing vision of expecta∣tion!
Adieu! fortune! distinction! title!</P>
<P>Adieu! what she valued infinitely more,
the tender union of consenting hearts, of
those hearts she had fondly fancied made
for each other!</P>
<P>She had the mortification to find, this
<HI>most amiable of men,</HI> this <HI>all-accomplished</HI>
Lord Melvile; this Lord Melvile, whose
soul was <HI>an entanation of the divinity,</HI> a per∣fect
resemblance of the <HI>first good, first per∣fect,</HI>
and <HI>first fair,</HI> had never regarded her
in any more honourable light than that of
a kept-mistress.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="132" REF="130"/>
<HEAD>CHAP IV.</HEAD>
<P>TO Lord Claremont's offer of the bank-note
Miss Villiers had made no other
answer than a repulsive, and not less grace∣ful,
wave of her hand, and a smile of inef∣fable
disdain; but that smile expressed more
strongly than language could have done the
laudable resentment which filled her whole
soul.</P>
<P>Prepossessed as Lord Claremont was with
the idea of her dishonourable connexion
with his son, he was yet awed by the air
of dignity which she assumed.</P>
<P>He hesitated, and was at a loss in what
manner to proceed, when, having recol∣lected
herself, she addressed him in the fol∣lowing
terms:</P>
<P>“I am too sincere, my lord, to dissemble;
nor would dissimulation avail with a man
<PB N="133" REF="131"/>
of your lordship's discernment and know∣ledge
of the world.”</P>
<P>“Your lordship has awakened me from
a pleasing dream to a lively sense of my
own childish infatuation.”</P>
<P>“Both Lord Melvile and myself have
been mistaken: I, in imagining him a
man of honour; he, in supposing me a
woman devoted to infamy.”</P>
<P>“I am above disguise, my lord; I will
not deny that I have loved Lord Melvile;
or rather, that I have loved the beautiful
idol of my own creation, the ideal, the
all-perfect Lord Melvile, who no longer
exists but in the traces of my deluded
imagination.”</P>
<P>“I am punished; my self-love perhaps
merited this punishment, therefore I sub∣mit
<PB N="134" REF="132"/>
to it without complaining, and am
thankful I am undeceived so soon.”</P>
<P>“I would say something in my own vin∣dication.
I am incoherent, my lord, but
it is perhaps impossible to be otherwise at
this moment.”</P>
<P>“I do not condemn Lord Melvile; every
man has his own characteristic way of
thinking.”</P>
<P>“I am unknown to you, my lord, which
is your only excuse for what I have just
heard; but from this moment learn to
respect a woman whose family is not in∣ferior
to your own, whose virtues do not
disgrace her birth, and whose error in
this instance has been owing only to her
youth, her inexperience of the depravity
of mankind, her frank her open unsus∣pecting
temper, her too great esteem of
Lord Melvile; and, in some degree, per∣haps,
<PB N="135" REF="133"/>
to a vanity which is pardonable at
her season of life.”</P>
<P>“Perhaps I am, however, still more cul∣pable,
perhaps Lord Melvile's rank was
one of his attractions; perhaps my heart,
filled as it was with tenderness for an ob∣ject
which appeared to me most amiable,
yet adverted in some degree to those ex∣ternal
advantages which ought to have
been below my attention, and that I
looked forward with too much pleasure
to a situation to which my fortune gave
me less right to aspire in this age of un∣exampled
venality, than those who are in
every other respect infinitely below me.”</P>
<P>“I know not the lady whom your lord∣ship
has mentioned as the intended bride
of Lord Melvile; but perhaps fortune is
the only advantage she has over the de∣scendant,
and that not very remote, of
one of the noblest houses in the king∣dom.”</P>
<P><PB N="136" REF="134"/>
“Do not mistake these tears, my lord;
they are not those of weakness, but of
generous indignation.”</P>
<P>“Your lordship must necessarily observe
the present agitation of my mind, and the
painful effort I make to behave as be∣comes
me; and therefore have, I am con∣vinced,
too much politeness to prolong a
visit which cannot but be extremely em∣barrassing
to us both.”</P>
<P>Lord Claremont regarded her with a
mixture of surprize and admiration.</P>
<P>Ill as he thought of human-kind, he
almost believed her a woman of honour.</P>
<P>At all events, however, he could not
deny her the praise of being at least a
woman of spirit.</P>
<P><PB N="137" REF="135"/>
He could not determine whether she
played a part or not; but if she did, he al∣lowed
her the merit of playing it admi∣rably.</P>
<P>He felt, as strongly as Miss Villiers, the
propriety of shortening the visit; and, after
attempting an apology, which he had better
have let alone, as it only served to encrease
their mutual embarrassment, he retired, and
left our unfortunate heroine to her reflec∣tions.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. V.</HEAD>
<P>TO her reflections? Alas! what reflec∣tions?</P>
<P>She threw herself, exhausted, and almost
breathless, into a chair; the tears trickled
<PB N="138" REF="136"/>
down her face, which she covered with both
her hands, as if ashamed of her weakness,
though without spectators.</P>
<P>Not the injured royal Constance felt more
strongly the Dauphin's perfidious alliance—</P>
<LG>
<L>“Gone to be married? gone to swear a truce?”</L>
</LG>
<P>Impossible! Lord Claremont had de∣ceived
her, in order to break off the attach∣ment.</P>
<P>These arts were common amongst avari∣cious
fathers.</P>
<P>She had read of them in an hundred
novels, and at least half a dozen true his∣tories.</P>
<P>How should she know whether her con∣jecture
was founded in truth?</P>
<P><PB N="139" REF="137"/>
She owed it to Lord Melvile, as well as
herself, to come to an eclaircissement.</P>
<P>Suppose she should write to him!</P>
<P>Write to a man who had treated her with
such indignity?</P>
<P>But how was she certain it was Lord Mel∣vile
from whom she had received this indig∣nity?</P>
<P>If her suspicions were true, he was not
only innocent, but equally injured with her∣self.</P>
<P>They must be true; Lord Melvile's soul
was the genuine seat of honour.</P>
<P>She sat down—she began—she burnt the
letter—she wrote a second—she threw away
<PB N="140" REF="138"/>
the pen—all her resentment revived at the
remembrance of Lord Claremont's last in∣sult.</P>
<P>After a moment's reflection she deter∣mined,
at all events, to write; justice to
Lord Melvile made this step an absolute
duty.</P>
<P>The most abandoned criminal had a right
to be heard.</P>
<P>She, however, thought it prudent to defer
the execution of this design till her mind
should be a little less agitated.</P>
<P>The succession of her ideas was astonish∣ingly
rapid.</P>
<P>She considered the whole transaction in
every point of view; and every moment felt
more strongly the impossibility of Lord Mel∣vile's
<PB N="141" REF="139"/>
being a party in the indelicate beha∣viour
of his father.</P>
<P>From thinking it <HI>possible</HI> Lord Melvile
might still be the amiable being she had
ever believed him, she proceeded to sup∣pose
it <HI>probable;</HI> from thence the transition
to its being <HI>certain</HI> was amazingly easy.</P>
<P>Behold the naturally progressive action of
a sanguine temper!</P>
<P>Her mind became, by degrees, more
calm.</P>
<P>A ray of hope darted across the <HI>palpable
obscure</HI> of the preceding half hour.</P>
<P>Lord Melvile's idea once more presented
itself in all its charms: she saw the smile of
truth and candour on his lips.</P>
<P><PB N="142" REF="140"/>
We will leave her to renew her acquaint∣ance
with the gay phantom which had already
missed her, and do ourselves the honour to
pay a visit to Lady Blast.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VI.</HEAD>
<P>THIS most dove-like of all possible
dowagers had taken Harry into her
service the moment he quitted that of Miss
Villiers.</P>
<P>Amongst her other perfections, Lady
Blast was a pretty good scribbler, and had
more than once enriched the—Maga∣zine
with little anecdotes of her most inti∣mate
female friends; anecdotes which
wanted no recommendation except the very
useless one of being true.</P>
<P><PB N="143" REF="141"/>
She had interrogated Harry with the pre∣cision
of an inquisitor; and had discovered
enough to form an admirable <HI>tete à tete</HI> his∣tory
of Lord M-lv-le and Miss V-ll-rs.</P>
<P>Harry had accidentally mentioned Mrs.
Merrick's affectionate attachment to our he∣roine,
and that she had sometimes called her
by the tender appellation of <HI>the dear child.</HI></P>
<P><HI>The</HI> dear child, must undoubtedly have
been Harry's mistake; she must, to a cer∣tainty,
have said, <HI>my</HI> dear child.</P>
<P>Yes, <HI>the</HI> must have been an interpola∣tion
of Harry's: nothing was so easy as such
a mistake.</P>
<P>The genuine original text must, undoubt∣edly,
have been <HI>my.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="144" REF="142"/>
The meaning of this very endearing ex∣pression
was obvious; Mrs. Merrick was,
to an absolute certainty, her mother.</P>
<P>This discovery was happy; the brilliant
invention of Lady Blast supplied the rest.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VII.</HEAD>
<P>HER ladyship's manuscript, replete
with gall, in its journey from her li∣brary
to the press, had fallen into the hands
of the compositor to a scandalous magazine,
who, besides his being a man of so much
feeling as to detest his present employment
(an employment by which, however, he
supported a wife and seven children), was
a particular friend of Mrs. Merrick's bro∣ther,
had often visited Mrs. Merrick, and
<PB N="145" REF="143"/>
had more than once seen our heroine as she
passed the door of Mrs. Merrick's sitting
parlour to her carriage.</P>
<P>The names of Mrs. M-rr-ck and Miss
V-ll-rs had struck him on his beginning to
see the press.</P>
<P>As he proceeded, he found the scene of
this infamous romance to be Berners-street.</P>
<P>The similarity of names and places was
too great to be accidental.</P>
<P>His heart now became interested; he
left his work unfinished, put the manuscript
into his pocket, and hastened to find his
friend.</P>
<P>A moment's digression if you please, gen∣tle
reader, on the present fashionable ma∣nufacture
of printed calumny.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="146" REF="144"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. VIII.</HEAD>
<P>AMONGST the evils of the present
hour, there is not one which more
loudly demands redress, or which is more
difficult to be redrest, than the licentious
malignity of that press, the liberty of which
is at once the glory and the strength of our
constitution.</P>
<P>Beauty, youth, genius, all which can dis∣tinguish
one human being from another,
are the destined mark, the helpless prey, of
the literary slanderer.</P>
<P>He counteracts the bounty of the benig∣nant
Creator, and turns the choicest bles∣sings
of heaven into curses.</P>
<P>His venal pen, tempted by a gain more
shameful than that which pays the midnight
robber, sacrifices the peace of families,
<PB N="147" REF="145"/>
the honour, the tranquillity, nay sometimes
the lives, of the most virtuous individuals,
on the merciless altar of Envy.</P>
<P>Yes, indignant reader, you feel the atro∣city
of his crime: you justly execrate the
man who scatters arrows and death, and
says, “Is it not in sport?”</P>
<P>The murderer of reputation merits the
severest punishment which human laws,
framed for human happiness, can inflict.</P>
<P>He merits to be driven from society, the
sweets of which he tinges with the deadliest
poison; to be driven from human converse
to herd with congenial monsters, with the
merciless inhabitants of the howling wilder∣ness.</P>
<P>The just object of universal abhorrence,
what punishment does not his crime de∣serve!</P>
<P><PB N="148" REF="146"/>
The pangs of poverty, dishonour, exile—death,
if you please—I will not plead his
cause; death is perhaps too mild an expia∣tion
of his offence.</P>
<P>But let us pause a moment—You—What
do not you deserve?—You, who read his
unhallowed works with approbation?</P>
<P>You, who tempt his distress to forge the
savage tale?</P>
<P>You, who unsolicited by hard necessity,
his dreadful plea, cruelly wound the fame
of your unsuspecting neighbour, to gratify
a malignant temper, or the idle curiosity of
a moment?</P>
<P>Do you not—unfeeling as you are—by
encouraging such detestable publications,
wantonly plant yourself the envenomed dag∣ger
in the bosom of innocence?</P>
<P><PB N="149" REF="147"/>
It is in your power alone to restrain the
growing evil, to turn the envenomed dart
from the worthy breast.</P>
<P>Cease to read, and the evil dies of itself:
cease to purchase, and the venal calumnia∣tor
will drop his useless pen.</P>
<P>Think, whilst the cruel smile yet mantles
on your cheek, that your own heart may
be the next that is wrung by the malignant
tale.</P>
<P>The amiable friend of your choice—the
sister endeared to you by the tender ties of
blood—the blooming daughter you edu∣cated
with such anxious care—</P>
<P>Yourself—may be the next devoted
victim.</P>
<P><PB N="150" REF="148"/>
Reflect one moment, and you will exe∣crate
the barbarous pleasure you have felt
on reading these slanderous chronicles of
falsehood.</P>
<P>You wish to be amused; I pardon, I
commend your wish; but you may be
amused without wounding the better feel∣ings
of your soul.</P>
<P>Believe me, the human mind is curious,
not malignant.</P>
<P>It delights in well-painted pictures of life
and manners, but does not demand that they
shall be all drawn in shade.</P>
<P>The lovely form of virtue; of virtue,
crowned by prosperity, or nobly struggling
with the tide of adverse fortune, will amuse,
will interest, will charm, beyond the black∣est
<PB N="151" REF="149"/>
tints, wrought by the baleful hand of
the literary assassin.</P>
<P>But to our story, which has been perhaps
too long interrupted.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="9" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. IX.</HEAD>
<P>OUR compositor had a wife and seven
children, dependent on his labours for
bread.</P>
<P>His heart had always revolted against his
present employment, but there were rea∣sons
for continuing in it which had hitherto
stifled its generous murmurs.</P>
<P>We have said, he had a wife and seven
children dependent on him for bread.</P>
<P><PB N="152" REF="150"/>
He could not, perhaps, hope to be so
well paid for attending a press more wor∣thily
employed.</P>
<P>If he declined this illiberal engagement,
another, less scrupulous, would certainly
accept it.</P>
<P>He had not till this moment seen in full
light the pernicious tendency of this species
of publication.</P>
<P>The injury might, for aught he knew,
be, with the personages, merely ideal.</P>
<P>Lord H—and Lady M—were beings
in the moon, nor did he know that such
characters actually existed; they were as
much out of the circle of his knowledge as
if inhabitants of Japan.</P>
<P><PB N="153" REF="151"/>
This was the first instance of his knowing
that any of the parties traduced had real
existence.</P>
<P>From this moment he resolved to quit his
present employment.</P>
<P>His children should not, he determined,
eat the bread which was moistened by the
tears of calumniated virtue.</P>
<P>He gave notice to the person who em∣ployed
him, and whom he met accidentally
on the stairs, to provide himself with ano∣ther
compositor.</P>
<P>His heart grew lighter as he spoke.</P>
<P>The pleasurable swell of self-approbation
expanded his honest bosom.</P>
<P><PB N="154" REF="152"/>
The benevolent Father of all must cer∣tainly
(thus he reasoned) see with more than
indulgence a resolution founded on the
best feelings of the human heart.</P>
<P>To Providence therefore directing his in∣dustry,
he resolved to trust for his future
support.</P>
<P>To Providence we will leave him for a
moment, and return to Berners-street.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="10" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. X.</HEAD>
<P>WE left our heroine struggling, against
conviction, to believe Lord Mel∣vile
faithful to engagements which he had
never entertained the remotest idea of
forming.</P>
<P><PB N="155" REF="153"/>
Engagements, which, to do his lordship
justice, had their existence only in her cre∣dulity,
her pardonable vanity, her sanguine
temper, and absolute ignorance of the
world.</P>
<P>He had intended to <HI>seduce,</HI> but had no
design to <HI>deceive</HI> her.</P>
<P>On the contrary, he had offered her <HI>a
settlement</HI> in terms, which, being sufficiently
intelligible to himself, he concluded were
so to her.</P>
<P>She was, however, determined to be∣lieve,
and therefore did believe, his mar∣riage
a fiction invented by an interested fa∣ther,
and for interested ends.</P>
<P>This was not a very improbable conjec∣ture;
but it has been well observed by
<PB N="156" REF="154"/>
somebody, that probability is not always on
the side of truth.</P>
<P>She rose on Monday, after a sleepless
night, half resolved to write Lord Melvile
a narrative of his father's visit and conver∣sation,
and to demand an eclaircissement on
a point in which both his happiness and ho∣nour
were so deeply interested.</P>
<P>That quick sensibility to the <HI>beautiful,</HI>
the <HI>becoming,</HI> in the intercourse of life; that
spontaneous feeling of</P>
<LG>
<L>“A grace, a manner, a decorum,”</L>
</LG>
<P>in morals; to which women owe half their
virtue, alone prevented her taking so humi∣liating
a step.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="11" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="157" REF="155"/>
<HEAD>CHAP XI.</HEAD>
<P>THERE was another subject on which
it was necessary for her to think; an∣other
care which obtruded itself even
through all her anxiety in respect to Lord
Melvile; nay, which that very anxiety con∣tributed
greatly to heighten.</P>
<P>She had entered into a style of life not
to be supported at a trifling expence.</P>
<P>She had not five pounds in the world,
nor did she know where to get a supply.</P>
<P>She had tried her <HI>friend</HI> Lady Hardy,
and we have seen the mortifying result of
the experiment.</P>
<P>She had but one friend to whom it be∣came
her to apply, Col. Dormer, her re∣spectable
<PB N="158" REF="156"/>
uncle; and how should she assume
courage to tell him of her extravagance?</P>
<P>How acquaint him, that, a dupe to hope,
misled by the glittering of a meteor, she
had expended the revenue of years in little
more than a month's absence from Belfont?</P>
<P>Her literary hopes were at an end.</P>
<P>Alas! was not her every hope as ill
founded?</P>
<P>Lord Claremont's story, it was at least
<HI>possible,</HI> might be true.</P>
<P>She shuddered at taking a view of her
situation.</P>
<P>She could not expect another hundred
pounds to drop from the clouds: John had,
by her orders, paid it all away, though it
was Sunday when she received it.</P>
<P><PB N="159" REF="157"/>
By the way, to whom could she have
been thus obliged?</P>
<P>The doubt must have struck my reader,
as well as the lovely Maria.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="12" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. XII.</HEAD>
<P>AS we are not writing a fairy tale, but
the true history of a young lady in
Old England; a country where these little
benevolent beings have long left off their
delightful midnight gambols, and do not
even condescend to drop a sixpence in the
shoe of Marian; it may be necessary to ac∣count
for this very well-timed, though ano∣nymous,
act of friendship.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="13" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. XIII.</HEAD>
<PB N="160" REF="158"/>
<P>LADY Hardy and Lady Blast, whom we
left whispering in a corner, at Mrs.
Harwood's assembly, were tittering over our
heroine's letter to the former, requesting
her to lend her an hundred pounds till she
could receive a remittance from the coun∣try;
when Mr. Hammond, whose visit to
Mrs. Harwood that evening was meerly ac∣cidental,
happened to approach the bene∣volent
pair.</P>
<P>As he was nearly related to Lady Blast,
he took the liberty of asking the cause of
their exuberant mirth, when Lady Hardy
very politely gave him the letter to read.</P>
<P>Both the name and the writing were too
familiar to him to be mistaken.</P>
<P><PB N="161" REF="159"/>
He very composedly put the letter in his
pocket, and left the room without speaking
a syllable.</P>
<P>The ladies called after him, but to no
manner of purpose.</P>
<P>He crossed the street to Mrs. Merrick,
and received from her a very circumstantial
and very satisfactory account of the birth,
fortune, connexions, virtues, hopes, and ro∣mantic
expectations, of Miss Villiers; ex∣pectations
of which he knew the fallacy,
being perfectly acquainted with Lord
Claremont's negotiation with Mr. Harding.</P>
<P>After enjoining Mrs. Merrick secrecy on
the subject of this conversation, he retired
to his lodgings, took a bank note of an hun∣dred
pounds out of his bureau, sealed it up
in a blank cover; and, in the morning, sent
it to Miss Villiers by a servant on whom he
<PB N="162" REF="160"/>
could depend, in the manner we have
already recited.</P>
<P>But his philanthropy did not stop here.</P>
<P>He saw her on the borders of a preci∣pice,
and determined to withdraw her from
it, in spite of herself.</P>
<P>He saw the utmost delicacy must be pre∣served
in the attempt.</P>
<P>He was a poet, therefore his ideas were
rapid.</P>
<P>He formed his plan in a moment, and
ordered his chaise to the door, to put it in
execution.</P>
<P><PB REF="161"/>
THE EXCURSION.</P>
<P>BOOK VIII.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="8" TYPE="book">
<PB N="165" REF="162"/>
<HEAD>THE EXCURSION.</HEAD>
<HEAD>BOOK VIII.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. I.</HEAD>
<P>IF Mr. Hammond's wheels had been as
rapid as his ideas, he would have
reached Belfont (for thither he bent his
course) with the velocity of a spirit.</P>
<P><PB N="166" REF="163"/>
He arrived at this abode of tranquillity
about twelve on Monday morning, and
found Col. Dormer hanging with undissem∣bled
rapture over an expanding rose-bud in
his Lilliputian green-house.</P>
<P>Mr. Hammond could not have met with
a more favourable occasion of being elo∣quent,
and even poetical, than the present.</P>
<P>He knew all of which Lady Blast was
capable.</P>
<P>He had, by accident from a female friend,
heard all the slanderous effusions of the pair
of dowagers, in respect to our amiable heroine.</P>
<P>His fears for her reputation were much
stronger than those he felt in respect to her
fortune, though he thought both in the
most imminent danger.</P>
<P><PB N="167" REF="164"/>
He might have similized in the garden
for an hour, without going a step out of his
way.</P>
<P>He might have observed to Col. Dormer,
that, whilst his green-house engaged his at∣tention,
a fairer rose than any which bloomed
there, was menaced with a blight from the
empoisoned breath of Envy.</P>
<P>He might have said—</P>
<P>In short, he might have said a thousand
pretty things, if saying pretty things had
been the purpose of his journey.</P>
<P>This, however, not being the case, and
being determined not to enter abruptly on
the subject nearest his heart, the dangerous
situation of Miss Villiers, he for once went
out of his character, and made use of an in∣nocent
artifice to avoid alarming Col. Dor∣mer
too soon.</P>
<P><PB N="168" REF="165"/>
After having apologized politely for what
appeared an intrusion, he reminded Col.
Dormer, who had totally forgot him, of
their having been fellow students and friends
at Oxford; and, without entering on his
real motive for this visit, told him he could
not pass the door of an old acquaintance,
without stopping to enquire after his health.</P>
<P>He added, that he had an additional mo∣tive
for calling, which was, to tell him he
had seen his amiable niece, Miss Villiers, a
few days before, in town, and had left her
in good health and spirits.</P>
<P>There are no people so happy in meet∣ing
unexpectedly with their friends, and
especially the friends of their youth, as
those who, in advanced age, pass their time
retired in the country.</P>
<P>In this situation, the arrival, even of a
common visitant, is of consequence, as it re∣lieves
<PB N="169" REF="166"/>
the too regular uniformity of occupa∣tion,
which is the only drawback on the
tranquil delights of retirement.</P>
<P>The arrival of a <HI>friend,</HI> in such a situa∣tion,
is an event, a little aera, worthy of spe∣cial
note in the chronological table of se∣cluded
life.</P>
<P>Col. Dormer's garden was to him a source
of inconceivable pleasure—But—always the
garden!</P>
<P>Besides—more than half the real value of
every enjoyment depends on the social idea
of its being communicated.</P>
<P>There is no such thing as solitary happi∣ness.</P>
<P>The vernal family of Col. Dormer ac∣quired
new charms in his eyes in propor∣tion
as they became the admiration of
others.</P>
<P><PB N="170" REF="167"/>
Mr. Hammond was a new admirer, whose
praises enhanced the beauties of every
flowret which engaged his attention.</P>
<P>He was also a new companion to fill up
the void in the society of Belfont, occasioned
by the absence of Maria.</P>
<P>Louisa's conversation would have been
sufficient to Col. Dormer's happiness, had he
not been also habituated to that of her sister.</P>
<P>We feel severely the privation of every
pleasure to which we have been long accus∣tomed.</P>
<P>The lovely prattler!—</P>
<P>The creative eye of fancy presented her
tripping, with Louisa, delighted by his
side.</P>
<P><PB N="171" REF="168"/>
That lovely prattler!</P>
<P>With what impatience did he not expect
her return to Belfont!</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. II.</HEAD>
<P>AFTER a tour round the garden, a
particular visit to every favourite
daughter of the spring, and a little retro∣spective
chat on the subject of old college
adventures; Col. Dormer, having first ob∣tained
Mr. Hammond's promise of spend∣ing
a few days at Belfont, presented him to
the bright Louisa, who appeared to him
only less charming than her sister.</P>
<P>For that sister the good old man felt an
enthusiastic partiality, which, had he been
<PB N="172" REF="169"/>
younger, would have amounted to a pas∣sion.</P>
<P>He regarded Louisa with admiration;
she was, he acknowledged, lovely—But
Maria—</P>
<P>Louisa had the finest blue eyes in the
world, but he hated blue eyes.</P>
<P>Maria's were eyes indeed—eyes informed
by the radiant blaze of genius—</P>
<P>The vivid glow of her complexion—the
animated changes of her countenance as her
ideas varied—the enchantment of her
smile—</P>
<P>In short, he was ready to exclaim, in the
words of the Spectator,</P>
<LG>
<L>“Louisa is beautiful, but Maria, thou art
beauty!”</L>
</LG>
<PB N="173" REF="170"/>
<P>They passed a chearful evening, and re∣tired
early to bed, in favour of Mr. Ham∣mond's
fatigue.</P>
<P>He slept little during the first part of the
night; he revolved in his mind the circum∣stance
which occasioned his journey.</P>
<P>He found a thousand difficulties in respect
to the manner in which he should enter on
the subject of Miss Villiers's situation.</P>
<P>He might have said, with more propriety,
her <HI>indiscretion,</HI> but he would not even allow
that she was indiscreet.</P>
<P>He called her profusion the ebullition of
a noble mind; and found merit even in that
heedless inattention to forms which threat∣ened
such dreadful consequences.</P>
<P><PB N="174" REF="171"/>
He at last determined, as he intended stay∣ing
two or three days, to trust to the chap∣ter
of accidents, and only be on the watch
to find a favourable moment.</P>
<P>He could not, even in this short inter∣course,
have missed Col. Dormer's prevail∣ing
passion; and rightly judged that a mild
vernal shower, or the blowing of a new
auricula, might have the best effect possible
on the mind of his friend.</P>
<P>The morning being uncommonly fine, the
carriages were ordered to the door at eleven.</P>
<P>Col. Dormer proposed to give Mr. Ham∣mond
the pleasure of seeing Burghley, the
celebrated seat of the still more celebrated
statesman whose name it bears, from whence
Belfont was distant only a few miles.</P>
<P>To Burghley therefore they proceeded.</P>
<P><PB N="175" REF="172"/>
As a lover of the imitative arts, Mr. Ham∣mond
was charmed with seeing the noble
works of the divine masters with which this
magnificent seat is ornamented and en∣riched.</P>
<P>But he felt (as a patriot worthy of the
name) a much sublimer pleasure in calling
to remembrance the public virtues of the
great, the wise, the uncorrupt, minister,
who raised the glory of his country to its
utmost summit.</P>
<P>He regarded his portrait with reverential
delight.</P>
<P>He fancied he saw his venerable shade in
every apartment through which he was con∣ducted.</P>
<P>Our party returned to Belfont, but not
alone.</P>
<P><PB N="176" REF="173"/>
They met in the avenue, within a few
paces of the house, Mr. Montague, the ru∣ral
philosopher of whom we have spoken
before, as lord of the manor of Belfont.</P>
<P>He was coming on a visit to the benevo∣lent
master of this superb mansion, who was
however, at this time, absent in London.</P>
<P>His son, the object that had reconciled
Louisa to shades and solitude, and whom
our little family supposed to be attending
his studies at Cambridge, was with him.</P>
<P>They were both on horseback, and both
stopped on seeing Col. Dormer's carriage.</P>
<P>Mr. Montague the younger had been ill
of a fever at college, and had been sent
home (where he arrived the evening before)
for change of air, by his physicians.</P>
<P><PB N="177" REF="174"/>
His illness had left a paleness which only
rendered his countenance, if possible, more
interesting than ever.</P>
<P>Mr. Hammond was struck with a face so
full of expression, and was going to ask his
name, when he approached the chaise in
which the good old man was with the lovely
Louisa.</P>
<P>On seeing the object of her tenderest af∣fection
in a manner thus unhoped and unex∣pected,
the cheek of Louisa became suffused
with the liveliest crimson; her heart beat
thick, her voice faltered, and her repeated
attempts to speak terminated in broken and
inarticulate accents.</P>
<P>By a movement, not only involuntary,
but unknown at the time to herself, she,
with a trembling hand, let down the glass
of the carriage at Mr. Montague's ap∣proach.</P>
<P><PB N="178" REF="175"/>
He addressed her with an emotion which,
though perhaps favourable to his beauty,
was far from being so to his elocution.</P>
<P>The confusion, the agitation, the pleasure
visible in the countenances of both, were
too perceptible to escape Mr. Hammond's
observation.</P>
<P>Their looks were sufficiently intelligible
to stand in no need of an historian to inform
him of the situation of their hearts.</P>
<P>He now thought Louisa as handsome as
her sister.</P>
<P>She had lost that air of still-life which
had at first sight extremely displeased him.</P>
<P>Her blue eyes were become lovely by
being impassioned.</P>
<P><PB N="179" REF="176"/>
In short she appeared to him another
being; so much does beauty depend on
animation.</P>
<P>She was no longer a faultless statue, but
an enchanting woman; an object, not merely
of admiration, but of passion.</P>
<P>Mr. Montague left his son by the side of
Miss Villiers's chaise, and, giving his horse
to a servant, returned to Belfont in that of
Col. Dormer.</P>
<P>The party separated at Mr. Montague's
door, who invited himself, and his family,
consisting of this son, and a very amiable
daughter, to spend the afternoon at Col.
Dormer's.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="180" REF="177"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. III.</HEAD>
<P>WHEN we last set out for London,
we left Mr. Montague the younger
at Col. Dormer's gate, where he arrived in
the intention of explaining himself in the
clearest terms to Louisa on the subject of his
passion.</P>
<P>This resolution we have observed had
been a little precipitated by the report that
a man of great fortune had made proposals
to Col. Dormer for his niece; which report,
however, happened not to be true.</P>
<P>As minute details of conversation between
lovers are much more interesting to the par∣ties
concerned than to anybody else, we
shall wave particulars, and only say, that
Mr. Montague was not dissatisfied with the
interview; and that during the three weeks
<PB N="181" REF="178"/>
of his stay at Belfont, for he went to college
a week sooner than he intended, he had
brought her to promise never to marry any
other man, though she persisted in refusing
to enter into any positive engagement with
him, unless with his father's most perfect
approbation.</P>
<P>He went to Cambridge satisfied in some
degree with this promise, and determined
to write the state of his heart to his father.</P>
<P>He was, however, prevented by a fit of
illness, brought on by his fears that Mr.
Montague, indulgent as he was, would not
approve an alliance in which interest had so
little share.</P>
<P>He had forgot that this excellent father
was a philosopher in the most extensive sense
of the word; and that, setting his philoso∣phy
aside, his very prejudices would in this
instance be in his favour.</P>
<P><PB N="182" REF="179"/>
In short, he was not, though he ought to
have been, exempt from the baneful error
of young people, in supposing it possible
they can have any friend half as much in∣terested
in their happiness as a parent.</P>
<P>He wrote, however, to his sister, who had
always been the confidante of his passion,
and told her his determination to ask his
father's permission to marry Miss Villiers,
as soon as he should return to Belfont.</P>
<P>On hearing of his illness, alarmed for his
life, Miss Montague disclosed the secret to
her father, who had ordered his carriage to
be ready in the morning, in the intention
of going himself to fetch him from Cam∣bridge,
when he arrived in a post-chaise at
the door.</P>
<P>Mr. Montague, who thought happiness
the first object of every rational being, and
<PB N="183" REF="180"/>
knew it did not depend on wealth, was per∣fectly
satisfied with the choice his son had
made; but as marriage is a step there is no
retrieving, he was anxious to be clearly in∣formed
as to the inclinations of the young
lady, before he took any measure prepara∣tory
to a union, to which, supposing their
attachment mutual, he had not the shadow
of an objection.</P>
<P>The ride of this morning had, acciden∣tally,
saved him much trouble on this sub∣ject.</P>
<P>He had observed the countenance of Miss
Villiers, on his son's approach, with the
most scrutinizing eye, and had not a doubt
remaining.</P>
<P>In the full conviction that the future feli∣city
of both depended on their union, he
had taken his place in Col. Dormer's chaise,
and had asked his consent to present his son
<PB N="184" REF="181"/>
to Miss Villiers in the afternoon, as a can∣didate
for the honour of her hand.</P>
<P>There was but one point in which these
two excellent men had disagreed.</P>
<P>Col. Dormer was for deferring the mar∣riage
two or three years longer, and Mr.
Montague for concluding it immediately.</P>
<P>When the former had exhausted all his
arguments, which Mr. Montague heard
with more patience than he was accustomed
to show when contradicted, he made the fol∣lowing
reply:</P>
<P>“I cannot, my good friend, account for
your arguing so unphilosophically, on any
principle except that of your supposing a
little assumed reluctance becomes you, as
standing in the place of the young lady.”</P>
<P><PB N="185" REF="182"/>
“But let me entreat you to lay aside your
coyness for a moment, and talk like a rea∣sonable
being.”</P>
<P>“My son's happiness depends on his
being united with Miss Villiers; and let
me, with the pardonable pride of a pa∣rent,
add, that the qualities of his heart
promise that the happiness consequent on
this union will be reciprocal.”</P>
<P>“You and I, by keeping in the formal
beaten track, may postpone the aera of
their felicity a few years longer.”</P>
<P>“But reflect a moment, and answer me
one plain question; do you think it possi∣ble
to be happy too soon?”</P>
<P>“The poet justly complains, that”</P>
<LG>
<L>“Man never <HI>is,</HI> but always <HI>to be,</HI> blest.”</L>
</LG>
<PB N="186" REF="183"/>
<P>“I am afraid this is too generally our
own fault.”</P>
<P>“We are preparing for happiness when
we might be enjoying it.”</P>
<P>“Human life is too short, and too uncer∣tain,
to have its best hours wasted in ex∣pectation.”</P>
<P>“You talk of his staying at college till
he has taken a degree.”</P>
<P>“I have not the least objection to his
keeping the necessary residence till that
time, which is not very distant: but I see
no reason to delay his marriage on that
account, as he is not a candidate for a
fellowship.”</P>
<P>“As to foreign travel, I am in this re∣spect
a little singular; but I am not
<PB N="187" REF="184"/>
ashamed of being singularly in the
right.”</P>
<P>“I do not wish him to wear out his heart,
poison his principles, and ruin his consti∣tution,
by despicable connexions with
French opera girls, or Italian courtezans.”</P>
<P>“Still less do I wish him to run the effe∣minate
circle of <HI>frivolité</HI> and <HI>ton</HI> at Paris;
or to pore over rusty coins, and study
<HI>vertù</HI> at Rome.”</P>
<P>“A young antiquarian is every way a
soloecism.”</P>
<P>“If a young man must have pursuits, as
he certainly must, let them be the pur∣suits
of his season of life.”</P>
<P>“I can forgive even an irregular passion
for animated beauty; but the man who at
twenty-two,</P>
<P><PB N="188" REF="185"/>
Sighs for an Otho, and neglects his bride,”</P>
<P>“should be disinherited if a son of mine.”</P>
<P>“But to our business; I am the happiest
man on earth in the choice my son has
made; and in being convinced Miss Vil∣liers
honours him with her esteem.”</P>
<P>“The favour of such a woman might
make an emperor proud.”</P>
<P>“I have long hoped their childish affec∣tion
for each other would ripen into
love; and had I never observed their mu∣tual
tenderness before, their meeting just
now would have flashed conviction on my
mind.”</P>
<P>“Determined to guard my son against
the misery of selling himself to keep the
family estate together, I have always had
this moment in view.”</P>
<P><PB N="189" REF="186"/>
“My estate is three thousand pounds a
year, of which I have laid by half ever
since I was married; that I might become
rich enough to make my children happy
without retrenching my own expences.”</P>
<P>“I have purchased Charles a thousand
pounds a year, with a pretty house, about
fix miles off; and have ten thousand
pounds to give my daughter whenever
she chuses to marry; and all this without
lessening my paternal fortune a shilling?”</P>
<P>As Mr. Montague pronounced the last
sentence, the chaise stopped at his door.</P>
<P>Col. Dormer set him down, and entered
his own house with an air of satisfaction
which did not escape Louisa.</P>
<P>He was gay beyond his usual custom; his
eye spoke the most perfect content whenever
it met that of his amiable niece.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="190" REF="187"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. IV.</HEAD>
<P>MR. Hammond, who observed this
without absolutely knowing the
cause, could not find in his heart to damp
the joy of his friend by speaking to him on
so painful a subject as that of Maria's indis∣cretion.</P>
<P>A day or two had elapsed in visits to and
from the Montagues.</P>
<P>The most important articles of the mar∣riage
treaty were settled; Mr. Hammond
had arranged, in idea, his intended conver∣sation
with Col. Dormer, and was waiting the
latter's return from the manor-house, where
he was in consultation with Mr. Montague,
when he received, by the post, from Mrs.
Merrick, the malevolent history of Maria,
which had been brought to her by the honest
<PB N="191" REF="188"/>
compositor of whom we have spoken in the
last book.</P>
<P>Our heroine, in this infamous picture,
was drawn in the darkest colours that false∣hood
and envy in conjunction could furnish.</P>
<P>She was described, and with some ap∣pearance
of plausibility, as an adventurer,
and of the most abandoned kind.</P>
<P>As the illegitimate daughter of Mrs.
Merrick, by a certain foreign dancer, whom
we are authorized to say Mrs. Merrick
never beheld.</P>
<P>As having received from this ideal father
an education which distinguished her from
her equals, and a degree of art and address
which enabled her to undertake, and to sup∣port,
the difficult <HI>rôle</HI> of a woman of birth
and condition.</P>
<P><PB N="192" REF="189"/>
As having been educated by her supposed
parents expressly for the purposes of pros∣titution.</P>
<P>As having been sold at seventeen to Mr.
Hammond, who had taken an apartment at
Mrs. Merrick's for that very purpose; and
as having been supported by him in an ex∣pensive
style of life, in order to draw in
some young man of fashion to marry her.</P>
<P>As having failed in her plan in respect to
Lord Melvile, and as having condescended
to live with this nobleman on other terms,
when she found her hope of seducing him
into a matrimonial engagement abortive.</P>
<P>As having been left by him on the ap∣proach
of his intended marriage, and being
now on sale to the highest bidder.</P>
<P><PB N="193" REF="190"/>
The reader will judge of Mr. Hammond's
feelings on reading this diabolical scroll,
but no words can paint his astonishment at
finding himself one of the heroes of the
tale.</P>
<P>If he had wanted a proof of its false∣hood,
could one have been produced equally
decisive with this?</P>
<P>He was now doubly obliged to stand
forth her champion.</P>
<P>How should he act on so extraordinary an
occasion?</P>
<P>Should he communicate this vile fable to
Col. Dormer?</P>
<P>He knew his warmth of temper and quick
sense of honour, and therefore dreaded the
consequences of trusting him with a secret
<PB N="194" REF="191"/>
of this kind, in which he was so nearly in∣terested.</P>
<P>He knew the world, and the delicate na∣ture
of female honour.</P>
<P>The press must be stopped at all events.</P>
<P>He trembled at the idea of what might
happen in his absence.</P>
<P>He regarded the manuscript with more
attention.</P>
<P>The hand-writing was disguised, but he
instantly knew it to be that of Lady Blast.</P>
<P>Afraid of trusting so dark a transaction
to an amanuensis, this good lady (who had
made the penny-post her vehicle of convey∣ance)
had transcribed this benevolent off∣spring
of her brain for the press herself.</P>
<P><PB N="195" REF="192"/>
This circumstance was extremely fortu∣nate
for our heroine.</P>
<P>Her ladyship hated, but she also feared,
Mr. Hammond.</P>
<P>It was not probable she had sent the
printer a second copy of her libel, as such
a step might have led to a discovery of the
author.</P>
<P>The first was happily in Mr. Hammond's
own possession.</P>
<P>The most important point was to see
Lady Blast as soon as possible.</P>
<P>In such a situation not an instant was to
be lost.</P>
<P>It was not necessary to embarrass Col.
Dormer with this disagreeable affair.</P>
<P><PB N="196" REF="193"/>
His mind was more pleasingly occupied
by the approaching marriage of Louisa.</P>
<P>It would be inhuman to disturb the feli∣city
of his friend.</P>
<P><HI>Allons, donc!</HI> The carriage was immedi∣ately
ordered.</P>
<P>Col. Dormer returned from his early vi∣sit,
and was astonished to find Mr. Ham∣mond's
chaise at his gate.</P>
<P>The good old man apologized for this
unexpected flight.</P>
<P>Some business, which he had only that
moment recollected, rendered it impossible
for him to continue an instant longer one of
the happy group at Belfont.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="197" REF="194"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. V.</HEAD>
<P>MR. Hammond's wheels never stopped
till he reached the door of Lady
Blast.</P>
<P>He defied, and he escaped, all the dan∣gers
of Enfield chace, and arrived about
eleven at night at the house of this respec∣table
dowager, which he found full of com∣pany.</P>
<P>He sent for her down to her dining-par∣lour,
and, without the least preface, looking
her earnestly in the face,</P>
<P>“Do you know this paper, Madam?”</P>
<P>If she could have turned paler, she would
at the sight. She hesitated—“That paper,
cousin”—</P>
<P><PB N="198" REF="195"/>
“I disclaim all relationship, Madam, till
you have atoned for this infamous ac∣tion.”</P>
<P>“I will not expose you to your visitants,
but let me see you at my lodgings early
to-morrow morning: I hope, for your
sake, I am the only person who knows
of this affair.”</P>
<P>His looks, his authoritative tone, and her
own consciousness of guilt, appalled her.</P>
<P>She told him with hesitation, she would
see him in the morning, and returned trem∣bling
to her company.</P>
<P>Mr. Hammond went from thence to Mrs.
Merrick's, where he learned from a servant,
Mrs. Merrick being out, that Miss Villiers
had been gone three days into the country.</P>
<P><PB N="199" REF="196"/>
“Into the country? She was not at Bel∣font.”</P>
<P>He was bewildered; but as he was also
extremely fatigued, he thought it best to go
home, and give the night to repose.</P>
<P>His mind was still that of a knight-errant,
but his body was not quite so able to keep
pace with its flights as it had been at twenty-two.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VI.</HEAD>
<P>THE morning after Mr. Hammond
had set out for Belfont, Miss Villiers,
though the knew not half her danger, had
risen in a state of mind which Lady Blast
herself would almost have pitied.</P>
<P><PB N="200" REF="197"/>
She saw the precipice on the borders of
which she stood, though she saw it not in all
its horrors.</P>
<P>She knew not Lady Blast's inventive ge∣nius,
nor did she know herself the object of
her malice.</P>
<P>She saw disappointment, she saw distress,
before her; but she had not the remotest
apprehension of infamy.</P>
<P>She knew not the blow now levelled at
her same.</P>
<P>She knew not that the stroke, if given,
would probably be fatal; that the wounds
of calumny are never perfectly healed.</P>
<P>The human mind, impelled by its own
restless nature, fond of the marvellous, and
ever seeking food for that curiosity which
<PB N="201" REF="198"/>
carries us to so much good and so much
evil, imbibes with eagerness the animated
tale of slander, because animated.</P>
<P>To investigate its truth, to withdraw the
veil which covers a well-invented falsehood,
requires a cool dispassionate exertion of the
understanding, a patience of enquiry, to
which few, not personally interested, will
submit.</P>
<P>It is an effort, and from all effort the mind
of man naturally flies.</P>
<P>Infatuated girl! Why did she leave her
household gods?</P>
<P>Those household gods are alone the cer∣tain
guardians of female honour.</P>
<P>We have said, her quick sensibility of the
<HI>becoming,</HI> had prevented her writing, <HI>on
Monday,</HI> to Lord Melvile.</P>
<P><PB N="202" REF="199"/>
That sensibility gave way, <HI>on Tuesday,</HI> to
the august idea of justice.</P>
<P>Lord Melvile had a <HI>right</HI> to be heard in
his own defence.</P>
<P>After resolving, doubting, re-resolving,
an hundred times, she sat down, and wrote
him a letter full of confidence and senti∣ment.</P>
<P>“What inconsistency!” It is true, but
the human heart <HI>is</HI> inconsistent.</P>
<P>She owned her tenderness; a tenderness
justified, and even rendered meritorious, by
his virtues; by virtues which it would be
profaneness even to doubt.</P>
<P>She recounted, but with as much soften∣ing
as the case would admit, the supposed
artifices of Lord Claremont to break this
<PB N="203" REF="200"/>
union of two enamoured hearts; of two
hearts so evidently <HI>formed for each other.</HI></P>
<P>She proceeded, like a miss educated in
shades, to promise him everlasting love.</P>
<P>Could she do less?—He was so superior
to all his sex!—“To her the whole uni∣verse
contained no other being.”</P>
<P>In short, she ran on in the high romance
style the length of two quarto pages, and
then dispatched John to his lordship's house,
with orders to deliver it to himself, if at
home, and to wait his answer.</P>
<P>Her chariot, which she had determined
<HI>indeed</HI> to keep only that <HI>little week</HI> (a week
could not make much difference in the ex∣pence),
drove up to the door about a quar∣ter
of an hour after John set off; and in five
minutes was obliged to give way to another;
<PB N="204" REF="201"/>
which Miss Villiers took for granted was
that of Lord Melvile.</P>
<P>Interested as she was in the question, she
had not courage to satisfy herself by going
to the window.</P>
<P>The rustling of silks on the stairs first in∣formed
her she was mistaken in her conjec∣ture.</P>
<P>The door opened, and she saw—not Lord
Melvile, but Mrs. Herbert, whom she sup∣posed
to be still in France.</P>
<P>Mrs. Herbert! What unexpected hap∣piness!</P>
<P>The friend of her heart at the moment
when a friend was most necessary.</P>
<P>She was breathless with joy—</P>
<P><PB N="205" REF="202"/>
“My dear Miss Villiers, need I say how
charmed I am to find you in town?”</P>
<P>“My dear madam—no words—”</P>
<P>“I was afraid you had company, as I
saw a chariot at your door.”</P>
<P>Maria blushed—</P>
<P>“By the way, my dear, you will pardon
the digression?—May I ask whose cha∣riot
it is? It is by much the prettiest I
have seen in England.”</P>
<P>She hesitated—</P>
<P>“It is—it is mine, madam.”</P>
<P>“Yours, my dear? Do I understand
you? Are you then married?”</P>
<P><PB N="206" REF="203"/>
“Not yet—But I am so happy to see
you”—</P>
<P>At this moment John entered, and in∣formed
Miss Villiers, that having asked for
Lord Melvile, he was informed his lordship
was gone into the country, to the seat of
his intended father-in-law, Mr. Harding,
and would not be in town till after his mar∣riage.</P>
<P>His marriage!—Her misery was then
certain—she sunk motionless into a chair.</P>
<P>As Miss Villiers had too little art to hide
her feelings, and Mrs. Herbert too much
knowledge of the world to mistake them,
the latter was soon <HI>au fait</HI> as to the interest
her friend took in all that related to Lord
Melvile.</P>
<P>She however spared her confusion, told
her she looked pale, that she saw the town
<PB N="207" REF="204"/>
did not agree with her, and insisted on
taking her for three or four days to the villa
of her mother-in-law, Lady Sophia Herbert,
about twenty miles from town.</P>
<P>“I will send off one of my servants this
moment to apprize Lady Sophia of our
intended visit, and if you please, my dear
we will be with her at dinner to-morrow:
this day I insist on your spending with me:
we will be denied, and chat over all our
Rutland adventures.”</P>
<P>Our heroine was too unhappy at home,
and too weary of her own society, not to be
delighted with the proposal.</P>
<P>She endeavoured to hide the emotion she
could not absolutely restrain; and Mrs.
Herbert, who saw her distress, and wished
to give her time to recover from the shock,
pretended to have visits to pay, and left her
till dinner to herself.</P>
<P><PB N="208" REF="205"/>
We have said Miss Villiers had a mind,
which, though full of sensibility, was natu∣rally
carried to see every thing on the
brightest side.</P>
<P>Mrs. Herbert's absence was, as she ima∣gined
it would be, a relief to her friend.</P>
<P>She sat down, she read the letter John
had brought back; she dropped a tear of
regret—she dropped a second.</P>
<P>She wept the loss of the <HI>most charming of
mankind;</HI> she grieved such a letter, for it
was admirably written, should be thrown
away.</P>
<P>No ray of hope remained as to the first
source of her grief; as to the second, she
determined to insert this letter in her next
novel.</P>
<P><PB N="209" REF="206"/>
“Her next novel?” Is she not then
cured of the disease of writing?</P>
<P>Alas! my friend, it is plain you have
never been an author.</P>
<P>One rational motive of consolation how∣ever
remained.</P>
<P>Her folly in writing that letter was only
known to herself.</P>
<P>It had not reached the hand for which it
was destined.</P>
<P>It had not swelled the triumph of the in∣tended
Lady Melvile.</P>
<P>She also felt that certainty of evil is more
supportable than doubt.</P>
<P>These reflections were interrupted by her
frizeur.</P>
<P><PB N="210" REF="207"/>
A fresh subject of consolation now of∣fered.</P>
<P>She approached the glass—</P>
<P>O Vanity! benevolent goddess! How
much are human miseries alleviated by thy
celestial influence!</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. VII.</HEAD>
<P>OUR fair heroine, drest with the ut∣most
taste, and with an air of <HI>ton</HI>
which surprized Mrs. Herbert, arrived a lit∣tle
after four at the house of that lady.</P>
<P>They dined; Miss Villiers wished to un∣bosom
herself to her friend, but wanted
courage.</P>
<P><PB N="211" REF="208"/>
Her presence, however, restor'd some
part of her tranquillity.</P>
<P>They talked of Belfont, of Col. Dormer,
of her sister: her heart seemed lightened of
half its load.</P>
<P>Mrs. Herbert made her smile by drawing
ridiculous pictures of some of her country
acquaintance.</P>
<P>They were drinking their coffee in Mrs.
Herbert's dressing-room when a servant
threw open the door.</P>
<P>“Blockhead! Did I not give orders to
be denied?”</P>
<P>“It is Col. Herbert, madam.”</P>
<P>“My brother? You will excuse me, my
dear Miss Villiers; I am never denied to
him.”</P>
<P><PB N="212" REF="209"/>
Maria rose, and turning her head, saw
enter the room the very man who had
broken-in on her <HI>tete à tete</HI> with Lord
Melvile.</P>
<P>He was even in the same dress; it was
impossible she could be mistaken.</P>
<P>She blushed—she looked down—</P>
<P>Mrs. Herbert introduced her brother; he
addressed Maria without shewing any con∣sciousness
of having ever seen her before.</P>
<P>His eyes had, however, betrayed him.</P>
<P>Maria had remarked a glance of mixed
enquiry and surprize, from which he reco∣vered
in a moment, but which convinced
her he had not forgot the adventure.</P>
<P><PB N="213" REF="210"/>
She felt his delicacy, and was charmed
with it; but it humbled her infinitely in
her own eyes.</P>
<P>Was there a moment of her life for which
she had occasion to blush?</P>
<P>In what a light must she have appeared
to the brother of her friend!</P>
<P>What must he think of her when he felt
it necessary to dissemble that he had seen
her before!</P>
<P>She was superior to every evil but loss of
honour.</P>
<P>Was hers suspected? And for whom?
For a man who had left her for another—who
had not even deigned to bid her fare∣well.</P>
<P><PB N="214" REF="211"/>
Would to heaven she had never seen
Lord Melvile!</P>
<P>Her reverie was interrupted by Col.
Herbert, who acquainted his sister he came
ambassador from Lady Sophia to invite her
to spend a few weeks with her in Surry.</P>
<P>“And I, my dear brother, have this
morning sent William to acquaint Lady
Sophia of my intention to pass some days
with her, and to have the pleasure of in∣troducing
this young lady.”</P>
<P>“What say you, Miss Villiers? will you
do the maddest thing in the world, de∣spise
the danger of travelling in the dark,
and set out for Surry this moment?”</P>
<P>Col. Herbert looked at his sister: he had
been surprized at finding with her a person
<PB N="215" REF="212"/>
whose character appeared to him something
beyond equivocal.</P>
<P>He was much more so to find she intended
to introduce her to his mother.</P>
<P>He must be mistaken: she could not be
the person whom he had surprized at mid∣night
<HI>tete à tete</HI> with Lord Melvile.</P>
<P>It was necessary to clear his suspicions be∣fore
the visit to Lady Sophia was under∣taken;
yet he would have died rather than
have hinted those suspicions to Mrs. Herbert.</P>
<P>He called her into another room on pre∣tence
of business, and after speaking in rap∣tures
of the beauty of her visiter, asked,
but in a careless manner, as if a mere acci∣dental
question, who she was.</P>
<P>Mrs. Herbert, who observed the emotion
which he endeavoured to hide, and who at∣tributed
<PB N="216" REF="213"/>
it all to the charms of Miss Villiers,
smiled at his affectation of unconcern, and
assured him her friend was as amiable as she
was lovely, and had but one fault in the
world, which was, that her fortune was
inadequate to her birth.</P>
<P>That she was a woman of perfect ho∣nour;
but with all the fire, and she was
sorry to say, all the indiscretion of the very
opposite character.</P>
<P>That, as a proof of this, she had found
her in town, on her return from France, in
the most improper situation imaginable,
alone, in a lodging, and passing her time in
<HI>a certain set.</HI></P>
<P>“A <HI>set,</HI> my dear brother, which I need
not tell you is the very worst of all possi∣ble
society, especially for a young woman,
whose reputation is equally endangered
by their malice and their example.”</P>
<P><PB N="217" REF="214"/>
“A <HI>set,</HI> who are wholly engrossed by
play, intrigue, and scandal; and so par∣ticularly
devoted to the first, that they see
the approach of the genial spring with
horror.”</P>
<P>“For them no vernal shower descends,
no roses bloom; they prefer December to
May, and execrate the smiling Zephyrs
for blowing away their cards.”</P>
<P>“In order to restore the bright polish of
her fame, which must have been a little
injured by this indiscreet connexion, I
am going to introduce her to the shrine of
honour; that is, in plain terms, I intend
to put her for a few weeks under Lady
Sophia's protection.”</P>
<P>“My acquaintance with her began last
summer in Rutland, where I found her
in the bosom of domestic happiness, with
<PB N="218" REF="215"/>
her uncle, one of the most respectable
characters I know.”</P>
<P>“A man of the finest understanding, and
politest manners; and who, I believe,
never did a foolish thing but when he suf∣fered
Miss Villiers to come to town un∣protected.”</P>
<P>“In short, it is amazing to me how a
man of Col. Dormer's turn of mind could
suffer his niece—”</P>
<P>“Col. Dormer! Let me understand you,
sister: did you say Miss Villiers was the
niece of Col. Dormer?”</P>
<P>“I did.”</P>
<P>“Is it possible you can be in earnest?
You have no idea, my dear sister, how
happy you have made me.”</P>
<P><PB N="219" REF="216"/>
“I began my military life a cadet of
seven years old in Col. Dormer's regi∣ment:
he is the man on earth to whom
I am most obliged.”</P>
<P>Mrs. Herbert smiled—</P>
<P>They returned to Maria, who began to
be alarmed at their absence.</P>
<P>Col. Herbert, whose doubts were all dis∣pelled
by the conversation which had just
passed, approached Miss Villiers, his eyes
sparkling with pleasure, and made a thou∣sand
enquiries after the health of his
friend.</P>
<P>Mrs. Herbert's chariot, and her brother's
horses, came to the door; they set off,
though it was almost dark, and reached
Lady Sophia's little villa exactly at ten
o'clock.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="8" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="220" REF="217"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. VIII.</HEAD>
<P>IF Virtue—gentle, indulgent, feminine
Virtue, had chosen to descend on earth
in a human form, she would have assumed
that of Lady Sophia Herbert.</P>
<P>With a figure still elegant, and a face
which wanted only the bloom of youth to
be beautiful, she had an air which spoke
her birth to have been the most distin∣guished:
an air which would have been
commanding, had not its impression been
softened by the smile of undissembled good∣ness.</P>
<P>Her countenance spoke, in the most ex∣pressive
language, that calm sunshine of the
soul which is the happy monopoly of virtue.</P>
<P>She was perfectly well-bred, without the
remotest tincture of affectation.</P>
<P><PB N="221" REF="218"/>
She had mixed in the <HI>world;</HI> but her in∣clination,
and the mediocrity of her for∣tune,
had preserved her from mixing in the
<HI>ton.</HI></P>
<P>Left a widow extremely young, she had
devoted her whole time to the care of edu∣cating
Col. Herbert, her only child, and
pointing out his road to glory, by showing
him the paths marked out by his illustrious
ancestors.</P>
<P>He had returned her cares by meriting
them, and by a filial affection which bor∣dered
on enthusiasm.</P>
<P>Mr. Herbert's estate had been inherited
by his eldest son, born of another mother,
the husband of Miss Villiers's friend.</P>
<P>On his death, without children, what re∣mained
of the family fortune had descended
to Col. Herbert.</P>
<P><PB N="222" REF="219"/>
He received it a good deal impaired by
his brother's profuseness, and by Mrs. Her∣bert's
jointure.</P>
<P>He had, however, remaining about seven
hundred pounds a year, which he divided
with his mother, whose situation was before
by no means suitable to her birth, but which
this addition made perfectly easy.</P>
<P>She had remonstrated, but to no pur∣pose;
he rightly observed, that he was a
single man, and that whilst he continued so,
a handsome lodging, and a hired chariot,
were all the exteriors for which he had oc∣casion,
and that his pride was much more
interested in her ladyship's appearance than
his own.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="9" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="223" REF="220"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. IX.</HEAD>
<P>A Word or two, gentle reader, in re∣spect
to this young man; after which
we will leave the party at Lady Sophia's to
get acquainted, and see what is become of
Mr. Hammond.</P>
<P>Col. Herbert had entered into the army,
as we have observed, a perfect child, where
he had acquired all the frankness and gene∣rosity
of the military character; to which,
by the cares of his mother, he had added a
competent share of learning, and a particu∣lar
taste for polite literature.</P>
<P>He had travelled, not in the modern
style, under his own guidance, at nineteen,
with some needy dependent French adven∣turer
as an apology for a tutor, but with a
nobleman, his near relation, who had been
<PB N="224" REF="221"/>
ambassador at one of the first courts in
Europe.</P>
<P>He had therefore literally seen courts,
and had conversed, not with little Abbés,
Parisian <HI>Gens de Loix,</HI> or the despicable
beings that in France assume the name of
<HI>Philosophers,</HI> but with the first, the best, the
most accomplished, persons in every coun∣try
through which he accompanied Lord
L——.</P>
<P>Too poor to be flattered, too well-born
to descend to flatter others, he had acquired
dignity of mind without vanity or pride,
and ease and attention without servility.</P>
<P>He had fine sense, which his natural fire,
and proper self-confidence, produced on
all occasions to the best advantage.</P>
<P>He was open, brave, generous, sincere,
well-bred; and, being in perfect good-humour
<PB N="225" REF="222"/>
with himself, was extremely in∣clined
to be so with others.</P>
<P>He loved women, but he also esteemed
them, because he had been accustomed to
the society of the most estimable; and had
besides seen the female character in its most
beautiful light at home.</P>
<P>His person was rather pleasing than what
is generally called handsome.</P>
<P>He was of the middle stature, well-made,
easy, genteel, and had the air and deport∣ment
of a man of fashion.</P>
<P>His education, and his military life, had
given him great perfection in those exercises
which improve the figure, and are becom∣ing
a soldier and a gentleman.</P>
<P>His complexion was brown, and ren∣dered
browner by his profession; he had
<PB N="226" REF="223"/>
very fine chesnut hair, and the most ex∣pressive
dark eyes in the world.</P>
<P>Let us leave our friends to amuse them∣selves
by little tours about the neighbour∣ing
country; to read, chat, sing, dance,
play at quadrille, and be happy, whilst we
return a moment to town.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="10" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. X.</HEAD>
<P>AFTER a comfortable night's sleep,
Mr. Hammond rose, in good spirits,
to receive Lady Blast's visit.</P>
<P>She came, she apologized, she almost
blushed.</P>
<P>He menaced, she trembled, she acceded
to the conditions of forgiveness he proposed,
<PB N="227" REF="224"/>
which were, to burn her delectable manu∣script,
and give the honest compositor an
hundred pounds as a small reward for hav∣ing
saved her the infamy of publishing so
shameful a libel.</P>
<P>Our heroine's fame being thus rescued
from the danger which threatened it, Mr.
Hammond pleaded business to shorten Lady
Blast's visit, and went to Mrs. Merrick's;
where, finding the good woman at home,
he learned that Miss Villiers was at Lady
Sophia Herbert's in Surry, where she was
to stay a fortnight longer.</P>
<P>His heart glowed with pleasure; half his
work was done to his hands; he was the
intimate friend and near relation of Lady
Sophia, knew her virtues, the estimation in
which they stood, and the importance of
the visit to Miss Villiers.</P>
<P><PB N="228" REF="225"/>
He enquired into the state of her finances,
and, venturing to act as her parent for the
time being, paid the few debts she had re∣maining,
discharged her lodging and her
chariot, wrote to Col. Dormer that she was
in the country on a visit to the most re∣spectable
woman in the world, where he
intended to join the party, and, attended by
Miss Villiers's faithful old John, who had
been left behind, set out for Lady Sophia's
villa.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="11" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. XI.</HEAD>
<P>THERE are some people who have
the happy art of gaining, not only
your friendship, but your confidence, in a
moment.</P>
<P>Col. Herbert was one of these.</P>
<P><PB N="229" REF="226"/>
Warm, sincere, open, undisguised him∣self,
it was almost impossible to have dis∣guise
with him.</P>
<P>He had made it a point to gain the
esteem and confidence of Miss Villiers, and
had succeeded.</P>
<P>After passing five or six delightful days
at Greenwood, in that sweet social inter∣course
of congenial minds which wants a
name, she had taken courage, as they were
walking in the garden together, whilst the
two ladies were paying a visit of form, to
mention the evening in Berner's-street.</P>
<P>“I am ashamed, Colonel,” said she, with
some hesitation, “to own I have seen you
before, and feel most sensibly your deli∣cacy
in not appearing to recollect a cir∣cumstance
so little to my honour.”</P>
<P><PB N="230" REF="227"/>
“My indiscretion did not merit this de∣licacy;
and yet I feel that I could not
bear my folly should be known to any
person less candid than yourself.”</P>
<P>“I should even be shocked if it was
known to Mrs. Herbert, though I love
her with the warmest affection.”</P>
<P>“As I must appear to you at present in
a very unfavourable light, and as I have
the most ardent desire of convincing you
I am not unworthy your esteem, I will
beg you to hear me with patience whilst
I explain to you every little particular in
respect to my acquaintance with Lord
Melvile, whom I blush to own I <HI>did</HI> love,
and whom perhaps I do not yet think of
with the indifference I ought.”</P>
<P>She proceeded to relate her little history,
and to draw a faithful picture of her heart,
<PB N="231" REF="228"/>
with a sincerity in which Col. Herbert
found a thousand charms.</P>
<P>She even owned that the splendor of
Lady H's equipage had first misled her, and
that ambition had had too large a share in
her partiality for Lord Melvile; though
she insisted, and with a vehemence which
Col. Herbert did not dislike, that she really
<HI>had</HI> loved him.</P>
<P>He knew that a woman seldom owns a
passion till it ceases to exist.</P>
<P>He began to love her, and thought Lord
Melvile far from a dangerous rival, even
had not his situation in respect to Miss
Harding been what it was.</P>
<P>He, who was himself a man of fire, be∣lieved
it impossible a man of <HI>ton</HI> should in∣spire
a lasting affection: sensibility alone is
the food of sensibility.</P>
<P><PB N="232" REF="229"/>
He had been struck <HI>en passant</HI> with Miss
Villiers's person the first moment he saw
her, but thought no more of her till they
met at Mrs. Herbert's.</P>
<P>When he found her not only a woman
of honour, but the niece of his friend, her
charms appeared with redoubled lustre.</P>
<P>From that evening he determined to gain,
at least, her friendship.</P>
<P>Her friendship! How are we misled by
words without meaning?</P>
<P>It was her love to which he aspired, and
which he resolved to gain.</P>
<P>Charming in London, at Greenwood he
found her divine.</P>
<P><PB N="233" REF="230"/>
Having with him no designs, no preten∣sions,
no views either dictated by ambition
or love, she was with him perfectly at ease;
and only exerted that general desire of
pleasing, which a young and beautiful
woman naturally feels with an amiable man
who shews her particular attention.</P>
<P>The thorn of anxiety, which her visionary
schemes had planted in her bosom, and
which had always given a constraint to her
manner in her conversations with Lord
Melvile, was withdrawn, and had left her
all herself.</P>
<P>She was now natural, artless, gay, viva∣cious,
undesigning.</P>
<P>In short, she was the Maria of Belfont,
not of Berner's-street.</P>
<P><PB N="234" REF="231"/>
The ingenuity of the confession she had
just been making had touched Col. Herbert
in the most lively manner.</P>
<P>It was not her beauty, her genius, her
various accomplishments, which had riveted
his chains, but her noble sincerity, and the
feelings of her heart.</P>
<P>She expressed sentiments for Lord Mel∣vile,
of which he died to be himself the
object.</P>
<P>A momentary silence had taken place, and
both seemed immersed in thought, when
they were arroused by the sound of car∣riages.</P>
<P>As the road was directly under the low
wall on the top of which they were leaning,
Miss Villiers immediately knew Lord Mel∣vile,
<PB N="235" REF="232"/>
who was in a splendid chariot with—
Lady Melvile—for their hands had been
joined about an hour.</P>
<P>The train of attendant coaches, and the
white favours in the hats of the servants,
made it unnecessary for her to ask any
questions.</P>
<P>A glow of mingled disdain, expiring love,
and wounded vanity, suffused her cheek.</P>
<P>We need not say in what manner Col.
Herbert felt this event.</P>
<P>It is however necessary to account for
the new-married pair's having passed Lady
Sophia's wall.</P>
<P>The seat of Mr. Harding, though we did
not find this of consequence enough to men∣tion
sooner, was only two miles distant from
the villa of Lady Sophia.</P>
<P><PB N="236" REF="233"/>
As the families did not visit, this had es∣caped
Miss Villiers's knowledge.</P>
<P>Lady Sophia kept little company, and was
extremely delicate in the choice of it: meer
money was by no means a sufficient pass∣port
to the happiness of her acquaintance.</P>
<P>She had a particular objection to admit∣ting
Mr. Harding into her coterie, which
was that <HI>his</HI> father had been a menial ser∣vant
to <HI>hers.</HI></P>
<P>But to our business.</P>
<P>Our heroine was embarrassed, and Col.
Herbert a little at a loss how to resume the
conversation, when they were relieved by
the arrival of the ladies and Mr. Hammond,
who had accidentally met at the gate.</P>
<P><PB N="237" REF="234"/>
Mr. Hammond at Greenwood? Mr.
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a friend of this family? What
a pie<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sing surpri<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to the lovely Maria!</P>
<P>She <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> however at the idea of his
being the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of her authorship.</P>
<P>She hoped he had too much honour to
betray her.</P>
<P>He approached her with all the gallantry
of sixty-five, proclaimed his passion before
the whole company; and observed, after
St. Evremond, that there was not the least
impropriety in an old man's loving, though
there might be in his expecting to be be∣loved,
to which happiness he assured her he
made not the smallest pretension.</P>
<P>After a turn round the garden, Lady
Sophia proposed adjourning to a party at
loo in the drawing-room.</P>
<P><PB N="238" REF="235"/>
Whilst the cards were preparing, Mr.
Hammond regarded Maria with looks of
the strongest compassion.</P>
<P>“I cannot suffer her to return to town.
I must withdraw her from the precipice,
but without letting her see the hand
which saves her.”</P>
<P>“The utmost delicacy is requisite on this
occasion: a mind like hers will bear no
reproof but its own.”</P>
<P>These were his reflections; and they pro∣duced
a proposal of making a tour of a
week, in which he was to be master of the
revels, with unlimited power to amuse them
in whatever manner he thought proper.</P>
<P>Miss Villiers, who, not having money to
settle her affairs, was unable to quit London
intirely, who dreaded returning to it, who
<PB N="239" REF="236"/>
wished to avoid even the possibility of meet∣ing
Lord Melvile, and who was too happy
in her present society to think without re∣luctance
of changing it, accepted the pro∣posal
with transport.</P>
<P>It was at least throwing reflection at a
week's distance, which is an amazing point
gained.</P>
<P>Whilst Lady Sophia and Mrs. Herbert
were settling the necessary preparations for
this little party, Miss Villiers and the Col.
set down to picquet.</P>
<P>Miss Villiers had never observed him so
attentively before; the fire of his eyes, the
spirit of his whole countenance, formed such
a contrast with the maukish, unmeaning,
uninformed, macaroni faces about town, as
could not fail to strike very forcibly a wo∣man
of her turn of mind.</P>
<P><PB N="240" REF="237"/>
He was certainly not so handsome as
Lord Melvile—O! not a thousandth part
so handsome—</P>
<P>And yet she knew not how—but he was
more interesting—had mor soul—</P>
<P>There was an animation—something so
speaking in his every look—not an atom of
Lord Melvile's <HI>sang froid.</HI></P>
<P>In short, he was a very amiable man, and
though a woman would be unpardonable
who should <HI>love</HI> twice, yet there was cer∣tainly
no impropriety in having a friendship
for a man of such distinguished merit.</P>
<P>There was something so charming in his
attention to his mother—he was so per∣fectly
well-bred to women—so much more
than well-bred, so much in earnest, so <HI>em∣pressé,</HI>
to oblige them—</P>
<P><PB N="241" REF="238"/>
But what was all this to her?—Lord Mel∣vile
was false, but his falsehood would be
a very inadequate apology for hers.</P>
<P>Yes, he was indeed false, but he was still
as dear to her as ever.</P>
<P>“Adored object of my tenderness, whilst
this heart beats, it shall beat for thee.”</P>
<P>Col. Herbert interrupted this sentimental
reverie by producing point, quint, and qua∣torze,
which finished the game almost as
soon as it was begun.</P>
<P>The ladies and Mr. Hammond returned;
the play became general; loo took the place
of picquet: supper was announced, Pam
retired; they chatted away an extremely
pleasant evening, and set out at nine the
next day; Lady Sophia and Mr. Hammond
in her ladyship's post-chaise; and Col. Her∣bert,
<PB N="242" REF="239"/>
with Miss Villiers and his sister, in
that of Mr. Hammond.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="12" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>CHAP. XII.</HEAD>
<P>THE plan of our travellers was to have
no plan at all, which we take to be
the most rational and eligible that human
invention can suggest.</P>
<P>They went every day exactly as far as
they chose, without giving attention either
to hours or mile-stones; flew like the wind,
or passed leisurely to observe the face of
the country, just as inclination pointed
out.</P>
<P>They mounted every hill that promised
an agreeable prospect, whether it lay in or
out of the direct road; stopped at a twelve-penny
<PB N="243" REF="240"/>
hop, at a strolling play, at a wake,
at a village-wedding; and partook of twenty
more little innocent amusements which we
have not time to specify.</P>
<P>They saw all the fine houses on the road
which contained any thing worth observa∣tion;
but, as we think seeing fine houses
the dullest of all things which assume the
name of pleasure, we beg to be excused de∣scending
to particulars.</P>
<P>The sixth day of their tour arrived: the
proposed week was almost at an end.</P>
<P>Lady Sophia first observed it was time to
think of returning to town.</P>
<P>Miss Villiers's heart sunk at the proposal:
return to town! return to anxiety, to soli∣tude,
to distress!</P>
<P><PB N="244" REF="241"/>
She had been so happy! They were be∣come
so much one family! She adored
Lady Sophia; perhaps she might never see
her again.</P>
<P>A sudden damp pervaded every bosom:
they lamented that the hours of happiness
should ever have an end; that friends so
well suited to each other should ever part.</P>
<P>A sigh of regret escaped Maria; Col.
Herbert observed it, and pressed her hand
by an involuntary impulse.</P>
<P>The dreaded order was given; the horses
heads were turned towards London, from
whence they were now distant eighty miles.</P>
<P>They travelled later this evening than
they had ever done before, in order to reach
an inn which Mr. Hammond strongly re∣commended,
<PB N="245" REF="242"/>
and which was kept by one of
his servants, for whom he had a great affec∣tion.</P>
<P>In vain the host of the inn they left ex∣hausted
all the common-place rhetoric usual
on these occasions; assured them the roads
were bad, being cross the country; that
there were highwaymen abroad; that it
threatened a storm.</P>
<P>Mr. Hammond was obstinate, the ladies
compliant, and the chaises moved forward.</P>
<P>After they had gone about ten miles in
a very indifferent road, the night came on
almost imperceptibly.</P>
<P>To render its shades more gloomy, a
thick cloud obscured the whole horizon.</P>
<P>They were now at the entrance of an ex∣tensive
common: the postilions stopped,
<PB N="246" REF="243"/>
declared themselves utterly unacquainted
with the road, and unable to proceed far∣ther
without a guide, which it was now im∣possible
to procure.</P>
<P>It was happy for them that Col. Herbert
had been accustomed to <HI>reconnoitre:</HI> he
quitted the chaise, mounted his servant's
horse, and directing the postilions to stop
till his return, undertook to be their <HI>avant
coureur.</HI></P>
<P>The storm now broke at once upon them;
the big tempest rose, the winds whistled
round and shook the trees to their lowest
roots, the rain descended in torrents, the
thunder rolled, the streaming lightnings
ran along the ground, and produced a lu∣minous
glare more terrific than darkness
itself.</P>
<P>Col. Herbert had been gone from them
half an hour; an interval of which my
reader will imagine all the horrors.</P>
<P><PB N="247" REF="244"/>
What a situation for women! For women
delicately bred, and unused</P>
<LG>
<L>“To bide the pelting of the pityless storm.”</L>
</LG>
<P>Their fears were more than doubled by
Col. Herbert's long absence, and by their
anxiety on his account.</P>
<P>They called to him, but no sound re∣turned,
except that of their own voices,
reverberated by the echo.</P>
<P>It is easy to image the feelings of a mo∣ther
on such an occasion; nor were those of
Mrs. Herbert and Miss Villiers much less,
keen.</P>
<P>Mr. Hammond said every thing he could
to encourage them, but to no purpose: their
apprehensions were raised to the highest
pitch, all contributed to make them pant
<PB N="248" REF="245"/>
for an asylum, when Col. Herbert returned,
and informed them, that, dark as it was, he
had discovered the track of wheels, and had
heard, though faintly, the barking of vil∣lage
dogs.</P>
<P>With what transport they received this
intelligence none but those who have been
in a similar situation can conceive.</P>
<P>They now hoped to regain the haunts of
men.</P>
<P>At all events Col. Herbert was safe.</P>
<P>The storm lost half its terrors from this
consideration.</P>
<P>They advanced, though slowly and with
caution, in the track Col. Herbert pointed
out, and in about an hour had the happi∣ness
to hear a clock strike; and to see,
through a coppice of trees, a glimmering
light at a little distance.</P>
<P><PB N="249" REF="246"/>
Directed by the light, they turned the
corner of the coppice, and passed a row of
cottages, at the end of which, a little de∣tached
from the road, on a gently-rising
ground, they saw a house from whence the
light which had directed them proceeded.</P>
<P>They rang at the bell, two servants came
with lights, a lady and gentleman followed
them to the gate, and on getting out of the
chaise Miss Villiers found herself in the
arms of her sister.</P>
<P>“Maria!”</P>
<P>“Louisa!”</P>
<P>They could say no more: astonishment
and joy rendered them breathless.</P>
<P>Col. Dormer, though not less happy to
see her, was less agitated, and enough mas∣ter
<PB N="250" REF="247"/>
of himself to do the honours of his
house.</P>
<P>He was charmed to see Lady Sophia,
with whom he had been acquainted in her
married state, though he had not seen her
since she had been a widow.</P>
<P>What surprized Maria most was, to find
Mr. Hammond so well acquainted in the
family.</P>
<P>Our travellers entered the hospitable
walls of Belfont, and, instead of being in∣truders
on strangers, as they expected, had
the delight of finding themselves at home.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="13" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="251" REF="248"/>
<HEAD>CHAP. XIII.</HEAD>
<P>IT is unnecessary to paint the joyous
evening at Belfont; but it may not be
amiss to observe, that Mr. Hammond was
in such spirits after supper, that he fairly
owned the meeting of this group of friends
to have been, not accidental, but a surprize
of his contriving; and that he had commu∣nicated
the scheme, by letter, to Col. Dor∣mer,
who therefore had expected and pre∣pared
for them, but without betraying the
secret, even to Louisa, who was as much
astonished at the meeting as her sister.</P>
<P>“I protest, however,” said he, “that I
did not act in concert with the storm,
though I found it a very useful auxiliary.”</P>
<P>“I was under particular obligations to
the thunder, because, being unseasonable,
<PB N="251" REF="249"/>
and therefore unexpected, it had ten
times the more effect.”</P>
<P>“I must give the ladies credit for their
courage; they faced with heroism a war
of elements, which would have terrified a
<HI>macaroni</HI> into hysterics.”</P>
<P>“Confess, ladies, did you ever see so
charming an object as the light in this
parlour window?”</P>
<P>The hours passed on so rapidly, that it
was four in the morning before even the
female part of the company thought of re∣tiring.</P>
<P>Mr. Hammond, who was a <HI>bon vivant,</HI>
because it had been the <HI>ton</HI> in his youth,
insisted on one bottle of claret more to the
health of the ladies who had just left them.</P>
<P><PB N="253" REF="250"/>
His share of this bottle elevated Col.
Herbert, who was before a little <HI>in alt,</HI> to
the pitch of declaring his passion for Miss
Villiers to her uncle, and protesting, that,
though he was too poor at present to marry
her himself, he would run any other man
through the body who should dare to think
of her.</P>
<P>He was the best-humoured creature that
can be imagined, sung <HI>beviamo tutti tre,</HI>
danced an allemande with Mr. Hammond,
drank the king's health, and the ladies, on
his knees, threw the glasses over his head,
and committed a thousand indecorums, not
one of which had the least analogy with the
present style of elegant society.</P>
<P>Not but that he was one of the soberest
men in the world, but—after a storm—to
the health of one's prince, or one's mistress
—I forgive him with all my heart.</P>
<P><PB N="254" REF="251"/>
It was with great difficulty Mr. Ham∣mond
prevailed on him to retire to his
chamber, where, instead of going to bed,
he kept the good old man two hours to hear
him protest five hundred times over, and in
nearly the same words, that Cleopatra and
Helen of Greece were dowdies compared to
the divine Maria Villiers.</P>
<P>Morpheus at last took compassion on Mr.
Hammond, and inclined our young soldier
to let him retire to his apartment.</P>
<P>The leaden god kept possession of the
whole company till eleven the next day,
when on assembling in the breakfast par∣lour,
they met Mr. Montague with his son
and daughter, who, having heard of Maria's
arrival, with her friends, came to invite
them to a little ball the next day at the
manor-house.</P>
<P><PB N="255" REF="252"/>
The invitation was accepted, and the
Montagues consented to spend the day at
Col. Dormer's.</P>
<P>Col. Herbert, after making a thousand
apologies to Col. Dormer for having kept
him up the night before, took him into the
garden; and having, as in duty bound, paid
his devoirs to the reigning Sultana of his
green-house, a hyacinth of distinguished
beauty, very <HI>soberly</HI> asked his permission to
address his lovely niece.</P>
<P>“Your claret, my dear sir, has done a
great deal for me, by precipitating my
confession.”</P>
<P>“I love Miss Villiers, and my reason and
my heart are equally touched. Besides
regarding her as the most lovely of wo∣men,
I find myself unhappy at the idea of
losing her society.”</P>
<P><PB N="256" REF="253"/>
“If I had a throne, I would offer it to
her; I have only a cottage, and I esteem
her enough to believe, that, if I am so
happy as to be agreeable to her, the dif∣ference
between one and the other is not
essential.”</P>
<P>“My paternal fortune is small; and I
divide it with my mother, whose little in∣come
before was really insufficient to sup∣port
her with decency.”</P>
<P>“I have only to offer, the glorious hopes
of a soldier; a soldier well-born, well-allied,
and fond of his profession, which
he has not disgraced.”</P>
<P>“If Miss Villiers will condescend to share
those hopes, and, in the mean time, to
conform to my present situation, I shall
be the happiest man on earth.”</P>
<P><PB N="257" REF="254"/>
“My mother is at this moment plead∣ing
my cause with Miss Villiers; may I
ask you to add your persuasions?”</P>
<P>“Here she comes herself, my dear
Charles, and I leave you to settle the
point with her.”</P>
<P>“You will say more for yourself in five
minutes, than Lady Sophia and I should
say in ten years.”</P>
<P>“I have only to observe, that gain my
niece's consent, and you are sure of mine
at any time.”</P>
<P>There is no eloquence so successful as the
language of an impassioned heart: before
this conversation ended, Miss Villiers was
convinced of two truths very important to
female happiness, that it is possible to love
<PB N="258" REF="255"/>
twice, and to be happy without either a
coach and six or a title.</P>
<P>Miss Villiers left him not devoid of hope,
and hastened to dress with her sister, her
own apartment being given up to Lady
Sophia.</P>
<P>During this interval the two sisters en∣tered
into mutual confidence on all which
had happened to them during this absence;
and Maria had the pleasure to find the ami∣able
Louisa was in a few days to be united
to a man she had always loved.</P>
<P>She then related her history, and dwelt
particularly on her first interview with Col.
Herbert.</P>
<P>“If I should marry him,” said she, “it
would be the most extraordinary com∣mencement
of a matrimonial engagement
that ever happened.”</P>
<P><PB N="259" REF="256"/>
“I have been very indiscreet indeed,
Louisa, but the inconveniences I have
found from that indiscretion will make
me a pattern of circumspection for the
future.”</P>
<P>On relating the circumstance of the hun∣dred
pounds which had dropped from the
clouds, Louisa's suspicions fell very rightly
on Mr. Hammond.</P>
<P>The whole constellation of friends, the
Montagues included, were drinking their
coffee after dinner, when Col. Dormer's ser∣vant,
whom he had sent on business to Stam∣ford,
returned, and brought <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his letters
from the post.</P>
<P>The first he opened was from his tulip-merchant
at the Hague, with advice of his
having purchased him a polyanthus, which
<PB N="260" REF="257"/>
he assured him would grace the garden of
an emperor.</P>
<P>Joy lighted up his whole countenance on
reading the second; he gave it to Mr.
Hammond, who, by his desire, read aloud
as follows:</P>
<P>“MY LORD, Naples, Jan. 15, 1775.</P>
<P>IT is my duty to inform your lordship,
that my old lord, your honoured kinsman,
the Earl of Clairville, died this morning,
and has left your lordship the family estate,
with sixty thousand pounds in the stocks.</P>
<P>It is expressed in the will that my lord
left the estate and money to your lordship,
both that it might not be divided from the
title, which is your lordship's by inheri∣tance,
and to make you amends for his
having treated you harshly in his life-time.</P>
<P><PB N="261" REF="258"/>
I hope to have the honour of being con∣tinued
in your lordship's service, and am,</P>
<CLOSER>My Lord,
With respect,
Your Lordship's dutiful Servant,
<SIGNED>WILLIAM JOHNSON.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1>
<P>P. S. I have directed the letter in your
lordship's old name, for fear of mistakes at
the post-office.”</P>
<P>The relationship was so distant, and the
late Lord Clairville's treatment of the pre∣sent
so unworthy, that grief could not be
supposed to have any share in the feelings
of the latter.</P>
<P>Congratulations are points taken for
granted, had not every person present been,
what however they were, personally inte∣rested
in the change of Col. Dormer's situa∣tion.</P>
<P><PB N="262" REF="259"/>
“I have always,” said he, addressing his
nieces, “expected this event, but would not
communicate my hopes to you, lest they
should end in disappointment. I may
now be allowed to build castles in the
air; it depends greatly on you, my dear
girls, to realize them.”</P>
<P>“I have more money than I know how
to make use of myself: I therefore pre∣sent
each of you with twenty thousand
pounds, and leave it to yourselves to be∣stow
it as you please.”</P>
<P>“I wish you (though in this I leave you
perfectly free) to fix in this neighbour∣hood,
because no accession of fortune
would make me amends for the loss of
your society.”</P>
<P><PB N="263" REF="260"/>
“Louisa has already made a choice which
leaves me nothing to wish in respect to
her.”</P>
<P>“Maria, are you determined on celi∣bacy?”</P>
<P>Her eyes were involuntarily turned on
Col. Herbert; she perceived it, looked
down, and blushed.</P>
<P>“I understand you, and am happy: I will
spare your confusion, my dear Maria, and
give you to my cadet.”</P>
<P>“And now for my airy project; it is to
form a neighbourhood of persons en∣deared
to each other by the most tender
ties.”</P>
<P><PB N="264" REF="261"/>
“My duty to my prince and my country
will oblige me to reside part of the year
in London: I will take a house there suf∣ficiently
large for us all, where every one
shall be at home, and without the shadow
of restraint.”</P>
<P>“For our best, our rural, house, as Lord
Clairville, who lived abroad, and hated
his native country, long since sold the fa∣mily
seat of his and my ancestors, I have
a house and little domain in view for my∣self,
not two miles distant, at the top of
yon hill, on the other side the rivulet
which divides the two counties<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Of Rutland and Northampton.</NOTE>.”</P>
<P>“Col. Herbert and Maria, being soldiers,
and therefore citizens of the world, shall,
if, as I hope, it is agreeable to them,
make mine their country-house.”</P>
<P><PB N="265" REF="262"/>
“There, perhaps, Mr. Hammond, to
whom Maria has obligations of which she
is at present ignorant, will join our syl∣van
party, and be literally”</P>
<LG>
<L>“Our guide, philosopher, and friend.”</L>
</LG>
<P>“And there,” said the good old man,
your lordship shall build us a theatre;
and Miss Villiers and I will, in defiance
of managers, write tragedies, and play
them ourselves.”</P>
<P>Maria blushed, and Lord Clairville pro∣ceeded.</P>
<P>“We will build a little, plant a great
deal, and above all, garden to infinity.”</P>
<P>“Perhaps Lady Sophia will dispose of
her villa in Surry, and honour Belfont by
making it her future residence.”</P>
<P><PB N="266" REF="263"/>
“You will love this country, madam; it
is still”</P>
<LG>
<L>“A land unspoil'd by barbarous wealth,”</L>
</LG>
<P>“and inhabited by our old race of Eng∣lish
gentlemen.”</P>
<P>“I will write directly to my lawyer, and
my correspondent at the Hague: the mar∣riage
settlements shall be drawn, and the
polyanthus imported.”</P>
<P>“I will indulge an innocent folly, if it is
a folly, which gives offence to no one, and
extremely gratifies myself.”</P>
<P>“And now who will say that Fortune,
though in herself contemptible, does not
sometimes contribute to happiness?”</P>
<P>“She has enabled me to spend the even∣ing
of my life in the society of all those
<PB N="267" REF="264"/>
most dear to me, to give my amiable
Louisa and Maria to the two men on
earth who, in my opinion, most deserve
them, and to have a collection of vegeta∣tive
beauty which shall be the wonder
and the envy of the universe.”</P>
<TRAILER>THE END.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>
