<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet TYPE="text/css" href="http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE><DATE>yyyy-mm-dd</DATE><RESPSTMT><NAME>[name of reviewer]</NAME><RESP>MURP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM></CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>

<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K112129.000">
<STC T="C">T143945</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3317029256</BIBNO>
<VID SET="ecll">1206201000</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE ENGLISH GARDEN: A POEM. BOOK THE FOURTH. BY W. MASON, M. A.</P>
<P>YORK PRINTED BY A. WARD: And sold by J. DODSLEY, Pall-Mall; T. CADELL, in the Strand; and R. FAULDER, in New Bond-Street, London; and J. TODD, in York. M.DCC.LXXXI.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="book">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE ENGLISH GARDEN. BOOK THE FOURTH.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>NOR yet withdraw thy aid, thou NYMPH divine!<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">SIMPLICITY. See the beginning of the Poem. The following lines recapitulate the subject of the three preceding Books. The 1st to the pause in ver. 4th; the 2d from thence to that in ver. 7th; and the third finishes with the paragraph.</NOTE></L>
<L>That aid auspicious, which, in Art's domain,</L>
<L>Already has reform'd whate'er prevail'd</L>
<L>Of foreign, or of false; has led the curve</L>
<L>That Nature loves thro' all her sylvan haunts;<MILESTONE N="5"/></L>
<L>Has stol'n the fence unnotic'd that arrests</L>
<L>Her vagrant herds; giv'n lustre to her lawns,</L>
<L>Gloom to her groves, and, in expanse serene,</L>
<L>Devolv'd that wat'ry mirror at her foot,</L>
<L>O'er which she loves to bend and view her charms.<MILESTONE N="10"/></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="3"/>
<L>And tell me Thou, whoe'er hast new-arrang'd</L>
<L>By her chaste rules thy garden, if thy heart</L>
<L>Feels not the warm, the self-dilating glow</L>
<L>Of true Benevolence. Thy flocks, thy herds,</L>
<L>That browze luxurious o'er those very plots<MILESTONE N="15"/></L>
<L>Which once were barren, bless thee for the change;</L>
<L>The birds of Air (which thy funereal Yews</L>
<L>Of shape uncouth, and leaden Sons of Earth,</L>
<L>Antaeus and Enceladus, with clubs</L>
<L>Uplifted, long had frighted from the scene)<MILESTONE N="20"/></L>
<L>Now pleas'd return, they perch on ev'ry spray,</L>
<L>And swell their little throats, and warble wild</L>
<L>Their vernal minstrelsy; to Heav'n and Thee</L>
<L>It is a hymn of thanks: do thou, like Heav'n,</L>
<L>With tutelary care reward their song.<MILESTONE N="25"/></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Ere-while the Muse, industrious to combine</L>
<L>Nature's own charms, with these alone adorn'd</L>
<L>The Genius of the Scene; but other gifts</L>
<L>She has in store, which gladly now she brings,</L>
<L>And he shall proudly wear. Know, when she broke<MILESTONE N="30"/></L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="4"/>The spells of Fashion, from the crumbling wreck</L>
<L>Of her enchantments sagely did she cull</L>
<L>Those reliques rich of old Vitruvian skill,</L>
<L>With what the Sculptor's hand in classic days</L>
<L>Made breathe in Brass or Marble; these the Hag<MILESTONE N="35"/></L>
<L>Had purloin'd, and dispos'd in Folly's fane;</L>
<L>To him these trophies of her victory</L>
<L>She bears; and where his awful nod ordains</L>
<L>Conspicuous means to place. He shall direct</L>
<L>Her dubious judgment, from the various hoard<MILESTONE N="40"/></L>
<L>Of ornamental treasures, how to chuse</L>
<L>The simplest and the best; on these his seal</L>
<L>Shall stamp great Nature's image and his own,</L>
<L>To charm for unborn ages.—Fling the rest</L>
<L>Back to the Beldame, bid her whirl them all<MILESTONE N="45"/></L>
<L>In her vain vortex, lift them now to day,</L>
<L>Now plunge in night, as, thro' the humid rack</L>
<L>Of April cloud, swift flits the trembling beam.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But precepts tire, and this fastidious Age</L>
<L>Rejects the strain didactic: Try we then<MILESTONE N="50"/></L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="5"/>In livelier Narrative the truths to veil</L>
<L>We dare not dictate. Sons of Albion, hear!</L>
<L>The tale I tell is full of strange event,</L>
<L>And piteous circumstance; yet deem not ye,</L>
<L>If names I feign, that therefore facts are seign'd:<MILESTONE N="55"/></L>
<L>Nor hence refuse (what most augments the charm</L>
<L>Of storied woe) that fond credulity</L>
<L>Which binds th' attentive soul in closer chains.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>At manhood's prime ALCANDER's duteous tear</L>
<L>Fell on his Father's grave. The fair Domain,<MILESTONE N="60"/></L>
<L>Which then became his ample heritage,</L>
<L>That Father had reform'd; each line destroy'd</L>
<L>Which Belgic dulness plann'd; and Nature's self</L>
<L>Restor'd to all the rights she wish'd to claim.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Crowning a gradual hill his Mansion rose<MILESTONE N="65"/></L>
<L>In antient English grandeur: Turrets, Spires,</L>
<L>And Windows, climbing high from base to roof</L>
<L>In wide and radiant rows, bespoke its birth</L>
<L>Coëval with those rich cathedral fanes,</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="6"/>(Gothic ill-nam'd) where harmony results<MILESTONE N="70"/></L>
<L>From disunited parts; and shapes minute,</L>
<L>At once distinct and blended, boldly form</L>
<L>One vast majestic whole. No modern art</L>
<L>Had marr'd with misplac'd symmetry the Pile.</L>
<L>ALCANDER held it sacred: On a height,<MILESTONE N="75"/></L>
<L>Which westering to its site the front survey'd,</L>
<L>He first his taste employ'd: for there a line</L>
<L>Of thinly scatter'd Beech too tamely broke</L>
<L>The blank Horizon. "Draw we round yon knowl,"</L>
<L>ALCANDER cry'd, "in stately Norman mode,<MILESTONE N="80"/></L>
<L>"A wall embattled; and within its guard</L>
<L>"Let every structure needful for a Farm</L>
<L>"Arise in Castle-semblance; the huge Barn</L>
<L>"Shall with a mock Portcullis arm the gate,</L>
<L>"Where Ceres entering, o'er the flail-proof floor<MILESTONE N="85"/></L>
<L>"In golden triumph rides; some Tower rotund</L>
<L>"Shall to the Pigeons and their callow young</L>
<L>"Safe roost afford; and ev'ry buttress broad,</L>
<L>"Whose proud projection seems a mass of stone,</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="7"/>"Give space to stall the heifer, and the steed.<MILESTONE N="90"/></L>
<L>"So shall each part, tho' turn'd to rural use,</L>
<L>"Deceive the eye with those bold feudal forms</L>
<L>"That Fancy loves to gaze on." This achiev'd,</L>
<L>Now nearer home he calls returning Art</L>
<L>To hide the structure rude where Winter pounds<MILESTONE N="95"/></L>
<L>In conic pit his congelations hoar,</L>
<L>That Summer may his tepid beverage cool</L>
<L>With the chill luxury; his Dairy too</L>
<L>There stands of form unsightly: both to veil,</L>
<L>He builds of old disjointed moss-grown stone<MILESTONE N="100"/></L>
<L>A time-struck Abbey <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><P>It was said in the first Book, ver. 384, that of those architectural Objects which improved a fine natural <HI>English</HI> prospect, the two principal ones were a <HI>Castle</HI> and an <HI>Abbey</HI>. In conformity with this Idea, ALCANDER first begins to exercise his taste, by form∣ing a resemblance of those two capital artificial features, <HI>uniting them</HI>, however, <HI>with utility</HI>. The precept is here meant to be conveyed by description, which had before been given more directly in Book II. ver. 21.</P><P><HI>Beauty</HI> scorns to dwell</P><P>Where <HI>Use</HI> is exil'd.</P></NOTE>. An impending grove</L>
<L>Screens it behind with reverential shade;</L>
<L>While bright in front the stream reflecting spreads,</L>
<L>Which winds a mimic River o'er his Lawn.</L>
<L>The Fane conventual there is dimly seen,<MILESTONE N="105"/></L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="8"/>The mitred Window, and the Cloister pale,</L>
<L>With many a mouldering Column; Ivy soon</L>
<L>Round the rude chinks her net of foliage spreads,</L>
<L>Its verdant meshes seem to prop the wall.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>One native Glory, more than all sublime,<MILESTONE N="110"/></L>
<L>ALCANDER's scene possest: 'Twas Ocean's self—</L>
<L>He, boist'rous King, against the eastern cliffs</L>
<L>Dash'd his white foam; a verdant vale between</L>
<L>Gave splendid ingress to his world of waves.</L>
<L>Slaunting this vale the mound of that clear stream<MILESTONE N="115"/></L>
<L>Lay hid in shade, which slowly lav'd his Lawn:</L>
<L>But there set free, the rill resum'd its pace,</L>
<L>And hurried to the Main. The dell it past</L>
<L>Was rocky and retir'd: Here Art with ease</L>
<L>Might lead it o'er a Grot, and filter'd there,<MILESTONE N="120"/></L>
<L>Teach it to sparkle down its craggy sides,</L>
<L>And fall and tinkle on its pebbled floor.</L>
<L>Here then that Grot he builds, and conchs with spars,</L>
<L>Moss petrified with branching corallines</L>
<L>In mingled mode arranges: All found here<MILESTONE N="125"/></L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="9"/>Propriety of place; what view'd the Main</L>
<L>Might well the shelly gifts of Thetis bear.</L>
<L>Not so the inland cave: with richer store</L>
<L>Than those the neighb'ring mines and mountains yield</L>
<L>To hang its roof, would seem incongruous Pride,<MILESTONE N="130"/></L>
<L>And fright the local Genius from the scene <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">A precept is here rather more than hinted at; but it appeared to be so well founded and yet so seldom attended to by the fabricators of Grottos, that it seemed necessary to slide back a little from the narrative into the didactic to inculcate it the more strongly.</NOTE>.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>One vernal morn, as urging here the work</L>
<L>Surrounded by his hinds, from mild to cold</L>
<L>The Season chang'd, from cold to sudden storm,</L>
<L>From storm to whirlwind. To the angry main<MILESTONE N="135"/></L>
<L>Swiftly he turns and sees a laden Ship</L>
<L>Dismasted by its rage. "Hie, hie we all,"</L>
<L>ALCANDER cry'd, "quick to the neighb'ring beach."</L>
<L>They flew; they came, but only to behold,</L>
<L>Tremendous sight! the Vessel dash its poop<MILESTONE N="140"/></L>
<L>Amid the boiling breakers. Need I tell</L>
<L>What strenuous Arts were us'd, when all were us'd,</L>
<L>To save the sinking Crew? One tender Maid</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="10"/>Alone escap'd, sav'd by ALCANDER's arm,</L>
<L>Who boldly swam to snatch her from the plank<MILESTONE N="145"/></L>
<L>To which she feebly clung; swiftly to shore,</L>
<L>And swifter to his home the youth convey'd</L>
<L>His clay-cold prize, who at his portal first</L>
<L>By one deep sigh a sign of Life betray'd.</L>
<L>A Maid so sav'd, if but by nature blest<MILESTONE N="150"/></L>
<L>With common charms, had soon awak'd a flame</L>
<L>More strong than Pity, in that melting heart</L>
<L>Which Pity warm'd before. But she was fair</L>
<L>As Poets picture Hebe, or the Spring;</L>
<L>Graceful withal, as if each limb were cast<MILESTONE N="155"/></L>
<L>In that ideal mould whence RAPHAEL drew</L>
<L>His Galatea <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Alluding to a Letter of that famous Painter, written to his Friend Count B<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ser Castiglione, when he was painting his celebrated picture of Galatea, in which he tells him, "essendo carestia di belle donne, io mi servo di cer<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a idea che viene alla mente." See Bellori <HI>Discriz. delle imagini dipinte da Raffaello d' Urbino</HI>, or the Life of B. Casti∣glione, prefixt to the London Edition of his Book entitled, <HI>Il Cortegiano</HI>.</NOTE>: Yes, th'impassion'd Youth</L>
<L>Felt more than pity when he view'd her charms.</L>
<L>Yet she, (ah, strange to tell) tho' much he lov'd,</L>
<L>Supprest as much that sympathetic flame<MILESTONE N="160"/></L>
<L><PB N="10" REF="11"/>Which Love like his should kindle: Did he kneel</L>
<L>In rapture at her feet? she bow'd the head,</L>
<L>And coldly bad him rise; or did he plead,</L>
<L>In terms of purest passion, for a smile?</L>
<L>She gave him but a tear: his manly form,<MILESTONE N="165"/></L>
<L>His virtues, ev'n the courage that preserv'd</L>
<L>Her life, beseem'd no sentiment to wake</L>
<L>Warmer than gratitude; and yet the love</L>
<L>Withheld from him she freely gave his scenes;</L>
<L>On all their charms a just applause bestow'd;<MILESTONE N="170"/></L>
<L>And, if she e'er was happy, only then</L>
<L>When wand'ring where those charms were most display'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>As thro' a neighb'ring Grove, where antient beech</L>
<L>Their awful foliage flung, ALCANDER led</L>
<L>The pensive maid along, "Tell me," she cry'd,<MILESTONE N="175"/></L>
<L>"Why, on these forest features all-intent,</L>
<L>"Forbears my friend some scene distinct to give</L>
<L>"To Flora and her fragrance? Well I know</L>
<L>"That in the general Landscape's broad expanse</L>
<L><PB N="11" REF="12"/>"Their little blooms are lost; but here are glades,<MILESTONE N="180"/></L>
<L>"Circled with shade, yet pervious to the sun,</L>
<L>"Where, if enamell'd with their rainbow-hues,</L>
<L>"The eye would catch their splendor: turn thy Taste,</L>
<L>"Ev'n in this grassy circle where we stand,</L>
<L>"To form their plots; there weave a woodbine Bower,<MILESTONE N="185"/></L>
<L>"And call that Bower NERINA's." At the word</L>
<L>ALCANDER smil'd; his fancy instant form'd</L>
<L>The fragrant scene she wish'd; and Love, with Art</L>
<L>Uniting, soon produc'd the finish'd whole.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Down to the South the glade by Nature lean'd;<MILESTONE N="190"/></L>
<L>Art form'd the slope still softer, opening there</L>
<L>Its foliage, and to each Etesian gale</L>
<L>Admittance free dispensing; thickest shade</L>
<L>Guarded the rest.—His taste will best conceive</L>
<L>The new arrangement, whose free footsteps, us'd<MILESTONE N="195"/></L>
<L>To forest haunts, have pierc'd their opening dells,</L>
<L>Where frequent tufts of sweetbriar, box, or thorn,</L>
<L>Steal on the green sward, but admit fair space</L>
<L>For many a mossy maze to wind between.</L>
<L><PB N="12" REF="13"/>So here did Art arrange her flow'ry groups<MILESTONE N="200"/></L>
<L>Irregular, yet not in patches quaint <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">There is nothing in picturesque Gardening which should not have its archetype in unadorned Nature. Now, as we never see any of her plains dotted with dissevered patches of any sort of vegetables, except, perhaps, some of her more barren heaths, where even Furze can grow but sparingly, and which form the most disagreeable of her scenes, there∣fore the present common mode of dotting clamps of flowers, or shrubs on a grass-plat, without union, and without other meaning than that of appearing irregular, ought to be avoided. It is the form and easy flow of the grassy interstices (if I may so call them) that the designer ou<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ht first to have a regard to; and if these be well formed, the spaces for flowers or shrubbery will be at the same time ascertained.</NOTE>,</L>
<L>But interpos'd between the wand'ring lines</L>
<L>Of shaven turf which twisted to the path,</L>
<L>Gravel or sand, that in as wild a wave</L>
<L>Stole round the verdant limits of the scene;<MILESTONE N="205"/></L>
<L>Leading the Eye to many a sculptur'd bust</L>
<L>On shapely pedestal, of Sage, or Bard,</L>
<L>Bright heirs of fame, who living lov'd the haunts</L>
<L>So fragrant, so sequester'd. Many an Urn</L>
<L>There too had place, with votive lay inscrib'd<MILESTONE N="210"/></L>
<L>To Freedom, Friendship, Solitude, or Love.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And now each flow'r that bears transplanting change,</L>
<L>Or blooms indigenous, adorn'd the scene:</L>
<L><PB N="13" REF="14"/>Only NERINA's wish, her woodbine bower,</L>
<L>Remain'd to crown the whole. Here, far beyond<MILESTONE N="215"/></L>
<L>That humble wish, her Lover's Genius form'd</L>
<L>A glittering Fane, where rare and alien plants</L>
<L>Might safely flourish <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>M. Le Giradin</HI>, in an elegant French Essay, written on the same subject, and f<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rmed on the same principles, with this Poem, is the only writer that I have seen (or at cast recollect) who has attempted to give a stove or hot-house a picturesque eff<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ct It i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> his hint, pursued and considerably dilated, which forms the description of ALCANDER's Conservatory. See his Essay, <HI>De la composition des Paysages. Geneva</HI>, 1777.</NOTE>; where the Citron sweet,</L>
<L>And fragrant Orange, rich in fruit and flowers,</L>
<L>Might hang their silver stars, their golden globes,<MILESTONE N="220"/></L>
<L>On the same odorous stem: Yet scorning there</L>
<L>The glassy penthouse of ignoble form,</L>
<L>High on Ionic shafts he bad it tower</L>
<L>A proud Rotunda; to its sides conjoin'd</L>
<L>Two broad Piazzas in theatric curve,<MILESTONE N="225"/></L>
<L>Ending in equal Porticos sublime.</L>
<L>Glass roost the whole, and sidelong to the South</L>
<L>'Twixt ev'ry fluted Column, lightly rear'd</L>
<L>Its wall pellucid. All within was day,</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="15"/>Was genial Summer's day, for secret stoves<MILESTONE N="230"/></L>
<L>Thro' all the pile solstitial warmth convey'd.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>These led thro' isles of Fragrance to the Dome,</L>
<L>Each way in circling quadrant. That bright space</L>
<L>Guarded the spicy tribes from Afric's shore,</L>
<L>Or Ind, or Araby, Sabaean Plants<MILESTONE N="235"/></L>
<L>Weeping with nard, and balsam. In the midst</L>
<L>A Statue stood, the work of Attic Art;</L>
<L>Its thin light drapery, cast in fluid folds,</L>
<L>Proclaim'd its antientry; all save the head,</L>
<L>Which stole (for Love is prone to gentle thefts)<MILESTONE N="240"/></L>
<L>The features of NERINA; yet that head,</L>
<L>So perfect in resemblance; all its air</L>
<L>So tenderly impassion'd; to the trunk,</L>
<L>Which Grecian skill had form'd, so aptly join'd,</L>
<L>PHIDIAS himself might seem to have inspir'd<MILESTONE N="245"/></L>
<L>The chissel, brib'd to do the am'rous fraud.</L>
<L>One graceful hand held forth a flow'ry wreath,</L>
<L>The other prest her zone; while round the base</L>
<L>Dolphins, and Triton shells, and plants marine</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="16"/>Proclaim'd, that Venus, rising from the sea,<MILESTONE N="250"/></L>
<L>Had veil'd in Flora's modest vest her charms.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Such was the Fane, and such the Deity</L>
<L>Who seem'd, with smile auspicious, to inhale</L>
<L>That incense which a tributary world</L>
<L>From all its regions round her altar breath'd:<MILESTONE N="255"/></L>
<L>And yet, when to the shrine ALCANDER led</L>
<L>His living Goddess, only with a sigh,</L>
<L>And starting tear, the statue and the dome</L>
<L>Reluctantly she view'd. And "why," she cry'd,</L>
<L>"Why would my best Preserver here erect,<MILESTONE N="260"/></L>
<L>"With all the fond idolatry of Love,</L>
<L>"A Wretch's image whom his Pride should scorn,</L>
<L>"(For so his Country bids him). Drive me hence,</L>
<L>"Transport me quick to Gallia's hostile shore,</L>
<L>"Hostile to thee, yet not, alas! to her<MILESTONE N="265"/></L>
<L>"Who there was meant to sojourn: there, perchance,</L>
<L>"My Father, wafted by more prosp'rous gales,</L>
<L>"Now mourns his Daughter lost; my Brother there</L>
<L>"Perhaps now sooths that venerable age</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="17"/>"He should not sooth alone. Vain thought! perchance<MILESTONE N="270"/></L>
<L>"Both perish'd at Esopus—do not blush,</L>
<L>"It was not thou that lit the ruthless flame;</L>
<L>"It was not thou, that, like remorseless Cain,</L>
<L>"Thirsted for Brother's blood: thy heart disdains</L>
<L>"The savage imputation. Rest thee there,<MILESTONE N="275"/></L>
<L>"And, tho' thou pitiest, yet forbear to grace,</L>
<L>"A wretched Alien, and a Rebel deem'd,</L>
<L>"With honors ill-beseeming her to claim.</L>
<L>"My wish, thou know'st, was humble as my state;</L>
<L>"I only begg'd a little woodbine bower,<MILESTONE N="280"/></L>
<L>"Where I might sit and weep, while all around</L>
<L>"The lilies and the blue bells hung their heads</L>
<L>"In seeming sympathy." "Does then the scene</L>
<L>"Displease?" the disappointed lover cry'd;</L>
<L>"Alas! too much it pleases," sigh'd the fair;<MILESTONE N="285"/></L>
<L>"Too strongly paints the passion which stern Fate</L>
<L>"Forbids me to return;" "Dost thou then love</L>
<L>"Some happier youth?" "No, tell thy generous soul</L>
<L>"Indeed I do not." More she would have said,</L>
<L><PB N="17" REF="18"/>But gushing grief prevented. From the Fane<MILESTONE N="290"/></L>
<L>Silent he led her; as from Eden's bower</L>
<L>The Sire of Men his weeping Partner led,</L>
<L>Less lovely, and less innocent than she.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Yet still ALCANDER hop'd what last she sigh'd</L>
<L>Spoke more than gratitude; the War might end;<MILESTONE N="295"/></L>
<L>Her Father might consent; for that alone</L>
<L>Now seem'd the duteous barrier to his bliss.</L>
<L>Already had he sent a faithful friend</L>
<L>To learn if France the reverend Exile held:</L>
<L>That friend return'd not. Mean-while ev'ry sun<MILESTONE N="300"/></L>
<L>Which now (a year claps'd) diurnal rose</L>
<L>Beheld her still more pensive; inward Pangs,</L>
<L>From grief's concealment, hourly seem'd to force</L>
<L>Health from her cheek, and Quiet from her soul.</L>
<L>ALCANDER mourn'd the change, yet still he hop'd;<MILESTONE N="305"/></L>
<L>For Love to Hope his flickering taper lends,</L>
<L>When Reason with his steady torch retires:</L>
<L>Hence did he try by ever-varying arts,</L>
<L>And scenes of novel charm her grief to calm.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="18" REF="19"/>
<L>Nor did he not employ the Syren Powers<MILESTONE N="310"/></L>
<L>Of Music and of Song; or Painting, thine,</L>
<L>Sweet source of pure delight! But I record</L>
<L>Those arts alone, which form my sylvan theme.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>At stated hours, full oft had he observ'd,</L>
<L>She fed with welcome grain the household fowl<MILESTONE N="315"/></L>
<L>That trespast on his lawn; this wak'd a wish</L>
<L>To give her feather'd fav'rites space of land,</L>
<L>And lake appropriate: in a neighb'ring copse</L>
<L>He plann'd the scene; for there the crystal spring,</L>
<L>That form'd his river, from a rocky cleft<MILESTONE N="320"/></L>
<L>First bubbling broke to day; and spreading there</L>
<L>Slept on its rushes. "Here my delving hinds,"</L>
<L>He cry'd, "shall soon the marshy soil remove,</L>
<L>"And spread, in brief extent, a glittering Lake</L>
<L>"Chequer'd with isles of verdure; on yon Rock.<MILESTONE N="325"/></L>
<L>"A sculptur'd River-God shall rest his urn;</L>
<L>"And thro' that urn the native fountain flow.</L>
<L>"Thy wish'd-for bower, NERINA, shall adorn</L>
<L>"The southern bank; the downy race, that swim</L>
<L><PB N="19" REF="20"/>"The lake, or pace the shore, with livelier charms,<MILESTONE N="330"/></L>
<L>"Yet no less rural, here will meet thy glance,</L>
<L>"Than flowers inanimate." Full soon was scoopt</L>
<L>The wat'ry bed, and soon, by margin green.</L>
<L>And rising banks, inclos'd; the highest gave</L>
<L>Site to a rustic fabric, shelving deep<MILESTONE N="335"/></L>
<L>Within the thicket, and in front compos'd</L>
<L>Of three unequal arches, lowly all</L>
<L>The surer to expel the noontide glare,</L>
<L>Yet yielding liberal inlet to the scene;</L>
<L>Woodbine with jasmine carelessly entwin'd<MILESTONE N="340"/></L>
<L>Conceal'd the needful masonry, and hung</L>
<L>In free festoons, and vested all the cell.</L>
<L>Hence did the lake, the islands, and the rock,</L>
<L>A living landscape spread; the feather'd fleet,</L>
<L>Led by two mantling swans, at ev'ry creek<MILESTONE N="345"/></L>
<L>Now touch'd, and now unmoor'd; now on full sail,</L>
<L>With pennons spread and oary feet they ply'd</L>
<L>Their vagrant voyage; and now, as if becalm'd,</L>
<L>'Tween shore and shore at anchor seem'd to sleep.</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="21"/>Around those shores the Fowl that fear the stream<MILESTONE N="350"/></L>
<L>At random rove: hither hot Guinea sends</L>
<L>Her gadding troop; here midst his speckled Dames</L>
<L>The pigmy Chanticleer of Bantam winds</L>
<L>His clarion; while, supreme in glittering state,</L>
<L>The Peacock spreads his rainbow train, with eyes<MILESTONE N="355"/></L>
<L>Of sapphire bright, irradiate each with gold.</L>
<L>Mean-while from ev'ry spray the Ringdoves coo,</L>
<L>The Linnets warble, captive none <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">See Rousseau's charming description of the Garden of Julie, <HI>Nouvelle Eloise</HI>, 4 <HI>par∣tie. Lett.</HI> 11<HI>th.</HI> In consequence of pursuing his idea, no birds are introduced into AL∣CANDER's Menagerie, but such as are either domesticated, or chuse to visit it for the security and food they find there. If any of my more delicate readers wish to have th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>irs flocked with <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arer kind of fowls, they must invent a picturesque Bird-cage for themselves.</NOTE>, but lur'd</L>
<L>By food to haunt the umbrage: all the Glade</L>
<L>Is Life, is Music, Liberty, and Love.<MILESTONE N="360"/></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And is there now to Pleasure or to Use</L>
<L>One scene devoted in the wide domain</L>
<L>Its Master has not polish'd? Rumour spreads</L>
<L>Its praises far, and many a stranger stops</L>
<L>With curious eye to censure or admire.<MILESTONE N="365"/></L>
<L><PB N="21" REF="22"/>To all his Lawns are pervious; oft himself</L>
<L>With courteous greeting will the critic hail,</L>
<L>And join him in the circuit. Give we here</L>
<L>(If Candour will with patient ear attend)</L>
<L>The social dialogue ALCANDER held<MILESTONE N="$70"/></L>
<L>With one, a Youth of mild yet manly mein,</L>
<L>Who seem'd to taste the beauties he survey'd</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>"Little, I fear me, will a stranger's eye</L>
<L>"Find here to praise, where rich Vitruvian Art</L>
<L>"Has rear'd no temples, no triumphal ares;<MILESTONE N="$$$"/></L>
<L>"Where no Palladian bridges span the stream,</L>
<L>"But all is homebred Fancy." "For that cause,</L>
<L>"And chiefly that," the polish'd Youth reply'd,</L>
<L>"I view each part with rapture. Ornament,</L>
<L>"When foreign or fantastic, never charm'd<MILESTONE N="380"/></L>
<L>"My judgment; here I tread on British ground;</L>
<L>"With British annals all I view accords.</L>
<L>"Some Yorkist, or Lancastrian Baron bold,</L>
<L>"To awe his vassals, or to stem his foes,</L>
<L>"Yon massy bulwark built; on yonder pile,<MILESTONE N="385"/></L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="23"/>"In ruin beauteous, I distinctly mark</L>
<L>"The ruthless traces of stern HENRY's hand.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>"Yet," cry'd ALCANDER, (interrupting mild</L>
<L>The stranger's speech) "if so yon antient seat,</L>
<L>"Pride of my ancestors, had mock'd repair,<MILESTONE N="390"/></L>
<L>"And by Proportion's Greek or Roman laws</L>
<L>"That pile had been rebuilt, thou wouldst not then,</L>
<L>"I trust, have blam'd, if, there on Doric shafts</L>
<L>"A temple rose; if some tall obelisk</L>
<L>"O'ertopt yon grove, or bold triumphal arch<MILESTONE N="395"/></L>
<L>"Usurpt my Castle's station."— "Spare me yet</L>
<L>"Yon solemn Ruin," the quick youth return'd,</L>
<L>"No mould'ring aqueduct, no yawning crypt</L>
<L>"Sepulchral, will console me for its fate."</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>"I mean not that," the Master of the scene<MILESTONE N="400"/></L>
<L>Reply'd; "tho' classic rules to modern piles</L>
<L>"Should give the just arrangement, shun we here</L>
<L>"By those to form our Ruins; much we own</L>
<L><PB N="23" REF="24"/>"They please, when, by PANINI's pencil drawn,</L>
<L>"Or darkly grav'd by PIRANESI's hand,<MILESTONE N="405"/></L>
<L>"And fitly might some Tuscan garden grace;</L>
<L>"But Time's rude mace has here all Roman piles</L>
<L>"Levell'd so low, that who, on British ground</L>
<L>"Attempts the task, builds but a splendid lye</L>
<L>"Which mocks historic credence. Hence the cause<MILESTONE N="41$"/></L>
<L>"Why Saxon piles or Norman here prevail:</L>
<L>"Form they a rude, 'tis yet an English whole."</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>"And much I praise thy choice," the stranger cry'd,</L>
<L>"Such chaste selection shames the common mode,</L>
<L>"Which, mingling structures of far distant times,<MILESTONE N="415"/></L>
<L>"Far distant regions, here, perchance, erects</L>
<L>"A fane to Freedom, where her BRUTUS stands</L>
<L>"In act to strike the tyrant; there a Tent,</L>
<L>"With crescent crown'd, with scymitars adorn'd,</L>
<L>"Meet for some BAJAZET; northward we turn,<MILESTONE N="420"/></L>
<L>"And lo! a pigmy Pyramid pretends</L>
<L>"We trend the realms of PHARAOH; quickly thence</L>
<L>"Our southern step presents us heaps of stone</L>
<L>"Rang'd in a DRUID circle. Thus from age</L>
<L><PB N="24" REF="25"/>"To age, from clime to clime incessant borne,<MILESTONE N="425"/></L>
<L>"Imagination flounders headlong on,</L>
<L>"Till, like fatigu'd VILLARIO <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">See Pope's Epistle to Lord Burlington, ver. 88.</NOTE>, soon we find</L>
<L>"We better like a field." "Nicely thy hand</L>
<L>"The childish landscape touches," cries his host,</L>
<L>"For Fashion ever is a wayward child;<MILESTONE N="430"/></L>
<L>"Yet sure we might forgive Her faults like these,</L>
<L>"If but in separate or in single scenes</L>
<L>"She thus with Fancy wanton'd: Should I lead</L>
<L>"Thy step, my Friend, (for our accordant tastes</L>
<L>"Prompt me to give thee that familiar name)<MILESTONE N="435"/></L>
<L>"Behind this screen of Elm, thou there might'st find</L>
<L>I too had idly play'd the truant's part,</L>
<L>"And broke the bounds of judgment." "Lead me there,"</L>
<L>Briskly the Youth returned, "for having prov'd</L>
<L>"Thy Epic Genius here, why not peruse<MILESTONE N="440"/></L>
<L>"Thy lighter Ode or Eclogue?" Smiling thence</L>
<L>ALCANDER led him to the Woodbine bower</L>
<L>Which last our Song describ'd, who seated there,</L>
<L>In silent transport view'd the lively scene,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="25" REF="26"/>
<L>"I see," his host resum'd, "my sportive art<MILESTONE N="445"/></L>
<L>"Finds pardon here; not ev'n yon classic form,</L>
<L>"Pouring his liquid treasures from his vase,</L>
<L>"Tho' foreign from the soil, provokes thy frown.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">It is hoped that, from the position of this River-God in the menagerie; from the situation of the busts and vases in the flower-garden; and that of the statue in the con∣servatory, the reader will deduce the following general precept, "that all adventitious ornaments of sculpture ought either to be accompanied with a proper back-ground, (as the Painters term it) or introduced as a part of architectural scenery; and that when, on the contrary, they are placed in open lawns or parterres, according to the old mode, they become, like Antaeus and Enceladus, mentioned in the beginning of this book, mere <HI>scare-crows</HI>."</NOTE></L>
<L>"Try we thy candor further: higher art,</L>
<L>"And more luxurious, haply too more vain,<MILESTONE N="450"/></L>
<L>"Adorns yon southern coppice." On they past</L>
<L>Thro' a wild thicket, till the perfum'd air</L>
<L>Gave to another sense its prelude rich</L>
<L>On what the eye should feast. But now the grove</L>
<L>Expands; and now the Rose, the garden's Queen,<MILESTONE N="455"/></L>
<L>Amidst her blooming subjects' humbler charms,</L>
<L>On ev'ry plot her crimson pomp displays.</L>
<L>"Oh Paradise!" the ent'ring youth exclaim'd,</L>
<L>"Groves whose rich trees weep odorous gums and balm,</L>
<L>"Others whose fruit, burnish'd with golden rind,<MILESTONE N="460"/></L>
<L><PB N="26" REF="27"/>"Hang amiable, Hesperian fables true,</L>
<L>"If true, here only <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">See Milton's Paradise Lost, book iv. ver. 248, &amp;c.</NOTE>." Thus, in Milton's phrase</L>
<L>Sublime, the youth his admiration pour'd,</L>
<L>While passing to the dome; his next short step</L>
<L>Unveil'd the central statue: "Heav'ns! just Heav'ns,"<MILESTONE N="465"/></L>
<L>He cry'd, "tis my NERINA." "Thine, mad Youth?</L>
<L>"Forego the word," ALCANDER said, and paus'd;</L>
<L>His utterance fail'd; a thousand clust'ring thoughts,</L>
<L>And all of blackest omen to his peace,</L>
<L>Recoil'd upon his brain, deaden'd all sense,<MILESTONE N="470"/></L>
<L>And at the statue's base him headlong cast,</L>
<L>A lifeless load of being.—Ye, whose hearts</L>
<L>Are ready at Humanity's soft call</L>
<L>To drop the tear, I charge you weep not yet,</L>
<L>But fearfully suspend the bursting woe:<MILESTONE N="475"/></L>
<L>NERINA's self appears; the further isle</L>
<L>She, fate-directed, treads. Does she too faint?</L>
<L>Would Heav'n she could! it were a happy swoon</L>
<L>Might soften her fixt form, more rigid now</L>
<L><PB N="27" REF="28"/>Than is her marble semblance. One stiff hand<MILESTONE N="480"/></L>
<L>Lies leaden on her breast; the other rais'd</L>
<L>To heav'n, and half-way clench'd; stedfast her eyes,</L>
<L>Yet viewless; and her lips, which op'd to shriek,</L>
<L>Can neither shriek nor close: So might she stand</L>
<L>For ever: He, whose sight caus'd the dread change,<MILESTONE N="485"/></L>
<L>Tho' now he clasps her in his anxious arms,</L>
<L>Fails to unbend one sinew of her frame;</L>
<L>'Tis ice; 'tis steel. But see, ALCANDER wakes;</L>
<L>And waking, as by magic sympathy,</L>
<L>NERINA whispers, "All is well, my friend;<MILESTONE N="490"/></L>
<L>"'Twas but a vision; I may yet revive—</L>
<L>"But still his arm supports me; aid him, friend,</L>
<L>"And bear me swiftly to my woodbine bower;</L>
<L>"For there indeed I wish to breathe my last."</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>So saying, her cold cheek, and parched brow,<MILESTONE N="495"/></L>
<L>Turn'd to a livid paleness; her dim eyes</L>
<L>Sunk in their sockets; sharp contraction prest</L>
<L>Her temples, ears, and nostrils: signs well known</L>
<L><PB N="28" REF="29"/>To those that tend the dying. <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">These lines are taken from the famous passage in Hippocrates in his book of Prog∣nostics, which has been held so accurately descriptive, that dying persons are, from hence, usually said to have the <HI>facies Hippocratica</HI>. The passage is as follows: <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> Both the youths</L>
<L>Perceiv'd the change; and had stern Death himself<MILESTONE N="500"/></L>
<L>Wav'd his black banner visual o'er their heads,</L>
<L>It could not more appall. With trembling step,</L>
<L>And silent, both convey'd her to the bower.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Her languid limbs there decently compos'd,</L>
<L>She thus her speech resum'd: "Attend my words<MILESTONE N="505"/></L>
<L>"Brave CLEON! dear ALCANDER! generous Pair:</L>
<L>"For both have tender interest in this heart</L>
<L>"Which soon shall beat no more. That I am thine</L>
<L>"By a dear Father's just commands I own,</L>
<L>"Much honour'd CLEON! take the hand he gave,<MILESTONE N="510"/></L>
<L>"And with it, Oh, if I could give my heart,</L>
<L>"Thou wert its worthy owner. All I can,</L>
<L>"(And that preserv'd with chastest fealty)</L>
<L>"Duteous I give thee, CLEON it is thine;</L>
<L><PB N="29" REF="30"/>"Not ev'n this dear preserver, e'er could gain<MILESTONE N="515"/></L>
<L>"More from my soul than Friendship—that be his;</L>
<L>"Yet let me own, what, dying, sooths the pang,</L>
<L>"That, had thyself and duty ne'er been known,</L>
<L>"He must have had my love." She paus'd; and dropt</L>
<L>A silent tear; then prest the Stranger's hand;<MILESTONE N="520"/></L>
<L>Then bow'd her head upon ALCANDER's breast,</L>
<L>And "bless them both, kind Heav'n!" she pray'd and died,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>"And blest art thou," cry'd CLEON, (in a voice</L>
<L>Struggling with grief for utterance) blest to die</L>
<L>"Ere thou hadst question'd me, and I perforce<MILESTONE N="525"/></L>
<L>"Had told a tale which must have sent thy soul</L>
<L>"In horror from thy bosom. Now it leaves</L>
<L>"A smile of peace upon those pallid lips,</L>
<L>"That speaks its parting happy. Go fair saint!</L>
<L>"Go to thy palm-crown'd father! thron'd in bliss,<MILESTONE N="530"/></L>
<L>"And seated by his side, thou wilt not now</L>
<L>"Deplore the savage stroke that seal'd his doom;</L>
<L>"Go hymn the Fount of Mercy, who, from ill</L>
<L>"Educing good, makes ev'n a death like his,</L>
<L><PB N="30" REF="31"/>"A life surcharg'd with tender woes like thine,<MILESTONE N="535"/></L>
<L>"The road to Joys eternal. Maid, farewell!</L>
<L>"I leave the casket that thy virtues held</L>
<L>"To Him whose breast sustains it; more belov'd,</L>
<L>"Perhaps more worthy, yet not loving more</L>
<L>"Than did thy wretched CLEON." At the word<MILESTONE N="540"/></L>
<L>He bath'd in tears the hand she dying gave,</L>
<L>Return'd it to her side, and hasty rose.</L>
<L>ALCANDER, starting from his trance of grief,</L>
<L>Cry'd "stay, I charge thee stay;" "and shall he stay,"</L>
<L>CLEON reply'd, "whose presence stabb'd thy peace?<MILESTONE N="545"/></L>
<L>"Hear this before we part: That breathless Maid</L>
<L>"Was daughter to a venerable Sage,</L>
<L>"Whom Boston, when with peace and safety blest,</L>
<L>"In rapture heard pour from his hallow'd tongue</L>
<L>"Religion's purest dictates. 'Twas my chance,<MILESTONE N="550"/></L>
<L>"In early period of our civil broils,</L>
<L>"To save his precious life: And hence the Sire</L>
<L>"Did to my love his Daughter's charms consign;</L>
<L>"But, till the war should cease, if ever cease,</L>
<L><PB N="31" REF="32"/>"Deferr'd our nuptials. Whither she was sent<MILESTONE N="555"/></L>
<L>"In search of safety, well, I trust, thou know'st;</L>
<L>"He meant to follow; but those ruthless flames,</L>
<L>"That spar'd nor friend nor foe, nor sex nor age,</L>
<L>"Involv'd the village, where on sickly couch</L>
<L>"He lay confin'd, and whither he had fled<MILESTONE N="560"/></L>
<L>"Awhile to sojourn. There (I see thee shrink)</L>
<L>"Was he that gave NERINA being burnt!</L>
<L>"Burnt by thy Countrymen! to Ashes burnt!</L>
<L>"Fraternal hands and christian lit the flame. —</L>
<L>"Oh thou hast cause to shudder. I meanwhile<MILESTONE N="565"/></L>
<L>"With his brave son a distant warfare wag'd;</L>
<L>"And him, now I have sound the prize I sought,</L>
<L>"And finding lost, I hasten to rejoin;</L>
<L>"Vengeance and glory call me." At the word,</L>
<L>Not fiercer does the Tigress quit her cave<MILESTONE N="570"/></L>
<L>To seize the hinds that robb'd her of her young,</L>
<L>Than he the Bower. "Stay, I conjure thee, stay."</L>
<L>ALCANDER cry'd, but ere the word was spoke</L>
<L>CLEON was seen no more. "Then be it so,"</L>
<L><PB N="32" REF="33"/>The youth continu'd, clasping to his heart<MILESTONE N="575"/></L>
<L>The beauteous corse, and smiling as he spoke,</L>
<L>(Yet such a smile as far out-sorrows tears)</L>
<L>"Now thou art mine entirely—Now no more</L>
<L>"Shall Duty dare disturb us—Love alone—</L>
<L>"But hark! he comes again—Away vain fear!<MILESTONE N="580"/></L>
<L>"'Twas but the fluttering of thy feather'd flock.</L>
<L>"True to their custom'd hour, behold they troop</L>
<L>"From island, grove, and lake. Arise my Love,</L>
<L>"Extend thy hand—I lift it, but it falls.</L>
<L>"Hence then, fond fools, and pine! NERINA's hand<MILESTONE N="585"/></L>
<L>"Has lost the power to feed you. Hence and die."</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus plaining, to his lips the icy palm</L>
<L>He lifted, and with ardent passion kist,</L>
<L>Then cry'd in agony, "on this dear hand,</L>
<L>"Once tremblingly alive to Love's soft touch,<MILESTONE N="590"/></L>
<L>"I hop'd to seal my faith:" This thought awak'd</L>
<L>Another sad soliloquy, which they,</L>
<L>Whoe'er have lov'd, will from their hearts supply,</L>
<L>And they who have not will but hear and smile.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="33" REF="34"/>
<L>And let them smile, but let the scorners learn<MILESTONE N="595"/></L>
<L>There is a solemn luxury in grief</L>
<L>Which they shall never taste; well known to those,</L>
<L>And only those, in Solitude's deep gloom</L>
<L>Who heave the sigh sincerely: Fancy there</L>
<L>Waits the sit moment; and, when Time has calm'd<MILESTONE N="600"/></L>
<L>The first o'erwhelming tempest of their woe,</L>
<L>Piteous she steals upon the mourner's breast</L>
<L>Her precious balm to shed: Oh, it has power,</L>
<L>Has magic power to soften and to sooth,</L>
<L>Thus duly minister'd. ALCANDER felt<MILESTONE N="605"/></L>
<L>The charm, yet not till many a ling'ring moon</L>
<L>Had hung upon her zenith o'er his couch,</L>
<L>And heard his midnight wailings. Does he stray</L>
<L>But near the fated temple, or the bower?</L>
<L>He feels a chilly monitor within,<MILESTONE N="610"/></L>
<L>Who bids him pause. Does he at distance view</L>
<L>His grot? 'tis darken'd with NERINA's storm</L>
<L>Ev'n at the blaze of noon. Yet there are walks</L>
<L>The lost one never trod, and there are seats</L>
<L><PB N="34" REF="35"/>Where he was never happy by her side,<MILESTONE N="615"/></L>
<L>And these he still can sigh in. Here at length,</L>
<L>As if by chance, kind Fancy brought her aid,</L>
<L>When wand'ring thro' a grove of sable yew,</L>
<L>Rais'd by his ancestors; their Sabbath-path</L>
<L>Led thro' its gloom, what time too dark a stole<MILESTONE N="620"/></L>
<L>Was o'er Religion's decent features drawn</L>
<L>By Puritanic zeal. Long had their boughs</L>
<L>Forgot the sheers; the spire, the holy ground</L>
<L>They banish'd by their umbrage. "What if here,"</L>
<L>Cry'd the sweet Soother, in a whisper soft,<MILESTONE N="625"/></L>
<L>"Some open space were form'd, where other shades,</L>
<L>"Yet all of solemn sort, Cypress and Bay</L>
<L>"Funereal, pensive Birch its languid arms</L>
<L>"That droops, with waving Willows deem'd to weep,</L>
<L>"And shiv'ring Aspens mixt their varied green;<MILESTONE N="630"/></L>
<L>"What if yon trunk, shorn of its murky crest,</L>
<L>"Reveal'd the sacred Fane?" ALCANDER heard</L>
<L>The Charmer; ev'ry accent seem'd his own,</L>
<L>So much they touch'd his heart's sad unison.</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="36"/>"Yes, yes," he cry'd, "Why not behold it all?<MILESTONE N="635"/></L>
<L>"That bough remov'd shews me the very vault</L>
<L>"Where my NERINA sleeps, and where, when Heav'n</L>
<L>"In pity to my plaint the mandate seals,</L>
<L>"My dust with her's shall mingle." Now his hinds,</L>
<L>Call'd to the task, their willing axes wield;<MILESTONE N="640"/></L>
<L>Joyful to see, as witless of the cause,</L>
<L>Their much-lov'd Lord his sylvan arts resume.</L>
<L>And next, within the centre of the gloom,</L>
<L>A shed of twisting roots and living moss,</L>
<L>With rushes thatch'd, with wattled oziers lin'd,<MILESTONE N="645"/></L>
<L>He bids them raise <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">If this building is found to be in its right position, structures of the same kind will be thought improperly placed when situated, as they frequently are, on an emi∣nence commanding an extensive prospect. I have either seen or heard of one of this kind, where the builder seemed to be so much convinced of its incongruity, that he endeavoured to atone for it by the following ingenious motto:<Q><L>Despicere unde queas alio<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, passimque videre</L><L>Errare, atque viam palanteis quaerere vita<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L><BIBL>Luc. lib. ii. v. 9.</BIBL></Q>But it may be said, t<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eal Hermitages are fr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>quently found on high mountains. Yet there the difficulty of access gives that idea of retirement, not easily to be conveyed by imitations of them in a garden scene, without much accompanying shade and that low¦ness of situation, which occasions a seclusion from all gay objects.</NOTE>: it seem'd a Hermit's cell;</L>
<L><PB N="36" REF="37"/>Yet void of hour-glass, scull, and maple dish,</L>
<L>Its mimic garniture: ALCANDER's taste</L>
<L>Disdains to trick with emblematic toys</L>
<L>The place where He and Melancholy mean<MILESTONE N="650"/></L>
<L>To six NERINA's bust, her genuine bust,</L>
<L>The model of the marble. There he hides,</L>
<L>Close as a Miser's gold, the sculptur'd clay;</L>
<L>And but at early morn and latest eve</L>
<L>Unlocks the simple shrine, and heaves a sigh;<MILESTONE N="655"/></L>
<L>Then does he turn, and thro' the glimm'ring glade</L>
<L>Cast a long glance upon her house of death;</L>
<L>Then views the bust again, and drops a tear.</L>
<L>Is this idolatry, ye sage ones say? —</L>
<L>Or, if ye doubt, go view the num'rous train<MILESTONE N="660"/></L>
<L>Of poor and fatherless his care consoles;</L>
<L>The sight will tell thee, he that dries their tears</L>
<L>Has unseen angels hov'ring o'er his head,</L>
<L>Who leave their heav'n to see him shed his own.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="37" REF="38"/>
<L>Here close we, sweet SIMPLICIY! the tale,<MILESTONE N="665"/></L>
<L>And with it let us yield to youthful bards</L>
<L>That Dorian reed we but awak'd to voice</L>
<L>When Fancy prompted, and when Leisure smil'd;</L>
<L>Hopeless of general praise, and well repaid,</L>
<L>If they of classic ear, unpall'd by rhyme,<MILESTONE N="670"/></L>
<L>Whom changeful pause can please, and numbers free,</L>
<L>Accept our song with candour. They perchance,</L>
<L>Led by the Muse to solitude and shade,</L>
<L>May turn that Art we sing to soothing use,</L>
<L>At this ill-omen'd hour, when Rapine rides<MILESTONE N="675"/></L>
<L>In titled triumph; when Corruption waves</L>
<L>Her banners broadly in the face of day,</L>
<L>And shews th'indignant world the host of slaves</L>
<L>She turns from Honour's standard. Patient there,</L>
<L>Yet not desponding, shall the sons of Peace<MILESTONE N="680"/></L>
<L>Await the day, when, smarting with his wrongs,</L>
<L>Old England's Genius wakes; when with him wakes</L>
<L>That plain Integrity, Contempt of gold,</L>
<L>Disdain of slav'ry, liberal Awe of rule,</L>
<L><PB N="38" REF="39"/>Which fixt the rights of People, Peers, and Prince,<MILESTONE N="685"/></L>
<L>And on them founded the majestic pile</L>
<L>Of BRITISH FREEDOM; bad fair ALBION rise</L>
<L>The scourge of tyrants; sovereign of the seas;</L>
<L>And arbitress of empires. Oh return,</L>
<L>Ye long-lost train of Virtues! swift return<MILESTONE N="690"/></L>
<L>To save ('tis ALBION prompts your Poet's prayer)</L>
<L>Her Throne, her Altars, and her laureat Bowers.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>THE END.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="postscript">
<PB REF="40"/>
<HEAD>GENERAL POSTSCRIPT.</HEAD>
<P>FEW Poems, in the course of their composition, have been laid aside and resumed more casually, or, in con∣sequence, published more leisurely, than the foreg<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing; on which account, while it does not pretend to the Hor<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tian merit of a nine-years scrutiny under the correcting hand of its Au∣thor, it will not thence, he may perhaps hope, be found to have that demerit which arises from ill-connected parts and an indigested plan. For, as a scheme was formed for the whole four books before even the first was written; and as that scheme has since been pursued with very little, if any devia∣tion, it is presumed that the three latter books will be found strictly consonant with the general principles advanced in the former; which, as it contained the principles, and ended episodically with a kind of historic deduction of the rise and progress of the Art, might have been considered in the light of an entire work, (as the advertisement before it hinted) had the succeeding books been never written.</P>
<P>However, as the whole design is at length completed, it may not be amiss to give in this place a short analysis of the
<PB N="40" REF="41"/>
several books, in their order, to shew their connection one with another; and to obviate a few objections which have been made to certain parts of each, by some persons whose opinions I highly respect; objections which I flatter myself might arise from their having examined those parts separately, as the separate publication of the books necessarily led them to do; and which, perhaps, had they seen the whole together, they would not have found of so much importance.</P>
<P N="1">I. The first book, as I have said, contains the general Principles of the Art, which are shewn to be no other than those which constitute Beauty in the sister art of Landscape Painting; Beauty which results from a well-chosen variety of curves, in contradistinction to that of Architecture which arises from a judicious symmetry of right lines, and which is there shewn to have assorded the principle on which that formal disposition of Garden Ground, which our ancestors borrowed from the French and Dutch, proceeded. A principle never adopted by Nature herself, and therefore constantly to be avoided by those whose business it is to embellish Nature.</P>
<P><PB N="41" REF="42"/>I know of no objection that has been made to any thing that I have asserted on this head, except to that part in which I have exploded Vistas and Avenues, which, it has been said, have in themselves a considerable share of intrinsic beauty. I am myself far from denying this; I only assert that their beauty is not picturesque beauty; and therefore, that it is to be rejected by those who follow picturesque principles. It is architectural beauty, and accords only with architectural works. Where the Artist follows those principles, vistas are certainly admissible; and the French, who have so long followed them, have therefore not improperly (though one cannot help smiling at the title) given us in their Dictionary of Sciences, an article of <HI>Architecture du Jardinage</HI>. But did Gaspar Poussin, or Claude Lorrain, ever copy these beauties on their canvas? Or would they have produced a picturesque effect by their means if they had? I think this single con∣sideration will induce every person of common taste to allow that these two principles oppose one another, and that, when∣ever they appear together, they offend the eye of the beholder by their heterogeneous beauty: If therefore vistas are ever to be admitted, or rather to be retained, it is only where they form an approach to some superb mansion, so situated, that
<PB N="42" REF="43"/>
the principal prospect and ground allotted to picturesque im∣provement lie entirely on the other side; so much so, that the two different modes of planting can never appear together from any given point of view; and this is the utmost that I can concede on this subject.</P>
<P N="2">II. The picturesque principle being thus established in the first book, as well by proofs of its beauty when followed, as of the deformity which results from its being deserted, the second book proceeds to a more practical discussion of the subject, but confines itself to one point only, the disposition of the ground-plan, and, that very material business immediately united with it, the proper disposition and formation of the paths and sences. The necessity of attending constantly to the curvilinear principle is first shewn, not only in the formation of the ground-plan, with respect to its external boundary, but in its internal swellings and sinkings, where all abruptness or angular appearances are as much to be avoided as in the form of the outline that surrounds the whole.</P>
<P>The pathways or walks are next considered, and that pecu∣liar curve recommended for their imitation which is so fre∣quently
<PB N="43" REF="44"/>
found in common roads, foot-paths, &amp;c. and which being casually produced appears to be the general curve of nature.</P>
<P>The rest of the book is employed in minutely describing the method of making sunk sences, and other necessary divi∣sions of the pleasure-ground or lawn from the adjacent field or park; a part of the art which is of most essential conse∣quence, and which is frequently very difficult both to design and execute.</P>
<P>The dryness of this part of the subject led me to enliven the book with a concluding Episode, and also to throw into other places of it as much as I could of poetical embellish∣ment; in one instance perhaps improperly, because I have found it has generally been blamed. It is the apostrophe which I have made to the Genius or Muse of Painting, when I am about to teach the best colour for concealing upright fences. It has been said, "Why all this parade about daub∣ing a rail?" Now, though I believe I might defend myself <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y the practice of my Masters in Didactic Poetry, who frequently by such apostrophes endeavour to bestow con<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>quence on little
<PB N="44" REF="45"/>
matters, to which they think it necessary to call the attention, yet I rather chuse to give the objection its full force, and pro∣mise to soften the passage in the next edition; taking leave, however, here to assert in prose that it is highly necessary to observe the rule in question; because if such means be not taken for concealment, fences of that kind create much de∣formity in the general scene.</P>
<P N="3">III. The THIRD BOOK proceeds to add natural ornament to that ground-plan which the second book had ascertained, in its two capital branches, Wood and Water.</P>
<P>The formation of the outline and position of the latter might indeed have been treated in the former book: But as Water, though the greatest ornament of any rural scene, is certainly but an ornament, inasmuch as the scene may exist without it; and as there are many beautifully-adorned Places where this additional grace cannot be produced, I thought proper to consider it only as an adjunct. Somebody has said (perhaps rather quaintly, yet certainly not without good meaning) that "water is the eye, and wood the eye-brow of nature," and if so, there is surely no impropriety in treating
<PB N="45" REF="46"/>
the two features together. Certain it is, that, when united, they contribute more than any thing else to what may be called Scenical Expression, without which the picturesque Beauty we treat of loses much of its value.</P>
<P>With respect to the judicious arrangement of Wood, con∣sidered separately, I treat it under two distinct heads, that of planting it with a view of concealing defects, and introducing beauty in their place; and for the purpose of ornamenting the opener lawns. On the former of these I am more diffuse, because it is a subject which admits of precise rules. On the latter, as it is the peculiar province of Taste, and depends chiefly on the eye of the Planter, who must necessarily vary his mode of planting as peculiar situations vary, more could not be said with propriety: For, where the only thing need∣ful is to avoid formality, and to treat Nature (as Mr. Pope excellently expresses it)▪
<Q><L>like a modest fair,</L>
<L>Not over dress, nor leave her wholly bare,</L></Q>
explicit rules rather tend to mislead than to direct. I have, however, from ver. 209 to ver. 250, ventur▪ to prescribe a few material precepts which are incapable of being misapplied;
<PB N="46" REF="47"/>
and if to these be added, what I have said in the first book concerning the false taste of planting distances, I am in hopes I shall not be thought to have treated this part of my subject superficially.</P>
<P>For I would wish my reader to consider that the Plan of this Poem differs very materially in one respect from that of the Georgies of Virgil; and when I speak merely of Plan, I may hope, without appearing arrogant, to bring them to a comparison. His four books treat of four distinct subjects; Tillage, Planting, Breeding of Cattle, and Bees. He has no introductory book which treats of the general Art of Agricul∣ture: Whereas this Poem, as appears from the analysis here given, employs the first book entirely on that general subject, of which the three following are to be considered only as illu∣strations and amplifications: Where therefore that book had sufficiently explained any topic, more could not be added in any succeeding one without tautology. And this, I hope, will sufficiently obviate the objection which has been made to this part of the third book.</P>
<P><PB N="47" REF="48"/>As to the second general topic, Water, as I have heard no objections made to what I have there asserted, and believe every assertion consonant to the general principles of the art, I shall here add nothing. Yet in the little Episode at the end of it, I have been frequently questioned whom I meant by LIGEA; and it has been thought that I ought not to have run away with one of Virgil's Sea-Nymphs<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">Drymoque, Z<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nthoque, <HI>Ligeaque</HI>, Phyll<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>doceque. C<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>OR. iv. ver. <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>6</NOTE>, to transport her into an English inland scene. There is some weight in this objec∣tion; and to shew that I think so, I will here discover what I have hitherto kept as a sort of secret. The lines, where this Nymph is mentioned, were written in a very retired grove belonging to Mr. Frederic Montagu, who has long honoured me with his friendship, where a little clear trout∣stream (dignified perhaps too much by the name of a River) gurgles very dcliciously. The name of this stream is the LIN, and the spring itself rises but a little way from his plantations <NOTE N="†" PLACE="foot">At P<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pplewick, in N<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ttingh<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mshire, on the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of the Forest of S<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>wood. The village it<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> has not been without po<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tical not<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, P<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> J<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>son having taken s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me of his <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>dramat<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI>, from it, in his u<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>finished Pas<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oral Com<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>day, called <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</NOTE> I seem to find myself asked here pretty ab∣ruptly, Why then did you not call your Nymph LIN<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>? I
<PB N="48" REF="49"/>
will own the truth. I had resolved, when I first planned my Poem, to bring no instances from any individual scene: For I thought the nature of its composition, as it excluded particu∣lar satire, would not, with more propriety admit of particular panegyric; and therefore, by a slight alteration in the name, and by some other as slight deviations from the scenery, I cautiously masked the Naiad in question.</P>
<P>I will here give the reader another instance of similar cau∣tion: Finding, in the same book, occasion to explode the too great fondness for exotic plants, I thought that the most poetical way of doing it was to exhibit an instance somewhat in the same manner in which Virgil introduces his old Corycian Gardener: But to prevent all possible application, as I thought, I laid my scene on the banks of the remote Swale, where I imagined the taste for exotics had not yet reached, or at least had not yet been carried to any excess; yet I have been since told, that the neighbourhood immediately pointed out a cer∣tain very worthy Gentleman as the undoubted object of my satire, whose improvements I had never seen, nor even heard, that, from the inclemency of the climate, his plantations had ever suffered in the way that I have described. I have, there∣fore,
<PB N="49" REF="50"/>
only to desire that my readers, now possessed of one of my secrets, would substitute an N for a G where the name LIGEA occurs; and that the respectable Gentleman, now acquainted with the other, would acquit me of any premedi∣tated ridicule on his subject.</P>
<P N="4">IV. Factitious or artificial ornaments, in contradistinction to natural ones last treated, form the general subject of the FOURTH BOOK, and conclude the plan. By these is meant not only every aid which the art borrows from architecture; but those smaller pieces of separate scenery appropriated either to ornament or use, which do not make a necessary part of the whole; and which, if admitted into it, would frequently occasion a littleness ill-suiting with that unity and simplicity which should ever be principally attended to in an extensive pleasure-ground.</P>
<P>Though this subject was in itself as susceptible of poetical embellishment as any that preceded it, and much more so than those contained in the second book; yet I was appre∣hensive that descriptive poetry, however varied, might pall
<PB N="50" REF="51"/>
when continued through so long a poem; and therefore, by interweaving a tale with the general theme, I have given the whole a narrative, and in some places a dramatic cast. The idea was new, and I found the execution of it somewhat difficult: However, if I have so far succeeded as to have con∣veyed, thro' the medium of an interesting story, those more important principles of taste which this part of my subject re∣quired, and if those rules only are omitted which readily result from such as I have descriptively given; if the judicious place and arrangement of those artificial forms, which give the chief embellishment to a finished garden-scene, be distinctly noti∣ced, I am not without hope that this conclusion will be thought (as Sir Henry Wotton said of Milton's juvenile Poems at the end of a miscellany) to leave the reader in some small degree <HI>con la bocca dolce</HI>.</P>
<P>With respect to the criticisms, which may be made on this last book, there is one so likely to come from certain readers, that I am inclined to anticipate it; and taking for granted that it will be said to breathe too much of the spirit of party, to return the following ready answer: The word <HI>Party</HI>, when
<PB N="51" REF="52"/>
applied to those men, who, from private and personal motives, compose either a majority or minority in a house of parliament, or to those who out of it, on similar principles, approve or condemn the measures of any administration, is certainly in its place: But in a matter of such magnitude as the present American War, in which the dearest interests of mankind are concerned, the puny term has little or no meaning. If, how∣ever, it be applied to me on this occasion, I shall take it with much complacency, conscious that no sentiment appears in my Poem which does not prove its author to be of THE PARTY OF HUMANITY.</P>
<P>The whole of the Plan being now explained, I might here finish, did not a general objection remain which I have heard made to the species of Versification in which I chose to com∣pose it. I must, therefore, beg the reader's patience while I inform him why I preferred blank verse to rhyme on this oc∣casion.</P>
<P>When I first had the subject in contemplation, I found it admitted of two very different modes of composition: One
<PB N="52" REF="53"/>
was that of the regular Didactic Poem, of which the Georgics of Virgil afford so perfect an example; the other that of the preceptive epistolary essay, the model of which Horace has given in his Epistles <HI>Ad Augustum &amp; ad Pisones</HI>. I balanced sometime which of these I should adopt, for both had their peculiar merit. The former opened a more ample field for picturesque description and poetical embellishment; the latter was more calculated to convey exact precept in concise phrase<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">See Mr. Pope's account of his <HI>d<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>n</HI> in writing the Ess<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y on M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n, in which the peculiar merit of that way, in which he so greatly excelled, is most happily explained. He chose, as he says, "Verse, and even Rhyme, for two reasons: Verse, became precepts, so written, strike more strongly, and are retained more easily: Rhyme, be∣cause it expresses arguments or instructions more concisely than even Prose itself."</NOTE>. The one furnished better means of illustrating my subject, and the other of defining it; the former admitted those orna∣ments only which resulted from lively imagery and figurative diction, the latter seemed rather to require the seasoning of wit and satire; this, therefore, appeared best calculated to expose false taste, and that to elucidate the true. But false taste, on this subject, had been so inimitably ridiculed by Mr. Pope, in his Epistle to Lord Burlington, that it seemed to preclude all other authors (at least it precluded me) from touching it after him; and therefore, as he had left much
<PB N="53" REF="54"/>
unsaid on that part of the art on which it was my purpose principally to enlarge, I thought the Didactic method not only more open but more proper for my attempt. This mat∣ter once determined, I did not hesitate as to my choice between blank verse and rhyme; because it clearly appeared, that num∣bers of the most varied kind were most proper to illustrate a subject <HI>whose every charm springs from variety</HI>, and which painting Nature, as <HI>scorning control</HI>, should employ a versifi∣cation for that end as unfettered as Nature itself. Art at the same time, in rural improvements, pervading the province of Nature, unseen and unfelt, seemed to bear a striking analogy to that species of verse, the harmony of which results from measured quantity and varied cadence, without the too studied arrangement of final syllables, or regular return of consonant sounds. I was, notwithstanding, well aware, that by choosing to write in blank verse, I should not court popularity, because I perceived it was growing much out of vogue; but this reason, as may be supposed, did not weigh much with a writer, who meant to combat Fashion in the very theme he intended to write upon; and who was also convinced that a mode of English versification, in which so many good poems, with
<PB N="54" REF="55"/>
Paradise Lost at their head, have been written, could either not long continue unfashionable; or if it did, that Fashion had so completely destroyed Taste, it would not be worth any writer's while, who aimed at more than the reputation of the day, to endeavour to amuse the public.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<HEAD>ERRATUM.</HEAD>
<P>Ver. 665. For SIMPLICIY, read SIMPLICITY.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>
