<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2007-03-23</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Check for blanks. Checked for signatures. Checked for #s. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Corrected 93 $-groups. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N34195">
<STC T="E">44789</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99006260</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="044789_0000_101F06520CE24760"/>
<PB REF="044789_0001_101F065513A6EA10"/>
<P><HI>The</HI> TRUE CHURCH <HI>of CHRIST Described;</HI> IN A SERMON, DELIVERED AT RUTLAND, ON OTTER-CREEK; <HI>At the gathering of a</HI> CHURCH <HI>in that</HI> TOWN. OCTOBER 20th, A. D. 1783.</P>
<P><HI>By the Reverend</HI> Benajah Roots, A. M. <HI>Of late,</HI> PASTOR <HI>to the First CHURCH in</HI> SYMSBURY, CONNECTICUT.</P>
<Q><HI>Fair as the</HI> MOON; <HI>clear as the</HI> SUN, <HI>and terrible as an</HI> ARMY <HI>with</HI> BANNERS:
<BIBL>KING SOLOMON.</BIBL></Q>
<Q><HI>A Woman cloathed with the Sun, and the Moon under her Feet, and upon her Head a Crown of Twelve Stars.</HI>
<BIBL>ST. JOHN.</BIBL></Q>
<P><HI>BENNINGTON:</HI> PRINTED BY HASWELL &amp; RUSSELL.</P>
<P>1783</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="preface">
<PB REF="044789_0002_101F0657D3A5D4B8"/>
<HEAD>Preface.</HEAD>
<P>THE <HI>population of this wilderness, so lately the range of savages, and the lonesome haunt of wild beasts, echoing with the frightful screeches, and sonorous bootings of desolate owis, is truely sur∣prizing! Every town, almost, north and south, thro' that tract west of Connecticut river, lately called the province of New-Hampshire; hath more or less inhabitants: As it is probable most of the towns, in this large extended wilderness hath. One (I am in∣formed) hath more than two hundred families in it; others are various. The town of Rutland, situate about seventy miles from the north line of the pro∣vince of the Massachusett's-Bay, hath thirty-five families in it: more are coming.</HI></P>
<P><HI>But what is truly affecting is, That there is not more than one regular Minister of the standing or∣der settled, as ever I have heard of, in all this large extent; yea for a hundred miles or more, in length, and in breadth; perhaps as many from Con∣necticut river, to Hudson's river; and from the north line of Massachusett's-Bay, to Canada; in which there are even a multitude of people. And indeed, there are but few Ministers of any denomi∣nation! Not only this; but what is still more af∣fecting is, The poverty or nearness of some, and the want of an inclination in many others, seem to for∣bid their having any at all, in most places, at least
<PB N="iv" REF="044789_0003_101F06595928B068"/>
at the present; and the affecting consequences of a peo∣ple continuing long in such circumstances; with regard to religion, the worship of God, and the</HI> Salvation <HI>of their souls, is easy to be perceived by the judicious.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Having a call, in providence, to preach the Gos∣pel in this wilderness, in the midst of which I now am, and have been for some time; and being desired to assist in gathering a Church at Rutland, Octo∣ber</HI> 20, 1783; <HI>and to preach on that occasion, (to which I consented) I thought proper, as suitable to the occasion, to give a description of the true Church of Christ; without the least thoughts of its ever appearing in public: However, it now appears, with a very little alteration, from what it was, when delivered; excepting the improvement, which I have considerably enlarged.</HI></P>
<P><HI>I have but very little to say by way of apology for its publication; besides that very common one,</HI> <ABBR><HI>viz.</HI></ABBR> "That it is published at the earnest desire of those that heard it." <HI>For I have not the vanity to think, that there is any thing very extraordinary in it, to recommend it to the public: I apprehend, it contains plain truths, in a style suited to the ca∣pacity of the auditory.</HI></P>
<P><HI>I add this was some further inducement to me, to consent to its publication, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR>. That I expect many of the books will be scattered in this wilderness, where books are scarce: And if they may be of ser∣vice to form in the minds of any, just sentiments of the true Church of Christ, and awaken in them, an earnest solicitude to belong to this Church of Christ, my end is, in some measure, answered.</HI></P>
<P><HI>I shall only add, I ask the candour of my readers;
<PB N="v" REF="044789_0003_101F06595928B068"/>
to which I am ready to fancy, I am the more inti∣tled; since I am in the midst of this vast wilderness, without the ordinary helps in such cases; and desti∣tute of any of my brethren in the ministry to con∣verse or advise with.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Requesting the prayers of God's people, on behalf of the people inhabiting in this wilderness; who seem to be in imminent danger of perishing for lack of vision; I subscribe myself your servant, for Jesus sake.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>B. R.</SIGNED> <DATELINE><HI>Rutland,</HI> <DATE><HI>November</HI> 25, 1783.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="sermon">
<PB REF="044789_0004_101F065AE08B5068"/>
<HEAD>A Description of the TRUE CHURCH of CHRIST.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>I. PETER, ii. 5.</BIBL>
<Q><HI>Ye also as living Stones, are built up a</HI> SPIRITUAL HOUSE, <HI>an</HI> HOLY PRIESTHOOD, <HI>to offer up</HI> SPIRITUAL SACRIFICES, <HI>acceptable to</HI> GOD, <HI>by</HI> JESUS CHRIST.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>THE Apostle is here giving us a lively description of the true <HI>Church</HI> of <HI>Christ.</HI> Having first described the foundation of the <HI>Church,</HI> <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> Jesus Christ, whom he calls a '<HI>Living Stone,</HI>' (in the preceding verse) <Q><HI>Disallowed indeed of men, but chosen of God and precious.</HI></Q> In our text he speaks of the Church, under the same metaphor, '<HI>Living Stones,'</HI><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><P><HI>Living Stones;</HI> is according to the translation in my Bi∣ble: Since the composure of the Sermon, I have seen it translated '<HI>Lively,</HI>' In some other Bibles.</P>
<P>But, as I have not the original by me, nor is it in these parts; by which I might determine which is the rightest; therefore I shall let it stand as it is penn'd.</P></NOTE> '<HI>Ye also as Living Stones,' &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>Where we may observe, he (the Apostle) de∣scribes the Church.</P>
<P>I. By her likeness to Christ, with respect to internal, spiritual or divine life; '<HI>living.</HI>'</P>
<P>II. By her stability '<HI>Stones.</HI>'</P>
<P><PB REF="044789_0005_101F065DB98EC1A8"/>
III. By her union with herself; '<HI>Built up a Spiritual House.</HI>'</P>
<P>IV. By her divine constitution; '<HI>An Holy Priesthood.</HI>'</P>
<P>V. By her exercises; '<HI>To offer up Sacrifices.</HI>'</P>
<P>VI. By the quality of these sacrifices, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> '<HI>Spiritual and holy.</HI>'</P>
<P>VII. By their acceptance with God; '<HI>Accep∣table to God.</HI>'</P>
<P>VIII. By whose merits these spiritual sacri∣fices are acceptable to God, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> The merits of Christ, '<HI>Acceptable to God by Jesus Christ.</HI>' Each of these particulars, in the description of the true Church of Christ, I purpose briefly to con∣sider.</P>
<P>I. THE first decription of the true Church, is in her likeness to Christ, her foundation, with respect to her internal, spiritual or divine life; '<HI>Living.</HI>'</P>
<P>'<HI>Christ lives;</HI> and because he lives,' '<HI>They shall live also.</HI>' John 14. 19.</P>
<P>Every true member <HI>lives by Christ's life,</HI> for he lives in them; '<HI>I live,</HI>' (saith the Apostle) <HI>yet not I, but Christ liveth in me.</HI> Gal. XX. 20.</P>
<P>So likewise, they have the same <HI>kind</HI> of spiri∣tual life, that is in Christ. Jesus Christ <HI>a living Stone;</HI> the foundation of this spiritual building! So likewise, the true members of his Church are <HI>living Stones;</HI> compacted together in this building▪ The foundation and the superstruc∣ture are alike in this; they are <HI>living Stones.</HI> This spiritual life consists in holiness, divine love or benevolence. Some indeed suppose, that
<PB N="9" REF="044789_0005_101F065DB98EC1A8"/>
holiness is nothing but divine love; because what the law of God requires of us, is holiness, and the sum of what the law requires of us, is love: Love is the fulfilling of the law; (saith the Apostle.) And upon these two command∣ments of love to God and our neighbour, our Saviour makes to hang all the law and the pro∣phets. However, some would make a little difference between holiness and divine love: Holiness in God (they say) is the sum of all his divine attributes: And holiness in men they make comprehensive of all the variety of christian graces, to be exercised in the life of a christian; as love, joy, peace, long suffering, gentleness, goodness, faith, meekness, and temperance; which are called the fruits of the holy spirit; Gal. v. 22, 23. And can any say, and say truly, that divine love, or benevolence, is not com∣prehended of all the forementioned graces? Doubtless holiness, is to be universally of a right temper of mind: So likewise, for ought I know, love is radically this; a man destitute of love, hath no right temper; without divine love, he doeth nothing that is truly virtuous; nothing that is truly praise worthy; without this, no∣thing is done from a right principle, or to a right end: He that hath no true love to God, hath no sincere regard to his glory, in any thing that he doth. Without this, faith hath no real good∣ness, or moral virtue in it. All gifts &amp; knowledge is vain without it: Yea, had a man all faith, so that he could remove mountains, and understood all mysteries, and could speak with the tongues of
<PB N="10" REF="044789_0006_101F065F81E46FA0"/>
men and angels, and was destitute of this di∣vine principle, they would make him no better than sounding brass, or a tinkling cymbal; a bare sign or representation of something, when there is really nothing! Nay, should a man give all his goods to feed the poor, and his body to be burnt in sacrifice for his religion, and be desti∣tute of love, it would profit him nothing: See all this confirmed, I Cor. Chap. xiii. Love is the very soul and essence of every grace, and the distinguishing character of a good man, for with∣out this, he is a wicked man, and dead in tres∣passes and sins. Love therefore, is the sum of all moral virtue, and of every christian grace; yea the very soul and life of them all: As without natural or animal life, there would be no natural actions; so also without <HI>divine love,</HI> there would be no spiritual action. <HI>Natural self-love</HI> excites natural men to those <HI>exercises,</HI> or ac∣tions, which are proper for moral agents: So su∣pernatural and divine love excites to those <HI>spiri∣tual exercises</HI> and <HI>holy actions,</HI> which are <HI>peculiar</HI> to a <HI>renewea man.</HI> Without love of some kind or other, I cannot conceive of a man's acting at all, as a moral agent; and without supernatu∣ral or divine love, I can have no apprehension of his acting at all in a spiritual manner; or with the least regard to God, any more than I can conceive of a man's acting as a natural man, without natural life. Hence it is, I apprehend, that divine love is called <HI>spiritual life:</HI> And cer∣tain it is, without divine love, men are dead, yea, wholly dead, in a spiritual sense. But the
<PB N="11" REF="044789_0006_101F065F81E46FA0"/>
true members of Christ's Church, are conforma∣ble to their spiritual and public head, in this; Christ the <HI>living Stone,</HI> in the foundation of his Church, and the Church built up of <HI>living Stones,</HI> upon this foundation</P>
<P>II. The true Church of Christ is described by her stability, <HI>Stones.</HI> A metaphor borrowed from Stones which are compacted into a building, with an adjective, expressing their peculiar, and distinguishing quality, <HI>living Stones.</HI> A Stone is solid and durable, not easily moved with the wind; when wrought into a building, they continue for a great length of time. So the Church of Christ, compared to <HI>living Stones,</HI> built upon Christ, the <HI>living Stone,</HI> is durable, staple and firm: It continues through every age, firm as the everlasting mountains: It continues through all the convulsions of States and King∣doms. Whatever devastations and revolutions take place, in the world, the Church must live; though earth and hell conspire together to de∣stroy it, '<HI>Yet must this building rise!</HI>' Though Satan, with all his malicious arts, and diabolical subtilty, lay ten thousand snares to destroy it, he cannot prevail; <HI>for it is founded on a rock.</HI> He that fights against her, fights against God; who will be sure to avenge '<HI>The quarrel.'</HI> 'Tis with respect to the Church that he says <Q><HI>Touch not mine anointed, and do my prophets no harm?</HI></Q> Psal. cv, 15. Hurt not (q. d.) the people con∣secrated to me, by the gifts and graces of my spirit; and those, especially among them, to whom I farmiliarly reveal my mind and will, that
<PB N="12" REF="044789_0007_101F066246E843C8"/>
they may teach others. The Church is called the bride, the lamb's wife, and is most dear to the almighty bridegroom: And whosoever touches his bride, (i.e. hurts or injures her,) shall find the arm of her almighty husband to be strong; who will '<HI>Soon avenge the wrong.</HI>' For thus saith the Lord, to his Church; '<HI>He that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of mine eye..</HI>' Zach. 2, 8. And how <HI>precious!</HI> how <HI>dear!</HI> the Church of Christ is to him, he hath manifest∣ed in many striking instances of his providence, in punishing those that injured or were unkind to her. For this cause he plagued and destroyed the Egyptians, and when they pursued his peo∣ple to the red sea, they were all myraculously drowned in it; they sank as lead in the mighty waters; yea they sank like a stone to the bot∣tom: That this was the case is further evident from Joel, iii, 19. <HI>Egypt shall be a desolation, for the violence against the children of Judah, because they shed innocent blood in their land.</HI> How did it fare with the Amalekites for their unkindness, because they did not meet God's antient Church with bread and water; but instead of this, they smote the hindermost part of them that were weary and faint; therefore the Lord gave it in charge, utterly to destroy Amalak, and to blot out his name from under heaven; which was fully accomplished.</P>
<P>And how did it fare with the Babylonians, for captivating God's people? though done by his permission and direction of his providence. They were threatned with perpetual desolation for it,
<PB N="13" REF="044789_0007_101F066246E843C8"/>
which threatning has been and still is fulfilling: <Q><HI>Babylon shall become a heap, a dwelling place for dragons, an astonishment, and an hissing, without an inhabitant.</HI></Q> Jer. ii 37. This city, though the most extensive, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> magnificent of any in the known world, is made a perpetual deso∣lation, <HI>never more to be built or inhabited from ge∣neration to generation forever.</HI> See Jer. I. 39, 40, ver▪ and Isa. xiii, 19, to the end, where the desolation, perpetual desolation of Babylon, is very fully and emphatically expressed. And how did it fare with the Jews themselves, when they rejected the King of Zion, and persecuted his Church? Why he <HI>miserably destroyed those murderers, and burnt up their city Jerusalem.</HI> Tho' Kings, Rulers and people of Israel joined to de∣stroy the Church, yet they failed. What though with hand joined in hand, they set themselves against the Lord, and against his anointed, yet, <Q><HI>He that sitteth in the Heavens laughed, as the Lord then had them in derision.</HI></Q> And though all the powers of Rome, when she was mistress of the world, were bent to destroy and to root out the christian name, from under Heaven; though she (Rome) murdered millions, and christian blood flowed down like rivers; she could not prevail. Under all these trials, the Church rather increased, than diminished; the suffering of one martyr was sometimes the means of converting numbers. They who per∣secuted the Church, made war with the lamb, and he overcame them; for he is <HI>Lord of Lords and King of King's.</HI> Rev. xvii, 14. Thus staple
<PB N="14" REF="044789_0008_101F06650FF426F8"/>
and firm is the true Church of Christ, and no∣thing shall be able to destroy it: earth and hell have tried out their strength, in combinations and have not prevailed; for the Lord God and the Lamb is in the midst of her. He keeps her, he watches over her with as much care and ten∣derness as the apple of his eye; and the gates of hell cannot prevail against her, cannot overcome her. Thus the church is firmer than heaven and earth, and more unshaken than the solid world; her foundation is strong, she is built up∣on a living rock, from which she cannot be sha∣ken or removed, for she is united to it, and the union is indissoluble.</P>
<P>III. The true church of Christ is described by her union with herself, <HI>built up a spiritual house.</HI></P>
<P>This metaphor shews how the church is unit∣ed with itself. As stones which are compacted to∣gether in a building, by the artist, are all united together and make one house; so the Church of Christ, as <HI>living stones,</HI> is one <HI>spiritual house built</HI> together by the great master builder, in which house he dwells forever. As this building is unit∣ed to the living stone which is its foundation, so likewise these <HI>living stones</HI> which compose this building, are united among themselves, cement∣ed in love, which holds it together, and the uni∣on is indissoluble: Not one living stone shall e∣ver fail in this building. For this the redeemer prayed and his prayer is always effectual. John xvii. 11, 21, 22, 23. "Holy father, keep through thine own name those whom thou hast given me, <HI>that they may be one as we are.'</HI> <Q><HI>That they all
<PB N="15" REF="044789_0008_101F06650FF426F8"/>
may be one,</HI> as thou father art in me, and I in thee, that they also may be ONE in us: And the glory, which thou gavest me, have I gi∣ven them; that they may be ONE, even as we are ONE: I in them and thou in me; that they may be made perfect in ONE: That the world may know that thou hast sent me, and hast <HI>loved them even as thou hast loved me.</HI></Q></P>
<P>The Church is called <Q><HI>The only one</HI> of her mother, and the <HI>choice one</HI> of her that bare her.</Q> Cant. vi, 9, which denotes that the Church of Christ is <HI>one,</HI> and is most dear to him, who is the great founder of it. This union in the Church, the Apostle describes by the similitude of a hu∣man body, which is united to the head, by joints and bands, from which it receives nou∣rishment, and being knit together it increaseth, with the increase of God, Coll. ii, 19. and that which cements together the several parts of Christ's mystical body, (the Church) is love, Coll. ii, 2. <HI>Being knit together in love.</HI> The liv∣ing members, in Christ's Church, are <HI>one,</HI> in all the following respects, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> They all have one and the same public head, even Christ, from whom they receive spiritual nourishment and growth in grace. They all trust their salvation in his merits alone. They all with one consent hold the essential doctrines of the Gospel, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> Such as these, Salvation from sin and hell, by free and sovereign grace alone, bestowed thro' the merits of the great Redeemer. Their de∣pendence is solely upon the righteousness of Christ to clothe them in the sight of a holy God; they
<PB N="16" REF="044789_0009_101F0666F14678B0"/>
all trust in the merits of his blood, for the at∣tonement of their sins: The merit of his obedi∣ence, &amp; death for the justification of their persons, and acceptance with God, both of their persons and services; eternal life and happiness in the enjoyment of God: They all depend upon his spirit and grace to sanctify them and make them meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the saints in light. In these they all agree, if they are capable of understanding doctrines: If there be babes in Christ, that do not clearly under∣stand doctrines at present, yet surely they have a disposition to understand, and as soon as they do understand, or have just notions of the truth, they cordially embrace it: They have a <HI>spiritual taste</HI> and <HI>appetite</HI> for the doctrines of free grace; they are pleased with them and like them in their hearts; for like new born babes, in health, they desire the sincere milk of the word, that they may grow thereby, which no unsanctified soul doth. Doubtless there are ma∣ny, who have so much light and conviction of the truth, that they are forced to acknowledge it; yet have no love for it; no appetite for it at all in their hearts. They may have the form of knowledge and of the truth, who do not love it: This the Apostle asserts Rom. ii. 20, to 24. concerning those to whom he does not give a very good character, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR>. That they made their boast of the law, and knew God's will, but ne∣ver taught themselves; to whom he says, '<HI>The name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles through you.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="17" REF="044789_0009_101F0666F14678B0"/>
<HI>Once more, every living member of Christ's Church have all the same spirit of divine love, that bond of perfectness, of which the Apostle speaks,</HI> Coll. iii: 14. <HI>Wherever they are scattered up and down the world, this is the spirit that dwells in them;</HI>' this their distinguishing character: By the <HI>spirits of love,</HI> or true benevolence, which they have to each other <Q><HI>All men may know, that they are Christ's disciples,</HI></Q> John xiii. 35 <Q><HI>And by this, we may know, that we are of God; and that he dwelleth in us, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR>. by the spirit which he hath given us,</HI></Q> As saith the Apostle, I John iii. 24. And to the same purpose is the Apostle Rom. viii. 9, <Q><HI>If any man have not the spirit of Christ, he is none of his.</HI></Q></P>
<P>False pretenders to religon, may profess themselves to be his disciples, when they are intirely destitute of the distinguishing character of his true disciples, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> <HI>divine love.</HI> Doubt∣less there are many such professors, who are in∣tirely destitute of any true love, either to God or man: We have a record of some, who pro∣fessed well, and no doubt had a very good opi∣nion of themselves, to whom Christ says, <Q><HI>I know you, that ye have not the love of God in you.</HI></Q> Not all that profess faith in Christ, will put their trust in him; the scribes and pharisees professed to believe in a Messiah to come, but when he came, they rejected him; they <Q><HI>Trust∣ed in themselves that they were righteous, and despised others;</HI></Q> and what reason is there to think, but many at the present day, are of the same spirit; they profess to believe in Christ,
<PB N="18" REF="044789_0010_101F0668ADBF0388"/>
but trust in themselves, '<HI>Walking in the light of their own fire, and in the sparks which they have kindled.</HI>' There were some who professed to be Christ's disciples, his cordial friends; to whom he would not commit himself, but hid himself from them, because he knew them, he knew their hearts; <Q><HI>For he knew all men, and needed not that any should testify of man, for he knew what was in man,</HI></Q> John ii. 24. 25. Yea many that professed to be Christ's disciples, and were so called, took disgust at some important doc∣trines which he taught, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of attonement, <HI>That they <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> walked no more with him▪</HI> John <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> what if some renounced their <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Christ and the gospel, and forsook the <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and fel∣lowship of his true disciples <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> an evi∣dence that they did not belong to them. <Q><HI>They went out from us,</HI> (saith the Apostle) <HI>But they were not of us, for if they had been of us, they would, no doubt, have continued with us; but they went out, that they might be made ma∣nifest, that they were not all of us.</HI></Q> 'Tis no∣thing strange, that that, which hath no root or deepness of earth, should wither away: It is nothing strange, that those who are not <HI>living Stones,</HI> and not belonging to Christ's building; having no special grace, no love to Christ in their hearts; nothing strange, for these to re∣nounce their profession, and turn to another, where they can better gratify their pride or their passions in so doing: But the living members of Christ have an <HI>unction</HI> from the <HI>holy one,</HI> i. e.
<PB N="19" REF="044789_0010_101F0668ADBF0388"/>
an holy anointing, from the holy spirit, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> Those divine influences, or special graces shed abroad in the heart, which secures them from falling; 'tis an unfailing bond, which holds them fast, and forever secures them; it is the bond of perfectness; therefore they shall never finally fall away: This bond of perfectness, or divine love maintains the union among them∣selves.</P>
<P>IV. THE Church is described by her divine constitution, <HI>an holy priesthood.</HI> One special part of the priests office, under the law, was to offer sacrifices. Besides this, they were to be whol∣ly devoted to God, seperated from the world, and to be constantly employ'd in the service of the sanctuary, and in teaching the people▪ in allusion to this, the Church of Christ is called <HI>a holy priesthood,</HI> in the text; because she is to be seperated to the service of God: she offers up herself as <Q>A living sacrifice, holy and ac∣ceptable to God, through Jesus Christ: And hath made us, (says the church) Kings and priests unto God, and his <HI>father,</HI></Q> Rev i. 6. This spiritual and holy priesthood, is peculiarly descriptive of the true Church of Christ, it is their peculiar and distinguishing character, as it cannot justly be attributed to any other. None truly give up themselves to God, as liv∣ing sacrifices, none are devoted to his service but saints; of which are composed the true Church of Christ.</P>
<P>V. The true Church of Christ is described by her exercises, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> <HI>to offer up sacrifices:</HI> which she
<PB N="20" REF="044789_0011_101F066B158A5FB0"/>
does in consequences of her divine constitution, '<HI>A holy priesthood.</HI>'</P>
<P>These sacrifices consist in the offering up of their souls, their bodies, with all their powers and faculties to God, to be employed in his ser∣vice. Their hearts are given to God; (i. e.) <HI>they sincerely love him.</HI> It is not uncommon for lovers to say to the beloved friend, <Q>You have my heart! or I have given you my heart!</Q> So the Church of Christ has given him her heart; and Christ hath set his heart upon the Church, his spouse: the divine will is her will; this is the rule by which she walks. She choos∣es those things which God chooses; Christ and his Church have the same object of love and hatred: she is ready both to do and to suffer for Christ's sake. <Q><HI>In the worship of her God, she spends her daily breath.</HI></Q> She dearly loves the worship and ordinances of Christ, where he is wont to reveal his power and grace: She loves to hear of Christ, of his love and divine excellencies: And her meditation of him is sweet, even in the night watches; she is ready to part with all for his sake; to sacrifice name, estate, and life itself, for his sake <Q><HI>whom her soul loveth.</HI></Q> Yea to esteem reproaches, for Christ, to be great riches, Heb. xi. 26▪ She can take joyfully the spoiling of her goods, and part with father and mother, and other near and dear relatives, houses and lands, and life itself for his sake and the Gosple's. Unless men can part with all for Christ's sake and the Gospel's, they are not, nor can they be his true deciples; (this
<PB N="21" REF="044789_0011_101F066B158A5FB0"/>
we have from his own mouth) this truth is il∣lustrated from the words of the Apostle; <Q><HI>I am not only ready to be bound</HI> (says he) <HI>but to die for the name of Jesus,</HI></Q> Acts, xxi, 13. <Q><HI>yea, doubtless, and I count all things but loss, for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord, for whom I have suffered the loss of all things, and do count them but dung,</HI></Q> &amp;c. Phil. iii. 8. And, not only St. Paul, but every living mem∣ber in the Church of Christ, is ready to sa∣crifice every thing, and count them as dung for Christ's sake. In this manner the Church offers up sacrifice to God.</P>
<P>VI. The Church is further described by the quality of those sacrifices which she offers, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> <HI>spiritual and holy,</HI> they are not such earnal sacri∣fices, as were in use under the law; nor do they consist in modes and forms or meer bodily exer∣cises, which profiteth little, I. Tim. iv. 8. which may be done intirely without the heart; but they are sacrifices spiritual and holy; spiritual sacrifices, are such religious exercises, as are per∣formed by the special and genuine influences of the holy spirit; from whence the term spiritu∣al is taken in scripture. They are such exer∣cises therefore, as are peculiar to the spiritual man, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> Saints; and is given in our text, as one of the distinguishing characteristics of the true Church of Christ: Certainly, none but spiritual men of∣fer spiritual and holy sacrifices; and the spiritual man in the scripture dialect, is the distinguish∣ing character of a good man, or a true Saint, I Cor. ii. 14, 15, and Gal. vi. I. The natural
<PB N="22" REF="044789_0012_101F066CD42A4EC8"/>
man receiveth not the things of the spirit of God, &amp;c. <HI>But he that is spiritual judgeth all things: Ye which are spiritual, restore such an one in the spirit of meekness:</HI> By which it is abun∣dantly plain, that by a spiritual man, he means a true Saint, or a living member in Christ's Church. And it is peculiar to such as are spi∣ritual, to offer up spiritual sacrifices; otherwise a corrupt tree may bring forth good fruit; but in a word, spiritual and holy sacrifices, are such exercises as God requires, being done with those inward and holy affections; such as faith, love, joy, &amp;c. which are effected and maintained by the holy spirit of grace, dwelling in those who are the subjects of those graces, by his genuine operations, in which he communicates his own image or nature: Such are said to <HI>be made partakers of the divine nature.</HI></P>
<P>VII. THE true Church of Christ is described by the acceptance of her sacrifices, '<HI>Acceptable to God.</HI>' By this the living members of Christ's Church are distinguished from all others; none besides those who belong to the true Church are <HI>acceptable to God:</HI> The sacrifices, i. e. Spiritual sacrifices of the true Church alone, are acceptable to God; '<HI>But the sacrifices of the wicked are an abomination.</HI>' Do you desire to know what acceptance means? I will endeavour to inform you. In our text it must mean <HI>favora∣bly</HI> or <HI>kindly</HI> to <HI>receive;</HI> it signifies, being <HI>pleased,<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> delighted with;</HI> thus God is pleased or <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with his Church. This is evident in <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> he is said to see '<HI>No spot or wrinkle in her'</HI>▪
<PB N="23" REF="044789_0012_101F066CD42A4EC8"/>
It is further evident, in that he is said '<HI>To re∣joice over her.</HI>' That the Lord Jesus likewise takes peculiar pleasure and delight in his Church and in the exercise of her graces, is evident from many endearing appellations, that he gives her as <Q><HI>My sister, my spouse, my love, my dove, my un∣defiled;</HI></Q> often repeated, <Q>I am come into my garden, my sister, my spouse: <HI>I have gathered my myrrh with my spice; I have eaten my honey comb with my honey; I have drank my wine with my milk.</HI></Q> Cant. V, I. These expressions, no doubt, have reference to the Church's graces, in which he greatly delights; that the prayers of the Saints are pleasing and delightful to God, is evident, in that they are compared to <HI>incense,</HI> Rev v, 8. (which was a rich perfume, used in sacrifices by God's appointment, typify∣ing the precious blood of Christ,) likewise the preaching of the Gospel, by the faithful ministers of Christ, is mentioned as most pleasing and ac∣ceptable to God; though some did not believe, 2 Cor. ii, 15. '<HI>We are unto God,'</HI> <Q><HI>A sweet sa∣vour of Christ, in them that are saved, and in them that perish;</HI></Q> and in a word, every spiri∣tual sacrifice is pleasing and acceptable to God; which he will most graciously reward; this brings me to say.</P>
<P>VIII. BY whose merits these spiritual sacri∣fices are acceptable to God, '<HI>Acceptable to God by Jesus Christ.</HI>' That is, by his merits: excel∣lent as the Church is, and, however high in God's account, yet neither the Church nor her sacri∣fices, (or religious services) are acceptable to
<PB N="24" REF="044789_0013_101F06735BAB86D0"/>
God on account of her own merits or excellency, but wholly by the merits of Christ; she is ac∣counted righteous, by his righteousness imput∣ed; acquitted from the guilt of sin, by the vir∣tue of his atonement; made holy by the sanc∣tification of his spirit; otherwise she could not be acceptable to God. Hence it is, we are said to '<HI>Be made accepted in the beloved,'</HI> Eph. i. 6. The prayers of <HI>all</HI> Saints are said to ascend, with the incense of Christ's merit, see Rev. viii, 3, 4. However it may be, that some sinners expect acceptance with God, on account of their own excellencies and virtue of their good deeds (as it is certain they have no dependence upon, or trust in the merits of Christ) yet it may be presumed, that the Saints, or the living members of Christ, (acting in character) have no dependence upon any goodness or merit of their own, to recom∣mend them to the divine favour; nor indeed, do they so much as desire acceptance with God, either of their persons or services, but by the merits of Christ; because in no other way, can God, consistently with the honor of his divine, perfections, accept of them: And as they love the divine honor, they cannot in any other way, desire acceptance. This, in one view, is the true Church of Christ, <ABBR>viz.</ABBR> She is alive; all the members in this Church, are living members of Christ; they live, by Christ living in them: The life is a spiritual and divine life: The same kind of life is in every true member of this mys∣tical body of Christ; as is in the divine head: From this divine head, spritual life is commu∣nicated
<PB N="25" REF="044789_0013_101F06735BAB86D0"/>
to every true▪ member in this building; the foundation and the superstructure are alike. The essence of this life, consists in holiness or divine love. This house (the Church) is built upon a rock, and built with <HI>living Stones;</HI> there∣fore no storms can overthrow it: The blowing winds, and driving rains, how fiercely soever they beat upon it, cannot overturn it: No storms of persecution; no trial or temptation nor yet the gates of hell can overcome it.</P>
<P>Not one of these living Stones, shall ever be jostled from its foundation; not one can ever be moved out of its place; nor one Stone sepe∣rated from another, in this building; for they are cemented together by an indissoluble union: And the cement that holds them together, is divine love, which never fails. <HI>Charity never faileth:</HI> This is a <HI>Royal Priesthood,</HI> whose busi∣ness is to offer up spiritual sacrifices; which are holy and acceptable to God, by the merits of Christ; by which she is distinguished from all others: None of all the human race besides, can be compared to her in these respects; no o∣ther can offer such sacrifices: The sacrifices of the rest of mankind, are carnal and dead; as dif∣ferent as those offered by Cain and Able; but the sacrifices offered by this Royal Priesthood, are spiritual and holy, pleasing and acceptable to God; in which he smells a sweet savour, being perfumed with the most costly <HI>incense;</HI> the pre∣cious <HI>merits, righteousness</HI> and <HI>atoning blood of God,</HI> Acts xx. 28. Thus I have endeavoured to give you a plain description of the true Church of Christ; agreeable to our text.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="application">
<PB N="26" REF="044789_0014_101F0676895D23F8"/>
<HEAD>I now proceed to the IMPROVEMENT.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Improvement.</HEAD>
<P>FROM this description of the Church of Christ, it is easy to perceive, even at the very first blush, that no unrenewed, unbelieving person, belongs to the true Church of Christ. They have none of those distinguishing charac∣teristics of his true Church, as for instance, they have no <HI>spiritual or divine life or love:</HI> They are not <HI>built upon the living Stone,</HI> Christ Jesus, the foundation of the Church: They have no union with Christ the head: They derive no spiritual nourishment from him: If they creep into his fold among his sheep, they come not in by Christ, the door; but climb over some other way; and after all, they are but goats, who leave a stinking savour behind them; and will be set on the left hand of Christ, in the last great day of trial. Though they eat and drink at his table, they are not nourished; and will at last be disowned by Christ: And though they have had the faith of miracles, and have cast out devils in his name, he will bid them depart ac∣cursed into everlasting fire: And though they be counted among the living branches in Christ the vine, they have no vital union with him nor do they derive any sap or nourishment from him, but are dry and useless branches, that will be pruned off and cast into the fire. They have
<PB N="27" REF="044789_0014_101F0676895D23F8"/>
no proper and indissoluble union among the living branches: If in any respect, they may be said to be united to the Saints, it is an im∣proper sense; the union can be no better, nor any other, than <HI>the union of the dead and the living together;</HI> in which case there can be no <HI>spiritual communion.</HI> Communion signifies fellowship, a par∣ticipation, or receiving together▪ But living and dead branches have no fellowship; com∣munion, or participation of vital sap from the true vine Christ Jesus; for <Q><HI>For what communi∣on on hath light with darkness, or what part have be∣lievers with unbelievers.</HI></Q> "Can the dead a∣rise and eat the banquet of the living?" (saith Mr. J. Allen.) And can they any more, who are spiritually dead, participate of the spiritual banquets of those spiritually alive? Surely no. And however, graceless, unrenewed souls, may be numbered in the Church of Christ; they are not living, but dead; and truly and really be∣long not to it; for this building is made up of living Stones; not one dead Stone is to be found in it; but of <HI>living Stones, is built a spiritual house.</HI> This is another distinguishing character, which every graceless-person is destitute of; for they never have the character of spiritual, but carnal, given to them in scripture: Spiritual and carnal are very different and opposite cha∣racters; by which Saints and sinners are distin∣guished. The term spiritual is taken from the holy siprit, (as before noted) they and they on∣ly, are called spiritual in the scripture dialect; in whom the holy spirit dwells, by his genuine
<PB N="28" REF="044789_0015_101EFEB3799C1F88"/>
operations; in which he communicates his own nature; <HI>but not his divine essence:</HI> The nature which he communicates is a temper or disposi∣tion of mind like himself, i. e. the moral image of God in the soul. Now this indwelling of the holy spirit is peculiar to the Saints. Hence the Apostle saith, '<HI>If any man have not the spirit of Christ, he is none of his.</HI>' That it is abundantly evident, that no unrenewed person, can have a∣ny just pretensions to union with, or interest in this spiritual house, the true Church. Nor can they lay any just claim to this holy Priesthood; they are not yet set apart, (by the divine influ∣ences of the holy spirit) to offer spiritual sacri∣fices; this they can have no just pretensions to; for none but spiritual men can offer spiritual sa∣crifices. They never gave up themselves, soul and body to God; nor any thing that is their's, to be employed in his service. That unholy souls do not offer up spiritual sacrifices, is evi∣dent; because these sacrifices are holy: And a corrupt tree cannot bring forth good fruit; <HI>nor doth a bitter fountain send forth sweet waters. Men do not gather grapes of thorns, or figs of this∣tles.</HI> Even nature itself teaches, that the fruit cannot be superior to the tree that bears it. By these similitudes our saviour shews, that it is the distinguished character of a good man, to bring forth good fruit, as he himself explains it.</P>
<P>Furthermore, no graceless person can justly pretend to acceptance with God: Acceptance, as heretofore explained, signifies to be pleased or delighted, &amp;c. But God can be pleased, or
<PB N="29" REF="044789_0015_101EFEB3799C1F88"/>
delighted with no one out of Christ, as hath been shewn; that even the Saints <Q><HI>Are made accepted in the beloved,</HI></Q> Eph. vi. 6. Upon whose account then do Christless, graceless sin∣ners expect acceptance? Not on Christ, surely; for they reject him, and are not united to him; but this <HI>union to Christ, is the ground upon which Saints are accepted.</HI></P>
<P>Nor can graceless sinners, expect acceptance with a God of infinite holiness, on their own account, without the most daring presump∣tion and infidelity; for if Saints, who have some degree of holiness within, '<HI>Are made ac∣cepted only in Christ the beloved,</HI>' in whose righte∣ousness shall the wicked and ungodly appear. Not in their own indeed▪ for that is no better than filthy rags; and when trusted in for ac∣ceptance, is odious and detestable in the sight of God; whose abhorence of it, is expressed, by its being <Q><HI>A smoke in his nose, a fire that burneth all the day.</HI></Q> His abhorence is further mani∣fest by his fearful declaration, concerning those <HI>that walk</HI> in the light of their own fire, and in the sparks which they had kindled; <Q><HI>This shall ye have at mine hand,</HI> (saith the Lord) <HI>ye shall lie down in sorrow.</HI></Q> This is further evident from the accumulated woes, denounced against the scribes and pharisees; <HI>Who trusted in them∣selves that they were righteous and despised others.</HI> Hence it appears, that sinners are not accepted, either by Christ's rightousness, or their own, for the reasons mentioned above.</P>
<P N="2"><PB N="30" REF="044789_0016_101F067E1E1975A8"/>
2d. Is the true Church so high in God's ac∣count, as you have heard; as dear as the apple of his eye: We hence learn, how dear she should be to us! How high in our esteem! For what God highly esteems and values, he would have as highly esteemed and valued to▪ It is ration∣al and fit, that what God has set his greatest and everlasting love upon (in union with the glory of his own attributes,) that his rational and in∣telligent creatures, should also, in like manner, set their hearts upon: And God hath set his un∣changeable, and everlasting <HI>love,</HI> upon his Church, <HI>Christ hath redeemed it with his own blood</HI>▪ Acts xx. 28.▪ So ought we to <HI>engrave her as upon the palms of our hands; and set her as a signet up∣on our right arm, as a seal upon our heart.</HI> As Christ laid down his life for the Church; so ought we '<HI>To lay down our lives for the brethren,</HI> saith the Apostle.</P>
<P>We hence learn, how excellent the Church is is. This appears from her being so greatly be loved by the sacred three: True she is imperfect in herself and in her outward dress, according to the divine law, considered in a seperate view, (mean without her relation to Christ,) but view her as united to her husband, Christ Jesus; and she '<HI>Has no spot nor wrinkle, nor any such thing</HI> as saith the Apostle: She is compleatly adorned with the righteousness of the law; for Christ is the end of <HI>the law for righteousness, to every o<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> that believeth,</HI> Rom. x. 4. There is none to <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> compared with her, especially, if we consider her in her married state: <Q><HI>She is excellent as the Ce∣dars
<PB N="31" REF="044789_0016_101F067E1E1975A8"/>
comely as <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>irzah, looking forth as the morning: Fair as the Moon; clear as the Sun; and terrible as an Army with Banners.</HI></Q></P>
<P>As to internal excellencies; she has all those divine virtues or graces, which are to be found in Christ her head and husband; who hath '<HI>Formed her beauties like his own.</HI>' She has re∣ceived of his fulness, and grace for grace; grace answering to the grace that is in Christ: She is compared to a bride adorned for her husband, Rev. xxi. 2. She is compared to the King's daughter, <Q><HI>All glorious within, and her garments of wrought gold;</HI></Q> and her beloved calls her '<HI>The fairest</HI>' among women: Her spiritual beau∣ties are described by metaphors borrowed almost from every thing excellent in nature. Howe∣ver, the shines not altogether with reflected rays like the moon, which is a dark body, and shines only as it is shone upon. The sun shines upon the moon, and from thence its rays are reflected to the earth, but after all it hath no light in itself; but it is not so with the Church of Christ: True she hath nothing that she did not receive; but then, the divine excellencies that make her shine, <HI>are living principles within, which will continue and abide forever: God dwells in his Church, in every member of it; Christ lives in them, as you have heard. The Holy Ghost lives and dwells in every true member of Christ's Church forever; and is in them, a foundation of light, love, joy and eve∣ry grace. They are made partakers of the divine nature; they have the divine image in them;</HI> they are become <HI>little suns, which shine always, yea will eternally shine; they have light within.</HI></P>
<P N="4"><PB N="32" REF="044789_0017_101F06821CE92368"/>
4th. Is the Church so dear to God, so high in his esteem, as you have heard? Hence see how very dangerous it is to injure this spouse of Christ, though but in one of her members; touch her, and you touch the apple of his eye; injure her, and his almighty arm shall soon a∣venge the wrong. She is injured, when she is deprived of the ministry of the word and ordi∣nances of the Gospel; those breasts of consola∣tion, by which she is refreshed, and her spiritual appetite regaled. The word and ordinances of God, are those cloudy cysterns, from which dis∣til inriching and refreshing showers upon them; therefore, whoever deprives her of these, greatly injures her.</P>
<P>This may be done many ways; but particu∣larly, she may be deprived of the word and or∣dinances of the Gospel, by raising persecution a∣gainst her, or her officers; either with the sword of steel, or of the tongue: This may be done by stiring up the people against the Pastor, or against the truth, unjustly fomenting divisions: A house divided against itself, cannot stand: Schisms and rents in the body wounds it, divide it in the midst, and it is destroyed. True it is, this Church of Christ can never be destroyed; yet it may be wounded and injured; <Q>For it must needs be (saith our Lord) that offences come, but woe unto that man, by whom the offence cometh; it were better for him that a mill∣stone were hanged about his neck, and he drowned in the midst of the sea, than to of∣tend one of these little ones, who believe in
<PB N="33" REF="044789_0017_101F06821CE92368"/>
me.</Q> See them, the amazing danger which they expose themselves unto, who wound and injure this spouse of Christ.</P>
<P N="5">5th. Do none belong to the true Church of Christ besides those, whom the scripture calls '<HI>living Stones,</HI>' in our text, compacted into one building, cemented together by divine love: Then it is glaringly evident, <HI>that out of this Church, there is no Salvation:</HI> No building of this kind can stand, unless built upon the living, the chief corner Stone, Christ Jesus, in the foun∣dation of this building▪ for a house built upon the sand will fall: None but living branches are united to the vine, so as to derive any sap or nourishment from it; but will be pruned off, seperated from that <HI>superficial and seeming union that they have, and cast into the fire.</HI> The King of the Church hath declared, the gates of hell shall never prevail against his Church, built up∣on a rock, but they will eternally prevail a∣gainst every dry branch in it. Here it is easy to see, that no unbeliever is built upon this rock; Such as are only visibly, in appearance, or by profession, in the Church of Christ, are the children of the kingdom that shall be cast our, Mat. viii. 12. These, (he hath told us) he will disown, as none of his, at the last day; and pro∣fess he never knew them to be such as they pro∣fessed themselves to be; notwithstanding any boasted profession of having <HI>eat and drank in his presence;</HI> or of many great and miraculous things done in his name, even that of casting out devils. Every <HI>plant (saith our Saviour) which
<PB N="34" REF="044789_0018_101F06850C32C5B0"/>
my heavenly father hath not planted, shall be rooted up. Christ laid down his life for the sheep:</HI> And it was the Church that was redeemed by his blood; so that out of this Church there is no salvation.</P>
<P>This discourse may be further improved by way of enquiry; whether we do truly belong to this living Church of Christ or not.</P>
<P N="1">1st. The first thing to be enquired after, is, whether you have any spiritual or divine life in you or not; for there are no lifeless members in the true Church of Christ, as you have heard. If you are able to determine this point, it will be sufficient to determine your character. Let me ask you? Do you perceive any signs of life in you? Do you breathe spiritually? Do you perform the functions of the living? If you are alive (in the sense we speak,) Christ lives in you, the holy spirit dwells in you by his divine influences; for the Apostle has given, us this sign, if you have this divine life, '<HI>You have the witness in yourselves:</HI>' Ask yourselves, whether you have the fruits of the spirit, as faith, love, joy, meekness, patience, long suffering, gentle∣ness, goodness, &amp;c. I add, if you have this e∣vidence, you have been quickened, i. e. made spiritually alive; who before, were dead in trespasses and sins. If you be risen with Christ, you seek those things that are above, where Christ Jesus is: If so, your treasures are laid up in heaven, and your hearts are there also: If you are new born, you will desire the sincere milk of the word, that you may grow thereby;
<PB N="35" REF="044789_0018_101F06850C32C5B0"/>
you will hunger and thirst after righteousness; you will long after perfect conformity to God: If you be a living member in Christ, God will be the object of your supreme love and desires: Your souls will pant after God; they will thirst for God, even for the living God: your meditations of him will be sweet in the night watches: You will make his word your study and delight, the man of your council, your guide: According to this rule, you will endeavour to form your hearts and lives. Again enquire: Have you had a <HI>real, sensible discovery</HI> of the <HI>ravishing beauty</HI> of Christ, the excellency of his person and charac∣ter; so that he has been very precious to you, high in your account, your joy, your trust, your foundation upon which you build your righte∣ousness, your atonement, the chiefest among ten thousands, and altogether lovely, your all and in all. Again enquire: Is sin your burden? your grief, your abhorence? And do you abhor yourself, and repent as in dust in ashes.' Can you sincerely answer these queries, and honestly apply all these rules of trial? If so, then are ye Christ's disciples indeed, members of his true Church.</P>
<P>And to you this discourse administers sweet consolation; for the eternal God, with all his fulness is yours forever, your unfailing portion. God is your everlasting father and unchangeable friend. The enjoyment of this God, is consum∣mate happiness and endless bliss: This divine consolation is greater than can be expressed! How refreshing, that the eternal God has made
<PB N="36" REF="044789_0019_101F0686B5FB0BC8"/>
you his son and heir; 'heir of all things.' <HI>If sons, then heirs</HI> (saith the Apostle) <HI>heirs of God, and joint heirs with Christ.</HI> O, the inexpressible riches contained in this inheritance; how comfortable the thoughts, that Jesus Christ, with all his un∣searchable riches is yours! that Christ Jesus, in whom dwells all the fulness of the Godhead, with all his saving benefits, is yours! How com∣fortable to reflect, that you have a wedding gar∣ment, a beautiful and spotless robe, even the righ∣teousness of Christ, a garment fit to be worn in the palace of the King of heaven, a garment which shines with equal brightness, if not supe∣rior to those worn by angels: How comforta∣ble this; when you reflect how naked you once were; not having cloathing to hide your shame, but now adorned with a gorgeous robe, which will never fade, nor be soiled in the least, nor be at all the worse for wearing! How comfortable to reflect upon that near relation you have to the son of God; <Q><HI>That you are his brother, sister or mother, his body his member; his flesh and his Bones, his bride his wife.</HI></Q> And that this re∣lation will never cease; that the Almighty hus∣band will never disown you; that nothing can seperate you from his love: neither angel nor spirit; life nor death; nor any other creature: this your union to Christ being indissoluble! How comfortable to reflect that all the promises are yours in Christ, being first made with him; that in him they are, yea and in him amen; your bread, upon which you may most sweetly feed: Promises of all good▪ temporal, spiritual and
<PB N="37" REF="044789_0019_101F0686B5FB0BC8"/>
eternal. Eternal life and glory▪ and, <HI>no good thing will be withhold from them that love him!</HI> How comfortable to think, that the holy spirit of promise is given to you, and dwelleth in you, and shall abide with you forever: This truly is the sum of all gospel blessings: He is the spirit of grace and consolation, and his consolations are neither small nor few. He is the comforter, the spirit of truth that will abide with you forever. The consolations are so numerous, which flow from this union to Christ; that there is no end of them: Even a large volume would not contain them all, if particularly mentioned. I shall therefore leave you to enlarge in your contemplations upon them, 'While life &amp; being lasts;' and shall conclude with a word of exhortation, to those of a different character; I mean the Christless and un∣believing, to come and participate of this happiness.</P>
<P>Come precious souls, and be incorporated into this spiri∣tual building: Be united to Christ the living Stone by faith: Be ye living Stones also; living branches in Christ the true vine: And for motive consider, this is the way, the only way to inexpressible, inconceiveable happiness; which hath no end; the road to eternal bliss: The way to every kind of felicity: For out of this Church there is no salvati∣on as you have heard: But if out of this Church, you are in the high road to perdition, your way leads down to death and misery: Suffer me then, precious souls, with all the bowels of tenderness and compassion to persuade you to be happy: Shall we suppose you are in love with death, with your own misery and ruin? Can human nature be sunk below the principles of natural reason and self preserva∣tion? If otherwise, why will you not be persuaded to ac∣cept of happiness suitable, both in kind and duration, to your being? I beseech you by all the joys of heaven, and the torments of the damned, that you come into this spiri∣tual house; you have no safety elsewhere; no not for a mo∣ment. I beseech you by the unparellelled love of God the father, who gave his only begotten son to purchase your ransom: I beseech you by the immense love of a dying Sa∣viour; by his agony in the garden; his bloody sweat, his strong cries and tears, while he bore the heavy load of sin and guilt which was laid upon him; by his dying groans and precious blood, which streamed from his sacred side,
<PB N="38" REF="044789_0020_101F068865F83AE8"/>
while he was suspended on that cursed engine of cruelty, the cross; that you will consent to be happy by believing in Jesus, and thereby becoming one of his living members, yea, I beseech you by every thing desirable, every thing dear to you, by the eternal happiness of your precious and immor∣tal souls, that you join this happy society without delay, in the mid<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t of which God dwells. Secure an inheritance in this delightful city, the New Jerusalem, the true Church of Christ; in the midst of which, the Lord God and the lamb is the light thereof; where streams of delight and drivers of uninterrupted, unabated pleasure forever roll.</P>
<P>Why sleep ye, precious souls, in this your market day? Rouze every power, awake every passion; and now make sure an inheritance among the Saints in light. Now is the time to make yourselves forever; a precious opportunity is now in your hands; <Q><HI>But boast not of to-morrow; for ye know not what a day may bring forth,</HI></Q> to-morrow may be too late; make no delay, least you fail, the season be past, and the door of mercy be so ever shut, and God swear in his wrath, ye shall never enter into his rest. Then, Oh then, you will gnaw your tongues for anguish, and gnash your teeth with pain and horror inexpressible! Oh! can you bear the thoughts of being shut out from all good, and plunged into the depths of misery? Oh <HI>flee, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> from <HI>wrath</HI> to come, and the the Lord mercy on you, to the praise of his glorious grace in Christ Jesus, Amen and Amen.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

