<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2005-09-23</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Simon Charles</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Corrected 2 illegibles of 4. Converted 2 illegibles to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf".</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="K077856.000">
<STC T="C">T096678</STC>
<BIBNO T="docno">CW3305152129</BIBNO>
<VID SET="ECSS">0028202200</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>AN
INVESTIGATION
OF
The Cause
OF THE PRESENT
HIGH PRICE OF PROVISIONS.</P>
<P>BY THE AUTHOR OF THE ESSAY ON THE
PRINCIPLE OF POPULATION.</P>
<P>LONDON:
PRINTED FOR
J. JOHNSON, IN ST. PAUL'S-CHURCH-YARD,
BY DAVIS, TAYLOR, AND WILKS, CHANCERY-LANE.
1800.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>AN
INVESTIGATION,
<HI>&amp;c.</HI></HEAD>
<P>AMONG the many causes that have been
assigned of the present high price of provisions,
I am much inclined to suspect, that the principal
one has hitherto escaped detection; at least, in
the discussions on the subject, either in print or
conversation, which have fallen within my know∣ledge,
the cause, which I conceive to have ope∣rated
most strongly towards increasing the price
of the necessaries of life, has not yet been sug∣gested.
There are some disorders, which, though
they scarcely admit of a cure, or even of any
considerable mitigation, are still capable of being
made greatly worse. In such misfortunes it is of
great importance to know the desperate nature of
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
the disease. The next step to the alleviation
of pain, is the bearing it with composure, and
not aggravating it by impatience and irritation.</P>
<P>It cannot admit of a doubt with persons of
sense and information, that, during the last year,
there was a scarcity, to a certain extent, of all
sorts of grain; but it must be at the same time ac∣knowledged,
that the price was higher than the
degree of that scarcity would at first sight appear
to warrant.</P>
<P>In the Summer of 1799, in the course of a
northern tour, I passed through Sweden. There
was at that time a general dearth of corn through∣out
the country, owing to a long drought the
preceding year. In the province of Wurmland,
adjoining to Norway, it approached almost to a
famine, and the lower classes of people suffered
most severe distress. At the time we were passing
through that part of the country, which was in
July, they were reduced to two most miserable
substitutes for bread; one, made of the inner bark
of the fir, and the other, of the common sorrel
dried, and powdered. These substances, though
made into the usual shape of their rye bread, had
no affinity to it whatever in taste, and but very
little, I believe, in nourishment, as the effects of
this miserable food were but too visible in their
pallid and unhealthy countenances.</P>
<P><PB N="3" REF="4" MS="y"/>
There could be little doubt, that the degree of
scarcity then prevailing in that part of Sweden,
was considerably greater than any we have hitherto
experienced here; and yet, as far as we could learn,
the price of rye, which is the grain principally
used for bread, had not risen above double its
usual average; whereas in this country last year,
in a scarcity, that must be acknowledged to be
very greatly inferior in degree, wheat rose to
above three times its former price.</P>
<P>The continuation of extraordinary high prices,
after a harvest that was at one time looked for∣ward
to as abundant, has contributed still more
to astonish and perplex the public mind. Many
men of sense have joined in the universal cry of
the common people, that there must be roguery
somewhere; and the general indignation has fallen
upon monopolizers, forestallers, and regraters—words,
that are vented from every mouth with
fearful execrations, and are applied indiscrimi∣nately
to all middle men whatever, to every kind
of trader that goes between the grower of the
commodity and the consumer.</P>
<P>This popular clamour, headed by the Lord
Chief Justice, and enforced throughout the coun∣try
by the instructions of the grand juries, must
make every reflecting mind tremble for the
<PB N="4" REF="5"/>
future supply of our markets. I cannot but think,
therefore, that I should do an acceptable service,
if I could succeed in accounting for the present
high price of the necessaries of life, without cri∣minating
a class of men, who, I believe, have
been accused unjustly, and who, every political
economist must know, are absolutely necessary in
the complicated machinery that distributes the
provisions and other commodities of a large
nation.</P>
<P>I ought first to premise, however, that I am
not interested in this question, further than as a
lover of truth, and a well-wisher to my country.
I have no sort of connection whatever with any
of these middle men or great farmers, who are
now the objects of public indignation: and, as an
individual with a small fixed income, I am cer∣tainly
among that class of persons on whom the
high price of provisions must fall the heaviest.</P>
<P>To proceed to the point: I am most strongly
inclined to suspect, that the attempt in most parts
of the kingdom to increase the parish allowances
in proportion to the price of corn, combined with
the riches of the country, which have enabled it
to proceed as far as it has done in this attempt,
is, comparatively speaking, the sole cause, which
has occasioned the price of provisions in this
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>
country to rise so much higher than the degree
of scarcity would seem to warrant, so much higher
than it would do in any other country where this
cause did not operate.</P>
<P>It may appear, perhaps, at first, to the reader,
that this cause is inadequate to the effect we ex∣perience;
but, if he will kindly allow me a few
minutes of patient and candid attention, I hope I
shall be able to convince him, that it is not only
adequate to produce the present high price of
provisions of which we complain; but, admitting
a real scarcity, that the attempt to carry it actually
into execution, might raise the quartern loaf be∣fore
the expiration of a year, to as many shillings
as it is now pence.</P>
<P>Adam Smith has most justly stated, that the
actual price at which a commodity is sold, is com∣pounded
of its natural price, the price at which it
can be brought to market, allowing the usual
profit in times of moderate plenty, and the pro∣portion
of the supply to the demand. When any
commodity is scarce, its natural price is necessarily
forgotten, and its actual price is regulated by the
excess of the demand above the supply.</P>
<P>Let us suppose a commodity in great request
by fifty people, but of which, from some failure
in its production, there is only sufficient to supply
forty. If the fortieth man from the top have two
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
shillings which he can spend in this commodity,
and the thirty-nine above him, more, in various
proportions, and the ten below, all less, the ac∣tual
price of the article, according to the genuine
principles of trade, will be two shillings. If more
be asked, the whole will not be sold, because there
are only forty who have as much as two shillings
to spend in the article; and there is no reason for
asking less, because the whole may be disposed of
at that sum.</P>
<P>Let us suppose, now, that somebody gives the
ten poor men, who were excluded, a shilling a∣piece.
The whole fifty can now offer two shil∣lings,
the price which was before asked. Ac∣cording
to every genuine principle of fair trading,
the commodity must immediately rise. If it do
not, I would ask, upon what principle are ten, out
of the fifty who are all able to offer two shillings,
to be rejected? For still, according to the suppo∣sition,
there is only enough for forty. The two
shillings of a poor man are just as good as the two
shillings of a rich one; and, if we interfere to pre∣vent
the commodity from rising out of the reach
of the poorest ten, whoever they may be, we must
toss up, draw lots, raffle, or flight, to determine
who are to be excluded. It would be beyond my
present purpose, to enter into the question whe∣ther
<PB N="7" REF="8"/>
any of these modes would be more eligible,
for the distribution of the commodities of a
country, than the sordid distinction of money;
but certainly, according to the customs of all ci∣vilized
and enlightened nations, and according to
every acknowledged principle of commercial
dealing, the price must be allowed to rise to that
point which will put it beyond the power of ten
out of the fifty to purchase. This point will,
perhaps, be half-a-crown or more, which will
now become the price of the commodity. Let
another shilling a-piece be given to the excluded
ten: all will now be able to offer half-a-crown.
The price must in consequence immediately rise
to three shillings or more, and so on <HI>toties quoties.</HI></P>
<P>In the progress of this operation the ten ex∣cluded
would not be always entirely the same.
The richest of the ten first excluded, would pro∣bably
be raised above the poorest of the first forty.
Small changes of this kind must take place. The
additional allowances to the poorest, and the
weight of the high prices on those above them,
would tend to level the two orders; but, till a
complete level had taken place, ten must be
always excluded, and the price would always be
fixed, as nearly as possible, at that sum which the
fortieth man at the top could afford to give. This,
<PB N="8" REF="9"/>
if the donatives were continued, would raise the
commodity to an extraordinary price, without
the supposition of any combination and conspiracy
among the venders, or any kind of unfair dealing
whatever.</P>
<P>The rise in the price of corn, and of other pro∣visions,
in this country, has been effected exactly
in the same manner, though the operation may be
a little more complicated; and I am firmly con∣vinced,
that it never could have reached its pre∣sent
height, but from the system of poor laws and
parish allowances, which have operated precisely
in the same mode as the donatives of a shilling
in the instance I have just adduced.</P>
<P>The harvest of 1799 was bad, both in quality
and quantity. Few people could deny that there
appeared to be a very considerable deficiency of
produce: and the price of the load of wheat rose
in consequence almost immediately to £. 20. I
returned from the North in the beginning of No∣vember,
and found the alarm so great and general,
and the price of corn so high, that I remember
thinking that it was probably fully adequate to
the degree of the deficiency, and, taking into con∣sideration
the prospect of importation from the
very early alarm, that it would not rise much
higher during the year. In this conjecture, it
<PB N="9" REF="10"/>
appears that I was much mistaken; but I have
very little doubt that in any other country equally
rich, yet without the system of poor laws and pa∣rish
allowances, the price would never have ex∣ceeded
£.25 the load of wheat; and that this
sum would have been sufficiently high to have
excluded such a number of people from their
usual consumption, as to make the deficient crop,
with the quantity imported, last throughout the
year.</P>
<P>The system of poor laws, and parish allowances,
in this country, and I will add, to their honour,
the humanity and generosity of the higher and
middle classes of society, naturally and necessarily
altered this state of things. The poor com∣plained
to the justices that their wages would not
enable them to supply their families in the single
article of bread. The justices very humanely,
and I am far from saying improperly, listened to
their complaints, inquired what was the smallest
sum on which they could support their families,
at the then price of wheat, and gave an order of
relief on the parish accordingly. The poor were
now enabled, for a short time, to purchase nearly
their usual quantity of flour; but the stock in the
country was not sufficient, even with the prospect
of importation, to allow of the usual distribution
<PB N="10" REF="11"/>
to all its members. The crop was consuming
too fast. Every market-day the demand exceeded
the supply; and those whose business it was to
judge on these subjects, felt convinced, that in a
month or two the scarcity would be greater than
it was at that time. Those who were able, there∣fore,
kept back their corn. In so doing, they
undoubtedly consulted their own interest; but
they, as undoubtedly, whether with the intention
or not is of no consequence, consulted the true
interest of the state: for, if they had not kept it
back, too much would have been consumed, and
there would have been a famine instead of a scar∣city
at the end of the year.</P>
<P>The corn, therefore, naturally rose. The poor
were again distressed. Fresh complaints were
made to the justices, and a further relief granted;
but, like the water from the mouth of Tantalus, the
corn still slipped from the grasp of the poor; and
rose again so as to disable them from purchasing
a sufficiency to keep their families in health. The
alarm now became still greater, and more ge∣neral <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">I am describing what took place in the neighbourhood where I then lived; and I have reason to believe that some∣thing nearly similar took place in most counties of the king∣dom.</NOTE>. The justices in their individual capa∣cities
<PB N="11" REF="12"/>
were not thought competent to determine
on the proper modes of relief in the present crisis,
a general meeting of the magistrates was called,
aided by the united wisdom of other gentlemen
of the county; but the result was merely the con∣tinuation
and extension of the former system of
relief; and, to say the truth, I hardly see what else
could have been done. In some parishes this re∣lief
was given in the shape of flour; in others,
which was certainly better, in money, accompa∣nied
with a recommendation not to spend the
whole of it in wheaten bread, but to adopt some
other kind of food. All, however, went upon the
principle of inquiring what was the usual con∣sumption
of flour in the different families, and of
enabling them to purchase nearly the same quan∣tity
that they did before the scarcity. With this
additional command of money in the lower classes,
and the consequent increased consumption, the
number of purchasers at the then price would na∣turally
exceed the supply. The corn would in
consequence continue rising. The poor's rates in
many parishes increased from four shillings in the
pound to fourteen; the price of wheat necessarily
kept pace with them; and before the end of the
year was at near forty pounds a load; when pro∣bably
<PB N="12" REF="13"/>
without the operation of this cause it would
not have exceeded twenty or twenty-five.</P>
<P>Some of the poor would naturally make use
of their additional command of money to pur∣chase
butter, cheese, bacon, pickled pork, rice,
potatoes, &amp;c. These commodities are all more
limited in quantity than corn; and would, there∣fore,
more suddenly feel the increased demand.
If butter, cheese, bacon, pickled pork, and the
coarser parts of meat, had continued at their
usual price, they would have been purchased by
so many, to come in aid of an inferior kind of
bread, or to give a relish and additional nourish∣ment
to their potatoes and rice, that the supply
would not have been half adequate to the quan∣tity
of these articles that was wanted. These
commodities, therefore, rose as naturally and as
necessarily as the corn; and, according to the ge∣nuine
principles of fair trade, their price was
fixed at that sum which only such a number could
afford to give, as would enable the supply to
answer the demand.</P>
<P>To fix upon this sum is the great object of
every dealer and speculator <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> every commodity
whatever, and about which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> must, of course,
exercise his private judgment. A reflecting
<PB N="13" REF="14"/>
mind, far from being astonished that there are
now and then errors in speculation, must feel
much greater astonishment that there are so few;
and that the supplies of a large nation, whether
plentiful or scanty, should be distributed so
equally throughout the year. Most happily for
society, individual interest is, in these cases, so
closely and intimately interwoven with the public
interest, that one cannot gain or lose without a
gain or loss to the other. The man who refuses
to send his corn to market when it is at twenty
pounds a load, because he thinks that in two
months time it will be at thirty, if he be right
in his judgment, and succeed in his specula∣tion,
is a positive and decided benefactor to the
state; because he keeps his supply to that pe∣riod
when the state is much more in want of
it; and if he and some others did not keep it
back in that manner, instead of its being thirty
in two months, it would be forty or fifty.</P>
<P>If he be wrong in his speculation, he loses per∣haps
very considerably himself, and the state
suffers a little; because, had he brought his corn
to market at twenty, the price would have fallen
sooner, and the event showed that there was
corn enough in the country to allow of it; but
the slight evil that the state suffers in this case
<PB N="14" REF="15"/>
is almost wholly compensated by the glut in the
market, when the corn is brought out, which
makes the price fall below what it would have
been otherwise.</P>
<P>I am far from saying that there can be no
such thing as monopoly, and the other hard
words that have been so much talked of. In a
commodity of a confined nature, within the
purchase of two or three large capitals, or of a
company of merchants, we all know that it has
often existed; and, in a very few instances, the
article may have been in part destroyed, to en∣hance
the price, as the Dutch Company de∣stroyed
the nutmeg-trees in their spice islands:
but in an article which is in so many hands as
corn is, in this country, monopoly, to any perni∣cious
extent, may safely be pronounced impos∣sible.
Where are the capitals, or where is the
company of merchants, rich enough to buy
such a quantity of corn, as would make it an∣swer
to them to destroy, or, which is the same
thing, not to sell a great part of it? As they
could not, by the greatest exertions, purchase
one fourth of all the corn in the country, it is
evident that, if any considerable part of their
stock remained unsold, they would have enriched
all the other dealers in corn at their own expense;
<PB N="15" REF="16"/>
and would not have gained half so much in pro∣portion
to their capital as the rest of the farmers
and cornfactors. If on the contrary all their
stock sold, it would be a proof that the specula∣tion
had been just, and that the country had really
benefited by it.</P>
<P>It seems now to be universally agreed, that the
stock of old corn remaining on hand at the begin∣ning
of the harvest this year was unusually small,
notwithstanding that the harvest came on nearly
a month sooner than could have been expected
in the beginning of June. This is a clear, de∣cided,
and unanswerable proof that there had
been no speculations in corn that were preju∣dicial
to the country. All that the large farmers
and cornfactors had done, was to raise the corn to
that price which excluded a sufficient number
from their usual consumption, to enable the
supply to last throughout the year. This price,
however, has been most essentially and powerfully
affected by the ability that has been given to the
labouring poor, by means of parish allowances,
of continuing to purchase wheat notwithstanding
its extraordinary rise: and this ability must neces∣sarily
prevent the price of corn from falling very
materially, till there is an actual glut in the
market; for, while the whole stock will go off at
<PB N="16" REF="17"/>
thirty pounds a load, it cannot, on any regular
principle of trade, sink lower. I was in very
great hopes, just before the harvest, that such a
glut was about to take place; but it is now
to be feared, from the nature of the present crop,
that no such happy event can be hoped for during
the year.</P>
<P>I do not know whether I have convinced my
reader that the cause which I have assigned of the
present extraordinary price of provisions is ad∣equate
to the effect; but I certainly feel most
strongly convinced of it myself; and I cannot
but believe that, if he differ from me, it can only
be in degree, and from thinking that the prin∣ciple
of parish allowances has not yet been car∣ried
far enough to produce any material effect.
With regard to the principle itself, if it were
really carried into execution, it appears to me
capable almost of mathematical demonstration,
that, granting a real scarcity of one-fourth, which
could not be remedied by importation, it is ad∣equate
to the effecting any height of price that
the proportion of the circulating medium to the
quantity of corn daily consumed would admit.</P>
<P>It has often been proposed, and more than
once I believe, in the House of Commons, to
proportion the price of labour exactly to the
<PB N="17" REF="18"/>
price of provisions. This, though it would
be always a bad plan, might pass tolerably in
years of moderate plenty, or in a country that
was in the habit of a considerable exportation of
grain. But let us see what would be its ope∣ration
in a real scarcity. We suppose, for the sake
of the argument, that by law every kind of labour
is to be paid accurately in proportion to the price
of corn, and that the rich are to be assessed to
the utmost to support those in the same manner
who are thrown out of employment, and fall
upon the parish. We allow the scarcity to
be an irremediable deficiency of one fourth of
all the provisions of the country. It is evi∣dent
that, notwithstanding this deficiency, there
would be no reason for economy in the labouring
classes. The rise of their wages, or the parish
allowances that they would receive, would enable
them to purchase exactly the same quantity of
corn, or other provisions, that they did before,
whatever their price might be. The same quan∣tity
would of course be consumed; and, accord∣ing
to the regular principles of trade, as the stock
continued diminishing, the price of all the ne∣cessaries
of life would continue rising, in the
most rapid and unexampled manner. The mid∣dle
classes of society would very soon be blended
<PB N="18" REF="19"/>
with the poor; and the largest fortunes could
not long stand against the accumulated pressure
of the extraordinary price of provisions, on the
one hand, and the still more extraordinary assess∣ments
for allowances to those who had no other
means of support, on the other. The corn∣factors
and farmers would undoubtedly be the
last that suffered, but, at the expiration of the
three quarters of a year, what they received with
one hand, they must give away with the other;
and a most complete levelling of all property
would take place. All would have the same
quantity of money. All the provisions of the
country would be consumed: and all the people
would starve together.</P>
<P>There is no kind of fear, that any such tra∣gical
event should ever happen in any country;
but allowed myself to make the supposition;
because, it appears to me, that, in the compli∣cated
machinery of human society, the effect
of any particular principle frequently escapes
from the view, even of an attentive observer, if
it be not magnified by pushing it to extremity.</P>
<P>I do not, however, by any means, intend to
infer, from what I have said, that the parish
allowances have been prejudicial to the state;
or that, as far as the system has been hitherto
<PB N="19" REF="20"/>
pursued, or is likely to be pursued, in this
country, that it is not one of the best modes of
relief that the circumstances of the case will
admit. The system of the poor laws, in gene∣neral,
I certainly do most heartily condemn, as
I have expressed in another place, but I am in∣clined
to think that their operation in the pre∣sent
scarcity has been advantageous to the
country. The principal benefit which they have
produced, is exactly that which is most bitterly
complained of—the high price of all the neces∣saries
of life. The poor cry out loudly at
this price; but, in so doing, they are very little
aware of what they are about; for it has un∣doubtedly
been owing to this price that a much
greater number of them has not been starved.</P>
<P>It was calculated that there were only two-thirds
of an average crop last year. Probably,
even with the aid of all that we imported, the
deficiency still remained a fifth or sixth. Sup∣posing
ten millions of people in the island;
the whole of this deficiency, had things been
left to their natural course, would have fallen
almost exclusively on two, or perhaps three
millions of the poorest inhabitants, a very con∣siderable
number of whom must in consequence
have starved. The operation of the parish al∣lowances,
<PB N="20" REF="21"/>
by raising the price of provisions so
high, caused the distress to be divided among
five or six millions, perhaps, instead of two or
three, and to be by no means unfelt even by the
remainder of the population.</P>
<P>The high price, therefore, which is so much
complained of by the poor, has essentially mi∣tigated
their distress by bringing down to their
level two or three millions more, and making
them almost equal sharers in the pressure of the
scarcity.</P>
<P>The further effects of the high price have
been to enforce a strict economy in all ranks of
life; to encourage an extraordinary importa∣tion,
and to animate the farmer by the powerful
motive of self-interest to make every exertion
to obtain as great a crop as possible the next
year.</P>
<P>If economy, importation, and every possible
encouragement to future production, have not
the fairest chance of putting an end to the scarcity,
I confess myself at a loss to say what better means
can be substituted. I may undoubtedly on this
subject be much mistaken; but to me, I own,
they appear more calculated to answer the pur∣pose
intended, than the hanging any number of
farmers and cornfactors that could be named.</P>
<P><PB N="21" REF="22"/>
No inference, therefore, is meant to be drawn
against what has been done for the relief of the
poor in the present scarcity, though it has with∣out
doubt greatly raised the price of provisions.
All that I contend for is, that we should be
aware of the effect of what we ourselves have
done, and not lay the blame on the wrong
persons.</P>
<P>If the cause, which I have detailed, be suffi∣cient
to account for the present high price of
provisions, without the supposition of any unfair
dealing among the farmers and cornfactors, we
ought surely to bear the present pressure like
men labouring under a disorder that must have
its course, and not throw obstacles in the way of
returning plenty, and endanger the future supplies
of our markets, by encouraging the popular cla∣mour,
and keeping the farmers and corn-dealers
in perpetual fear for their lives and property.</P>
<P>To suppose that a year of scarcity can pass
without distressing severely a large part of the in∣habitants
of a country, is to suppose a contra∣diction
in the nature of things. I know of no
other definition of a scarcity than the failure of
the usual quantity of provisions; and if a great
part of the people had but just enough before,
they must undoubtedly have less than enough at
<PB N="22" REF="23"/>
such a period. With regard to the scarcity being
artificial, it appears to me so impossible, that,
till it has been proved that some man or set of
men, with a capital of twenty or thirty millions
sterling, has bought up half the corn in the
country, I own I must still disbelieve it. On
this subject, however, I know that I differ from
some very respectable friends of mine, among
the common people, who say that it is quite im∣possible
that there can be a real scarcity, because
you may get what quantity of corn you please,
if you have but money enough; and to say the
truth, many persons, who ought to be better in∣formed,
argue exactly in the same way. I have
often talked with labouring men on this subject,
and endeavoured to show them, that if they,
or I, had a great deal of money, and other peo∣ple
had but little, we could undoubtedly buy
what quantity of corn we liked, by taking away
the shares of those who were less rich; but that
if all the people had the same sum, and that there
was not enough corn in the country to supply all,
we could not get what we wanted for money,
though we possessed millions. I never found,
however, that my rhetoric produced much im∣pression.</P>
<P>The cry at present is in favour of small farms,
<PB N="23" REF="24"/>
and against middle men. No two clamours can
well be more inconsistent with each other, as the
destruction of the middle men would, I conceive,
necessarily involve with it the destruction of small
farmers. The small farmer requires a quick re∣turn
of his scanty capital to enable him to pay
his rent and his workmen; and must therefore
send his corn to market almost immediately after
harvest. If he were required to perform the
office of corn-dealer, as well as farmer, and wait
to regulate his supplies to the demands of the
markets, a double capital would be absolutely
necessary to him, and not having that, he would
be ruined.</P>
<P>Many men of sense and information have at∣tributed
the dearness of provisions to the quan∣tity
of paper in circulation. There was un∣doubtedly
great reason for apprehension, that
when, by the stoppage of the Bank to pay in
specie, the emission of paper ceased to have its
natural check, the circulation would be over∣loaded
with this currency; but this certainly
could not have taken place to any considerable
extent without a sensible depreciation of bank
notes in comparison with specie. As this depre∣ciation
did not happen, the progress of the evil
must have been slow and gradual, and never
<PB N="24" REF="25"/>
could have produced the sudden and extraor∣dinary
rise in the price of provisions which was
so sensibly felt last year, after a season of mode∣rate
cheapness, subsequent to the stoppage of the
Bank.</P>
<P>There is one circumstance, however, that
ought to be attended to. To circulate the same,
or nearly the same<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">In a scarcity the quantity of commodities in circulation is probably not so great as in years of plenty.</NOTE>, quantity of commodities
through a country, when they bear a much
higher price, must require a greater quantity of
the medium, whatever that may be. The cir∣culation
naturally takes up more. It is pro∣bable,
therefore, that the Bank has found it ne∣cessary
to issue a greater number of its notes on
this account. Or, if it has not, this deficiency
has been supplied by the country bankers, who
have found that their notes now stay out longer,
and in greater quantity, than they did before the
scarcity, which may tempt many to overtrade
their capitals. If the quantity of paper, there∣fore,
in circulation has greatly increased during
the last year, I should be inclined to consider it
rather as the effect than the cause of the high
price of provisions. This sulness of circulating
<PB N="25" REF="26"/>
medium, however, will be one of the obstacles
in the way to returning cheapness.</P>
<P>The public attention is now fixed with anxiety
towards the meeting of Parliament, which is to
relieve us from our present difficulties; but the
more considerate do not feel very sanguine on
this subject, knowing how little is to be done
in this species of distress by legislative inter∣ference.
We interfere to fix the assize of bread.
Perhaps one of the best interferences of the
Legislature, in the present instance, would be
to abolish that assize. I have certainly no ten∣dency
to believe in combinations and conspi∣racies;
but the great interval that elapses be∣tween
the fall of wheat and the fall of flour,
compared with the quick succession of the rise
of flour to the rise of wheat, would almost tempt
one to suppose, that there might be some little
management in the return of the meal weighers
to the Lord Mayor. If the public suffer in this
instance, it is evidently owing to the assize,
without which, the opportunity of any such ma∣nagement
would not exist. And what occasion
can there be for an assize in a city like London,
in which there are so many bakers? If such a re∣gulation
were ever necessary, it would appear to
be most so in a country village or small town,
<PB N="26" REF="27"/>
where perhaps there is but one person in the
trade, and who might, therefore, for a time, have
an opportunity of imposing on his customers;
but this could not take place where there was
such room for competition as in London. If
there were no assize, more attention would be
constantly paid to the weight and quality of the
bread bought; and the bakers who sold the best
in these two respects would have the most cus∣tom.
The removal of this regulation would
remove, in a great measure, the difficulty about
brown bread, and a much greater quantity of it
would probably be consumed.</P>
<P>The soup-shops, and every attempt to make
a nourishing and palatable food of what was be∣fore
not in use among the common people, must
evidently be of great service in the present dis∣tress.</P>
<P>It is a fact now generally acknowledged, and
it has lately received an official sanction in a
letter of the Duke of portland to the Lord
Lieutenant of the county of Oxford, that of late
years, even in the best seasons, we have not
grown corn sufficient for our own consumption;
whereas, twenty years ago, we were in the con∣stant
habit of exporting grain to a very consider∣able
amount. Though we may suppose that
<PB N="27" REF="28"/>
the agriculture of the country has not been in∣creasing,
as it ought to have done, during this
period; yet we cannot well imagine that it has
gone backwards. To what then can we attri∣bute
the present inability in the country to sup∣port
its inhabitants, but to the increase of po∣pulation?
I own that I cannot but consider
the late severe pressures of distress on every de∣ficiency
in our crops, as a very strong exem∣plification
of a principle which I endeavoured to
explain in an essay published about two years
ago, entitled, <HI>An Essay on the Principle of
Population, as it affects the future Improve∣ment
of Society.</HI> It was considered by many
who read it, merely as a specious argument, in∣applicable
to the present state of society; be∣cause
it contradicted some preconceived opi∣nions
on these subjects. Two years reflection
have, however, served strongly to convince
me of the truth of the principle there advanced,
and of its being the real cause of the continued
depression and poverty of the lower classes of
society, of the total inadequacy of all the pre∣sent
establishments in their favour to relieve
them, and of the periodical returns of such
seasons of distress as we have of late experi∣enced.</P>
<P><PB N="28" REF="29"/>
The essay has now been out of print above a
year; but I have deferred giving another edi∣tion
of it in the hope of being able to make it
more worthy of the public attention, by apply∣ing
the principle directly and exclusively to the
existing state of society, and endeavouring to
illustrate the power and universality of its opera∣tion
from the best authenticated accounts that we
have of the state of other countries. Particular
engagements in the former part of the time, and
some most unforeseen and unfortunate inter∣ruptions
latterly, have hitherto prevented me
from turning my attention, with any effect,
towards this subject. I still, however, have it
in view. In the mean time I hope that this
hasty attempt to add my mite to the public stock
of information, in the present emergency, will be
received with candour.</P>
<TRAILER>THE END.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

