<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-01-09</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Check for blanks. Checked for signatures. Checked for #s. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Converted 91 $-groups to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld". Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N01303">
<STC T="E">1551</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99020402</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="001551_0000_0FB3A2C7172579E0"/>
<PB REF="001551_0001_0FB3A2C83A140AC0"/>
<P><HI>Grace Defended.</HI> A CENSURE ON THE Ungodliness, By which the Glorious GRACE of GOD, is too commonly Abused. A SERMON Preached on the <HI>Twenty fifth Day of</HI> December, 1712. Containing Some SEASONABLE Admonitions of Piety. And Concluded, with a brief DISSERTATION on that CASE, <HI>Whether the Penitent Thief on the Cross, be an Example of one Repenting at the</HI> LAST HOUR, <HI>and on such a Repentance received unto Mercy?</HI></P>
<P>By Cotton Mather, D. D.</P>
<BIBL>Isai. lviii. 1.</BIBL>
<Q><HI>Cry aloud, Spare not.</HI></Q>
<P><HI>BOSTON</HI> Printed by <HI>B. Green,</HI> for <HI>Samuel Gerrish,</HI> at his Shop in Marlborough Street. 1712.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="sermon">
<PB REF="001551_0002_0FB3A2C9C0BADBF0"/>
<HEAD>Grace Defended. On the Twenty-fifth of December, 1712. BOSTON-Lecture.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>JUDE 4.</BIBL>
<Q>Ungodly Men, turning the Grace of our God into Wantonness.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>WHat? And so Early, such Unhappy Men and Things <HI>Creep</HI> into the Churches of God! It seems Christian Churches cannot Easily be too much cautioned against <HI>Sly-Adversaries,</HI> and <HI>Swift-Apostasies.</HI> OURS, I am sure, are <HI>Old</HI> enough to be so; In Age gone be∣yond those who were now immediately Written to. And it is to be done, as with a mighty Thun∣der from a flaming Mountain!</P>
<P>I take the Writer of this Epistle, to be, not that <HI>Jude</HI> the <HI>Apostle,</HI> who was in the Syriack Dialect called <HI>Thaddaeus,</HI> and from the Place to which he belong'd, <HI>Lebbaeus:</HI> but the <HI>Jude,</HI> who was one of the <HI>Four,</HI> that are called, <HI>The Brethren of our Lord:</HI> The <HI>Sons of His Mother,</HI> from whom He Suffered
<PB N="2" REF="001551_0003_0FB3A2CC055F0000"/>
the Grievous Humiliation of being treated as an <HI>Alien,</HI> till probably His <HI>Resurrection</HI> from the Dead, brought them into the Number of <HI>Believers</HI> on Him. He now presumes not on such a Style, as that of, <HI>A Brother;</HI> but he takes one, than which the Highest Archangel in Heaven knows none more Glorious; <HI>A Servant of</HI> JESUS CHRIST. Behold him now doing a <HI>Service,</HI> very proper for, very worthy of, such an One. Behold him Warning and Arming the People of God, against the <HI>Errors</HI> which began <HI>betimes</HI> to infest the Churches of the Lord.</P>
<P>The <HI>Antinomians</HI> made a very Early Appearance, I see, among the Depravers and Subverters of the <HI>Faith once delivered unto the Saints.</HI> There are in∣deed very few <HI>New Errors</HI> broached in our <HI>Later-Dayes;</HI> the most of them, which now disturb the Churches of the Faithful, are only from I scarce know what <HI>Enchantments,</HI> raising the <HI>Ghosts</HI> of such as were Dead and Damn'd many Ages ago.</P>
<P>The Impious, and Mischievous Men, against whom the Inspired Writer is now Engaged, have their Impiety here declared. First, The <HI>Ungodly Men</HI> stand charged with <HI>Filthiness.</HI> They were, that I may use the most agreeable Term, which the French Translation Leads me to, A very <HI>Disso∣lute</HI> Generation. I take notice by the way, that the Greek Term, here used for, <HI>Lasciviousness,</HI> or <HI>Wantonness,</HI> is derived from the Name of the Town <HI>Selga;</HI> a Place infamous for such <HI>Dissolute</HI> Practices. It makes me wish, that no Town of ours, may in our Dayes, have any <HI>Vice</HI> abounding in it, so as with a lasting Infamy to derive a Name unto it. I am lothe here to Explain my self too particularly<HI>!</HI> I go on with my Remarks, and
<PB N="3" REF="001551_0004_0FB3A2CE3474ECB0"/>
say; That I would not be so unacquainted with <HI>Church-History,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>to think, the <HI>Gnosticks</HI> to be the <HI>Ungodly Men</HI> peculiarly intended here, tho' a well-known Interpreter, with an Oddity not unlike <HI>many more</HI> in him, with which he has most shame∣fully injured the Sacred Scriptures, ridiculously enough runs every where upon it. There were <HI>Other</HI> and <HI>Older</HI> Hereticks, which this Iniquity might be charged upon. And indeed, it is well known, and from Authority much better than <HI>Epiphanius,</HI> that the Hereticks of those Dayes were noted for Indulged <HI>Impurities.</HI> But then, secondly; To our Astonishment, we find, what it was, that the Ungodly men, made the <HI>Encouragement</HI> o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> their <HI>Filthiness.</HI> Astonishing! It was the <HI>Grace of God,</HI> which they <HI>turned into Wantonness.</HI> by the <HI>Grace of God,</HI> is meant, the Revelation which is in the <HI>Gospel</HI> brought unto us; what we have, in [Act. XX. 24.] <HI>The Gospel of the Grace of God:</HI> A Reve∣lation wherein, <HI>Grace! Grace!</HI> the Glorious <HI>Grace</HI> of God, shines in its Meridian Glory, and with an amazing Splendor on the Children of Men When it is said, They <HI>Turned it;</HI> there is a Word used, that signifies, they <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rested</HI> it, they <HI>Wronged</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, they <HI>Transferred</HI> it from the right use of it, they horribly Abused it. I am stop'd a little. <HI>Whose Grace?</HI> We are told, <HI>The Grace of OUR God.</HI> Sirs, If we have any Sense of an Interest in GOD, and if we re∣joyce in Him as OUR God, we shall have a <HI>Zeal for Holiness</HI> boiling in our Souls. If we care not whether <HI>Holiness</HI> flourish or no, we want a Good Mark, that the <HI>Holy God</HI> is OURS <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Lord▪ If thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> OUR God, we shall be lothe to see <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Gospel abused with any unholy Practices.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="4" REF="001551_0005_0FB3A2D0022529F0"/>
But you must now attend unto a DOCTRINE, that calls for a very Serious Attention with you.</P>
<Q>To turn the Grace of God into Wantonness, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, Wantonly to Abuse the Grace of God, is the Common Custome, and the Cer∣tain Symptom, of Ungodliness.</Q>
<P>There is a great Number of Criminals, who are to Stand this day <HI>Indi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed</HI> before the Bar of the Glorious GOD. I shall have Time to do little more, than just call over their <HI>Names,</HI> and let them know, That they <HI>have not the Fear of God before their Eyes.</HI></P>
<P>I am now to Enquire;
<HI>Who are the Ungodly Ones, by whom the Grace of God is turned into Wantonness?</HI></P>
<P>In brief; All they that are not by the <HI>Favour</HI> of God, brought the more to Love so Gracious a God, by whom they are so <HI>favourably</HI> dealt with∣al. In Sum; All they that are the <HI>Worse,</HI> because they have so <HI>Good</HI> a God for to deal withal: These are they, to every One of whom it may be said, <HI>Thou art the Man!</HI></P>
<P>More particularly,</P>
<P>I. <HI>Ungodly Men</HI> they are, who from the <HI>Decree</HI> of God, Encourage themselves in the Neglect of their <HI>Duty</HI> to GOD. We believe a, <HI>Predestination to Life, wherein God with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Everlasting Purpose, has decreed by His Counsel, to bring those whom He hath Chosen in Christ out of Mankind, unto Everlasting
<PB N="5" REF="001551_0006_0FB3A2D13A48F988"/>
Salvation.</HI> We can Subscribe this Article, [The <HI>Seventeenth</HI> of the <HI>Church of Englands</HI> famous XXXIX,] because we find the Sacred Epistles to the <HI>Romans</HI> and <HI>Ephesians,</HI> Expressly asserting it. And when we have <HI>Subscribed</HI> it, we shall not then <HI>Deny</HI> it, then <HI>Decry</HI> it, then <HI>Oppose</HI> it; We should Look on it, as a very Scandalous <HI>Treachery</HI> to do so. This <HI>Election</HI> of <HI>Some</HI> to Everlasting Life, which unavoidably implies a <HI>Rejection</HI> of <HI>Others,</HI> 'tis cal∣led, Rom. XI. 5. <HI>The Election of Grace.</HI> Oh<HI>!</HI> Sovereign <HI>Grace!</HI> Why has our God, <HI>Chosen us in Christ before the Foundation of the World,</HI> and <HI>Predestinated us unto the Adoption of Children!</HI> The <HI>Praise of the Glory of His Grace,</HI> is design'd in it; is display'd in it. Why are <HI>Some</HI> Taken, to be Redeemed, Converted, Saved; when <HI>Others</HI> are not so! Tis, because, <HI>I will be gracious to whom I will be gracious,</HI> saith the Infinite GOD, who <HI>gives none Account of His Matters.</HI> Tis all from <HI>Unaccountable Grace.</HI> Tis, <HI>Even so, Father, because it pleases thee.</HI> Now, See what <HI>Ungodly Men</HI> will do! They will be at <HI>No Pains</HI> to Turn unto God; <HI>No Pains</HI> to get the Chains of Death Knock'd off their Souls; <HI>No Pains</HI> to lay hold on Eternal Life. Why so? Why,—<HI>Si Salvabor, Salvabor; If it be Decreed that I shall be Saved,</HI> say they, <HI>I shall be so, Let me do nothing at all about it, I shall yet be Saved, if it be Decreed, I shall.</HI> And so, they'l do nothing! Thus they <HI>turn the Grace of God into Wantonness, and Idleness.</HI> These <HI>Idle Words,</HI> a Severe <HI>Account</HI> must be given of them in the <HI>Judgment</HI> of God. But, O <HI>thou Slothful and Wicked Servant,</HI> It is Untrue what thou sayest. Thou shalt not be <HI>Saved,</HI> if thou dost not <HI>Work about thy own Salvation.</HI> We are directed, 2 Pet.
<PB N="6" REF="001551_0007_0FB3A2D2EC6E6B90"/>
I. 10 <HI>Give all Diligence, to make your Calling and Election sure.</HI> God has Decreed the <HI>End</HI> and the <HI>Means</HI> together. One <HI>Decreed for Life,</HI> will <HI>Strive to Enter the Strait Gate,</HI> and be in Agony lest he fall short of Entring into Life. The Man who will not <HI>give all Diligence</HI> to make his <HI>Cal∣ling Sure,</HI> and in that way his <HI>Election</HI> so. can∣not <HI>Inherit Eternal Life.</HI> There is no <HI>Decree</HI> of God, that will carry Such an One into His King∣dom. Oh! Do not go on in a <HI>Sleepy</HI> Impeniten∣cy, Lest you be found <HI>fore ordained</HI> unto—What is to be trembled at? A <HI>Damnation that Slumbers not.</HI></P>
<P>II. Who but <HI>Ungodly Men</HI> are they, who from the <HI>Contrivance</HI> of their <HI>Salvation,</HI> Encourage them∣selves, as if it gave them an <HI>Allowance</HI> for their <HI>Sinfulness.</HI> That we have Such a SAVIOUR as our IMMANUEL; Oh! the <HI>Riches of Grace</HI> dis∣covered in it! Oh! the <HI>Unspeakable Gift!</HI> We may and must cry out, <HI>God SO Loved the World, and has been So gracious to us!</HI> The Motto to be written upon all that is done for us, in and by our Saviour, is in those Golden Letters; Eph. II. 5. <HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> GRACE YE ARE SAVED.</HI> But what is the <HI>Use</HI> that Some do make of this <HI>Grace▪ Because there is a Saviour, I will Venture to be a Sin∣ner:</HI> This <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s the Language, how <HI>foaming,</HI> and how <HI>shameful!</HI> of <HI>Ungodliness▪</HI> The <HI>New Covenant</HI> is a <HI>Covenant of Grace.</HI> There is a shout of, <HI>Grace! Grace!</HI> to be made upon every stroke! But <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> shall see how this <HI>Grace</HI> is plaid upon. In this <HI>Covenant,</HI> we <HI>Merit nothing by doing</HI> any thing. Then sayes the Sluggard, <HI>I will do nothing. Self</HI> is to be Annihilated in this <HI>Covenant;</HI> the Perpe∣tual Projection of it is, <HI>CHRIST is All! CHRIST
<PB N="7" REF="001551_0008_0FB3A2D4FAC63038"/>
is All!</HI> Then sayes the Sluggard, <HI>I have my self nothing to do.</HI> Tis not by our <HI>Own Works,</HI> that we attain to <HI>Righteousness;</HI> but in our Saviour we have our <HI>Justifying Righteousness.</HI> Then, sayes the Slug∣gish Sinner, <HI>Tis no Matter, tho' I be Careless about the works of Righteousness.</HI> We can do nothing to any <HI>Good Purpose,</HI> except our Saviour do <HI>Quicken</HI> us, do <HI>Assist</HI> us, do <HI>Strengthen</HI> us. Then, sayes the <HI>Door</HI> upon its Hinges, <HI>I will stand still; I will never try to stir; Tis to no purpose at all for me to do any thing.</HI> Our Faithful Saviour, who is <HI>Able to keep us from Falling</HI> has engaged for the <HI>Preservation</HI> of the Saints; that they shall be <HI>Kept by His Mighty Power;</HI> that <HI>None shall Pluck them out of His Hand.</HI> Then sayes one of them that would be at <HI>Ease in Zion, Let me fold my Hands to Sleep; what need I to keep a Strong Guard, and a Strict Watch upon my self? I stand, and why should I take heed lest I fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l?</HI> Ungodly Men, You stand in the way of a dread∣ful Thunderbolt. It comes down upon you, from, Rom. VI. 1, 2. <HI>What shall we say then? Shall we continue in Sin, that Grace may abound? GOD FORBID.</HI> At this <HI>Rebuke, O F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie</HI> from your Sloth∣fulness; At the <HI>Voice of this Thunder, O Haste away</HI> from your Ungodliness. Let the <HI>Spirit</HI> of the <HI>New Covenant</HI> come upon you; and then Your Habitual, Your continual Inclination will be this; <HI>A Glorious</HI> CHRIST <HI>He who does all for me. Oh! Let me then Love Him, and Seek Him, and Glorify Him unto the Uttermost; and be alwayes afraid of disobliging Him.</HI></P>
<P>III. Can they be any other than <HI>Ungodly Men,</HI> who from the <HI>Readiness</HI> of the Divine Mercy for the <HI>Pardoning</HI> of <HI>Sin,</HI> Encourage themselves
<PB N="8" REF="001551_0009_0FB3A2D677502418"/>
to be the <HI>Readier</HI> in the <HI>Committing</HI> of <HI>Sin? Lord, Thou art READY TO PARDON!</HI> Who can hear such a Word, and the <HI>Grace</HI> of it not melt the Heart of Stone within him? The <HI>Grace of God,</HI> in <HI>Pardoning</HI> of Sin, 'tis Wonderful; 'Tis Wonderful! When we are <HI>Justifyed,</HI> it is, <HI>Freely by His Grace.</HI> It is the Name of our God, Exod. XXXIV. 6, 7. <HI>The Lord, the Lord God, Merciful and Gracious, and abundant in Goodness, Forgiving Iniquity, and Transgression, and Sin.</HI> For Monsters of Wickedness, to be made Monuments of Par∣doning Mercy; For Monstrous <HI>Menassehs,</HI> and <HI>Mary Magdalenes,</HI> to be received into the Favour of God, and be favoured by a Reconciled God as much as if they had never Sinned against Him! For <HI>all manner of Sin and Blasphemy to be forgiven unto men;</HI> and a <HI>Fountain set open,</HI> to which the most abominable Creatures in the World, are invited, there to <HI>Wash and be Clean:</HI> What but Infinite <HI>Grace</HI> can do such a thing! You shall now, but Oh! do it not without Horror! See what Improvement <HI>Ungodly Men</HI> will make of such <HI>Grace:</HI> An Improvement which one would wonder that any but a <HI>Devil</HI> should presume upon! They will Venture to <HI>Sin,</HI> in Hope of a <HI>Pardon.</HI> Perhaps, they will be so Senseless, and Sottish, and Exceeding Sinful, as to flatter themselves, that a, <HI>God forgive me,</HI> or a, <HI>Lord, Have Mercy upon me,</HI> will at any time obtain a <HI>Pardon</HI> for them. This Emboldens them to Sin, with a Prodigious Obstinancy; to be <HI>Stout hearted, and far from Righteousness:</HI> They stick at no Abominations. There is a God that <HI>will have Mercy, and will abundantly Pardon;</HI> So they will hold on Sinning, and <HI>Sin abundantly.</HI>
<PB N="9" REF="001551_0010_0FB3A2D818961CF8"/>
And because there have been Some called, at the <HI>Eleventh</HI> Hour, and <HI>then</HI> found Mercy with God; therefore they will Sin on, Sin with <HI>Ma∣ny Transgressions and Mighty Sins,</HI> and put off till <HI>the Last Hour,</HI> the necessary Addresses to Heaven for Mercy. They <HI>Persist</HI> in Enmity and Rebel∣lion against the Glorious God all their Days; they <HI>Presume,</HI> 'tis only to <HI>Ask</HI> and <HI>Have a Pardon</HI> at the Last. Hideous <HI>Ungodliness!</HI> We read, Psal. CXXXIV. 4 O Lord, <HI>There is Forgiveness with thee, that thou ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st be feared.</HI> But now, to say; <HI>There is Forgiveness with God, therefore I will cast off His Fear, and Go on without His Fear;</HI> O Vile Perversion! To Sin from the <HI>View</HI> of a <HI>Pardon,</HI> one would think, it should be very near, <HI>very near!</HI> Sinning beyond the <HI>Reach</HI> of a <HI>Pardon.</HI></P>
<P>IV. Will not all Heaven Pronounce those <HI>Ungodly Men,</HI> who because they take themselves delivered from the <HI>Condemning</HI> Power of the <HI>Law,</HI> Encourage themselves to shake off the <HI>Commanding</HI> Power of the <HI>Law?</HI> The <HI>Grace of God,</HI> has Delivered us from the <HI>Curse</HI> of the <HI>Law.</HI> It is a sweet Advice brought unto us: Gal. III. 13 <HI>CHRIST has Redeemed us from the Curse of the Law, being made a Curse for us.</HI> The Punishment, which by the <HI>Law</HI> of God be∣longed unto us for our <HI>Sin,</HI> has been inflicted on our <HI>Saviour.</HI> Our Blessed <HI>Surety</HI> has Paid our <HI>Debt,</HI> by Suffering for us, the <HI>Curse</HI> which belong∣ed unto us. The <HI>Law</HI> of God has now no De∣mand upon the Believer, that the Divine <HI>Justice</HI> may be Satisfyed: Our <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> has given Satis∣faction <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Grace</HI> of i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>comparabl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Sweetness.</HI> How <HI>Sweet,</HI> how <HI>Sweet,</HI> the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> unto the <HI>Taste</HI> of Piety! But now, the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> which <HI>Ungodly Men</HI> will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> They suppose
<PB N="10" REF="001551_0011_0FB3A2D987330098"/>
themselves rescued from the <HI>Curse</HI> of the <HI>Law.</HI> They make it an Advantage for their Escape also from the <HI>Rule</HI> of the <HI>Law. Silly Ones;</HI> An Escape, that is to say, into <HI>Chains of Darkness;</HI> into the most rueful Captivity in the World. This <HI>Law,</HI> Man; 'tis the <HI>Law of Liberty!</HI> 'Tis an <HI>Enlarged Soul,</HI> that is effectually in the <HI>Bonds</HI> and <HI>Wayes</HI> of this <HI>Law!</HI> But the <HI>Slaves</HI> of Sin; They will indulge themselves in gross Violati∣ons of the <HI>Law;</HI> but still their In<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ard <HI>Peace</HI> not Violated. No Breaches of the <HI>Law,</HI> will break the <HI>Peace</HI> into which they have dozed their Minds. They will flatter themselves into a <HI>Great Peace,</HI> tho' they do not <HI>Love the Law.</HI> Why, say the Hardened Wretches; <HI>We are not under the Law; We must not fetch our Peace from the Law; Christ has answered the Law for us!</HI> What an Affront is this, unto the <HI>Grace of God?</HI> We read; Rom. VI. 14. 15. <HI>Sin shall not have Dominion over you; for you are not under the Law, but under Grace. What then? Shall we Sin, because we are not under the Law, but under Grace? God forbid.</HI> Sirs, You are not yet under <HI>Grace,</HI> but under the <HI>Law,</HI> if you can be content, that <HI>Sin</HI> should still <HI>have Dominion</HI> over you. If you <HI>Sin,</HI> because you are not <HI>under the Law,</HI> it is very sure, you are still under it, in the worse sense of being so. The <HI>Law</HI> does <HI>Condemn</HI> you, if you won't let it <HI>Com∣mand</HI> you. If you shake off that Everlasting <HI>Rule</HI> of Living to God, which His <HI>Law</HI> Prescribes, O <HI>Unholy</HI> and <HI>Unthankful</HI> ones, you shall still hear the Thunder of its <HI>Wrath Cursing</HI> of you.</P>
<P>V. Is it possible for any but <HI>Ungodly Men,</HI> from Gods <HI>Delayes</HI> in <HI>Striking</HI> of them, to En∣courage
<PB N="11" REF="001551_0012_0FB3A2DB4C6D88A8"/>
themselves to <HI>Delay,</HI> their <HI>Seeking</HI> to Him, their <HI>Serving</HI> of Him. The <HI>Grace of God</HI> is very Bright, in His <HI>Patience</HI> towards the Provoking Children of Wickedness. The Psalmist observes, [VII. 11] <HI>God is a Righteous Judge, and is Pro∣voked every Day;</HI> and has <HI>bent His Bow, and made it Ready.</HI> Yet such is His <HI>Grace,</HI> that He does not presently let fly His <HI>Arrows;</HI> Deserved <HI>Ar∣rows,</HI> and Oh! how Destroying Ones! how tor∣turous and worse than Lightning, to the <HI>Spirits,</HI> which they Light upon<HI>!</HI> A Patient God spares wicked men: He does not Strike them Dead; tho' they daily challenge Thunderbolts. O Peer∣less <HI>Grace!</HI> Of a Provoked, a Righteous, an Al∣mighty God; yet, <HI>Waiting to be Gracious.</HI> But now, the use that <HI>Ungodly</HI> and Ungrateful men make of this <HI>Grace.</HI> What can be more Ma∣licious, what more Venemous, than that which you read! Eccl. VIII. 11. <HI>Because Sentence against an Evil Work, is not Executed Speedily; therefore the heart of the Sons of Men is fully set in them to do Evil.</HI> Horrible Stupidity! Because the Threat∣ned Judgments of God, have <HI>not yet come</HI> upon them, for their Crimes, they fancy, they'l <HI>never come;</HI> the <HI>threatned folks,</HI> have still a <HI>long white to Live.</HI> Because they don't yet feel the <HI>Evil.</HI> that is <HI>Pursuing of Sinners,</HI> they comfort themselves, that such <HI>Evil</HI> will never overtake them. They Live; Yea, they Thrive. God <HI>Wounds</HI> them not; For that very cause they grow Secure, they grow Hardy, they <HI>go on still in their Trespasses.</HI> God has not yet <HI>Cut them down</HI> for the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Fruits they bear; He Lengthens out their Time They bear the more <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Fruits</HI> for that; and the wicked men <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> worse and worse.</HI> God gives them a <HI>Space
<PB N="12" REF="001551_0013_0FB3A2DD32B47418"/>
to Repent;</HI> They do, for that very cause Delay to Repent, and make it a <HI>Space</HI> to act more <HI>Wick∣edness,</HI> and with more of <HI>Greediness.</HI> But, <HI>O Ye Bruitish among the People;</HI> What are you doing? Shake before that awful Thunderclap: Rom. II. 4, 5. <HI>Despisest thou the Riches of His Goodness, and Forbearance, and Long Suffering▪ not knowing that the Goodness of God Leads thee to Repentance? But after thy Hardness and Impenitent Heart, treasurest up unto thy self Wrath against the Day of Wrath?</HI> Impenitents; Know you not, That <HI>Abused Pa∣tience</HI> will at Length be turned into <HI>Terrible Fury?</HI> and that, according to Speech usual in the Church of God. The <HI>Justice</HI> which has <HI>Leaden Feet,</HI> will at length find <HI>Iron Hands,</HI> to do its Executions? Oh! Turn to God in this <HI>Day of His Patience!</HI> Oh! Let the <HI>Long suffering of God,</HI> but make you Stay no longer from accepting His offered <HI>Sal∣vation.</HI> Because God seems to <HI>Keep Silen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI> Do you think, He is even <HI>Such an One</HI> as your selves, and approves your Doings? You will find it otherwise, when He shall come to <HI>Set your Sins in order</HI> before you; to <HI>tear you in Pieces, and there shall be none to deliver</HI> you.</P>
<P>VI. 'Tis a thing of an <HI>Ungodly</HI> Aspect, for Men, from such <HI>Liberties</HI> as are <HI>Lawful</HI> Ones, to En∣courage themselves in taking such as are <HI>Un∣lawful</HI> Ones. There are Great <HI>Liberties,</HI> which the <HI>Grace of God</HI> has granted unto <HI>Christians;</HI> Es∣pecially now the <HI>Mosaic Yoke</HI> is taken off, by the <HI>Grace</HI> of a more Evangelical Dispensation. But what sayes the <HI>Law</HI> of CHRIST? 1 Cor. VIII. 9. <HI>But take heed, Lest by any means this Liberty of yours become a Stumbling Block, to them that are weak.</HI>
<PB N="13" REF="001551_0014_0FB3A2DEB864B8C8"/>
Mind this; When things are so <HI>Indifferent,</HI> that there is no <HI>Necessity</HI> of them, and no <HI>Command∣ment</HI> of God obliges to do them, we should think; <HI>Tis true, I may do this thing; But wont my do∣ing of it, cause other People to Sin against my Saviour?</HI> In this Case we must forbear; Else we make a wrong use of our <HI>Liberty. Luther</HI> had an Holy saying; <HI>Omnia Libera per Fidam, S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rva per Chari∣tatem.</HI> O Redeemed People of God; This is a Case that calls for a more Frequent, and Solemn Consideration, than it commonly finds among you! Thus, the <HI>Grace of God</HI> is also Trampled on, When we run into an <HI>Excess</HI> in the use of <HI>Lawful Things.</HI> The Christian has from the <HI>Grace of God,</HI> A CHARTER, for the whole <HI>Creation.</HI> I will show you my <HI>Charter.</HI> It runs in those Terms, 1 Tim. IV. 4 <HI>Every Creature of God is Good, and nothing to be refused, if it be received with Thanks∣giving.</HI> Well, But the <HI>Precepts</HI> of GOD, and the <HI>Maxims</HI> of a <HI>Godly</HI> and <HI>Sober</HI> and <HI>Righteous</HI> Life, must set Bounds to us, in our using of our <HI>Charter.</HI> A Man may <HI>Eat</HI> any thing: But yet he may not be a <HI>Glutton.</HI> A Man may <HI>Drink</HI> what he will; But for all that, he must not be <HI>Drunk.</HI> To be <HI>Slave</HI> unto the use of an <HI>Indian Weed,</HI> or any other <HI>Trifle,</HI> is beneath a Christian, who has Right Thoughts of <HI>Liberty.</HI> He may use it; but not so, as to be in Pain, if he be not alwayes at it. Any Civil <HI>Modes of Apparel</HI> may be fol∣lowed: but <HI>Vanity</HI> and <HI>Luxury</HI> in Apparel; Ha∣bits that are the <HI>Ensigns</HI> of a Foolish Mind; Im∣moderate and Exorbitant <HI>Gaieties;</HI> The Disciples of the Humble JESUS, must put off such things. <HI>Liberty</HI> is turned into <HI>Slavery,</HI> when it runs into <HI>Extravagances.</HI> I never <HI>Sin,</HI> but I <HI>Enslave</HI> my self.</P>
<P><PB N="14" REF="001551_0015_0FB3A2E072162C90"/>
VII. 'Tis a Branch of <HI>Ungodliness,</HI> for Men, from the <HI>Relation</HI> they bear to the God of Hea∣ven, to Encourage themselves in Miscarriages to∣wards the <HI>Men</HI> on Earth, whom they stand Re∣lated to. The <HI>Grace of God</HI> bestows mighty <HI>Priviledges,</HI> on them, whom He raises unto the Relation of His <HI>People,</HI> and His <HI>Children.</HI> But what sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s the Apostle? 1 Pet. II. 16 <HI>As free, not using your Liberty, as a Cloke of Maliciousness, but as the Servants of God.</HI> Thro' the <HI>Grace of God,</HI> my Conscience is exempted from all <HI>Humane Empire;</HI> None but the Great GOD can Command my <HI>Conscience;</HI> I may not Complement any Man, tho' he were a greater Tyrant than him at <HI>Versailles,</HI> with a Subjection of my <HI>Conscience</HI> unto him. For all that, I must <HI>make Conscience</HI> of Sub∣mitting to the Government, which is an <HI>Ordi∣nance of God. Paul</HI> writing to the <HI>Romans,</HI> cauti∣o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s them of this; That they should not on the score of their <HI>Christianity</HI> pretend an Exemption from the Jurisdiction of the <HI>Magistrate;</HI> in the Things for which <HI>God has Ordained him.</HI> So No∣thing but the WORD of God, is to <HI>Order</HI> all things in the <HI>Church</HI> of God; Things are never done <HI>Decently</HI> there, but when done <HI>according to that Order.</HI> The <HI>Inventions</HI> of Men may not be imposed there; We are to Reject such <HI>Schis∣matical Impositions;</HI> The <HI>Imposers,</HI> however Libe∣ral they are in bestowing the Term upon others, are to be look'd upon as the true <HI>Schismaticks.</HI> For all this; the Church is to <HI>Pray for all that are in Authority;</HI> and its People are to <HI>Lead Pea∣ceable Lives in all Godliness and Honesty.</HI> In the Church, the <HI>Pastors</HI> must not <HI>Lord it over the
<PB N="15" REF="001551_0016_0FB3A2E1F66B7520"/>
Heritage.</HI> The <HI>People</HI> must have the <HI>Choice</HI> of their own <HI>Pastors:</HI> The <HI>Pastors</HI> must proceed with the <HI>Consent of the People</HI> in things of com∣mon concernment. This was the true State of Things in the <HI>Primitive Church,</HI> and so they continued for some hundreds of years, and un∣til they were overwhelmed with the Usurpati∣ons of Antichrist. It is an <HI>Obstinacy</HI> little short of a <HI>Miraculous</HI> Infliction, which they discover, who will at this time of Day, <HI>Contradict</HI> things that are so notoriously demonstrated. Sacred and Precious <HI>Liberties!</HI> But now, you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; Gal. V. 13. <HI>Brethren, Ye have been called unto Li∣berty; Only use not your Liberty for an occasion to the Flesh▪ but by Love Serve one another.</HI> O dear Flocks of the Lord; You must not now forget that word; <HI>Obey them that have the Rule <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ver you, and Watch for your Souls.</HI> Nor forget that word; <HI>Let the Elders that Rule well be counted worthy of double Honour:</HI> Nor for∣get that word; <HI>Know them that are over you in the Lord, and Esteem them very highly in Love.</HI> The <HI>Grace of God</HI> should indeed cause <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> and <HI>People,</HI> to be always loading One another with Tokens of Mutual Affection. In our Fa∣milies, <HI>Humanity</HI> goes a great way, and <HI>Christi∣anity</HI> much further, in this; That a <HI>Servant</HI> becomes a <HI>Brother.</HI> But if the <HI>Servant</HI> shall now Despise his Master, Insult his Master, <HI>Disobey</HI> the Master, which the <HI>Fifth Commandment</HI> has bound him to; Let that <HI>Brother</HI> be beaten into <HI>better Matters;</HI> make him to know his <HI>Inferiour Con∣dition</HI> a little better. He Saucily Pla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es upon the <HI>Grace of God;</HI> and should be chastised for it.</P>
<P><PB N="16" REF="001551_0017_0FB3A2E3B78F5BB0"/>
VIII. 'Tis a flaming <HI>Ungodliness,</HI> when from the <HI>Gifts</HI> of God unto Men, their <HI>Sins</HI> against God, are encouraged, are furnished, are nou∣rished. The <HI>Grace of God,</HI> grants <HI>Gifts</HI> unto Men; Oh, why should it be said, <HI>Unto the Re∣bellious! Ungodly Men,</HI> they make the <HI>Gifts</HI> of God unto them, only a <HI>Furniture</HI> and a <HI>Nourish∣ment</HI> for them, in carrying on <HI>Rebellions</HI> against Him. <HI>Unrighteous</HI> Ones; They fall into the Fault of <HI>Jeshuru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</HI> Deut. XXXII. 15. <HI>He waxed fat, and Kicked.</HI> Have they any <HI>Wit? Fools</HI> have the keeping of it; They are only, <HI>Wise to do Evil.</HI> Have they <HI>Health</HI> and <HI>Strength</HI> of Body? It only renders them the more <HI>Able,</HI> and the more <HI>Eager</HI> to <HI>Commit Iniquity.</HI> Are they <HI>Beautiful?</HI> They are <HI>Proud</HI> of it: And with it, they Tempt <HI>the Simple ones, and those that are void of Understanding.</HI> Do <HI>Riches increase</HI> up∣on them? All goes to feed, the <HI>Lust of the Flesh,</HI> and the <HI>Lust of the Eye,</HI> and the <HI>Pride of Life.</HI> They do but the more put their <HI>Trust in Uncertain Riches</HI> God has little <HI>Honour from their Substance.</HI> Are they put into <HI>Commissions;</HI> or advanced unto Stations and Places of some <HI>Dignity?</HI> It fills them with empty Conceits of <HI>themselves.</HI> They employ their Opportunities, not so much to <HI>Do Good</HI> in the World, as that they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be <HI>made Rich, and the Glory of their H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>use increased.</HI> The XLVII Chapter of <HI>Genesis,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me Exhibits an Example of such an <HI>Abused Advancement,</HI> which I must own, I cannot with∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Scandal, and Sorrow, and Wonder think <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> But how much imitated in our Later <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>? Marvellous Disingenuity! To fight
<PB N="17" REF="001551_0018_0FB3A2E666AAC208"/>
against the Blessed God, with <HI>His Own Weapons,</HI> at such a rate▪ Thus to take <HI>His Corn,</HI> and <HI>His Wins,</HI> and <HI>His Wool<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</HI> and only <HI>Serve diverse Lusts</HI> with them! Thus to take <HI>His Talents,</HI> and only Trade for the <HI>Devil</HI> with them! With such <HI>Ungodly Men,</HI> how Suitably, how Pungently may we use that Expostulation! Deut XXXII. 6 <HI>Do ye thus Requite the Lord, O foolish People an Unwise!</HI> A Base Requital for the <HI>Grace</HI> of a Good God! On! Blush, and be Ashamed of it.</P>
<P>IX. I have one word more to speak; and I may the more freely speak it, inasmuch as the Cause of <HI>Godliness</HI> is Evidently Concerned in it. It is this, 'Tis an Evident Affront unto the <HI>Grace of God,</HI> for Men to make the <HI>Birth</HI> of our <HI>Holy Saviour,</HI> an Encouragement and an Oc∣casion for very <HI>Unholy Enormities.</HI> The <HI>Grace of God</HI> never Shone out more Gloriously, than in that Occurrence upon which an <HI>Angel</HI> flew from Heaven to tell us, <HI>Behold I bring you good Ti∣dings of Great Joy; That unto you there <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> born this Day a Saviour.</HI> But if such an <HI>Angel</HI> were <HI>this Day</HI> to Preach among you, do you think, He would not Thunder and Lighten Wonderfully against the Vicious practices, in which this <HI>Grace of God,</HI> and that Holy Saviour, is this Day Af∣fronted by multitudes of <HI>Ungodly Men</HI> in the World I do not now propose any matter of <HI>Doubtful Disputation,</HI> but One, wherein I shall have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Godly Persons</HI> of whatever different Perswasions <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> things, Concurring with me. I do not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> whether they who three or four hundred <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> after the Birth of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="18" REF="001551_0019_0FB3A2E7B6ED0900"/>
first began the Festival of his Nativity (I say, <HI>first began,</HI> for <HI>Vossius</HI> himself confesses it was not kept in the first and second Century, and <HI>Chem∣nitius</HI> truly sayes, <HI>Apud Vetustissimos nunquam Legitur!</HI>) did not mistake the <HI>Time</HI> of it. For they who say, <HI>Thou hast given thy Son to be born this Day,</HI> know not what they say; The <HI>Day</HI> is concealed; yea, it is now beyond Contesta∣tion proved, that not only the <HI>Month</HI> but also the very <HI>Year</HI> of it, has been Egregiously mistaken.<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>The La<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e most accurate</HI> Professor of the Mathematicks, <HI>in</HI> Cambridge, <HI>has in his Exquisite work about the</HI> Chronology of the Bible, <HI>brought this Matter under such a Demonstration, that it is no longer to be disputed of. The whole Process of the Demonstration, is too large to be introdu∣ced here. But briefly; we are certain, that our Saviour was born before the Death of</HI> Herod, <HI>that horrible Tyrant, whom they call,</HI> The Great. <HI>We have now discovered Irrefragable Proofs, that this Monster Expired, on the Twenty-fifth of</HI> No∣vember, <HI>in the 4710 year of the</HI> Julian Period, <HI>which was, Three years and above a Month, before the present</HI> Christian AEra. <HI>Besides many other unquestionable Accounts, concer∣ning the Date of</HI> Herods <HI>Reign, we have a most infallible one, in the</HI> Eclipse <HI>of the Moon, which happened, as all agree, on the thirteenth of</HI> March <HI>before his Death. By this infal∣lible Mark, he died in the</HI> 4710 <HI>year of the</HI> Julian Period, <HI>which was the</HI> 4001 <HI>year of the World. And the Jewish Ka∣lender has all along made the</HI> 25 <HI>day of</HI> November, <HI>an Holi∣day.</HI> Because on that Day <HI>Herod</HI> the King died. <HI>Now the</HI> Birth <HI>of our Saviour must be, at least a Month before the</HI> Death of Herod <HI>And on the other side, we cannot allow <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> more than a Month; because of the Time, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> now Easily determined, for the Attendance of the Father of</HI> John Baptist <HI>at the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> The Opinion of Dr.</HI> Lightfoot <HI>and Some others, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> place the Birth of our Saviour Two years before the Death of</HI> Herod, <HI>can by no means be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB N="19" REF="001551_0020_0FB3A2E9F93297E8"/>
supported. It must unavoidably be the</HI> Same Year; <HI>But then, it could not possibly be after</HI> October. <HI>Nor, do I know, why it should not be, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> many Learned men have judged, about the Time of the</HI> Feast of Tabernacles, <HI>which was a glori∣ous and elegant Figure of it. The Conjecture, That</HI> October <HI>being really the</HI> Tenth Month, <HI>to them who begin the Year in</HI> January, <HI>the Primitive Christians had a Tradition of our Saviours being born on the</HI> 25 <HI>day of the</HI> Tenth Month; <HI>and this threw the first I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stitutors of the present Holiday, into the Error which has ever since been gone upon; I Know no need of Paying any Respect unto it. Upon the whole; It is now determined, that the</HI> Christian AEra, <HI>the Computation whereof was first made by</HI> Dion<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sius Exiguus, <HI>between five and six hundred years after the Birth of our Saviour, has misreckoned above three years; insomuch that we are now truly entred into the Year of our Lord,</HI> 1716 <HI>And it is also determined, that the Birth of our Saviour was before the Month of</HI> November, <HI>in which the Bloody</HI> Iduma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an, <HI>who sought His Death, found his own.</HI></NOTE> I do not now dispute, whether People do well to Observe such an <HI>Uninstituted Festival</HI> at all, or no. Good Men may love one another, and may treat one another with a most Candid Charity, while he <HI>that Regardeth a Day, Regardeth it unto the Lord,</HI> and he that <HI>Regardeth not the Day,</HI> also shows his <HI>Regard unto the Lord,</HI> in his <HI>not Re∣garding</HI> of it. Tho' this I will take leave to say: If the Churches of NEW ENGLAND preserve the <HI>Religion of the LORDS DAY,</HI> it will in the <HI>Day of Reformation</HI> that must come on, be judg'd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Dishonour to them, that they have harmo∣nized with their <HI>United Brethren</HI> in <HI>Scotland,</HI> in a Point for which the last of their peculiar Kings once applauded their <HI>Purity,</HI> even their not ha∣ving a <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> observed among them. What I am
<PB N="20" REF="001551_0021_0FB3A2EC594B99E8"/>
going to animadvert upon, is a thing, which there can be <HI>no doubt</HI> about. And there are some things that render it highly Seasonable, to dispense those <HI>Admonitions of God our Saviour,</HI> unto our Children, which I am now to pour down upon them. The famous <HI>Perkins</HI> long since complained; <HI>That the Feast of Christs Nati∣vity is spent in Revel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing. Dicing, Carding, Masking, and in all Licentious Liberty, for the most part, as tho' it were some Heathen Feast, of</HI> Ceres, <HI>or</HI> Bac∣chus. Yea, the zealous Martyr <HI>Latymer</HI> com∣plained. <HI>That Men dishonour Christ more in the Twelve Days of Christmas, than in all the twelve Months of the Year besides.</HI> All the truly Reli∣gious People in the World, still make the Com∣plaint with Lamentation We also must <HI>Mourn in our Complaint, and make a Noise,</HI> upon it. My Concern is now, with our own Children; and for such as we must faithfully Admonish in our Ministry, as we shall answer the same unto GOD. Children, We lay the Charges of God upon you; That if any People take <HI>this Time,</HI> for any thing of a <HI>Riotous Tendency,</HI> you do not associate with them, in such <HI>Ungodliness.</HI> No, but let your Answer to those Children of Folly be, <HI>The Grace of God in Sending us a Great Saviour calls for more Pious Acknowledgments.</HI> Let your Own <HI>Conscience</HI> be appeal'd unto; the Preacher which every one of you has in his own bosome, hearken'd to! Can you in your <HI>Con∣science</HI> think, that our <HI>Holy Saviour</HI> is honoured, by <HI>Mad Mirth,</HI> by long <HI>Eating,</HI> by hard <HI>Drink∣ing,</HI> by lewd <HI>Gaming,</HI> by rude <HI>Revelling;</HI> by a <HI>Mass</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it for none but a <HI>Saturn,</HI> or a <HI>Bacchus,</HI> or the Night of a <HI>Mahometan Ramadam?</HI> You
<PB N="21" REF="001551_0022_0FB3A2EDE6F19AC0"/>
cannot possibly think so! At the <HI>Birth</HI> of our Saviour, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>A Multitude of the Heavenly Host was hear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI> shall it be said, That at the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> our Saviour for which we owe as High Praises to God as they can do, We take the Time to Please the <HI>Hellish Le∣gions,</HI> and to do Actions that have much more of <HI>Hell</HI> than of <HI>Heaven</HI> in them? I must faith∣fully tell you, This way of honouring the Bles∣sed JESUS, who came to <HI>Redeem us from a Vain Conversation, received by Tradition from our Fathers,</HI> 'tis a practical <HI>Blasphemy</HI> upon Him; an High∣handed <HI>Blasphemy</HI> upon Him! It is to outrage the Holy Son of God! It is to Expose your selves unto that Indignation of Heaven, which they who <HI>take the Name of the Lord our God in Vain,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly open unto. If you will yet go on, and will do Such Things, I forewarn you, That the Burning Wrath of God, will break forth among you. All Persons, of any the least <HI>Godliness,</HI> will approve my Faithfulness, in what I have now Spoken; If any Man Dislike it, and Revile it, he only shows the Brand of an <HI>Ungodly Man,</HI> and a <HI>Contempt</HI> from every Citizen of <HI>Zion,</HI> accordingly belongs unto him.</P>
<P>Upon the Whole: The EXHORTATION that now calls upon us all, must be that: 2 Cor. VI. 1. <HI>We beseech you, that ye receive not the Grace of God in Vain.</HI> Oh! Don't <HI>Wanton∣nize </HI> upon the <HI>Grace of God.</HI> But upon every Instance of <HI>Grace,</HI> make that Reflection. <HI>What shall I render to the Lord?</HI> In short, Remem∣ber this; Obligations to Holiness, You are still to Read <HI>Them,</HI> in all that is ever done by
<PB N="22" REF="001551_0023_0FB3A2EF36610158"/>
the <HI>Grace of God</HI> for a Sinful World. If GOD be <HI>Gracious,</HI> My Friend, thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> from it must alwayes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>must be Holy; O my God, make me so!</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in the more, because of the <HI>Grace</HI> in our God; Verily, Tis the foulest <HI>Prophanity;</HI> An attempt it is, to call in the God who <HI>is of Purer Eyes than to behold Evil, and can∣not Look on Iniquity,</HI> and render Him a <HI>Patron</HI> of all <HI>Evil,</HI> all <HI>Iniquity.</HI> Tis the grossest <HI>Ingratitude; Evil rendred for Good,</HI> in the most odious man∣ner that ever was heard of: <HI>Evil will never de∣part</HI> from the Doer of it. And, <HI>What will ye do in the End thereof?</HI> Endless, <HI>Endless</HI> Misery will be the <HI>End</HI> thereof! I must say unto you, It is the blackest Note of a <HI>Reprobate Mind;</HI> a Soul Forsaken of God! And it will pull down a <HI>Wrath unto the Uttermost.</HI> Sinner, If <HI>Grace</HI> it self become thy <HI>Foe,</HI> what <HI>Friend</HI> canst thou have in Heaven or Earth? To <HI>Wantonnize</HI> upon it, is the way to make it so.</P>
<P>That Saving drawes on a COROLLARY, which my Discourse may do well to Lodge in the Conclusion of it. If it be an <HI>Ungodly</HI> thing, and a <HI>Dangerous,</HI> to <HI>turn the Grace of God into Wantonness,</HI> You must Look on it, as the Same thing, to <HI>turn the Wrath of God into Ridicule.</HI> The Truth is, These Two Things go together. They who do the One, do the Other too. O you that are yet in your Sins; Unbelievers, that have not made your Flight by Faith unto the Only Saviour; You, you are they, of whom it is said; Joh. III 36. <HI>The Wrath of God abideth on them.</HI> Certainly, You <HI>Ridicule</HI> that <HI>Wrath,</HI> or you could not continue in your Sins; You could not but be in Agony, for a <HI>Deliverance from the
<PB N="23" REF="001551_0024_0FB3A2F0B8E51040"/>
Wrath to come.</HI> You make light of that Wrath, which throws down <HI>Rocks,</HI> and whereby <HI>Moun∣tains</HI> are overturned: An <HI>Anger,</HI> which, <HI>O Lord, who knowes the Power of!</HI> Miserable Ones, yet walking in the Sinful Wayes for which your own Hearts condemn you; Wayes that have <HI>Destruction</HI> and <HI>Misery</HI> in them: Oh! Break off your Sins, and Accept and Embrace the JESUS who would Save you from your Sins. Other∣wise, you will anon feel the <HI>Wrath</HI> of God, but find the Force of it Irresistible, the weight of it Insupportable, the Tortures of it in your <HI>Wounded Spirit,</HI> Intolerable. You will roar out the Words, which a late famous Protestant A∣postatising to the Popish Idolatry, did in un∣speakable Horror of Conscience, Dy withal; those words, Heb. X. 31. <HI>It is a fearful thing to fall into the Hands of the Living God.</HI></P>
<P>¶ It ought rather to be an <HI>Ingredient</HI> of this Discourse, than an <HI>Appendix</HI> to it, for me to treat you with yet another COROLLARY.</P>
<P>You have all this while seen the <HI>Word of God</HI> brandished against those <HI>Armies of the Aliens,</HI> who <HI>turn the Grace of God into Wantonness.</HI> We hope, We are better skill'd at <HI>making Inferences,</HI> than those Men, whose <HI>Transgression sayes, There <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> no Fear of God before their Eyes.</HI> I am sure, this is a Right One. For men from the <HI>Word of God</HI> it self to Encourage themselves in things very <HI>Contrary</HI> to that <HI>Holy Word;</HI> this is a very Wrong Thing. Yea, Let it come into the Catalogue; and make up the <HI>Decad</HI> of the Wayes, wherein
<PB N="24" REF="001551_0025_0FB3A2F332846F20"/>
Men <HI>turn the Grace of God into Wantonness.</HI> That we Enjoy the <HI>Word of God,</HI> wherein the <HI>Day spring from on <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> has Visited us,</HI> 'tis thro' the <HI>tender Mercy of our God.</HI> And it is, <HI>The Good Word of His Grace,</HI> which this <HI>Tender Mercy of our God</HI> has bestow'd upon us. Now, to fetch from this very <HI>Word of God,</HI> which is all of it <HI>Written that we may not Sin,</HI> the Plea's to Excuse, to Defend, to Embolden Sin; truly this is to <HI>Sin Impudently,</HI> and with peculiar Aggravations. 'Tis to do what we read, 2 Pet. III. 16 <HI>They wr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st the Scriptures unto their own Destruction.</HI> What else do they do, who because we read, <HI>Take no Thought for to Morrow,</HI> give themselves up to <HI>Slothfulness</HI> in their Business? What else do they, who because we read, <HI>If any man provide not for his own, he is worse than an Infidel,</HI> there∣fore will out of that <HI>Provision,</HI> spare little or nothing for the <HI>Pious Uses</HI> directed of God? What else do they, who because we read, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that Eateth and Drinketh at the Table of the Lord Unworthily, Eateth and Drinketh Judgment unto himself,</HI> therefore <HI>Stay away Unworthily,</HI> and never Prepare to come thither, as they ought to do? But this <HI>Ungodliness</HI> is never more Exemplified, then in the <HI>Ungodly Inferences,</HI> drawn from the <HI>Scriptural Examples,</HI> of them who have Sinned grievously, while they have had the <HI>Grace of God</HI> asleep in their Souls, or have after Great and Long Sinning been thro' the <HI>Grace of God</HI> received unto Mercy. <HI>Noah</HI> Sinned, <HI>Lot</HI> Sinned, Abominable things were done by <HI>David, Peter</HI> did an horrible Thing. And, <HI>Why may not I venture to do so too?</HI> This was an <HI>Ungodliness</HI>
<PB N="25" REF="001551_0026_0FB3A2F51F9622C8"/>
of old run into; <HI>Si</HI> Noah, <HI>cur non et Ego? Si</HI> David, <HI>cur non et Ego?</HI> Alas, Children, These <HI>Examples</HI> are for our <HI>Admonition.</HI> Why do you misapply them for your <HI>Depravation?</HI> They are to make you <HI>Afraid</HI> of provoking the Holy One, to leave you unto your selves; Lest you <HI>Sin like them,</HI> and then Endure such <HI>Broken Bones,</HI> as made them to <HI>Roar by reason of the Disquietness of their Heart,</HI> under the Impres∣sions of His dreadful Displeasure, when they did the <HI>things which displeased the Lord.</HI> While you hearten your selves to <HI>Sin,</HI> because these Men have <HI>Sinned,</HI> you wretchedly divert the Re∣lation from the true Purposes, for which the Pens of God have Written it; and you Forget the <HI>Sad Hours,</HI> which the Sins of these Persons brought them to!</P>
<P>But of all the Examples in the Bible, there never was any wherein the <HI>Grace of God</HI> has been so abused, as that of the <HI>Thief on the Cross.</HI> The <HI>Cross</HI> of that Penitent <HI>Thief,</HI> has been a Stumbling-block to Millions of Ungodly Men. He it seems, put off his <HI>Repentance</HI> to the <HI>Last Hour,</HI> and <HI>then,</HI> he found Mercy with God. Therefore, sayes the Impenitent Sinner. <HI>I will do so too.</HI> I apprehend, it will be a Service to the Interests of <HI>Godliness,</HI> that this case be a little spoken to: and I will therefore, in a brief <HI>Dissertation,</HI> Conclude with it.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="conclusion">
<PB N="26" REF="001551_0027_0FB3A2F6090CC9A8"/>
<HEAD>A Few Thoughts on that QUESTION; Whether the Penitent Thief on the Cross, be not an Example of One Repenting at the Last Hour, and on such a Late Repentance received unto Mercy?</HEAD>
<P>I Am far from a <HI>Perempto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y Denial</HI> of it. I cannot prove, that we <HI>have not</HI> such an Example here given unto us. Who can tell what <HI>Soveraign Grace</HI> may do? We cannot <HI>Limit the Holy One</HI> from doing such a Thing. 'Tis a <HI>Possible Thing;</HI> And the Glorious Lord may leave us in the Story a <HI>Room</HI> for such a Possibility, that the Sinful Children of Men overtaken by their <HI>Last Hour</HI> in their Sins, may not be abandoned unto a <HI>total Despair</HI> of Mercy. And that their Surviving Friends may not <HI>Sor∣row as those that have no Hope,</HI> on their occasion▪ But at the same time, there are many things which render it <HI>Probable,</HI> that the Penitent now before us, will prove <HI>no such Example,</HI> and that the Impious <HI>Procrastination</HI> of Repentance, which is too commonly encouraged from <HI>this Example,</HI> will be found utterly spoiled of all its pretended Encouragement. It has been a Matter of just
<PB N="27" REF="001551_0028_0FB3A2F8590361A0"/>
Resentment unto the Friends of Piety, that the <HI>Thief on the Cross,</HI> going a Villian thither, and <HI>at the Last Hour</HI> finding <HI>Repentance</HI> and <HI>Forgive∣ness</HI> there, has been the <HI>Goliahs Sword,</HI> and a sort of <HI>Enchanted Spear,</HI> by which the cause of <HI>Persisting Impenitency,</HI> has been maintained in the World. I am willing to Disarm the Enemy of his boasted Weapon.</P>
<P>Unto me, it seems not at all <HI>Improbable,</HI> nay, there appears an high <HI>Probability</HI> for it; That the Malefactor now Repenting on the Cross, <HI>brought thither</HI> the <HI>Saving Dispositions of Repen∣tance</HI> with him, and had before now <HI>begun</HI> upon him a Work of that <HI>Repentance, which is unto Salvation.</HI> For,</P>
<P>First, there is nothing in the Sacred History, to brand this Poor Man with the Character of an <HI>Unrepenting Sinner,</HI> at the Time of his being brought forth to his Execution. Two of the Evangelists, <HI>Matthew,</HI> and his Follower and A∣bridger <HI>Mark,</HI> indeed Speak in the Plural Num∣ber, as if <HI>both</HI> of the <HI>Thieves</HI> at first joined in the Reproaches of our Saviour. And if it were so, it may remain a <HI>Quere,</HI> How far a <HI>true Penitent</HI> heartily bewayling of all his Wickedness, and believing in the Sacrifice of the Promised <HI>Messiah</HI> for the Pardon of it, might yet be so circumstanced, as to be kept <HI>Invincibly Ignorant,</HI> that our Blessed JESUS, was this Messiah? But then I concur with those more Judicious Writers, who do by no means allow, that the Thief whom we now have our Eye upon, did <HI>himself</HI> Reproach our Saviour. <HI>Drusius</HI> is displeased at them who make this objection of the <HI>Plural Number,</HI> and sayes, <HI>Apagi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, qui non didicistis Liter as Hebraicas.</HI>
<PB N="28" REF="001551_0029_0FB3A2FB47E10F30"/>
They are ignorant of the <HI>Hebrew Style.</HI> [See Judg. XII. 7.] It is also observed as a peculiar, but perpetual way, taken by the Evangelist <HI>Matthew,</HI> in his Writing, That where <HI>Several</HI> Persons are joined, and <HI>One</HI> Speaks, and it is either in the Name of the rest, or the rest are Silent at it, he refers the Speeches or Actions of that <HI>One,</HI> unto the <HI>whole Number</HI> present, [A Notable Example, see Matth. XX. 30 with Mar. X. 46. And another, Matth. XXVI 8. with Joh. XII. 4.] Thus, we read of Things <HI>Written in the Prophets,</HI> when only <HI>One</HI> of the Prophets wrote them. <HI>Glassius</HI> will further satis∣fy you. Tis a frequent <HI>Synecdoche.</HI> This is in∣deed an <HI>Ancient Observation:</HI> and it leaves us cause to Suspect, as very Learned Expositors have conjectured, That the <HI>other Thief alone</HI> Reproached our Saviour, as <HI>Luke</HI> relates it, and this was wholly Silent at the First, until the Violence of his Companions Language, and the consideration of the astonishing Accidents than in his View, compelled him at once to rebuke his Companion, and Confess his Redeemer. I am far from thinking the <HI>Apostolical Constitutions,</HI> to be of that Antiquity and Authority which a famous Arian in our Dayes would assign un∣to them. Yet some things in them, are of such <HI>Antiquity,</HI> as to deserve that Reverence and Re∣ception with us, which is due to the Opinion of the <HI>Ancients.</HI> And it is a little Confirmation of my Opinion in this case, that the <HI>Apostolical Constitutions</HI> do favour it. <HI>Jerom</HI> also and <HI>Austin</HI> are of the same Opinion. A <HI>Syllepsis</HI> here, sayes <HI>Jerom;</HI> An <HI>Enallage,</HI> saith <HI>Austin.</HI></P>
<P>But then,</P>
<P><PB N="29" REF="001551_0030_0FB3A2FCC11A6110"/>
Secondly; Without having Recourse to the Judgment of the Great <HI>Voetius,</HI> That this Trans∣gressor had the Beginning of a <HI>Regenerate State,</HI> before he was left unto his Capital Transgres∣sions; It is an Easy thing to Suppose, and there is little Reason to question the Supposal; That this Thief had <HI>Opportunity,</HI> in the <HI>Prison,</HI> for some while before his Execution, to come unto a Serious <HI>Repentance</HI> of his Ungodly Life. His Miserable Condition, would naturally lead him to <HI>Consider of his Wayes.</HI> There were also Some <HI>Godly Men</HI> in the Town, whose Charity might lead them to Visit him with their Instructions. We still have some Footsteps of the Care, which the Godly among the Jews took of, <HI>The Con∣demned.</HI> They would not <HI>Scourge,</HI> much less, would they <HI>Hang</HI> a Criminal, without Instructing him from the <HI>Sacred Scriptures.</HI> He might also be long before <HI>Instructed</HI> in those Truths of Re∣ligion, which the Spirit of God might here bring home unto his Mind, with a Sanctifying Efficacy. 'Tis very possible, and more than so, that this Man, might while in the <HI>Gaol,</HI> and many Weeks before his <HI>Death,</HI> be brought, bitterly to <HI>Lament,</HI> and sincerely to <HI>Abhor,</HI> all his wicked Courses, and heartily to <HI>Prefer</HI> a Life devoted unto the Service of God, and rely on the Offering of the <HI>Son of God</HI> then Expected, for his Recon∣ciliation to the Glorious One, in <HI>whose Favour is Life;</HI> and be truly desirous to Know and to Do the whole <HI>Duty</HI> of a Repenting Sinner. Yea, there is nothing to hinder, but that he might have <HI>heard</HI> so much concerning the <HI>Fame</HI> of the <HI>Wisdom</HI> of God in our Blessed JESUS, <HI>with his Ears,</HI> that the <HI>Destruction</HI> and the <HI>Death</HI> to which
<PB N="30" REF="001551_0031_0FB3A2FEF0DBA120"/>
he was near, might find him exceedingly dis∣posed for the Faith of this our JESUS too.</P>
<P>And;</P>
<P>Thirdly, that which very much Countenances the Conjecture, that it might be so, is; The <HI>Wonderful Readiness</HI> of the Thief, at all the Ex∣pressions of this Repentance, <HI>as soon</HI> as you see him exposed on the Cross. Every thing looks as if he came thither <HI>Prepared</HI> with the <HI>Grace,</HI> which he so readily, and so notably Expresses there. We have not the least Intimation of any <HI>Pains</HI> taken there to <HI>Enlighten</HI> him, and <HI>Admonish</HI> him; Nor do the <HI>Torments</HI> then upon him, and the <HI>Clamours</HI> of the People about him, seem to allow the <HI>Words of the Wise,</HI> then to do much, at reaching of him. And yet the <HI>Grace</HI> Exer∣cised by this Penitent, was of so Various and Marvellous an Application, that one may say, He does in a <HI>few Hours</HI> the work of <HI>some Years;</HI> and in a <HI>few Minutes</HI> runs thro' the <HI>whole Race</HI> of Christianity! It looks as if he brought hi∣ther with him, a <HI>Broken and a Contrite Heart;</HI> and the Humble Sense of his having deserved not only <HI>Death</HI> from the hand of Man, but much more <HI>Hell</HI> from the hand of God, whereof he made now such a Ready Acknowledgment. <HI>We Suffer justly; we receive the due Reward of our Deeds!</HI> The words are dictated from an Heart, that seems to have been some time deeply af∣fected, with the sense of what is uttered in them. And, as <HI>Grotius</HI> notes, <HI>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m est P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nitentiae Sig∣num, in Paena sua acquiescere.</HI> It looks also as if he <HI>brought hither</HI> with him, a pretty clear and strong Perswasion, of Things concerning the <HI>Messiah,</HI> which it is plain from the Gospel of <HI>John,</HI>
<PB N="31" REF="001551_0032_0FB3A30136D06CC8"/>
the Church in those dayes did more thoroughly believe, than some too disaffected unto <HI>true Christianity</HI> in our Dayes, are willing to allow of. He is perswaded, of a <HI>Future State;</HI> That in the World to come, the Children of Men shall be <HI>Raised from the Dead:</HI> That the <HI>Messiah</HI> shall have a <HI>Kingdom</HI> in that World: That there must be Two <HI>Comings</HI> of the <HI>Messiah:</HI> And that the <HI>Messiah</HI> will do those things for His People, when He <HI>Comes in His Kingdom,</HI> which can be done by none, but One who is <HI>God</HI> as well as <HI>Man.</HI> All these, and more than these Illustrious Arti∣cles, are professed in the <HI>Faith</HI> of this Penitent. But what <HI>Opportunity</HI> could he have to be <HI>Taught</HI> these Things, after he was Nailed unto the Tree? The Spirit of God, it is true, now Excited the <HI>Exercise</HI> of his <HI>Faith,</HI> on these Articles, after a Wonderful Manner. But shall we say, that the <HI>Idea's</HI> and <HI>Impressions</HI> of the Things in these Articles were <HI>now,</HI> and never till now, purely by an <HI>In∣ternal Irradiation,</HI> produced in his Mind? This would indeed <HI>Multiply the Miracles</HI> in this matter; but surely, <HI>Citra Necessitatem!</HI> And it may be also said, <HI>Contra Utilitatem.</HI> There is no <HI>Need</HI> of such an Imagination; and some have thought, the <HI>Good</HI> of it, has been as little.</P>
<P>Yet more;</P>
<P>It was not only a <HI>True Faith,</HI> which the Pe∣nitent here Exercises; but he looks like one grown <HI>Strong in Faith,</HI> in <HI>giving such Glory to God.</HI> My <HI>Calvin</HI> sayes truly upon it. <HI>Cert<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vix a Mundo condito magis rar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m et memorabile <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>idei Exemplum unquam <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>xtitit.</HI> Perceiving our JESUS to be that <HI>Son of God,</HI> on whom he had Believed, he now makes a most Marvellous <HI>Confession</HI> of His <HI>Glory.</HI>
<PB N="32" REF="001551_0033_0FB3A302C1625308"/>
He ascribes to <HI>Him</HI> the <HI>Glory,</HI> which belongs unto the Promised <HI>Messiah,</HI> and that <HI>Seed</HI> that was to <HI>bruise the Head of the Angel of Death.</HI> And, as it was of old remarked, <HI>A Latrone victi sunt Apostoli, qui tun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> credidit, quando illi defecerunt;</HI> He was the only <HI>Apostle</HI> our Saviour now had cleaving unto him; I had almost said, <HI>The only Visible Believer,</HI> in the World, at least, the <HI>only Thorough paced</HI> One. He supplied the Room of <HI>Judas,</HI> (who was a <HI>Thief;</HI>) He Preached Him on the <HI>Cross,</HI> whom <HI>Judas</HI> betray'd to the <HI>Cross.</HI> Yea, he was, as one calls him, <HI>The A∣postle of the Apostles.</HI> He declared his <HI>Faith,</HI> when it could afford no <HI>Temporal Advantage</HI> at all unto him; He did it, when it would rather augment the <HI>Shame</HI> and <HI>Scorn,</HI> which was now heaping upon him; He did it, when as <HI>Austin</HI> sayes, <HI>His Confessing of a Crucified Christ, was in a Man∣ner,</HI> (quantum si fuisset pro Domino Cruci∣fixus,) <HI>as much as if he had been himself Cruci∣fied for Him, whom he Confessed.</HI></P>
<P>Finally; The <HI>Labour</HI> he uses to convince his Companion of his Impiety, and Reclame him from it, and Quicken the <HI>Fear of God</HI> in him; it looks as if he <HI>came thither armed</HI> with a Zea∣lous and Intense Desire to Propagate a Sense of God in the Hearts of others. A Repentance has usually made a little <HI>Progress,</HI> before it Comes into this Operation. One does not <HI>Per Saltum,</HI> come to this <HI>Degree.</HI> Methinks, All these Things conspire, to Proclaim a <HI>Saving work of Repentance begun</HI> in this Penitent, before his <HI>Last Hour</HI> came upon him. However, <HI>This</HI> I am sure they do; and <HI>this</HI> is what I mainly aim at: they utterly
<PB N="33" REF="001551_0034_0FB3A3044DD1DB68"/>
destroy all the <HI>Assurance,</HI> which any Presuming Sinner has, that this Man did <HI>not Repent</HI> until his <HI>Last Hour</HI> was arrived unto him. They leave him therefore without any <HI>Assurance,</HI> that <HI>ever any One</HI> in the World, who disobey'd calls to Repent until the <HI>Last Hour,</HI> did it <HI>then</HI> Effectu∣ally, and found Mercy with God.</P>
<P>I do not affirm that my Arguments, for the more <HI>Early Repentance</HI> of my Penitent, are ab∣solutely <HI>Decisive,</HI> and infallibly <HI>Conclusive;</HI> but yet, I think them enough to retund the <HI>Confi∣dent Prof<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/></HI> of them, who encourage the <HI>Delay</HI> of their Conversion to God, from the <HI>Pattern</HI> of the <HI>Thief,</HI> Repenting and Accepted on the Cross. And it may be further observed unto them, that the Holy and Worthy Divines, who take up with the common Opinion, and Glo∣rify God, in the Highest Apprehensions of <HI>Mi∣racle</HI> in the Sudden <HI>Producing</HI> and <HI>Ripening</HI> of this Repentance, do still with mighty Energy Thunderstrike, that Profane <HI>Abuse</HI> of the Exam∣ple. They tell you, Ye <HI>Fools,</HI> That if it be a <HI>Pattern,</HI> yet it is a <HI>Pattern</HI> without a <HI>Promise.</HI> And as One of the Ancients Expresses it, <HI>Ad Consequendam Fidem non fuit illi Extrema Hora, s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d Prima;</HI> they tell you, That it might more properly be said, He came in at the <HI>First Hour,</HI> than at the <HI>Last Hour;</HI> for he had not Enjoy'd the <HI>Means of Grace</HI> before, nor Sinn'd against them, as <HI>they</HI> do, who embolden themselves to Sin, from what was done for <HI>him.</HI> They tell you, The most you can make, if the Example be granted you, is, <HI>One Example</HI> in all the Bible.
<PB N="34" REF="001551_0035_0FB3A305B90240E8"/>
But then Mr. <HI>Greenham</HI> smartly upbraids the Rashness of them who hope for the like: You may as well Spur an A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s to make him Speak, because <HI>Balaam's</HI> once did Speak with the Voice of Man. They also tell you, That the Con∣version of this Penitent was at a <HI>Season,</HI> the like to which will never again occur in the World; It was an <HI>Extraordinary Time.</HI> As Mr. <HI>Fenner</HI> notes, The Day of a <HI>Kings Coronation,</HI> sets Ma∣lefactors at <HI>Liberty,</HI> which at another Time could not escape the <HI>Death</HI> which belongs unto them. The most astonishing <HI>Expression</HI> of the <HI>Divine Mercy,</HI> that ever was given to the World, was now Exhibiting. It is Congruous enough, that there should now in One Penitent be a most astonishing <HI>Monument</HI> of it. Our Penitent stood close by the <HI>Great Sacrifice.</HI> If there should be an <HI>Uncommon Experiment</HI> of the Vertue in the <HI>Balsom,</HI> just as it was Preparing, it is not with∣out some Congruity. Our Great Redeemer was now <HI>Triumphing openly over the Powers of Darkness.</HI> If in the <HI>Field of Battel,</HI> he actually rescued a <HI>Prey</HI> from the Mouth of the Adversary; the Con∣gruity was yet more beautiful. Mr. <HI>Beverly</HI> speaks well upon it. No Sinner in the World, will ever see such a Time again! Briefly, It was a Time fill'd with <HI>Miracles.</HI> One utters his Mind after this awful manner, on this occasion; <HI>You may as well Expect Christ to be Crucified again, as Expect such another Instance of such unusual Mercy</HI> I would not say, <HI>quite so.</HI> But certainly, to put off <HI>Repentance</HI> upon an Expectation of being received at <HI>the Last Hour,</HI> because One once in such rare circumstances was so; 'tis to <HI>do Presumptuously, and to reproach the Lord</HI></P>
<P><PB N="35" REF="001551_0036_0FB3A30754FBE708"/>
In fine; I should be as much offended, as the Martyr <HI>Bilney,</HI> to hear any one discouraging an <HI>Old Penitent,</HI> from Hopes of Pardoning Mercy. But it is as great an offence, to hear the folly and madness, and Egregious Nonsense of a Sinner <HI>Delaying</HI> to become a <HI>Penitent,</HI> because there was a <HI>Thief,</HI> that at <HI>the Last Hour</HI> found a Pardon. I break off with Saying. That if this <HI>Penitent</HI> might from the <HI>Paradise</HI> where our Saviour has Lodg'd him, now Preach unto us, we should certainly hear him saying, <HI>I desire, that among them who delay their Conversion to God, my Exam∣ple may no more be for their Ungodly Purpose in∣sisted on!</HI>—</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<PB REF="001551_0037_0FB3A309675411C8"/>
<HEAD>This Vacant Page will be well-filled, with an Hymn of my excellent Friend Mr. WATTS, Entituled, A Complaint of Ingratitude.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>IS this the Kind Return,</L>
<L>And these the Thanks we owe?</L>
<L>Thus to abuse Eternal Love</L>
<L>Whence all our Blessings flow?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>To what a Stubborn Frame</L>
<L>Has Sin reduc'd our Mind?</L>
<L>What Strange rebellious Wretches we,</L>
<L>And God as Strangely Kind?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>On us He bids the Sun</L>
<L>Shed His Reviving Rays,</L>
<L>For us the Skies their Circles run</L>
<L>To Lengthen out our Dayes.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The Brutes obey their God,</L>
<L>And bow their Necks to Men:</L>
<L>But we, more base. more bruitish things,</L>
<L>Reject His easy Reign.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Turn, Turn us, Mighty God,</L>
<L>And Mould our Souls afresh,</L>
<L>Break, Sovereign Grace, these Hearts of Stone,</L>
<L>And give us Hearts of Flesh.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Let Old Ingratitude</L>
<L>Provoke our Weeping Eyes,</L>
<L>And Hourly as new Mercies fall</L>
<L>Let Hourly Thanks arise.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>THE END.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's advertisement">
<PB REF="001551_0038_0FB3A30A328C8570"/>
<HEAD>Advertisement.</HEAD>
<P>THere is now in the Press, and will Speedily be Publish'd, a Book Intituled, <HI>Practical Religion Exemplified, in the</HI> LIVES <HI>of Mrs.</HI> Mary Terry, <HI>who dyed</HI> December 8<HI>th.</HI> 1708. <HI>in the Eighteenth Year of her Age. And Mrs.</HI> Clissould, <HI>who departed this Life the</HI> 12<HI>th. of</HI> December, 1711. <HI>in the Twenty-ninth Year of her Age.</HI></P>
<P>By <HI>Thomas Reynolds:</HI> Recommended by <HI>Increase Mather,</HI> D. D.</P>
<P>Reprinted at <HI>Boston</HI> in <HI>New-England</HI> Sold by <HI>Samuel Gerrish</HI> at his Shop <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="aeld" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Marlborough Street, over against the South Meeting House. 1713.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

