<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2005-09-15</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for signatures. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Converted 196-groups to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N00682">
<STC T="E">827</STC>
<STC T="W">m1085</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99030016</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="000827_0000_0FAB4027C9C90528"/>
<PB REF="000827_0001_0FAB402867B3B628"/>
<P>The BOSTONIAN EBENEZER.</P>
<P>SOME Historical Remarks, On the State of Boston, The <HI>Chief Town</HI> of <HI>New-England,</HI> and of the <HI>English</HI> AMERICA.</P>
<P>With Some, Agreeable Methods, FOR Preserving and Promoting, the <HI>Good State</HI> of THAT, as well as any <HI>other Town,</HI> in the like Circumstances.</P>
<P>Humbly Offer'd, By a <HI>Native</HI> of <HI>Boston.</HI></P>
<Q><BIBL><HI>Ezek 48 35.</HI></BIBL>
<P>The Name of the City from that Day shall be, <HI>THE LORD IS THERE.</HI></P></Q>
<P><HI>Boston,</HI> Printed by <HI>B Green</HI> &amp; <HI>J. Allen,</HI> for <HI>Samuel Phillips,</HI> at the Brick Shop 1698</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="quotation">
<PB REF="000827_0002_0FAB402928124148" MS="y"/>
<P>Ʋrbs Metropolis, ut sit maximae Auctoritatis, consti∣tuatur praecipuum pietatis Exemplum et Sacrarium.</P>
<BIBL><HI>Aphor. Polit.</HI></BIBL>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="introduction">
<PB N="3" REF="000827_0002_0FAB402928124148"/>
<HEAD>The HISTORY of BOSTON, Related and Improved.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">At <HI>Boston</HI> Lecture 7. <HI>d. 2. m.</HI> 1698.</HEAD>
<P>REmarkable and Memorable, was the Time, when an <HI>Army</HI> of Terrible <HI>Destroyers</HI> was coming against one of the <HI>Chief Towns,</HI> in the Land of <HI>Israel.</HI> God Rescued the <HI>Town</HI> from the Irresistible Fury and Ap∣proach of those <HI>Destroyers,</HI> by an Immedi∣ate Hand of Heaven upon them. Upon that Miraculous Rescue of the <HI>Town,</HI> and of the whole Country whose Fate was much enwrapped in it, there follow'd, that Action of the Prophet SAMUEL, which is this Day, to be, with some Imi∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tion Repeated, in the midst of thee, O BOSTON, <HI>Thou Helped of the Lord.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="lecture">
<PB N="4" REF="000827_0003_0FAB4029E7C86708"/>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><BIBL><HI>1 SAM. VII. 12.</HI></BIBL>
<P>Then SAMUEL took a Stone, and set it up, — and called the Name of it, <HI>Ebenezer,</HI> saying, Hitherto the Lord hath Helped us.</P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>THE Thankful Servants of God, have used sometimes, to Erect Monuments of <HI>Stone,</HI> as dureable Tokens of their <HI>Thankfulness</HI> to God, for <HI>Mercies</HI> Received in the places thus distinguished. <HI>Jacob</HI> did so; <HI>Joshua</HI> did so; and <HI>Samuel</HI> did so; but they so did it, as to keep clear of the Trans∣gression forbidden, in Lev. 26 1. <HI>Ye shall not set up an Image of Stone in your Land, for to Bow down unto it.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Stone</HI> Erected by <HI>Samuel,</HI> with the Name of <HI>Ebenezer,</HI> which is as much as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> say, <HI>A Stone of Help</HI>; I know not whet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> any Thing might be <HI>Writt</HI> upon it: but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB N="5" REF="000827_0003_0FAB4029E7C86708"/>
am sure, there is one thing to be now <HI>Read</HI> upon it, by our selves, in the Text where we find it: Namely, thus much,</P>
<P><HI>That a People whom the God of Heaven hath Remarkably Helped, in their Distresses, ought Greatly and Gratefully to acknowledge, what <HI>Help</HI> of Heaven they have Received.</HI></P>
<P>Now, 'tis not my Design to lay the Scene of my Discourse, as far off as <HI>Bethear,</HI> the place where <HI>Samuel</HI> set up his <HI>Ebenezer</HI>▪ I am immediately to Transfer it into the Heart of <HI>Boston,</HI> a place where the <HI>Remar∣kable Help Received from Heaven,</HI> by the People, does loudly call for an <HI>Ebenezer.</HI> And I do not ask you, to change the Name of the Town, into that of <HI>Help-Stone,</HI> as there is a Town in <HI>England</HI> of that Name, which may seem the English, of <HI>Ebenezer</HI>; But my <HI>Sermon</HI> shall be this Day, your <HI>Ebenezer,</HI> if you will with a Favourable, and a Profitable Attention Entertain it. May the Lord Jesus Christ, Accept me, and Assist me now, to <HI>Glorify Him,</HI> in the <HI>Town,</HI> where I drew my First Sinful Breath; A <HI>Town,</HI> whereto I am un∣der Great Obligations, for the Precious Opportunities to <HI>Glorify Him,</HI> which I have
<PB N="6" REF="000827_0004_0FAB402AA7C69A18"/>
quietly and publickly enjoy'd therein, for Near Eighteen years together. <HI>O my Lord God, Remember me, I pray thee, and Streng∣then me this once, to speak from thee, unto thy People!</HI></P>
<P>And now, Sirs, That I may set up an EBENEZER among you, there are these Things to be Inculcated.</P>
<P N="1"><HI>I.</HI> Let us Thankfully, and <HI>Agreeably,</HI> and <HI>Particularly,</HI> Acknowledge <HI>What <HI>Help</HI></HI> we have Received from the God of Heaven, in the years that have Rolled over us. While the Blessed Apostle <HI>Paul,</HI> was, as it should seem, yet short of being <HI>Threescore</HI> years old, how affectionately did he set up an <HI>Ebenezer,</HI> with an Acknowledgment, in Act. 26.22. <HI>Having obtained Help of God, I continue to This Day</HI>! Our Town is now <HI>Threescore and Eight</HI> years old; and certainly 'tis Time for us, with all possible affection, to set up our <HI>Ebenezer,</HI> saying, <HI>Having obtained Help from God, the Town it continued, until almost the Age of man is passed over it</HI>! The Town hath indeed <HI>Three Elder Sisters</HI> in this Colony; but it hath Wonderfully <HI>Outgrown</HI> them all; and
<PB N="7" REF="000827_0004_0FAB402AA7C69A18"/>
her Mother, old <HI>Boston,</HI> in <HI>England</HI> also; Yea, within a Few years, after the first-Settlement, it <HI>grew</HI> to be, <HI>The Metro∣polis of the whole English America.</HI> Little was <HI>This</HI> Expected, by them that First-Settled the Town, when, for a while, <HI>Boston,</HI> was proverbially called, <HI>Lost Town,</HI> for the mean and sad Circumstan∣ces of it. But, O <HI>Boston,</HI> it is because thou hast <HI>Obtained Help from God</HI>; even from the Lord Jesus Christ, who, for the sake of His <HI>Gospel,</HI> Preached and once prized here, undertook thy Patronage. When the World and the Church of God, had seen <HI>Twenty six</HI> Generations, a Psalm was Composed, wherein that Note occurs with <HI>Twenty six</HI> Repetitions; <HI>His Mercy endu∣reth for ever.</HI> Truly, there ha's not one year passed over this Town, <HI>Ab Urbe Con∣dita,</HI> upon the Story whereof, we might not make that Note, our <HI>Ebenezer; His Mercy endureth for ever.</HI> It ha's been a Town of Great Experiences. There have been several years, wherein the <HI>Terrible <HI>Famine</HI>,</HI> hath Terribly Stared the Town in the Face: We have been brought some∣times unto the <HI>Last Meal</HI> in the Barrel;
<PB N="8" REF="000827_0005_0FAB402B67C219C0"/>
We have cryed out, with the Disciples, <HI>We have not Loaves enough to feed a Tenth part of us!</HI> But the fear'd <HI>Famine</HI> ha's alwayes been kept off; alwayes, we have had Seasonable and Sufficient Supplyes, after a Surprising manner sent in unto us: Let the <HI>Three last years</HI> in this thing most Eminently Proclame the Goodness of our Heavenly <HI>Shepherd</HI> and <HI>Feeder.</HI> This ha's been the <HI>Help</HI> of our God; <HI>Because His Mercy endureth for ever!</HI> The <HI>Angels of <HI>Death</HI>,</HI> have often Shot the <HI>Arrows of <HI>Death</HI>,</HI> into the midst of the Town; The <HI>Small Pox,</HI> ha's especially <HI>Four Times,</HI> been a <HI>Great Plague</HI> upon us: How often have there been Bills desiring Prayers, for more than an Hundred Sick, on one Day in one of our Assemblies? In <HI>One Twelve-Month,</HI> about one <HI>Thousand</HI> of our Neigh∣bours, have one way or other been carried unto their long Home: And, yet we are after all, many more than <HI>Seven Thousand</HI> Souls of us, at this Hour, Living on the Spot. Why is not, a, <HI>Lord, have Mercy upon us,</HI> written on the Doors of our Abandon'd Habitations? This hath been the <HI>Help</HI> of our <HI>God</HI>; Because <HI>His Mercy endureth for ever.</HI>
<PB N="9" REF="000827_0005_0FAB402B67C219C0"/>
Never was any Town under the Cope of Heaven, more liable to be laid in <HI>Ashes,</HI> either through the <HI>Carelesness,</HI> or through the <HI>Wickedness,</HI> of them that <HI>Sleep</HI> in it. That such a <HI>Combustible Heap,</HI> of Contigu∣ous Houses, yet Stands, it may be called, A <HI>Standing Miracle</HI>; It is not, because <HI>the Watch-man keeps the City:</HI> Perhaps there may be too much cause of <HI>Reflection</HI> in that thing, and of <HI>Inspection</HI> too; No, <HI>It is from thy Watchful Protection, O Thou keep∣er of</HI> Boston, <HI>who neither Slumbers nor Sleeps. <HI>Ten Times</HI></HI> ha's the <HI>Fire</HI> made Notable <HI>Ruines</HI> among us, and our <HI>Good Servant</HI> been almost our <HI>Master</HI>: But the <HI>Ruines</HI> have mostly and quickly been Rebuilt. I suppose, That many more than a <HI>Thou∣sand Houses</HI> are to be seen, on this little piece of Ground, all fill'd with the un∣deserved Favours of God. Whence this preservation? This hath been the <HI>Help</HI> of our <HI>God</HI>; Because <HI>His Mercy endureth for ever</HI>! But if ever this Town saw a <HI>Year of Salvations,</HI> transcendently such was the <HI>Last Year</HI> unto us. A Formidable <HI>French Squadron,</HI> hath not Shot one Bomb, into the midst of thee, O thou <HI>Munition of Rocks</HI>;
<PB N="10" REF="000827_0006_0FAB402C2A4C52C8"/>
Our Streets have not Run with Blood, &amp; Gore, and horribly Devou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing Flames, have not Rag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d upon our Substance: Those are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, then hast thou been
<PB N="11" REF="000827_0006_0FAB402C2A4C52C8"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>City of Destruction:</HI> Or, I will rather say, <HI>A City of Salvation</HI>: And this, by the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elp</HI> of God; Because <HI>His Mercy Endureth for ever.</HI> Shall I go on? I will. We have not had the <HI>Bread of Adversity</HI> and the <HI>Water of Affliction,</HI> Like many other places. But yet, all this while, <HI>Our Eyes have seen our Teachers.</HI> Here are several <HI>Golden Candlesticks</HI> in the Town. <HI>Shining and Burning Lights,</HI> have Illuminated them. There are gone to Shine in an <HI>Higher Orb,</HI> Seven Divines that were once the <HI>Stars</HI> of this Town, in the Pastoral Charge of it; besides many others▪ that for some years gave us transient Influences <HI>Church∣es</HI> flourishing with much Love, and Peace and many <HI>Comforts of the Holy Spirit,</HI> have hitherto been our greatest <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. I wish, That some <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad <HI>Eclipse</HI> do not come e're long upon this <HI>Glory</HI>▪ The Dispensations of the <HI>Gospel</HI> were never Enjoy'd by any Town, with more <HI>Liberty</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, for so long a while together. Our <HI>Opportuni∣ties</HI> to Draw near unto the L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d Jesus Christ, in His <HI>Ordinances,</HI> cannot be pa∣rallel'd. <HI>Boston,</HI> Thou hast been <HI>Lifted up to Heaven</HI>; There is not a Town up∣on
<PB N="12" REF="000827_0007_0FAB402CE7C7E238"/>
<HI>Earth,</HI> which on some Accounts has more to answer for. Such, O Such, has been our <HI>Help</HI> from our God, Because <HI>His Mercy Endureth for ever.</HI></P>
<P N="2"><HI>II.</HI> Let us Acknowledge, <HI>Whose <HI>Help</HI></HI> it is, that we have Received, &amp; not <HI>Give the Glory of our God unto another.</HI> Poorly <HI>Helped</HI> had we been, I may tell you, if we had none but <HI>Humane Help,</HI> all this while to depend upon. The Favours of our Superiors we Deny not; we Forget not the Instruments of our <HI>Help.</HI> Ne∣vertheless, this Little <HI>Outcast Zion,</HI> shall with my consent, Engrave the Name of no MAN, upon her <HI>Ebenezer</HI>! It was well confess'd in Psal. 108.12. <HI>Vain is the Help of man!</HI> It was well counsell'd in Psal. 146.3. <HI>Put not your trust in Princes, nor in the Son of man, in whom there is no Help.</HI></P>
<P>Wherefore,</P>
<P>First, Let <HI>God</HI> in our Lord <HI>Iesus Christ,</HI> have the <HI>Glory,</HI> of <HI>Bestowing</HI> on us, all the <HI>Help,</HI> that we have had. When the Spirit of God came upon a Servant of His, he cried out unto <HI>David,</HI> in 1 Chron. 12.18. <HI>Thy God Helpeth thee.</HI> This,
<PB N="13" REF="000827_0007_0FAB402CE7C7E238"/>
This is the voice of God, from Heaven to <HI>Boston</HI> this Day, <HI>Thy God hath Helped thee: Thou hast by thy Sin destroyed thy self, but in thy God hath been thy Help.</HI> A Great man, once Building an Edifice, caused an Inscription of this Importance, to be written on the Gates of it, <HI>Such a place planted me, Such a place watered me, and</HI> Caesar <HI>gave the Increase</HI> One that pass'd by, with a witty Sarcasm, wrote under it, <HI>His Deus nihil f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cit.</HI> i. e. <HI>God, it seems, did nothing for this man.</HI> But the Inscrip∣tion upon our <HI>Ebenezer,</HI> owning what <HI>Help,</HI> this Town hath had, shall say, <HI>Our God hath done all that is done!</HI> Say then, O <HI>Helped <HI>Boston</HI>,</HI> say as in Psal. 121.2. <HI>My Help is from the Lord, which made Heaven and Earth.</HI> Say, as in Psal. 94.17. <HI>Unless the Lord had been my Help, my Soul had quickly dwelt in silence.</HI> And, Boldly say, <HI>'Tis only because the Lord has been my Helper, that Earth and Hell, have never d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that they would unto me.</HI></P>
<P>Let our Lord JESUS CHRIST, be prais'd as our Blessed <HI>Helper</HI>: That <HI>Stone</HI> which the <HI>Foolish Builders</HI> have <HI>refused,</HI> Oh! Set up that <HI>Stone</HI>; even, that <HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gh
<PB N="14" REF="000827_0008_0FAB402DA8B68028"/>
Rock,</HI> Set Him on High in our praises, and say, That, <HI>That is our Ebenezer.</HI> 'Tis our Lord JESUS CHRIST, who in His Infinite Compassions for the Town, hath said; as in Isa. 63.5. <HI>I Looked, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> there was none to Help; Therefore my own Arms hath brought Salvation</HI> unto it. It is fore∣told concerning the Idolatrous Roman Catholicks, That together with the Lord Jesus Christ, they shall <HI>Worship</HI> other <HI>Ma∣uzzim</HI>: that is to say, other <HI>Protectors.</HI> Ac∣cordingly, All their Towns, ordinarily have singled out their <HI>Protectors,</HI> among the <HI>Saints</HI> of Heaven; such a <HI>Saint</HI> is En∣tituled unto the <HI>Patronage</HI> of such a Town among them, and such a <HI>Saint</HI> for ano∣ther: Old <HI>Boston,</HI> by Name, was but Saint <HI>Botolphs Town.</HI> Whereas, Thou, O <HI>Boston,</HI> shalt have but one <HI>Pro∣tector</HI> in Heaven, and that is, our Lord JESUS CHRIST. Oh! Rejoice in Him alone, &amp; say, <HI>That Lord is my Fortress and my Deliverer!</HI> There was a Song once made for a <HI>Town,</HI> which in its Distresses had been <HI>Helped</HI> wondrously; &amp; the First Clause in that Song, [you have it in Isa. 26.1.] may be so rendred, <HI>We have a
<PB N="15" REF="000827_0008_0FAB402DA8B68028"/>
strong Town; Salvation</HI> [or JESUS, the Lord whose Name hath <HI>Salvation in it] Will appoint Walls and Bulwarks.</HI> Truly, What <HI>Helps</HI> we have had, we will Sing, <HI>'Tis our JESUS, that hath appointed them.</HI> The old Pagan Towns, were sometimes mightily solicitous, to conceal the Name of the particular God, that they counted their <HI>Protector, Ne ab hostibus E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>catus, alio commigraret.</HI> But, I shall be far from do∣ing my Town any Damage, by publish∣ing the Name of its <HI>Protector</HI>; No, Let all Mankind know, That the Name of our <HI>Protector,</HI> is JESUS CHRIST: For, <HI>Among the Gods, there <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> none like unto thee, O LORD▪ Nor <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> any Help like unto thine: And there is no Rock, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to our God.</HI></P>
<P>Yea, When we <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>scribe the Name of <HI>Helper,</HI> unto our Lord JESUS CHRIST, Let us also acknowledge, that the Name is not sufficiently Expressive, Emphatical, and Significant. <HI>Lactantius</HI> of old, bla∣med the Heathen, for giving the Highest of their Gods, no Higher a Ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le, than that of, <HI>Jupiter,</HI> or, <HI>Juvans Pater,</HI> i. e. An <HI>Helping Father,</HI> and he says, <HI>Non intelligit Divina Beneficia, qui se a Deo tantummodo
<PB N="16" REF="000827_0009_0FAB402E67B74068"/>
Juvari putat</HI>: The <HI>Kindnesses</HI> of God, are not understood, by that man, who makes no more than an <HI>Helper</HI> of Him. Such indeed is the penury of our Language, that we cannot coin a more <HI>Expressive Name.</HI> Nevertheless, when we say, The Lord JESUS CHRIST hath been our <HI>Helper,</HI> Let us Intend more than we Ex∣press; <HI>Lord, Thou hast been All unto us.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly; Let the <HI>Sacrifice</HI> of our Lord Jesus Christ, most Explici<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly, have the <HI>Glory</HI> of <HI>Purchasing</HI> for us all our <HI>Help.</HI> What was it, that procured, an <HI>Ebenezer,</HI> for the People of God? We read, in 2 Sam. 7.9. <HI>Samuel took a Sucking-Lamb, and offered it a Burnt Offering wholly unto the Lord; and Samuel Cryed unto the Lord for Israel, and the Lord Heard him.</HI> Shall I tell you? Our Lord Jesus Christ, is that <HI>Lamb of God</HI>; and he has been a <HI>Lamb Slain as a Sacrifice</HI>; and He is a <HI>Sacrifice</HI> pleadable, not only for <HI>persons,</HI> but also for <HI>peoples</HI>▪ that belong unto Him. To Teach us this Evangelical and Com∣fortable <HI>Mystery,</HI> there was, <HI>A Sacrifice for the whole Congregation,</HI> prescribed in the <HI>Mosaic</HI> Paedagogy. 'Tis notorious, that the <HI>Sins</HI> of this Town, have been many
<PB N="17" REF="000827_0009_0FAB402E67B74068"/>
Sins, and mighty Sins; The <HI>Cry</HI> thereof hath <HI>gone up to Heaven.</HI> If the Almighty God should from Heaven Rain down upon the Town▪ an <HI>horrible Tempest</HI> of Thunderbolts, as He did upon the Cities <HI>which He overthrew in His Anger, and re∣pented not,</HI> it would be no more than our Unrepen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed Sins deserve. How comes it then to pass, that we have had so much <HI>Help</HI> from Heaven after all? Truly, The <HI>Sacrifice</HI> of our Lord Jesus Christ, has been plea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed for <HI>Boston,</HI> and, <HI>Therefore,</HI> say, <HI>Therefore</HI> it is, that the Town is not made a <HI>Sacrifice</HI> to the Vengeance of God. God sent <HI>Help</HI> to the Town, that was the very <HI>Heart</HI> and <HI>Life</HI> of the Land, that He had a pitty for: But why so? He said, in Isa▪ 37.35. <HI>I will desend this Town, to Save it, for my Servant Davids sake.</HI> Has this Town been <HI>Defended?</HI> It has been for the sake of the <HI>Beloved</HI> JESUS; Therefore has the Daughter of <HI>Boston</HI> sha∣ken <HI>her Head</HI> at you, O ye Calamities, that have been Impending over <HI>her Head.</HI> O <HI>Helped,</HI> and Happy Town! Thou hast had those Believers in the midst of thee, that have pleaded this with the Great
<PB REF="000827_0010_0FAB418A6CA590C0"/>
God; <HI>Ah! Lord, Thou hast been more Ho∣noured by the Sufferings of our Lord Jesus Christ than thou couldest be Honoured by o∣verwhelming this Town with all the plagues of thy Just Indignation. If thou wilt Spare, and Feed, and Keep, and Help this poor Town, the Sufferings of our Lord Jesus Christ, shall be own'd, as the price of all our Help.</HI> 'Tis <HI>This,</HI> that hath procured us all our <HI>Help</HI>: 'Tis <HI>This</HI> that must have all our <HI>praise.</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly; Let the Lord be in a special manner <HI>Glorified,</HI> for the Ministry of His Good <HI>Angels,</HI> in that <HI>Help</HI> that has been ministred unto us. A <HI>Jacob</HI> lying <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n a <HI>Stone,</HI> saw the <HI>Angels</HI> of God <HI>Helping</HI> him. We are setting up an <HI>Ebenezer</HI>; but when we Lay our Heads and our Thoughts up∣on the <HI>Stone,</HI> Let us then see, <HI>The Angels of God have Helped us.</HI> When <HI>Macedonia,</HI> was to have some <HI>Help</HI> from God, an <HI>Angel,</HI> whom the Apostle, in Acts 16.9. Saw Habited like a <HI>man of Macedonia,</HI> was a mean of its being brought unto them. There is abundant cause to think, That every Town in which the Lord Jesus Christ is worshipped, hath an <HI>Angel</HI> to watch over it. The Primitive Christians,
<PB N="19" REF="000827_0010_0FAB418A6CA590C0"/>
were perswaded from the Scriptures of Truth, to make no Doubt of This, <HI>Quod per Civitates distributae sunt Angelorum prae∣fecturoe.</HI> When the Capital Town of <HI>Ju∣daea,</HI> was rescued from an Invasion, we read in 2 King. 19.35. <HI>The Angel of the Lord WENT OUT, and smote the Camp of the Assyrians.</HI> It should seem, There was an <HI>Angel,</HI> which did Reside in, and Prae∣side over the Town, who <HI>went out</HI> for that amazing Exploit. And is it not Likely, That <HI>the Angel of the Lord WENT OUT for to smite the Fleet of the Assyrians,</HI> with a Sickness, which the Last Summer hindred their Invading of this Town? <HI>The Angel of</HI> BOSTON, was concerned for it! Why have not the <HI>Destroyers</HI> broke in upon us, to prey upon us, with sore <HI>Destruction</HI>? 'Tis because we have had, <HI>A Wall of Fire</HI> about us; that is to say, A Guard of <HI>Angels,</HI> those <HI>Flames</HI> of <HI>Fire,</HI> have been as a <HI>Wall</HI> unto us. It was an <HI>Angel,</HI> that <HI>Help</HI>'d a <HI>Daniel,</HI> when the <HI>Li∣ons</HI> would else have swallowed him up. It was an <HI>Angel,</HI> that <HI>Help</HI>'d a <HI>Lot,</HI> out of the Fires that were coming to Consume his Habitation. It was an <HI>Angel,</HI> that
<PB N="20" REF="000827_0011_0FAB418B2B35EF78"/>
<HI>Help</HI>'d an <HI>Elias</HI> to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, when he wanted it. They were <HI>Ang<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat <HI>Help'd</HI> the whole <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of God, in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Wilderness, to their <HI>Daily Bread</HI>▪ Their <HI>Manna,</HI> was <HI>Angels Food</HI> And is it nothing, that such <HI>Angels</HI> have done for this Town, Think you? Oh! Think not so. Indeed, If we sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uld go to Thank the <HI>Angels</HI> for doing these things, They would zealously say, <HI>See <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> do it not!</HI> But if we Thank Their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and ours, for His Employing Them <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o Do these things, it will exceedingly <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> them. Wherefore, <HI>Bless <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, ye his Angels; And Bless <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI> Town, for these <HI>His Angels!</HI></P>
<P N="3"><HI>III.</HI> Let the <HI>Help</HI> which we have <HI>Hi∣therto</HI> had from our God, Enc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ge <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Hope</HI> in Him, for <HI>More Help</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, <HI>as the Matter may R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>quire.</HI> The <HI>He<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> God had given to His People, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Commemorated, as with <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Pil∣lars,</HI> conveying down the Remembrance of it, unto their Children. And what for? We are told, in Psal. 78.7. <HI>That they might se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> their Hope in God, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Forget the Works of God.</HI> I am not willing to say,
<PB N="21" REF="000827_0011_0FAB418B2B35EF78"/>
How much this Town may be Threaten∣ed, even with an <HI>U<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter Extirpation.</HI> But this I will say, The <HI>Motto</HI> upon all out <HI>Ebenezers</HI> is, <HI>Hope in God! Hope in God!</HI> The <HI>Use</HI> of the <HI>Former Help</HI> that we have had from God, should be an <HI>Hope</HI> for <HI>Future Help,</HI> from Him that is, <HI>A Pre∣sent Help in the Time of Trouble.</HI> As in the Three First Verse o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the <HI>Eighty Fifth</HI> Psalm, Six times over there occurs, <HI>Thou hast, Thou hast</HI>: all to usher in this; <HI>Therefore Thou WILT still do so</HI> O Let our <HI>Faith</HI> proceed in that way of Arguing, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 2 Cor. 1.10. <HI>The Lord hath Delivered, and H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> doth Deliver, and in Him we Trust, that He will still Deliver.</HI> We are to Day Wil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing, <HI>Hitherto the Lord hath Helped us</HI>; Let us write under it, <HI>And we ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, the Lord <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lp for us, in the Time of Need</HI>! It may be▪ some are purposi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g Su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>denly and Hastily to <HI>Leave</HI> the Town, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> their Fears of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that may come upon it. But I would not have you be too Sudden and Hasty in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>our purposes, as too many have been▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nto <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>-<HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rrow.</HI> There was a Time when P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ople were so Discouraged about a <HI>Subsistence</HI> in
<PB N="22" REF="000827_0012_0FAB418BEDD52780"/>
the principal Town of the Jews, that the talk'd of plucking up Stakes, and flying <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>way; but the Minister of God came to them, [And so do I to you, this Day! Saying, in Isa. 30 7. <HI>I Cried concerning<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> This, Their Strength is to Sit Sill! Bosto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> was no sooner come to some <HI>Consistenc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> Threescore years ago, but the People foun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> themselves plunged into a sad <HI>Non plu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> what way to take for a <HI>Subsistence.</HI> Go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> then immediately put them into a way<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and, <HI>Hitherto the Lord has Helped us</HI>! Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Town is at this Day full of <HI>Widows</HI> an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Orphans,</HI> and a multitude of them, are very <HI>Helpless</HI> Creatures. I am Astonish'd, Ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> they Live! In that Church, whereof <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> am the Servant, I have counted▪ The <HI>Widows</HI> make about a <HI>Sixth Part</HI> of ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Communicants, and, no doubt, in the whole Town, the proportion differs no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> very much. Now, stand still, my Friends and Behold, the <HI>Help</HI> of God! Were any of these ever <HI>Starved</HI> yet? No, These <HI>Widows</HI> are every one in some sort pro∣vided for. And let me tell you, Ye Hand-Maids of the Lord, You shall be <HI>Still</HI> pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>vided for! The Lord, whose <HI>Family</HI> you
<PB N="23" REF="000827_0012_0FAB418BEDD52780"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elong unto, will conveniently and won∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erfully provide for you; if you say, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>! Say! of Him, <HI>The Lord is my Helper, will not Fear</HI>!</P>
<P>What shall I say? When <HI>Moses</HI> was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ady to faint, in his <HI>Prayers</HI> for his Peo∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le, we read, in Exod. 17.12 <HI>They took a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>one and put it under him</HI> Christians, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>here are some of you, who abound in <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rayers,</HI> that the <HI>Help</HI> of God may be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>anted unto the Town; the Town is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uch upheld by those <HI>Prayers</HI> of yours. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow, that you may not faint in your <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rayers,</HI> I bring you a <HI>Stone</HI>: The <HI>Stone,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s our <HI>Ebenezer</HI>; or, the Relation of the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elp</HI> that <HI>hitherto</HI> the Lord hath given us.</P>
<P N="4"><HI>IV.</HI> Let all that bear <HI>Publick Office</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Town, Contribute all the <HI>Help</HI> they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, that may continue the <HI>Help</HI> of God <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>to us. <HI>Austin,</HI> in his <HI>Confessions,</HI> gives <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hanks to God, That when he was an <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elpless Infant,</HI> he had a <HI>Nurse</HI> to <HI>Help</HI> him, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> one that was both Able &amp; Willing to <HI>Help</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Infant-<HI>Boston,</HI> Thou hast those, whom <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Bible calls, <HI>Nursing-Fathers.</HI> Oh, Be not <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oward,</HI> as thou art, in thy Treating of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Nurses</HI>; but give Thanks to God for
<PB N="24" REF="000827_0013_0FAB4193C9DAEB30"/>
them. I Forget my self; 'Tis with the <HI>Fathers</HI> themselves, that I am concerned.</P>
<P>When it was demanded of <HI>Demosthenes,</HI> what it was, that so long Preserved <HI>Athens</HI> in a flourishing State, he made this answer, <HI>The Orators are men of Learning &amp; Wisdom; the Magistrates do Justice, the Citizens love Quiet, and the Laws are kept among them all.</HI> May <HI>Boston</HI> flourish in such happy Order!</P>
<P>And first, You may assure yourselves▪ That the <HI>Ministers</HI> of the Lord Jesus Christ among you will be <HI>Joyful</HI> to ap∣prove themselves, as the Book of God has called them, <HI>The Helpers of your Joy.</HI> O our dear <HI>Flocks</HI>; we owe you our <HI>All</HI>; All our <HI>Love,</HI> all our <HI>Strength,</HI> all our <HI>Time</HI>; We, <HI>Watch for you, as th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se that must give an Account</HI>: And I am very much mistaken▪ if we are not willing to <HI>Dy</HI> for you t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o, if called unto it. If our Lord Jesus Christ should say, to us, <HI>My Servant, if you'l Dy to Night, you shall have this Reward; The People that you Preach to, shall be all Converted unto me!</HI> I think, We should with Triumphing Souls Reply, <HI>Ah! Lord, Then I'l Dy with all my Heart.</HI> Syrs, we should go away <HI>Rejoycing with Joy unspeakable &amp;
<PB N="25" REF="000827_0013_0FAB4193C9DAEB30"/>
full of Glory.</HI> I am satisfied, That the most Furious and Foul mouth'd Reviler, that God may give any of us, to be <HI>Buf∣feted</HI> withal, if he will but come to so∣ber Thoughts, he will say, That there is not any <HI>One man</HI> in the Town, but the <HI>Ministers</HI> wish that man as well as they do their own Souls, and would gladly Serve that man by Day or by Night, in any thing that it were possible to do for him. Wherefore, O our Beloved People, I beseech you, Leave off, Leave off, to Throw <HI>Stones</HI> at your <HI>Ebenezers.</HI> Instead of <HI>That, Pray for us,</HI> and <HI>Strive together with us, in your Prayers to God for us.</HI> Then with the <HI>Help</HI> of Christ, we'l promise you; We will set our selves to observe what <HI>Special Truths</HI> may be most needful to be Inculcated upon you, and we will Inculcate them. We will set our selves to observe the <HI>Temptations</HI> that beset you, the <HI>Afflictions</HI> that assault you, and the <HI>Duties</HI> that are incumbent on you, and we will accommodate our selves unto them. We will set our selves to observe, what Souls among you, do call for our m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re <HI>particular Addresses,</HI> and we will Ad∣dress
<PB N="26" REF="000827_0014_0FAB41942D372648"/>
them faithfully, and even <HI>Travail i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Birth</HI> for them. Nor will we give over <HI>Praying,</HI> and <HI>Fasting,</HI> and <HI>Crying</HI> to our Great LORD for you, until we Dy. Whatever other <HI>Helpers</HI> the Town En∣joyes, they shall have that convenience, in Ezra. 5.2. <HI>With them were the Prophets of God, Helping them.</HI> Well then, Let the rest of our Worthy <HI>Helpers,</HI> Lend an <HI>Hel∣ping</HI> Hand, for the promoting of those things, wherein the Weal of the Town is wrapped up! When the <HI>Jews</HI> thought that a <HI>Defiling</HI> Thing was breaking in a∣mong them, in Acts 21.28. <HI>They cried out, Men of Israel, Help.</HI> Truly, there is cause to make that Cry, <HI>Men of Boston, Help</HI>! for Ignorance, and Prophaness, and Bad Living, and the worst things in the World, are breaking in upon us.</P>
<P>And now, Will the JUSTICES of the Town, set themselves to consider, <HI>How they may Help to Suppress all growing Vice<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> among us?</HI></P>
<P>Will the CONSTABLES of the Town, set themselves to consider, <HI>How they may Help to prevent all Evil Orders among us?</HI></P>
<P>There are some who have the Eye of
<PB N="27" REF="000827_0014_0FAB41942D372648"/>
the <HI>Town</HI> so much upon them, that the very Name of, TOWNS-MEN, is that by which they are distinguished. Syrs, Will <HI>You</HI> also consider, <HI>How to Help the Affairs of the Town, so as that all Things may go well among us?</HI></P>
<P>Moreover, may not SCHOOL-MAS∣TERS, do much to instil Principles of <HI>Religion,</HI> and <HI>Civility,</HI> as well as other points of good Education into the Chil∣dren of the <HI>Town?</HI> Only Let the <HI>Town</HI> well Encourage its Well Deserving <HI>School-Masters.</HI></P>
<P>There are some other <HI>Officers</HI>; But concerning <HI>All,</HI> there are these Two Things to be Desired. First, It is to be Desired, That such <HI>Officers</HI> as are <HI>Chosen</HI> among us, may be Chosen in the <HI>Fear of God.</HI> May none but <HI>Pious,</HI> and <HI>Prudent</HI> men, and such as <HI>Love</HI> the Town, be Chosen to Serve it. And, Secondly, It is to be Desired, That <HI>Officers</HI> of several sorts, would often come together, for <HI>Con∣sultation.</HI> Each of the sorts by themselves, may they often come together, to Con∣sult, <HI>What shall we do to Serve the Town, in those Interests which are committed unto
<PB REF="000827_0015_0FAB4194EE1A1020"/>
our Charge.</HI> Oh! What a Deplorable Thing, will it be, for persons to be En∣trusted with <HI>Talents,</HI> [your Opportunities to Serve the <HI>Town,</HI> are so many <HI>Talents!</HI>] and they never seriously consider, <HI>What Good shall I do, with my Talents, in the place where God hath Station'd me?</HI></P>
<P>And, Will the REPRESENTATIVES of the Town, be considered among the rest, as Entrusted with some singular Ad∣vantages for our <HI>Help</HI>! The <HI>Lord give you understanding in all Things.</HI></P>
<P N="5"><HI>V.</HI> God <HI>Help</HI> the Town, to manifest all that <HI>Piety,</HI> which a Town so <HI>Helped</HI> of Him, is oblig'd unto! When the People of God, had been carried, by His <HI>Help,</HI> through their Difficulties, they set up <HI>Stones,</HI> to keep in mind how He had <HI>Help∣ed</HI> them: And something was written on the <HI>Stones</HI>: But what was written! See; Josh. 8.32. <HI>Joshua wrote upon the Stones, a Copy of the Law.</HI> Truly, upon those <HI>Ebenezers,</HI> which we set up, we should write the <HI>Law</HI> of our God, and Recognize the Obligati∣ons which the <HI>Help</HI> of our God, ha's laid upon us to keep it.</P>
<P><PB N="29" REF="000827_0015_0FAB4194EE1A1020"/>We are a very Unpardonable Town, if after all the <HI>Help</HI> which our God ha's given us, we do not ingenuously Enqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>▪ <HI>What shall we Render to the Lord, for all His Be∣nefits?</HI> Render! Oh! Let us our selves thus answer the Enquiry; <HI>Lord, we will Render all possible, and Filia Obedience unto thee, because Hitherto thou hast Helped us: Only do thou also Help us, to Render that Obe∣dience!</HI> Mark what I say; If there be so much as one <HI>Prayerless House</HI> in such a <HI>Town</HI> as this, 'tis Inexcusable! How Inexcusable then, will be all <HI>Flagitious Outrages?</HI> There was a Town, [T'was the Town of <HI>Sodom!</HI>] that had been wonderfully Saved out of the Hands of their Enemies. But after the <HI>Help</HI> that God sent unto them, the Town went on to Sin against God, in very prodigious Instances. At last, a provoked God sent a <HI>Fire</HI> upon the Town, that made it an Eternal Desolation. Ah, <HI>Boston,</HI> Beware, Beware, lest the Sins of <HI>Sodom</HI> get Footing in thee! And what were the Sins of <HI>Sodom?</HI> We find in Ezek. 16.49. <HI>Be∣hold, This was the Iniquity of Sodom; Pride, Fulness of Bread, and Abundance of Idleness was in her; Neither did she Strengthen the
<PB N="30" REF="000827_0016_0FAB4195B1BEBDC0"/>
Hand of the Poor and the Needy</HI>; There was much Oppression there. If you know of any <HI>Scandalous Disorders</HI> in the Town, do all you can, to Suppress them, and Redress them: And let not those that send their Sons hither from other parts of the world, for to be improved in <HI>Virtue,</HI> have cause to Complain, <HI>That after they came to</HI> Boston, <HI>they lost, what little Vertue was before Bud∣ding in them: That in</HI> Boston <HI>they grew more Debauched &amp; more Malignant than ever they were before!</HI> It was noted concerning the famous Town of <HI>Port Royal</HI> in <HI>Jamaica,</HI> which you know, was t'other Day Swal∣low'd up, in a Stupendous <HI>Earthquake,</HI> that just before the <HI>Earthquake</HI> the People were Violently and Scandalously set upon going to <HI>Fortune Tellers</HI> upon all Occasions: much Notice was taken of this <HI>Impiety,</HI> generally prevailing among the People: but none of those Wretched <HI>Fortune-Tellers</HI> could Foresee, or Forestal the direful <HI>Catastrophe.</HI> I have heard, That there are <HI>Fortune-Tellers</HI> in this Town, sometimes consulted by some of the Sinful Inhabitants. I wish the Town could be made too Hot for these <HI>Dangerous Transgressors.</HI> I am sure, the
<PB N="31" REF="000827_0016_0FAB4195B1BEBDC0"/>
preservation of the Town, from horren∣dous <HI>Earthquakes,</HI> is one thing that bespeaks, our, <HI>Ebenezers</HI>; 'Tis from the Merciful <HI>Help</HI> of our God unto us. But, Beware, I beseech you, of those <HI>Provoking Evils</HI> that may Expose us to a Plague, Exceeding all that are in the Catalogue of the <HI>Twenty Eighth of Deuteronomy.</HI> Let me go on, to say; What? Shall there be any <HI>Bawdy-Houses</HI> in such a Town as This! It may be, the Neighbours, that could Smoke 'em, and Rout 'em, if they would, are loth to Stir, for fear of being reputed <HI>Ill Neighbours.</HI> But, I say unto you, That you are <HI>Ill Neigh∣bours,</HI> because you do it not: All the Neigh∣bours are like to have their Children and Servants poisoned, and their Dwellings laid in Ashes, because you do it not! And, Oh! that the <HI>Drinking-Houses</HI> in the Town, might once come under a laudable <HI>Regulation.</HI> The Town ha's an <HI>Enormous Number</HI> of them! Will the <HI>Haunters</HI> of those <HI>Houses,</HI> hear the Counsils of Heaven? For <HI>You</HI> that are the <HI>Town Dwellers,</HI> to be oft, or long in your <HI>Visits</HI> of the <HI>Ordi∣nary,</HI> 'twill certainly Expose you to Mis∣chiefs more than ordinary. I have seen
<PB N="32" REF="000827_0017_0FAB419670CDE580"/>
certain <HI>Taverns,</HI> where the Pictures of horrible <HI>Devourers</HI> were hang'd out for the <HI>Signs</HI>; and thought I, 'twere well, if such <HI>Signs</HI> were not sometimes too too <HI>Significant</HI>! Alas, men have their Estates <HI>Devoured,</HI> their Names <HI>Devoured,</HI> their Hours <HI>Devoured,</HI> and their very Souls <HI>De∣voured,</HI> when they are so besotted, that they are not in their Element, except they be Tipling at such Houses. When once a man is Bewitched, with the <HI>Ordinary,</HI> what usually becomes of him? He is a <HI>gone man</HI>; And when he comes to Dy, he'l cry out, as many have done, <HI>Ale ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ses are Hell-Houses! Ale-houses are Hell hou∣ses!</HI> But Let the <HI>Owners</HI> of those <HI>Houses,</HI> also now hear our Counsils. <HI>Oh! Hear∣ken to me, that God may Hearken to you a∣nother Day</HI>! It is an <HI>Honest,</HI> and a <HI>Lawful,</HI> tho' it be not a very <HI>Desireable,</HI> Employ∣ment, that you have undertaken: You may <HI>Glorifie</HI> the Lord Jesus Christ in your Employment, if you will, and Benefit the Town considerably. There was a very Godly man, that was an <HI>Inn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>keeper</HI>; and a Great Minister of God, could say to that man, in 3 Joh. 2. <HI>Thy Soul prospereth.</HI> O
<PB N="33" REF="000827_0017_0FAB419670CDE580"/>
Let it not be said of you, since you are fallen into this Employment, <HI>Thy Soul wi∣thereth!</HI> It is thus, with too many: Espe∣cially, when they that get a <HI>License</HI> per∣haps to Sell Drink out of Doors, do stretch their <HI>License</HI> to Sell within Doors. Those <HI>Private Houses,</HI> when once a Professor of the Gospel, comes to <HI>Steal</HI> a Living out of them, it commonly praecipitates them, into abundance of wretchedness and con∣fusion. But, I pray God, assist you that keep <HI>Ordinaries,</HI> to keep the <HI>Commandments</HI> of God, in them. There was an <HI>Inn</HI> at <HI>Bethlehem</HI>; where the Lord JESUS CHRIST was to be met withal. Can <HI>Boston</HI> boast of many such? Alas, Too or∣dinarily it may be said, <HI>There is no Room for Him in the Inn</HI>! My Friends, Let me beg it of you; Banish <HI>the unfruitful works of Darkness</HI> from your <HI>Houses,</HI> and then the <HI>Sun of Righteousness</HI> will shine upon them. Don't countenance <HI>Drunkenness, Revelling,</HI> &amp; <HI>Mispending</HI> of precious Time in your Houses: Let none have the <HI>Snares of Death</HI> Laid for them in your Houses. You'l say, <HI>I shall Starve then!</HI> I say, <HI>Bet∣ter Starve than Sin.</HI> But you, <HI>shall not.</HI>
<PB N="34" REF="000827_0018_0FAB41972B471230"/>
It is the Word of the Most High, <HI>Trust in the Lord, and do Good, and verily thou shalt be Fed.</HI> And is not <HI>Peace of Conscience,</HI> with a <HI>Little,</HI> better than those <HI>Riches</HI>▪ that will shortly melt away, and then run Like Scalding Metal down the very Bow∣els of thy Soul!</P>
<P>What shall I say more? There is one Article of <HI>Piety</HI> more to be Recommend∣ed unto us all; and it is an Article, which all <HI>Piety</HI> does exceedingly Turn upon▪ That is, <HI>The Sanctification of the Lords Day.</HI> Some very Judicious Persons, have obser∣ved, That as <HI>they Sanctified the Lords Day, Remisly or Carefully, just so, their Affayrs usually prospered all the Ensuing Week.</HI> Sirs, You cannot more consult the Prosperity of the Town, in all its Affayrs, than by Endeavouring that the <HI>Lords Day</HI> may be Exemplarily <HI>Sanctifyed.</HI> When People about <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> took too much Liberty on the <HI>Sabbath,</HI> the Ruler of the Town <HI>Con∣tended</HI> with them, and said, <HI>Ye bring wrath upon Israel by prophaning the Sabbath</HI>▪ I fear, I fear, There are many among us, to whom it may be said, <HI>Ye bring wrath upon</HI> Boston, <HI>by prophaning the Sabbath.</HI> And what
<PB N="35" REF="000827_0018_0FAB41972B471230"/>
<HI>Wrath? Ah Lord, prevent it!</HI> But there is an awful Sentence in Jer. 17.27. <HI>If ye will not Hearken unto me, to Sanctify the Sabbath-Day, then will I kindle a Fire</HI> on the Town, <HI>and it shall Devour, and shall not be Quenched.</HI></P>
<P>Finally, Let the <HI>Piety</HI> of the Town ma∣nifest it self, in a due Regard unto the <HI>Institutions</HI> of Him, whose <HI>Help</HI> ha's <HI>Hitherto</HI> been a <HI>Shield</HI> unto us. Let the <HI>Ark</HI> be in the Town, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd God will <HI>Blest</HI> the Town! I believe, it may be found, That in the <HI>Mortal Scourges</HI> of Heaven, which this Town ha's felt, there ha's been a <HI>Discernable Distinction,</HI> of those that have come up to Attend all the <HI>Ordinances</HI> of the Lord Jesus Christ, in the Communion of His <HI>Churches.</HI> Though these have had, as 'tis fit they should, a Share, in the <HI>Com∣mon Deaths,</HI> yet the <HI>Destroying Angel,</HI> ha's not had so great a proportion of these in his Commission, as he ha's had of others. Whether <HI>This</HI> be so, or no; To Uphold, and Support, and Attend the <HI>Ordinances</HI> of the Lord Jesus Christ in <HI>Reforming Churches,</HI> This will Entitle the Town to the <HI>Help</HI> of Heaven; for, <HI>Upon the Glory, there shall be a Defence</HI>! There were the Victorious
<PB N="36" REF="000827_0019_0FAB4197ED77B5A0"/>
Forces of <HI>Alexander,</HI> that in going back∣ward and foreward, pass'd by <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> without Hurting it. Why so? said the Lord, in Zech 9.8. <HI>I will Encamp about my House, because of the Army.</HI> If our God have an <HI>House</HI> here, He'l Encamp about it. <HI>Nazianzen,</HI> a famous Minister of the Gos∣pel, taking his Farewel of <HI>Constantinople,</HI> an old man, that had sat under his Ministry, cryed out, <HI>Oh! my Father, Don't you dare to go away, you'l carry the whole Trinity with you</HI>! How much more, may it be cryed out, <HI>If we Loose or Sleight, the Ordinances of the Lord Jesus Christ, we Foregoe the Help of all the Trinity with them!</HI></P>
<P N="6"><HI>VI.</HI> Extraordinary <HI>Equity</HI> &amp; <HI>Charity,</HI> as well as <HI>Piety</HI> well becomes a Town, that hath been by the <HI>Help</HI> of God so Extra∣ordinarily signalized. A Town marvel∣lously <HI>Helped</HI> by God, has This Foretold concerning it, in Isa. 1 26. <HI>Afterward thou shalt be called, The City of Righteousness, The Faithful City.</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Ebenezer</HI>▪ of this Town, render it, <HI>A Town of Equity,</HI> and, <HI>A Town of Charity!</HI> Oh! There should be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="35" REF="000827_0019_0FAB4197ED77B5A0"/>
with Heaven ha's Dealt so Favourably. Let us <HI>Deal Fairly</HI> in <HI>Bargains; Deal Fairly</HI> in <HI>Taxes; Deal Fairly</HI> in paying Re∣spects to such as have been <HI>Benefactors</HI> unto the Town. 'Tis but <HI>Equity,</HI> that they, who have been <HI>Old Standers</HI> in the Town, and both with <HI>Person</HI> and <HI>Estate</HI> Served the Town unto the utmost for many years together, should on all Proper Occasions be considered. For <HI>Charity,</HI> I may indeed speak it without Flattery, this Town has not many Equals on the Face of the Earth. Our Lord Jesus Christ from Heaven, wrote, unto the good people of a Town, in the Les∣ser <HI>Asia,</HI> [Rev. 2.19.] <HI>I know thy works, and Charity.</HI> From that Blessed Lord, I may venture to bring that Message unto the Good people of this Town; <HI>The Glo∣rious Lord of Heaven, knows thy works,</HI> O Boston, <HI>and all thy Charity.</HI> This is a <HI>poor</HI> Town; and yet it may be said of the <HI>Bostonians,</HI> as it was of the <HI>Macedonians, Their Deep poverty hath abounded unto the Riches of their Liberality.</HI> O ye Bountiful people of God, All your <HI>Daily Bounties</HI> to the Needy, All your <HI>Subscriptions</HI> to
<PB N="36" REF="000827_0020_0FAB4198AB7AAD20"/>
Send the <HI>Bread of Life</HI> abroad unto place<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that are perishing in Wickedness, All your <HI>Collections</HI> in your Assemblies as of∣ten as they are called for; <HI>All these Alms are come up for a Memorial before God</HI>! The Lord Jesus Christ in Heaven hath Beheld your <HI>Helpfulness,</HI> and <HI>Readiness to every good Work</HI>; and He hath Requited it, with His <HI>Helpful Ebenezers.</HI> It was said, in Isa. 32.8. <HI>The Liberal Deviseth Liberal Things, and by Liberal Things he shall stand.</HI> There are some in this Town, that are always <HI>Devi∣sing Liberal Things,</HI> and our Lord Jesus Christ, Lets the Town <HI>Stand</HI> for the sake of those! Instead of <HI>Exhorting</HI> you, to <HI>Augment</HI> your <HI>Charity,</HI> I will rather utter an <HI>Exhortation,</HI> or at Least, a <HI>Supplication,</HI> that you may not <HI>Abuse</HI> your <HI>Charity,</HI> by misapplying of it. I remember, I have Read, That an Inhabitant of the City <HI>Pisa,</HI> being asked, Why their Town so went, as it then did, unto Decay, he fetch∣ed a deep sigh, and said, <HI>Our young men are too prodigal, our old men are too Affecti∣onate, and we have no punishment for those that spend their years in Idleness.</HI> Ah, The last stroak of that complaint, I must here
<PB N="37" REF="000827_0020_0FAB4198AB7AAD20"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igh it over again. <HI>Idleness,</HI> alas, <HI>Idleness,</HI> increases in the Town exceedingly: <HI>Idle∣ness,</HI> of which there never came any <HI>Goodness; Idleness,</HI> which is a <HI>Reproach to any people. We</HI> work hard, all Summer, and the <HI>Drones</HI> count themselves wrong'd, if they have it not in the Winter divided among them. The <HI>Poor</HI> that can't <HI>Work,</HI> are Objects for your <HI>Liberality.</HI> But the <HI>Poor,</HI> that can <HI>Work</HI> and won't, the best <HI>Liberality</HI> to them, is to <HI>make</HI> them. I beseech you▪ Syrs, Find out a method quickly, That the <HI>Idle persons</HI> in the Town, may Earn their <HI>Broad</HI>; It were the best piece of <HI>Charity,</HI> that could be shown un∣to them, and <HI>Equity,</HI> unto us all. Our <HI>Beggars,</HI> do shamefully grow upon us, and such <HI>Beggars</HI> too, as our Lord Jesus Christ Himself hath Expresly forbidden us to countenance. I have Read a printed Sermon, which was Preached before <HI>Both Houses of Parliament,</HI> the <HI>Lord Mayor and Aldermen</HI> of <HI>London,</HI> and the <HI>Assembly of Divines</HI>; the Greatest Audience then in the World: And in that Sermon, the Preacher had this passage; <HI>I have Lived in a Countrey, where, in seven years, I never
<PB N="38" REF="000827_0021_0FAB41996C563070"/>
saw a Beggar, nor heard an Oath, nor look<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d upon a Drunkard.</HI> Shall I tell you where that <HI>Utopia</HI> was? 'Twas NEW-ENG∣LAND! But they that go from hence, must now tell another Story.</P>
<P N="7"><HI>VII.</HI> May the <HI>Changes,</HI> and especially the <HI>Judgments,</HI> that have come upon the Town, direct us, what <HI>Help</HI> to petiti∣on from the <HI>God of our Salvations.</HI> The <HI>Israelites</HI> had formerly seen <HI>dismal Things,</HI> where they now set up their <HI>Ebenezer:</HI> The <HI>Philistines</HI> had no less than Twice beaten them there, and there taken from them the <HI>Ark</HI> of God. Now we are setting up our <HI>Ebenezer,</HI> Let us a little call to mind some <HI>Dismal Things</HI> that we have seen; the <HI>Ebenezer</HI> will go up the better for it.</P>
<P>We read, in 1 Sam. 6.18. concerning, <HI>The Great Stone of Abel.</HI> Some say, That <HI>Adam</HI> Erected that <HI>Stone,</HI> as a <HI>Grave stone</HI> for his <HI>Abel,</HI> and wrote that Epi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aph upon it, <HI>Here was poured out the Blood of the Righ∣teous ABEL</HI> I know nothing of <HI>This,</HI> The Names, I know, differ in the Origi∣nal; But as we may Erect many a <HI>Stone</HI>
<PB N="39" REF="000827_0021_0FAB41996C563070"/>
for an <HI>Ebenezer,</HI> so, we may Erect many a <HI>Great Stone of ABEL,</HI> that is to say, We may write, MOURNING and SOR∣ROW, upon the Condition of the Town in various Examples. Now, from the <HI>Stones</HI> of <HI>Abel,</HI> we will a little gather what we should wish to write upon the <HI>Stones</HI> of our <HI>Ebenezer.</HI></P>
<P>What <HI>Changes</HI> have we seen, in point of <HI>Religion</HI>? It was Noted by <HI>Luther, He could never see Good order in the Church, last more than Fifteen years together in the Purity of it.</HI> Blessed be God, <HI>Religion</HI> hath here flourished in the <HI>Purity</HI> of it, for more than <HI>Fifteen years together.</HI> But, certainly, the <HI>Power of Godliness</HI> is now grievously decay'd among us. As the Prophet of old Excla∣med, in Joel 1.2. <HI>Hear this, ye old men, and give Ear, ye Inhabitants; Ha's this been in your Dayes:</HI> Thus may I say, <HI>Hear this, ye old men, that are the Inhabitants of the Town</HI>: Can't you Remember, that <HI>in your Dayes,</HI> a Prayerful, a Watchful, a Fruitful Christi∣an, and a well Governed Family, was a more common Sight, than it is now in <HI>our Dayes?</HI> Can't you Remember, that <HI>in your Dayes,</HI> those Abominable Things did not
<PB N="40" REF="000827_0022_0FAB419A2B360300"/>
<HI>Show their Heads,</HI> that are now <HI>Bare-faced</HI> among us? Here then is a Petition to be made unto our God; <HI>Lord, Help us to Re∣member whence we are Fallen, and to Repent, and to Do the First Works.</HI></P>
<P>Again; What <HI>Changes</HI> have we seen, in point of <HI>Mortality</HI>? By <HI>Mortality,</HI> al∣most all the <HI>Old Race</HI> of our <HI>First Planters</HI> here, are carryed off; the <HI>Old Stock,</HI> is in a manner Expired. We see the Fulfil∣ment of that word, in Eccl. 1 4. <HI>One Ge∣neration passeth away, and another Generation cometh.</HI> It would be no unprofitable Thing for you, to pass over the several Streets, &amp; call to mind, <HI>Who Lived here so many years ago?</HI> Why? In <HI>that place</HI> lived such an one; and in <HI>that place</HI> lived such an one. But, <HI>Where are they Now?</HI> Oh! They are <HI>Gone,</HI> They are <HI>Gone</HI> into that Eternal World, whither <HI>We</HI> must quickly follow them. Here is another Petition, to be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> unto our God; <HI>Lord, Help us to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> our Dayes, and apply our Hearts unto Wis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> that when the places that now know <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> us no more, we may be gone into the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of God.</HI></P>
<P>Furthermore; What <HI>Changes</HI> have we
<PB N="41" REF="000827_0022_0FAB419A2B360300"/>
seen, in point of <HI>Possessions?</HI> If some <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat are now <HI>Rich,</HI> were once <HI>Low</HI> in the World, 'tis possible, more that were once <HI>Rich,</HI> are now brought very <HI>Low.</HI> Ah! <HI>Boston,</HI> Thou hast seen the <HI>Vanity</HI> of all <HI>Worldly Possessions</HI>▪ One fatal Morning, which laid Fourscore of thy <HI>Dwelling Hou∣ses,</HI> and Seventy of thy <HI>Ware houses,</HI> in a Ruinous Heap, not Nineteen years ago, gave thee to Read it in Fiery Characters. And an huge <HI>Fleet</HI> of thy Vessels, which they would make, if they were all together, that have miscarried in the late War, ha's given thee to Read more of it. Here is one Petition more, to be made unto our God; <HI>Lord, Help us to Ensure a Better and a lasting Substance in Heaven, and the Good part that cannot be taken away.</HI></P>
<P>In fine; How dreadfully have the <HI>Young People</HI> of <HI>Boston,</HI> perished under the <HI>Judg∣ments</HI> of God! A Renowned Writer, a∣mong the <HI>Pagans,</HI> could make this Remark; There was a Town, so Irreligious and A∣theistical, that they did not pay their <HI>First-fruits</HI> unto God: (which the <HI>Light of Na∣ture</HI> taught the Pagans to do!) and sayes he, they were▪ by a Sudden Desolation so
<PB N="42" REF="000827_0023_0FAB419AECD10D90"/>
Strangly Destroy'd, that there were no Remainders either of the <HI>Persons,</HI> or of the <HI>Houses,</HI> to be seen any more. Ah, <HI>My Young Folks</HI>; There are few <HI>First-fruits</HI> paid unto the Lord Jesus Christ among you. From hence it comes to pass, that the Consuming Wrath of God, is every day upon you. <HI>New England</HI> ha's been like a <HI>Tott'ring House</HI>; the very <HI>Foundations</HI> of it have been Shaking: But the House thus over setting by the <HI>Whirlwinds</HI> of the Wrath of God, hath been like <HI>Jobs</HI> House; <HI>It falls upon the Young men, and they are Dead!</HI> The Disasters on our <HI>Young Folks</HI> have been so multiplied, that there are few Parents among us, but what will go with <HI>Wounded Hearts,</HI> down unto their Graves: Their dayly moans are, <HI>Ah, My Son cut off in his Youth! My Son, my Son</HI>! Behold then, the <HI>Help</HI> that we are to ask of our God; and why do we, with no more Dayes of <HI>Pray∣er</HI> with <HI>Fasting,</HI> ask it? <HI>Lord, Help the Young People of Boston, to Remember thee in the Dayes of their Youth, and Sanctify unto the Survivers, the Terrible Things that have come upon so many of that Generation.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="43" REF="000827_0023_0FAB419AECD10D90"/>And now as <HI>Joshua,</HI> having Reasoned with his people, a little before he Died, in Josh. 24.26, 27. <HI>Took a Great STONE▪ and set it up, and said unto all the people, Be∣hold, this Stone shall be a witness unto you, Lest ye Deny your God.</HI> Thus, we have been this Day setting up a STONE, even an <HI>E∣benezer,</HI> among you; &amp; I conclude, Ear∣nestly testifying unto you, <HI>Behold this Stone, shall be a witness unto you, that the Lord</HI> JE∣SUS CHRIST, <HI>has been a Good Lord unto you; and if you Seek Him, He will be still found of you, but if you Forsake Him, He will cast you off for ever.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="lecture">
<PB N="44" REF="000827_0024_0FAB419BAC28F650"/>
<HEAD>Houshold Religion, Recommended, for the Preservation of our HOUSES.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">At <HI>Boston</HI> Lecture. 26. <HI>d.</HI> 7. <HI>m.</HI> 1695.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><BIBL><HI>It is Written in</HI> JOB <HI>XXII.23.</HI></BIBL>
<P>If thou Return to the Almighty, thou shalt be Built up; Thou <HI>shalt put away Ini∣quity, far from thy Tabernacles.</HI></P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P>IT is Reported, as the Special and Signal Favour of God, unto His People, in Exod. 1.20, 21. <HI>The People multiplied, and He made Them</HI> [that is, <HI>the People,</HI> for the word is in the Masculine Gender,] <HI>Houses</HI>: Which Favour of God in the nearest and strictest sense wherein that expression is commonly used, is not only most <HI>Merciful∣ly</HI> Vouchsafed, but almost <HI>Miraculously</HI> con∣tinued,
<PB N="45" REF="000827_0024_0FAB419BAC28F650"/>
unto us who now Compose this Assembly. Our Gracious God ha's given us <HI>Houses,</HI> wherein we Enjoy the Comforts of Life, Covered and Sheltered from for∣reign injuries; Yea, and we have the <HI>Houses</HI> of our Gracious God also set open unto us, without the Liberties whereof, I hope, we should not find our s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ves able to <HI>Tast</HI> the Comforts of our own. Let it not be thought <HI>Unseasonable,</HI> I am sure, it should not be <HI>Unprofitable,</HI> for us to hear in the <HI>House</HI> of God at this Time, some Singular Things, wherein the Welfare of our own is more than a little concerned.</P>
<P>Concerning the <HI>Houses,</HI> with which our God ha's favoured us, there are Two Considerations, which doubtless, every man in this Assembly, of his own Accord, hath Entertained.</P>
<P>First, I suppose, We are all sensible, That for us to Loose our <HI>Houses</HI> by any Disaster whatsoever, would be a very terrible Calamity; Oh! It would be a <HI>Judgment</HI> of God, wherein the <HI>Anger</HI> of God, would be seen written with <HI>Fiery</HI> Characters. If by an Accident, or by an Enemy our <HI>Houses</HI> be Laid in Deso∣lations,
<PB N="46" REF="000827_0025_0FAB419C6B74D8F0"/>
every Roar of the Raging Flames, every Crack of the Tumbling Timbers, every Downfal of the Undermined Walk, and every Jangle of the <HI>Bells</HI> then tolling the Funeral of those Houses, would loud∣ly utter that voice, in Deut. 32.22. <HI>A Fire is Kindled in the Anger of God!</HI> It were a dismal Thing for our <HI>Houses</HI> be∣coming too <HI>Hot</HI> for us, to say, <HI>Be gone; ye sinful Inhabitants, Be gone; you shall never Eat, or Sleep, or Talk, or Pray, in us, any more</HI>; and for our Consorts &amp; Children with us, to be Stript in a few Hours, of all that we have been getting for many years, and be turn'd Shiftless and Help∣less <HI>out of Doors,</HI> to Lodge <HI>Next Door</HI> unto Beggary. A Town so Afflicted, may have this Lamentable Account given of them, in Isa. 42.25. <HI>The Lord hath poured on them the Fury of His Anger, and it hath let them on Fire round about.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, And there is as much cause for us to be sensible, That it is the meer <HI>Power</HI> and <HI>Patience</HI> of our Good God, which keeps us from such a Terrible Ca∣lamity, as the Loss of our <HI>Houses.</HI> How easy a thing were it, for the Vengeance of
<PB N="47" REF="000827_0025_0FAB419C6B74D8F0"/>
Heaven, to Lay all our <HI>Houses</HI> in Ruinou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Heaps before to morrow morning! Tru∣ly, We may say, <HI>'Tis because we have ob∣tained Help from God, that we continue to this Day.</HI> We may sit in our Combusti∣ble Houses, and make that Confession, in Psal. 127.1. <HI>The Lord keeps the Town; the Watchman waketh b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t in vain.</HI> When we think, how much Destruction may arise from one <HI>Spark,</HI> or one <HI>Snuff,</HI> and, as the Apostle speaks, <HI>How great a matter a Little Fire kindles</HI>! And when we think, how many <HI>Careless,</HI> how many <HI>Foolish,</HI> how many <HI>Drunken,</HI> yea, and how many hor∣ribly <HI>Malicious</HI> persons, persons wicked enough, <HI>To burn their Neighbours Houses, only that they may Roast their own Eggs,</HI> may creep in among us; Or when we think of him whom we may call OG, which is in Eng∣lish, <HI>The Burner,</HI> for the Delight that he has taken in <HI>Scorching men with Fire</HI>; We may with Admiration acknowledge, <HI>'Tis our God that is our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI> Oh! we must make that Acknowl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dgment before the Lord, in Psal. 121.4. <HI>Behold, He that keepeth Israel, doth neither Slumber nor S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eep</HI>; Else we should be wak'd out of
<PB N="48" REF="000827_0026_0FAB419D2D950588"/>
our next <HI>Sleep,</HI> with a Formidable <HI>Outcry.</HI></P>
<P>Sensible of these Things, we shall not count it Improper, to bestow a brief Discourse, upon the <HI>Methods,</HI> which we are, as <HI>Christians,</HI> to take for the Comfor∣table Preservation of our <HI>Houses</HI>; especi∣ally, now the Season of the year advan∣ces, wherein there are the most pungent Invitations, for such <HI>Methods</HI> to be consi∣dered.</P>
<P>Behold then the Great Method, for the secure Enjoyment of our <HI>Tabernacles,</HI> which the Oracles of God have directed us un∣to: It is, <HI>The putting away Iniquity far from our Tabernacles.</HI></P>
<P>That <HI>Perfect</HI> and <HI>Upright</HI> m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n, <HI>Job,</HI> had this among the Heavy Trials befal∣ling of him, That he Lost his <HI>House:</HI> Now under this Trial, one of his Friends gives him this Advice: That he would by <HI>Ac∣quaintance</HI> with God, and <HI>Repentance</HI> of Sin, Endeavour, to answer the Expectati∣ons of Heaven concerning him. To Encourage him hereunto, here is this Blessing promised, <HI>Thou shalt be Built up</HI>: q. d. Thou shalt then have thy <HI>House</HI> Re∣paired, without the fear of <HI>Loosing</HI> it any more.</P>
<P><PB N="49" REF="000827_0026_0FAB419D2D950588"/>The Clause which falls under our more particular Notice is that; <HI>Thou shalt put a∣way Iniquity, far from thy Tabernacles</HI>: which is here mentioned, as the Effect of <HI>Return∣ing to the Almighty.</HI> Now, by <HI>Iniquity,</HI> we may understand, either the <HI>Practice</HI> of <HI>Iniquity,</HI> or the <HI>Punishment</HI> of <HI>Iniquity.</HI> Take it for the <HI>Practice</HI> of <HI>Iniquity,</HI> and then the sense runs thus; <HI>Mani∣fest thy Returning to the Almighty, by thy not▪ Suffering of any <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>niquity in thy Tabernacles.</HI> Take it for the <HI>punishment</HI> of <HI>Iniquity,</HI> and then the sense runs thus; <HI>By Returning to the Almighty thou wilt Save thy Tabernacles, from such Ruines as will come upon them, If thou continue in Iniquity.</HI> Take it which way you will, there is this <HI>Doctrine</HI> in it. <HI>The Way for us to secure the Comfortable En∣joyment of our Tabernacles, is, by Returning unto the Almighty, to put Iniquity far from our Tabernacles.</HI></P>
<P>There are Three plain Assertions be∣fore us, by which I may come fairly at my Design, to promote <HI>Houshold-Reli∣gion,</HI> in the management of an Argu∣ment fetch'd from the Benefit thence ari∣sing, unto the very <HI>Houses,</HI> wherein we mentain that <HI>Religion.</HI></P>
<P N="1"><PB N="50" REF="000827_0027_0FAB419DEC116328"/><HI>I.</HI> In true <HI>Religion,</HI> men do <HI>Return unto the Almighty God.</HI> There was a Blessed <HI>Communion</HI> with God, which man had at his first <HI>Creation</HI> by God. But how Long did this continue? Alas, It was not Long, before Man turned his Back upon the <HI>Service</HI> and the <HI>Glory</HI> of His Maker: It was not Long before Man Embraced the <HI>Vain Things</HI> of this World, instead of the God that made him. Every Sinner is now Guilty of that F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lly, that Frenzy, that <HI>Horrible Thing,</HI> in Jer. 2.13. <HI>He hath forsaken the Fountain of Living Waters, and he hath hew<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d him <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut Broken Cisterus.</HI> Well, but now in <HI>Religion,</HI> there is a <HI>Conversion</HI> and a <HI>Returning</HI> of the Sinner; he saies, <HI>I will Return to my first Object, because it is best being with him.</HI> The Term <HI>From which</HI> a man does <HI>Return</HI> in <HI>Religion,</HI> is, <HI>All Sin</HI> whatsoever; and every <HI>Pleasure,</HI> every <HI>Profit,</HI> every <HI>Honour,</HI> which the Heart is by <HI>Sin</HI> carried forth unto. Thus 'tis said, in Jer. 18.11▪ <HI>Return ye now eve∣ry one from his Evil way.</HI> The Term <HI>To which</HI> a man does <HI>Return</HI> in <HI>Religion,</HI> is, God in the Lord Jesus Christ; so that
<PB N="51" REF="000827_0027_0FAB419DEC116328"/>
God becomes his <HI>Best <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> End,</HI> and the Lord Jesus Christ becomes his <HI>Prophet,</HI> his <HI>Priest,</HI> and his <HI>King</HI> for e∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er. Thus 'tis said, in Jer. 4.1. <HI>If thou wilt Return, Return unto me, saith the Lord.</HI></P>
<P N="2"><HI>II.</HI> Those men that <HI>Return to the Al∣mighty God, will put away Iniquity far from their Tabernacles.</HI> The <HI>House</HI> as well as the <HI>Heart</HI> of a man is cleansed by <HI>Religi∣on</HI>; it will Reform not only his <HI>Living,</HI> and his <HI>Walking,</HI> but his <HI>Dwelling</HI> also. The Godly man is one that <HI>puts away</HI> all Iniquity, yea, that <HI>puts it far away</HI>: he doe▪ in <HI>Repenting</HI> of Iniquity, as the God of Heaven does in <HI>pardoning</HI> of it. In the <HI>pardoning</HI> of Iniquity, 'tis said, in Psal. 103 12. <HI>As far as the East is from the West, so far does God Remove our Transgres∣sions from us</HI>; Thus, in the <HI>Repenting</HI> of I∣niquity, the man saith, <HI>I would have all my Transgressions to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e as far from me, as the East is from the West: The East and West will never meet, nor would I ever shake hands with any Iniquity.</HI> Even, the very <HI>Shadow</HI> of Iniquity is banished from a Regenerate man; the very <HI>Appearance of
<PB N="52" REF="000827_0028_0FAB419EAD3FDCC0"/>
Evil,</HI> is the matter of his <HI>Abstinence,</HI> his <HI>Abhorrence:</HI> he puts it <HI>far away</HI> from his <HI>Conversation, far away</HI> from his <HI>Approbati∣on, far away</HI> from his <HI>Inclination</HI>: But this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s not all; He puts it <HI>far away</HI> from his <HI>Habitation</HI> too. Every <HI>Good</HI> man is <HI>Com∣m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nitative</HI> of his Goo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; he would have all about him to be as <HI>Good,</HI> as Holy, as Happy as himself; and those of his own <HI>House</HI> most of all: He will not <HI>permit</HI> any <HI>Iniquity,</HI> that he can <HI>prevent.</HI> A Religious <HI>Christian</HI> would be a Religious <HI>Housholder</HI> too; he would be such an <HI>Housholder,</HI> as <HI>Jacob,</HI> who, in Gen. 35.2. <HI>Said unto his Houshold, and unto all that were with him, put away the Strange Gods that are among you</HI>; he would be such an <HI>Housholder,</HI> a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>David,</HI> who said, in Psal. 101.2, 7. <HI>I will walk in my House, with a perfect Heart; He that works Deceit, shall not dwell within my House; he that telleth Lies, shall not tarry in my sight.</HI> Or, as <HI>Joshua,</HI> who said, <HI>As for me and my House, we will Serve the Lord.</HI></P>
<P N="3"><HI>III.</HI> By <HI>Putting away Iniquity far from our Tabernacles,</HI> we do secure to our selves the <HI>Comfortable Enjoyment</HI> of them. Let
<PB N="53" REF="000827_0028_0FAB419EAD3FDCC0"/>
us drive <HI>our Sins</HI> out of our <HI>Houses,</HI> that we may not be driven out of them, <HI>our selves.</HI></P>
<P>It is very time; A pious man, may have his <HI>Tabernacle</HI> taken from him; the loss of <HI>Houses</HI> is one of those Things, wherein the <HI>Soveraignty</HI> of God, will have <HI>All things come alike to all.</HI> A Treble <HI>Concession</HI> is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be made concerning this matter.</P>
<P>First, A Godly man may Suffer the loss of his <HI>House,</HI> in a Common Calamity, with wicked men. If a Righteous <HI>Let</HI> live in a <HI>Sodom,</HI> his <HI>House</HI> must be Bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ed among the Rest in the Vicinity.</P>
<P>Again, A Godly man may Suffer the loss of his <HI>House,</HI> when man<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wicked men Escape that Calamity. A <HI>Job,</HI> one who <HI>Fears God and Shuns Evil,</HI> may have his <HI>House</HI> laid even with the Ground, while he could yet complain, <HI>The Tabernacles of Robbers prosper.</HI> Yea,</P>
<P>Thirdly, At the <HI>House</HI> o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a Godly man may begin that Calamity, that shall In∣volve the loss of many other <HI>Houses</HI> in it. A <HI>Fire</HI> may be carried, even from the <HI>Altar</HI> it self, over the <HI>whole City</HI>: and we know, <HI>Trouble may begin at the House of God.</HI> Wherefore, upon the whole; Those
<PB N="54" REF="000827_0029_0FAB419FA8400038"/>
persons are not alwayes the <HI>Greatest Sin∣ners,</HI> who are the <HI>Greatest Sufferers,</HI> in such a Calamity. Those <HI>Tabernacles</HI> may mis∣carry in which yet there are no abound∣ing miscarriages of <HI>Iniquity.</HI></P>
<P>But all this Concession, will not Eva∣cuate this Position; That we shall very much Consult the Safety of our <HI>Houses,</HI> if we keep <HI>Iniquity</HI> out of them. If we would not be <HI>put out</HI> of our <HI>Tabernacles</HI> our selves, it should be our Study, to <HI>put Iniquity far away from our Tabernacles.</HI> There are many wayes, by which men seek to Secure unto themselves the Com∣fortable Enjoyment of their <HI>Houses.</HI> They look to the <HI>Stuff,</HI> and the <HI>Place,</HI> of their <HI>Building</HI>; they have their <HI>Water Engines,</HI> their <HI>Ensurances,</HI> and their <HI>Friendly Societies.</HI> 'Tis well: But, Sirs, there is one way more to be laid in, which I now mention, in the approach of the Time of the year, when the Dangers of our being Turned out of our <HI>Houses,</HI> are the greatest; That is, Let us <HI>Put Iniquity far from our Taber∣nacles.</HI> Of this way, I may say, as <HI>David</HI> about the Sword of <HI>Goliah, There is none like it</HI>! For, There are <HI>Promises</HI> of our
<PB N="55" REF="000827_0029_0FAB419FA8400038"/>
God, that the <HI>Tabernacles</HI> of men shall be spared, when the <HI>Iniquities</HI> of men are not spared in their <HI>Tabernacles: Promises,</HI> to be interpreted, with the Exceptions of the New Covenant. We have the word of a faithful God for it, <HI>Let no Sins dwell with you, and I will not cut off your Dwellings</HI>▪ It is His Word, in Zeph. 3.7. <HI>I said, Surely, Thou wilt Fear me, thou wilt Receive Instruction, So their Dwelling should not be cut off.</HI> There is that <HI>Promise</HI> given to the Reformers of <HI>Iniquity,</HI> in Isa. 65.21. <HI>They shall Build Houses and Inhabit them</HI>: There is that <HI>Promise</HI> given to the For∣sakers of <HI>Iniquity,</HI> in Ezek. 28.26. <HI>They shall Build Houses, and they shall dwell with Con∣fidence therein.</HI> It was no mistake, in him that said, in Job 8 5, 6. <HI>If thou wouldest seek unto God, if thou were't pure and upright, He would make the Habitation of thy Righ∣teousness Prosperous.</HI> A <HI>Righteous</HI> Habita∣tion, is like to be a <HI>Prosperous</HI> Habitation, and therefore a <HI>Preserved</HI> Habitation.</P>
<P>But on the other side, There are the <HI>Menaces</HI> of our God, That if the <HI>Iniquities</HI> of men are not put away from their <HI>Ta∣bernacles,</HI> their <HI>Tabernacles</HI> then shall be
<PB N="56" REF="000827_0030_0FAB41A13507AB18"/>
taken away from them. It is that which the most High God ha's threatned, <HI>Let your Sins go, or I will make your Houses go.</HI> See Zeph. 1 12, 13. It is Threatned, that God will <HI>Deprive</HI> us of our Houses, if <HI>Ini∣quity</HI> be countenanced in them; and this He can do when He will, by His <HI>Fiery Rebukes.</HI> We have it Threatned, in Ezek. 16.41. <HI>They shall Burn thine Houses with Fire.</HI> It is also Threatned, That God will <HI>Empty</HI> our Houses of us; and this can be done quickly, by <HI>Oppression,</HI> by <HI>Poverty,</HI> by <HI>Mortality.</HI> We have it Threatned, in Isa. 5.9. <HI>Many Houses shall be Desolate, even Great and Fair ones, without Inhabitant▪</HI> Briefly, If we would not have the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> God, issue out a <HI>Writ of Ejection</HI> upon us, to Turn us out of our Houses, <HI>Let us put away Iniquity far from our Tabernacles.</HI></P>
<P>In this one Expression, all <HI>Houshold Religion,</HI> is to be understood, as contain∣ed and Intended. Accordingly,</P>
<P>The CASE,</P>
<P>Wherewith you are now to be treated,
<PB N="57" REF="000827_0030_0FAB41A13507AB18"/>
<HI>What is that <HI>Houshold Religion</HI></HI>▪ or, <HI>what are those Cares, and those Acts of Religion, in our Houses, whereby the Comfortable Enjoyment of our Houses, may be Secured unto us</HI>?</P>
<P>In answer hereunto, Let these <HI>Faithful Sayings</HI> be counted <HI>Worthy of all Acceptation</HI> with us.</P>
<P N="1"><HI>I.</HI> If we would Comfortably Enjoy our <HI>Tabernacles,</HI> Let us particularly <HI>Put away</HI> those <HI>Iniquities,</HI> which have a particular Tendency to provoke, and procure our being <HI>Put out</HI> of our <HI>Tabernacles.</HI> The Jews thought they consulted the safety of their <HI>Houses,</HI> when they Sought, and Cast, all their <HI>Leven</HI> out of their <HI>Houses.</HI> Let us in like manner Search our <HI>Houses,</HI> for every <HI>Iniquity,</HI> which may be like <HI>Leven</HI> in them, and let us, Away with it, <HI>Away with it all</HI>! Indeed, Every Iniquity is per∣nicious, not only to the <HI>Heart,</HI> but also to the <HI>House</HI> that gives a Lodging there∣unto; and therefore we should fall out with all <HI>Iniquity.</HI> If any one should ma∣liciously <HI>Burn</HI> us out of <HI>House</HI> and <HI>Home,</HI>
<PB N="58" REF="000827_0031_0FAB41A1AB8DC7C0"/>
we should never Endure the sight of such a Wretch; but see the Law of Death Executed on him. Why <HI>Sin,</HI> I say unto you, <HI>Si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> would be such an Incendiary: it is said, in Isa. 9.18. <HI>Wickedness, burneth as Fire.</HI> But there are some <HI>Iniquities,</HI> which are more especially, and certainly, and frequently, as <HI>Fire balls</HI> upon the <HI>Houses</HI> wherein they are committed; and the Counsil thereupon unto us is, <HI>Oh! Turn those unfruitful works of Darkness out of D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ors, Lest we be our selves Turn'd out of Doors for the sake thereof.</HI></P>
<P>It was of old Required, concerning an <HI>House,</HI> which had the <HI>Leprosy</HI> Spreading and Fretting on it, in Lev. 14.45. <HI>The Priest shall break down the House, the Stones of it, and the Timber thereof, and all the Mortar of the House.</HI> What that <HI>Plague</HI> of <HI>Leprosy</HI> was, we do not in this Part and Age of the World seem to understand; if it were not a <HI>Plague</HI> peculiar unto <HI>Ca∣naan,</HI> perhaps it means an Infection in the <HI>Walls</HI> of an House, from whence the Inhabitants might be in Hazzard of catching the <HI>Leprosy.</HI> But this may be said in Allusion hereunto; I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you keep a∣ny
<PB N="59" REF="000827_0031_0FAB41A1AB8DC7C0"/>
<HI>Bad Orders</HI> in your <HI>Houses,</HI> I must come unto you, with such Language, as was then directed, <HI>It seems to me▪ there <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, as it were a Plague in the House</HI> Do not now stand asking of me, what I mean by <HI>Bad Orders.</HI> Ask your sober, honest, industrious Neighbours; or ask your own Consciences; They will tell you, What <HI>Bad Orders</HI> are. But Oh! Get thy House cleared of that <HI>Plague</HI> which is to be seen in the <HI>Bad Orders</HI> of it; Lest our Lord Jesus Christ the <HI>High Priest of the Creation,</HI> do <HI>break down</HI> that <HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>use,</HI> and, it may be <HI>burn</HI> thee out of such an <HI>House.</HI></P>
<P>There are <HI>Houses,</HI> where God is not Ser∣ved, but where the people give themselves up to <HI>all Excess of Ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t; Gaming</HI> Houses, <HI>Drinking</HI> Houses, perhaps <HI>Baw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y</HI> Houses; <HI>Houses,</HI> where Troops Assemble to Har∣lots; <HI>Houses,</HI> where young people De∣bauch themselves &amp; one another. Those <HI>House<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> which make the <HI>Parents</HI> and <HI>Masters</HI> in the Town, continually afraid of ha∣ving their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>olks undone by those Houses. Me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ks, I see written on their Doors, <HI>Lord, have mercy upon us!</HI> There is a <HI>Plague</HI> in them. The <HI>Keepers</HI> of such Houses,
<PB N="60" REF="000827_0032_0FAB41A26B0123D8"/>
are not in this Congregation to Day. But, those that may keep a strict eye upon them are here; and unto them, I would say, If the Worshipful <HI>Justices,</HI> and the <HI>Constables,</HI> and the <HI>Tything men,</HI> would In∣vigorate their Zeal, to Rout the villanous Haunts of those <HI>Houses,</HI> the whole Town would be vastly the safer for it. There were Four whole Towns together once, in which there were many Houses, full of Riotous Iniquities; The Prophet says, There was nothing but <HI>Pride,</HI> and <HI>Luxury</HI>; and <HI>Idleness</HI> in their <HI>Houses</HI>; And the Wrath of God so broke forth against those Towns, that they were all consumed at once, and not one <HI>House</HI> Left Standing in them. The <HI>Nineteenth</HI> Chapter of <HI>Ge∣nesis,</HI> will tell you, what I mean.</P>
<P>And besides these House consuming <HI>Bad Orders,</HI> there is especially one <HI>Iniquity</HI> more which will horribly Endanger the <HI>Tabernacles,</HI> that are Guilty of it; and that is, proper <HI>Iniquity,</HI> I mean, <HI>Dishonesty.</HI> It was a Remarkable passage, in Zech. 5.2, 4. <HI>A Flying Roll, the Length thereof Twenty Cubits, the Breadth thereof Ten Cubits; This is the Curse that goeth forth; I will bring it
<PB N="61" REF="000827_0032_0FAB41A26B0123D8"/>
forth, saith the Lord of Hosts, and it shall enter into the House of the Thief, and the House of him that sweareth falsely; and it shall consume it, with the Timber thereof, and the Stones thereof.</HI> The Porch of the Temple, was, <HI>The Length thereof Twenty Cubits, and the Breadth thereof Ten Cubits:</HI> Now, 'tis Judg'd, there were men Em∣ploy'd as <HI>Trustees</HI> of the <HI>Money</HI> gathered for the Building of the Temple: but some of them were such <HI>Thieves</HI> as to convert part of this unto their own use, and yet they <HI>Swore Falsely,</HI> in swearing to the Truth of their Accounts. Now, says the Lord, If the <HI>Temple</HI> it self were a <HI>Roll,</HI> or a Book, filled with <HI>Curses,</HI> it could not Express more <HI>Curses,</HI> than I will swiftly bring upon the <HI>Houses</HI> of such Dishonest men. Truly, All <HI>Dishonesty</HI> in Dealings, does Endanger the <HI>Houses</HI> of the Dealers. Men that go to feather their <HI>Nests</HI> by any <HI>Dishonesty,</HI> do but carry <HI>Coals</HI> into them. The <HI>Flying Roll</HI> of the Curses from God, comes as a <HI>Fiery Roll,</HI> to con∣sume the <HI>Houses</HI> of them that by <HI>Stealing,</HI> by <HI>Cheating,</HI> by <HI>Lying,</HI> propose to Enrich themselves.</P>
<P N="2"><PB N="62" REF="000827_0033_0FAB41A3F3D0CD10"/><HI>II.</HI> If we would comfortably Enjoy our <HI>Tabernacles,</HI> Let us <HI>Dedicate</HI> them unto God, and Employ them in Uses agreea∣ble to such a <HI>Dedication.</HI> We read in Psal. 30. Tit. concerning, <HI>The<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Dedication of the House of David.</HI> With such a <HI>De∣dication</HI> Let us consecrate our <HI>Houses</HI> unto God, professing unto Him, <HI>Lord, This House which thou hast here given to me, I do give back to thee again, and I will use it for thy Glory, as Long as thou wilt Let me Live <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it</HI>! And then according to this <HI>Conse∣cration,</HI> as we read sometimes concerning, <HI>The Church in the House,</HI> of such or such a person, Let our <HI>Houses</HI> be a sort of Little <HI>Churches,</HI> for the Sacred Use that we put them unto. It was said of <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> in Zech. 2 5. <HI>I, saith the Lord, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> unto <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a Wall of Fire round about, and I will be the Glory in the midst of her.</HI> Thus, Let God be <HI>Glorified</HI> in the <HI>midst</HI> of our Hou∣ses, and there will be a <HI>Wall of Fire,</HI> that is, a Guard of <HI>Angels,</HI> round about them, and so no other <HI>Fire</HI> shall prey upon them. Let our <HI>Houses</HI> be used, as if built on purpose for Works of <HI>Piety,</HI> and Works
<PB N="63" REF="000827_0033_0FAB41A3F3D0CD10"/>
of <HI>Charity,</HI> to be therein performed; and Let our Character be that, in Acts 10.2. <HI>A Devout man, one that feared God, with all his House, which gave much Alms to the people, and pray'd unto God alway.</HI> There are two Names, that we should make our <HI>Houses</HI> now to become worthy of▪ the Name of <HI>Bethel,</HI> and the Name of <HI>Bethesda</HI>: both an <HI>House of God,</HI> and an <HI>House of Good.</HI> Let our Houses be as tho' Devoted unto the <HI>Service</HI> of God; Let Praying, and Reading, and Singing, be the Daily Exercises therein attended; so that you may look upon this and that Apartment with such a joyful Reflection in your minds, <HI>If the Walls of this place could speak, they would speak of many a good Hour which I have had with the Lord in this place.</HI> And let our <HI>Houses</HI> be, as tho' De∣voted also unto the <HI>Succour</HI> of man; As far as you can, make <HI>Alms houses</HI> of them; Do what the Lord has bid, <HI>Bring the poor, that are cast out, unto thy House.</HI> Let an <HI>Hungry</HI> Jesus, a <HI>Naked</HI> Jesus, a <HI>Travelling</HI> Jesus, in His Members, be often Refresh∣ed there. I tell you, The very <HI>Angels</HI> of God, Love to <HI>Watch</HI> about the <HI>Hou∣ses,</HI>
<PB N="64" REF="000827_0034_0FAB41A4AB7DF8E0"/>
that are so Devoted unto the Lord.</P>
<P>When the Jews built their Houses, they still had their <HI>Gualijoth,</HI> their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>APEΩA, their <HI>Upper Chambers</HI> in them. There was alwayes a <HI>Room,</HI> in the <HI>Upper part</HI> of the House, which they set apart for Sacred Employments: It was their <HI>Oratory,</HI> and they had in it a Window, which they called, <HI>Gods Window,</HI> opening towards the Temple. Here <HI>Daniel</HI> waited upon God; Here <HI>Hezekiah</HI> lay Sick; <HI>Paul</HI> took this Room to Preach in, when <HI>Euti∣chus</HI> fell, 'tis probable, from that very <HI>Window.</HI> Even the Wickedest men a∣mong them, would not have an House without such a <HI>Room</HI> and such a <HI>Window</HI> in the Room; Hence the Lord said of one, in Jer. 22.14. <HI>Wo to him, that saith, I will build me a wide House, and large Upper Chambers, and cutteth him out Windows</HI> there. But now, that which is to be urged upon us, in these Dayes, when <HI>Holiness of Places</HI> is abolished, is this; Let every <HI>Room</HI> of our <HI>Houses,</HI> in some sort or other, be the Lords.</P>
<P N="3"><HI>III.</HI> Our <HI>Tabernacles</HI> must not be <HI>Prayer∣less
<PB N="65" REF="000827_0034_0FAB41A4AB7DF8E0"/>
Tabernacles,</HI> if we would Comfortably Enjoy these <HI>Tabernacles.</HI> If we will Deny <HI>God,</HI> in our <HI>Houses,</HI> 'tis but just that He should then Deny <HI>Houses</HI> unto us. It is a dreadful Imprecation, in Jer. 10.25. <HI>O Lord, pour out thy Fury on the Families, that call not on thy Name.</HI> And wherein will that <HI>Fury</HI> be discovered? It will be par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly discovered, in Turning those <HI>Families</HI> out of their <HI>Houses.</HI></P>
<P>If there be so much as one owner of a <HI>Prayerless House,</HI> now appearing in this <HI>House of Prayer</HI>; yea, if there be so much as one of you, that <HI>Pray</HI> any seldome<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> with your <HI>Families,</HI> than ordinarily Twice in a Day, with a <HI>Morning</HI> and an <HI>Evening</HI> Sacrifice, I would address that man, with an Earnest Expostrilation.</P>
<P>Friend; The very <HI>Turks,</HI> do at this Day uphold a <HI>Family Worship</HI> among them; and art thou worthy to be called a <HI>Christian,</HI> that livest without any <HI>Family-Worship</HI> at all? No, Thou art in this Thing, worse than a <HI>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rk</HI>▪ It is noted concerning <HI>Obed-Edom, The Lord blessed Obed-Edom, and his Houshold, while the Ark of the Lord was there.</HI> Even so, The <HI>Lord</HI>
<PB N="66" REF="000827_0035_0FAB41A56B83A218"/>
would <HI>Bless</HI> thee, and thy <HI>Houshold,</HI> if <HI>Prayer to the Lord</HI> were there. But thy Sinful, Woful <HI>Family</HI> lies open to the <HI>Curse</HI> of God, as long as thou dost not carry those poor Children and Servants unto the Lord Jesus Christ, for His <HI>Blessing</HI> to be bestow'd upon them: And how hide∣ously, will <HI>They</HI> also <HI>Curse</HI> thee, through∣out Eternal Ages, when they shall with Intolerable Anguish cry out, <HI>Oh! that I had never seen that Prayerless House! 'Tis that House, which ha's brought me to this Hell for ever!</HI> But there is this particu∣lar Aggravation of thy Impiety; That if the Town be laid in Ashes, 'tis thy <HI>Pray∣erless House</HI> that is among the just causes of it.</P>
<P>Come then; Don't any more plead, That you have <HI>no Time</HI> for <HI>Family-Prayer.</HI> Did God Give thee all thy <HI>Time</HI>; and shall <HI>He</HI> have none of it? Find a little Time for thy <HI>Soul,</HI> as well as for the <HI>World</HI>; Or, go write that Sentence upon thy Mantle tree, <HI>What is a man pro∣fited, if he gain the whole World, and loose his own Soul</HI>?</P>
<P>And plead no more, That you want
<PB N="67" REF="000827_0035_0FAB41A56B83A218"/>
<HI>Confidence</HI> or <HI>Utterance,</HI> for <HI>Family Prayer.</HI> But, Meditate on that Warning of the Lord Jesus Christ, <HI>Whosoever shall be A∣shamed of me, of him also shall the Son of Man be Ashamed.</HI> Sit down, and ponder, What are your Sins, your Wants, your Woes; There is no need of making Elegant Orations before the Lord: Call thy Folks together; Fall down before the Lord among them all; Cry to the Lord for them as well as He shall en∣able thee: Try, to Night, if thou never didst before; Try; God will Help thee, man; and thou wilt come to the Mini∣ster who thus advised thee, and say, <HI>Blessed be the Lord, and Blessed be thy Advice, and Blessed be thou for giving it</HI>!</P>
<P N="4"><HI>IV.</HI> If we would Comfortably Enjoy our <HI>Tabernacles,</HI> Let us Conscientiously <HI>Instruct</HI> and <HI>Govern</HI> those that are under our charge, in our <HI>Tabernacles.</HI> Let us do what we can, that there may be none but such as may Know and Serve God in our <HI>Houses,</HI> and it may be Hoped that God will permit our <HI>Houses</HI> to stand before Him. There is to be Recommend∣ed
<PB N="68" REF="000827_0036_0FAB41A62C0AFE70"/>
unto us, the Great Exemple of <HI>Abra∣ham,</HI> in Gen. 18.19. <HI>I know him, that he will command his Children and Houshold after him, and they shall keep the way of the Lord.</HI> Oh! Let not the <HI>Houses</HI> of <HI>Christians,</HI> be∣come like the <HI>Wigwams</HI> of <HI>Indians,</HI> for the Unnurtured, Uninstructed, Ungo∣verned, <HI>Families</HI> in them! Wherefore, Let us Faithfully <HI>Teach</HI> the Little Folks in our <HI>Houses; Teach</HI> them, as <HI>David</HI> and <HI>Bethsheba</HI> did their <HI>Solomon; Teach</HI> them to <HI>Know</HI> those things from their <HI>Childhood,</HI> whereby they may be <HI>made Wise unto Sal∣vation</HI>: See that they be none of them unacquainted with the <HI>Covenant</HI> of God, or, with any agreeable <HI>Doctrine of God their Saviour.</HI> Let us also Fervently <HI>Charge</HI> those Little Folks: <HI>Charge</HI> them to <HI>Serve the Lord with a Perfect Heart and a Willing Mind; Charge</HI> them to <HI>Believe</HI> on Christ, and <HI>Repent</HI> of Sin, and <HI>Return</HI> to God; <HI>Charge</HI> them to <HI>Enter into their Closets, and Pray to their Heavenly Father in Secret</HI>; Admonish them, that they do <HI>Consider their Wayes</HI>; and that especially they Shun all <HI>Bad Company,</HI> and <HI>not Con∣sent, if Sinners do Entice them.</HI> If any of
<PB N="69" REF="000827_0036_0FAB41A62C0AFE70"/>
them do fall into any Sin against God, be sure to <HI>Reprove</HI> that Sin; <HI>Reprove</HI> it Scripturally, <HI>Reprove</HI> it Effectually. And <HI>Restrain</HI> them from every Sin, which they would be Ready to Run into. Let there be no <HI>Children of Belial</HI> with you, none that shall be free from the <HI>Yoke</HI> of a Serious <HI>Discipline.</HI></P>
<P>There is especially one Sin, which the Lord has Required <HI>Housholders</HI> to keep all within their <HI>Houses</HI> from.</P>
<P>The Fourth Commandment is, That the <HI>Lords Day</HI> shall not be profaned, by <HI>thy Son, or thy Daughter, thy Man servant, or thy Maid servant, nor thy Stranger that is within thy Gates.</HI> And it was once the Menace of Heaven, <HI>If ye will not hearken unto me, to hallow the Sabbath-day, then I will kindle a Fire▪ and it shall devour, and it shall not be quenched</HI>! Oh! consider of it!</P>
<P N="5"><HI>V.</HI> Let us carefully <HI>Attend, Esteem, Sup∣port</HI> the <HI>Tabernacles</HI> of the Lord, and that will be the way for us comfortably to Enjoy our own. When <HI>David</HI> was Ba∣nished from his own <HI>House,</HI> his value for the <HI>House</HI> of God, was Recompensed
<PB N="70" REF="000827_0037_0FAB41A6EBEE79A8"/>
with a Return unto his own. Would we never be Banished at all; out of our <HI>Hou∣ses?</HI> Let us value the <HI>House</HI> of God above our own; and let us <HI>Build</HI> up <HI>His House,</HI> Lest He <HI>Burn</HI> down ours. Would we have many <HI>Dayes</HI> in our <HI>Tabernacles?</HI> Let us then heartily say, as in Psal. 84.1.10. <HI>How Amiable are thy Tabernacles, O Lord of Hosts? A Day there is better than a thou∣sand elsewhere.</HI> Would we have the <HI>Love</HI> and the <HI>Eye</HI> of God upon our <HI>Habitations?</HI> Let us then heartily say, as in Psal 26.8. <HI>Lord, I have Loved the Habitation of thy House, and the place where thy Honour dwells.</HI> The Jewes give this, as the Definition of a <HI>Bad Neighbour: A Bad Neighbour is one who dwells in a Town, where there is a Sy∣nagogue, and never comes unto the Synagogue.</HI> Truly, that person, who comes not unto the <HI>Houses</HI> of God, in the Town, is a <HI>Bad Neighbour</HI>; and our own <HI>Houses</HI> may fare the worse for having such a <HI>Bad Neighbour</HI> near unto them. They plead perhaps, <HI>That they have not Cloaths good enough.</HI> But you that are their Friends, I pray, ask them, whether they had not better come to the House of God, with
<PB N="71" REF="000827_0037_0FAB41A6EBEE79A8"/>
<HI>mean Cloaths,</HI> than Loose the <HI>Garments of Salvation,</HI> which are here to be put upon their Souls. Ask them, whether they must not shortly be Shrowded in a <HI>Wind∣ing Sheet,</HI> and then they will <HI>mourn at the Last,</HI> that ever <HI>mean Cloaths</HI> were their Excuse for not coming to the House of God. If they profanely tell you, They stay at Home to <HI>Read a Chapter in Job,</HI> Turn 'em to a Chapter in <HI>Job,</HI> and that mark of a Godly man, in Job 23 12. <HI>I have Esteemed the words of His mouth more than my necessary Food.</HI> Briefly, It is the <HI>Church</HI> of God, that is the <HI>House</HI> of God. Now, Let the <HI>Church</HI> of God, receive all possible Regard and Kindness from you▪ Upon this Encouragement, you <HI>cannot</HI> Show so much Respect unto the <HI>House</HI> of God, but God will show more to yours.</P>
<P N="6"><HI>VI.</HI> Let us be Humbly Thankful, for the Mercies of God, which we Enjoy in our <HI>Tabernacles,</HI> if we would still comfor∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ably Enjoy our <HI>Tabernacles.</HI> If we would not be Turned out of our <HI>Houses,</HI> Let us <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay the Rent which we owe to our Great <HI>Land lord</HI> for them: That <HI>Rent</HI> is this,
<PB N="72" REF="000827_0038_0FAB41A7AC22C460"/>
<HI>Let us offer the praise that will Glorifie Him, and Let us order our Conversations aright.</HI> We are not Abroad obnoxious to the Hardships of the Weather, <HI>Consumed,</HI> as the Patriarch was, <HI>In the Day by the Drought, and in the Night by the Frost</HI>; nor are we confined unto the wretched Cottages of the <HI>Salvages.</HI> Now unto what is this to be ascribed?</P>
<P>I'l mention unto you, a very Heart-mel∣ting Thought! Our Precious and Glori∣ous Lord Jesus Christ, could say, in Mat. 8.20. <HI>The Foxes have Holes, and the Birds of the Air, have Nests; but the Son of Man has not where to Lay his Head.</HI> Now 'tis to this <HI>Humiliation</HI> of our Lord Jesus Christ, that we are to ascribe, the <HI>Mercies</HI> which we have, in our Commodious <HI>Houses.</HI> Oh! Let us Thankfully say be∣fore the Lord, <HI>My Lord Jesus Christ, by being Harbourless in this Evil World, has procured for me this Benefit, that I am in a Good Harbour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hore. Bless the Lord, O my Soul, and Forget not such a Benefit!</HI> Here∣upon, When we Look round about our <HI>Houses,</HI> and see the manifold Smiles of God in every Corner of them, we should
<PB N="73" REF="000827_0038_0FAB41A7AC22C460"/>
then Study with our selves, <HI>What shall I now render to the Lord?</HI> It is noted of <HI>Da∣vid,</HI> in 2 Sam 7.1, 2. <HI>He sat in his House, and the Lord had given him Rest,</HI> and he then thought, <HI>What shall I do for the Ark of God?</HI> Would we <HI>Sit</HI> long, and <HI>Sit</HI> safe, and <HI>Sit</HI> quiet in our <HI>Houses?</HI> Let us, when we <HI>Sit</HI> there, contrive what <HI>Returns</HI> we shall make to the God of Heaven for them.</P>
<P N="7"><HI>VII.</HI> Would we comfortably Enjoy our <HI>Tabernacles?</HI> Then Let us Remember that they are no more than <HI>Tabernacles.</HI> When you go into your Comfortable <HI>Houses,</HI> rec∣kon them no more than <HI>Stages,</HI> whereat you can only stay to Bait a while in your Journey, to your Eternal State. Oh! Live like <HI>Strangers</HI> in your own <HI>Houses</HI>; and be the <HI>House</HI> never so convenient, yet count not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur selves at <HI>Home,</HI> in that <HI>House.</HI></P>
<P>I beseech you, to Lay up this Admoni∣tion with you. If you would <HI>Keep</HI> any thing, in this World, you must not set your <HI>Hearts</HI> upon it: and indeed, it is fit that men should keep nothing of this World, which they do set their <HI>Hearts</HI>
<PB N="74" REF="000827_0039_0FAB41A86C1BA040"/>
upon. The way for us, to have our <HI>Hou∣ses</HI> taken away from us, is, to have our <HI>Hearts</HI> vainly fond of continuing in them. It was therefore an Annual, and a most suitable <HI>Ceremony,</HI> which the Lord Enjoin∣ed upon His People of old; When a Good <HI>Harvest</HI> had fill'd their <HI>Houses,</HI> God ordered them to go out of their <HI>Houses</HI>; they must then go make Little <HI>Tabernacles</HI> abroad, and keep the Feast of <HI>Tabernacles.</HI> Thus did the Lord mind them of their Condition in this World; when they had never so much of <HI>this World</HI> about them, they must not forget that they were no more than <HI>Sojourners</HI> in the World. This I say; Tho' we have <HI>Houses</HI> that we can <HI>Feast</HI> in, yet Let us have the Temper of a <HI>Feast of Taberna∣cles</HI> in us. Let our <HI>Hearts</HI> be gone out of our <HI>Houses,</HI> &amp; the Lord will give <HI>us,</HI> Leave to stay the Longer in them.</P>
<P>Oh! Let us not be those <HI>Fools,</HI> of whom 'tis said in Psal. 49 11. <HI>Their Inward Thought is, that their Houses shall continue for ever, and their Dwelling-places to all Generations</HI>: Nor let us foolishly count, the <HI>Goods</HI> in our Houses, <HI>Goods laid up for
<PB N="75" REF="000827_0039_0FAB41A86C1BA040"/>
many years.</HI> As we walk about our <HI>Houses,</HI> let this Consideration come into our Hearts; <HI>How easily can all these Riches take themselves Wings and flee away! One or Two Hours, may lay this House Level with the Ground.</HI> But there is a further Consideration, which is then also to come into our Hearts; <HI>'Tis but a little while that I shall remain in this House; It won't be long, before I am Lock'd up in a Coffin under Ground, when the place that now knows me, will know me no more.</HI></P>
<P>And what should be the Issue of such Considerations? I would Pray you, let it be <HI>This.</HI> Let us make sure of an <HI>House Eternal in the Heavens,</HI> to be Enjoy'd by us, when our <HI>Earthly Tabernacles</HI> can be no more useful to us. If you Enquire, <HI>How this is to be done?</HI> I answer, in one Word; By giving to the Lord Jesus Christ, the Lord of Heaven, a <HI>Dwelling</HI> in our Souls. Our <HI>Houses</HI> here, though made of <HI>Brick</HI> and <HI>Stone</HI> it self, they are only <HI>Tabernacles.</HI> But the Apostle tells us, in 2 Cor. 5.1. <HI>We have an House Eternal in the Heavens.</HI> The Blasphemous <HI>Julian,</HI> would insolently call our Lord Jesus
<PB N="76" REF="000827_0040_0FAB41A92BC57990"/>
Christ, <HI>The Carpenters Son.</HI> But, Christi∣ans; Be assured, That Blessed <HI>Son in Law of a Carpenter,</HI> is He that ha's built a Stately Palace, in the Heavenly Regions, for all His Chosen ones; and He hath said, in Joh. 14.2. <HI>In my Fathers House are many Mansions</HI>; Even, as there were ma∣ny <HI>Chambers</HI> to Lodge the Priests, an∣nexed unto the <HI>Temple</HI> of old. The For∣midable Fires, that shall dispatch the <HI>Conflagration</HI> of the World, of which <HI>Conflagration,</HI> the <HI>Fires</HI> multiplied in our Dayes, are doubtless a Shadow, and an <HI>Omen</HI>; Those <HI>Fires,</HI> I say, will not reach this Illustrious <HI>House.</HI></P>
<P>When the Worthy Minister of <HI>Nola,</HI> had his <HI>House</HI> burnt, he lift up his Eyes to Heaven, saying, <HI>Domine, ubi Omnia Mea Tu Scis</HI>; Lord, Thou knowest, I have a better <HI>House</HI> than This. Oh! Let us make sure of a <HI>Mansion</HI> in Heaven, by Faith in the Lord Jesus Christ; and so, when our other Houses fail us, <HI>We shall be Received into Everlasting Habitations.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="conclusion">
<HEAD>CORONIS.</HEAD>
<P>But there is a Tribe of <HI>Zebulon,</HI> which makes no little part of our Neigh∣bourhood.
<PB N="77" REF="000827_0040_0FAB41A92BC57990"/>
There are so many of our Neighbours, whose Employment lies at Sea, that in my own particular Congrega∣tion, I have counted near <HI>Ninety</HI> Persons, in one Day recommended unto our Pray∣ers, by Bills from those who were Sollici∣tous for their Friends then abroad.</P>
<P>My Neighbours, Your <HI>Vessels</HI> are your <HI>Houses</HI>; what are your <HI>Ships,</HI> your <HI>Ketches,</HI> your <HI>Brigantines,</HI> and your <HI>Sloops,</HI> but your <HI>Tabernacles?</HI> Oh! may <HI>Iniquity</HI> be <HI>Put far</HI> from them! Since we have been pressing of that <HI>Religion,</HI> which may have a Ten∣dency to preserve our <HI>Standing Houses</HI> a <HI>Shore,</HI> let us also press that <HI>Religion,</HI> by which the preservation of your <HI>Floating Houses</HI> at <HI>Sea</HI> may be be-friended.</P>
<P>It is a passage, in Psal. 107.23.24. <HI>They that go down to the Sea in Ships, that do Business in great Waters, These see the works of the Lord, and His Wonders in the Deep.</HI></P>
<P>In the First place, before ever you Em∣bark in those your <HI>Moving Tabernacles,</HI> be∣come United unto the Lord Jesus Christ, by <HI>Faith</HI> in Him, that so you may be pre∣pared for all the <HI>Wonders</HI> of those <HI>Dangers,</HI> which you may be Exposed unto. There
<PB N="78" REF="000827_0041_0FAB41AA91900090"/>
are wonderful <HI>Storms,</HI> which may Encoun∣ter and Endanger those your <HI>Feeble Ta∣bernacles:</HI> But <HI>Calms,</HI> may likewise In∣commode you worse than <HI>Storms.</HI> By Numberless <HI>Accidents,</HI> these <HI>Tabernacles</HI> may be Sunk and Lost in the <HI>Waters</HI>; but the <HI>Fires</HI> especially may more terribly threaten you, than the <HI>Waters. Enemies</HI> do much prey upon these <HI>Tabernacles</HI> on the Ocean, as the Greater <HI>Fishes</HI> in it, upon the lesser ones; but the worst Enemies, are the <HI>Pyrates</HI> of our own Nation, who barbarously butcher all that may discover them. In short, So Sensibly near to Death are you in these your <HI>Tabernacles,</HI> that, in Truth, <HI>I am prope mors urget, quam prope cernis Aquam</HI>: 'tis but the Breadth of a Plank to two. My Friends, That Pitch't Box of Plank, what is it, but a larger sort of a <HI>Coffin?</HI> Our <HI>Seafaring Folks,</HI> may say with the Psalmist, <HI>My Soul is continually in my Hand.</HI> But, before it come to this, O man if thou Love thy <HI>Soul,</HI> effectually put thy <HI>Soul,</HI> into the Hand of the Lord Jesus Christ, Repairing to Him, and Relying on Him, for thy Righteousness, thy Blessed∣ness, thy Everlasting Life. The Poet
<PB N="79" REF="000827_0041_0FAB41AA91900090"/>
counted him a Bold man, [<HI>Audax Japeti Genus</HI>] who Ventured first of all <HI>to go to Sea.</HI> Yea, but I earnestly Protest unto you, He that will venture to <HI>Sea,</HI> before he hath Savingly Closed with the Lord Je∣sus Christ, by Faith, is a Bold, an Hardy, a Sottish, and a desperately Venturesome Creature. Sirs, Will you go to <HI>Sea,</HI> before you have made up your <HI>Accounts</HI>? There are sad Accounts between God and you; I beseech you, get 'em all made up, in your Believing on the Lord Jesus Christ, for the <HI>Pardon</HI> of all your Sins, before you stir. The First <HI>Ship,</HI> even the <HI>Ark,</HI> was in this, a <HI>Type</HI> of the Lord Jesus Christ, that the Salvation of your Souls does depend on your being <HI>in Him.</HI> Neighbours, Don't Step into any <HI>Ship,</HI> till you are first got in∣to that <HI>Ark!</HI> And Now,</P>
<P>Be sure, That you Abandon those <HI>Vi∣ces,</HI> that <HI>Sailors</HI> too too generaly are used, or at Least, are <HI>Tempted</HI> unto.</P>
<P>The first man, that ever set up a <HI>Ship,</HI> once fell into the Sin of <HI>Drunkenness.</HI> Are none of you, that Sail in a <HI>Ship,</HI> too Liable to that woful Sin? Beware of that <HI>Beastly Vice. Beastly</HI> did I call it? Alas, I have
<PB N="80" REF="000827_0042_0FAB41AAAC54C910"/>
wronged the <HI>Beasts</HI> in so calling it: <HI>Beasts</HI> will not seek to be <HI>Drunk</HI>; To be <HI>Drunk,</HI> turns men into worse than <HI>Beasts.</HI> A <HI>Drunken</HI> man, is q. d. a <HI>Drowned</HI> man; Let our <HI>Sailors</HI> Take heed of being <HI>Drun∣kards,</HI> Lest God Almighty <HI>Drown</HI> them, yea, <HI>Damn</HI> them, for their being so. And is not the Sin of profane <HI>Swearing</HI> and <HI>Cursing,</HI> become too notorious among our <HI>Marriners</HI>? Reform that Impiety Syrs; Lest you that now Sail in a vast Sea of <HI>Waters,</HI> e're Long have that profane <HI>Tongue</HI> tortured in the Fiery Wrath of God, where you shall in vain cry, <HI>Oh! for a Drop of water to cool my Tongue</HI>! The <HI>Tongue</HI> is fitly compared unto the <HI>Helm, which turns about the Ships, tho' they be so great, and are dri∣ven of fierce winds</HI>: That Little <HI>Helm,</HI> in thy mouth, Govern it, O man, and Re∣strain it by the Rules of the Word of God, else thy Soul will be horribly <HI>Ship∣wrack'd.</HI></P>
<P>Filthy Speaking, Baudy speaking, vile <HI>Ribaldry,</HI> is too frequent a Vice of Marri∣ners. Leave it off, I beseech you; and, <HI>Keep thy Tongue from Evil.</HI> It may be, <HI>Mispence of Time,</HI> is to be reckoned a <HI>prin∣cipal</HI>
<PB N="81" REF="000827_0042_0FAB41AAAC54C910"/>
Vice among you; certainly, 'tis a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ernicious one. The Sails of <HI>Time,</HI> are <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urling</HI> apace, and yet how many weary contrivances have you to <HI>pass this Time</HI> a∣way? Yea, but thy Soul is ready to put a∣shore in Eternity; and then, thou wilt wish, thy <HI>Time</HI> had been more of it spent in <HI>Reading,</HI> and <HI>Thinking,</HI> and <HI>Praying</HI> over <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he State of thy Soul.</P>
<P>The <HI>Ships</HI> of <HI>Jehoshaphat</HI> were <HI>Broken</HI>: His men were an abominable Crue! Hear∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en, Brothers; you'l hazard the <HI>Breaking</HI> of your <HI>Ships,</HI> if you don't <HI>break off</HI> your Ungodliness. Let the <HI>Sea,</HI> no Longer-say, <HI>Wisdom is not in me!</HI> on the occasion of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Follies almost universally indulged a∣mong the <HI>Sea faring.</HI></P>
<P>Finally; Use <HI>Prayer,</HI> before you <HI>Go to Sea,</HI> that you may bespeak the presence of the Lord Jesus Christ, in your <HI>Fleeting Tabernacles.</HI> You tell us, <HI>You desire the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rayers of the Congregation.</HI> 'Tis but a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ocking of God, if you make no <HI>Prayers</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> your own. But Invigorate your <HI>Pray∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs,</HI> with <HI>Faith,</HI> in such promises as that▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Isa. 42.3. <HI>When thou passest thro the Wa∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rs, I will be with thee.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="82" REF="000827_0043_0FAB41AB6BD7B588"/>And my <HI>Masters,</HI> continue your <HI>Pray∣ers,</HI> with your <HI>Companies,</HI> even as with your <HI>Families,</HI> during all the Voyage. You are worse than <HI>Jonahs</HI> Marriners, if you do it not.</P>
<P>It may be, you have Received the Fa∣vours of God, on the <HI>Waters.</HI> Don't Write the memory of them, as on the <HI>Waters,</HI> and forget the <HI>Vows</HI> of God that are upon you.</P>
<P>Consider, <HI>Heaven</HI> as you <HI>Haven.</HI> And be desirous, that your <HI>Soul</HI> may like his, in 3 Joh. 2. make a <HI>Good Voyage</HI> of it▪ Have an Eye of <HI>Dayly Observation</HI> on th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Lord Jesus Christ, as the <HI>Sun of Righte∣ousness.</HI> Don't neglect the <HI>Pole Star</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Scripture. Ply the <HI>Pump</HI> of <HI>Repen∣tance,</HI> with continual Zeal to get Sin out of the Hold of the Heart. When the <HI>Gales</HI> of the <HI>Spirit</HI> Striving with you, are blowing, Spread the <HI>Sails</HI> of your Soul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> before them, and Sail right before that blessed Wind. Often see <HI>What Way</HI> you make; and whatever you <HI>cast over-board</HI>▪ make <HI>no Shipwrack of Faith and a Goo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Conscience.</HI> And so, God Smile upon your Voyages.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

