<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2005-06-27</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Converted 145 $-groups to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N00609">
<STC T="E">743</STC>
<STC T="W">j1111</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99002770</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="journal">
<PB REF="000743_0000_0FAA535D71C001F8" MS="y"/>
<PB N="1" REF="000743_0001_0FAA535E52E8CE18" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>A JOURNAL Of what Passed in the Expedition of His Excellency Coll. <HI>Benjamin Fletcher,</HI> Captain General and Governour in Chief of the Province of <HI>New-York, &amp;c.</HI> To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>ANY,</HI> to Renew the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ovenant Chain with the five <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ations of <HI>Indians,</HI> the <HI>Mohaques, Oneydes, Onondages,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and <HI>Sinnekes.</HI></HEAD>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> 17. ON <HI>Thursday</HI> after Sun set his Excellency im∣barqued at <HI>Gre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ch.</HI> On <HI>Tuesday</HI> mor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣ing arrived at <HI>Albany.</HI></P>
<P>This day his Excellency viewed the Fortifications of the City, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to the Mayor &amp; Aldermen for such Reparations <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> needful in the Block-houses, Platforms and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</P>
<P>The 27th. <HI>Sunday</HI> afternoon, The Sachims of <HI>One<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> at <HI>Albany,</HI> in the Evening they supped with his E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>llency giving great expressions of the Joy and Satis∣facti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> had in meeting his Excellency.</P>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> his Excellency sent Capt. <HI>James Wee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s</HI> to view <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Sche<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ectady,</HI> and bring report to his Excellency <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Repairs are wanting. Which was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
<P><PB N="2" REF="000743_0002_0FAA535F1E5EBFF0"/>This day the Sachims of the other three Nations arrived, an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> desired time to rest themselves till to morrow.</P>
<P>The 29th, His Excellency called the Sachims together, an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> spake.</P>
<LIST>
<HEAD>At a Meeting of the Sachims of the five Nations at <HI>Albany,</HI> the <HI>29</HI>th of <HI>Sept. 1696.</HI></HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Present, His Excellency Coll.</HI> Benjamin Fletcher, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Coll</HI> Nicholas Bayard, <HI>of the Council.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>William Pinhorn, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR> of the Council.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Major</HI> Peter Schuyler, <HI>of the Council.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Matthew Clarkson, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR> Secretary.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Major, Recorder &amp; Aldermen of</HI> Albany, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>His Excellency said, <HI>Brethren,</HI> It is an unexpressible Satis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>faction to me that I see you here. I do heartily Condole▪ the loss our Brethren of the <HI>Onondages</HI> and <HI>Oneydes</HI> have sustained by the late Eruption of the <HI>French</HI> Army from <HI>Canada.</HI></P>
<P>Upon the first certain Intelligence I had <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with what Force I could hastily gather for your assistance.</P>
<P>And I am now here, and present you the <HI>Onondages</HI> an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Oneydes</HI> these two Belts of Wampum, as a Confirmation of m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Sincerity, and these Kettles to repair your loss in that kind.</P>
<P><HI>Brethren,</HI> Two Moneths ago I received at <HI>New-York</HI> the fir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Intelligence that the French had made an Insult upon you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Country, I forth-with came up, as I said before, to your R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lief and Assistance. I had an account, before I did reach <HI>Alban<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> from some of your People, That the French Army were r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>treated, and marched back towards <HI>Canada</HI>; I then sent E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>presses desiring you all to meet me at this place. Some tim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> after I received your Answer, That you would meet me a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> this time in <HI>Albany.</HI> And I am now come up a second Time <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Summer, in order to renew the Covenant Chain, and to co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sult
<PB N="3" REF="000743_0003_0FAA535FA944E930"/>
with the Brethren what is most proper, and may be most conducing to the common good &amp; safety of the whole House.</P>
<P><HI>Brethren,</HI> I do acquaint you from my most Illustrous Master the King of <HI>Great Brittain, France</HI> and <HI>Ireland,</HI> that he will always extend his gracious Protection to you, and a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a Seal of it his Majesty has commanded me to deliver you these Presents to keep bright the Covenant Chain from all Rust, &amp; to strengthen it in behalf of all his Majesties Subjects, not only of this Pro∣vince, but these also of <HI>New-England, Connecticut,</HI> the <HI>Jarseys, Pennsilvania, Maryland</HI> and <HI>Virginia.</HI></P>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The <HI>List</HI> of the Presents sent from the Kings most Excellent Majesty, and given to the <HI>Indians, viz.</HI></HEAD>
<ITEM>24 Blew Coats, laced with broad Lace,</ITEM>
<ITEM>24 laced Hats,</ITEM>
<ITEM>24 pair of Shoes with Buckles,</ITEM>
<ITEM>24 Shirts,</ITEM>
<ITEM>22 doz. of Hose,</ITEM>
<ITEM>30 Gun Barrels and Locks,</ITEM>
<ITEM>50 Brass Kettles,</ITEM>
<ITEM>1 Barrel of Powder,</ITEM>
<ITEM>4 C. weight of Lead,</ITEM>
<ITEM>1000 Flints,</ITEM>
<ITEM>1 groce of Tobacco Pipes, of Wood and Tin,</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 groce of Knives,</ITEM>
<ITEM>6 Pound of Vermillion.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>Prime cost in <HI>England</HI> of the above goods 200 <HI>l. st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rl.</HI></P>
<LIST>
<HEAD>A List of Presents added by the Government of <HI>New-York.</HI></HEAD>
<ITEM>1 Piece of D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffils,</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 Cask of Swan Shot,</ITEM>
<ITEM>7 Barrels of Powder,</ITEM>
<ITEM>14 large Kettles,</ITEM>
<ITEM>7 Pieces of white Hamils for shirts,</ITEM>
<ITEM>100 Hatchets,</ITEM>
<ITEM>54 pound &amp; a half of Tobacco in Roll,</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 groce of Pipes,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Wampum 3 <HI>l.</HI> 9 <HI>s.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>28 Gallons of Rum,</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL> </CELL>
<CELL><HI>l.</HI></CELL>
<CELL><HI>s.</HI></CELL>
<CELL><HI>d.</HI></CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>All which cost in <HI>New-York</HI> Money,</CELL>
<CELL>169</CELL>
<CELL>05</CELL>
<CELL>04</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>For Provision to the Indians, &amp; rapairing their Arms,</CELL>
<CELL>130</CELL>
<CELL>19</CELL>
<CELL>07</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Cash for Messengers, Indian Scouts for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntelligence of the Enemy's motion, paid by Mr. <HI>Dellius,</HI> Mr. <HI>Banker</HI> Major <HI>Schuyler,</HI> and Major <HI>Wessells,</HI></CELL>
<CELL>100</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>From <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>l. sterl.</HI> in <HI>N. York</HI> Money is</CELL>
<CELL>260</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
<CELL>00</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>In all</CELL>
<CELL><HI>L.</HI> 660</CELL>
<CELL>04</CELL>
<CELL>11</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
<LIST>
<PB N="4" REF="000743_0004_0FAA536219773210"/>
<HEAD>At a Meeting of the Sachims of the five Nations, at <HI>Albany,</HI> the <HI>1</HI>st of <HI>October, 1696.</HI></HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Present His Excellency</HI> Benjamin Fletcher, <HI>&amp;c:</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Coll.</HI> Nicholas Bayard,</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Pinhorn, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR> of the Council.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Major</HI> Peter Schuyler,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Matthew Clarkson, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR> Secretary,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Mayor, Recorder &amp; Aldermen of</HI> Albany, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><HI>Sononguirese,</HI> a Sachim of the <HI>Mohaques,</HI> was Speaker.</P>
<P><HI>BRother Cajenquiragoe,</HI> We return you Thanks for what you have said the day before yesterday, in condoling of our loss, and for the Kettles which you gave us to boyl our Victuals, in the room of those that are lost by the Enemy, as also for the two Belts of Wampum, given us as a token of your Sincerity, by which our hearts are mightily rejoyced and sifted up in this our poor Condition.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquiragoe,</HI> We are exceedingly rejoyced that the great King, over the Sea, has sent to us in this our low Condition, by which our hearts are lifted up. We were ready to sink in a miserable perishing state, and this makes us revive again. He laid down six Beaver Skins.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> We come to desire you to acquaint the great King, That the Enemy has brought us to a very low Condition, and has destroyed five of our Castles, one is now left, and if that be destroyed, we know not what to do, we know not what shall become of us next. Pray let the great King know this.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> We desire, that since the great King of <HI>England, &amp;c.</HI> has Canows of seventy great Guns a piece, and many Forces, you may acquaint him, That its a great pity we should be so plagued with so small an Enemy a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he <HI>French</HI> and
<PB N="5" REF="000743_0005_0FAA5362DAE05B18"/>
<HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>dians</HI> of <HI>Canada.</HI> We are not able of our selves to destroy them. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e are become a small People, and much lessened by the War the People of <HI>Virginia, Maryland, Pennsilvania,</HI> the <HI>Jarseys, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onnecticut</HI> and <HI>New-England,</HI> who have all put their hands to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e Covenant Chain, will joyn with the Inhabitants of this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ace, we are ready to go and root the <HI>French</HI> and all our Ene∣mies out of <HI>Canada.</HI> He then laid down a bundle of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Beaver skins,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Quebeck, Troy Rivier Mont Real.</HI></NOTE> and upon the out-side thereof a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>raught of the River of <HI>Canada,</HI> with the chief <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>laces thereof, marked, to shew the smallness of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nemy, and how they are seated upon <HI>Canada</HI> River, which they desire may be sent over and shown to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reat King.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquiragoe,</HI> We again thank you for the Message <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou have brought us from the great King. And we pray you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o send again <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him for us, with all vigou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and speed, and to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> before the King what we have here said: fail not in writing, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> not to let the King know it; we give these five Beavers to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he man that writes, to pay for Paper, Pen and Ink.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> We desire you to acquaint the great <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing, as before, That we are a small People, and he has a great People, and many Canows with great Guns. We desire <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou to write to him to know whether he will send them to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>estroy <HI>Canada</HI> or not, against the next time the Trees grow <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reen; and if he will not send Forces to subdue <HI>Canada,</HI> then <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o send us word thereof, that we may make Peace for our selves <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orever▪ or for some time. And we earnestly pray you will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esire the great King to send us an Answer by the next time the Trees gro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> green. He laid down a bundle of six Beavers.</P>
<LIST>
<PB N="6" REF="000743_0006_0FAA53643827B798"/>
<HEAD>At a Meeting of the Sachims of the five Nations, at <HI>Albany,</HI> the <HI>2</HI>d of <HI>October, 1696.</HI></HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Present His Excellency</HI> Benjamin Fletcher, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Coll.</HI> Nicholas Bayard, <HI>of the Council.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>William Pinhorn, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR> of the Council.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Major</HI> Peter Schuyler, <HI>of the Council.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Matthew Clarkson, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR> Secretary,</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The Mayor, Recorder &amp; Aldermen of</HI> Albany, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><HI>Dackashata,</HI> a Sachim of the <HI>Sinnekes,</HI> was Speaker.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI></P>
<P>WE come to condole the loss you daily receive, havin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> daily Alarms of skulking Parties of the Enemy doin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> mischief. Then laid down a Belt of Wampum.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> We come with the whole House to co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sider what tends to the common good of the whole House.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> We come here to quicken the fire, an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> renew the Covenant Chain.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> We come to renew the Covenant Chai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> with all the Brethren of <HI>New-England▪ Connecticut, New-Yor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> the <HI>Jarseys, Pennsilvania, Maryland</HI> and <HI>Virginia,</HI> that the may pertake of the warmth of this fire.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> We recommend to all that are in th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Covenant Chain to be vigorous to keep it up.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> When all is said, I drink all yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Healths, and then I deliver you the Cup.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> There has been a Cloud, and we co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to remove it, as the Sun that comes in the Morning and remov<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the darkness of the Night</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> The Tree of Safety and Well<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> here, we confirm it.</P>
<P><PB N="7" REF="000743_0007_0FAA536505C28878"/><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> As the Tree is planted here, and con∣firmed, so we make fast all the Roots and Branches of it, all the Brethren of the five Nations, and the Brethren of <HI>Virginia, Maryland, Pennsilvania,</HI> the <HI>Jarseys, New<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>York, Connectic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> and <HI>New-England.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> We wish we may rest in quietness under that Tree, we fill it with new Leaves, and wish that all that are in the Covenant Chain may have the benefit to sit down quiet under its shadow.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> I do hereby renew the Covenant Chain with all that have put their hands in it, <HI>Virginia, Maryland, Pennsilvania,</HI> the <HI>Jarseys, N York, Connecticut</HI> &amp; <HI>N. England.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> We renew the Covenant Chain in behalf of the whole House, the <HI>Mohaques, Oneydes, Onondages, Cajonges</HI> and <HI>Sinnekes.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> We have lately had the loss of two Castles by the Enemy, we have concluded to do our best to assist them, and we desire <HI>Cajenquirago</HI> will do the same.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> We wish the Canows may go to and again in safety, that the great King may know what we have here said, and that we may have an answer. We have now made our word good, here is the Cup. Then laid down some small bundles of Beaver, saying, it is but small, but is, as it were, saved out of the fire.</P>
<P>His Excellency stood up, and said,</P>
<P><HI>Brethren,</HI> I have heard what you have said, and have here renewed the Covenant Chain with all the five Nations, the <HI>Mohaques, Oneydes, Onondages, Cojonges</HI> and <HI>Sinnekes,</HI> in behalf of the Brethren of this Province, <HI>Virginia, Maryland, Penn∣silvania,</HI> the <HI>Jarseys, Connecticut</HI> &amp; <HI>New<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>England.</HI> And I do <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the five Nations of his Majesties Protection. I have
<PB N="8" REF="000743_0008_0FAA5365E1F8AF90"/>
provided for you some Victuals, and Drink to drink the King<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Health<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ and in Confirmation thereof, that it may last so long <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Sun and Moon endures, I give this Belt of Wampsum.</P>
<P>The principal Sachim of the <HI>Mohaques,</HI> called, <HI>Oheee.</HI></P>
<P>The whole Assembly answered, <HI>Heeeeee Hogh.</HI></P>
<P>The principal Sachim of the <HI>Oneydes,</HI> called, <HI>Oheee.</HI></P>
<P>The whole Assembly answered, <HI>Heeeeee Hogh.</HI></P>
<P>The principal Sachim of the <HI>Onondages,</HI> called, <HI>Oheee.</HI></P>
<P>The whole Assembly answered, <HI>Heeeeee Hogh.</HI></P>
<P>The principal Sachim of the <HI>Cajonges,</HI> called, <HI>Oheee.</HI></P>
<P>The whole Assembly answered, <HI>Heeeeee Hogh.</HI></P>
<P>The principal Sachim of the <HI>Sinnekes,</HI> called, <HI>Oheee.</HI></P>
<P>The whole Assembly answered, <HI>Heeeeee Hogh.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Octob.</HI> 2. In the Evening his Excellency did appoint the prin∣cipal Sachims to mee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> him at a private Conference next morning.</P>
<LIST>
<HEAD>At a private Meeting of the Sachims at <HI>Albany,</HI> the <HI>3</HI>d of <HI>Oct. 1696.</HI></HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Present, His Excellency Coll.</HI> Benjamin Fletcher, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Coll.</HI> Nicholas Bayard, <HI>of the Council.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>William Pinhorn, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR> of the Council.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Major</HI> Peter Schuyler, <HI>of the Council.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Matthew Clarkson, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR> Secretary.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>His Excellency said,</P>
<P><HI>BRethren,</HI> It was proposed by the Speaker of the five Na∣tions the first day, That I should write to my grea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Master▪ the King of <HI>England, &amp;c.</HI> concerning the War that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> between the five Nations, and the French and Indians of <HI>Canada</HI>
<PB N="9" REF="000743_0009_0FAA5366956E6788"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd that I should g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t an Answer from the great King, to you, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Brethren, against the next time the Trees grow green.</P>
<P><HI>Brethren,</HI> I must assure you, its utterly impossible in so short time to send over to my great Master, &amp; to receive an answer, or Reasons which I shall now give you.</P>
<P>The way over the great Sea is long, the danger and hazards <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e many, and in the Winter season happen many Storms and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ontrary Winds.</P>
<P><HI>Brethren,</HI> I do promise you to use all the speediest means with the first opportunity, to write to the great King, and to get you an answer, which I am sure will be to your content and satisfaction, and so soon as it comes I shall communicate <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t to you.</P>
<P><HI>Brethren,</HI> In the mean time I have appointed Major <HI>Schuyler,</HI> Mr. <HI>Delli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,</HI> Major <HI>Wessels,</HI> and the Mayor of the City of <HI>Albany</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o receive your Propositions, upon any occasion that may offer <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my absence.</P>
<P><HI>Brethren,</HI> I do heartily wish you well home to your Castles, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd that you may look out, and be careful not to be surprized. You can never be too watchful. I now take my leave of you, and give each of you a Keg of Rum, for a Dram, to comfort you in the way home, and a Coat to keep you warm in the Winter. I shall see you again, God willing, next Summer, or sooner if your affairs call, if it please God to continue my health.</P>
<P>The Sachims offer to make some Propositions.</P>
<P><HI>Sononguirese,</HI> Sachim of the <HI>Mohaques,</HI> was Speaker.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago;</HI></P>
<P>WE have been a long time in the Covenant Chain with the Brethren of <HI>New-York,</HI> in which afterwards, at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, the Brethren of <HI>Virginia, Maryland, Pennsilvania,</HI>
<PB N="10" REF="000743_0010_0FAA53674CE83AD0"/>
the <HI>Jarseys, Connecticut</HI> and <HI>New-England,</HI> came and linked them<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>selves▪ they liked the Chain of Peace▪ but where are the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> now? They do not like to take part with us in the War. They are all asleep, They come not to our Assistance against the Ene<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>my, Their hands hang down <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>aight, and their Arms are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>me▪ We see none to mind the War but the Brethren of <HI>New-York.</HI></P>
<P>We are now down upon one knee, but we are not quit down upon the ground. Let the great King of <HI>England</HI> sen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the great Canows with 70 Guns each, and let the Brethren o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Virginia, Maryland, Pennsilvania, the Jarseys, Connecticut</HI> and <HI>New-England</HI> awake, and we will stand up straight again upo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> both feet; our heart is yet stout and good; we doubt not bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to destroy the Enemy. Then laid down a Belt of Wampum.</P>
<P><HI>Brother Cajenquirago,</HI> We again desire you to write to the great King, and to get us an answer against the next time the Trees become green, and that there may be no delay.</P>
<P>Let it not be said to us, that the Canows are lost unde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> water, or that the wind has carried them into anoth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Country or the like Excuse, but let us have the Answer against the Tree<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> become green without fail, for we are in great need of it. The<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> laid down a Beaver skin.</P>
<P>To which his Excellency made answer,</P>
<P><HI>BRethren,</HI> I shall be faithful and exact to my Promi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to you, I shall send to the great King▪ my Maste<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> by the first Opportunity, and be careful in sending yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the great Kings answer, as I told you before. But I ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not be positive to a Time, when the Voyage depends upo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Wind and Weather, which are so uncertain. I wish you we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to your Castles.</P>
<P>The principal Sachim of the <HI>Mohaques,</HI> called, <HI>Oheee.</HI></P>
<P>The whole Number of Sachims answered, <HI>Heeeeee Hogh</HI>▪</P>
<P><PB N="11" REF="000743_0011_0FAA5367EFB5B6F0"/>The principal Sachim of the <HI>Oneydes,</HI> called, <HI>Oheee.</HI></P>
<P>The whole Number of Sachims answered, <HI>Heeeeee Hogh.</HI></P>
<P>The principal Sachim of the <HI>Onondages,</HI> called, <HI>Oheee.</HI></P>
<P>The whole Number of Sachims answered, <HI>Heeeeee Hogh.</HI></P>
<P>The principal Sachim of the <HI>Cajonges,</HI> called, <HI>Oheee.</HI></P>
<P>The whole Number of Sachims answered, <HI>Heeeeee Hogh.</HI></P>
<P>The principal Sachim of the <HI>Sinnekes,</HI> called, <HI>Oheee.</HI></P>
<P>The whole Number of Sachims answered, <HI>Heeeeee Hogh.</HI></P>
<P><HI>October</HI> 4<HI>th.</HI> Cloaths were delivered out to the Companys, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eing the gratuity of the Assembly to those Souldiers that had <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erved the preceeding Winter, being of the 500 <HI>l.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Oct.</HI> 5. The Companies were mustered by <HI>M. Clarkson,</HI> <ABBR>Esq</ABBR> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ecretary, and afterwards the Oaths administred to them, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>very man had two Dollars paid him of the 4 <HI>d. per day</HI> likewise <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rante<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> by the Assembly. The Money was taken up upon <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>redit the Tax not being paid, nor the first Moyety payable <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll the 29th of <HI>September</HI> last.</P>
<P>His Excellency, on the Head of each Company, did en∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ourage the Men, and told them not to believe the Reports of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctious disaffected People, promising, That the 4 <HI>d. per Day</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hould be paid into their own hands.</P>
<P>In the afternoon the same day, his Excellency imbarqued for <HI>New-York,</HI> being attended to the Shore by the Mayor, Recorder, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ldermen and Common Council, with the Souldiers and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rain-bands in Arms. And having recommended to the Ma∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>strates of the City and Officers to be vigilant and amicable, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d to unite in their Endeavours for the Defence of the place, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ok leave of them about three a Clock afternoon.</P>
<P><HI>Oct.</HI> 9. <HI>Fryday</HI> Morning his Excellency arrived at <HI>New-York.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>David Jamison, Cl. Concilij.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

