<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2005-08-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Converted 270 $-groups to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N00651">
<STC T="E">790</STC>
<STC T="W">m1099</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99031792</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="000790_0000_0FAA547162F5F380"/>
<PB REF="000790_0001_0FAA5471826B6668"/>
<P>Ecclesiastes.</P>
<P>The LIFE OF THE <HI>Reverend</HI> &amp; <HI>Excellent,</HI> Jonathan Mitchel; A <HI>Pastor</HI> of the CHURCH, AND A <HI>Glory</HI> of the COLLEDGE, IN CAMBRIDGE, NEW-ENGLAND.</P>
<P>Written by <HI>COTTON MATHER.</HI></P>
<Q><L>—Simul et Jucunda et Idone<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dicere Vitae,</L>
<L>Lectorem Delectando Simul atque monendo.</L></Q>
<P>MASSACHƲSET; Printed by <HI>B. Green,</HI> and <HI>J. Allen.</HI> Sold at the Booksellers Shops in <HI>BOSTON.</HI> 1697.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB N="3" REF="000790_0002_0FAA547281712FB8" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>The Epistle Dedicatory. To the Church at <HI>CAMBRIDGE</HI> in <HI>New-England,</HI> AND To the <HI>STUDENTS</HI> of the <HI>Colledge</HI> there.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Right Worshipfull, Reverend, and dearly Beloved.</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>THERE have been few Churches in the World so <HI>lifted up to Hea∣ven</HI> in Respect of a Succession of Supereminent Ministers of the Gospel, as the Church in <HI>Cambridge</HI> ha's been. <HI>Hooker, Shepard, Mitchel, Oakes</HI> (all of them <HI>yours</HI>) were <HI>Great Lights.</HI> You know that if <HI>Light</HI> ha's been brought into a Room, when it is Removed, the Place becomes <HI>Darker,</HI> than if never any such <HI>Light</HI> had been there. A Learned Pen in an <HI>Epistle Dedicatory</HI> to the Inhabitants of <HI>Boston</HI> in <HI>Lincolnshire</HI> puts them in mind of what an Hap∣py People they once were,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Dr. <HI>Tuckney</HI> E∣pistle prefixed to Mr. <HI>Cotton</HI> on Ecclesiastes.</NOTE> while under the Teaching of Mr. <HI>Cotton</HI>
<PB N="4" REF="000790_0003_0FAA5472FA573DE0"/>
who was from them removed to plant Churches for Christ, in this <HI>American Desart</HI>: And pray's them to Consider,
<Q>That as Empires and King∣doms, so particular Churches have had their Periods. <HI>Bethel</HI> has proved a <HI>Beth-haven</HI>: In after times we find young profane Mockers in <HI>Bethel,</HI> and scornful Neuters in <HI>Penuel.</HI> Go to <HI>Shiloh</HI>; think of the sometimes Glorious Church∣es in <HI>Asia,</HI> says he. And he adds, That he had on purpose visited some places, where God had before Planted His Church, and a Faithful Mi∣nistry, to see, if He could Discern any Footsteps and Remembrances of such a Mercy, and <HI>Lo, they were all overgrown with Thorns, and Nettles had over covered the Face thereof, and the Stone-wall thereof is Broken down.</HI> And as he further well observes, when the Lord has been provoked to remove the Candlestick, He is very hardly in∣duced to Restore it again. The <HI>Ark</HI> never re∣turned to the same Place, from whence it was in a way of Judgment removed, and the <HI>Glory of the Lord,</HI> when after its Gradual Removes, was at last quite gone from the <HI>First Temple,</HI> was not Restored in the <HI>Second,</HI> till Christ's <HI>First Co∣ming,</HI> nor will it be in this their Rejection, till His <HI>Second.</HI></Q>
Mercy forbid that such Things as these should be verified in <HI>New-England,</HI> or in <HI>Cambridge!</HI> That this may not be your Case, it concerns you not wantonly to <HI>play</HI> or <HI>fight</HI> by the <HI>Light</HI> yet remaining, but to make the Best Im∣provement of your present Advantages, giving all
<PB N="5" REF="000790_0004_0FAA5473B34D6C40"/>
due Encouragement to that Worthy Person, who is now over you in the Lord.</P>
<P>Concerning your Famous Pastor, <HI>Mitchel,</HI> I confess, I had the Happiness of a special Intima∣cy with him, in his <HI>Life</HI> time, nor do I know any one <HI>Death</HI> (that of natural Relations except∣ed) that ever has been so Grievous and Afflictive to my Spirit, as was <HI>his</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> reason of his Emi∣nent Parts and Piety <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> an happy Influence on all these <HI>Churche<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> Many of them fare the better at this Day, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the Preachers whom they are now In<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>cted by whilst <HI>Students</HI> at the <HI>Colledge</HI> lived un<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> his Ministry. The <HI>Colledge, Cambridge, New<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>gland</HI> may Glory, that ever such an One <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his Education there! As for the Description o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is <HI>Life,</HI> by my SON Emitted herewith, I have nothing to say concerning the <HI>Writer,</HI> or this Endeavour of his, because of my Relation to him; Only, that it is what he could Collect, whet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er by Informations from those that knew that Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lent man, or from his private Manuscripts, w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ich he had the perusal of. It is not without <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Providence of Christ, that it should be Committed to the <HI>Press, <HI>at such a Time</HI>,</HI> when there are Agitations about some <HI>Dis∣ciplinary Questions</HI> amongst your selves. What the Judgment of that <HI>Man of God</HI> was, you have in the subsequent Relation of his Life presented to your view.</P>
<P>The Original Manuscript Written by Mr. <HI>Mitchel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> own Hand, I have by me. Whether
<PB N="6" REF="000790_0005_0FAA5474726FF108"/>
he committed his Thoughts to Writing, with any Design of Publication, or for the satisfaction of some Persons in a more private way, I know not: but it is now Evident, that when his Spirit was inclined thereunto, Heaven designed his Medita∣tions should be brought into <HI>publick view.</HI> Whilst he was Living, you that were of his Flock, had (and considering his great Worth and Wisdom, it would have been a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eproach to you, if you had not had) in high <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of his Judgment. <HI>Being Dead he yet speaketh</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou, out of his Grave. Those of you that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ving Remembrance of him, in your Hearts, will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> discern some∣thing of Mr. <HI>Mitchels</HI> Spirit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the way of his Arguing. He does therein <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ccording to his wonted manner) express him <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with gre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <HI>Cau∣tion</HI> and <HI>Prudence,</HI> avoiding <HI>Extre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/></HI> in the Con∣troverted Subject. It cannot be denied; but that there has been an Error in some Churches, who have made this or that <HI>Mode</HI> to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Divine Insti∣tution,</HI> which Christ has not made <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o be so: And that there has been an unjustify <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Severity,</HI> in Imposing <HI>Circumstantials</HI> not In<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ted, whereby some truly Gracious Souls have b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en Discouraged from Offering themselves to joyn in Fellowship with such Churches. Thus it has been, when an Oral Declaration of <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Repentance</HI> has been Enjoyned on all Communicants, and that before the <HI>whole Congregation</HI>; when as many an Hum∣ble Pious Soul has not been Gifted with such <HI>Confidence.</HI> So likewise has it been, when an Ex∣act
<PB N="7" REF="000790_0006_0FAA5475552694D0"/>
Account of the <HI>Time</HI> and <HI>Manner</HI> of <HI>Conversion</HI> has been Required: Whenas there have been mul∣titudes of true Believers (such especially as have been advantaged with a <HI>Religious Education</HI>) that the Seed of <HI>Grace</HI> has sprung up in their Souls,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Mr. Baxter, of present Baptism.</HI> p. 129.133.</NOTE> <HI>they know not how</HI> Mark 4.27. Mr. <HI>Baxter</HI> relates, that he was once at a Meeting of many Christians as Eminent for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> most in the Land, of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> were <HI>Ministers</HI> of Gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame; And it was desi∣red, that every one <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hould give an Account of the <HI>Time</HI> and <HI>Manner</HI> of his Conversion, and there was but <HI>One</HI> of them all, that could do it. And (says he) <HI>I A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>r from my Heart, that I neither know the Day <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Year, when I began to be s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n∣cere.</HI> For Churches, then to expect an Account of <HI>that</HI> from all, that they Receive into their Fellowship, is <HI>Unscriptural,</HI> and <HI>Unreasonable.</HI> Ne∣vertheless, it concerns them to Beware of the o∣ther <HI>Extream <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f Laxness</HI> in Admission unto the Lord's <HI>Holy T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>e.</HI> You know that your Pastor <HI>Mitchel</HI> had a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Latitude</HI> in his Judgment as to the Subject of <HI>Baptism</HI> (as also Dr <HI>Ames,</HI> Mr. <HI>Cotton,</HI> and others of the <HI>Congregational Perswasi∣on</HI> had,) but as to Admissions to the Sacrament of the <HI>Lord's Supper.</HI> I know no man, that was more Conscientiously careful to keep <HI>unqualified persons</HI> from partaking therein than was <HI>he.</HI> As for this or that <HI>Mode</HI> in <HI>Examining</HI> of Persons, that offer themselves to be Communicants in
<PB N="8" REF="000790_0007_0FAA5476164C09D0"/>
our Churches, whether it shall be by a more continued <HI>Relation</HI> of the Work of Grace, in their Hearts, or <HI>by Questions</HI> and <HI>Answers</HI> (as was pra∣ctised in the Church at <HI>Hartford</HI> in Mr. <HI>Hookers</HI> time, and which may possibly be as Edifying a way, as the former) or whether the Persons de∣signing to partake in the <HI>Lord's Supper,</HI> shall De∣clare their Experiences <HI>Orally,</HI> or in Writing, are <HI>Prudentials,</HI> which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Lord has left unto Church∣es to Determin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> find most expedient for their own <HI>Edifica<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>.</HI> Nevertheless the <HI>Sub∣stance</HI> of the Thing (viz. <HI>ei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>r a Relation, as 'tis called, or an Equivalent</HI>) ought to be insisted on. Churches <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> bound in Duty to Enquire, not on∣ly into the <HI>Knowledge</HI> and <HI>Ortho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>xy,</HI> but into the <HI>Spiritual Estate</HI> of those whom <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Receive into full Communion in all the Ordinances of Christ. Some have thought, that such Qualifications are not to be expected from <HI>Children</HI> born in the Church, as from <HI>Strangers</HI>; but they never had that Opinion out of the Scriptur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, which says expresly concerning them that wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d Eat the Pas∣sover, that, <HI>There is One Law to him that is Home∣born, and to the Stranger.</HI> Exod. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 49. Numb. 9.14. Wherefore in the P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tform of Dis∣cipline it is said,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Capt.</HI> 12. § 7.</NOTE> <HI>The like Trial is to be Required of such Members of the Church as were born in the same, or Received their Membership, and were Baptised in their Infancy, or Minority, by virtue of the Covenant of their Parents, when being grown up to years of Discretion, they shall desire to be
<PB N="9" REF="000790_0008_0FAA5479941B6660"/>
made Partakers of the Lords Table, unto which, be∣cause Holy Things are not to be given to the Unwor∣thy, therefore it is Requisite, that those as well as others should come to their Trial and Examination, and ma∣nifest their Faith and Repentance by an open Professi∣on thereof, before they are Received to the Lord's Sup∣per, and otherwise not to be Admitted thereunto</HI>; These are the words, in the <HI>Platform of Discipline</HI> agreed unto by the Elders and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the Chur∣ches in the Synod at <HI>Cambrid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI>▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> which <HI>Synod,</HI> were Mr. <HI>Cotton,</HI> Mr. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>gers,</HI> Mr. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, Learned and Aged Divines, b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>des many others of Great Eminency. It is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Opinion of <HI>men,</HI> but the <HI>Scripture</HI> which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> decide the Controversy. Nevertheless, the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>dgment of those <HI>Eminent Di∣vines</HI> who had d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ply searched into these Matters, is not to be slighted. Nor is the <HI>Private Senti∣ment</HI> of this on that person, to be laid in the Bal∣lance, with the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>udgment of a <HI>Synod,</HI> consisting of Persons, of far <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reater Authority than any youn∣ger ones pretend<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d to be of a contrary Opinion. Nor is there wei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ht in that Allegation, that when a man declares hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> own <HI>Experiences,</HI> he <HI>Testifies con∣cerning himself,</HI> and therefore his Testimony is of no validity. By <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> same reason it may be said, Churches are not to Examine those, that Essay to Joyn themselves to them, about the soundness of their <HI>Faith.</HI> For they may (as <HI>Arius</HI> did) pro∣fess, that they <HI>Believe</HI> Articles of Faith, which God knows, they do not <HI>Believe,</HI> nor is there any thing but their <HI>own Testimony</HI> to prove that they
<PB N="10" REF="000790_0009_0FAA547A66286EC0"/>
do <HI>believe</HI> as they <HI>profess.</HI> But above all, their Notion is to be Rejected, as a <HI>Church corrupting Principle,</HI> who Assert that the <HI>Sacrament</HI> is a <HI>Con∣verting Ordinance. Papists, Erastians,</HI> and some o∣thers, whom I forbear to mention have so taught; but their <HI>Heterodoxy</HI> has been abundantly Refu∣ted, not only by <HI>Congregational</HI> Writers, such as Mr. <HI>John Beverly</HI> against <HI>Timpson,</HI> but by Worthy Authors of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Perswasion, particular∣ly by Mr. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> his <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rons Rod,</HI> Dr. <HI>Drake</HI> in his Answer to Mr. <HI>Hump<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s,</HI> and Mr. <HI>Vines,</HI> in his Treatis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of the <HI>Lord's <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>pper.</HI> If the Sacra∣ment were appointed to be <HI>Converting Ordinance,</HI> then the most <HI>Scandalous</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in the World, yea, <HI>Heathen</HI> people ought to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it Administred unto them, for we may not wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>hold from them the Means appointed for their <HI>Conversion.</HI> The Scripture says, <HI>Let a man Examine himself, and so let him Eat of that Bread.</HI> 1 Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 11.28. which clearly intimates, that if upon <HI>Examination,</HI> he finds himself in a State of <HI>Sin</HI> and Unregeneracy, he ought <HI>not</HI> to <HI>Eat of that Brea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></P>
<P>Blessed Mr. <HI>Mitchel</HI> would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>requently Assert, That if it should pass for Current Doctrine in <HI>New England,</HI> That all persons <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rthodox in Judg∣ment,</HI> as to matters of <HI>Faith,</HI> and <HI>not Scandalous in Life,</HI> ought to be admitted to partake of the <HI>Lords Supper,</HI> without any Examination, concern∣ing the <HI>Work of Saving Grace in their Hearts,</HI> it would be a <HI>Real Apostacy</HI> from former Principles, and a <HI>Degeneracy</HI> from the <HI>Reformation,</HI> which we
<PB N="11" REF="000790_0010_0FAA547A864028A0"/>
had attained unto. I am willing upon this Occa∣sion, to bear my Testimony to the <HI>present Truth</HI>▪ and to Leave it upon Record unto Posterity; not knowing how soon the Lord Jesus may by one Providence or other (of which I have had several Warnings) remove me from my <HI>present Station</HI> among these Churches. The Arguments which have induced me to Believe and Testify, as now I do, are such as these.</P>
<P N="1">1. Time was when <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>New-England</HI> believed there was <HI>clean Scripture</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for the pra∣ctice we plead for. Particularly that Scripture, Psal. 40.10. <HI>I have not hidden thy Righteousness from the great Congre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ation.</HI> And that, Psal. 66.16. <HI>Come and hear all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that fear God, and I will de∣clare what he ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> done for my Soul.</HI> And that Scripture, 1 Pet. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.15. <HI>be ready always to give an answer to every man that asks you a reason of the hope that is in you,</HI> does by just consequence inti∣mate as much as what we assert. Some have been bold to say▪ that since the Apostle in the place alledged, speaks of Believers <HI>Apologizing</HI> for their Hope before Persecutors, it is an abuse of Scripture from th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ce to infer, that any thing of that nature ought <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o be done for the satisfaction of Churches. But Renowned Mr. <HI>Hooker</HI> in a Manuscript which I have seen, answering the Objections of some who disliked the practice of these Churches, in Examining and Inquiring into the Spiritual Estate of their Communicants, (es∣pecially their requiring an account from the Chil∣dren
<PB N="12" REF="000790_0011_0FAA547B8ABBE8D8"/>
of the Church) argues Judiciously that if Christians are bound to give an account of the grounds of their hope to Persecutors, much more to Churches that shall desire it. So Mr. <HI>Shepard,</HI> the faithful and famous Pastor of the Church in <HI>Cambridge,</HI> in his Answer to Mr. <HI>Ball.</HI> And to the same purpose, in the Platform of Discipline it is inferred, that men must declare and shew their Repentance, and Faith▪ and Effectual Calling, because <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> reason of a well-grounded hope. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> any man <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o charge these Wor∣thies of the Lord, and the <HI>Platform of Discipline,</HI> which abusing Scripture when they made such an Inference, is a very unbe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ming presumption. It was formerly thought, that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cripture Examples are not wanting to warrant th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> practice of our Churches in this matter, since <HI>Jo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> required those whom he admitted to his Baptism, to make a Confession of their Sins. And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Apostles ex∣pected a Declaration of their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>epentance from such as they admitted into the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rimitive Church. <HI>Acts</HI> 2.38. And <HI>Philip</HI> Examin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> the <HI>Eunuch</HI> con∣cerning the sincerity of his Fai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>. <HI>Acts</HI> 8.37.</P>
<P N="2">2. <HI>That Principle which tends <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o bring persons not duly qualified, to partake in Holy Things, must needs be displeasing to the Holy Lord Jesus Christ.</HI> He would have his Servants to <HI>Distinguish betwixt the precious and the vile.</HI> Jer. 15.19. And to <HI>Turn a∣way</HI> from such as have only <HI>the Form, and not the Power of Godliness</HI> in them. 2 Tim. 3.5. they that have only a <HI>Doctrinal Knowledge,</HI> and an <HI>External
<PB N="13" REF="000790_0012_0FAA547C012D6FF8"/>
Conversation</HI> free from Scandal, without Regene∣ration. have no more than a <HI>Form of Godliness.</HI> If Christians should not make such persons their <HI>Fa∣miliars,</HI> certainly they ought not to Admit them to their <HI>Sacred Communion.</HI> It is a very solemn word, which the Lord has spoken, saying, <HI>You have brought into my Sanctuary Uncircumcised in Heart, to be in my Sanctuary to pollute it; even in my House, when you Offer the Bread and the Blood. No Stranger Uncircumcised in Hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ll enter into my Sanctuary.</HI> Ezek. 44▪7, 9. Tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> man does but <HI>defile</HI> the Sanctuary of the Lord, that has not the <HI>Water of Separation</HI> (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Blood of Christ through Faith) <HI>Sprinkled upo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> him.</HI> Numb. 19.20. But this Principle or Position, That persons are to be ad∣mitted to the <HI>Table</HI> of the Lord, without Enqui∣ring into their <HI>Regeneration,</HI> tends to bring the <HI>Uncircumcised in Heart,</HI> into the <HI>Sanctuary.</HI> If Churches should neglect all Examinations concer∣ning the <HI>Orthod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y</HI> of those they Receive into their Communion; would not that have a Natural Ten¦dency to bring <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eterodox,</HI> and it may be <HI>Heretical</HI> persons into their Communion! By a <HI>Parity of Reason,</HI> the Omitting all <HI>Enquiries,</HI> as to the <HI>Spiri∣tual Experiences</HI> of them that come to the Table of the Lord, has a Tendency to fill the Sanctu∣ary with those, who never had any <HI>Experimental Knowledge</HI> of the Things of God.</P>
<P N="3">3. <HI>The Church ought to know, as far as men can Judge, that the Persons whom they Admit to the Lords Table are fit, and have a right to be there.</HI> Now
<PB N="14" REF="000790_0013_0FAA547CB67B6340"/>
none are meet to partake of the <HI>Lords Supper,</HI> ex∣cepting such as have experienced a <HI>Saving <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Grace.</HI> They must be such as can and will, <HI>Exa∣mine themselves.</HI> 1 Cor. 11.28. And therefore must have the <HI>Matter</HI> of <HI>Self-Examination,</HI> which is <HI>Faith, Repentance, and Love,</HI> and <HI>other Graces.</HI> Thus it was in the Primitive Apostolical Church, Acts 2.47. <HI>The Lord added to the Church dayly, such as should be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI> Churches are to receive such as the <HI>Lord <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>eived</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 14.1, 2, 3. Such as are <HI>United <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,</HI> 1 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> 12.27. 1 Thes. 1.1. <HI>Living Stones</HI> must be in that <HI>Building,</HI> 1 Pet. 2.5. Made ready by a work of Divine Grace on and in them, before they are laid where; of which the <HI>Prepared Materials</HI> in <HI>Solomons</HI> Temple were a Type, 1 King. 6.7. They ought to be <HI>Saints,</HI> and <HI>Eaith∣full in Christ Jesus.</HI> Eph. 1.1. How shall the Churches <HI>know,</HI> that the Persons who offer them∣selves to their Communion are such, unless they pass under their <HI>Trial.</HI> Rev. 2.2. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a man claim <HI>Right</HI> to a Priviledge, and yet sheweth no sufficient <HI>Reason,</HI> he ought to be debarred u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>til he can some way, or other prove his <HI>Claim.</HI> It is true, the Judgment of Churches is <HI>fallible</HI>▪ Grace being a <HI>Secret</HI> Thing, hid in the Heart▪ only <HI>Christ</HI> seeth it: Churches cannot always discern the <HI>Tares</HI> from the <HI>Wheat.</HI> Nevertheless, they may not <HI>will∣ingly</HI> receive in <HI>Hypocrites. Bellarmin</HI> himself is fain to Confess, as much as that comes to. When such were found in Churches in the Apostolical Times, it is said, that they <HI>crept in privily &amp; una∣wares.</HI>
<PB N="15" REF="000790_0014_0FAA547D8C342540"/>
Gal. 2.4. Jude 4. <HI>v.</HI> Which intimates unto us, that they did not <HI>willingly</HI> admit such into their Fellowship. When the Enemy sowed <HI>Tares</HI> in the Field, a Culpable <HI>Sleeping</HI> in those, that should have been more Watchful was the cause of it. Math. 13.25. They who object, that we are bound in <HI>Charity</HI> to believe, that the Persons, who offer themselves to our Communion, are Regene∣rate, without ever making any <HI>Enquiry</HI> into their Spiritual Estate, may with as good Reason affirm, that we are bound in Charity to believe, that they are <HI>sound in the Faith,</HI> without <HI>Examining</HI> them a∣bout that matter. A <HI>Rational Charity,</HI> grounded upon <HI>Evidence,</HI> and not a <HI>Blind Charity</HI> is the Rule according to which Churches are to proceed.</P>
<P N="4">4. <HI>That Practice, which Christ has owned with His special Blessing and Presence, ought not to be Decryed as an Humane Invention, but rather owned as a Divine Institution.</HI> Was not the Lord's Blessing <HI>Aaron's</HI> Rod an Effectual Demonstration, that his Ministry had a Divine Approbation? Is not <HI>Paul's</HI> calling to the Ministry, and <HI>Peter's</HI> also, proved from this Argument, that God owned &amp; <HI>Blessed</HI> them both? 1 Cor. 9.1, 2. Gal. 2.7, 8, 9. That Christ has owned His Churches, in their <HI>Enquiries</HI> into the Spiritual Estate of such as they admit into their Communion with His special Gracious Presence, is most certain. Have not <HI>some</HI> been <HI>Converted</HI> by hearing <HI>others</HI> give an Account of their Conversi∣on! How <HI>many</HI> have been Comforted, and how
<PB N="16" REF="000790_0015_0FAA547E2D70E388"/>
<HI>many</HI> Edified thereby! which proveth, that this Practice is Lawful and Laudable, and that to <HI>Stigmatize</HI> it so, as some have done is not pleasing to the Lord.</P>
<P N="5">5. <HI>To use all Lawful means to keep Church Com∣munion pure, is a Duty incumbent upon all Churches, and most eminently on Churches in New England.</HI> It is known to the World, that <HI>Church Reformation,</HI> and <HI>Purity</HI> as to all Administrations therein, was the Thing designed by our Fathers, when they followed the Lord into this Wilderness: And therefore Degeneracy in that Respect would be a Greater Evil in us, than in any People. We shall not Act like <HI>Wise Children,</HI> if we seek to <HI>pull down with our Hands,</HI> That House (or any <HI>Pillar</HI>-Prin∣ciple, whereon it is founded) which our Wise Fa∣thers have built. The <HI>Debasing th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>' matter of Par∣ticular Churches</HI> must needs Corrupt them. A Learned and Renowned Author has Evinced, <HI>That the Letting go this Principle, That Particular Churches ought to Consist of Regenerate Persons▪</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Owen. Theol. Lib. 6. cap. 8.</NOTE> <HI>brought in the Great Apostasy of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Christian Church.</HI> The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay to prevent the like <HI>Apostasy</HI> in these Churches, is to Require an <HI>Account</HI> of those, that offer themselves to Communion therein, concern∣ing the <HI>Work of God on their Souls,</HI> as well as con∣cerning their <HI>Knowledge</HI> and <HI>Belief.</HI> If once this Practice and Principle of Truth be deserted, <HI>A World of unqualifyed Persons</HI> will soon fill, and pester and corrupt the House of God, and cause Him to
<PB N="17" REF="000790_0016_0FAA547EEF1B20B8"/>
<HI>go far off from His Sanctuary.</HI> We may then justly fear that these <HI>Golden Candlesticks,</HI> will be no long∣er so, but become <HI>Dross,</HI> and <HI>Tin,</HI> and <HI>Reprobate Silver,</HI> until <HI>the Lord has rejected them.</HI> Let us Dread to have an hand, in causing it to be so! It is a solemn Passage which Mr. <HI>Cotton</HI> (whom Dr. <HI>Goodwin</HI> calls the <HI>Apostle of this Age</HI>) has in his Judicious Treatise of <HI>the Holiness of Church Mem∣bers. p.</HI> 60. <HI>Methinks</HI> (saies he) <HI>the Servants of God should Tremble to Erect such a State of the visi∣ble Church, in Hypocrisy and Formal Profession, as whose very Foundation threatneth certain Dissolution and Desolation.</HI> True it is, That we may not <HI>Do Evil,</HI> that <HI>Good may come of it.</HI> We may not Use any <HI>Unlawful Practice</HI> to prevent Impurity, as to the matter of our Churches But no man can say, That the Practice we plead for is <HI>Sinful.</HI> If then the Use of it may (by the Bl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssing of Christ) be a means to keep our Churches and Communion pure,, why should it be laid aside? Mr. <HI>Mitchel</HI> in a Manuscript of his, which I have seen, has these weighty words.
<Q>The O∣ver enlarging of full Communion or Admission of persons thereunto, upon slight Qualifications without insisting upon the Practical and Spiri∣tual part of Religion, will not only Lose the Power of Godliness, but in a little time, bring in Profaneness, and Ruine the Churches these two ways. 1. Election of Ministers will soon be carried by a formal, looser sort. 2. The Ex∣ercise of Discipline, will by this means be ren∣dred
<PB N="18" REF="000790_0017_0FAA54811BB00728"/>
impossible. Discipline falling, Profaneness riseth like a Flood. For the major part want∣ing zeal against Sin, will foster Licentiousness. It is not setting down good Rules and Directi∣ons, that will Salve it: For the Specification of Government, is from men, not from Laws. Let never so good a Form of Government be a∣greed upon, it will soon degenerate, if the Instruments (or men) that manage it, be not Good.</Q>
Blessed <HI>Mitchel!</HI> These are thy words; This was thy Spirit!</P>
<P N="6">6. <HI>In the Primitive &amp; Purest Times of the Church, there was great strictness used in Examining such as were admitted to Sacraments, concerning the Sincerity of their Repentan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> towards God, and their Faith in the Lord Jesus Christ.</HI> There are who pretend, That this is a <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>actice,</HI> begun by a few <HI>Se∣paratists</HI> in <HI>Amsterdam,</HI> not an Hundred years since. But such persons discover their <HI>Ignorance,</HI> and that they are unacquainted and unstudied in <HI>Ecclesiastical Story. Justin Martyr</HI> (who lived 150 years after Christ) in his Second Apology for the Christians, writeth, That they did <HI>Exa∣mine such as were Admitted to their Communion, whe∣ther they were able to conform themselves in all things to the Word and Will of God.</HI> If we would know what Things were practised by the Churches in the Primitive Times, the Writings of <HI>Tertullian,</HI> and <HI>Cyprian,</HI> (as Learned <HI>Usher</HI> has truly observ∣ed) give us the clearest discovery thereof. It is evident from them, that in those Dayes, there
<PB N="19" REF="000790_0018_0FAA5481E32E1698"/>
was rather too much <HI>Rigidity,</HI> than too much <HI>Laxness,</HI> in their Admission to Sacraments. They would keep men, who were <HI>Catechumens</HI> &amp; <HI>Com∣petentes</HI> a long time, before they did receive them into full Communion in the Church. They Re∣quired not only a Profession of <HI>Faith,</HI> and a Con∣fession of <HI>Sins,</HI> but a Submission to a severe <HI>Scru∣tiny</HI> concerning their <HI>Sincerity</HI> therein. <HI>Fiunt Scrutinia, ut saepius explorentur,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Alcuinu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></NOTE> <HI>an post Renunciationem Satanae sacra verba datae Fidei radicitus Corde defixerint.</HI> They were to be Examined again and again, to find out, whether the <HI>Words</HI> of the Faith they professed, were indeed fixed in their <HI>Hearts. Cyprian</HI> in his third Epistle sayes, <HI>Mihi labor est persuadere fratri∣bus ut recipiendis Consentiant, Vix Plebi persuadeo, ut ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es patiantur admitti, quia nec cum vera paenitentia venerant.</HI> That he could not easily perswade the <HI>Brethren</HI> in <HI>Churches,</HI> to consent to the Admis∣sion of such Persons to their Communion, of whose <HI>Sincere Repentance,</HI> there was any doubt. <HI>Origen</HI> declares, as much as that amounts to. When in after Ages, Churches degenerated, <HI>Chrysostom</HI> complains, that by Admitting ungodly men into the Church, they had <HI>filled the Temple with Beasts,</HI> and he professed, that he would sooner choose to have his <HI>Right hand</HI> cut off, than Administer the Sacrament to a <HI>Known wicked man.</HI> It is well known, that the <HI>Waldenses,</HI> amonst whom Religion was preserved, during the Reign of <HI>Popery,</HI> were strict in this matter. And so were the <HI>Bohemian</HI>
<PB N="20" REF="000790_0019_0FAA5482C3F411D8"/>
Brethren: <HI>Commenius</HI> testifies concerning them, that they used a <HI>Diligent Exploration,</HI> concerning the <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Repen∣tance</HI> of their Communicants,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ratio disciplin. Fratrum. Bohem p.</HI> 44. <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE> lest haply it should be only <HI>Superficiary</HI> and <HI>Fallacious.</HI> There was an <HI>Ex∣amen Conscientiarum</HI> used amongst them. It must be acknowledged, that in the <HI>Protestant Reformati∣on,</HI> there has been a Great <HI>Neglect</HI> and <HI>Defect,</HI> as to what concerns the Discipline and Government of Christ in His Church. As the <HI>Apostasy</HI> was gradual, so ha's the <HI>Reformation</HI> been. And there was (as Dr. <HI>Owen</HI> well observes) a wise Providence in ordering it to be so.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Dr.</HI> Owen, <HI>of the Nature of a Gospel Church p.</HI> 13.</NOTE>
<Q>For had the <HI>First Re∣formers</HI> set themselves to re∣move out of the Church all such as were unmeet for it's Communion, and to have Reduced things to their <HI>Primitive Institution,</HI> by Reason of the <HI>Paucity</HI> of the Number of such Church Members, the Endeavour for a <HI>General Reformation</HI> of Doctrine and Worship would have been obstructed. Hence it comes to pass, That the <HI>Reformation</HI> of the Church, as unto the <HI>Mat∣ter</HI> of it, was not attempted, until <HI>Calvin</HI> set up his Discipline in <HI>Geneva,</HI> which has filled the World with Clamours against him to this day. In most other places the <HI>Matter</HI> or <HI>Members</HI> of Churches were, as to their Lives and Conversa∣tion as bad as the <HI>Papists.</HI></Q>
Nevertheless, Emi∣nent Divines of the <HI>Reformation,</HI> in this and the
<PB N="21" REF="000790_0020_0FAA54844959A570"/>
last Century, have approved of that which we are pleading for. <HI>Beza</HI> laments the <HI>Re∣misness</HI> of <HI>Protestant Churches</HI> in not taking more care about the Qualifi∣cations of their Members;<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Beza. Epist.</HI> 14.</NOTE> concluding that there will never be such a <HI>Reformation</HI> as ought to be en∣deavoured after, <HI>nisi a Conversione Cordium Initium Instaurationis sumatur,</HI> except men with <HI>Converted Hearts,</HI> be laid in the <HI>Foundation. Bucer</HI> finds fault with the <HI>English Churches</HI> for their Admitting Children who had been Baptised, unto the <HI>Lords Supper,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Bucer. Script. Anglio. Cap</HI> 17. <HI>p.</HI> 482, 483.</NOTE> upon too <HI>low Terms.</HI> He says, there should be <HI>manifest Signs of Regeneration in them first: That they should appear to be such as had upon their Hearts a sense of the word of God, and that they did use Secret Prayer</HI> &amp;c. But how should such things be known concerning them without Enquiry into their <HI>Spiritual State! Chamier</HI> commends the Strictness used in the <HI>Primitive Times,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Chamier de Baptismo L.</HI> 5. <HI>cap.</HI> 15.</NOTE> in <HI>Ex∣amining</HI> those that desired to Joyn to the Chuch, <HI>ne quantum fieri pote∣rit lateant Simones,</HI> that so <HI>Simon Magus</HI> may not creep into the Church, if it were possible to prevent it. <HI>Luther</HI> did at last sorrow∣fully bewail it, That he began his <HI>Reformation</HI> with such <HI>Promiscuous Admissions</HI> to the <HI>Table</HI> of the Lord, heartily wishing, that he had Taught and Practised such a <HI>Church Discipline,</HI> as that which was professed by the <HI>Bohemian Brethren. Chemnitius</HI>
<PB N="22" REF="000790_0021_0FAA5484F3DCC778"/>
wisheth that the <HI>Strictness</HI> used among the Anci∣ents in the <HI>Probation</HI> of Communicants were re∣stored and revived in the Churches of the <HI>Refor∣mation.</HI> His Godly desire and hope that in Time it will be so, is approved of by <HI>Gerhard</HI> in his com∣mon place, <HI>de Sacra Caena.</HI></P>
<P>Some of those that are called <HI>Presbyterians</HI> fully concur with us, as to the <HI>Substance</HI> of what we plead for. When Mr. <HI>Norton</HI> in his Answer unto <HI>Apollenius,</HI> does assert, That four things are to be required of those, that desire Admission into Church-Fellowship. 1. A Confession of <HI>Faith.</HI> 2. <HI>A De∣claration of their Experience concerning a Work of Faith.</HI> 3. A blameless <HI>Conversation.</HI> 4. Professed <HI>Subject∣ion</HI> to the Gospel, and the order of it. That Learned and worthy Professor of Divinity, in the University of <HI>Leyden,</HI> Dr. <HI>Hornbeck,</HI> declares his Concurrence with him therein,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Hornbeck E∣pistola ad Du∣raum p.</HI> 299.</NOTE> and that, in these Particu∣lars, those of the <HI>Congregational way,</HI> agree with some other <HI>Refor∣med Churches.</HI> To my certain knowledge, Emi∣nent Ministers of the <HI>Presbyterian</HI> Perswasion, in <HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ndo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> Examine their Communicants (before they admit them to partake with them, at the Lords Table) concerning their <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Repen∣tance.</HI> And so (notwithstanding what is <HI>pleaded</HI> for by the Godly Learned Mr. <HI>Rutherford</HI>) some do in <HI>Scotland,</HI> as divers worthy Ministers of that Nation, have assured me.</P>
<P>The Difference as to this Matter, between a
<PB N="23" REF="000790_0022_0FAA5485CFB41888"/>
<HI>Presbyterian</HI> and a <HI>Congregational</HI> man, (who are nevertheless <HI>United Brethren</HI>) is this. There is no <HI>Congregational</HI> man, but he <HI>reports to the Church</HI> something of what the person desiring Commu∣nion with them, has Related to him; which the <HI>Presbyterian</HI> does not, only Declares his own satis∣faction, and giveth the Brethren a Liberty to ob∣ject against the Conversation of the <HI>Admittendi.</HI> I know <HI>Presbyterians,</HI> who are stricter in their Ex∣aminations and Admissions, than some <HI>Congrega∣tional</HI> men. It appears therefore, that such <HI>Enqui∣ries</HI> into the <HI>Spiritual Estate</HI> of them, who are to be Admitted unto full Communion, in all the Or∣dinances of the Gospel, is no <HI>Singular</HI> or <HI>Novel</HI> Practice: Nothing but what is confirmed by <HI>Re∣verend Antiquity,</HI> and has been strenuously Assert∣ed by the Great <HI>Reformers,</HI> both of the former, and this present Age. Whether the <HI>Brethren,</HI> as well as the <HI>Elders</HI> should not be concerned as <HI>Judges,</HI> concerning the Qualifications of those whom they Receive into their Communion, is a∣nother <HI>Question,</HI> which I shall not here enlare up∣on. It is certain, that in the <HI>Primitive Ages</HI> of the Church, they had that Liberty; otherwise <HI>Cyprian</HI> would never have said, <HI>Vix Plebi persuadeo ut Tales patiantur admitti,</HI> &amp;c. And elsewhere con∣fessed his Obligations, and Resolutions, <HI>Nihil sine consensu plebis, privata sententia gerere.</HI></P>
<P>It is also certain, that this is an avowed princi∣ple of all who are esteemed <HI>Congregational</HI> In the Declaration of the <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Order</HI> owned
<PB N="24" REF="000790_0023_0FAA54867698CE80"/>
and practised in <HI>Congregational Churches</HI> in <HI>England,</HI> agreed and consented unto, by their Elders and Messengers, in their Meeting at the <HI>Savoy, Octob.</HI> 12. 1658. They declare, <HI>That the Members of Par∣ticular Churches are Saints by calling, visibly mani∣festing their Obedience to the Call of Christ, who be∣ing further known to each other by. their Confession of Faith wrought in them by the Power of God, declared by themselves, or otherwise manifested, consent to walk together according to the appointment of Christ.</HI> I have known many in <HI>England</HI> of that way; but never any that did not concern the <HI>Brethren</HI> as well as themselves, to be <HI>Judges</HI> of the fitness of those who have desired to be received into their Communion. It is evident, that the Church, (and not the Officers only) have power given them by Christ to Judge who are meet to be <HI>put out</HI> of their Communion. <HI>Math.</HI> 18.17. 1 Cor. 5.12 Then they must needs have the like pow∣er as to those that are to be <HI>taken into</HI> their Com∣munion. <HI>Ejusdem est potestatis constituere et destitu∣ere,</HI> is a known received <HI>Axiom.</HI> If the <HI>whole Church</HI> has power to <HI>Judge</HI> of the Repentance of one that is to be <HI>Re admitted,</HI> then of the Repen∣tance of one that is to have his <HI>first Admission.</HI> But the Apostle speaks to the <HI>Church,</HI> and not to the <HI>Officers</HI> only to restore the penitent <HI>Corinthian</HI> to their Communion. 2 Cor. 2.8. Again, If the <HI>whole multitude of Disciples</HI> have power to Judge whether persons are qualified with that Wisdom and Grace as to be meet for <HI>Office-Relation</HI> in the Church, then they have power to Judge concern∣ing
<PB N="25" REF="000790_0024_0FAA54873063F850"/>
the Knowledge and Grace of <HI>Communicants.</HI> The Argument is <HI>a majori ad minus.</HI> They that are meet <HI>Judges</HI> in a <HI>greater matter,</HI> much more in that which is <HI>less.</HI> But the former is clear from the Scripture. Acts. 6.2, 3, 4. For further satis∣faction in this point, Mr. <HI>Norton,</HI> and Mr. <HI>Shepard</HI> may be consulted, with that man of vast Reading and Learning, Mr. <HI>Robert Parker.</HI></P>
<P>These things I have supposed to be proper for me to Write to you the Church of Christ in <HI>Cam∣bridge</HI>; not as doubting of your Stedfastness in the Truth to this day professed and practised by you, but as desiring that those who shall succeed you, may continue to walk therein; &amp; that so I might testify, the peculiar Respect, that I do (and ought to) bear unto you, on the account of the Unde∣served Love, which all of you have manifested towards me. Five years are not expired, since you were pleased unanimously to Invite me to Ac∣cept of the <HI>Pastoral Office</HI> over you. But the unwillingness of the Dear People among whom I have been Labouring in the Gospel for the space of Thirty six years, that I should leave them, in consideration with some other Obstacles, kept me from complying with that your loving motion. Nevertheless, I cannot but whilst I Live, have a Dear Affection for you, and know not how to express it more, than by Endeavouring what in me lies, that you, and your Children after you, may be Confirmed in those wayes of the Lord, which your Fathers, and your selves too, have ex∣perienced so much of His Presence in. And I
<PB N="26" REF="000790_0025_0FAA5487F3A4EE98"/>
have also considered, that you are singularly cir∣cumstanced, in that there are Residing with you, the <HI>Sons of the Prophets,</HI> whose Establishment <HI>in the present Truth,</HI> I am more than any man in the World, under an Obligation to promove, and I certainly know (not altogether without an Awful Sense of it) that the <HI>Son of God,</HI> will e're long Enquire of me, whether I did, in this matter, Discharge my Duty, according to his Expectation, to whom I must be accountable concerning the Improvement of whatever <HI>Talents</HI> or Opportuni∣ties to Serve His Interests, He has or shall Trust me with, whilst I am in this World.</P>
<P>A few words let me further speak to you, who belong to that <HI>Nursery,</HI> for Religion and Learning, which has for a long time been the <HI>Glory,</HI> not of <HI>Cambridge</HI> only, but of <HI>New England.</HI> Sixteen years will this <HI>Summer</HI> be Lapsed since God, by His Providence, devolved the <HI>Praesidentship</HI> of that So∣ciety into my Hands, to manage it (so far as my <HI>Insufficiencies</HI> for such a Service will permit) for the Ends, which He (and our <HI>Fathers,</HI> as His <HI>Instru∣ments</HI>) did at first Erect a <HI>Colledge</HI> in <HI>New England</HI> upon; which was chiefly, that so <HI>Scholars</HI> might there be Educated for the special Service of Christ and His Churches, in the <HI>Work of the Ministry,</HI> and that they might be seasoned in their Tender years with such <HI>Principles</HI> as brought their Blessed Proge∣nitors into this Wilderness. What my Sollicitudes for this have been in both <HI>Englands,</HI> is known to Him, who said to the Churches, <HI>I know your works.</HI> There is no One Thing of greater Concernment
<PB N="27" REF="000790_0026_0FAA5488B1591E20"/>
to these Churches, in present and after times, than the Prosperity of that <HI>Society.</HI> They cannot sub∣sist without a <HI>Colledge.</HI> There are at this day not above Two or Three of our Churches but what are supplyed from thence. Nor are the Churches like to continue <HI>pure Golden Candlesticks,</HI> if the <HI>Colledge,</HI> which should supply them, prove <HI>Apostate.</HI> If the <HI>Fountain</HI> be corrupted, How should the <HI>Streams</HI> be pure, which should <HI>make Glad the City of God</HI>? How should <HI>Plants of Renown</HI> spring up from thence, if the <HI>Colledge</HI> it self become a <HI>Degenerate Plant</HI>? You that are <HI>Tutors</HI> there, have a Great Advantage put into your Hands (and I Pray God give you Wisdom to know it!) to pre∣vent it. The Lord hath made you <HI>Fathers</HI> to ma∣ny <HI>Pupils.</HI> You will not deny, but that He has made <HI>me</HI> a <HI>Father</HI> to <HI>you</HI> It was my Recommen∣dation, that brought you into that <HI>Station.</HI> And therefore, as my <HI>Joy</HI> will be the Greater to see you Acquit your selves <HI>Worthily,</HI> so my earnest Sollici∣tudes for it must needs be the more, on <HI>that</HI> Ac∣count. There are many (I believe, you wish you could say so of all of them) who were once un∣der your <HI>Tuition,</HI> that do worthily in <HI>Ephratah,</HI> and are like to be famous in <HI>Bethlehem,</HI> for which you ought to (and I doubt not but you do) humbly Bless the Lord, That <HI>you</HI> (and they who shall suc∣ceed you) may be yet <HI>Greater Blessings,</HI> Let me Commend unto you the Example of this Blessed Man, whose <HI>Life</HI> is here described. When <HI>Jerom</HI> had considered the Life of <HI>Hilarion,</HI> he Resolved <HI>Hilarion shall be the Champion, whom I will follow!</HI>
<PB N="28" REF="000790_0027_0FAA5489B5222470"/>
Say each of you, <HI>Mitchel,</HI> (once a <HI>Tutor</HI> in <HI>Har∣vard Colledge) shall be the Example, whom I will Imitate</HI>! You will see in the Story of his Life, that he did not only Instruct his <HI>Pupils</HI> in the Know∣ledge of the <HI>Tongues</HI> and <HI>Arts,</HI> but that he would sometimes discourse them about the <HI>Spiritual Estate</HI> of their Immortal Souls. Such private <HI>Personal Instructions,</HI> are many times more Effectual to <HI>Con∣version</HI> than <HI>Publick Sermons.</HI> Some very worthy Persons who were once his <HI>Scholars,</HI> have a Living Remembrance of his Words, to this Day. Others of them are now with him in Glory, blessing God to Eternity, whose Providence disposed them un∣der such a <HI>Tutor.</HI> Famous Dr. <HI>Preston</HI> chose rather to Live in <HI>Cambridge,</HI> than in any place in <HI>Eng∣land,</HI> because by Reason of the <HI>University</HI> there, he had an Opportunity, <HI>Non modo dolare Lapides sed Architectos,</HI> to <HI>prepare Builders for the House of God.</HI> The <HI>Angels</HI> in Heaven would not think it beneath them, to be employed in so Great a Work and Service for the Churches of Christ as that which Infinite Grace has call'd <HI>you</HI> unto. If you follow those, that have gone before you (<HI>Mitchel</HI> in particular) as they have <HI>followed Christ,</HI> your <HI>Names</HI> will be Precious &amp; Honourable like theirs, &amp; you shall <HI>Live</HI> after you are <HI>Dead,</HI> as they now do.</P>
<P>As for you that are the <HI>Students</HI> in the <HI>Colledge</HI>: I have often (as you know) in my Discourses a∣mong you, Exhorted you above all things to <HI>Stu∣dy Christ,</HI> and to be mindful of, <HI>The One Thing Ne∣cessary. Gifts</HI> without <HI>Grace</HI> will be of no Avail unto you at last. You may excel in <HI>Knowledge,</HI>
<PB N="29" REF="000790_0028_0FAA548AA996E190"/>
and yet be of all in the world the most <HI>miserable,</HI> and most like to the <HI>Devils,</HI> as a <HI>Converted Indian</HI> once said concerning some <HI>Scholars.</HI> You know that many Philosophers who were <HI>Heathen</HI> excel∣led in that which is called, <HI>Humane Learning.</HI> And so have some <HI>Popish</HI> Authors (<HI>Jesuites</HI> especially) done, whose Books have been very Edifying to others. I must confess, that as to that small mea∣sure of <HI>Knowledge</HI> which I have attained unto, I have, (for some part of it) been beholden to the Divine Providence for the Works of <HI>Ricciolus, Galtruchius,</HI> and others of that Fraternity, who were very Learned men, though Enemies of the <HI>True Protestant Religion.</HI> Knowledge then without <HI>Christ and Holiness,</HI> will never bring you to Hea∣ven. One has written a Book, <HI>De Salute Aristote∣lis</HI>; And another, <HI>De Animabus Paganorum</HI>; en∣deavouring to prove, that the Philosophers who <HI>Knew not the Only True God,</HI> nor <HI>Jesus Christ,</HI> have <HI>Eternal Life.</HI> Let such and all other <HI>Pelagian</HI> and <HI>Arminian</HI> Principles be far from you. But do not think that it is enough, if you be <HI>Orthodox,</HI> in the <HI>Fundamental Points</HI> of Religion. It was not (I can assure you) on any such Account that your Fa∣thers followed Christ into this <HI>Wilderness, when it was a Land not sown.</HI> If you degenerate from the <HI>Order of the Gospel</HI> (as well as from the <HI>Faith of the Gospel</HI>) you will justly merit the Name of <HI>Apo∣states,</HI> and of <HI>Degenerate Plants.</HI> And such Dege∣neracy in the Children of <HI>New-England,</HI> and most of all in <HI>you</HI> will be worse, than in any Children in the world. If any of you shall prove such, Re∣member
<PB N="30" REF="000790_0029_0FAA548AF018A710"/>
that you were told, that <HI>you take an unhappy time to Degenerate in.</HI> He whose <HI>Fan is in his Hand, will throughly purge his Floor.</HI> The <HI>Day is near,</HI> when the Lord Jesus Christ will make His Church∣es more pure &amp; <HI>Reformed,</HI> than in the former Ages; and will you at such a Time corrupt your selves with loose and large Principles in matters relating to the House of God, <HI>Whose House Holiness becomes for ever</HI>! How if some of you should live to see that Scripture verified, where the Lord says, <HI>The Levites that are gone far from me, when Israel went astray, they shall not come near unto me, to do the Of∣fice of a Priest unto me, but the Sons of</HI> Zadok <HI>that kept the Charge of my Sanctuary, they shall enter into my Sanctuary, and they shall come near to my Table to Minister unto me!</HI> Ezek. 44.10, 15. Let me Re∣commend unto you the weighty words of my most dear and worthy Friend and Predecessor, Mr. <HI>Oakes,</HI> once your Learned <HI>President,</HI> which he deli∣vered (and afterwards Printed) on a very solemn Occasion. He speaketh to you thus.
<Q>Consider (saith he) what will be the <HI>End</HI> of Receding or making a <HI>Defection</HI> from the Way of <HI>Church Government</HI> esta∣blished amongst us.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>In his Electi∣on Sermon on Deut.</HI> 32.29. <HI>p.</HI> 44. <HI>&amp;c.</HI></NOTE> I profess, I look upon the Discovery and Settlement of the <HI>Congregational Way,</HI> as the Boon, the Gratuity, the largeness of Divine Bounty, which the Lord graciously bestowed on His People that followed Him into this Wil∣derness; and a great part of the <HI>Blessing</HI> on the Head of <HI>Joseph,</HI> and of them who were <HI>Sepa∣rate
<PB N="31" REF="000790_0030_0FAA548DF518AAA8"/>
from their Brethren.</HI> These Good Peoplo that came over, shewed more Love, Zeal, and Affectionate Desire of <HI>Communion</HI> with God in <HI>pure</HI> Worship and Ordinances, and did more in Order to it than others, and the Lord did more for them than for any people in the world, in shewing them the <HI>Pattern</HI> of His House, and the true <HI>Scriptural way</HI> of Church Government and Administrations. God was certainly in a more than ordinary way of favour present with his Servants, in laying of our <HI>Foundations,</HI> and in settling the way of <HI>Church Order,</HI> according to the Will and Appointment of Christ. Consider what will be the <HI>sad issue</HI> of Revolting from the way fixed upon, to one Extream or to another, whether it be to <HI>Presbyterianism</HI> or <HI>Brownism</HI>; as for the <HI>Presbyterians,</HI> it must be acknowledged, that there are among them as Pious, Learned, Sober, Orthodox men, as the World affords; &amp; that there is as much of the <HI>Power of Godliness</HI> a∣mong that party, and of the Spirit of the good <HI>Old Puritans,</HI> as among any people in the World. And for their way of <HI>Church Govern∣ment,</HI> it must be confessed, that in the Day of it, it was a very considerable step to <HI>Reformation.</HI> The Reformation in K. <HI>Edwards</HI> days was then a Bles∣sed Work. And the Reformation of <HI>Geneva &amp; Scotland,</HI> was then a larger step, and in many Respects purer than the other. And for my part I fully believe that the <HI>Con∣gregational way</HI> far exceeds both, and is the <HI>Highest step</HI> that has been taken towards <HI>Reformation,</HI> and for the Substance of it, it is the very same way, that was esta∣blished &amp; practised in the <HI>Primitive Times,</HI> according to
<PB N="32" REF="000790_0031_0FAA548EC5E07888"/>
the Institution of Jesus Christ. I must needs say, that I should look upon it, as a sad Degeneracy, if we should leave the <HI>good old way,</HI> so far as to turn <HI>Councils</HI> &amp; <HI>Synods</HI> in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o-<HI>Classes</HI> &amp; <HI>Provincial Assemblies,</HI> and there should be <HI>such a Laxness in Admission of Members to Communion, as is pleaded for, and practised by many Presbyterians, &amp; El∣ders should manage all themselves</HI> in an <HI>Autocratorical way,</HI> to the Subversion of the Libert<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> &amp; Priviledge of the <HI>Brethren.</HI></Q>
Thus Mr. <HI>Oak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI> As for that Excellent∣ly Learned &amp; Holy Man Mr. <HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es Chauncey,</HI> who for many years <HI>Presided</HI> over <HI>Harvard-Colledge,</HI> none of you who now belong to that Society can remember him But you have heard what his <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing Charge</HI> to his Sons (who through Grace tread in their Fathers Steps) was, in his <HI>Last Will &amp; Testament,</HI> which you may see Published with his <HI>Life,</HI> in due time. He that is now your Presi∣dent— <HI>A longe sequitur v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stigia semper adorans</HI>; yet is willing not to Ev<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> or undermine the <HI>Foundation,</HI> which his Blessed Predecessors, have layed, but to Build thereon. I remember <HI>Buckanan</HI> (who was Tutor to K. <HI>James</HI> I.) in the Preface to his <HI>Baptisies,</HI> which he <HI>Dedicates</HI> to that K. sayes, That the Reason why he did so, was,
<Q>That in case He should through the Influence of Evil Coun∣sellors, or from any other Cause, be Guilty of Male-Administration in His Government, after Ages should know, that the Blame ought to be Imputed not to His Tutor, but to Himself.</Q>
So let me say, If <HI>you</HI> the Stu∣dent in <HI>Harvard-C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lledge,</HI> or any of you, shall deviate and degenerate from the Holy <HI>Principles</HI> and <HI>Practices</HI> of your <HI>Father,</HI> the World shall know, and Posterity shall know, That the Reason of it, is not for want of being otherwi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e instructed by your Present, as well as by For∣mer <HI>Presidents</HI></P>
<CLOSER><DATE>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> 7. 1697.</DATE>
<SIGNED>INCREASE MATHER.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="biography">
<PB N="33" REF="000790_0032_0FAA548FF74A30A8" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>Ecclesiastes. OR, The LIFE of Mr. Jonathan Mitchel.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><L>Sanctorum <HI>Vitas</HI> Legere &amp; non Vivere, frustra est;</L>
<L>Sanctorum Vitas <HI>Degite,</HI> non <HI>Legite.</HI></L></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P N="1">§ 1. IT is Reported concerning the Anci∣ent <HI>Phrygians,</HI> that when a <HI>Priest</HI> ex∣pired among them, they Honoured him with a <HI>Pillar</HI> Ten Fathom high, whereon they placed his <HI>Dead</HI> Body, as if he were to continue, after his <HI>Death,</HI> from thence Instructing of the People. Nor can a <HI>Mi∣nister</HI> of the Gospel have any more Honourable Funeral, than <HI>That,</HI> by which his Instruction of the People, may be most continued unto the Peo∣ple, after his Expiration. But I may without any Danger of <HI>Mistake,</HI> venture to affirm, That there cannot Easily be found, a <HI>Minister</HI> of the Gospel,
<PB N="34" REF="000790_0033_0FAA54902D479D20"/>
in our Dayes, more worthy to have the Story of his <HI>Life</HI> employed for the Instruction of <HI>Mankind,</HI> after his Decease, than our Excellent <HI>Mitchel.</HI> And therefore I shall now Endeavour to set him on as high a <HI>Pillar,</HI> as the best <HI>History,</HI> that I can give of his Exemplary <HI>Life,</HI> can erect, for that Worthy man; for whom Statues of <HI>Corinthian Brass,</HI> were but Inadaequate Acknowledgments.</P>
<P N="2">§ 2. If it were counted an Honour, to the Town of <HI>Halifax</HI> in <HI>York</HI> shire, that the famous <HI>John de Sacro Bosco,</HI> Author of the well known Treatise, <HI>De Sphaera,</HI> was born there; this Town was no less Honoured by it's being the Place of Birth to our no less worthyly famous <HI>Ionathan Mitchel,</HI> the Author of a better Treatise, Of <HI>Hea∣ven,</HI> who being descended (as a Printed Account long since ha's told us) of <HI>Pious</HI> and <HI>Wealthy</HI> Pa∣rents, here drew his first Breath, in the year 1624. The precise <HI>Day</HI> of his Birth is lost, nor is it worth while for us to enquire by an <HI>Astrological Calcu∣lation,</HI> what Aspect the <HI>Stars</HI> had upon his Birth, since the <HI>Event</HI> has proved, That <HI>God the Father</HI> was in the <HI>Horoscope, Christ</HI> in the <HI>Mid Heaven,</HI> the <HI>Spirit</HI> in the <HI>Sixth-House, Repentance, Faith</HI> and <HI>Love,</HI> in the <HI>Eighth</HI>: and in the <HI>Twelfth,</HI> an <HI>Eter∣nal Happiness,</HI> where no <HI>Saturn</HI> can dart any malig∣nant Rayes. Here, while the <HI>Father of his Flesh</HI> was endeavouring to make him <HI>Learned</HI> by a pro∣per Education, the <HI>Father of Spirits,</HI> used the Me∣thods of Grace to make him <HI>Serious</HI>; especially by
<PB N="35" REF="000790_0034_0FAA54910F4E78E8"/>
a sore <HI>Feavour,</HI> which had like to have made the <HI>Tenth</HI> year of his Life, the <HI>Last,</HI> but then settled in his <HI>Arm,</HI> with such Troublesome Effects, that his Arm grew, and kept, a little <HI>bent,</HI> and he could never stretch it out <HI>Right,</HI> until his Dying Day. And upon this Accident he afterwards wrote this Reflection; <HI>Thus the Lord sought to make me Seri∣ous (Oh! when will it once be!) by steeping my first Entrance into years of Understanding, and into the Changes of Life, and my first motions to</HI> New-Eng∣land, <HI>in Eminent and Special Sorrows.</HI> Now his <HI>First Motions to New-England,</HI> mentioned in this Reflection, invite us to Hasten unto that part of our History, which is to Relate, that his Parents were some of those Exemplary <HI>Christians,</HI> which by the <HI>Unconscionable</HI> Impositions and Persecutions of the English <HI>Hierarchy</HI> upon the <HI>Consciences</HI> of People, as Remarkable for True <HI>Christianity,</HI> as any in the Realm, were driven out of it. In the year 1635. the Ship, which brought over Mr. <HI>Richard Mather,</HI> and many more of those <HI>Puritans,</HI> which had found the Church of <HI>England,</HI> then governed by such an <HI>Assembly of Treacherous men,</HI> (a Faction to whom that Name, <HI>The Church of England,</HI> never truly belonged) that they were put upon wishing with the Persecuted Prophet, <HI>Oh! that I had in the Wilderness a Lodging place of way∣faring men</HI>! was further enriched by having on Board our <HI>Jonathan,</HI> than a Child about Eleven years of Age; whose Parents with much Difficul∣ty and Resolution carried him unto <HI>Bristol</HI> to take
<PB N="36" REF="000790_0035_0FAA5491D198C6A8"/>
Shipping there, while he was not yet Recovered of his Illness. On the Coast of <HI>New England,</HI> they were delivered from a most eminent and amazing hazard of perishing, in a most <HI>horrible Tempest</HI>; upon which Deliverance Mr. <HI>Mather</HI> Preached a Sermon from that Scripture Joh. 5.14. <HI>Sin no more, least a worse thing come unto thee</HI>; whereby farther Impressions or <HI>Seriousness</HI> were made upon the Soul of this <HI>Young Disciple.</HI></P>
<P N="3">§ 3. The Godly Father of our <HI>Jonathan</HI> found, that <HI>America</HI> as well as <HI>Europe, New-England</HI> as well as <HI>England,</HI> was a part of Old <HI>Adam's</HI> World; well stocked every where, with the <HI>Thorns</HI> of Worldly <HI>Vanities</HI> and <HI>Vexations</HI>; and that a <HI>Wilder∣ness</HI> was a Place, where <HI>Temptation</HI> was to be met withal. All his Family, and the <HI>Jonathan</HI> of the Family, with the Rest, were visited with <HI>Sickness,</HI> the Winter after their first Arrival at <HI>Charlstown,</HI> and the <HI>Scarcity</HI> then afflicting the Countrey, ad∣ded unto the Afflictions of their <HI>Sickness.</HI> Re∣moving to the Town of <HI>Concord,</HI> his <HI>greater mat∣ters</HI> continually became <HI>smaller</HI> there, his <HI>Begin∣nings</HI> were there Consumed by <HI>Fire,</HI> and some o∣ther Losses befel him in the <HI>Latter End</HI> of that Winter. The next Summer he Removed unto <HI>Say brook,</HI> and the next Spring unto <HI>Weathersfield,</HI> upon <HI>Connecticut</HI> River, by which he Lost yet more of his Possessions, and plunged himself into other Troubles. Towards the Close of that year, he had a Son-in-law Slain by the <HI>Pequot In∣dians</HI>;
<PB N="37" REF="000790_0036_0FAA54928C812C00"/>
and the Rest of the Winter they Lived in much fear of their Lives from those Barba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ians, and many of his Cattel were destroyed, and his Estate unto the value of some Hundreds of Pounds was damnified. A <HI>Shallop,</HI> which he sent unto the River's mouth was taken, and burned by the <HI>Pequots,</HI> and Three men in the Vessel Slain, in all of whom he was nearly concerned: So that indeed the <HI>Pequot</HI> Scourge fell more on this Fami∣ly, than on any other in the Land. Afterward there arose unhappy <HI>Differences</HI> in the place where he Lived, wherein he was an <HI>Antagonist</HI> against some of the <HI>Principal Persons</HI> in the place, and hereby <HI>he</HI> that had hitherto <HI>Lived in precious E∣steem with Good men, wherever he came</HI> (as a Re∣cord I have seen, testifies concerning him) now suffered much in his <HI>Esteem</HI> among many such men, as 'tis usual in such Contentions, and he met with many other Injuries: For which Causes, he transferred himself, with his Interests, unto <HI>Stam∣ford</HI> in the Colony of <HI>New Haven.</HI> Here his House, Barn and Goods were again Consumed by <HI>Fire</HI>; And much Internal <HI>Distress of mind</HI> ac∣companied these Humbling Dispensations. At last, that <HI>Most Horrible of Diseases,</HI> the <HI>Stone,</HI> ar∣rested him, and he underwent unspeakable Do∣lours from it, until the year 1645. when he went unto his Rest, about the Fifty Fifth Year of his Age.</P>
<P N="4">§ 4. Although the Good Spirit of God, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ave our <HI>Jonathan</HI> to Improve much in Holy Disposi∣tions
<PB N="38" REF="000790_0037_0FAA5493441CE6F8"/>
while he was yet a Youth, by the Calami∣ties, which thus befel his Father; and particularly upon Occasion of a sad thing befalling a Servant of his Father's, who instead of Going to the Le∣cture at <HI>Hartford,</HI> as he had been Allowed and Advised, would needs go fell a Tree for himself, but a broken Bough of the Tree struck him Dead, so that he never spoke or stirred more; our <HI>Jonathan,</HI> who was then about Fifteen years old, in one of his Papers does Relate, <HI>This Ama∣zing Stroke did much stirr my Heart, and I spent some time in Endeavouring the work of Repentance, accor∣ding to Mr.</HI> Scudder's <HI>Directions in his Daily Walk</HI>: nevertheless he had this Disadvantage, that he was thereby Diverted from <HI>Study</HI> and <HI>Learning,</HI> for the first seven years after his Coming into the Countrey. Had it not been for the Disadvan∣tage of this <HI>Intermission,</HI> we had seen some Lively Emulation of <HI>Bellarmine's</HI> open Lectures of Divi∣nity, at Sixteen years of Age, or <HI>Torquato Quasso's</HI> Receiving his Degrees in Philosophy and Divini∣ty at Seventeen, or <HI>Grotius's</HI> publishing of Com∣mentaries, at the like Seventeen. For he was, as the Historian observes, all that will prove <HI>Considerable,</HI> must be, <HI>Puer, qui Seminario Vertutum Generosiore con∣cretus, aliquid Inclytum designasset.</HI> But after so long an <HI>Intermission,</HI> as until <HI>September</HI> in the year 1642. and the Eighteenth year of his Age, upon the Earnest Advice of some that had Observed his great Capacity, and especially of Mr. <HI>Mather,</HI> with whom he came into <HI>New-England,</HI> he Re∣sumed
<PB N="39" REF="000790_0038_0FAA54941F9F98A8"/>
his Designs for <HI>Study</HI> and <HI>Learning</HI>: where∣in he made so vigorous a Progress, that in the year 1645. he was upon a strict <HI>Examination,</HI> Ad∣mitted into <HI>Harvard Colledge.</HI> Nor was it very long before Mr. <HI>Mather,</HI> who was the Adviser of this matter, had the Consolation of seeing the Excellent Labours of this person, in the Pulpit, worthy of his own Constant <HI>Journeys</HI> to his month∣ly <HI>Lectures</HI>; yea, and the most Considerable <HI>Fa∣thers</HI> of the Countrey, with himself, treating this person, as not <HI>Coming behind the very Chiefest of them all,</HI> and Tasting his Communications, not as <HI>Unripe Grapes,</HI> or <HI>Wine just out of the Press.</HI></P>
<P N="5">§ 5. But before we can fairly Arrive to <HI>that</HI> part of our Story, it will be as <HI>profitable,</HI> as <HI>necessary</HI> for us, to Observe the <HI>Steps</HI> whereby God made him <HI>Great.</HI> The Faculties of Mind, with which the <HI>God that Forms the Spirit of man,</HI> enriched him, were very Notable. He had a <HI>Clear Head,</HI> a Copious <HI>Fancy,</HI> a Solid <HI>Judgment,</HI> a Tenacious <HI>Memory,</HI> and a certain <HI>Discretion,</HI> without any Childish <HI>Laschete,</HI> or <HI>Levity</HI> in his Behaviour, which commanded Respect from all that viewed him: So that it might be said of him, as it once was of a Great Person, in the English Nation, <HI>They that knew him from a Child, never knew him any other than a Man.</HI> Under these Advantages, he was an <HI>Hard Student,</HI> and he so Prospered in his Indefatigable <HI>Studies,</HI> that he became a Scho∣lar of <HI>Illuminations,</HI> not far from the <HI>First Magni∣tude</HI>: Recommended by which Qualifications, it
<PB N="40" REF="000790_0039_0FAA5494C34A25D8"/>
was not long before he was Chosen, a <HI>Fellow</HI> of the <HI>Colledge.</HI> But the main Strokes of his <HI>Colledge-Life,</HI> that I shall single out for my Readers Ob∣servation, are of yet an higher Character. Know then, that as it was his own Counsel to his B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣ther, <HI>The Writing of sometimes your former and pre∣sent Life, would be a Thing of Endless Use,</HI> thus it was his manner, whilst in the <HI>Colledge,</HI> to keep a brief <HI>Diary,</HI> written in the <HI>Latine Tongue,</HI> which he wrote indeed fluently and handsomely; and from a part of this <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ry,</HI> by him Entituled, <HI>Vitae Hypomnemata,</HI> happily fallen into my Hands, I shall note some few Remarkables.</P>
<P>He kept a strict Eye upon his <HI>Interior State,</HI> before God; and upon the Dispositions of his <HI>Heart,</HI> as well in <HI>Sacred,</HI> as in <HI>Civil</HI> Entertain∣ments: but with an Extreme <HI>Security</HI> of <HI>Reflection</HI> upon himself, when perhaps, at the same time the <HI>Severest Spectator</HI> upon Earth besides, would have judged every thing in him worthy to have been <HI>Admired,</HI> rather than <HI>Censured.</HI> He would Record such Things as these.</P>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 LANG="lat" TYPE="version">
<P><HI>One Time,</HI></P>
<P>Inter precandum, Deus ab Insipido as Desolato Corde juste ab fuit, ut me (quo ni∣hil magis necessarium) humi∣liaret; Nam aliter (si paulo meius asiquando se haboat Cor) est in me, quod propha∣na Spirituali Superbia titil∣latur.
<PB N="41" REF="000790_0040_0FAA5495822C8C90"/>
Eram tamen inde non∣nihil ad Deum Excitatior.</P>
<P><HI>At another time,</HI></P>
<P>Jèjunio privato interfui, ubi multo Stupore, et multa <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>avitate Oppletus sum; ali∣gua tamen viguerant Suspiria et Deus non visus est me om∣nino abdicare, sed paulo meli∣oreon fecit; utinam te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>m et fovissen Desi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>a, gua tunc ac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ndit.</P>
<P><HI>At another time</HI></P>
<P>Locum communem habui; vix abstinui a secreta super∣bia; Licet turpissima vanitas Animi (qua nunquam non omnia mea venenantur) me coram Deo, prostravisset, praeter alia mea peccata, quae me infra vermes ponunt, Ne∣que sane unquam aliquid aut facio aut dico, unde plus pu∣doris quam Honoris, mihi non nascitur, si omnia mecum per∣pendo; et Deus solet semper aliquid relinquere, unde me (saltem apud me) pude∣facit.</P>
<P><PB N="42" REF="000790_0041_0FAA5496EB137F10"/><HI>At another time,</HI></P>
<P>Collequiis Hilaribus, cum Sociis quibusdam nimis in∣dusi</P>
<P><HI>At another time,</HI></P>
<P>Adibam <HI>Bostonium,</HI> et i∣bi Libertatem Civilem acce∣pi, sed ex Oblectamentis Leve et Insipidum Cor.</P>
<P><HI>At another,</HI></P>
<P>Liberius quam prudentius quaedam l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cutus sum, unde mihi pudor.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 LANG="eng" TYPE="version">
<P>In my Prayer, God was justly withdrawn from my Unsavoury and Desolate Heart, that so He might Humble me; than which there is nothing more need∣ful for me. For otherwise (if my Heart be at any time in a little better frame)
<PB N="41" REF="000790_0040_0FAA5495822C8C90"/>
there is that in me, which is tickled with Spiritual Pride. Nevertheless I was from hence more Excited God-ward.</P>
<P>I was present at a private Fast, where I was filled with much Sotti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hness &amp; Vanity: Yet I had some Lively Sigh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; &amp; God seemed not wholly to cast me off, but made me a little Better than I was before. I wish I had Retained &amp; Cherished the Desires, which He then Enkindled!</P>
<P>I Common-placed. I could Scarce abstain from Secret Pride; altho' a very base Vanity of mind (with which every thing of mine is poison'd!) had laid me low in th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Dust before God; besides my other Sins, which lay me lower th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> the very Worms of the D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t But indeed, I never Do or Say, any thine, from whence there arises not more of Shame than of Honour to me, if I Consider all things; &amp; God uses in all ever to leave something, by which He makes me, at least ashamed of my self.</P>
<P><PB N="42" REF="000790_0041_0FAA5496EB137F10"/>I gave too much Liberty unto Merry Talk, with some of my Friends.</P>
<P>I went unto <HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ston,</HI> and there took a Civil Liberty: But from such Entertain∣ments my Heart grew light and unsavoury.</P>
<P>I discoursed some things with more Freedom than Wisdom; for which, I was ashamed of my self.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P>Again; He laid up the more especial <HI>Admoni∣tions</HI> which touched him, in the Sermons that he heard Preached, or in other more private and useful Conferences, and the <HI>Resolutions</HI> which he thereupon, asked the help of Heaven to follow. He would Record such Things as these.</P>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 LANG="lat" TYPE="version">
<P><HI>One time</HI></P>
<P>Vix aliquid apud Deum sapui, sed excitavit me Concio <HI>Magistri Shepar∣di,</HI> Tremenda plane et prae stantissima. Docuit Ali∣quos esse qui videntor In veniri et Servari a Christo et tamen postea pereunt. Haec me terrebant (et uti nam infixa haererent!) ne tantum <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> esse
<PB N="43" REF="000790_0042_0FAA549708D980C0"/>
Christi, et ne ad mortem <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sque sic pergerem. Rogavi Deum, ut mei Misertus totam rem ageret. Illa Nocte multo pudore, apud me suffusus eram, quod hactenus nibil in <HI>Medita∣tione quotidiana</HI> fece∣um, et hinc caecus et ig <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rus in Divinis, extra meipsum, et sine Deo, per Integras Septimanas vix uam. Jam Statui <HI>Me∣ditandi</HI> opus, quotidie ur∣gere, quod ante hac aliquo∣ties statui, sed, heu! Pro∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ossta violavi; unde suc∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>set Deus. Ab, Quot et Qeanta scire potuissem de Deo, si serius et constans in <HI>Meditatione</HI> fuissem!</P>
<P><HI>At another time,</HI></P>
<P><HI>D. Shepardus</HI> utilissime doeuit. Illa Nocte Seriae instabant Cogitationes, de infanda mea miseria, qua sine Deo, sine Redemptione,
<PB N="44" REF="000790_0043_0FAA5497AD77F420"/>
a Sabbato ad Sabbatum miserrimus pergo. Inde <HI>Tria</HI> statuebam mihi Ob∣servanda, quae etiam Deo, commendabam, ut in me efficeret. <HI>Primo,</HI> Non Quiete manendum in hac mea conditione; Intolera∣bile esse, ut sic pergerem. <HI>Secundo,</HI> Precand<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n∣stanter, sine Languore, aut Intermissione, mane nocte∣que Implorandum Deum, intimis et ineffabilibus sus∣piriis. <HI>Tertio,</HI> si Deus non auscultaverit, et quae opus sunt praestarit, in A∣more suo manifestando, saltem Lugeam et Lachry∣mem, et pergam in Ama∣ritudine Animae; si Conso∣lationem et Pacem a Deo, non habuero, saltem nullam emnino habeam!</P>
<P><HI>At another time,</HI></P>
<P><HI>D. Samuel Matherus</HI> eximie concionatus est, de Immutabilitate Dei. Iude Redarguebat mutabilitatem
<PB N="45" REF="000790_0044_0FAA549A17E09838"/>
et Inconstantiam Hominum erga Deum. Haec me te tigerunt: Conscius eram Inconstantiae meae; Et se rio, intimeque perculsus, prostratus coram Deo ve∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>menter Orabam Grati <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 LANG="eng" TYPE="version">
<P>I had little Savour on my Spirit before God: but a terrible &amp; Excellent Ser∣mon of Mr. <HI>Shepards</HI> awa∣kened me. He taught, that there are some who seem to be found and Sav'd by Christ, and yet afterwards they perish. These things terrified me, (and I wish, they had stuck fast in me!) lest I should only seem to
<PB N="43" REF="000790_0042_0FAA549708D980C0"/>
belong unto Christ, and lest I should thus go on unto Death. I Beg'd of God, that He would have mercy on me, and accomplish the whole work of His Grace for me. That Night I was covered with no little shame, because I had hitherto done in a manner, nothing at the work of DAILY MEDI∣TATION, and hence I had lived Blind, and Igno∣rant in Divine Things, a stranger to my self, &amp; with∣out God, for whole Weeks together. I now Resolved, every Day to urge the work of MEDITATION, which heretofore I have often Re∣solved, but alas, I have Vi∣olated my purposes; for which cause, God is Angry with me. Ah! How ma∣ny, how mighty Things of God might I have under∣stood, if I had been Serious and Const<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt in MEDI∣TATION!</P>
<P>Mr. <HI>Shepard</HI> Preached most profitably. That night, I was followed with Serious Thoughts, of my Inexpressible misery, where∣in
<PB N="44" REF="000790_0043_0FAA5497AD77F420"/>
I go on most miserably from Sabbath to Sabbath, without God, and without Redemption. From hence I determined, That there are Things which I must Observe; and I Commend∣ed these Things unto God, that he would Effect them in me. <HI>First</HI>; That I must not remain quietly in this my condition; but that it is Intolerable for me to pro∣ceed as I am. <HI>Secondly</HI>; That <HI>I</HI> must pray con∣stantly, without fainting, or any Intermission: Day and Night <HI>I</HI> must cry unto the Lord, with Groans that cannot be uttered. <HI>Thirdly</HI>; If God will not Hear me, nor do the Things that a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> needful for me, in manifest∣ing to me His Love, let me at least Mourn, &amp; Weep, and go on in the Bitterness of my Soul. If <HI>I</HI> shall not have Comfort, and Peace, from God, let me have None at all!</P>
<P>Mr. <HI>Samuel Mather</HI> Preached Excellently, con∣cerning, <HI>The Ʋncheangeable∣ness of God.</HI> From hence
<PB N="45" REF="000790_0044_0FAA549A17E09838"/>
he Rebuked the Changea∣bleness &amp; Inconstancy of men, towards God. These Things Touch'd me; for <HI>I</HI> was Conscious to my own Inconstancy; and being Se∣riously &amp; Inwardly Smitten with the sense of it, <HI>I</HI> cast my self down at the Feet of God, with Vehement Supplications for His Favour.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P>Furthermore, He Acquitted himself, as One concerned for the <HI>Souls</HI> of his <HI>Pupils,</HI> when he came to have such under his Charge; &amp; was very desirous to see their <HI>Hearts</HI> renewed by <HI>Grace,</HI> the <HI>(Beginning or) Head of Knowledge,</HI> as well as their <HI>Heads</HI> furnished with other <HI>Knowledge.</HI> He would Record such things as these.</P>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 LANG="lat" TYPE="version">
<P><HI>At one Time,</HI></P>
<P>Alloquehar <HI>M. W.</HI> de Salutis Negotio. Multis il∣lem hortabar, monebam, et dirigebam, ad illud cu∣candum, ne suffucaret Convi∣ctiones, et inconstantia Deum luderet, sed precibus ΙΙΡΟΣ
ΚΑΡΤΕRΗΣ Η. Utinam ips<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> praestarem, quae dixi! Deus, Ierva illum Juve∣nem!</P>
<P><PB N="46" REF="000790_0045_0FAA549B19B00CC0"/><HI>At another time,</HI></P>
<P><HI>S. M.</HI> primus e Pupillis meis, me allecutus est de Animae suae statu; plura quidem quam spe∣rassem Laetus audivi; et (quod Deus dedit) Consili um addidi, ut pergeret di∣ligenter Deum sequi, Ani∣mabam ad sequendum De∣um; At pudebat me Ari∣ditatis Animi mei.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 LANG="eng" TYPE="version">
<P><HI>I</HI> spoke unto <HI>M. W.</HI> a∣bout the matters of Eternal Salvation, <HI>I</HI> largely Exhor∣ted him, advised him, di∣rected him to be careful of This, that he did not Stiffle his Convictions, &amp; mock God by Inconstancy, but be instant in Prayer. <HI>I</HI> wish <HI>I</HI> could my self Do, what <HI>I</HI> spoke! Lord, Save that Young man!</P>
<P><PB N="46" REF="000790_0045_0FAA549B19B00CC0"/><HI>S. M.</HI> the first of my Pupils, had some Speech with me, about the State of his own Soul; <HI>I</HI> Gladly heard more from him, than I Expected; &amp; (with the Help of God) I Coun∣selled him, that he would go on to follow hard after God. <HI>I</HI> Encouraged him to follow the Lord; but <HI>I</HI> was ashamed of the Bar∣renness of my own Soul!</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P>Yea, How watchful he was, on all Occasions, to Observe what Occasions he might have to <HI>Do Good</HI> among all the Scholars, I shall no more than Transcribe the following Passage, to intimate.</P>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 LANG="lat" TYPE="version">
<P>Nocte, inter Scholares, multa seria dixi de Cognos∣cendis Rebus Pacis Nostrae, in Die nostro. Utinam ipse mihimet Auscultarem! Die sequenti plura ego collocutus sum cum Contubernalibus, ad probandum, esse <HI>Deum,</HI> et Scripturas esse ipsius verbum. Ah, nimium ser pit inter nos ΑΤΗΕΟ∣ΤΕS, et video Satanam multos perniciosissimos Di∣alogismos
<PB N="47" REF="000790_0046_0FAA549B8018A0B0"/>
in Non nullorum mentes injicere! Hoc malo peribunt multi Juvenes, ni miserearis, 0 Deus! Et sensi me ad huc in his mi∣serrime tenebricosum, nec magis aliquid Rogandum, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uam ut Stabiliret me quo ad Fundamentales istas ve∣ritates, claremque hic vi∣sionem deret! Hinc ali∣quando Occasiones Capto Realitatem, ΤΩΝ ΘΕΟΥ inculcandi, et illustrandi: quod non prorsus mane video. Utinam majori Cordis sensu, ego possem Deum praedicare. Sed quid mirum me opple∣is Tenebris, qui Oppletus sem Cupiditatibus!</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 LANG="eng" TYPE="version">
<P>At Night, among the Scholars, <HI>I</HI> uttered many Serious Things, about, <HI>Knowing the Things of our Peace in our Day.</HI> Oh! that I could my self herein but hearken to my self! The Day following, I dis∣coursed more, with my Chamber-fellows, to prove, That there is a GOD, and that the Scriptures are His Word. Alas, <HI>Atheism</HI> creeps in too much among
<PB N="47" REF="000790_0046_0FAA549B8018A0B0"/>
us, and I see that Satan does cast many most Pernicious Reasonings into the minds of some. Many Young men, will perish by this Mischief, Except thou, O Lord God, have Mercy on them! I found my self also most miserably dark in these things; nor is there any thing that I have more cause to ask, than this; That He would Establish me in these Fundamental Truths, and give me a Clear Vision of them! From hence I sometimes do Snatch at Oc∣casions, to inculcate and il∣lustrate the Reality of the Things of God: which I see, is not altogether in vain. I wish, I could Preach God, with greater sense upon my Heart But what wonder is it, if I that am full of <HI>Lusts,</HI> be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lso full of <HI>Darknes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>!</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P>Reader, see how impossible it was, for this Excellent young man to Record any thing in this <HI>Diary,</HI> without some stroke of <HI>Humiliation</HI> and <HI>Admonition</HI> to himself in the Close of all: The ready way of becoming <HI>Excellent</HI>!</P>
<P>And while he was thus a young man, residing
<PB N="48" REF="000790_0047_0FAA549C340DE998"/>
in the <HI>Colledge,</HI> he would sometimes, on the <HI>Sa∣turday,</HI> Retire into the <HI>Woods,</HI> near the Town, and there spend a great part of the Day, in Ex∣amining of his own <HI>Heart</HI> and <HI>Life,</HI> Bewailing the Evils, which made him want the Mercies of God, and Imploring the Mercies which he want∣ed of the Lord: which Custome of spending <HI>Saturday,</HI> he had formerly attended also at <HI>South-Hampton,</HI> while he was yet, but as a <HI>School-Boy</HI> there. Moreover, it was, while he thus Resided at the <HI>Colledge,</HI> that his Brother <HI>David,</HI> under deep Distresses of mind about his Everlasting Interests, addressed him for Counsel; and our <HI>Jonathan</HI> then wrote unto his Brother that <HI>Golden Letter,</HI> which was almost Thirty years after, published in <HI>London,</HI> at the End of his <HI>Discourse of Glory</HI>; A Letter whereof the famous <HI>Collins</HI> makes this Re∣mark, <HI>Every Reader sensible of Spiritual Things, will see it written with an Excellent Spirit, the Spirit of God, and drawn out of his own Experiences, and this when but newly Entring upon his Ministry:</HI> A Let∣ter, wherein he Discovers that Experimental Ac∣quaintance with the Operations of <HI>Sin,</HI> and of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ace,</HI> upon the Souls of men, which may Inti∣mate how Eminent he was in One of the Accom∣plishments most necessary to the <HI>Ministry</HI> of the Gospel, before he had yet <HI>Entred</HI> upon it. If <HI>Chrysostom,</HI> the <HI>Ancient,</HI> were sometimes called, <HI>Insignis Animorum tractandorum Artifex,</HI> Reader, here was a <HI>young man,</HI> who effectually proved himself, <HI>An Artist, at handling the Cases of a Son<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI>!
<PB N="49" REF="000790_0048_0FAA549CF0E0D140"/>
I Remember, that <HI>Alexander More</HI> judges Three certain <HI>Epistles,</HI> to be the most <HI>Consummate Pieces,</HI> that ever the World saw▪ Namely, <HI>That</HI> of <HI>Cal∣vin</HI> before his <HI>Institutions</HI>; That of <HI>Thuanus,</HI> be∣fore his <HI>History</HI>; and <HI>That</HI> of <HI>Casaubon,</HI> bfore his <HI>Polybius.</HI> Now though this Epistle of our young <HI>Mitchel,</HI> come not into that <HI>Class,</HI> for the Em∣bellishments of Literature, yet it has been Reck∣oned one of the most <HI>Consummate Pieces,</HI> in the Methods of Addressing a <HI>Troubled Mind.</HI></P>
<P N="6">§ 6. The Extraordinary <HI>Learning, Wisdom, Gravity</HI> and <HI>Piety</HI> of this Incomparable Young man, caused several of the most Considerable Churches in the Countrey, to contrive how they might become Owners of such a <HI>Treasure,</HI> even before ever he had, by one Publick Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n, brought forth any of the <HI>Treasure</HI> wherewith Hea∣ven had Endowed him The Church of <HI>Hart∣ford</HI> in particular, being therein Countenanced and Encouraged by the Reverend Mr. <HI>Stone,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ent a Man, and Horse, above an Hund<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed miles, to obtain a visit from him, in expectation to make him the Successor of their ever famous <HI>Hooker,</HI> and though upon the first motion to him from <HI>Hartford,</HI> his Humble Soul, wrote these words, <HI>I had more need get alone into a Corner, and weep, than think of Going out into the World, to Do such Work: Darkness and Death clouds my Soul!</HI> Yet he was prevailed withal to visit them. At <HI>Hartford</HI> he Preached his First Sermon. (<HI>June</HI> 24. 1649.)
<PB N="50" REF="000790_0049_0FAA549DE27113E0"/>
upon <HI>Heb.</HI> 11.27. <HI>He Endured, as seeing Him who is Invisible</HI>; On which Action, though with his usual <HI>Humility,</HI> he wrote this Reflection in his <HI>Diary; In Preaching I was not to seek of what I had prepared; but my own Heart was Drie, Carnal and Unaffected, and methought I could not speak with any Evidence, or Presence of the Spirit of God; so that when I had done, I was deeply ashamed within my self, and could not but Loath my self, to think how mi∣serably I had behaved my self, in that High Employ∣ment, and how unsavoury, sottish and foolish my Heart had been therein; I thought, I, and all I did, well de∣served to be Loathed by God and man:</HI> Yet that Judicious Assembly of Christians, were so well pleased with the Labours whereof he himself thought so meanly, that in a Meeting the Day following, they Concluded to give him an Invi∣tation to Settle among them: Adding, That if he saw it his best way to continue a year longer at the <HI>Colledge,</HI> they would however immediately upon his Acceptance of their Invitation advance a considerable Sum of Money, to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him in furnishing himself with a <HI>Library</HI> (not unlike what the <HI>Uratislavian</HI> Senate once did for the Hopeful young <HI>Lucas Pollio,</HI> when they saw him, <HI>Juvenem Dotibus Ornatum a Deo, non vulgaribus</HI>:) which they said, was, <HI>No new thing unto them, ha∣ving had Mr.</HI> Hooker's <HI>Instruction for Doing so.</HI> But he durst not then Accept of their kind Pro∣posals: For, before his Journey to <HI>Hartford,</HI> the Renowned Mr. <HI>Shepard,</HI> with the Principal Per∣sons
<PB N="51" REF="000790_0050_0FAA549E8535C168"/>
in <HI>Cambridge,</HI> had importunately pray'd him, that he would come down from <HI>Hartford,</HI> as free as he went up, insomuch as he did upon divers Accounts most belong to <HI>Cambridge,</HI> &amp; <HI>Cambridge</HI> did hope, that he would yet more belong unto them. When Mr. <HI>Shepard</HI> first mentioned this thing unto him, he did with his constant <HI>Humility</HI> record it in his Diary, with this Reflection, <HI>Ego mirabar hinc rem: Quid in me videt Populus Dei! Totum Negotium Reliqui Deo agendum. I wondred at this matter! What is it that the People of God sees in me? I left the whole Business to the Divine Ma∣nagement!</HI> And now Returning to <HI>Cambridge,</HI> he no sooner came into the Pulpit (<HI>Aug.</HI> 12. 1649.) but Mr. <HI>Shepard,</HI> must go out of it! Mr. <HI>Shepard</HI> in the Evening told him, <HI>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is was the Place, where he should, by right, be all the rest of his Dayes</HI>: and enquiring of some good Peo∣ple, <HI>How Mr. <HI>Mitchel's</HI> first Sermon was approv∣ed among them</HI>; they told him, <HI>Very well.</HI> Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n said he, <HI>My Work is done!</HI> And behold, within a few Dayes more, that Great Man was by Death taken off, so that the Unanimous Desire of <HI>Cam∣bridge</HI> for Mr. <HI>Mitchel</HI> to be their Pastor was Hastened, with several Circumstances of Necessi∣ty, for him to Comply with their Desire. But as the Jewes use to say about the Birth of <HI>R. Je∣huda,</HI> on the very same Day, that another famous <HI>Rabbi</HI> dyed, <HI>Eo die occidit Lax Israelis, et iterum Orta est</HI>; So I may now say, <HI>The same Day was the Light of</HI> New-England, <HI>Extinguished and Revived</HI>!</P>
<P N="7"><PB N="52" REF="000790_0051_0FAA549F5EE823D0"/>§ 7. <HI>Occubuit Sol; Nox nulla Secuta est.</HI> Upon the setting of <HI>Shepard</HI> there arose <HI>Mitchel,</HI> in whose <HI>Light</HI> not only the Church of <HI>Cambridge,</HI> but the Colledge, and the whole Country, were now <HI>to Rejoyce for a Season.</HI> The Eyes of all <HI>New-England</HI> were upon him, with <HI>Great Expectations</HI>; and he did more than answer their <HI>Expectations</HI>: for he was indeed, <HI>an Extraordinary Person.</HI> But scarce a Paragraph of his <HI>Life</HI> can be written <HI>to the Life,</HI> without some Reflection upon that <HI>Humi∣lity,</HI> with which the Spirit of the Lord Jesus Christ, both <HI>prepared</HI> him for, and <HI>adorned</HI> him in, all of that Figure, whereto he Arrived in the Ser∣vice of the Churches. Just upon the Time of his Beginning his Ministry at <HI>Cambridge,</HI> he was taken dangerously Sick of the <HI>Small Pox,</HI> but though he were <HI>Sick nigh unto Death, God had Mercy on him, and not on him only, but on all the Churches thro' this Wilderness in him.</HI> No sooner was he Recovered of that Sickness, but this Humble Soul, wrote, Octob 4. 1649. in his <HI>Diary,</HI> (which after this time, spoke <HI>English,</HI>) these among other passages: <HI>It has been of late Weeks a special time of Adversity with me, The Lord Help me to Consider it! I might say,</HI> My skin is Broken, and become Loathsome; <HI>and,</HI> There is no Rest in my Bones because of my Sin, my Loins are filled with a loathsome Disease, &amp; there is no soundness in my flesh; <HI>By such a foul, noisom, filthy Disease, it well appeared, what I indeed was; as the Prophet speaks,</HI> Full of putrefying Sores.
<PB N="53" REF="000790_0052_0FAA54A036BE5BC8"/>
<HI>It being at this Time, I was as a City set upon an Hill; That when I was attempting the Pure and Sacred Work of the Ministry, I should be surprized with that Horrible Disease! Do I begin to be some Body in the world? God will make me Vile in the Eyes of the whole Country; God will Humble me before the Sun, and in the Sight of all</HI> Israel. <HI>He will have me begin my Mi∣nistry with this Disease: He knows, that I have need of a Great Deal of Purifying, before I come to that. A loathsome Sinner shall have a loathsome Sickness!</HI> And the Grace of Heaven that made this Fit of <HI>Sickness,</HI> to be Considered thus as an <HI>Humiliation,</HI> by this Eminent young man, then Entring upon his Ministry, did by continually Infusing other Thoughts full of <HI>Humiliation</HI> into him, lay the <HI>Foundation</HI> of stately <HI>Superstructures.</HI> As our Lord Jesus Christ, entring upon His Ministry, endured the forest Conflict of <HI>Temptation,</HI> that He had e∣ver met withal, so did this <HI>Excellent Embassador</HI> of that Lord; He had his Mind sorely <HI>Buffeted</HI> with Amazing &amp; Confounding Apprehensions. Per∣haps it will be many ways profitable unto some <HI>Candidates</HI> of the <HI>Ministry,</HI> as well as others, to see these Papers Recite some of the <HI>sad Passages,</HI> that rolled over the Soul of a most <HI>Lovely Preacher,</HI> when he was Beginning to Preach the <HI>Gospel of Peace.</HI> We then find him at a Time, when every one admired the Excellencies that <HI>Beautifyed</HI> him, thus Writing and Thinking of himself, as the <HI>De∣formedest Sinner</HI> in the World. At one time.
<Q>I have Lived in this World almost Twenty
<PB N="54" REF="000790_0053_0FAA54A0C188A3A0"/>
five years, and unto this Day have known lit∣tle of God in Christ, made little Provision for Eternity, got little Acquaintance with the favour and love of God. How I have Improved this Time, Wo to me, I may be ashamed to speak, amazed to think!</Q>
<HI>At another time,</HI>
<Q>Lord, I know not whether ever such a Sinner, as I, came to Thee for Mercy; whether ever such a work was done to any poor Wretch, as the saving of my Soul must be.</Q>
<HI>At another time.</HI>
<Q>I have run through all the means of Knowledge, and yet see no Truth Really, and in the Glory of it; All Afflictions, and yet am not Humbled nor Serious; All Mercies, and yet am not Thank∣full; All Means of Good, and yet am Evil, only Evil, Transcendently Evil, in the highest De∣gree, to this Day.</Q>
<HI>At another time.</HI>
<Q>If God do me any Good, or do any Good by me, it must be a Creating work. Lord, I am fit for nothing; (Good for nothing at all) neither to Live, nor Dy; neither to Teach, nor Learn; neither to Think, nor Speak; neither to Do, nor suffer; neither to Communicate Good, nor receive any; Go through all that I am, either within, or without, what am I, but Vile∣ness, and Abomination?</Q>
<HI>At another time.</HI>
<Q>The Church will (I suppose) this day, consider, &amp; determine a Day for Ordination; but did there ever such a Creature, as I am, go about such a business? I was low, and vile this time Twelve-month, when they first made the Motion; but
<PB N="55" REF="000790_0054_0FAA54A16CC8E7A0"/>
I am far lower and viler now. Great is the wrath of God that lyes upon me; and the to∣kens of it are in some respects increased. I can∣not, with Confidence go to God, as my Father in Jesus Christ. I know no Truth of God to any purpose. I have no Treasure of Christian Experience: I know not what belongs to the main matters of Conversion and Salvation. My Sin is enough to bring a Curse upon all I do, &amp; upon the whole place: I am under the very feet of Satan, in respect of it. <HI>Object. But shall not my Sin then hinder me, and make me Refuse this Work of the Ministry?</HI></Q>
Answ.
<Q>That is to mend one Sin with another. The more evil, and the less good I have done, the more need I have to give my self up to do what good I can Now; Sure I should not chuse my Sin, and leave Gods Work; and if I cast it away, and go to God to take it away, and wait on Him, 'tis possible with Him, to deliver me from it, and to help me in His Work: Though that would be the greatest wonder, that ever was done! However, let me lye at His Feet, and leave my self with Him. <HI>Quest. Why do I enter upon it?</HI> Answ. Because God bids me, and Commands me? <HI>Luk.</HI> 5 He will have it so, and why should my self, or Sin, or Satan, say, What doest Thou? <HI>Object. But it may be God will take no Pleasure in me?</HI> Answ. I deserve He should not, but yet He deserves to be Honoured &amp; Served; and let it be my Hap∣piness and Joy to do that, whatever becomes of
<PB N="56" REF="000790_0055_0FAA54A3B7C2A498"/>
me at last.</Q>
<HI>At another time.</HI>
<Q>My case is now such (so Dreadful, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esperate and Forlorn) as I think, there never was the like upon Earth, since Adam was formed, unto this Day: There is only this place of Hope, That there is a Degree of Mercy in God, beyond what any ever yet made use of! for no man ever came to the End of Infinite Mercy: Lord, Honour Thy self by me, some way or other, what ever become of me.</Q>
<HI>At another time.</HI>
<Q>Lord, It is the Hour &amp; Power of Darkness with me; I feel the Dreadful Rage of Satan, and my vile Heart, now against me, to overturn me, and to cut off thy Name, which Thou callest me to bear in this Place. I know not what will become of me, nor what to say to Thee: but I leave my Woful Soul, and self to thy Disposing, Lord, I am in Hell, wil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thou let me lye there?</Q>
<HI>At another time.</HI>
<Q>God hath put this Fear into my Heart, lest this be the Fruit, and Recompence of my Sin, that I shall never know God for mine in Truth, but Live and Dy, in an unsound and self Deceiving way; that I should have many fears and Prayers, and Good Affections and Duties and Hopes, and Or∣dinances, and Seemings, but never an Heart soundly Humbled, and soundly Comforted unto my Dying Day, but be a Son of Perdition to the last, and never have God's special Love Revealed and Assured to me! Lord, keep this Fear alive in my Heart!</Q>
Such Passages as these, abundantly discover the <HI>Contritions,</HI> that laid
<PB N="57" REF="000790_0056_0FAA54A48D857CA0"/>
him exceeding <HI>Low,</HI> in his own Apprehension of himself, at the Time, when God was Raising him to <HI>High</HI> Improvements, among His People; and it was by these <HI>Abasements,</HI> that Heaven prepared him for those <HI>Improvements.</HI> But being, after such <HI>Pre∣parations,</HI> called forth to the Service of the Churches, his Employments came in so thick upon him, that he had not such liesure as heretofore to Enrich his <HI>Diarys,</HI> with his Observations. He was at length Reduced unto this Custom, that Ordinari∣ly, on the Week before he Administred the Sa∣crament of the <HI>Lords-Supper,</HI> which was once in two Months, he spent a Day in <HI>Prayer</HI> with <HI>Fasting,</HI> before the Lord; and one of his Exercises on such a Day, was to Remind and Record, such Passages of Divine Providence towards <HI>Himself,</HI> his <HI>House,</HI> his <HI>Flock,</HI> the whole <HI>Countrey,</HI> yea, and the whole <HI>Nation,</HI> as he judged Useful to be Remem∣bred with him; and such especially as might Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>icken the <HI>Humiliations</HI> &amp; the <HI>Supplications,</HI> where∣in he was engaged.</P>
<P N="8">§ 8. The <HI>Death</HI> of Mr. <HI>Shepard,</HI> was a <HI>Death-wound</HI> unto the Soul of Mr. <HI>Mitchel,</HI> whose Ve∣neration for the Great Holiness, Learning, and Wisdom, of his Predecessor, caused him to <HI>La∣ment</HI> exceedingly the Loss of so Rich a Blessing, and begin his own publick Ministry, at <HI>Cambridge,</HI> with Sermons full of those <HI>Lamentations.</HI> Indeed when he had Occasion to mention his own Li∣ving <HI>Four years</HI> under Mr. <HI>Shepard</HI>'s Ministry, he added, <HI>Unless it had been four years living in Hea∣ven,
<PB N="58" REF="000790_0057_0FAA54A58C0FF788"/>
I know not how I could have more cause to Bless God wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h wonder, than for those Four years.</HI> Under an Affliction, which he so much Resented, the Comf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rt which he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ught for himself, he thus expressed: <HI>What a blessed thing is it to have the Med<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ator, the Man Christ Jesus to go unto, when I have n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Friend that I can fully speak to, and open all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and Ails into His Bosome? I think, were Mr.</HI> Shepard <HI>now alive, I would go and intreat his Counsel and Help, and Prayer. Why, now I may go freely into the Bosome of the Man Christ Jesus, who is able, faithful, tender hearted above the best of meer men. And I may Go, and tell him not only my Sorrows (and yet that is no small matter,) but also my Sins, all my Sins; though not without shame, yet without fearful Despair. I may Complain to Him of a strong Lust, and of an Hard Heart. And He does not only Pity me (and that He does more than any man could do) but is also fully able to Help me against Sorrow, yea, and against Sin too. And in Him, I may see, and take hold of the Pity, and Love, and Grace of God the Father, who through Him, is well-pleased.</HI> But that he might signalize his Affecti∣on to the Memory of his Predecessor, he speedi∣ly took the pains to peruse and publish the Ser∣mons of that Worthy man, upon the <HI>Parable of the Ten Virgins,</HI> which make a Volumn in <HI>Folio</HI>; with a most Excellent, and Judicious Preface of <HI>his</HI> thereunto. Which afterwards, was not with∣out its <HI>Recompence</HI> in the <HI>Providence</HI> of God, when after his own Death, his own Sermons upon, <HI>The
<PB N="59" REF="000790_0058_0FAA54A5F4D19370"/>
Glory to which God hath called Believers by Jesus Christ</HI> (carefully Transcribed, and so Transmitted, by Captain <HI>Laurence Hammond</HI> of <HI>Charlstown,</HI> to whose cares about it, the Church is now behol∣den for this Treasure,) were by some surviving Friends, Printed at <HI>London.</HI> And he whom I have once already compared unto <HI>Pollio,</HI> who Dy∣ed, when between Forty and Fifty years old, was in <HI>this</HI> also, like that Germane Divine, who left behind him a Book of Sermons, <HI>De vita aeterna,</HI> whereof <HI>Melchior Adam</HI> says, <HI>Non solum suae Con∣fessionis Homines omnium Ordinum in Deliciis habue∣runt, atque habent; sed etiam Adversariorum nonnulli, minus morosi probaverunt</HI>: Both <HI>Friends</HI> and <HI>Fees</HI> approved it. The young Gentlewoman, whom his Predecessor had married a little before his De∣cease, <HI>he</HI> now also married, upon the general Re∣commendations of that Widow unto him: and the <HI>Epithalamiums,</HI> which the Students of the Col∣ledge then Celebrated that Marriage withal, were expressive of the Satisfaction, which it gave unto all the Good people in the Vicinity. Howbeit, before this, he had addressed himself unto the Ve∣nerable old Mr. <HI>Cotton,</HI> for leave to become <HI>his</HI> Son-in-law, and Mr. <HI>Cotton</HI> prognosticating the E∣minency, which he would arrive unto, had given Leave unto it. But the Immature Death of that Hopeful young Gentlewoman, Mrs. <HI>Sarah Cotton,</HI> preventing so desirable a Match, made way for his pursuing and obtaining this other Settlement. Being so settled; he wholly gave himself up to
<PB N="60" REF="000790_0059_0FAA54A6C162A510"/>
the Services of his Ministry, with such a Disposi∣tion, as h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>essed in his <HI>Parting Advice</HI> to a∣nother, who Travelling from hence to <HI>England,</HI> had these words from him at his <HI>Farewel; My se∣rious Advice to you is, That you keep out of Company, as far as Christianity and Civility will give you leave; Take it from me; The Time spent in your Study, you will generally find spent the most Profitably, Comforta∣bly and Accountably.</HI></P>
<P>§ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <HI>Eighteen year</HI>▪ did he continue a Pastor to the Church of <HI>Cambridge.</HI> And as that which Encouraged him to Accept at first the Pastoral Charge of that Flock, was his being able to write that Character of them, <HI>That they were a Gracious, Savoury-spirited people, principled by Mr.</HI> Shepard, <HI>liking an Humbling, Mourning, Heart-breaking Ministry and Spirit; Living in Religion, Praying men and women: Here</HI> (said He) <HI>I might have Occasions of many sweet Heart-breakings before God, which I have so much need of</HI>! So the Conti∣nual <HI>Prayers</HI> of such a People to the Lord Jesus Christ, for him, doubtless contributed more than a little, unto his being furnished from Heaven with such Rich <HI>Treasures</HI> of <HI>Light</HI> and <HI>Grace,</HI> as made his <HI>Ministry</HI> richly serviceable unto them all. In this his <HI>Ministry,</HI> he Preached over a great part of the Body of <HI>Divinity.</HI> And as <HI>Paul</HI> appealed unto his two first Chapters to the <HI>Ephesi∣ans,</HI> thus in some Degree, an Appeal might have been made unto those Labours of this Admirable
<PB N="61" REF="000790_0060_0FAA54A79AC18C60"/>
Preacher, to Demonstrate his <HI>Knowledge of the Mystery of Christ.</HI> He made a most Entertaining <HI>Exposition</HI> on the Book of <HI>Genesis,</HI> and part of <HI>Ex∣odus</HI>; he made many Incomparable Discourses on the four first Chapters of <HI>John: Occasional Subjects,</HI> he also Handled many, with much Variety: He likewise kept a <HI>Monthly Lecture,</HI> where he largely Handled Mans <HI>Misery</HI> by Sin, and <HI>Salvation</HI> by Christ, and entred on the Doctrine of <HI>Obedience</HI> due thereupon; and vast Assemblies of People from all the Neighbouring Towns, reckoned it, highly worth their pains to Repair unto that <HI>Le∣cture.</HI> The <HI>Sermons</HI> wherewith he fed the Church of God, were admirably <HI>Well-Studied</HI>; they still smelt of the <HI>Lamp</HI>; and, indeed, if there were nothing else to prove it, yet the Notes which he wrote in his Preparations for his Publick Exerci∣ses, were Proof enough of his being an Indefati∣gable <HI>Student.</HI> He ordinarily medled with no Point, but what he managed with such an extra∣ordinary <HI>Invention, Disposition,</HI> and Copious <HI>Appli∣cation,</HI> as if he would leave no material thing to be said of it, by any that should come after him. And when he came to Utter what he had Prepa∣red, his Utterance had such a becoming <HI>Tuneable∣ness,</HI> and <HI>Vivacity,</HI> to set it off, as was indeed <HI>Ini∣mitable</HI>; though many of our Eminent Preach∣ers, that were in his Time, Students at the <HI>Colledge,</HI> did essay to Imitate him. It has been observed by others, as well as <HI>Jerom,</HI> that <HI>Quae firmiter con∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>epimus, bene loqui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>, siquidem Talia in Animae
<PB N="62" REF="000790_0061_0FAA54A853201A58"/>
Substantiam quasi Concoquendo sunt Conversa</HI>: and our <HI>Mitchel,</HI> having accordingly well <HI>Concocted</HI> what he was to Deliver, with clear and strong Thoughts upon it, expressed it with a Natural <HI>E∣loquence,</HI> which, (as <HI>Tully</HI> says of all True <HI>Elo∣quence</HI>) cast the Hearers into <HI>Wonderment.</HI> Pro∣found <HI>Meditation</HI> having first, in his <HI>Heart</HI> got rea∣dy a well composed <HI>Meat-Offering</HI> for the House of God, his <HI>Tongue</HI> was as the <HI>Pen of a Ready Writer</HI> to bring it forth: and his Auditories usually count∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d themselves at a <HI>Feast</HI> with the Inhabitants of Heaven, while he was thus Entertaining of them. His Preaching was not that which Dr. <HI>Manton</HI> would justly Rebuke under the Name of <HI>Gentle∣man-Preaching:</HI> or, a sort of <HI>Harangue</HI> finely La∣ced and guilded with such <HI>Phalerate Stuff,</HI> as plain∣ly Discovers the Vanity of them, that <HI>jingle</HI> with it: but he still spoke, as reckoning, that, if <HI>Seneca's</HI> Philosopher was to Remember, <HI>Ad miseros vocatus as; o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>em laturus Naufragis, Captis, Aegris, Inten∣tae securi subjectum praestantibus Cap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI>: Such a thing is much more to be Remembred by a <HI>Mini∣ster</HI> of the Lord Jesus Christ. Hence, though he had a very <HI>Clean Style,</HI> and spoke, —<HI>Munda, sed e medio, Consuetaque verba</HI>;— by the same token, that when he had once used one word, in the Pulpit, which it may be, no body else besides himself would have so severely <HI>Criticised</HI> upon, af∣ter he came home, he wrote a severe Animadversion upon it; <HI>I was after, in my self Ashamed of it,</HI> (he wrote) <HI>as being a Phrase too Coarse for the Pulpit!</HI>
<PB N="63" REF="000790_0062_0FAA54A8F52C6D40"/>
Nevertheless, he had also a <HI>Plain Style,</HI> for which he might have been justly called, as <HI>Melancthon</HI> was by <HI>Keckerman, Ille, ut sie dicam, Perspicuitatis Genius:</HI> but so pungently improved, that what he <HI>spoke,</HI> was <HI>felt</HI> by his Hearers, as <HI>Quick and Power∣ful.</HI> One, that hath addressed the World with a Treatise of <HI>Ecclesiastical Rhetorick,</HI> saith, <HI>Credat mi∣hi Ministerii Candidatus; Tria sunt, quae valde com∣mendant Concionatorem; Vocis Amabilitas, Epitheto∣rem Emphasis, et Connexionis Concinnitas</HI>: Now all of these <HI>Three Commendations</HI> did belong to the Preaching of our <HI>Mitchel.</HI> And, as it was the Re∣mark of that then <HI>Matchless</HI> Preacher, <HI>Bucholtzer,</HI> to whom I have often in my Thoughts <HI>Match'd</HI> our <HI>Mitchel, That a Preacher was known by his Pero∣ration,</HI> So 'twas Remark't of our <HI>Mitchel,</HI> that tho' he were all along in his Preaching, <HI>as a very Love∣ly Song of one that hath a pleasant Voice,</HI> yet as he drew near to the close of his Exercises, his Come∣ly <HI>Fervency</HI> would Rise to a Marvellous measure of <HI>Energy</HI>; He would speak with such a Trans∣cendent <HI>Majesty</HI> and <HI>Liveliness,</HI> that the People (more <HI>Thunderstruck</HI> than they that heard <HI>Cicero</HI>'s Oration for <HI>Ligarius</HI>) would often <HI>Shake</HI> under his Dispensations, as if they had Heard the Sound of the <HI>Trumpets</HI> from the <HI>Burning Mountain,</HI> and yet they would <HI>Mourn</HI> to think that they were going presently to be Dismissed from such <HI>an Heaven upon Earth.</HI> He had indeed an Uncommon mea∣sure of that Priviledge, that is Reported of <HI>Buch∣oltzer, Ut, licet nonnisi finita Hora Altera per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>raret,
<PB N="64" REF="000790_0063_0FAA54A9AD4003D0"/>
nullum tamen Audiendi Taedium, vel e media cuiquam plebe, Obrepserit:</HI> though he Preached <HI>Long Ser∣mons,</HI> the People were never weary of <HI>Hearing</HI> them. Vast was the Happiness of the <HI>Scholars</HI> at the Col∣ledge, and (in them) of all the <HI>Churches</HI> in the Country, while <HI>Cambridge</HI> was Illuminated with such a Ministry! It was a Reflection upon this matter, long since Printed unto the World; <HI>Rea∣son and Prudence requireth, that the Minister of that Place, be more than Ordinarily endowed with Learn∣ing, Gravity and Wisdom, Orthodoxy, Ability, Excellent Gifts in Preaching, that so the Scholars, which are De∣voted to be Preachers of the Gospel, might be seasoned with the Spirit of such an</HI> Elijah: <HI>In which Regards this Holy man of God, was eminently furnished; and his Labours were abundantly blessed: For, very many of the Scholars bred up in his time (as is observ∣ed) do savour of his Spirit, for Grace, and a most at∣tractive manner of Preaching.</HI> Truly, as it was no rare thing for a <HI>German</HI> Divine to give solemn Thanks unto God, <HI>For being Born in the Dayes of</HI> Melancthon; so there is many a <HI>New English</HI> Di∣vine, who has given Thanks to God, <HI>For their be∣ing at ths Colledge in the Dayes of <HI>Mitchel</HI>.</HI> But it must here be added, That altho' the chief Labours of this Exemplary <HI>Pastor,</HI> were in the <HI>Study,</HI> and the <HI>Pulpit,</HI> yet he did not think himself thereby Excused from those <HI>Pastoral Visits</HI> which his Flock expected from him. Herein he visited at fit Hours, which he set apart for it, the several Fami∣lies of his <HI>Flock</HI>; not upon Trivial Designs, but
<PB N="65" REF="000790_0064_0FAA54AAB5B3C1C8"/>
with serious and solemn Addresses, to their Souls upon the matters of their <HI>Everlasting Peace</HI>; and the <HI>Gildas Salvianus</HI> of Mr. <HI>Baxter,</HI> was herein out <HI>Mitchel</HI> himself, as well as much Read and Priz'd by this Faithful <HI>Pastor,</HI> who <HI>Watch'd for Souls, as one that was to give an Account.</HI></P>
<P N="10">§ 10. What he was in his <HI>Ministry,</HI> the same he was in his <HI>Discipline,</HI> when <HI>Offences</HI> arose, that called for his Consideration, in the Church where∣to he was Related: <HI>Faithful, Prudent, Zealous, Ho∣ly,</HI> and like an <HI>Angel</HI> of a Church, <HI>Not Bearing with those that are Evil.</HI> When a publick <HI>Admoni∣tion</HI> was to be Dispensed unto any One, that had offended scandalously, one could have heard no∣thing more <HI>Pathetical,</HI> or more <HI>Powerful,</HI> than his Discourses, on those unwelcome Occasions: the Hearers would be all Drowned in Tears, as if the <HI>Admonition</HI> had been, as indeed he would with much <HI>Artifice</HI> make it be, directed unto them <HI>all</HI>: bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> such would be the <HI>Compassion</HI> &amp; yet the <HI>Gravity,</HI> the <HI>Majesty,</HI> the Scriptural and Awful <HI>Pungency</HI> of these his Dispensations, that the <HI>Conscience</HI> of the Offender himself, could make no Resistance there∣unto. But when the Lord Jesus Christ in ends to make any <HI>Steward</HI> in His House, em<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nently <HI>Prudent</HI> and <HI>Faithful,</HI> He commonly <HI>Tries</HI> that Person, by Ordering some very Difficult <HI>Church-Cases</HI> to arise, quickly after his fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st Entrance up∣on the <HI>Stewardship</HI> Some such Thorny <HI>Church-Cases</HI> did soon Exercise the Thoughts of this truly
<PB N="66" REF="000790_0065_0FAA54ABA2620C38"/>
<HI>Aged young man</HI>; in all of which he conscienti∣ously considered the <HI>Rights</HI> of the Fraternity to Judge in their own <HI>Church Cases,</HI> as that Renown∣ed Minister, and Martyr, the Blessed <HI>Cyprian</HI> did, when he could say in one of his Epistles unto his Flock, <HI>From the very Beginning of my Ministry, I de∣termined to do nothing without the Consent of my People</HI>: and again, <HI>All Church Affayrs, as mutual Respect requireth,</HI> [in commune tractabimus] <HI>we will manage them in common</HI>; and again, He would Restore and Admit none but those who <HI>should plead their cause before all the people</HI>; [Acturi apud plebem universam Causam suam:] and order none of their matters, but [praesentibus et Judi∣cantibus vobis,] <HI>with their Presence and Judgment.</HI> And if Mr. <HI>Mitchel</HI> had heard any reckon the <HI>Liberty</HI> of the <HI>Brethren</HI> thus confessed in the Dayes of <HI>Cyprian,</HI> to be an <HI>Apostasy</HI> from <HI>what was in the Beginning,</HI> he would have ask'd them, whether they reckon'd the Loss of this <HI>Liberty</HI> afterwards, in the Rise of <HI>Popery,</HI> to be any <HI>Beginning,</HI> or Tendency towards <HI>Church-Reformation,</HI> &amp; Recovery? Now tho' this <HI>Liberty</HI> of the <HI>Brethren,</HI> which our <HI>Mitchel</HI> according to the Primitive <HI>Congregational Church-Discipline</HI> allow'd, be that wherein for the most part the Repose of the <HI>Pastors</HI> has been by the compassionate wisdom of our Lord Jesus Christ provided for,) some <HI>Trouble</HI> sometimes has arisen to the <HI>Pastors</HI> from the <HI>Brethrens</HI> abuse of their Liberty, which has call'd for much <HI>Pati∣ence</HI> and <HI>Prudence</HI> in those that have the Rule o∣ver
<PB N="67" REF="000790_0066_0FAA54ABEC04D838"/>
them. And so there did unto our <HI>Mitchel,</HI> who on this Occasion, as on all others, was rea∣dier still to condemn himself, than any others▪ and once particularly, recorded this passage in his Diary. <HI>I was Troubled,</HI> [at some improper Cavils from the Brethren] <HI>and I fear spake not so Lovingly and Prudently as I should have done. I feel my Spirit ready to rise, and forget my Principles of Lying Low in the Dust, and bearing with others In∣firmities, and becoming all Things to all men, for their Edification. Oh! Lord Humble me, and Teach me how to carry it!</HI> Thus did this Excellent person write, when he was Enumerating his Humbling Circumstances, in a <HI>Secret Fast</HI> before the Lord. But there was an <HI>Harder Case</HI> than any of these, to Exercise him. Our <HI>Mitchel,</HI> presently upon his becoming the <HI>Pastor</HI> of <HI>Cambridge,</HI> met with a more than ordinary Trial, in that the Good Man, who was then the <HI>Praesident</HI> of the Colledge, and a Member of the Church, there was unaccoun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a∣bly fallen into the <HI>Briars</HI> of <HI>Antipaedobaptism</HI>; and being <HI>Briar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d</HI> in the <HI>Scrupl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> of that Perswasion, he not only forbore to present an <HI>Infant</HI> of his own unto the <HI>Baptism</HI> of the Lord, but also thought himself under some Obligation to bear his Testi∣mony in some Sermons, against the Administrati∣on of <HI>Baptism</HI> to any <HI>Infant</HI> whatsoever. The <HI>Brethren</HI> of the Church were somewhat vehement and vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lent in their signifying of their Dissatis∣faction, at the Obstruction, which the <HI>Reniten∣cies</HI> of that Gentleman, threatned unto the Peace∣able
<PB N="68" REF="000790_0067_0FAA54ADF7BD4D68"/>
Practice of <HI>Infant Baptism,</HI> wherein they had hitherto walked; and judged it necessary for the Vindication of the Churches Name abroad in the Countrey, and for the safety of the Con∣gregation at home, to desire of him, that he would cease <HI>Preaching</HI> as formerly, until he had better satisfied himself in the Point now Doubted by him. At these things, extream was the Uneasiness of our <HI>Mitchel,</HI> who told the Brethren, <HI>That more Light and less Heat would do better</HI>: but yet saw the zeal of some against this Good Man's Error, to push this matter on so far, that being but a <HI>Young man,</HI> he was likely now to be Embarassed in a Controversy, with so Considerable a Person, and with one who had been his <HI>Tutor,</HI> and a <HI>Wor∣thy</HI> and a <HI>Godly</HI> man. He could give this Ac∣count of it, <HI>Through the Churches being apt to Hurry on too Fast, and too Impatiently, I found my self much Oppressed; especially Considering my own Weakness to grapple with these Difficulties; This B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>siness did lye down and rise up, sleep and wake with me: It was a dismal thing to me, that I should Live to see Trut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> or Peace Dying or Decaying in poor</HI> Cambridge. But while he was with a <HI>Prudence</HI> incomparably be∣yond what might have been expected from a <HI>Young man,</HI> managing this <HI>Thorny Business,</HI> he saw cause to Record a passage, which perhaps will be judged worthy of some Remembrance. <HI>That Day</HI> (writes he, Decemb. 24 1653.) <HI>after I came from him, I had a strange Experience: I found Hurrying and Pressing Suggestions against</HI> Paedobaptism, <HI>and in∣jected
<PB N="69" REF="000790_0068_0FAA54AEC4836158"/>
Scruples and Thoughts whether the other way might not be Right, and</HI> Infant Baptism, <HI>an Invention of men: and whether I might with Good Conscience Baptise Children, and the like. And these Thoughts were Darted in with some Impression, and left a strange Confusion and Sickliness upon my Spirit. Yet me∣thought, it was not Hard to Discern that they were from the EVIL ONE.</HI> First, <HI>Because they were rather</HI> Injected, <HI>Hurrying Suggestions, than any deliberate Thoughts, or bringing any Light with them.</HI> Secondly, <HI>Because they were</HI> Unseasonable; <HI>Inter∣rupting me in my Study for the Sabbath, &amp; putting my Spirit into a Confusion, so as I had much a do, to do ought in my Sermon. It was not now a time to Study that matter; but when in the former part of the Week, I had given my self to that Study, the more I Studied it, the more Clear and Rational Light I saw for</HI> Pae∣do baptism. <HI>But now these Suggestions Hurryed me into</HI> Scruples. <HI>But they made me cry out to God for His Help; and He did afterward Calm and clear up my Spirit. I thought the End of them was,</HI> First, <HI>To shew me the Corruption of my</HI> Mind; <HI>How apt that was to take in Error, even as my</HI> Heart <HI>is to take in Lust.</HI> Secondly, <HI>To make me walk in</HI> Fear, <HI>and take hold on Jesus Christ to keep me in the Truth; and it was a check to my former</HI> Self Confidence, <HI>&amp; it made me fearful to go needlesly to</HI> Mr. D. <HI>for me∣thought I found a Venome and Poison, in his Insinuati∣ons and Discourses against</HI> Paedo-baptism. Thirdly, <HI>That I might be Mindful of the</HI> Aptness in others <HI>to be soon shaken in Mind, and that I might warn others
<PB N="70" REF="000790_0069_0FAA54B0118C4770"/>
thereof, and might know how to speak to them from</HI> Experience. <HI>And indeed my former</HI> Experience of Irreligious Injections, <HI>was some Help to me to Disco∣ver the nature of These. I Resolved also on</HI> Mr. HOokers <HI>Principle,</HI> That I would have an Argu∣ment, able to Remove a Mountain, before I would Recede from, or Appear against a Truth or Practice, received among the Faithful. <HI>After the Sabbath was over, and I had time to Reflect upon the Thoughts of those things, those Thoughts of Doubt de∣parted, and I Returned unto my former Frame.</HI> The Troubles thus Impending over the Church of <HI>Cam∣bridge,</HI> did Mr. <HI>Mitchel</HI> happily wade through; partly by much <HI>Prayer</HI> with <HI>Fasting,</HI> in Secret, before God, for the Good Issue of these things; partly, by getting as much Help as he could from the <HI>Neighbouring Ministers,</HI> to be Interposed in these Difficulti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s; and partly, by using much <HI>Meekness of Wisdom</HI> towards the Erroneous Gentleman; for whom our Mr. <HI>Mitchel</HI> continued such an E∣steem, that although his Removal from the Go∣vernment of the <HI>Colledge,</HI> and from his Dwelling place in <HI>Cambridge,</HI> had been procured by these Differences, yet when he Dyed, <HI>He</HI> Honoured him with an <HI>Elegy,</HI> from which I will transcribe one <HI>Stanza</HI> or two, because it very truly points out that Generous, Gracious, <HI>Catholick Spirit,</HI> which adorned that Person, who wrote it.</P>
<LG>
<L>Where Faith in <HI>JESUS</HI> is Sincere,</L>
<L>That Soul, He Saving, pardoneth;</L>
<L><PB N="71" REF="000790_0070_0FAA54B0713BF548"/>What wants or Errors else be there,</L>
<L>That may and do Consist therewith.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And though we be <HI>Imperfect</HI> here,</L>
<L>And in <HI>One Mind</HI> cant often meet,</L>
<L>Who <HI>know</HI> in part, in part may <HI>Err,</HI></L>
<L>Though <HI>Faith be</HI> One, <HI>All</HI> do not see't:</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Yet may we once the Rest obtain,</L>
<L>In Everlasting Bliss above,</L>
<L>Where Christ with <HI>Perfect Saints</HI> doth Reign,</L>
<L>In <HI>Perfect light,</HI> and <HI>perfect Love:</HI></L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Then shall we all <HI>Like-minded</HI> be,</L>
<L><HI>Faith's Unity</HI> is there full-grown;</L>
<L>There <HI>One Truth,</HI> all both <HI>Love and</HI> See,</L>
<L>And thence are Perfect made in One.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>There <HI>Luther</HI> both and <HI>Zuinglius,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Ridley</HI> and <HI>Hooper,</HI> there agree;</L>
<L>There all the truly Righteous,</L>
<L><HI>Sans</HI> Feud Live to Eternitie.</L>
</LG>
<P>But there was a <HI>special Design</HI> of Heaven, in Ordering these Trials to befal our <HI>Mithel,</HI> thus in the Beginning of his Ministry. He was here∣by put upon Studying and Maintaining the Do∣ctrine of <HI>Infant Baptism</HI>; and of Defending the <HI>Visible Interest</HI> of the <HI>Children</HI> of the Faithful in the <HI>Covenant of Grace,</HI> under the <HI>New</HI> Administra∣tion of it, as well as under the <HI>Old,</HI> wherein we all know the <HI>Infants</HI> of Believers enjoyed the <HI>Seal</HI> of being made <HI>Righteous by Faith.</HI> In the De∣fence
<PB N="72" REF="000790_0071_0FAA54B1368B0728"/>
of this <HI>Comfortable Truth,</HI> he not only Prea∣ched more than half a score ungainsayable Ser∣mons, while his own Church was in some Dan∣ger by the <HI>Hydrophobie</HI> of <HI>Anabaptism,</HI> which was come upon the Mind of an Eminent person in i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; but also when afterwards the Rest of the Churches were <HI>Troubled</HI> by a strong Attempt up∣on them from the <HI>Spirit of Anabaptism,</HI> there was a <HI>Publick Disputation</HI> appointed at <HI>Boston,</HI> two days together, for the clearing of the <HI>Faith,</HI> in this Article, this Worthy man was <HI>he,</HI> who did most Service, in this Disputation; whereof the Effect was, that although the <HI>Erring Brethren,</HI> as is usual in such cases, made this their Last Answer to the Arguments, which had cast them into much Con∣fusion, <HI>Say what you will, We will Hold our Mind!</HI></P>
<Q>[Concurrat veterum licet in Te Turba, potes Tu, Hac omnes una vincere voce, <HI>Nego:</HI>]</Q>
<P>Yet others were happily established, in the <HI>Right Wayes of the Lord.</HI> Nor was this all the Good and Great Work, for which this rare per∣son was marvellously prepared, by these Temptati∣ons: there is a further Stroke of our <HI>Church Hi∣story,</HI> to be here <HI>briefly</HI> Touched, though elsewhere more <HI>fully</HI> to be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
<P N="11">§ 11. <HI>New-England</HI> was a <HI>Wilderness</HI> Plant∣ed by a People, generally so Remarkable in their Holy Zeal, for the Ordinances belonging to the House of God, that for the sake of Enjoying the
<PB N="73" REF="000790_0072_0FAA54B1F1451150"/>
Administrations of those Ordinances with <HI>Scrip∣tural Purity,</HI> they had undergone the severe <HI>Perse∣cutions</HI> which at last Exiled them into that <HI>Ameri∣can</HI> Wilderness: And hence there were few peo∣ple of any Significancy, in the Transplantation, but what at their first Coming over, joyned them∣selves unto the <HI>full Communi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n</HI> of the Churches, in all <HI>special Ordinances,</HI> though many of them had (I say not, justifyably) made the <HI>Terms</HI> of their Communion so strict, that it might justly have been Reckoned a difficult thing for some <HI>Sincere Christians</HI> of smaller Attainments in <HI>Christianity</HI> to come up unto them. For this cause, although several of our <HI>Seers,</HI> did so far <HI>See</HI> the State, which our Matters would e're long devolve into, that they Laboured much to have the <HI>Principles</HI> of Truth concerning, <HI>The Church State of the Children born in the Churches,</HI> Declared and Asserted, in the <HI>Platform of Church Discipline,</HI> among the <HI>First Prin∣ciples of New England,</HI> nevertheless many Worthy men, were slow to make any <HI>Synodical Decision</HI> of those <HI>Principles,</HI> until there should arise more occa∣sion for the <HI>Practices,</HI> that were to be deduced from them. This Occasion did in Twenty or Thirty years time, come on with some <HI>Importunity</HI> and <HI>Impetuosity,</HI> when the Countrey began to be filled with the Adult <HI>Posterity</HI> of the <HI>First Planters</HI>; a∣mong which, there were Multitudes or Persons, who by the good Effects of a pious Education under the Means of Grace, observable upon them, in their Profession of the <HI>Faith,</HI> not contradicted
<PB N="74" REF="000790_0073_0FAA54B314A078C8"/>
by any thing scandalous in their <HI>Life,</HI> deserved a∣nother Consideration in the <HI>Churches,</HI> than what was allowed unto <HI>Pagans</HI>; and yet were not so far Improved, in all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Points of <HI>Experimental Godliness,</HI> that they c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uld boldly Demand an Ad∣mission unto the <HI>Mysteries,</HI> at the <HI>Table</HI> of the Lord; the Conditions whereof confined it unto persons that were sensibly <HI>Grown in Grace, and i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the Knowledge of the Lord Jesus Christ.</HI> The most of the Ministers <HI>then,</HI> and before <HI>then,</HI> in the Land were desirous to have the thus <HI>Qualified Posterity</HI> of the <HI>Faithful,</HI> acknowledged in the Churches, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the <HI>Nursery,</HI> from whence a successive supply of <HI>Communicants,</HI> was to be expected; and it wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> their Desire, that this <HI>Nursery</HI> might be <HI>Watered</HI> with <HI>Baptism,</HI> and <HI>Pruned</HI> with <HI>Discipline,</HI> as well as otherwise <HI>Dressed</HI> by the <HI>Ministry of the Word.</HI> Yea, they thought, that besides the Internal Bene∣fits of the <HI>New Covenant</HI> unto the <HI>Elect</HI> of God, the <HI>Sealing</HI> of that <HI>Covenant</HI> unto them, that were visibly the <HI>Right Subjects</HI> of it, would be an <HI>Assu∣rance</HI> from God, that when these persons grow up to years of Discretion, He would infallibly make them the <HI>Offer</HI> of His <HI>Covenant,</HI> and so continue the <HI>Gospel</HI> of it, among them: whereas if <HI>They</HI> and <HI>Theirs</HI> were no other accounted of than <HI>Heathens,</HI> there would not pass many Generations, before the <HI>Sacred Religion of Christ,</HI> would, through the just <HI>wrath</HI> of Heaven, be lost among them, in ut∣ter <HI>Heathenism.</HI> However, all men did not then <HI>see all things</HI>! When the Church of <HI>Roxbury</HI> par∣ticularly
<PB N="75" REF="000790_0074_0FAA54B3B2E4D6D0"/>
in the year 1653. was put upon Doing what was their Duty in this Respect, our <HI>Mitchel</HI> was yet (he said) <HI>in the Dark about it</HI>; he wished and wrote, <HI>That it might not yet be pressed</HI>; and added, <HI>The Lord teach me Humility, Modesty, Wis∣dom in these things!</HI> Many a day did this Excellent man spend now in <HI>Praying</HI> with <HI>Fasting</HI> before God; and when he was thus Engaged in the Exercises of a Sacred and Secret <HI>Fast,</HI> I find him, inserting <HI>this,</HI> as not the least cause of his being so Engaged: <HI>The Case of the Children of the Church, in Regard of the Doctrine and Practice about it. Oh! that God would show me His Mind, and Way clearly in those things: enable me to Teach them convincingly, and set upon the Practice thereof: and that the whole Countrey might be Guided aright therein; That</HI> Abra∣ham's <HI>Commanding Power might have its due Exer∣cise, as to the Children of our Churches. And that all the Remaining Knots, and Difficulties about</HI> Church-Discipline, <HI>and the Management of Christ's visible Kingdom, might once be clearly Resolved according to the Word. Lord, Humble me, and prosper my poor Studies, and Teach me to know and do thy whole Will herein! as</HI> Ezek. 43.11. And at another Time; <HI>The Points about</HI> Church Discipline, <HI>I have been long aiming to look more thoroughly into. Lord, Help and Guide me therein! and Grant that I may be kept from Extreams (the great Undoing of the World:) both from immoderate Rigidness, on the one Hand, either in Principles, Spirit, or Practice; and on the other hand, from wronging either Truth, or Conscience, by any sinful
<PB N="76" REF="000790_0075_0FAA54B440F10B08"/>
Compliance.</HI> To these Devotions, he joyned inde∣fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ble <HI>Studies</HI> upon the Great Question, then Agitated; and the <HI>Determination</HI> of the Question at last, was more Owing unto <HI>him,</HI> than unto any <HI>One man</HI> in the World: For He was a <HI>Great part</HI> in that Renowned <HI>Synod</HI>; that met a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Boston</HI> in the year 1662. The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of the <HI>Synod</HI> afterwards published, was chi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fly of his Composure, and when a most Elaborate Answer to that Result, was Published by some very worthy Persons, that were then <HI>Dissenters,</HI> the Hardest Service in the <HI>Defence</HI> was Assigned unto him. In fine, Our Lord Jesus Christ made this <HI>Great</HI> Man, even, while he was yet a <HI>Young</HI> man, one of the Greatest Instruments we ever had, of Explaining and Maintaining the <HI>Truths,</HI> relating to the <HI>Church-State</HI> of the <HI>Posteri∣ty</HI> in our Churches, and of the <HI>Church Care,</HI> which our Churches owe unto their <HI>Posterity:</HI> and I have laid before the Reader, one of the most Ex∣tensive and Expensive Labours, that exhausted his Life, when I have mentioned, <HI>The Propositions of the Synod about the Subject of Baptism.</HI> All that re∣mains necessary, to Illustrate this Paragr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ph of our H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>story, is to Desc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ibe in a line or two, the <HI>Dis∣position</HI> which our <HI>Mitchel</HI> did prosecute this <HI>Grand Concern</HI> withal; and I will therefore only <HI>Transcribe</HI> a Little from a Judicious Letter of hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, to Mr. <HI>Increase Mather,</HI> upon that Subject, which that Reverend Person afterwards Printed unto the World: with an Unanswerable Vindication
<PB N="77" REF="000790_0076_0FAA54B52BBA7540"/>
of these <HI>First Principles of New-England,</HI> both from the Imputations of <HI>Apostasy,</HI> by some ignorantly cast upon them, and from whatever other <HI>Ob∣jections</HI> might be advanced against them.
<Q><HI>As for the Substance of the Cause</HI> werein we have En∣gaged (saith he) I am daily more and more Confirmed, that it is the Cause of <HI>Truth,</HI> and of <HI>Christ,</HI> and that wherein, not a little of the <HI>Inter∣est of Christ's Kingdom,</HI> and of the <HI>Souls of men,</HI> is laid up. We have been Reflected upon by some, as <HI>seeking our selves,</HI> and Driving on, I know not what Design: though I cannot readily Imagine, what <HI>self Interest</HI> or <HI>self End,</HI> we here should be led by in this matter; Sure I am, that for my <HI>own part,</HI> I prejudice my self much, as to <HI>Name, Interest,</HI> and <HI>Ease,</HI> for my appearing in <HI>this Cause:</HI> Neither was I so unsensible, as not to feel it <HI>from the First.</HI> I know my self to be a poor, vile, sinful Creature, and I can with some feeling say, <HI>Chief of Sinners,</HI> and <HI>Least of Saints</HI>: but in this particular matter, I have often said, <HI>I wish my Brethren could see through me</HI>; for I know not any <HI>Design</HI> or <HI>Desire</HI> I have in it, in all the World, but only that the <HI>Will of God</HI> might be done among us, <HI>His Kingdom</HI> be ad∣vanced, these <HI>Churches,</HI> settled on <HI>Right Bases,</HI> and flourish in the wayes of <HI>Truth, Purity</HI> and <HI>Peace,</HI> and that the Good of the <HI>Souls</HI> of men might be promoted, both in this, and after Ge∣nerations. Touching the <HI>matter</HI> it self, that hath been in Debate, please to consider at Leasure, these <HI>Three Propositions.</HI></Q></P>
<P><PB N="78" REF="000790_0077_0FAA54B5F616AE00"/>
<Q>First, The <HI>whole Visible Church,</HI> under the <HI>New Testament</HI> is to be <HI>Baptised.</HI></Q></P>
<P><Q>Secondly, If a man be one in the <HI>Church</HI> (whether admitted at <HI>Age,</HI> or in <HI>Infancy</HI>) no∣thing less than <HI>Censurable-Evil,</HI> can put him out.</Q></P>
<P><Q>Thirdly, If the <HI>Parent</HI> be in the <HI>Visible Church,</HI> his Infant <HI>Child</HI> is so also.</Q></P>
<P><Q>Whether the Persons described in the <HI>Fifth Proposition</HI> of the <HI>Synod</HI> should be <HI>Baptised,</HI> as in a <HI>Catholick,</HI> or in a <HI>Particular</HI> Church State, is a∣nother Question: And I confess my self not altogether so peremptory in <HI>this Latter,</HI> is I am in the <HI>Thing</HI> it self; [viz. <HI>That they ought to be Baptised,</HI>] yet still I think, when all Stones are Turned it will come to this, <HI>That all the Baptised are and ought to be under Discipline in particular Churches.</HI></Q></P>
<P>And now 'tis more than time for us to Dismiss this part of our <HI>Mitchellian</HI> Pourtraiture, from any further <HI>Elaborations.</HI></P>
<P N="12">§ 12. Mr. <HI>Mitchel's</HI> Desire had been, <HI>To be kept from Extreams</HI>; and indeed there was nothing more <HI>Observable</HI> in his <HI>Temper,</HI> than such a Study of, a <HI>Temper</HI> in all Difficult Matters, as renders a Person <HI>amiable,</HI> wherever tis <HI>Observable.</HI> I re∣member, I have met with a Note of a very fa∣mous Preacher, who, in the midst of many <HI>Tem∣tations on both Hands,</HI> relieved himself by Interpre∣ting, from the Context, that Passage in Eccles 7.18. <HI>He that feareth God shall come forth from them
<PB N="79" REF="000790_0078_0FAA54B6745A6F70"/>
all</HI> to be meant of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Deliverance out of all <HI>Ex∣treams. The Fear of God</HI> in our <HI>Mitchel,</HI> had this Effect, and Reward: And his <HI>wise coming forth from all Extreams,</HI> was no where more Conspicu∣ous, than in those points of <HI>Church-Discipline,</HI> for the clearing of which he had been, (I may say <HI>Extreamly</HI>) exercised. Had the sweet, Charitable, Amicable <HI>Spirit,</HI> that Signalized this Good man, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>een expressed by all good men, as much as it was by him, a great part of the <HI>Ecclesiastical Dif∣ferences</HI> in the World had been evaporated, and it had not been so long before the Names of <HI>Pres∣byterian</HI> and <HI>Congregational,</HI> had been <HI>melted down</HI> into that <HI>One</HI> of <HI>United Brethren.</HI> It was the wish of our <HI>Mitchel,</HI> to have those Two Things, in the <HI>State</HI> of the <HI>Church,</HI> livelily Represented unto the <HI>Sense</HI> of the <HI>World.</HI> First, the <HI>Grace,</HI> and then at the same time, the <HI>Holiness,</HI> of the Lord Jesus Christ, the King of the <HI>Church</HI>: and for the Obtaining of such a Representation, he thought nothing more Effectual, than the <HI>middle way</HI>; For the <HI>Cildren</HI> of the Faithful, to be taken within the <HI>Verge of the Church,</HI> under the <HI>Wings</HI> of the Lord Jesus Christ, in his Ordinances, and under <HI>Church care,</HI> Discipline, and Government, and to be in a State of <HI>Initiation</HI> and <HI>Education,</HI> in the Church of God, and consequently to have <HI>Bap∣tism,</HI> which is the <HI>Seal</HI> of <HI>Initiation</HI>: But that they shall not come up to the <HI>Lords Table,</HI> nor be ad∣mitted unto an <HI>equal share,</HI> with the <HI>Communicants,</HI> in the Management of <HI>Church Affairs,</HI> peculiar to
<PB N="80" REF="000790_0079_0FAA54B773F12268"/>
<HI>them,</HI> until, as a Fruit of the aforesaid <HI>Helps</HI> and <HI>Means,</HI> they attain to such <HI>Qualifications,</HI> as may render their Admission fair, safe, and com∣fortable, both to themselves and others. His Words were, <HI>We make account, that if we keep</HI> Baptism <HI>within the Compass of the</HI> Non-Excommu∣nicable, <HI>and the</HI> Lords Supper, <HI>within the Compass of those that have</HI> (unto Charity) <HI>somewhat of the</HI> Power of Godliness (<HI>or,</HI> Grace in Exercise) <HI>we shall be near about the Right</HI> Middle-way <HI>of</HI> Church-Reformation. And hence, when he had pleaded with as Irresistible <HI>Reason,</HI> as Indefatiga∣ble <HI>Study,</HI> for the <HI>Grace</HI> of the <HI>Kingdom of Hea∣ven,</HI> to be exhibited in our Churches, by Admi∣nistring the <HI>Baptism</HI> of the Lord unto the <HI>Persons,</HI> and <HI>Infants</HI> of all, who <HI>understand the Doctrine of Faith,</HI> and <HI>publickly profess their Assent thereunto,</HI> and <HI>are not Scandalous in Life,</HI> and <HI>Solemnly own the Covenant of Grace before the Church, &amp; Subject them∣selves, and theirs unto the Government of the Lord in His Church</HI>: He then set himself to plead for the <HI>Holiness</HI> of that <HI>Kingdom,</HI> to be exhibited in the Churches, not only by <HI>Censuring</HI> the <HI>Baptised,</HI> when they fell into Scandalous Evils, but also by <HI>Requiring</HI> further degrees of <HI>Preparation,</HI> in those that they received unto the <HI>Supper</HI> of the Lord. Nothing was more agreeable unto him, than such a Notion of Things, as <HI>Polanus</HI> had, when Wri∣ting of the <HI>Lord's Supper,</HI> he had these words; <HI>Nec ad eam admittendi sunt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, nisi prius Pastoribus Ecclesiae exploratum sit, eos veram Fidei Doctrinam
<PB N="81" REF="000790_0080_0FAA54B80F6D8620"/>
recte tenere et profiteri, ac intelligere quid in sacra cae∣na agatur, quove fine, et seipsos probare possent, an si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t in Fide.—Quocirca etiam Catechumeni aut Imperiti, e vulgo; tamdiu differendi donec de Fide, et vita eorum Pastoribus probe constet.</HI> Now, because it may be a singular Service unto the Churches, to lay before them the Judgment of so Eminent a Person, up∣on a Concern of some Curious and Critical Con∣testation in them, I shall Reckon it no Digression from the Story of his <HI>Life,</HI> to Recite the Result of those Meditations, in the Digesting of which, no little part of his <HI>Life</HI> did Roll away. He thus wrote for his <HI>own</HI> satisfaction, on <HI>Januar.</HI> 4. 1664. And I shall be glad, if it may now be for my <HI>Reader's.</HI></P>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="propositions">
<HEAD>PROPOSITIONS.</HEAD>
<P N="1"><HI>I.</HI> It is a Necessary Qualification, in <HI>Worthy Receivers</HI> of the <HI>Lord's Supper,</HI> that they <HI>Examine themselves,</HI> and <HI>Discern the Lords Body.</HI> 1 Cor. 11 28, 29.</P>
<P N="2"><HI>II.</HI> Those whom the Church Admits to the <HI>Lord's Supper,</HI> must be such as she in Charity <HI>judgeth,</HI> that they can and will <HI>Examine them∣selves,</HI> and <HI>Discern the Lord's Body</HI>; Because she must Admit none, but such as are in Charity (or visibly) <HI>Worthy Receivers</HI>; and they only are in Charity <HI>Worthy Receivers,</HI> who in Charity have the <HI>necessary Qualifications</HI> of such. Either she must give it only to visibly <HI>Worthy Receivers,</HI> or she may give it to visibly <HI>Unworthy Receivers,</HI> which were to profane and pollute it. We
<PB N="82" REF="000790_0081_0FAA54B8E186F260"/>
must Dispence Ordinances, unto <HI>fit and proper</HI> Subjects, as Christ's <HI>faithful Stewards.</HI> 1 Cor. 4▪ 1, 2.</P>
<P N="3"><HI>III.</HI> None can be such <HI>Self-Examining</HI> and <HI>Discerning</HI> Christians without some <HI>Experience</HI> of a Work of <HI>Grace,</HI> (or without <HI>Grace in Exercise</HI>) so as to have in Experimental Savoury Acquain∣tance, with the <HI>Essentials</HI> of <HI>Effectual Calling,</HI> viz. <HI>Conviction</HI> of <HI>Sin</HI> and <HI>Misery</HI> by <HI>Nature, Illumi∣nation</HI> in the Knowledge of the <HI>Gospel,</HI> and <HI>Con∣version</HI> of Heart, by <HI>Repentance towards God, and Faith towards our Lord Jesus Christ.</HI> 1. <HI>Self-Exa∣mination</HI> implies both, that there is the <HI>Grace</HI> of <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Repentance</HI> (or of <HI>Vocation</HI>) the <HI>Matter</HI> to be Examined: And also an Ability to <HI>Re∣flect</HI> upon that <HI>Grace,</HI> that is and hath been wrought in us; to <HI>Prove</HI> it, and find it to be <HI>Approved,</HI> at least by a <HI>praeponderating Hope.</HI> 2. <HI>Discerning the Lord's Body,</HI> the shewing forth or Annunciation of His <HI>Death,</HI> imports some Acquaintance with, and Actual Eying of the main and most Spiritual <HI>Mysteries</HI> of the Gospel, concerning <HI>Christ,</HI> His <HI>Death, Righteousness, Re∣demption,</HI> and all the Benefits thereof; and thos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> as exhibited in this Ordinance of the <HI>Supper.</HI> 3. That a lively or special Exercise of <HI>Grace,</HI> (by Reviving and Renewing our <HI>Faith, Repen∣tance</HI> and <HI>Love</HI>) is required in Preparation for, and Participation of the <HI>Lord's Table,</HI> is abun∣dantly evident, both by the <HI>Sense</HI> of the Expres∣sions aforesaid, and by the <HI>Scope</HI> of this Ordi∣nance,
<PB N="83" REF="000790_0082_0FAA54B96D8F77A8"/>
which is to <HI>Seal</HI> not only <HI>Union,</HI> but <HI>Act∣ual Communion</HI> and <HI>Fruition.</HI> 1 Cor. 10.16. By the <HI>Active Use</HI> of all the <HI>Outward Senses,</HI> in Re∣ceiving the Sacrament, implying that there must be an Actual, and Active Use of <HI>Exercised Sen∣ses,</HI> in Reference to the <HI>Inward Part</HI> of it.</P>
<P N="4"><HI>IV.</HI> None can appear unto <HI>Rational Charity</HI> to have the <HI>Qualifications</HI> aforesaid, without <HI>Holding forth,</HI> the same in some way or other. Man can judge of <HI>Internal Qualifications,</HI> no way, but by <HI>External Signs. Invisible Grace</HI> is made <HI>visible</HI> to us by some Outward Tokens and Manifesta∣tions. Here, <HI>Esse, et Apparere, Non Esse, et Non Apparere,</HI> are all One.</P>
<P N="5"><HI>V.</HI> Besides a <HI>Doctrinal Knowledge</HI> of the Princi∣ples of Religion, there are <HI>Two Things</HI> Required to the <HI>Holding forth</HI> of <HI>Grace</HI> in Exercise (or of an Experimental Savoury Acquaintance with the <HI>Essentials</HI> of <HI>Effectual Calling</HI>) viz. 1. A Gracious <HI>Conversation.</HI> 2. Gracious <HI>Expressions.</HI> By a <HI>Gracious Conversation,</HI> I mean, not only Freedom from Notorious <HI>Scandal</HI> and <HI>Obstinacy</HI> therein, but a Conversation wherein <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he <HI>positive Fruits</HI> of <HI>Piety</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o appear, so as they that know the Parties, can give a <HI>positive Testimony</HI> for them. <HI>Gal.</HI> 5.6. Jam. 2.18.26. <HI>Gracious Expressions,</HI> or Words are, when a Person can so <HI>speak</HI> of the <HI>Essentials</HI> of <HI>Effectual Calling,</HI> as doth signify, not only a <HI>Doctrinal,</HI> but a <HI>Practical</HI> or <HI>Spiritual</HI> Ac∣quaintance therewithal. That these are Necssa∣ry to shew <HI>Grace in Exercise,</HI> appears; Because
<PB N="84" REF="000790_0083_0FAA54BBD04085C0"/>
1. <HI>Good Words</HI> are in Scripture made the great Sign of a <HI>Good Heart.</HI> Mat 12.34, 35, 37. Prov. 10.20. And if it be so, in <HI>Ordinary Con∣version,</HI> much more may this <HI>Sign</HI> be expected, when a man comes to <HI>Hold forth,</HI> and give <HI>Evi∣dence</HI> of the <HI>Grace</HI> that God has bestowed upon him, in Order to Partaking of the <HI>Lord's Table.</HI> 2. <HI>Confession with the mouth,</HI> is that by which <HI>Faith</HI> Evidences it self to be <HI>Saving</HI> and <HI>Effectu∣al.</HI> Rom. 10.9, 10. 3. It cannot be imagined, how a person can have had <HI>Experience</HI> of a Work of <HI>Grace,</HI> and that unto a <HI>Comfortable Discerning</HI> thereof in himself, but that he can <HI>speak of it,</HI> in some way or other, after a <HI>savoury manner.</HI></P>
<P N="6"><HI>VI.</HI> Hence, either a <HI>Relation of the work of Conversion,</HI> such as hath been ordinarily used, in most of our Churches, or <HI>Some-what Equivalent</HI> thereunto, is necessary in order unto <HI>Full Com∣munion,</HI> or, to Admission unto the <HI>Lords Table.</HI> There is an <HI>Equivalent</HI> thereunto. 1. When an Account of the <HI>Essentials</HI> of <HI>Conversion</HI> is given in way of <HI>Answers,</HI> unto <HI>Questions</HI> propounded thereabouts. 2▪ In a Serious, Solemn and Sa∣voury Profession, or Confession, <HI>De Praesenti,</HI> i. e. when a Person doth with <HI>Understanding</HI> and <HI>Af∣fection,</HI> express and declare himself sensible of his <HI>Sin</HI> and <HI>Misery,</HI> and Absolute need of <HI>Christ,</HI> his <HI>Believing,</HI> or Casting himself on <HI>Christ,</HI> in the <HI>Promise,</HI> for <HI>Righteousness</HI> and <HI>Life,</HI> and his unfaigned Purpose &amp; Desire, through the Grace and Strength of Christ, to Renounce every <HI>Evil
<PB N="85" REF="000790_0084_0FAA54C10644EB60"/>
way,</HI> and walk with God, in the wayes of <HI>New Obedience</HI>; pointing also to some special Truths, Considerations or <HI>Scriptures,</HI> that have or do affect his Soul with Reference to these Things, though he do not <HI>Relate</HI> the <HI>Series</HI> of former Passages and Experiences. 3. When a Person is <HI>eminently known</HI> to Excel in <HI>Gifts</HI> and <HI>Grace,</HI> (as a long approved Minister of the Gospel, or other eminently Holy Christian;) This, is more than <HI>Equivalent</HI> to such a <HI>Relation.</HI></P>
<P>The Sum is, The <HI>Modus Agendi,</HI> may be va∣rious and mutable, and much therein left unto the Prudence of <HI>Church Officers</HI>; But the <HI>Thing</HI> is necessary; <HI>viz.</HI> To <HI>Hold forth</HI> in one way or other, <HI>Experience</HI> of a Work of <HI>Grace,</HI> or a <HI>practical Acquaintance</HI> with the <HI>Essentials</HI> of <HI>Ef∣fectual Calling.</HI> The Reason is, Because without <HI>This,</HI> they cannot shew themselves, able to <HI>Ex∣amine themselves,</HI> and <HI>Discern the Lords Body,</HI> which is essentially Necessary to <HI>Worthy Receiving,</HI> and hence the <HI>Appearance</HI> of it Necessary, in a Subject of orderly Admission to the <HI>Lords Table.</HI> A man must make a <HI>Relation</HI> to himself; <HI>viz.</HI> By Reviewing of his <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Repentance,</HI> or at least an <HI>Equivalent</HI> present Renewing thereof, in Preparation for the <HI>Lords Table</HI>; i. e. To give himself a Comfortable <HI>Regular Admission</HI> there∣unto. And should he not <HI>Declare</HI> and <HI>Manifest</HI> such a Thing to the <HI>Church</HI> or <HI>Officers</HI> thereof, to give them a Comfortable Ground to Admit him?</P>
<P><PB N="86" REF="000790_0085_0FAA54C217959518"/>
<HI>Object.</HI> But why may it not Suffice, for a man publickly to say, <HI>I Believe on Christ, or do un∣feignedly Repent of my Sins?</HI> or to Consent to such Expressions being Read, or propounded unto him, without any more adoe?</P>
<P><HI>Answ.</HI> 1. He that can <HI>Groundedly</HI> so say, or profess before God, Angels and Men, that he <HI>hath,</HI> (yea, <HI>knows</HI> that he hath) unfeigned <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Repentance,</HI> can say somewhat more particularly to show the <HI>Reality</HI> of his Acquain∣tance with those things. And if he cannot say it, <HI>Groundedly,</HI> it is not meet to put him so to say.</P>
<P N="2">2. He that either <HI>Cannot,</HI> or <HI>Will not</HI> say any more than so, (especially in Times of such Light and Means, as we live in) he renders the <HI>Truth</HI> of his <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Repentance,</HI> Suspitious, so as that <HI>Rational Charity,</HI> cannot acquiesce in it. For all men know, that <HI>Faith</HI> is not dropt into mens Hearts out of the Clouds, with praevious, concomitant, and Subsequent Operations; or▪ if it was first wrought in <HI>Infancy,</HI> yet it will (especially when grown to such a Lively Exer∣cise, as fits for the <HI>Lords</HI> Supper) shew it self in <HI>Effects</HI>; Renewings, and Increasings, by the Word and Ordinances, so as a man will be able to hold forth some Experience of the Operations of Grace.</P>
<P N="3">3. That <HI>Mode</HI> of <HI>Profession,</HI> which the Ob∣jection
mentioneth, hath been found by plen∣tiful Experience, to be a Nurse of <HI>Formality,</HI> &amp; <HI>Irreligion.</HI> Now it is a Rule concerning the
<PB N="87" REF="000790_0086_0FAA54C280352578"/>
<HI>Modus Agendi,</HI> or such like circumstances, That when by <HI>Experience</HI> a thing proves Inconveni∣ent, and subject to Abuse, there ought to be an <HI>Alteration</HI> thereof.</P>
<P N="7"><HI>VII.</HI> Besides this, from the Qualifications Requisite to the <HI>Lords Supper,</HI> there be other Reasons Serving to confirm the Necessity of <HI>Fractical Confessions (viz.</HI> by Relations, or other∣ways, as was before said) in those that are Admitted to full Communion.</P>
<P>As 1. Let those <HI>Scripture Examples</HI> be consider∣ed, wherein the Grace wrought in the faithful, is Evidenced, or Collected, from the Lords Dealings with them in the Work of Conversi∣on, and Experiences relating thereto, or to the Fruits thereof. See 1 <HI>Thes.</HI> 1.4, 5, 6, 7, 9, 10. —Let those words be paraphrased according to their obvious Sense, they will make up a full <HI>Relation.</HI> And if <HI>Paul</HI> knew, or gathered the Grace that was in the <HI>Thessalonians,</HI> from such things as those, does it not show, that such things are a proper and rational Ground for us to gather Grace from? If they be <HI>famously known</HI> otherwise (as they were in that case to <HI>Paul</HI>) it sufficeth, as was above said; but o∣therwayes how should they be known, but from the parties own Mouth? So <HI>Col.</HI> 1.4—8.— Is there not a kind of Relation, of the work, and manner of the Conversion of those 3000. in <HI>Act.</HI> 2. Set down in that Chapter? And Consequently, the Substance of such a Relation,
<PB N="88" REF="000790_0087_0FAA54C36AF56020"/>
or Work, was then <HI>de facto,</HI> obvious to the Apostles And so, of the Conversion of <HI>Paul.</HI> Chap. 9. and of <HI>Cornelius,</HI> Chap. 10. Yea, if we look into most of the Examples in the <HI>Acts,</HI> Consider, if they be not more immediately Re∣ducible to [<HI>A manifestation of a Work of Grace</HI>] than to that of <HI>knowledge,</HI> and a <HI>Blameless Life? Paul</HI> had little to say, for a foregoing <HI>Blameless Life,</HI> to the Disciples of <HI>Damascus</HI>; but a work of <HI>Conversion</HI> he could hold forth to them, and a Profession, <HI>de praesenti,</HI> thereupon. So <HI>Act.</HI> 9.26, 27.</P>
<P N="2">2. Ministers, in giving the <HI>Lords Supper</HI> to Persons, do give a Great and Solemn Testimo∣ny <HI>to</HI> them, [<HI>Take, Eat, This is Christs Body, that was broken for you;</HI>] therefore surely they may take, and require a Solemn Testimony <HI>from</HI> them, and had not need to be Slight therein.</P>
<P N="3">3. The <HI>Power of Godliness</HI> will soon be lost, if only <HI>Doctrinal knowledge,</HI> and <HI>Outward Blame∣lesness</HI> be accounted sufficient, for all <HI>Church-Priviledges,</HI> and <HI>Practical Confessions,</HI> (or, Exa∣minations of mens Spiritual Estate) be laid a∣side. For that which People see to be Publick∣ly Required, and Held in Reputation, <HI>that</HI> will they look after, and usually <HI>no more,</HI> but con∣tent themselves with <HI>That.</HI> Consider; if this hath not been a reason of the Formality and Deadness, that hath overgrown many Churches.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><DATE><HI>January</HI> 4. 1664.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P>Thus did a Manuscript of this Worthy Mans, now in my Hands, <HI>Harmonize</HI> with a Notable
<PB N="89" REF="000790_0088_0FAA54C3FA37D2E8"/>
passage about the <HI>Bohemian</HI> Churches.</P>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 LANG="lat" TYPE="version">
<P>Demum, quia Objicieba∣tur, Fratres non habere Ec∣clesiam apertam cum plena Sanctorum Communione, sed Administrare Sacramenta Quibusdam tantum sibi ad∣dictis: Responsum fuit, Sancta dare non Sanctis, prohibuisse Christum; Christi∣anismumque a panitentia, auspicandum, non a Sacra∣mentis; neque Secundum Instituta Christi Absolutio∣nem nunciandam nisi Resi∣piscentibus et Credentibus, quod utrumque (Paenitenti∣am &amp; Fidem) ne Superfi∣ciarium sit et fallax, Exploratione Indigere; Ex∣ploratione vero Tempore Justo: et quia Nudis Sa∣cramentis Salutis Vim ad∣scribere, ex Opere Operato, Errorum in Papatu, Basis est, Errorem hunc corrigi non posse aliter, quam ut certa probatione, nec illae Subitanea, Cordium Arcana Revelentur, Novitiique diu &amp; caute tum Informentur, tum Explorentur.</P>
<P><HI>Ratio Discipl. Fatr. Bohem p. 4, 5.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 LANG="eng" TYPE="version">
<P>Because it was objected, That the Brethren have not an <HI>open Church,</HI> with the full Communion of Saints, but admininister the Sacraments only to <HI>some</HI> of their <HI>own party</HI>; It was Answered, That Christ hath forbid our Giving of <HI>Holy Things</HI> unto <HI>Ʋnholy Persons</HI>; and that Christia∣nity is to be Begun, with <HI>Repentance,</HI> and not with the <HI>Sacraments</HI>; and that according to the Institutions of our Lord, <HI>Absolution</HI> is not to be pronounced upon any but those that <HI>Repent</HI> and <HI>Believe</HI>; both of which (<HI>Repentance</HI> and <HI>Faith</HI>) that it may not be <HI>Superfi∣ciary,</HI> and <HI>Fallacious,</HI> it must have some <HI>Exploration</HI>; &amp; this <HI>Exploration,</HI> must have a <HI>Sufficient Time</HI> for it. And because to ascribe a <HI>Saving Vertue,</HI> unto the bare Sa∣craments <HI>Ex Opere Operato,</HI> is the Bottom of the Errors of <HI>Popery,</HI> this Error cannot otherwise be Corrected, than by this means; That
<PB N="90" REF="000790_0089_0FAA54C4AD1A6AD0"/>
by a <HI>certain,</HI> and no <HI>sudden Trial,</HI> the <HI>Secrets of mens Hearts</HI> may be laid open, and <HI>Novices</HI> may be, with a long Caution, both Instructed and Examined.</P>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<P><HI>Reader,</HI> If the Beating out of <HI>Truth</HI> in Contro∣versies, that have Risen among us, relating to our <HI>Church Discipline</HI> had not been the <HI>special Ser∣vice,</HI> wherein all our Churches beheld the Lord Jesus Christ making use of this our Learned, Able Holy, and no less <HI>Considerate,</HI> than <HI>Considerable <HI>Mitchel</HI>,</HI> I had not given thee so long an Enter∣tainment, as that of these <HI>Propositions; Propositions</HI>▪ which if they should in the Opinion of <HI>any,</HI> fall short of <HI>Demonstrations,</HI> and Contribute nothing to <HI>Unite</HI> and <HI>Settle</HI> the various Apprehensions of some very Worthy men among us, about an Im∣portant Point in our <HI>Church-Government,</HI> yet they will in the Opinion of <HI>all</HI> serve to express the <HI>Dispositions of Mind,</HI> which the rare Spirited Au∣thor of them did both <HI>Live</HI> and <HI>Dye</HI> withal. They show how much <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e was <HI>Against</HI> that <HI>Rigi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> Unscriptural, Uninstituted, and Unwarrantable Insisting upon <HI>Modes,</HI> wherein some of our Chur∣ches, had sinned sometimes against the <HI>Grace</HI> of the Lord Jesus Christ; and yet how much he was <HI>For</HI> all Scriptural and Rational <HI>Methods</HI> to pre∣serve the Churches from sinning against the <HI>Ho∣liness,</HI> which does <HI>Become those Houses of God for e∣ver.</HI></P>
<P N="13"><PB N="91" REF="000790_0090_0FAA54C5855157E8"/>§ 13. I have said, that the <HI>Life</HI> of our <HI>Mitchel</HI> was in a special manner Engrossed, by the <HI>Servi∣ces</HI> of Explaining, Maintaining and Perfecting those <HI>Principles,</HI> whereby the Christian Religion▪ must be preserved, with a True and Pure <HI>Church-State</HI> among us, and Conveyed and Secured unto Posterity: and this Leads me to that part of his Character, which Distinguished him, as much as any One whatsoever; Namely, <HI>A Care of all the Churches.</HI> Our Lord Jesus Christ complains, <HI>That the Children of this World are</HI> (for so I read it) <HI>wiser for their own Generation, than the Children of Light.</HI> But our <HI>Mitchel</HI> was <HI>Wise for his Genera∣tion,</HI> and Exercised his <HI>Wit</HI> with much Contri∣vance, and much Diligence, that his <HI>Generation,</HI> even the Faithful People of God in the World, might be accommodated in all their Interests. He was Endued with a certain soaring and se∣rious <HI>Greatness of Soul,</HI> which rendred <HI>Fly-catching</HI> too low a Business for him; though he were One of a very <HI>Lowly Spirit</HI> In his Disposition to be al∣ways Condemning of himself, yet he nourished in himself a Generous Disdain of <HI>Low,</HI> Little, Trifling Matters, and was of a <HI>Leading Spirit</HI> where hard Service was called for, and of a <HI>Pub∣lick Spirit,</HI> for Doing of Service to as many as he could: His Thoughts moved in a <HI>large Sphere</HI> of <HI>Usefulness,</HI> and he was continually projecting how to <HI>Do good,</HI> in the most extensive manner unto more than an whole Countrey. The <HI>Bucholtzeri∣an</HI>
<PB N="92" REF="000790_0091_0FAA54C62E9FA758"/>
Expression of the Apostolical ΠΑΝΤΑΧΟΥΣΙΑ might be transferred into our Account of Mr. <HI>Mitchel: <HI>He was a Circle, whereof the Center was at</HI></HI> Cambridge, <HI>and the Circumference took in more than all</HI> New-England. Hence, when he set apart his <HI>Dayes</HI> for Secret <HI>Prayer</HI> with <HI>Fasting</HI> before God, he would Recapitulate in his private Pa∣pers, the Humbling Occasions for <HI>Supplication,</HI> which he saw, not only in Afflictive Things on his own particular <HI>Flock,</HI> but also in all the <HI>sad Sights,</HI> which in Disasters either upon the <HI>Civil</HI> or Sacred <HI>Concerns</HI> throughout all our <HI>Three Colonies,</HI> and all <HI>Gradual</HI> Decayes of our <HI>Glory,</HI> occurr'd unto him; yea, and he would then Travel so far, as to Observe the Condition of the Church throughout Great <HI>Britain,</HI> and the Nations of the <HI>Europaean</HI> World: and all these Occasions of <HI>Dis∣tress</HI> and <HI>Request,</HI> he would enumerate before the Lord, with the Matters of his own <HI>Everlasting Welfare.</HI> From the same <HI>Heroick Vertue</HI> (as I may properly call it) in him it was, that in the <HI>Weekly Meetings</HI> of the Neighbouring Pastors, after the <HI>Weekly Lectures</HI> in the Towns which he could vi∣sit; and at all other such <HI>Meetings,</HI> he would with a most becoming <HI>Discretion</HI> and <HI>Modesty,</HI> be still putting forward <HI>something</HI> or other, that might be for <HI>General Advantage</HI>: And when the Ministers met at any time so much without <HI>Advantageous Effects</HI> of their Discourses, that it could be said, The <HI>Time</HI> had been <HI>Smoaked</HI> away to no purpose, he would be Troubled at it; It caused him once
<PB N="93" REF="000790_0092_0FAA54C6EB5C7E90"/>
to write this Lamentation; <HI>Little done! I have begun to feel the sadness of the present time, and the Lord's withdrawing from us and our Chariot wheels taken off: I find that in all Societies, where I have any thing to Do, Common wealth, and Church and Colledge, things stick, and we draw Heavily, and No∣thing can be gotten forward: All things, and all the Spirits of men, seem to be off the Hinges: Oh! Lord, Affect my Heart therewithal!</HI> In this Lamentation, the Reader finds the <HI>Colledge</HI> mentioned, and in∣deed the <HI>Colledge</HI> was nearer unto his <HI>Heart,</HI> than it was to his <HI>House,</HI> though next adjoyning to it. He was himself an Accomplished <HI>Scholar,</HI> and he loved a <HI>Scholar</HI> dearly; but his Heart was fervent∣ly set upon having the Land all over Illuminated with the Fruits of a <HI>Learned Education.</HI> To this End, he became a <HI>Father</HI> to the <HI>Colledge,</HI> which had been his <HI>Mother,</HI> and sought the Prosperity of that Society, with a very singular Sollicitude: but among other Contrivances which he had for the Prosperity of the <HI>Colledge,</HI> One was, <HI>A Model for the Education of Hopeful Students at the Colledge in</HI> Cambridge. His Proposals were, for Septennial <HI>Subscriptions</HI> by the more Worthy and Wealthy Persons, in this poor Wilderness; to be Disposed of by <HI>Trustees</HI> (namely, the Magistrates and Mi∣nisters of the <HI>six next Towns,</HI> for the time being, with seven other Gentlemen by them Chosen out of the said Towns, of which any <HI>Seven</HI> to be a <HI>Quorum,</HI> if three Ministers were among them,) who should single out <HI>Scholars</HI> eminently preg∣nant
<PB N="94" REF="000790_0093_0FAA54C961A7CC88"/>
and pious, and out of this Bounty support them in such Studies, as they should by these <HI>Trus∣tees</HI> be directed unto, until they had either <HI>perfor∣med</HI> such profitable Services, as were Imposed on them in the <HI>Colledge</HI> it self, or <HI>prepared</HI> themselves for other Services abroad in the World. He was mightily affected with a Passage of <HI>Luther's, If e∣ver there be any Considerable Blow given to the De∣vils Kingdom, it must be by Youth excellently Educa∣ted. And therefore,</HI> Res seria est, Ingens est, <HI>It is a serious Thing, a Weighty Thing, and a Thing that hath much of the Interest of Christ, and of Christianity in it, that Youth be well Trained up, and want no Helps for that end; that Schools, and School Masters, and poor Scholars be mentained. It is the Flourishing of a Common Wealth, to be well furnished with Learned, Worthy and Able men for all Purposes. And God will not give us such men by Miracle, seeing He hath vouchsafed us other wayes, and means to obtain them. Learning is an Unwelcome Guest to the Devil, and therefore he would fain Starve it out. But we shall never long retain the Gospel, without the Help of Learning. And, if we should have no Regard unto Religion, even the Outward Prosperity of a People in this World, would necessary Require Schools and Learned men. Alas, that none are carryed with Alacrity and Seri∣ousness to take care for the Education of Youth, and to Help the World with Eminent and Able men.</HI> 'Twas from Considerations, like these of <HI>Luther's,</HI> that he did with an Accurate and judicious Pen,
<PB N="95" REF="000790_0094_0FAA54DF03476AA0"/>
shape these <HI>Proposals.</HI> But, if <HI>New England</HI> then had not many Persons in it, of the same In∣clination with Pope <HI>Paul</HI> 2. who pronounced them, <HI>Hereticks,</HI> that should mention the Name of an <HI>Academy,</HI> and exhorted People, that they would not put their Children to <HI>Learning,</HI> inas∣much, as it was enough if they could but <HI>Read</HI> and <HI>Write</HI>; yet, through the Discouragements of <HI>Poverty</HI> and <HI>Selfishness,</HI> the <HI>Proposals</HI> came to <HI>nothing.</HI> Moreover, the Remarkable <HI>Acuteness</HI> joined with an Extraordinary <HI>Holiness,</HI> in this Renowned man, caused the <HI>Churches,</HI> in all Quar∣ters far and near, when their Difficult <HI>Church-Cases</HI> called for the Help of <HI>Councils,</HI> to make their Applications unto <HI>Cambridge,</HI> for Mr. <HI>Mitchel</HI> to come and Help them in their Difficulties. And in these <HI>Councils,</HI> as well as when <HI>Weighty Cases</HI> have been laid before the <HI>Elders</HI> of the Churches, by the the <HI>General Courts,</HI> though usually most of the Ministers present were <HI>Elder</HI> than he, yet the <HI>Sense</HI> and <HI>Hand</HI> of no Man, was relied more upon than <HI>His,</HI> for the Exact <HI>Result</HI> of all. With so much humble Wisdom and Caution, did he <HI>Temper</HI> the <HI>Significant For∣wardness</HI> at <HI>Well-Doing</HI> which he still carryed a∣bout him, that the Disproportion of <HI>Age,</HI> hin∣dered not the most Aged, and Able, and Vene∣rable <HI>Angels</HI> in our Churches, from their Paying a very strange Respect unto him. However he Encountred with such <HI>Temptations</HI> as must <HI>Buffet</HI> all that have in them, any thing of <HI>Significancy</HI>;
<PB N="96" REF="000790_0095_0FAA54DF2EF777D0"/>
For which cause, Once particularly, when <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> had been Admirably Acquitting himself in an Undertaking of Great Consequence to the Churches, he came home, and wrote these words. <HI>My Spirit was carryed out in too much forward∣ness: I see cause to be deeply abased and Loath my self, and hang down my Head before God and Men. How do I marr Gods Work, and marr what He gives me therein, by my own Folly! Sometimes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> am ready to Resolve to put forth my self no more in publick Work, but keep my self Silent, and un∣ingaged, as I see others do. But then I perceive, that this Tasteth of Forwardness and Pride. Lord, Give me more Wisdom to manage and demean my self! But if thy Service and Honour may be promoted by my Weakness and Folly, Let me be willing to be Vile, that God may be Exalted.</HI> 2 Sam. 6.21, 22. Upon the whole, he was unwilling to affect such an <HI>Un∣serviceable Privacy,</HI> that they who passed by his House, might say, <HI>Hic situs est <HI>Mitchellus</HI>,</HI></P>
<P N="14">§ 14. I know not how far that Learned <HI>Frenchman,</HI> who Writes, <HI>The Conformity of the Con∣gregational Church-Government unto that of the Anci∣ent Primitive Christians,</HI> hath seen verified his Ob∣servation, <HI>All Disinterested persons may easily be per∣swaded that the Congregational Communion, retains most of the Apostolick, because it is not only the Cream and Best of the others, but also because it hath more Charity. 'Tis very rarely seen</HI> (saith he) <HI>that any One of the Congregational Way, does not Love all
<PB N="97" REF="000790_0096_0FAA54E08A4C1BC0"/>
Good men of what Communion soever they be, and that they do not speak of them, as of the True Churches of Jesus Christ: whereas even the most Sober and honest party of the Episcopal men, and some of the Presbyterians, are so strongly possessed with Prejudices against those of Congregations, that they are in their Account, no better than Hypocrites, Schis∣maticks, and men of strange Enthusiasms.</HI> If any of the <HI>Congregational way</HI> do not answer this Character, Let these Words Condemn <HI>them</HI>; as I know those of the <HI>Presbyterian way</HI> in this Country, have by their <HI>Charitable Temper,</HI> much Confuted that part of the Discourse, by which they are here Characterized. But the Observa∣tion I am sure, was verifyed in our <HI>Mitchel</HI>; who was one fully Satisfyed and Established in the <HI>Congregational way</HI> of <HI>Church Government,</HI> and yet had a <HI>Spirit of Communion</HI> for all <HI>Godly men</HI> in other <HI>Forms,</HI> and was far from Confining of <HI>God∣liness</HI> unto his own. It was a frequent Speech with him, <HI>The Spirit of Christ, is a Spirit of Communion</HI>! And I can tell, what he would have said, if he had lived to see the Books of so Ridiculous a <HI>Schismatick,</HI> as he that has made him∣self Infamous by attempting to prove, <HI>That where there is no Episcopal Ordination, there is no True Church, Minister, Sacrament, or Salvation.</HI> His <HI>Great worth</HI> caused him to be called, forth several times, with an <HI>Early</HI> and <HI>Special</HI> Respect form the <HI>General Court</HI> of the Colony, to Preach on the Greatest Solemnity that the Colony afforded;
<PB N="98" REF="000790_0097_0FAA54E140FAFDE8"/>
Namely, <HI>The Anniversary Election of Governour &amp; Magistrates</HI>: And one of the Sermons which he Preached on those Occasions, was after his Death, published unto the World, under the Title of, <HI>Nehemiah upon the Wall.</HI> In that Sermon, Reader, Take notice of the Discovery which he gave of his own <HI>Chatholick Charity,</HI> when he says,
<Q>Do not wrong and marr an Excellent work, and Profession, by Mixing and Weaving in <HI>Spurions Principles,</HI> or <HI>Practices</HI>; as those of <HI>Separation, <HI>Anabaptism, Morellian</HI></HI> (Anarchical) Confusion. If any would secretly 'twist in, and espouse such things as those, and make them part of our <HI>Interest,</HI> we must needs Renounce it as none of <HI>our Cause,</HI> no part of the End, and Design of the Lords faithful Servants, when they followed him <HI>into this Land, that was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sown. Separation</HI> and <HI>Anabaptism,</HI> are wonted Intruders, and seeming Friends, but secret fatal <HI>Enemies,</HI> to <HI>Reformation.</HI> Do not, on pretence of avoiding <HI>Corruption,</HI> run into <HI>Sinful Separation</HI> from any <HI>True Churches</HI> of God, and that is <HI>Good</HI> there∣in; and yet it is our <HI>Errand into the Wilderness</HI> to Study and Practise True <HI>Scripture-Reformation,</HI> and it will be our <HI>Crown,</HI> in the Sight of God and Man, if we find it and hold if, without <HI>Adulterating deviations.</HI></Q>
Thus, though he were a <HI>Reformer,</HI> yet he had nothing in him of a <HI>Donatist</HI>: For which cause Mr. <HI>Baxter</HI> hearing of him, said, <HI>If an Oecumenical Council could be ob∣tained,</HI> Mr. Mitchel <HI>were worthy to be it's Mo∣derator.</HI>
<PB N="99" REF="000790_0098_0FAA54E1F2CFCC18"/>
And this Disposition of <HI>Charity,</HI> in him, was Rewarded, with the Respects, which he found from Learned and Pious men, that were in many things not of his own perswasion: Such <HI>Holiness,</HI> and <HI>Patience,</HI> and sweet <HI>Condescension,</HI> were his Incomparable <HI>Abilities</HI> accompanied withal, that Good men, who otherwise distered from him would still speak of him with Reve∣rence. To give one Particular Instance: 'Tis well known that the Reverend <HI>Charles Chancey,</HI> Praesident of the Colledge, and a Neighbour in the Town and Church, with our much younger <HI>Mitchel,</HI> at the Time of the <HI>Synod,</HI> zealously <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd publickly, by <HI>Pen</HI> as well as by <HI>Speech,</HI> op∣posed the <HI>Synodalian</HI> Principles whereof Mr. <HI>Mitchel</HI> was no small <HI>Defender</HI>: But so far was the Dissent between them, in the very <HI>Heat</HI> and <HI>Heighth</HI> of all the Controversy, from causing the Reverend Old Man to Handle his Antagonist, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n any measure as the Angry <HI>Dioscorus</HI> did the Dissenting <HI>Flavian,</HI> in the Council of <HI>Ephesus,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat he would commonly say of him, <HI>I know no man in this World, that I could Envy so much, as Worthy</HI> Mr. Mitchel, <HI>for the Great Holiness, Learning, Wisdom and Meekness, and other Quali∣ties of an Excellent Spirit, with which the Lord Jesus Christ hath Adorned him.</HI></P>
<P N="15">§ 15. And shall we a little more particular∣ly Describe that <HI>Holiness,</HI> of this <HI>Excellent Man,</HI> which we have so often mentioned? It is
<PB N="100" REF="000790_0099_0FAA53C5DA0E2698"/>
an Aphorism of a <HI>Machiavel,</HI> [and, Rea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er, was it not worthy of a <HI>Machiavel</HI>!] <HI>That he who Writes an History, must be a man of no Religion.</HI> By that profane Rule, the first and the best Histo∣rian in the World, the most <HI>Religious</HI> MOSES, was ill accomplished for a Writer of <HI>History.</HI> But the <HI>History,</HI> which we are now Writing, does Professedly intend nothing so much as the Ser∣vice of <HI>Religion,</HI> even of that <HI>Religion,</HI> whereof our MITCHEL made an Exemplary Profession. Wherefore we go on, to say; Know, Reader, That he was a Great Example of a <HI>Walk with God.</HI> He was much in <HI>Prayer,</HI> much in <HI>Fasting,</HI> Sometimes taking his Virtuous <HI>Wife,</HI> therein to make a <HI>Consort</HI> with him; and sometimes also he kept, whole <HI>Dayes of Thanks∣giving</HI> privately with his Family, besides what he did more publickly; Devoting himself, as a <HI>Thank Offering</HI> to God, for his <HI>Mercies,</HI> with a <HI>Rea∣sonable Service.</HI> In his <HI>Diary,</HI> He betimes laid that Rule upon himself, <HI>Oh! that I could Remember this Rule, never to go to Bed, until I have had some Re∣newed special Communion with God!</HI> He kept a strict <HI>watch,</HI> over not only his <HI>Words,</HI> but also his very <HI>Thoughts</HI>; and if by the <HI>Reflections,</HI> which he was continually making on himself, he judged that his Mind had not been always full of <HI>Hea∣ven,</HI> that his <HI>Heart</HI> had been, what he called, <HI>hard</HI> and <HI>slight,</HI> that he had been <HI>Formal,</HI> in his <HI>Devoti∣ons,</HI> that he had not <HI>profited</HI> abundantly by the <HI>Sermons</HI> of other men, that he had not made
<PB N="101" REF="000790_0100_0FAA53C6CEA01C30"/>
Conscience of Doing all the <HI>Good</HI> he could, when he had been in any <HI>Company</HI>; he would put <HI>Stings</HI> into his Reflections, and Rebuke and Reproach himself with an Holy Indignation. Severe might seem the Rule of <HI>R. Hanina. If two sit together and there be no Discourse of the Law, 'tis the Seat of the Scornful:</HI> Severe might seem the Rule of <HI>R. Simeon, If Three do Eat at one Table, and say nothing about the Law, they are as if they Eat the Sacrifices of the Dead</HI>: And severe might be the Rule of <HI>R. Hananiah, He that wakes in the Night or walks by the way, and let's his Heart lie Idle, sins against his own Soul:</HI> But our <HI>Mitchel</HI> reckoned it no <HI>Severity</HI> unto himself, to impose upon him∣self such <HI>Rules</HI> as these for his Conversation. I have Read, That <HI>Five</HI> Devout persons being toge∣ther, there was this Question started among them, <HI>How,</HI> In what wayes, By what means, <HI>they streng∣thened themselves in Abstaining from Sin against the God of Heaven</HI>? The First Answered, <HI>I frequently, meditate on the Certainty of Death, and the Uncertain∣ty of the Time for my Death, and this makes me Live in the Fear of Sin, every Day as my Last.</HI> The Second Answered, <HI>I frequently meditate on the strict Account of Sin that I am to give at the Day of Judg∣ment, and the Everlasting Torments in Hell, to be inflicted on them that can give no Good Account.</HI> The Third Answered, <HI>I frequently meditate on the vile∣ness, and filthiness, and loathsomeness of Sin, and the Excellency of Grace, which is contrary unto so vile a Thing.</HI> The Fourth Answered, <HI>I frequently medi∣tate
<PB N="102" REF="000790_0101_0FAA53C7EC1120C0"/>
on the Eternal Rewards and Pleasures Reserved in Heaven, for them that avoid the pleasures of Sin, which are but for a moment.</HI> The Fifth Answered, <HI>I frequently meditate on the Lord JESUS CHRIST, and His wondrous Love to miserable Sinners, in Dying a Cursed and a Bitter Death for our Sin; and this Helps me to Abstain from Sin, more than any other consideration whatsoever</HI>; And the Answer of this last was indeed the greatest of all. Now all these were the Subjects, which our Holy <HI>Mitchel,</HI> ob∣liged himself to an assiduous <HI>Meditation</HI> upon; and by <HI>Meditating</HI> on these it was, that he be∣came very <HI>Holy.</HI> Moreover, he was as <HI>Holy</HI> men use to be, very solicitous to make a due Improve∣ment of all <HI>Afflictions,</HI> that the Providence of Hea∣ven dispensed unto him. He would say, <HI>When God personally Afflicts a man, it is as if He called unto the man by Name, and jogged him, and said, Oh! Re∣pent, be Humbled, be Serious, be Awakened</HI>: Yea, he could not so much as be kept a little from the Labours of his Ministry, by an <HI>Hoarse Cold</HI> arresting him, without writing down this Improve∣ment of it; <HI>My Sin is Legible in the Chastisement: cold Duties, cold Prayers (my voice in Prayer,</HI> i. e. <HI>my Spirit of Prayer fearfully gone) my Coldness in my whole Conversation, chastised with a Cold; I fear that I have not Improved my voice for God formerly as I might have done, and therefore He now takes it from me.</HI> But the <HI>Affliction</HI> which most of all Ex∣ercised him, seems to have been in the successive <HI>Death</HI> of many and Lovely <HI>Children,</HI> though all of
<PB N="103" REF="000790_0102_0FAA53C8ACD23288"/>
them, in their <HI>Infancy.</HI> 'Tis an Observation made by some, upon several Passages in the Scripture concerning that Generous and Grac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>us man, <HI>Da∣vid,</HI> that he was <HI>Liberorum Amantissimus,</HI> full of Affections to his <HI>Children</HI>; and that was to be Observed in our Mr. <HI>Jonathan Mitchel</HI>; for which cause, when his <HI>Children</HI> were <HI>Sick,</HI> his Paternal Bowels felt more than ordinary wounds; and when they were <HI>Dead,</HI> his Humil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ions thereup∣on were extraordinary. He <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> whole <HI>Pages of Lamentations</HI> on these Occasions; and one of his <HI>Infants</HI> particularly Expiring before it could be brought forth to an orderly <HI>Baptism,</HI> I cannot but Recite a little of the <HI>Meditations</HI> then written by him: <HI>It was a further sad Hand of the Lord</HI> (saies he) <HI>that it should Dy Unbaptised. Though I do not think they are Orthodox, that hang Salvation upon</HI> Baptism, <HI>and not rather upon the</HI> Covenant, <HI>yet as it is appointed to be a Confirming Sign, and as it is an Ordinance of Grace, so to be Deprived of it, is a great Frown, and a sad Intimation of the Lord's An∣ger: And though it may be well with with the Child notwithstanding (that it becomes me to leave unto the Lord!) yet it is to us a Token of Displeasure. And what Constructions or Thoughts tending to the Lord's Dishonour, it may Occasion, I know not: That after my Labours in Publick about</HI> Infant Baptism, <HI>the Lord should take away my</HI> Child <HI>without and before</HI> Baptism! <HI>Hereby the Lord does again and again make me an Example of His Displeasure before all men, as if He did say openly, that He hath a special Contro∣versy
<PB N="104" REF="000790_0103_0FAA53C96F96DC80"/>
with me; Thus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> taking <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> One after another. The Lord brings me forth, and makes me go up and down, as one smitten of God: The Lord spits in my Face by this Thing.</HI> See 2 Sam. 12.12. Numb. 12.12. Deut. 28.45, 46, 58, 59. Such, and many more were the workings of his <HI>Tender Soul</HI> under his Repeated <HI>Afflictions.</HI> And such were the <HI>Unsearchable</HI> Dealings of God, that besides the <HI>Children</HI> which he sent unto Heaven before him, when he went unto Heaven himself, he left behind him <HI>Three Sons,</HI> and <HI>Two Daughters,</HI> all of which Lived unto somewhat of <HI>Youth,</HI> yet they have all of them since dyed in their <HI>Youth</HI>: except only a Virtuous Young Gentlewoman, married unto Captain <HI>Stephen Sewal</HI> of <HI>Salem</HI>; unto whom (with her Offspring, the only Poste∣rity of this Great man) may the Lord multiply all the Blessings of that <HI>Covenant,</HI> for which their Progenitor proved so Serviceable a Pleader in his Generation!</P>
<P>The last Thing that ever he wrote in his Re∣served Papers, after he had Bitterly Reproached, <HI>The Sinful Deadness, Straitness, Enmity, and Unsa∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ouriness</HI> (as he called it) <HI>upon his own Heart,</HI> up∣on which he added this Pathetical Expression, <HI>I feel I shall fall, and tumble down into the Pit of Hell, if left unto my self</HI>; It was <HI>June</HI> 7. 1668. To quick∣en his Cares of <HI>Daily Meditation.</HI></P>
<P><Q>First. Far Younger than I, some of them now got to Heaven, have done much this way. <HI>Nulla Dies sine linea.</HI></Q></P>
<P><PB N="105" REF="000790_0104_0FAA53CAA564B548"/>
<Q>Secondly. <HI>Meditation,</HI> yea, <HI>Daily</HI> Meditation, in general, is an Indispensable Duty. <HI>Psal.</HI> 1.2. and Psal. 119.97. And because it is so, there may be something of <HI>Meditation</HI> in <HI>Prayer,</HI> in <HI>Reading</HI> the Word; <HI>Josh.</HI> 1.8. with Deut. 19 19. and in <HI>Occasional</HI> Transient Thoughts: yet surely some <HI>sett Meditation</HI> daily besides these, is at least <HI>to me</HI> a Duty, who am set apart, for the Holy Work of the Ministry, wherein it would be Helpful, as well as to my own Soul.</Q></P>
<P><Q>Thirdly. <HI>Heaven</HI> is here begun upon <HI>Earth:</HI> shall I be <HI>Thinking</HI> on, and <HI>Talking</HI> with, <HI>Christ,</HI> to all Eternity, and not Discourse with Him, one quarter of an Hour in a Day <HI>now</HI>?</Q></P>
<P><Q>Fourthly. The Great Enemies of all Good, <HI>Flesh, Satan,</HI> and <HI>World,</HI> do of all other things, most oppose <HI>Meditation</HI> which showes that there is much <HI>Good</HI> in it. <HI>Flesh,</HI> by Awkness, Giddi∣ness; <HI>World,</HI> by Distractions; <HI>Satan,</HI> by stirring up both. <HI>Lord, Awaken me, and keep me Awake!</HI></Q></P>
<P N="16">§ 16. But <HI>what</HI> and <HI>when,</HI> was the End of this <HI>Holy Walk</HI>? The Incongruities, and Incon∣sistences, of <HI>Historians,</HI> are not more notorious in any∣one Article, than in that of, the <HI>Deaths</HI> of the <HI>Hero's,</HI> whose <HI>Lives</HI> they have <HI>Eternized.</HI> With what <HI>Varie∣ties</HI> are the <HI>Deaths</HI> of <HI>Cyrus,</HI> of <HI>Antiochus,</HI> of <HI>Alexander,</HI> of <HI>Hannibal,</HI> of <HI>Romulus,</HI> of <HI>Scipio,</HI> of <HI>Plato,</HI> of <HI>Aristo∣tle,</HI> reported? There is hardly any Philosopher, but he Dies Twice or Thrice over in <HI>Laertius</HI>; and there is hardly one of <HI>Plutarchs</HI> Worthies,
<PB N="106" REF="000790_0105_0FAA53CB70CE3788"/>
but he Dies as many wayes, The <HI>Dea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> of our <HI>Mitchel,</HI> remains now to be Related, with more of <HI>Certainty.</HI> Though <HI>Bodily Exercise does profit a little,</HI> as the Apostle concedes, namely, to the Health of the <HI>Body</HI>; and Mr. <HI>Mitchel</HI> had from a Principle of <HI>Godliness,</HI> used himself to <HI>Bodily Ex∣ercise</HI>; nevertheless he found it would not wholly free him from an Ill Habit of <HI>Body.</HI> Of extream <HI>Lean,</HI> he soon grew extream <HI>Fat</HI>; and at last, in an extream Hot Season, a <HI>Fever</HI> arrested him, just after he had been Preaching on those words, <HI>I know that thou wilt bring me to Death and unto the House appointed for all the Living.</HI> The <HI>Fever</HI> did not seem to Threaten his Death; however in his Illness, to them, that visited him, he said, <HI>If the Lord Jesus Christ have any Service for me to Do for Him, and His Dear People, I am willing to Do it; but if my Work be Done, His Will be done!</HI> But the Distemper suddenly assaulting him, with a Mortal Malignity, and Summoning him to the <HI>House appointed for all the Living,</HI> he fell to Admi∣ring the manifold <HI>Grace</HI> of God unto him, and broke forth into these words, <HI>Lord, Thou callest me away to Thee; I know not why, if I look to my self; but at thy Bidding, I come!</HI> which were some of the Last words, that he spoke in the World: For his Friends, who had not, for many Hours, En∣tertained the Expectation of any such dismal E∣vent, were compelled in Floods of Tears, to see him <HI>Dy,</HI> on <HI>July</HI> 9. 1668. in the Forty Third Year of his Age: When (as one expresses that
<PB N="107" REF="000790_0106_0FAA53CBB24B1770"/>
matter.) he left his Body to be dipped in the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of <HI>Jordan,</HI> that afterwards in its Resurrecti∣o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> passing into <HI>Canaan,</HI> it may, beyond the Sto∣ry of <HI>Achilles,</HI> become Impenetrable and Invulne∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>able. Wonderful were the <HI>Lamentations,</HI> which this Deplorable Death fill'd the Churches of <HI>New-England</HI> withal; For as the Jewish <HI>Rabbi's</HI> Lamen∣ted the Death of R. <HI>Jose,</HI> with saying, That af∣ter his Death, <HI>Cessarunt Botri,</HI> i. e. <HI>Viri tales, in quibus omnes, tum Eruditionis, cum Virtutis, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uli erant:</HI> So, after the Departure of our <HI>Mitchel,</HI> it was fear'd there would be few more such <HI>Rich Grapes</HI> to be seen growing in this Unthankful Wilderness. Yea, they <HI>Speak of this Great man in their Lamentations to this Day:</HI> and what they speak is briefly the same, that One of our most Eminent Persons has <HI>Writ,</HI> in those Terms, <HI>All</HI> New-England <HI>shook, when that Pillar fell to the Ground.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epitaph">
<HEAD>EPITAPH.</HEAD>
<P>AND now, Reader, Let us go to the best of <HI>Poets</HI> in the <HI>English</HI> Nation, for those Lines, which may, without the least wrong to Truth be applied as an <HI>EPITAPH,</HI> to this best of <HI>Preachers,</HI> in our little <HI>New English</HI> Nation. The Incomparable Dr. <HI>Blackmores</HI> Orator <HI>Tylon,</HI> shall, now be our MITCHEL.</P>
<L><PB N="108" REF="000790_0107_0FAA53CDD6299580"/>
TIS the Great <HI>Mitchel,</HI> whose Immortal worth,</L>
<L>Raises to <HI>Heav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n</HI> the <HI>Isle</HI> that gave him Birth.</L>
<L>A Sacred Man, a Venerable <HI>Priest,</HI></L>
<L>Who never spake, and <HI>Admiration</HI> mist.</L>
<L>Of <HI>Good</HI> and <HI>Kind,</HI> he the just Standard seem'd,</L>
<L>Dear to the <HI>Best,</HI> and by the <HI>Worst</HI> Esteem'd.</L>
<L>A Gen'rous <HI>Love,</HI> diffus'd to Humane kind,</L>
<L>Divine <HI>Compassion, Mercy</HI> unconfin'd,</L>
<L>Still Reign'd Triumphant, in his <HI>Godlike Mind.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Greatness</HI> and <HI>Modesty</HI> their Wars Compose,</L>
<L>Between them <HI>here</HI> a perfect <HI>Friendship</HI> grows.</L>
<L>His <HI>Wit,</HI> His <HI>Judgment, Learning,</HI> Equal rise;</L>
<L>Divinely <HI>Humble,</HI> yet Divinely <HI>Wise</HI>:</L>
<L>He seem'd <HI>Express,</HI> on <HI>Heav'ns</HI> High Errand sent,</L>
<L>As <HI>Moses</HI> Meek, As <HI>Aaron</HI> Eloquent.</L>
<L><HI>Nectar</HI> divine flows from his Heav'nly Tongue▪</L>
<L>And on his Lips, charming <HI>Perswasion</HI> hung.</L>
<L>When he the Sacred <HI>Oracles</HI> Reveal'd,</L>
<L>Our Ravish'd Souls in blest <HI>Enchantments</HI> held,</L>
<L>Seem'd lost in Transports of Immortal Bliss;</L>
<L>No Simple <HI>Man</HI> could ever speak like This!</L>
<L>Arm'd with Caelestial <HI>Fire,</HI> his Sacred <HI>Darts</HI></L>
<L>Glide thro' our <HI>Breasts,</HI> &amp; melt our yielding <HI>Hearts.</HI></L>
<L>So Southern Breezes, and the Springs mild Ray,</L>
<L>Unbind the <HI>Glebe,</HI> and thaw the Frozen clay.</L>
<L>He Triumph'd o'er our Souls, and at his Will,</L>
<L>Bid <HI>this</HI> Touch'd <HI>Passion</HI> rise, and <HI>that</HI> be still.</L>
<L>Lord of our <HI>Passions,</HI> he, with wondrous Art,</L>
<L>Could strike the Secret Movements of our <HI>Heart</HI>;</L>
<L><PB N="109" REF="000790_0108_0FAA53CDF2328278"/>Release our <HI>Souls,</HI> and make them soar above,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with Divine <HI>Desires,</HI> and Flames of <HI>Heav'nly Love.</HI></L>
<P>But what need I travel, as far as <HI>Europe</HI> for an <HI>Elegy</HI> upon this Worthy Man? Let it be known, that <HI>America</HI> can <HI>Embalm</HI> Great Persons, as well as <HI>Produce</HI> them, and <HI>New England</HI> can bestow, an <HI>Elegy,</HI> as well as an <HI>Education</HI> upon its <HI>Hero's.</HI> Let this Attempt at <HI>Poetry,</HI> now find a Room in our Pages.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<HEAD>To the MEMORY of the REVEREND JONATHAN MITCHEL Qucquid Agimus, quicquid Patimur, venit ex Alto.</HEAD>
<L>THE Countries <HI>Tears,</HI> be ye my <HI>Spring</HI>; my <HI>Hill</HI></L>
<L>A General <HI>Grave</HI>; Let <HI>Groans</HI> inspire my Quill.</L>
<L>By a warm <HI>Sympathie,</HI> Let <HI>Feaverish Heat</HI></L>
<L>Roam thro' my Verse unseen: And a <HI>Cold Sweat</HI></L>
<L>Limning <HI>Despair,</HI> attend me: <HI>Sighs</HI> disfuse</L>
<L><HI>Convulsions</HI> thro' my Language, such as use</L>
<L>To Type a Gasping Fancy; lastly, Shroud</L>
<L>Religions <HI>Splendor</HI> in a Mourning <HI>Cloud,</HI></L>
<L><PB N="110" REF="000790_0109_0FAA53CF439C54E8"/>Replete with <HI>Vengeance,</HI> for Succeeding <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Fertile in <HI>Woes,</HI> more Fertile in their <HI>Crimes.</HI></L>
<L>These are my <HI>Muses</HI>; These Inspire the <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ils</HI></L>
<L>Of Fancy, with their <HI>Sighs,</HI> instead of <HI>Gales.</HI></L>
<L>Reader, Read Reverend <HI>Mitchels</HI> Life &amp; then</L>
<L>Confess the World a <HI>Gordian knot</HI> agen.</L>
<L>Read his <HI>Tear delug'd</HI> Grave, and then decree,</L>
<L>Our present <HI>Woe,</HI> and future <HI>Miserie.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Stars Falling</HI> speak a <HI>Storm</HI>; when <HI>Samuel</HI> dies,</L>
<L><HI>Saul</HI> may Expect <HI>Philistia's</HI> cruelties.</L>
<L>So when Jehovahs <HI>Brighter Glory</HI> fled</L>
<L>The Temple, <HI>Israel</HI> soon was Captive led.</L>
<L><HI>Geneva's</HI> Triple light made one Divine:</L>
<L>But here that vast <HI>Triumvirate</HI> combine</L>
<L>By a blest <HI>Metempsychosis,</HI> to take</L>
<L><HI>One Person</HI> for their larger <HI>Zodiack.</HI></L>
<L>In Sacred Censures, <HI>Farels</HI> dreadful <HI>Scrol</HI></L>
<L><HI>Of Words,</HI> broke from the <HI>Pulpit</HI> to the <HI>Soul.</HI></L>
<L>In Balmy Comforts, <HI>Virets</HI> Genius came</L>
<L>From th'<HI>Wrinkled Alps,</HI> to Wooe the Western Dame;</L>
<L>And Courting <HI>Cambridge,</HI> quickly took from thence</L>
<L>Her <HI>Last Degrees</HI> of <HI>Rhetorick</HI> and <HI>Sense.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Calv<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ns</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aconicks thro' his Doctrine Spred,</L>
<L>And <HI>Childrens Children</HI> with their <HI>Manna</HI> fed.</L>
<L>His Exposition <HI>Genesis</HI> begun,</L>
<L>And fatal <HI>Exodus</HI> Eclips'd his <HI>Sun.</HI></L>
<L>Some say, that <HI>Souls</HI> oft sad <HI>Praesages</HI> give:</L>
<L><HI>Death breathing Sermons</HI> taught us last to <HI>Live.</HI></L>
<L>His <HI>System of Religion, half</HI> unheard,</L>
<L>Full <HI>Double,</HI> in his <HI>Preaching Life</HI> appear'd.</L>
<L><PB N="111" REF="000790_0110_0FAA53D01E7FA9B8"/>He's gone, to whom his <HI>Country</HI> owes a Love,</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>thy the <HI>Prudent Serpent,</HI> and the <HI>Dove.</HI></L>
<L>Religions <HI>Panoply,</HI> the Sinners <HI>Terrour,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Death</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>mmon'd hence; Sure by a <HI>Writ of Errour</HI>!</L>
<L>The <HI>Quaker</HI> Trembling at his <HI>Thunder,</HI> fled;</L>
<L>And with <HI>Caligula</HI> resum'd his Bed.</L>
<L>He, by the Motions of a <HI>Nobler Spirit,</HI></L>
<L>Clear'd <HI>Men,</HI> and made their Notions <HI>Swine inherit.</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Munster</HI> Goblin, by his Holy Flood</L>
<L>Exorcis'd, like a Thin <HI>Phantasma</HI> stood.</L>
<L><HI>Browns</HI> Babel, shatter'd by his <HI>Lightning,</HI> fell</L>
<L>And with <HI>Confused Horror</HI> pack'd to Hell.</L>
<L>The <HI>Scripture,</HI> with a <HI>Commentary</HI> bound,</L>
<L>(Like a Lost <HI>Calice</HI>) in his <HI>Heart</HI> was found.</L>
<L>When he was <HI>Sick,</HI> the <HI>Air,</HI> a <HI>Feaver</HI> took,</L>
<L>And Thirsty <HI>Phaebus</HI> quaff'd the Silver brook:</L>
<L>When <HI>Dead,</HI> the <HI>Sphaeres</HI> in <HI>Thunder, Clouds,</HI> &amp; <HI>Rain</HI></L>
<L>Groan'd his <HI>Elegium,</HI> mourn'd and wept our <HI>pain.</HI></L>
<L>Let not the <HI>Brazen Schismatick</HI> aspire;</L>
<L><HI>Lots</HI> leaving <HI>Sodom,</HI> left them to the <HI>Fire.</HI></L>
<L>'Tis true, the <HI>Bee's</HI> now dead; but yet his <HI>sting</HI></L>
<L>Death's to their <HI>Dronish Doctrines</HI> yet may bring.</L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epitaph">
<HEAD>EPITAPHIUM.</HEAD>
<L>Here Lies within this Comprehensive Span,</L>
<L>The Churches, Courts, and Countreys <HI>Jonathan.</HI></L>
<L>He that speaks <HI>Mitchell,</HI> gives the Schools the <HI>Lie</HI>;</L>
<L>Friendship in him gain'd an Ubiquity.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>F. D.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<PB REF="000790_0111_0FAA53D039032378"/>
<HEAD>ERRATA.</HEAD>
<P><HI>In the Preface.</HI> p. 7. in the Margin, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <HI>Infa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Baptism.</HI> p. 12. l. 13 for which, r. with p. 19. l. 19. dole <HI>the.</HI> p. 23. l. 22. r. Enlarge p. 30. l. 28. r. Largest.</P>
<P>Pag. 62. l. 20. f. <HI>as,</HI> r. <HI>es.</HI> p. 86. l. 19. f. with. r. without.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's advertisement">
<HEAD>Advertisement.</HEAD>
<P>THere is now in the Press, a small Book, En¦tituled, <HI>Humiliations follow'd with De¦liverances.</HI> Or, a brief Discourse on the <HI>Matt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> and <HI>Method</HI> of that <HI>Humiliation,</HI> which would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> an Hopeful Symptom of our <HI>Deliverance</HI> from Calamity. Accompanied and Accommodated▪ with a Narrative of a Notable <HI>Deliverance</HI> lat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eived, by some English <HI>Captives,</HI> from the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nds of Cruel <HI>Indians</HI>; and some Improvemen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of that <HI>Narrative.</HI> As also a Relation of one <HI>Hannah Swarton,</HI> Containing many Wonderful Passages, concerning her Captivity, and her Deliverance.</P>
<P>Printed for, and Sold by <HI>Samuel Phillip.,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Brick-Shop, near the <HI>Old Meeting-House</HI> in <HI>Boston.</HI> 1697.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

