<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2005-08-29</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for signatures. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Converted 982 $-groups to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N00659">
<STC T="E">801</STC>
<STC T="W">m1353</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99020000</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="000801_0000_0FAA49D1F65D9A40"/>
<PB REF="000801_0001_0FAA49C52D339C08" MS="y"/>
<P>NEVV-ENGLAND Pesecutors Mauld VVith their own VVeapons.</P>
<P>Giving some Account of the bloody Laws made at <HI>Boston</HI> against the Kings Subjects that dissented from their way of Worship.</P>
<P>Together with a brief Account of the Imprisonment and Tryal of <HI>Thomas Maule</HI> of <HI>Salem,</HI> for publishing a Book, entituled, <HI>Truth held forth and maintained, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P>By <HI>Theo. Philathes.</HI></P>
<Q><P>Truth faileth, and he that departeth from evil maketh himself a pray,</P>
<BIBL><HI>Isa. 59.14, 15.</HI></BIBL>
<P>As Troops of Robbers wait for a Man, so do the company Priests <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>∣der in t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e way by consent,</P>
<BIBL><HI>Hosea 6.9.</HI></BIBL>
<P>Shall the Throne of Iniquity have fellowship with thee, which frameth Mischief by a Law; they gather themselves together against the Soul of the Righteous, and condemn the Innocent Blood,</P>
<BIBL><HI>Psal <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>4.20, 21.</HI></BIBL></Q>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="preface">
<PB REF="000801_0002_0FAA49D206F43A48"/>
<HEAD>The Preface.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Christian Reader;</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>IT has not been without due Consideration, that we have seen cause to set forth and publish a true Account of some of the <HI>New-England</HI> Church Members cruel and bloody Laws, which through the Priests instigating the Magistrates, were by them made against both <HI>Quakers</HI> and all other Religious Persons within <HI>New-Englands</HI> Juris∣diction, that were found to dissent from their Worship, as also a short Relation of some few of the many Persons that suffered Persecution under the Anti-christian Power of the aforesaid Church, with some brief Observations on each Law, and the Preamble thereof. Unto which is added, an Account of the Priests, Rulers and Church Members great. Hurly-burley or Confusion made about a late Book, entituled, <HI>Truth held forth and maintained,</HI> &amp;c. by <HI>Thomas Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> of <HI>Salem,</HI> in which Book is contained thirty eight Chapters relating to the Principles of Truth, agreeing with the Testimony of the holy Prophets, Christ and his Apostles recorded in the holy Scriptures of Truth, together with an Account of Gods Judgments upon divers of the chief persecuting Priests and Rulers, and a Decla∣ration of the late great Judgment of God upon the Priests, Rulers &amp; their Followers, of whom Twenty were (through the Accusation by Specter Evidence, which Judgment con∣tinued</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="account">
<PB N="1" REF="000801_0003_0FAA49D359014E60"/>
<HEAD>Persecutors Maul'd with their own VVeapons.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Anti-Christian Freedom established by the Law of the Old Charter Priests and Rulers in <HI>New-England.</HI></HEAD>
<P>THis Court having considering the Proposals pre∣sented to this Court by several of the Inhabitants of the County of <HI>Middlesex,</HI> do declare and order, That no man whatsoever shall be admitted to the freedom of this Body Politick, but such as are Members of some Church of Christ, and in full Communion, which they declare to be the true intent of the <HI>antient</HI> Law, Anno 1031▪ 1660.</P>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Hence you may understand, that the County of <HI>middle∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>x,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Money and wealth, did encourage for sale, the high Priests Ware, as well as in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to seat them∣selves <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to the Magistrates <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Court of Injustice, against Dissenters from their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> which said Courts were kept in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, where the Priests <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> brought of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Estates, for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, to the Value of many hundreds of Pounds, with which the Priests and Rulers, with others of their Church <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> themselves from day to day, while they made Laws against them that dissented from the worship of their Priests, who when the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> were stuffed with the best Pro∣vision, and their heads with the richest sort of Wine, had not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> home to their Common Prayers against all dissenters as well
<PB N="2" REF="000801_0004_0FAA49D9326CD040"/>
as <HI>Quakers</HI>; and while they feasted themselves with the best of other mens Labour, they kept the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> thereof with the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> entertainment their Goal and Bridewell house did afford as by their cruel-suffering therein will hereafter appear, and as is rel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ted in the Book of Sufferings, under these persecuting Magistrates, that some went and demanded their fat Oxen of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> again, to which their answer <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>that we should sit and starve, while <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI> which was to make Laws to devour them and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> great encouragement to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Pol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tick, whose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> they ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l it, is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed to be, b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> their persecut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> other <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> in their Jurisdiction.</P>
<TRAILER><L>The Free-mans Law, by which a Body <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>No man that's true can <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Chu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ake</L>
<L>He that will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onour gain, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> at their hand,</L>
<L>He must forsake all good, then by their cause may stand.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Preamble to the Persecutor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Laws made against the People of God and the Kings good Subject</HEAD>
<P>WHereas there is a cursed Sect of Hereticks lately risen up in the world, which are commonly called <HI>Qua∣kers,</HI> who take upon them to be immediately sent of God, &amp; Infallibly assisted by the Spirit, to speak and w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e blasphe∣mous Opinions, despising Government and the Order of God in Church and common Wealth, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> king evil of Di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ties, repro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ching and reviling Magistrates and Ministers, seeking to turn Peop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e from the Faith, and gain Proselites to their pernitious way.</P>
<P><PB N="3" REF="000801_0005_0FAA49D9C70ED2E0"/><HI>Observe</HI>; Here's the Persecutors preamble to their Antichristian Law, the unrighteousness of which is of their Father the w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cked One, who from the beginning hath been an Accuser of the Brethren, wherefore the things of the Kingdom of God are hid from them, <HI>Mat.</HI> 11.25. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.21. In which state they remain as the rebelious <HI>Jews,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ling good evil, and the truth, blasphemous Opinions, ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing no more <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to accuse the <HI>Quakers</HI> of evil▪ then had the wicked <HI>Jews</HI> against the People of God in the A∣postles <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and will in this following work appear so to be, to every t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue Christian Readers view of the same.</P>
<TRAILER><L>Here <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> begins these free-mens sin,</L>
<L>I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> for w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ich Gods Judgments bring.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Prea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ble to these Persecutors Law.</HEAD>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Court Considering the Premises, and to prevent th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Mischief, as by their means is wrought in our nativ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Land.</P>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, That of their many Lyes and Unjust charge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> against <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Quakers, Baptists,</HI> and other Dissenters, as well as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> them of the <HI>Church of England,</HI> is a Record to the end of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, is also of their many other unrighteous Works against <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of God and the Kings Subjects, which had they and the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Brethren been as clear from all means of mischief as the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> there had neither Rebellion, Treason, or Murder against the King <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>een alledged to the charge of their <HI>New-England</HI> Brother <HI>Hugh Peters, V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mur,</HI> and others of their Brethren in <HI>England,</HI> which they call our native Land.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>New-England Persecutors Law.</HEAD>
<P N="1">1. Do hereby order, and by the Authority of this Court <HI>Be it ordered and Enacted,</HI> That no Master or Commander of any Ship, Bark, Pinnace, Ketch, or other Vessel, henceforth bring into any Harbour, Creek or Cove within this Jurisdiction, any known <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uaker</HI> or <HI>Quakers,</HI> or other blasphemous Hereticks, upon the Penalty
<PB N="4" REF="000801_0006_0FAA49DA2B0E79E8"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of One hundred Pounds, to be forth with paid to the Treasurer of the Cuntry, except it appeareth that such Master wanted due notice or information that they were such, and in that case he may clear himself by his Oath, when sufficient proof to the contrary is wanting; and for default of payment of the said Fine of one hundred Pounds, or good Security for the same, such Master shall be committed to Prison by Warrant from any Magistrate, there to continue till the said Fine be satisfied to the Treasurer, as aforesaid.</P>
<P N="2">2. And the Master or Commander of any such Ship or Vessel, that shall being them, being legally convicted, shall give in sufficient Security to the Governour or one more of the Magistrates, to carry them to the place whence he brought them; and on his refusal so to do, the Governour or said Magistrate or Magistrates, shall commit such Master or Commander to Prison, there to remain till he shall give in sufficient Security to the content of the Governour or said Magistrate.</P>
<P N="3">3. And if any Person or Persons within this Juris∣diction shall henceforth entertain and conceal any <HI>Quaker</HI> or <HI>Quakers,</HI> or other blasphemous Hereticks, Knowing them to be such, every such Person shall forfeit to the Country Forty Shillings for every hours entertainment and concealment of any such <HI>Quaker</HI> or <HI>Quakers</HI> as aforesaid, and shall be committed to Prison, as aforesaid, till the Fines be fullly satisfied and paid.</P>
<P><HI>Observe,</HI> That several of the Kings Subjects, Masters or Com∣manders of Vessels suffered to the utmost extreamity of this unrighteous Law, which is so repugnant to the Law of God, and the Kings Laws, that in making and prosecuting the
<PB N="5" REF="000801_0007_0FAA49DB27B82AC8"/>
same, they out do all their fore-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>athers all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Iniquity, which Law was so well pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sing to the Prie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the more that people might believe their wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to be sanctified, set one day apart for Preaching and Praying,, as a day of Thanksgiving for the same, hoping that by the means of a thorow pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ecution of this Law, to keep their Jurisdiction clear of every Person called a <HI>Quaker,</HI> and that then their freemen would take the more courage against the <HI>Baptists</HI> and them of the <HI>Church of England</HI>; for with the <HI>Quakers</HI> they were hard beset, and in fear they would deprive them of their God; and as <HI>Demetrius,</HI> their Trade would come to nothing, and in fear of being slain, as was their elder Brother, Vagabond <HI>Cain,</HI> who as these had no certain dwelling in the <HI>Truth,</HI> which if their Worship had been the true Worship of God, as we read, <HI>John</HI> 4.24. but on the contrary, as we read, <HI>Mark</HI> 7 6, 7, 8, 9. <HI>Mat.</HI> 15.8. they worship't they knew not what, <HI>John.</HI> 4 22. in which state of Disobedience they were far from the Rule of <HI>doing as themselves would have been done unto, Mat.</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 12 <HI>Luke</HI> 6 31. but in fleeing the Land to save their Purses with whi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h their minds did abide, regarded not the Rule <HI>to ente<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tain Strangers, Heb.</HI> 13.2. but on the contrary, gave them the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> entertainment as the wicked <HI>Jews</HI> did to Christ and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Apostles, from whose Rule of <HI>proving all things <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> that which is good,</HI> from the same do these Persecuto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> restrain, as will more at large hereafter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</P>
<TRAILER><L>Of the like Laws we ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> finde</L>
<L>By men, that God and King do mind</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>New England: Antichristian <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HEAD>
<P N="4">4. And every Person or Persons that shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> or defend any of their pernicious ways▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> writing or meeting on the Lords Day, or at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> time, shall after due means of conviction <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Penalty ensu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng. <HI>viz.</HI> Every one so meeting <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to the use of the Country, for every time, Ten Shilling<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> And every one speaking in such a Meeting <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Five Pounds▪</P>
<P><PB N="6" REF="000801_0008_0FAA49DBA623F638"/><HI>Observe,</HI> That by this Law, and the other afore-mentioned Law of forty Shillings for every hours entertainment to any Person or Persons, or others whom they account blasphemous Heretick<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, as they did account all that dissented from their Priests Worship, by which two Laws they gained abundance of Money for Fines of the Inhabitants, who were found either at the <HI>Quakers</HI> Meeting, or to entertain their Relations and Kindred, though Father or Mother, Brother or Sister, or any other Friend or Friends, or Relations and Kindred, whom in their Law They call by the name of <HI>Strangers</HI> and <HI>Vagabonds,</HI> as by the following Laws will further appear, and that every man by Membership admitted to the freedom of their Body Politick, was according to their Priests way of teaching, become a Ruler, to lord over the Faith of every Dissente<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; by which the Christian Reader may fully comprehend the nature of these Free-mens Body Politick.</P>
<TRAILER><L>Ʋnto Religion these Free-men do pretend,</L>
<L>We may all see that Money is their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>New-England Antichristian Law.</HEAD>
<P N="5">5. If any Person shall knowingly import into any Harb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur of this Jurisdiction, any <HI>Quakers</HI> Books or Writings concerning their damnable Opinions, he shall forfeit for every such Book or writing five Pound<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; and whosoever shall disperse or conceal such Book o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Writing, and it be found with him or her, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in his or her House, and shall not Immediately deliver the same to the next Magistrate, shall pay five-Pounds for di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣persing or concealing every such Book or Writing</P>
<P N="6">6 And every Person or Persons whatsoever that shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ev<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> or Person of Magistrates or Ministers, as is usual <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the <HI>Quakers,</HI> such Person or Persons, shall be severe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y whipt, or pay the Sum of five Pounds in money.</P>
<P><PB N="7" REF="000801_0009_0FAA49DC6CB4DEB8"/>The Reader may here note, That the substance of matter contained in these two <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t Law<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> is very agreeable with what is before, as also with what wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l follow, all which is to promote the works o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Unrighteousn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss against God and his People, there∣by to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> from receiving the Truth, who <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> pro∣ving all things to hold fast that which is good, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t as by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Law, p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y five Pounds, either for bringing any <HI>Quakers</HI> Books o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> writings into their Jurisdiction, or keeping the same in their House when they are, without immediate de∣livering <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> same to the next Magistrate, which doth evidently manifest <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> design is to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Peoples Money, as well as to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>idde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of rec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ving the Truth, which fulfil what is written, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>neither ent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> the Kingdom of Heaven themselves, nor s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffer or <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to go in, Mat.</HI> 22.13. but as those w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ck<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <HI>Jews</HI> die, so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o these Hypocrites most unrigh¦teously charge the People of God with reviling the Office and Persons of Magistrates and Ministers, when as on contrary, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> sedi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s were true for Gods cause against Pride, C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>tousness and Opp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ssion, which greatly abounded in the Magi∣strates, Priests and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ecuting free-men, who for the most Part by their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>eling Priests, were taught beyond all grace and com∣mon good, and that the whole Government of their Church and Common-wealth, as they call it, had as they concluded that dependency upon their old Charter, that as by their Law<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> it is manifest they neither feared God nor minded the Laws of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>English</HI> Nation; for they had assumed to themselves the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of both God, King and Bishops, wholly confiding in the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of their old Idol Char<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er.</P>
<TRAILER><L>Where Persecutors once gain Power,</L>
<L>Like Lyons, Bears, and Wolves devour.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>New-England's <HI>Anti-christian Law.</HI></HEAD>
<P N="7">7. And every Person that shall publi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h and main<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>in any, Heterodox Erro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious Doctrine, shall be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to be
<PB N="8" REF="000801_0010_0FAA4FB1B2BAA9F0"/>
questioned, and sen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ured by the County Court where <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hē liveth, according to the merit of his Offence.</P>
<P>The Reader may hence understand, That the County Courts were plenty of these Persecutors &amp; Plenty of Jackalls to hunt for their prey, which was to find out every Person in their Jurisdiction, that departed from the way of their Priests Wor∣ship, such person and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>son<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> came a prey, <HI>Isa.</HI> 59.15. who were c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sed to publish or maint<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> the Heterodox or Erronious Doctrine; at the opening of whi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Courts, were always some of their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to pray, pretending that what they did against Dissente<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, would be the more sanctified through the means of their Prayers, which they pretended was for the honour of God, and good of the Souls of them, on whom the said Court did inflict punishment, both to their Body and Purses, so that what with these H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ings unsanctified Prayers, and the like Advice to the Magistrates, they would be sure to lay load enough on the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>cks of the aforesaid Diss<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nters, especially upon the Innocent <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Quakers,</HI> whom so often in their Law, they call <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪ for unto the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> was the Priests greatest Rage manifested, through their wicked advice to the Magistrates, to have them all hanged, of whom four were put to Death, and more had been, had not their Bloody Hands been stopped through the means of the Kings Order to the Contra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, a Coppy of which Letter will hereafter appear in this Book, which before it came, many were they that were put to cruel Sufferings, both by <HI>long Impri¦sonment, cruel Whipping, Cutting off Ears, Branding with Red<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ct <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ons,</HI> ordering <HI>Men and Women to be sold for bond Slaves, lear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g the Bodie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of Innocent Women for Witches, besides Banishi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g upon pain of Death,</HI> and ab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ndance of their <HI>Estates taken for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> on which these men, so free to do the Devils Work, did live, eating and drinking at a high rate, whilst others suffered as aforesaid.</P>
<TRAILER><L>This was the mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Prie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,</L>
<L>Whose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="9" REF="000801_0011_0FAA4FB275D7B4E8"/>
<HEAD>New-England Antichristian Law.</HEAD>
<P N="8">8. whereas there is a pernicious Sect, commonly call<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <HI>Quakers,</HI> lately writen, who by word and writing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> published and maintained many dangerous and horrid Te∣nets, and take upon them to change and alter the laudable Customs of our Nation, in giving civil Respect to Equals<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Reverence to Superiors, whose Actions tend to undermine the Authority of civil Government, as also to destroy the Order of the Churches, by denying all established Forms of Worship, and by with drawing from the orderly Church Assemblies allowed and approved by all Orthrodox Prof¦fessors of the Truth, and instead thereof, and opposition thereunto, frequenting private Meetings of their own, insinuating into the minds of the simple, or such as are less affected to the Order and Government of our Church and Common Wealth, whereby divers of our Inhabitants have been Infected and seduced; and notwithstanding all former Laws made, upon Experience of their arrogant bold Ob∣trusions to Disseminate their Principles amongst us, pro∣hibiting their coming into this Jurisdiction, they have not been d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tered from their impetuous Attempts to undermine our Peace and hasten our Ruin.</P>
<P>The Reader may here note, the great Wickedness of these unrighteous Priests and Rulers, who to accuse the innocent, run themselves into further mischief, through their bold Attempts against God and the King, which hath proved to be their ruin, for whilest they were digging Pits, and making Rods, and laying Snares the innocent, God was preparing his Judgments against them, and all those whose silence gave consent thereto by which Judgments they do not only suffer
<PB N="10" REF="000801_0012_0FAA4FB33846D470"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> fruit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad Grain throughout their Juris∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="7 letters" DISP="〈7 letters〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> delivered into the hands of the Barbarous <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> suffers <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke them a double measure of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, which themselves (as by their Laws) have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> others, besides the loss of their old C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ter and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</P>
<TRAILER><L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ever <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for Innocent Blood Reward,</L>
<L>Though whi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> the Wicked live, little it regard.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>New-England Antichristian Law.</HEAD>
<P>For prevention thereof, this Court doth Order and Enact, that every Person of the cursed Sect of <HI>Quakers,</HI> who is not an Inhabitant, but found within this Jurisdiction, shall be apprehended without Warrant, where no Ma∣gistrate is at hand, by any Constable, Commissioner or Select Man, and conveyed from Constable to Constable, until they come before the next Magistrate, who shall commit the said Person or Persons to close Prison, there to remain without Bail, until the next Court of Assistants, where they shall have a legal Tryal by a special Jury, and being convict to be of the cursed Sect of <HI>Quakers,</HI> shall be sentenced to Banishment upon pain of DEATH.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> The Reader may hence understand, that the nearer the Ma∣gistrates Laws did extend to destroy the Lives of the Innocent, the more pleasing it was to the Hireling Priests, who in honour thereunto, would set Time apart lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the Churches Thank<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>giving.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>New-England Antichristian Law</HEAD>
<P>And that every the Inhabitants of this Jurisdiction, being convicted to be of the cursed Sect of <HI>Quakers,</HI> either by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aking up, publishing and defending the horrid Opinions
<PB N="11" REF="000801_0013_0FAA4FB3F6B60310"/>
of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rsed <HI>Quakers</HI>▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> stirring up <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of Rebellion against the Government of our Church as a Common Wealth, or by taking up their ab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rd and destru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣tive Practices, <HI>viz.</HI> denying civil Respect and Reverence<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Equals and Superiours, with-drawing from out Church Assemblies, and instead thereof, frequenting private Meet∣ings of their own, in Opposition to our Church Order, or by adhearing to, or approving of known <HI>Quakers,</HI> that are opposit to the Orthodox received Opinions of the Godly, and endeavouring to disaffect others to civil Government and Church Order established amongst us, and condemning the Practice and Proceedings of this Court against the <HI>Quakers,</HI> manifesting thereby compliance with those whose design is to overthrow the Order established in our Church and Common-Wealth.</P>
<P>The reader may here <HI>Observe</HI> the wretched state of these Bloody minded Persecutors, who for want of true faith were in the state of th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it elder Brother <HI>Cain,</HI> that was a murderer, like unto these who destroy the righteous for their Faith and Obedience to God, for which cause these Persecutors bear <HI>Cain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> mark, being in fear that those which are not of their murdering Spirits, will slay them; and knowing themselves to be like prin∣cipled, as was <HI>Hugh Peters, Venner,</HI> and many others of their <HI>New-England</HI> Brethren in Iniquity, stirring up Mutiny, Sedition and Rebellion against the English Government, and the Order of the English Church established by the Bishops, as by the <HI>Chro∣nicles</HI> of <HI>England</HI> doth at large appear of their Rebellion and Treason against the King and his Children, in that day of their inventing so much mischief against other<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in our Native Land, to set up themselves above all others; which Sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in those their persecuting Brethren, who impute that to
<PB N="12" REF="000801_0014_0FAA4FB4E51AC398"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> innocent <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> People, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> so highly guilty of, as is manifested by their setting up them∣selves, to lord it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ver the People of God and the Kings Subjects, as for fifty or sixty Years time they have done in <HI>New-England,</HI> where the hireling Priests kept a constant stroke of puting all that dissented from their Worship, into bear skins, and setting their followers to tear them in pieces, calling out in their preaching to their people, <HI>Curse ye Mero<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> Curse ye bitterly the Inhabitants that will not come to the help of the Lord against the mighty, <HI>Judg.</HI> 5▪ 23. and cursed be he that doth the Work of the Lord deceitfully, by withholding his Sword from Blood, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> 48.10 with more of the like, endeavouring to perswade, that Gods general Judgments would not depart, until they had hanged all the <HI>Quakers,</HI> and sent going all other Dissenters.</P>
<Q><L>The Judgments may remove, but when old Charter men</L>
<L>Are d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad, and then</L>
<L>Or when God sends <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere better men,</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll to rule in Government, then,</L>
<BIBL><HI>Pro. 29 2</HI></BIBL>
<L>From Devil and such Wicked Priests,</L>
<L>pray God deliver me</L>
<L>Then from all Mischief in the World,</L>
<L>be sure I shall be free.</L>
<BIBL><HI>Hosea 6.9.</HI></BIBL></Q>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>New-England Persecutors Laws against the Kings Subjects</HEAD>
<P>Every such Person upon Examination and Conviction before the Court of Assistants, in manner as aforesaid, shall be committed to close Prison for one Month, and unless they chose to depart the jurisdiction, shall give Bond for their appearance at the next Court of Assistants, where continuing obstinate, and refusing to retract and reform the afores<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id Opinions and Practices, shall be sentenced to Banishment, upon <HI>pain of Death,</HI> and in case of the aforesaid Voluntary departure not to remain, or
<PB N="13" REF="000801_0015_0FAA4FB578CB71A8"/>
to return again into this Jurisdiction, without the allowance of the major part of the Council first had and published, on penalty of being banished upon <HI>pain of Death</HI>; and any one Magistrate, upon complaint, or information, given him of any such Person, shall cause them to be apprehended, and it upon Examination of the cause, he shall find Just grounds for such complaint he shall commit such Person to Prison, until he come to his Tryal, as above expressed.</P>
<P><HI>Observe,</HI> Here you may still note the Work of the Wicked, in whom he that was a Lyar and Murderer from the beginning▪ gave them no rest from their bloody pursuit after the Lives of the Righteous, whom the Lord did preserve in all their deep sufferings and firey Tryals, that not one of the faithful Sufferers for his Cause conformed to their wicked Will, who would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> endure any that differed in Judgment from their Priests Worship to inhabit within their Jurisdiction, who without <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ear to God, or regard to Man, contrary to the Laws of the <HI>English Nation,</HI> without either fear or regard to God, King or Bishops, made the defence of their Faith, Church and Common Wealth (as they call themselves) as strong as poss<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ble they could with <HI>Sto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, Goal</HI> and <HI>Gallows,</HI> on which the chiefest strength of their Faith did depend; for when all their other Anti-christian Weapons failed them against the <HI>Quakers,</HI> the Gallows held, until the Kings Letter came, and removed the strength of their faith in that also; yet they continued by their old wonted way of picki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g away mens Estates, by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ining them in great Sums for dessenting from their Priests Worship, which from the <HI>Quakers, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> them of the <HI>Church of England</HI> and others am<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unted to abou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Twenty Thousand Pounds, in the bounds of <HI>New England.</HI></P>
<L>When Wolves once got a taste of Blood,</L>
<L>They are for killing all that's good.</L>
<P><PB N="14" REF="000801_0016_0FAA4FB62C492498"/>This Court being desirous to try all means, wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h as much le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y as may consist with our safety, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o prevent the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rusions of the <HI>Quakers,</HI> who besides their absurd and blasph<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mous Doctrines, do like Rogues and Vagabonds come in upon us, and have not been restrained by the Laws already prov<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ded.</P>
<P><HI>Observe</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ave <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>xes Preamble to their Wel <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Law, whose Ravinous blood-thirsty Nature is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> contented with the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>eece, but strive all they can <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as have done the Wicked <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> part) to have the innocent Blood <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lso (as did their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Bon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er</HI> in Queen <HI>Mary's</HI> time) whenas to many Thousands of People it is well known that those which suffered in <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w-England,</HI> under the Name of <HI>Quakers,</HI> were neither in Doctrine, P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inciple nor Practise, any way guilty of these Persecutor charge, b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t on the co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t any differing there-from, as Light from Darkness, Truth from Error, God from the Devil, Christ from <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and Heaven from Hell, from whence is the Power and Spirit of all these that put people to Death for their Faith and Obedience to God, who permits these things to be done by the instruments of the wicked one, for a tryal of Faith to those who are made w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ing to part with all for the sake of him that first <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ved them, and gives them that Power through which they re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e strength to withstand all the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers of Hell, from whence pro∣ceedeth the Spirit of these persecutors, as did them in dayes past, <HI>John</HI> 8.44. <HI>Mat.</HI> 23.32, 33, 34, 35, 36. whose safety did (as these to remain by the strength of unrighteous Laws, and as they sold, so say these, <HI>We have a Law, and by our Law, every Person dissenting from our Church Order, and against the Government of our Common Wealth, as is manifest the</HI> Quakers <HI>do, by condemning the Proceedings of this Court against Dissenters, who by our Law ought to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI> Which proves these Persecutors t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he true Vagabonds, by having no dwelling in the Truth.</P>
<TRAILER><L>Vagabonds are, as was their Brother Cain,</L>
<L>Who murder them, that in the Truth remain</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="15" REF="000801_0017_0FAA4FB6F4154080"/>
<HEAD>New-England Persecutors Laws against the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ings Subjects.</HEAD>
<P>Have ordered, That every such Vagabond <HI>Quaker</HI> found within any part of this Jurisdiction, shall be apprehended by any Person or Persons, or by the Constable of the Town, where he or she is found, and by the Constable, or in his absence, by any other Person or Persons, conveyed b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fore the next Magistrate of that shire, where they are taken, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Commissioner invested with Magistratical Power, and bring by them adjudged to be a wandering <HI>Quaker, viz.</HI> such that hath no orderly al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owance in this Ju∣ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>diction, and not giving civil Respect or by any other <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mani<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esting himse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to be a <HI>Quaker,</HI> shall by warrant under the hand of the said Magistrate or Commissioner▪ directed to the Constable of the Town, or to any other meet Person▪ be stripped from the middle, upward, and tyed to a Carts Fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l, and whipped through the Town, and from thence Immediately conveyed to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onstable of the next Town towards the b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rder, of our J<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>isdiction, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> their Warrant shall direct▪ til the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> conveyed through the outward most Towns of our jurisdiction</P>
<P><HI>Ob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erve</HI> That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the follow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of their many W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rants of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Blood<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Whipping of the Innocent <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> who by the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> allow∣ance to trade, buy or se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l with<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> for which cause of being so prohibit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, and found with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of Jurisdiction, are by them called <HI>Vagabonds,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> being found, as <HI>Cain</HI> was, to have no dwelling in i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> are the right time <HI>Vagabonds,</HI> endeavouring (as much as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>) to whip others from their certain dwellings <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to become <HI>Vagabonds</HI> like themselves.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="16" REF="000801_0018_0FAA4FB7D7237258"/>
<HEAD>A <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> one of their many Warr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt▪</HEAD>
<P><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="warrant">
<P>TO the Constable of <HI>Dover, Hampton, Salsbury, Newbe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Ipswich, Wenham, Li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n, Boston, Rox<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ury,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and untill these Vagabond. <HI>Quakers</HI> are carryed <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> jurisdiction, You, and every of you are required of the Kings Name to take <HI>Ann Coleman, Mary Tomkins, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Ambrose</HI> and make them fast to the Carts Tail, and driving the Cart through your several Towns to whip them upon their Naked Backs, and not exceeding Ten Stripes on each of them in each Town; and so to convey them from Constable to Constable, till they come out of this Jurisdiction, as you will answer it at your peril. And this shall be your Warrant. Dated at <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>over, December</HI> the 22th, 1662.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Per me Richard Walde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
<P><HI>Observe,</HI> Here are Eleven Towns in the Warrant, and from the first Town <HI>Dover,</HI> to the last Town <HI>Drah<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m,</HI> is about eight<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Miles, and Ten Stripes on each of them in each Town, is One hundred and Ten stpipes a peice with a Whip made with three small single hair twisted Cords, each of which being knotted <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for the Priests Work to defend their Faith, and so laid on the naked Backs of the innocent <HI>Quakers,</HI> as if it were possible, the Knots might kiss the Bones, which cruel work was agreeable to the Priests exhorting their Drudges from those Scriptures <HI>Judg</HI> 5.23 <HI>Jer.</HI> 48.10. which Work was as far from the Work of God, in this day, as Heaven is from Hell, as may be read. <HI>Luke</HI> 9.54, 55 56. <HI>Mat.</HI> 5.44, 45, 46. <HI>Luke</HI> 6.31 32, 33. <HI>Mat.</HI> 13.28, 29, 30. 2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 10 3, 4, 5, 6. but contrary to these Perse∣cutors act, as we read, <HI>John</HI> 8.44. <HI>Mat.</HI> 6.24. <HI>For his Servants they are to whom they obey,</HI> Ram. 6.16. But as their laws were
<PB N="17" REF="000801_0019_0FAA4FB8D1A90EA0"/>
bloody and their execution Cruel and Barbaron<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, so hath God suffered both he that drew the Warrant, with many more of his persecuting Brethren, to be destroyed, and their Riches consumed by the great Judgments of God upon them, as is mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> at large to be seen in the aforesaid late book, entituled <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>held forth and maintained, by Thomas Maule.</HI> And when the <HI>Quaker<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> were commonly so whipt, with their torn Flesh and bloody <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, had about fifty miles to travel through the Wilderness <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> before they came to their Friends at <HI>Rode-Island</HI>▪ and so hard weather with frost and snow, that divers People have been killed there-with in travelling between Town and Town, though was two or three <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> from each other.</P>
<TRAILER><L>The Devil and the Priests, and all such Wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rant Makers,</L>
<L>In full Commu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion are, with all such <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>The Persecutors Law against the Kings good Subject</HEAD>
<P>And if such Vagabond <HI>Quakers</HI> shall return again, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o be in the like manner apprehended, &amp; conveyed as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> as they shall be found within the limits of our Jurisdiction, provided every such Vagabond <HI>Quaker</HI> have been thrice convicted, and sent away, as aforesaid, and returning again into this Jurisdiction, shall be apprehended, and Com∣mitted by any Magistrate, as aforesaid, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the house of Correction within the County, where he or she is found, until the next Court within that County, where if the Court judge not meet to release them, they shall be branded with the Letter R on their left Should<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and sent away in manner as before.</P>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, here you may understand that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> se <HI>Cain-like</HI> p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ted Vagabonds, did extend <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, as well as these <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Quakers,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to dissen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> from their Priests <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="18" REF="000801_0020_0FAA4FB97B7C12B8"/>
against their unrighteous Proceedings against the People of God and the Kings Subjects, which was tyranical, cruel, bloody and barbarous, that if any Person (though the <HI>Church of England,</HI>) was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ound to petition to the King and Bishops to maintain their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> respecting their worship agreeable to the way of the <HI>English</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it was accounted high Rebellion by these Persecutors so to do for which Offence, no less then Imprisonment and three Hun∣dred Pound<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, would keep them from being hanged on the New-England gallows till dead, dead, and of this nature, by impri∣sonment and paying three hundred pounds apiece, was Dr. <HI>Child, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Maverick,</HI> and other Merchants in <HI>Boston,</HI> kept from being hanged, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> being taken, with a Petition to send to <HI>England,</HI> a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> aforesaid. Of which when I come to give an account of the <HI>English <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> being persecuted by these <HI>New-England</HI> Free-men, to do what they saw mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> pleasing to their Priests, shall the more speak relating to the aforesaid suffering of Dr. <HI>Child, Samue∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>verick</HI> and others of the <HI>Church of England</HI> as aforesaid.</P>
<TRAILER><L>From all Bloody Free <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, pray God deliver me,</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y are for Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ging <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, that one <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> toem not be.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> against the King<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Subjects.</HEAD>
<P>And if after this he or she shall return again, then to be proceeded again <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Incorrigible R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s and Enemies to the common Peace▪ and shall imm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>diately be apprehended and committed to the common Goal of the County, and the next Court of Assistants shall be brought to the Tryal, and proceeded against according to the former Law made 1658. for their punishment on Pain of Death. <HI>Psalm</HI> 94.20, 21.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> You may understand, that of this nature it hath been in all Ages to the People of God, for as it is written, <HI>He that is born after the flesh, persecution him that is born after the Spirit,</HI> even so it is now▪ <HI>Gal.</HI> 4.29. and that the People are great sufferers as by these Laws, when they fall into the hands of Hypocrites, which pretend so much
<PB N="19" REF="000801_0021_0FAA4FBC40679F58"/>
to Religion, as did the wicked <HI>Jews</HI> to destroy the righteous in that day, which work (as we read in the holy Scriptures, Books of Martyrs, and the like true Histories) ever did, as now it doth, begin at the house of the persecuting Priests, who would have none live save those that are one with them in all things that tend to the upholding them with Money for preaching, which is made up with other mens word, whose Life and experience they witness nothing of, but at random make a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> days Image with stolen words, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> which they fright the People that know no b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tter then to buy of their Ware, which further then they write it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, lose it before the next market day; such like is the preaching and teaching o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> every Hypocritical Hireling and Persecuting <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> does leaven every Persecutor of their Church <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> in the like covetous practice, through whose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> many have been horribly cheated. Now if <HI>New</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> be not highly guilty of these things, as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to Death for Religion, then the People <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the more to blame, to cry out at the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> so much as they do against <HI>Persecutors, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Doctrine, Surfeited Horses,</HI> and the like of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Cheats, with which it is common for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to trade.</P>
<TRAILER><L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/></L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>New-England Persecutors Laws against the King <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HEAD>
<P>And for such <HI>Quakers</HI> as shall arise from amongst our selves, they shall be proceeded against <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Anno 165<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. doth provide, until they have been <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> by the Court of Assistants, and bring <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> shall th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n be banished the Jurisdiction, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> they sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>l return, and be found in any part of this Ju<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>diction, then <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="20" REF="000801_0022_0FAA4FBD41523608"/>
be proceeded against as those that are strangers and Vaga∣bond▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> in manner as before expressed.</P>
<P><HI>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI> The Reader may hence understand, that as their Laws were blood<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, the cruel nature of their or believing hard hearts, was in the execution of their Laws, agreeable thereunto, who being be∣witched by a Company of hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eling Priests) not to obey the Truth, were through obedience to wicked Spirits, mad after the blood of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nnocent, that the devout Members of their Antichristi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n Church; did Act with that sury to the <HI>Quakers,</HI> as if they could never use t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o much Cruelty upon them, which was the more by the Priest-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>idden Executioners, through the Priests pronouncing Woes and bitter Curses against all such as should fail in the neglect of their work for the Devil, against both <HI>Quakers, Baptists,</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of the <HI>Church of England</HI> as well as against all other Dissenters, which Curses they still back't with Scripture words, as aforesaid, <HI>Judg.</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.23. <HI>Jer.</HI> 48.10. which work (as the wicked did, so these pretended) was done by them for the honour of God, and glory of his Name, and that their Church was the purest Reformed Church of all other <HI>Christian Churches in the World,</HI> But, if the pureity of a Church consist in such wicked works as they have done by virtue of unrighteous Laws against the People of God, and the Kings Sub∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ects, then it is manifest (by the length of time in the like cruel bloody Work) that their Mother Church of <HI>Rome</HI> is more purer then theirs. But if Persecution be the work of the Devil, (as by Scripture it is manifest so to be) then according to Christs own words, <HI>they are Children of him whose work they do,</HI> then it most consequently follow, that <HI>Romes</HI> Church, being the first under the Name <HI>Christian,</HI> found to persecute, that all under that name <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to persecute, are her children, whom so often they call the great Whore.</P>
<TRAILER><L>The Devil, Work not only done to Quaker!▪</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Dissenters were in part Pertakers.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="21" REF="000801_0023_0FAA4FBDCCD412A8"/>
<HEAD>New-England Persecutors Law against the Kings Subjects.</HEAD>
<P>And it is further Ordered That whatsoever charge shall arise about apprehending, whipping, conveying, or other∣wise about the <HI>Quakers,</HI> to be laid out by the Constable of such Town where it is expended, and to be repaid by the Treasurer, out of the next County Levy. And further ordered, That the Constables of their several Towns are hereby impowered, from time to time, to impress Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en, and other Assistance, for the Execution of this Order. 1661.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> The Reader may hence understand, That for the cloaking of the Devils Work they made all their unrighteous Warrants run in the Kings Name, as if he was the Author of their cruel Work against Dissenters, when as it manifestly appears, both by the holy Scriptures, and also by the Kings Letter (a Copy of which will follow) That they had no Warrant, Precept or Command either from God or the King, but did wholly act and do according to their own Wills, which still remain the same, to work Mischief against both <HI>Quakers, Baptists,</HI> and the <HI>Church of England</HI> also, (as will hereafter evidently appear) but their Horns at present are shortened, and their Cloak begins to appear threed-bare, and now their Hypocrisie and Deceit will no longer hide their Wickedness from the King and People, whose Money out of the Treasury must serve to defray the Charge of the Devil's Work against the Kings good Subjects, who had taken from them, by the persecuting Churches in <HI>New-England,</HI> to the value of Twenty Thousand Pounds, for Fines imposed upon them, because Dissenters from their way of Worship, whose Priests and Rulers had also of their People yearly Sallarys, according to the same Proportion of the aforesaid Sum of twenty thousand Pounds, through which mean, as these Persecutors lived at a high rate on that which others <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> laboured hard to get, went in thred-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are Coats, and their Famili<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
<PB N="22" REF="000801_0024_0FAA4FBE75674F78"/>
in want of that which was their own, and devoured by this perse∣cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, whereby their great Oppression reached the whole People of the ordinary degree, even as a sweeping Rain, that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> all before it.</P>
<TRAILER><L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, who for uprighteous Gain,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> as People do Oppress, themselves for to maintain.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>New-England Persecutors Laws against the Kings Subjects Suspended (during their pleasure.)</HEAD>
<P>This Court heretofore, for some Reasons inducing, did judge meet to suspend the Execution of the Laws against <HI>Quakers</HI> as such, so far as they respect corporal Punishment or Death, during the Courts pleasure.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> That tho' these Persecutors saw there was cause to suspend their bloody Laws against the Kings good Subjects, so far as they did respect corporal Punishment or Death, yee it must be only during their own pleasure, not the Kings, no, they could not stoop to that. But whether they did not herein manifest a Spirit of Re∣bellion against God, the Kings Order (as by his Letter will appear) and the Laws of the <HI>English Nation,</HI> I leave others to judge. Now the occasion of procuring this Order from the King, was their great Cruelty in banishing sober honest People out of their Juris∣diction upon <HI>Pain of Death,</HI> if they returned; for as before is said of Dr. <HI>Child, Samuell Maverick,</HI> and other Merchants, whose Im∣prisonment and three hundred Pounds a piece, saved them from the <HI>New-England</HI> Gallows, and none, without the like hazard, migh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> make complaint to <HI>England</HI>; but several banished <HI>Quakers</HI> adven∣tured to lay their said suffering case before the King, whose merciful Ear heard their Cry, and took Compassion on his suffering Subjects, and forth-with stopt <HI>New-England</HI> Persecutors wicked hands from shedding more innocent Blood, being acquainted with their great <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the manner of their Sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s by what
<PB N="23" REF="000801_0025_0FAA4FBF3310FB98"/>
their Brother <HI>H. Peters, Vennor,</HI> &amp; other of their <HI>N. England</HI> Brethren had done both against his Father and himself, as by his Letter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> with them, as afterwards it proved so to be, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> with the Tope Tile or covering of a fair outside Building, whose inside is full of all manner of Deceit, and the Foundation thereof very dangerous, by degrees, in working down-wards, till he comes to the Foundation, which after wards was wholly removed, through the loss of their Charter, which to them had been as an Idol Godd, in which they trusted as much as ever the People did in <HI>Baal</HI>; and if ever Silver and Gold procure such another, it may be at a high Rate, and they are like to be as cruel as before. But the <HI>English Laws</HI> are far before <HI>New-England</HI> Idols.</P>
<TRAILER><L>God will not ever permit the Devils Power,</L>
<L>Nor wicked Men the Righteous to devour</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>A Copy of the King's Letter.</HEAD>
<LETTER>
<OPENER><SIGNED>Charles R.</SIGNED></OPENER>
<P>TRusty and well beloved, We greet you well Having been informed that several of Our Sub∣jects amongst you, called <HI>Quakers,</HI> have been and are Imprisoned by you, whereof some have been Executed, and others in danger to undergo the like, We have thought sit to signifie Our Pleasure in that behalf, for the future, and do hereby Require, That if there be any of those People called <HI>Quakers</HI> amongst you, now already condemned to suffer Death, or are Imprisoned, and obnoctious to the like Condemnation, You are to
<PB N="24" REF="000801_0026_0FAA4FBFF3C46930"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> any further therein, but that you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ead the said Persons, whether condemned or imprisoned, over into this our Kingdom of <HI>England,</HI> to∣gether with their respective Crimes or Offences laid to their Charge, to the end such course may be taken with them here, as shall be agreeable to our Laws, and their Demerits. And for so doing, these Our Letter shall be your sufficient Warrant and Discharge.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE><HI>Given at our Court at</HI> White-hall,
<DATE><HI>the</HI> 9<HI>th day of</HI> Septemb. 1661. <HI>in the</HI> 13<HI>th Year of Our Reign.</HI></DATE></DATELINE>
<HI>Subscribed to Our trusty &amp; well-beloved</HI> John Endicot, <HI><ABBR>Esq</ABBR> and to all and every other Governours of Our Plantation of</HI> New-England, <HI>and to all the Collonies thereunto belonging, that now are, or hereafter shall be; and to all and every the Ministers and Officers of Our said Plantation and Col∣lonies whatsoever within the Continent of</HI> New-England.
<SIGNED><HI>By His Majesty's Command,</HI> W. Morris.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> Now these Persecutors had nothing to charge these Innocent People with, but that they were <HI>Quakers,</HI> against whom they had provided a Law, but this Law was repugnant to the Laws of the <HI>English Nation</HI>; and therefore upon the receipt of the Kings Letter, they durst do no other than set at liberty both them condemned to suffer Death, and those imprisoned also; but herein they did not obey the Kings Command; for he commanded them to send these <HI>Quakers</HI> so imprisoned or condemned, over to <HI>England,</HI> with the particular Crimes laid to their charge; but this they would not do, and good reason why, they had no Crimes to lay to their
<PB N="27" REF="000801_0027_0FAA4FC0BAA317D8"/>
Charge, but that they were <HI>Quakers.</HI> And being brought to this pinch, instead of sending a Ship load of <HI>Quakers,</HI> and a large Roll of their Crimes of Treason, Rebellion, Subversion of Govern∣ment, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> home to the King, they send a Ship load of Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts for a Present to the King, with a parcell of horrid Wicked Lyes against the <HI>Quakers</HI>; to defray the charge of which Presen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, the poor In∣habitants were severely Rated. After which their great Deceit and abominable Hypocrisie, the King came to find out, not only in do∣ing as aforesaid, but upon many other accounts, too large here to relate; and before I conclude, enough against them will appear, to manifest their great Wickedness against God, the King and People. Yet not withstanding all this, they could not long forbear their old work of Persecution, but soon put their Law in execution again; for the Kings Letter was dated, 1661. and they revived their old Law again in 1662. which was done more in obedience to the Devil, and to please their hireling Priests, than in honour to God, or respect to the King, against whom they did rebell in so doing, as appears by his Letter, and their not sending any of the <HI>Quakers</HI> over into the Kingdom of <HI>England,</HI> but instead thereof sent a Present with a parcell of Lyes, too large here to relate, and put their Law into Execution again, and as sharp, cruel and har∣barous was the Execution (respecting corporal punishment) as formerly, though the Towns were not to be so many in which they were to be whipt, yet the Whip with three single hair twisted small Cords (each being knotted, fit for the Devil and Priests Work) was the same as before the Kings Letter came, and did so continue till near or about the time they lost their Idol, <HI>viz.</HI> their old Charter, on which was their dependance, above <HI>GOD</HI> or <HI>KING,</HI> as is manifested by their Works.</P>
<TRAILER><L>Priests Rulers Masts for Ships, Deceit and Lyes withall.</L>
<L>Poor People made to pay, for Presents to <HI>White-hall.</HI></L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="28" REF="000801_0028_0FAA4FC176060460"/>
<HEAD><HI>New-England</HI> Persecutors Laws against the Kings good Subjects, (upon Complains of the Priests) put into Execution again.</HEAD>
<P>NOW forasmuch as new Complaints are made <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o this Court, of such Persons abounding, especially in the Eastern parts, endeavouring to draw away others to that wicked Opinion, it is Ordered, That the last Law, Tit. <HI>Vagabond, Quakers, May</HI> 1661 be hence-forth in force, in all respects, provided, their Whipping be but through three Towns, and the Magistrate or Commissioner signing the Warrant, shall appoint both the Towns, and number of Stripes in each Town to be given, 1662.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> Here by comparing this their Date to their Law, with the date of the Kings Letter, how little regard they had to the Kings Mind and Will therein contained, which was, <HI>whether conde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ned to suffer Death, or Imprisoned, or to suffer corporal Punishment, to forbear to proceed any further therein, but forthwith to send the said Person over into the Nation of</HI> England, <HI>with the respective Crimes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Offence <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to their Charge, to the end such course might be taken with them, accor∣ding to the Nature of the Offence, as should be agreeable to the English Laws.</HI> Which express command of the King was but a small time minded by them; for upon their considering the cause some small time, proposed to themselves, that by virtue of their Idol Charter, they had as much Power in <HI>New-England</HI> as the King had in <HI>Old-England,</HI> and had they the like strength of Men and Shipping, would (no doubt) with-stand all Kings and Princes that should ad∣venture to oppose their way; now had not I my self heard some of them say these things, durst not have charg'd it here upon them, to publick view; and for a further evidence of the same, witness their Proclaiming, (with a Trumpet before them,) against the Kings Commissioners in <HI>Boston,</HI> perswading the People, (as near <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB N="29" REF="000801_0029_0FAA4FC23715B710"/>
as they could) <HI>That their Commissions were made under a Hedge,</HI> with m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch more of the like Nature, too lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ge here to relate.</P>
<TRAILER><L>Priests Rulerr bloody Work, on People hath brought Wo,</L>
<L>With their consent that silent were to have it so.</L>
<L>They'r Works of him that is of Hell,</L>
<L>'Gainst God and King all such Rebell.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>New-England</HI> Persecutors Law against the Kings Subjects.</HEAD>
<P>Whereas it may be found amongst us, that mens Thresholds are set up by Gods Thresholds, and mens Posts by Gods Posts, especially in open Meetings of the <HI>QƲAKERS,</HI> whose damnable Heresies, and abo∣minable Idolatries are hereby promoted, imbraced and practised, to the Scandal of Religion, hazard of Souls and provocation of divine Jealousie against this People. For Prevention and Reformation whereof, it is Ordered by this Court, and the Authority thereof, That every Person found at a <HI>Quakers</HI> Meeting, shall be apprehended, <HI>ex Officio,</HI> by the Constable, and by Warrant from a Magistrate or Commissioner, shall be committed to the House of Cor∣rection, and there to have the Discipline of the House ap∣plyed unto them, and to be kept to work with Bread and Water for three days together, and then to be released; or else shall pay a fine of five Pounds in Money, to the Country, for every such Offence; and all Constables neglecting the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r Duty, in not faithfully executing this Order▪ shall in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur the Penalty of 5 <HI>l.</HI> upon conviction, one third part where∣of to the Inform<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></P>
<P><PB N="30" REF="000801_0030_0FAA4FC328E82718"/><HI>Obs.</HI> The Reader may here take Notice of one of these Perse∣cutors many horrid and wicked Lyes, so proved by their Contra∣diction, who in their Preambles to their Laws, accuse the <HI>Quakers</HI> with keeping their Meetings private, yet at unawares in their Bride-well Law they charge the contrary; and though they pretend the sin is great, yet it may be bought off for five Pounds in Mercy, as often as they please; but the said Sum not being paid them by any one, they were much enraged thereat, finding their covetous de∣sign in making said Law, disappointed, because it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>each no further than to punish them that were not free to pay 5 <HI>l.</HI> for being at a <HI>Quakers</HI> Meeting, as aforesaid, the Penalty of which Law several Merchants in <HI>Boston</HI> suffered, rather than to disobey God, by satis∣fying the lust of such covetous Priests and Rulers, who prefer the love of Money before punishing for that which themselves account so great sins, as by the Preamble of their Laws they pretend these above-mentioned to be.</P>
<TRAILER><L>Their bloody Laws are almost done,</L>
<L>Which Work the Priests at first begun.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>New-England</HI> Persecutors Preamble to their Laws against provoking Evils, as they call them.</HEAD>
<P>Whereas the most wise &amp; holy God for these several years past, hath not only warned us by his word, but chastized us with his Rod, inflicting upon us many general Judg∣ments, but we have neither heard the word nor rod as we ought to be effectually humbled for our sins, to repent of them, hence it is the righteous God hath hightened our Calamity, and given Commission to the barbarous <HI>Heathen</HI> to rise up against us, and become a smart Rod and severe Scourge to us, in burning and depopulating several hop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>¦ful
<PB N="31" REF="000801_0031_0FAA4FC3D5B27950"/>
Plantations, murdering many of our Inhabitants of all sorts, and seeming, as it were, to cast us off, and putting us to shame, and not going forth with our Arms, hereby speaking aloud to us, to search and try our ways, and turn again unto the Lord our God, from whom we have depart∣ed with great back-sliding</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> That to acknowledge the Truth is well, and well would it be indeed if they were found acknowledging the whole Truth, and to repent of shedding innocent Blood, which is the great sin of <HI>New England</HI> Priests and Rulers, as also of the consenting Church Members thereof; but of this there is no mention made in their Preamble confession of words, without Works of Truth and Righ∣teousness to God and People, according as is at large manifest by their afore-mentioned Laws, the neglect of which Execution was by their Priests imputed to be the main cause of general Judgment to come upon them. But they use to say, <HI>If all the</HI> Quakers <HI>were hanged, and all other Dissenters clear'd out of their Jurisdiction, then would their Land enjoy Peace:</HI> Unto which Work the Rulers were bewitched, so far as the Devil was permitted to drive them, who were as willing to run, and to work they went against all Dissenters, and set forth a Book against the <HI>Baptists,</HI> entituled, <HI>The Rise and Foundation of the cursed Sect of</HI> Annabaptists, in which was as many Lyes as they use to gather for their Pulpit Work on the first Day against the <HI>Quakers,</HI> which Lyes to hear also cost<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the People Money.</P>
<TRAILER><L>None are more blind than those that will not see,</L>
<L>The cause for which Gods general Judgments be.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>New-England</HI> Pers<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tors Law against Provoking Evils, as they call them.</HEAD>
<P N="1">1. This Court apprehending there is too great a neglect of Discipline in the Churches, and especially respecting
<PB N="32" REF="000801_0032_0FAA4FC72C59F930"/>
those that are their Children, through the non<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>acknowledg∣ment of them, according to the Order of the Gospel, in watching <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> them, as well as Catechizing of them, in∣quiring into their spiritual states, that being brought to take hold of the Covenant, they may acknowledge, and be ac∣knowledged, according to their relation to God and his Church, and their Obligation to be the Lord, and approve themselves so to be by a suitable Profession and Conver∣sation; And do therefore solemnly recommend it unto the respective Elders and Brethren of the Churches throughout this jurisdiction, to take effectual course for the Refor∣mation therein.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> By the afore-mentioned cruel bloody Laws against the People of God, what nature their Church Government was of, in which Covenant, the words, <HI>Beware of the Leaven of the Pharisees,</HI> was put of, and instead thereof they put in, <HI>Beware of the Leaven of the</HI> Quakers; for which see <HI>Salem</HI> Church Covenant, so called, caused to be so done by their high Priest, <HI>John Higinson,</HI> who in his preaching told the People, <HI>The</HI> Quakers <HI>Light was a stinking Vapour from Hell,</HI> with much more of the like, as was usual with him in his daily Preaching and Teaching against the <HI>Quakers, Baptists,</HI> and other Dissenters, this Old-Charter Priest, with other of his devout Church-Brethren in Iniquity, use to wish their Children might be Rogues and Whores, rather than <HI>Quakers</HI>; which was too nearly (tho' justly fullfilled upon many of them, as well as upon this old Priests, whose Daughter was highly accused of Witch-craft, and now maintained by the Parish. It is dreadful to consider what Wickedness is in mens hearts, to wish such horrid Wishes, as the <HI>Jews</HI> did, <HI>Mat.</HI> 27.25. which justly came upon them, as upon these of the like Spirit.</P>
<TRAILER><L>No Members Child, a Member then could be,</L>
<L>From <HI>Quakers</HI> Blood in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="33" REF="000801_0033_0FAA4FC8AD06CF48"/>
<HEAD><HI>New England</HI> Persecutors Laws against provoking Evils, as they call them.</HEAD>
<P N="2">2. Whereas there is manifest Pride openly appearing amongst us, in that long hair is worn by some men, either their own, or the hair of others made into Perriwigs; and by some Women wearing Borders of Hair, and their cut∣ting and cursing, and laying out their Hair; which Pra∣ctise doth prevail and increase, especially among the Younger sort. This Court doth declare against this evil Practise, as Offensive to them and divers sober <HI>Christians</HI> amongst us, and therefore do hereby Enact and Advise all Perso<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to use moderation in this respect. And further, to impower all Grand Juries to present to the County Courts all such Persons, whether Male or Female, whom they shall judge to exceed in the Premises; and the County Courts are authorized to proceed against such Delinquents, either by Admonition, or Fine, or Correction, according to their good Discretion.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> That through the long continuance of Disobedience, which is as Rebellion, and the sin of Witchcraft, being highly guilty of Innocent Blood, these Persecutors had lost their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> over their own Families, who began to run into great Super<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ity and Entravagancy of those things which were not comely, dec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and of good Report, in which they did greatly increase, and now abound beyond all the Power of their Laws to restrain. Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>refo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e they may now see, their ungodly wicked Wishes are come both upon themselves and Children; for <HI>the Curse of the Lord <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the House of them that have either actually or by consent <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Lord guilty of shedding Innocent Blood,</HI> Prov. 3.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>3 Mal. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
<TRAILER><L>From all evil Wishes, pray God deliver <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>And from all Wickedness me and mine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="34" REF="000801_0034_0FAA4FC8F473E6F8"/>
<HEAD><HI>N. England</HI> Persecutors Laws against provoking Evils, as they call them.</HEAD>
<P N="3">3. Notwithstanding the wholsom Laws already made by this Court for the restraining Excess in Apparel, yet through the corruption in many, and neglect of due execution of those Laws, the evil of Pride in Apparel, both for costliness in the poorer sort, and vain new strange Fashions, both in Poor and Rich, with naked Breasts and Arms, or as it were pin∣nioned with the Addiction of Superfluous Ribbands, both on Hair and Apparel, for redress whereof, it is Ordered by this Court, That the County Courts, from time to time, shall give strict Charge to present all such Persons, as they shall judge exceed in that kind; &amp; if the grand Jury shall neglect their duty herein, the County Courts shall impose a Fine upon them at their own Discretion.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> The outward Appearance of these Persecutors, by their <HI>smooth</HI> words &amp; fair speeches, as also their short hair even or above their Ears, with high crownd Hats, peacked Boards, as likewise their two or three inch broad Bands, and their Apparel agreeable thereunto, by which they appoured in the outward, like men dif∣fering from all other people whatsoever, which with their Priests dayly preaching, and their often loud praying, and their works not agreeable with their words, were by their fruits manifested to be men of the like Spirit whom Christ bid beware of, <HI>Mat.</HI> 7.15. which the more to be accounted <HI>good Christians,</HI> under which name they pretended all their proccedings against the evil of pride, to be for the honour of God, and the good of the People Souls, when on the contrary it appears otherwise, by their sailing that which themselves account sin, for money, which doth clearly manifest their work to be done in honour to themselves, whose love is to the Peoples Money, for the satisfying their own coveteous Desires; which work doth manifest Coveteousness, Pride and Oppresion
<PB N="35" REF="000801_0035_0FAA4FC9B3951018"/>
and Oppression in such Priests and Rulers that eat up the sin of the People, <HI>Hos.</HI> 4.8.9. <HI>Micah</HI> 3.11.</P>
<TRAILER><L>Gods Cause is that to which they do pretend,</L>
<L>But all men may see, Money is their end.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>New-England</HI> Persecutors Laws against provoking Evils, as they call them.</HEAD>
<P>And it is further ordered, That the County Court, single Magistrate or Commissioners Court in <HI>Boston,</HI> have hereby Power to summons all such persons so offending, before them, and for the first Offence to admonish them, and for each offence of that kind afterwards to impose a fine of Ten Shillings upon them, or if unable to pay, to inflict such pu∣nishment as shall be by them thought most suitable to the nature of the Offence; and the same Judges above-named are hereby impowered to judge of, and execute the Laws already extant against such Excess.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> Whipping, or the like punishment, was only to such person<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> unable to pay their Fine, though the offence was no breath of any <HI>English Law,</HI> but these Sin-sellers Laws are distinct from all the Laws of other Nations that I have read or heard of, and indeed, in most things their Doctrines, Principles and Practices the same, which are not only condemned by all <HI>true Christians,</HI> but also by the <HI>Indians, Turks</HI> and other moral <HI>Heathens,</HI> who abhor the practice of living upon the Fines of people not found to t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ansgress the Law or Laws of their Nation, as these <HI>New-England</HI> Priests and Rulers do, whose income for such like things, by them imputed to the Peoples trans∣gressing such like laws as above said is to les<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n Twelve Hundred Pounds a year, besides fif<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>een hundred Pounds a year from Persons chiefly of their own Churches, for the sin of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>cleanness, as also some years, no less th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rty Hundred Pounds a year for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,
<PB N="36" REF="000801_0036_0FAA4FCA8BB74098"/>
they compelled from the people of God and the Kings good Subjects dissenting from their Priests Worship, with which, and ten Thou∣sand Pounds yearly paid the Priests for preaching, and as much yearly paid the Rulers for making Laws and judging; all which came out of the poor Peoples labour within the bounds of <HI>New-Englands</HI> Priests and Rulers.</P>
<TRAILER><L>Where men can mak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> what Laws they pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ase,</L>
<L>Such Pri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sts and Rulers live at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>New-England</HI> Persecutors Laws against proving <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, as they call them▪</HEAD>
<P>It is ordered by this Court That no person within this Jurisdiction, nor any of their Relations depending upon them, whose visible Estates, real and personal shall not exceed the true value o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> two hundred Pounds, shall not wear any Gold or Silver Buttons, or Gold or Silver Lace, or Bone Lace above two Shillings <HI>p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ard,</HI> or Silk Hoods, or Silk Scarfs, Points or Ribbands, or great Boots, upon the penalty of ten Shillings for every such Offence.</P>
<P>And further ordered by the Authority aforesaid. That the Select men of every Town, are hereby impowered, enabled and required to assess every such Person so offending, in any of the Particulars above-mentioned, in the Country Rates, at two hundred Pounds Estates according as such men pay to whom such apparel is allowed. Alwayes provi∣ded, That this Law shall not extend to the Restraint of any Magistrate, or publick Officer of this Jurisdiction, their Wives and Children, who are left to their own dis∣cretion in wearing Apparel, or any settled Mili<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ary Officer, or Sou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dier in the time of Military Service, or any other Whose Education and imployment have been above the
<PB N="37" REF="000801_0037_0FAA4FCB5556B520"/>
ordinary Degree, or whose Estates have been considerable, though now deacyed; 1651.</P>
<P>It is further ordered and Enacted by this Court, and the Authority thereof, that all Persons within this Juris∣diction that shall wear any Apparel exceeding their quality and Condition of their Persons or Estates, and either of these be so Judged by the Grand Jury and County Court of that shire where such complaint is made, all such Persons being convicted, shall for the first Offence be admonished, for the second Offence pay a Fine of twenty Shillings, for the third Offence forty Shillings a time, and so following as the Offences are multiplied, to pay forty Shillings a time to the Treasurer of that County.</P>
<P>And further ordered, That if any Taylor shall make or fashion any Garment for Children or Servants contrary to the mind and order of their Parents or Governours, every such Taylor shall for the first Offence be admonished, and for the second Offence, forfeit double the value of such Apparel or Garment as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e shall make or fashion contrary to the mind and order of such Pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ents or Governours, as aforesaid, the one ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> thereof to the Owner, and the other half to the Country. And all Grand-Jurys are hereby en∣joyned to present all those whom they shall Judge breake<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> of this Order. 1662.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> That in the year aforesaid, 1662. through the Priests advice they were hot in persecuting both <HI>Quakers, Baptists,</HI> and all other Dissenters, thinking thereby to fine and whip the <HI>Christian<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> from
<PB N="38" REF="000801_0038_0FAA4FCC50F65C88"/>
their Religion, which according to the advice of their hireling Priests, being in hopes to do, that when they had to done, and over-come the aforesaid provoki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>vils of Pride in Apparel, that God would the more hear <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> loud Prayers. and remove his great Judgments from amongst <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> certainly true, my self is witness to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> them say, <HI>That Gods Judgments would never remov<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> them, till all the Quakers and other Dissenters were hange <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of their Jurisdiction.</HI> And for another Instance, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, when <HI>Thomas Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>le</HI> of <HI>Salem</HI> came to one of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Rulers, for a Warrant to search for one hundred Pound<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> other rich Goods stole out of his shop the night <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> whom this Ruler answered, <HI>He would grant him no Warrant, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the Court of any <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that did grant him a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Moreover, in my hearing said to him, If a man knoc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you on the head, or hang you, the recompence is in your own hands; for you are not to be protected by the Laws of this Government.</HI> This was the Justice of this great Ruler and Church Member, free of their Body <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, as they call themselves, whose Laws allow that Apparel to themselves which to others they impute the we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ring of, to be <HI>one of the p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ovoking Evils</HI>; for which Offence as they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>) the Offender (by their Law) must be equally rated with such to whom the Law allows the said Apparel, as also to pay 40 <HI>s.</HI> a time, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s the Offence mul∣tiply; and if not able to pay, then to be punished.</P>
<TRAILER><L>Pride, Oppression and Covetousness abound,</L>
<L>All which by Priests and Rulers Law is found.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD><HI>New-England</HI> Persecutors Laws against provoking Evils, as they call them.</HEAD>
<P>Whereas there is much Prophaneness amongst us, in Persons turning their backs upon the publick Worship before it be finished, and the blessing pronounced, It is Ordered by this Court, That the Officers of the Churches,
<PB N="39" REF="000801_0039_0FAA4FCCF649CFD8"/>
or select men, shall take care to prevent such Disorders, by appointing Persons to shut the Meeting-house Doors, or any other meet way to attain the end.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> The time was now near at hand in wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>h all their wicked Works against Dissenters, as well as on other accounts, came to be throughly looked into by the King and Powers in <HI>England,</HI> who found then Unrighteousness so great, that, as before related, their building began a pace to be overthrown, which People per∣ceiving, many of the Priests Hearers began to give little heed o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> regard to their Idol Worship, to which they had been so long kept for divers years, meerly by the strength of unrighteous Laws; and now at this time finding the Priests and Rulers strength to confide in little more besides the Meeting-house Doors, in a little time after they had been in Meeting, were willing to depart, without hearing any more of the Priests long winded Railing against the <HI>Baptists, Quakers,</HI> and all other Dissenters; for which cause, I say, many Persons turning their backs upon the Worship before it was finish∣ed, and the Money-blessing pronounced, the Priests Money Box, always when done, held out by one of the Church Officers, would fall much short of the Priests pay for his Sermon, to what it use to do, when their cruel Laws were in more force than at this time; but the strength of their Meeting-house Doars, did at length also fail; yet at times, as the evil Spirit moved in them, they must r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> whom the Devil permits to drive into such Unrighteousness, would be afflicting one Dissenter or another, especially by Fines, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, Cart loads of Corn I have then seen the Priests drudges fetch from the People called <HI>Baptists,</HI> as also Goods and Cattle from others.</P>
<TRAILER><L>It was Prophaneness, as these Persecutors say,</L>
<L>I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Cause, the Priests did <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> more pay.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="40" REF="000801_0040_0FAA4FCD75BCCE30"/>
<HEAD>Old Charter Magistrates Hypocrisie, with an Instance of the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Deceit and C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eat amongst themselves, at their General High-Court of Injustice to others.</HEAD>
<P>An eminent Merchant in <HI>Boston,</HI> who is said to have erected the Town-House at his own charge, besides several other considerable Gifts to publick Uses, he kept an honest sober young Man to sell his Merchandize, and its like some∣what differing in Judgment from their Priests way of Worship; he through a mistake sold a Bridle for some∣thing more than was allowed by these Rulers for men to advance on the Shilling; and being complained of was fined a great Sum of Money, and besides was ordered to stand one hour in a publick Place with the Bridle in his Chaps; and the Fine was divided amongst the Magistrates, as one of them testified, who being out of Court at the time when the Division was made, was by his Brethren in Iniquity defrauded of his share, who was so offended at the same, that he openly complained of the Wrong he had received by his Brethren in this matter.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> You may perceive, that these Old Charter-men had strange kind of Laws, whereby to enrich themselves and impoverish others, as is already proved by their aforesaid unrighteous Laws, so also by this it appears to agree with the same, That no Merchant must advance more than <HI>q d.</HI> profit in the Shilling, for Goods from <HI>England,</HI> by means of which Law their Cloathing and Necessaries were to them, &amp; all of their way, at a che<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p rate; for themselves were only Merchants of Law, and their Priests Merchants of that which they call their Gospel; which Law is their Wills, and their
<PB N="41" REF="000801_0041_0FAA4FCE40411810"/>
Gospel other mens Lines made ready to their hands; but the Laws of the <HI>English Nation</HI> are otherwise, and the true Gospel, to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that believe, is the Power of God to Salvation.</P>
<TRAILER><L>By Religion, with Deceit,</L>
<L>Makes Hypocrites to be a Cheat.</L></TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="account">
<HEAD>A brief Account of some of the Three Hundred and Nine Persons that suffered Persecution under the Anti-christian Power of the <HI>New-England</HI> Church, besides those four Servants of the Lord cruelly Murthered by a Law made at the Rulers and Priests high Court of Injustice against Dis∣senters found with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n their Jurisdiction belonging to <HI>Boston,</HI> which are is followeth, <HI>viz.</HI></HEAD>
<P><HI>NIcholas Ʋpshall,</HI> an old Man full of Years, seeing their Cru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>y to the harmless <HI>Quakers,</HI> and that they had condemned some of them to dye, both he and elder <HI>Wisewell,</HI> or other wise Deacon <HI>Wisewell,</HI> Members of the Church in <HI>Boston,</HI> bore their Testimonies in publick against their Brethrens horrid Cruelty to the said <HI>Qua∣kers.</HI> And the said <HI>Ʋpshall</HI> declared, <HI>That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> did look at it as a sad fore-runner of some heavy Judgment to follow upon the Country.</HI> Which they took so ill at his hands, that they fined him Twenty Pounds, and three Pound more <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t another of their Courts, for not coming to their Meeting, and would not abate him one Grote, but imprisoned him, and then banished him on pain of Death; which was done in a time of such extream bitter Weather for Frost, Snow and Cold, that had not the <HI>Heathen Indians</HI> in the Wilderness Woods taken compassion on his Misery, for the winter Season, he in all likelihood had perished, though he had then in <HI>Boston</HI> a good Estate in Houses and Land, Goods and Money, as also Wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e and
<PB N="42" REF="000801_0042_0FAA4FCEE6FAE990"/>
Children, but not suffered to come unto him, nor he to them but more of his Sufferings are at large related in the Books of the <HI>Quakers</HI> Suffering Persecution under the Anti-christian Power of the <HI>New-England</HI> Church, and so proved to be by their fore-going Laws. And more of their Cruelty will here follow.</P>
<P>The next I shall mention is <HI>Anne Burden,</HI> whose Husband being dead, and having left Money due to him from several in <HI>New-England,</HI> his said Widdow came into their Jurisdiction to get in the said Debts, for the use of her self and Children. Now these Persecutors had nothing to charge her with, but that she was a plain <HI>Quaker,</HI> and for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and coming into their Jurisdiction, she must abide the Penalty of their Law, and which they executed upon her, and then sent her away without greeting in her just Debts, for which she came into their Jurisdiction. Which was one of their in∣ventions to pay Debts to Dissenters with, especially the <HI>Quakers.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Christopher Holder</HI> and <HI>John Copeland,</HI> men of good Estates, and of good Life amongst men, for being of those called <HI>Quakers,</HI> and coming into their Jurisdiction, and declaring the Truth, were cruelly whipt with their old wonted Whip of three fold Cords, each being well knotted, fit for their Church work, where-with their Member Whipper gave each of these men Thirty Stripes a piece, which were so cruelly laid on, that at the sight of their torn flesh and bloody backs a tender-hearted Person fell down dead; after they had been thus whipt, they were put into Bridewell, and there kept for three days without Bread or Water; and with their wounded backs were forced to lie on the Boards without Bed or Straw; and for Nine VVeeks were kept close Prisoners, where none, except the Goaler (that devout Member) could come unto them. After which, both they and Coll. <HI>Rous</HI>'s Son of <HI>Barbadoes</HI> had their Ears cut by the Member of their Peace, <HI>viz.</HI> the common <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> man. Now the reason why <HI>John Rous</HI> escaped with the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, was the kindness they had for him, in respect to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, and his being a Gentleman,
<PB N="43" REF="000801_0043_0FAA4FD024C617D0"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page〉"/></P>
<P><PB N="44" REF="000801_0044_0FAA4FD08AD40C88"/><HI>Sarah Gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bins</HI> and <HI>Dorothy Waugh,</HI> two young VVomen, for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of those called <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and coming into their Jurisdiction▪ had for their entertainment in <HI>Boston,</HI> the flesh of their backs <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eaten to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> by their Priests <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> VVo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>man, <HI>viz.</HI> the Execu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ioner of their Law at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, and when to whipt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> other M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mber of their Churches Peace▪ <HI>viz.</HI> their Goaler, shut <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> close Room, where none was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome unto them, and th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ept three days together without all manner of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ood. And at another time kept them eight days without all manner of P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ovision; and had not the Lord preserved them at this time, bey<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd what men of themselves use <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to do they had perished <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>der the Cruelty of the <HI>New-England Church,</HI> their said Sufferings are more at large to be seen in the said Book of Sufferings.</P>
<P><HI>William Shattock,</HI> an Inhab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="5 letters" DISP="•••••"/> in <HI>Boston,</HI> for being one first day found in his House alone, was by one of the Priests <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to their House of Oppression, for entertaining of Strange<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, and in the time of his being kept <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with the lik<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> whipping, some of the Priests crew endeavoured to p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>swade his Wife wholly to leave him, and that they would place o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t his Children to Masters of Families, that tended their Meetings, whose sufferi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g is more at large to be seen in the said Book of Sufferings.</P>
<P><HI>Thomas Harris,</HI> for declaring against <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> (which the guilty proud Oppressors itching <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to hear) was committed to their House of Oppres<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> where the Goaler (that devout Member of their Church <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him up, and kept him eleven days, five of which he kept him <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, and though he had before been cruelly <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, Wretch gave his Weak bruised body Twenty blows <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> pitche<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, whose sufferings are more at large to be seen in the <HI>Quakers</HI> book of sufferings, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> aforesaid</P>
<P>Several Innocent Women c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lled <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, had <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Bodies <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rthed for Witches, which work <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mbe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB REF="000801_0045_0FAA4FD30AC6E558"/>
women, with such cruelty to their Bodie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, that one of the Women said, she did not the like trouble undergo in b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aring and bringing for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> five Children, besides what more they, suffered under the power of those who were as free to run as the Devil was to drive then to perform his l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st in the doing the aforesaid Anti-christian work, of which more is to be seen in the aforesaid Books of the <HI>Quakers</HI> suffering under the Anti-christian power of <HI>New-Englands</HI> Churches.</P>
<P><HI>William Brend,</HI> for coming into <HI>Bostons</HI> Jurisdiction, where all the aforesaid work of Anti-christ was acted and done, and for being one of them called a <HI>Quaker,</HI> and declaring the Truth, was cruelly whipt, and shut up into close Prison, where the Goaler and devout Member of their Church, lockt his Neck and Heels together, so close that there was only room for the Lock to go between, in which manner he kept him sixteen hours, and then gave his weak b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sed Bod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>One Hundred and Seventeen Blows</HI> with a pitched Rope. having thus beaten him for dead, an out cry was among the People, <HI>That the Goaler had <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a man</HI>; which to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the People bills were set upon the Prison doors, and else where, <HI>That the Goaler should be dealt with</HI>; but said <HI>Brends</HI> coming to rise again (though the Doctors said, it would be admit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ble if he did recover for his flesh was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eaten into a meer G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lly of Blood, however, as God would have it, he came to recover again, then to prevent the Goalers being punished for this his great peice of Wickedness to said <HI>Brend, John Horton</HI> their chief high Priest said, if William Brend <HI>will endeavours <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> our Gospel Ordinances <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, it was just upon him <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> he was beaten black and blue</HI>; and withall in said Book, that his counsel was to his Church Brethren in Iniquity, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> off the Fear skin, and put on the Fox Skin</HI>; which indeed is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Priest like, the more to deceive poor <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>orant People, of whom God hath opened the Eye of many, by which they see hirelings deceit.</P>
<P><HI>William <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> a Merchant, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Stevins</HI> and <HI>William <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eddra,</HI> as Informed the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a clother the other a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> man <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd Mary <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> wife to Mr Dier of Rode Island all which four were
<PB N="47" REF="000801_0046_0FAA4FD3E9BF06E8"/>
great sufferers in Bostons Jurisdiction under the cruel bloody hands of the Church Members, before they drove them with great number of their Priests <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to their bloody alter, and many more by the Priests and Rulers with their co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>senting Members <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Iniquity, were intended to be sacrificed an offering to their Anger and R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>venge, had not the Kings Letters as aforesaid, stopt their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hands, and when the Priests drudges, with their many, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Staves, Gu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s and Drums to drown, the Testimony of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Servants from being heard among the People, had <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> them to their Bloody Altar, where they chearfull<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> delivered up them Lives for the Truth God and Testimony of Jesus, which was to the be∣holders Admiration, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> rage of their Persecutors; when they were executed they cut down their Bodies, letting them fall, to the breaking the Skul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and tipped off their Shirts, drag∣ging their naked <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>odie either by the heels, or with a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> as they dragged them, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d their Teeth with meer <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, as they went on with their w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rk of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>agging their Bodi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> stinking Pit, into which they threw some of their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, and never would grant their Freinds liberty <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> from Ravenous Creatures, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> place any manner of fence whatsoever.</P>
<P>Seeing the Wickedness of these Pers<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cutors to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> great, and their Lyes against the People of God many, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of the many which might be produced to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>The</HI> Quakers <HI>might <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> would not accept it, therefore say such</HI> Lyers, <HI>they were <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to their own Death.</HI> But to prove the contrary <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Mer∣chants letter in print, who was no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> out wit∣ness to what follows, <HI>viz</HI></P>
<LETTER>
<HEAD><HI>Boston,</HI> the 26th of <HI>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>001.</HEAD>
<P>ON the 14th of this Instant here was one <HI>William L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>dra</HI> put to Death▪ The People of the Town
<PB N="46" REF="000801_0047_0FAA4FD436B0A028"/>
told me, he might go away if he would; but when I made further enquiry, I heard the Marshall say, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> he was chained in Prison from the time he was condemned, to the day of Execution. I am not of his Opinion, but yet truly me thought the Lord did mightily appear in the Man. I goes to one of the Magistrates of <HI>Cambridge</HI>▪ who had been of the Court that condomned him, as he told me himsel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and I asked him by what Rule he did it? he an∣swerd me, <HI>That he was a Rogue, a very Rogue.</HI> But what is this to the Question, said I? Where is your R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e? He said, <HI>He had abused Authority.</HI> Then I goes to the m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> and asked him, Whether he did not look on it as a breach of R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and underval<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Authority? and said, That <HI>Paul</HI> gave <HI>Fes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI> the Title <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, though <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> I do not say, those Mag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>trates are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. I saw then when the Man was on the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> me, and called me <HI>Fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nd</HI> and said <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>to off</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> leave <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> one <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to speak, I said▪ <HI>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntlem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> stranger <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oth to your Person an <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and yet a Friend to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oth</HI> (and I cryed aloud) <HI>for the Lord sake take <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> mans Life</HI> I said, <HI>Remember <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> counsel to the</HI> Jews, <HI>If this be of God it will stand, if not it will come to Nothing but be care <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> you be not found <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> against God.</HI> And the Captain said, Why had not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> come to the Prison. And the reason was, because I heard the Man might go <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> he would, and therefore <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> down from the Free, Come down <HI>William,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> may go away if you will. Then Capt. <HI>Oliver</HI> sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, it was
<PB N="48" REF="000801_0048_0FAA4FD519571368"/>
no such <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and asked me, what I had to do with it, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esides, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪ I told him, I was wil∣ling for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> endure to see this. And when I was in their own <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to simpathize my Grief, but I told them, they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> no Warrant from the Word of God, not President from our Country, nor Power from his Majesty to hang the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Your Friend,</HI> THOMAS WILKY▪</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>
<P><HI>Samuell Sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pack, Joshua <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Smith, Edward Wharton, Samuell <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Southwick,</HI> his Father and Mother, Sisters and Brothers, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Kitchin</HI> and his Wife, with others in <HI>Salem,</HI> were great <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> by these Perse∣cutors, both by long imprisonment, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> loss of abun∣dance <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f Goo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tle, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Land of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, and several <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> upon pain of Death, and others of them ordered to be s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id for B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d-sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ves; all these were of <HI>Salem,</HI> and more of the same Tow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> suffered much.</P>
<P><HI>Obs.</HI> By the fore going Lines the Reade<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> may <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> how they have Persecuted all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> in Judgment from the way of their Priests Worship. In the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> place I shall here Instance a little relating to what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of the <HI>Church of England</HI> suffer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> by which the Reader may <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> better understand their bold attempts, who neither fear <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> nor regard King or Bishops. First, you note the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of set <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, <HI>viz.</HI> the manner was and yet is, at the opening of their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to have some one or more of their Priests <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> pray, and to make tedious long ins<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ped Graces, as they call them, before and after Meals, as also to consult what Penalties and Sufferings were most fit to be inflicted on Offenders against their Arbitrary and no just Laws, and especially against any that were found to diss<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t from their way of Worship, in which case the Priests Advice would commonly be, to lay on load enough▪
<PB N="49" REF="000801_0049_0FAA4FD621008450"/>
and the Advice was believed to be sanctified, though at the same time, they could not but understand they drank the Wine of the condemned, so expresly cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ged as a sin on the Magistrates, Rulers and Priests of <HI>Jerusalem,</HI> of no small provoc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tion to the holy One of <HI>Israel,</HI> though the matter in Controvers<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> relating to such as dissente<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> from their Priests Worship, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o matter of Offence ag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> the Law of God, nor the Laws of the <HI>English Nation,</HI> not∣withstanding they minded not, but would pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>d, according to their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> respect to au<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> no, not so much as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o the <HI>Church <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> England,</HI> o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, suffered under the New-England Church, which pretended to make <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> seperation in point o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith and Doctrine as witness that Letter, of their fore fathers and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eaders into <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>abella</HI> to the Bishops and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Church of England,</HI> calling them Bre∣thren, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, and who would know more of it, let them <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> book printed at Bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ton by <HI>Joshua <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> about <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> 1693 remarkable in that it is s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t forth by a Member <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Communion, but how well they carried it to the <HI>Church of England,</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, these few of the many Instances which might be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, may sufficently evidence against them, that they spared not any sound to dissent from their Priests way of Worship, as for Instance, Dr. <HI>Childs, Samuel Mave<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ick</HI> and other <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, of whom I have before hinted, were of the way of worship of the <HI>English <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> and by these Persecutors cruel Laws, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> not suffered to have the least benefit of or by that Worship, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> wholly denyed of their priviledge, belonging to the Worship of the <HI>Church of England,</HI> they were sound to Petition to <HI>England</HI> for the maintaining their Right in <HI>Boston,</HI> but so soon as this was known to the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Persecutors, they impeacht the aforesaid Per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>gh Rebellion, for attempti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g the same, and forth-with im<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>oned them, and fined each of them three hundred Pounds, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> means of their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the <HI>New Engl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> only for Murder <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> from <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="50" REF="000801_0050_0FAA4FD6F77207E0"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page〉"/>
<PB N="51" REF="000801_0051_0FAA4FD7364C3CF0"/>
stood, continued his preaching and baptizing, according to his Commission from the Bishop of <HI>London,</HI> till at length he was threatned with Whipping, and understanding that the Constables h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Warrants from the persecuting Magistrates to seize him, and fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that end beset his Lodging; whereupon he returned privately to <HI>Carolina.</HI></P>
<P N="4">4. Nor were the Affronts offered to <HI>Robert Ratcliffe,</HI> the first estblished Minister of the <HI>Church of England</HI> in <HI>Boston,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> in silence: He came over in the Year 1686. with Authority from the Crown of <HI>Engand</HI> to establish a Church in <HI>Boston</HI>; this mans meekness and Sobriety was sufficiently knwn, yet were his Affronts many, by which they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ought to weary him out, not only by personal Abuses and publick Inimies, is breaking the Church W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ws, tearing the service Book, making <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of Mans Dung<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on the Doors, and filling the Key-holes with the same, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t also <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ed his Clark, and compelled, him to Prison in a Wheel <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, of which nature they acted many abuses against the aforesaid and his Che<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>, insomuch that no Minister longer being able to endure then <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Anti-christian Abuses which did more dayly increase against h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> and his Church, was necessitated (after about four years stay a∣mongst them) to leave his Charge, and go for <HI>England,</HI> where the late Queen preferred him to a living.</P>
<P N="5">5. And as a father sign of their hatred to that Church, at the time of the Revolution, they Imprisoned three Gentlemen, Mem∣bers thereof, without any charge against them <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, save that they had officiated as Justices of the Peace under the Kings Com∣mission, and although they Joyned with eight o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ten more of their own Church Members, who sate and Jo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntly acted with them in the same County, yet could find no complaint against their own Church Members; so apparently partial were they to their own party, and violent to others, by which (as aforesaid though not the thousand part of what might be brough<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> against them of their great Wickedness against the People of God and the Kings Subject<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et with a little more of the like nature to be added here<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>o,
<PB N="52" REF="000801_0052_0FAA4FD7EBF518F8"/>
will by their work<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to the understanding of every true <HI>Christian,</HI> That the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Church</HI> is not the true Church of Christ, that worship him in the Spirit and in the Truth, <HI>viz.</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> 4.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></P>
<P>Having thus mentioned some of the abuses offered to some Mem∣ber<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of the <HI>Church of England,</HI> I shall now draw Conclusion so soon I have given a short account of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Maule</HI> of <HI>Salem,</HI> about his Book, call'd Truth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>held forth, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> I shall begin thus, <HI>viz.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Thomas Maule,</HI> a Young Man about twelve years of Age, came from <HI>England</HI> to the Island of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and from thence (for his health <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ake) came to <HI>New-England,</HI> where <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> much preaching and loud praying; he began to think with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> what manner of People are the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e? whose Streets ring <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Preaching and P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aying; and having lived amongst them about three yeare he did experience their words to be good, but by their works to have no good hearts; at the end of which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> removed himself to another of their Towns, called <HI>Salem,</HI> where he found the Church Members to be in all respects (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s to rel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gion) on with them in the other Towns of their Jurisdiction; but in Salem he found a People of few wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ds and good works, agreable thereunto, with which people he Jo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ned, by kee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing to their Me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tings, which so inraged the Church Members▪ that with thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ests, they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ired up the Rulers against <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> them <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> where he kept <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Pounds for entertaining him; after which for his keeping open shop upon one of their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and speaking the Truth, against their P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iests <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing against the <HI>Quakers</HI> and the like, they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> times imprisond <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, device cruell, whipt him, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> their many <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> also a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ing him of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> day of the week, but he affirming the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> persons, w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es of one <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> known had <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Good in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> keeping, hath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> notwithstanding <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
<PB N="53" REF="000801_0053_0FAA4FD8EEADB500"/>
yet recorded they him a Lyar, when he had spoken no other <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Truth relating to the same, shall now proceed to the sum and as aforesaid. From which I shall now proceed to the Sum and sub∣stance of his late Trial, which was writ by a hand then present in their Courts, as followeth.</P>
<P><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="warrant">
<HEAD>The Copy of their Warrant Province of the Massachusets <HI>Bay.</HI></HEAD>
<P>TO the Sheriffe of the County of Essex, his under Sheriffe or Debuty, greeting. Whereas there is lying before the honourable Lieutenant Governour and Council a printed Pamphlet, entituled, <HI>Truth held forth and maintained,</HI> &amp; put forth in the name of <HI>Thomas Maule,</HI> said to be <HI>Thomas Maules,</HI> of <HI>Salem</HI> within your County, &amp; published without, Licence of Authority, in which is contained many notorious and wicked Lyes, and Slanders, not only upon private Persons, but also upon Government, and likewise divers corrupt and pernicious Doctrines utterly subversive of the true Christian and professed Faith.</P>
<P>These are therefore in his Majesties Name to Will and require you forthwith to make search in the House of the said <HI>Maule,</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ere else you shall be informed any of the said Pamphl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> are, or may be found, seize and secure all that you shall find thereof, and to cause the said <HI>Thomas Maule</HI> to appear before the Lieutenant Governour and Council, at the Council Chamber in <HI>Boston,</HI> upon <HI>Thirsday</HI> the 19th Currant, to answer what shall be objected against him, to his Majesties behalf. To the Premises hereof fail
<PB N="54" REF="000801_0054_0FAA4FD97986D650"/>
not, making return of this Warrant with your doings there∣in.</P>
<P>Dated at the Council Chamber in <HI>Boston, December</HI> 12th 1695. By Command of the Lieutenant Governour &amp; Council.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Js<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> Addition,</HI> Secretary <HI>A true Copy, attested by</HI> George C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>win, <HI>Sherriff.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
<P><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="return">
<HEAD>A Copy, of the Return of their Warrant.</HEAD>
<OPENER><DATELINE><HI>Salem</HI>
<DATE><HI>December</HI> 14<HI>th,</HI> 1695.</DATE></DATELINE></OPENER>
<P>ACcording to the within Warrant, I have been at the House of <HI>Thomas Maule,</HI> and there have found thirty one of said Pamphlets, and them served, as re∣quired, and have seized the said <HI>Maule,</HI> and delivered him to the keeper of their Majesties Goal in <HI>Salem,</HI> there to be secured, in order to his apearance at the time and Place within mentioned, and have sent the said <HI>Thomas Maule</HI> by the bearer <HI>Jeremiah Neale,</HI> to answer as within exprest, which <HI>Jeremiah Neale</HI> I do constitute and appoint to be my lawful Deputy, to make return of this Warrant, with the Body of said <HI>Maule,</HI> and to act in all things which shall be further ordered relating to the concerning the within Warrant.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>George C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>win, Sheriff This is a true Copy of the Original Return, attested By</HI> Jeremiah Neale, Sheriff-Deputy.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
<P><PB N="55" REF="000801_0055_0FAA4FDA3A4DE740"/><HI>Thomas Maule</HI> being brought by the said <HI>Neale,</HI> and said Goaler out of <HI>Salem</HI> County, into <HI>Boston</HI> County, where appearing at the Council Chamber, before the said Governour and Council who put divers Insuaring Question to said <HI>Maule.</HI></P>
<P>He made this Reply, That no righteous <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aw did bind or injoyn him to answer further then he saw good, and that they had not acted agreeable to Law, in compelling him into their County, to stand tryal before them, who in the case were not his equal Judges, and if they did intend to proceed against him, he did expect the benefit of the Kings Laws, which did allow his Judges to be <HI>Twelve men</HI> of his <HI>Equals,</HI> belonging to the same County he was of. The which being consented to, four hundred Pounds bond was given for his appearance to answer them at their High Court of Injustice against him, at <HI>Ipwswich</HI> the 19th of the 3rd Month <HI>May,</HI> 169<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. But before said <HI>Maule</HI> came to his Tryal they Imprisoned him and sacrificed sixteen pounds worth of his Books, a burnt Offering to their Anger and Revenge, though upon his Tryal the Jury could not find him in the least guilty of any evil fact, relating to their Charge about his Book.</P>
<P>The time of the Courts setting being come, said <HI>Maule</HI> was called to his Tyral before <HI>Thomas Danford, Elisha Cook</HI> and <HI>Samuel Sewal,</HI> three of the Council, and Judges of this Court, who demanded of <HI>Thomas Maule, If he did own that Book intituled,</HI> Truth held forth and maintained, <HI>&amp;c. to be of his putting forth?</HI></P>
<P>To which he said, The outside of the Book did not fully manifest to him what the inside thereof did contain. The Book being given to him, when he had lookt it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, return'd it again, with this answer, That all Printed in the Book, he did own to be Truths, which he did vindicate &amp; maintain, excepting the Printers Errors, and some mistakes occasioned through Authors, which were com∣mon to good Books.</P>
<P>Then Judge <HI>Danford</HI> said, <HI>You are to answer for Printing this Book without <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>scence of Authority.</HI></P>
<P>To which said <HI>Maule</HI> answered, <HI>That if he were accountable for so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, it was not to them, but to the Bishops of the English Church,</HI> and the King did allow him the same liberty to have his
<PB N="56" REF="000801_0056_0FAA4FDAF24B6D60"/>
Book printed, as they did to an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of their subjects, which seperated or dissented from their way of Worship.</P>
<P>Then Judge <HI>Coo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> said, <HI>You are to answer for publishing your Book in this Government with<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> the Lisence of the present Authority.</HI></P>
<P>To which said <HI>Maul</HI> r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>plyed, The Gove<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nment <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Kings, or ought so to be, and the Books are my own Goods, who <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s an Engli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h Merchant have good <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ght by the Kings Laws to dispose of my Goods in any of the King <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</P>
<P>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n <HI>Anthony Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> the Kings <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> said, <HI>Your Books are not lawful good to be dispos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eople, because t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ey <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>∣tain notorious wicked <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Province, as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Christian and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Faith, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> upon many <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Persons.</HI></P>
<P>To which said <HI>Maul</HI> made this Reply, That the Charge-as yet to prove, and which they could never prove against him; and so long as there was no evil fact, he was no Transgressor of any righteous Law; and if their Cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ge were true, as it is not, it is no more than what they and their Priests are guilty of against all Persons, as well as the <HI>Church of England,</HI> that dissented from their Priests way of Worship, for which cause, and persecuting the People of God and the Kings Subjects to death, their Doctrine, Principles and Practices were condemned by all true Christian People that did know or hear of their unrighteous Works, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> these many years have caused Gods Judgments to come upon this Land; and for not repenting me you now given up to murder one another, through the Devi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ccusation, by Specter Evidence, accusing both Priests, Rulers and People of being Witches</P>
<P>Then Judge <HI>Cook</HI> to this purpose said, <HI>You are a horrible Lyar, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it mor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> better you would for<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ear in this nature running your self into further Trouble by accusing the Churches and Government after such a horrible wicked rate, as you have done, and still do persist in for which you are to suffer, according to your Deserts.</HI></P>
<P>To which said <HI>Maul</HI> made this Reply, That the Truth by him to them was spoken, and so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> he did not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xceed the bounds thereof, he did no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fear their Whip, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oal or Gallows, and with∣al,
<PB N="75" REF="000801_0057_0FAA4FDBD62A7040"/>
that relating to this his Testimony, he had suffered ten times is their Jurisdiction, five times by Imprisonment, three times by the loss of Goods taken from him, and twice by cruel Whipping; and now before this Tryal they had both imprison <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d burnt sixteen Pounds worth of his Books, and as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> given him any Copy of the particulars of the Charge against him.</P>
<P>To which Judge <HI>Dansord</HI> said, <HI>It <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> reason that</HI> Thomas Maule <HI>should have a Copy of what we have to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him with, and also time to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it, w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ich by the renewing o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> his Bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> next</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. Which was agreed to.</P>
<P>Then Judg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> said, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>would have</HI> Thomas Maule <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>more careful of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to the Scripture<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, Bible.</HI></P>
<P>To which <HI>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> answered, That to compare that with the Bible which was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gree<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ble to in Holy Scriptures in the Bible, could be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> way found to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> undervalue the Bible. And as to Er<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ors now so much talke of, he did not know of any Book that was fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e; for as some of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>earned <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, <HI>Beza</HI> committed eight hundred <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his first Tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> New Testament, which by ame<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ding through hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> second Tra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tion, left three hun∣dred Errors therein and by compari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g <HI>Mat.</HI> 27 <HI>v.</HI> 5. w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th <HI>Acts</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.18. proves as great a Must <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e as a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y he knew to be in his Book.</P>
<P>Judge <HI>Cook</HI> commanded this Sentence to be writ down.</P>
<P>Then said <HI>Maul</HI> desired it might <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it down, <HI>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at at present <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e did <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI> Which being do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, he said, That it through his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> an <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, he did hope through co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> next Tryal.</P>
<P>Then Judge <HI>Cook</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, <HI>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and so con∣t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ry <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the</HI> Quakers <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Perfection, that it overthrows their</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</P>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, That it was not so, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> makes a charge from <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> come to for∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> Error to j<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yn <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, which makes free from
<PB N="58" REF="000801_0058_0FAA4FDE635AB090"/>
all that is evil; and had not the like in measure, been <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> state, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> have departed from evil, I had not become a prey to you, who have caused me to suffer for the Truth, as it is manifest you have done.</P>
<P>Then Judge <HI>Danford</HI> said, <HI>Thomas Maul, forbear, we have some∣thing else to do than to spend time to hear you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> after this kind of rate.</HI></P>
<P>To which <HI>Thomas Maul</HI> answered, That he was willing to for∣bear without further Trouble to him, by or from them.</P>
<P><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="presentment">
<HEAD>A Copy of the Grand Jurys Presentment, as also a Copy of the Judges Charge.</HEAD>
<P>AT a Superiour Court held at <HI>Salem,</HI> for our Soveraign Lord the King, in the County of <HI>Essex,</HI> in the Province of the <HI>Massa∣chusets Bay</HI> in <HI>New-England,</HI> the 10th day of the 9th Month, <HI>1696.</HI> The Grand Jury do present <HI>Thomas Maul</HI> of <HI>Salem,</HI> Shop-keeper, for publishing, or putting forth a Book, entituled, <HI>Truth held forth and maintained,</HI> wherein is contained divers Slanders against the Churches and Government of this Province; and for saying what he did before the honourable Court at <HI>Ipswich,</HI> in <HI>May</HI> last, as will appear on Record, reference thereunto being had, may more at large appear, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> this hereunto annexed.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>James Stivens, <HI>Fare-man.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
<P><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="charge">
<P><HI>Thomas Maule</HI> being bound over by Recogni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ance to this Court, and being asked concerning a Book put forth by him, entituled, <HI>Truth held forth and maintained,</HI> &amp;c. did in oppen Court declare and say, <HI>That there was as great mistakes in the Scriptures as in his Book,</HI> and instanced, comparing <HI>Mat. 27.</HI> v. <HI>5.</HI> with <HI>Acts 1. v. 18.</HI> and this being read to him, desires to be understood, That at present he beleeves so, at the Superiour Court of Judicature held as <HI>Ipswich</HI> on the third Tuesday <HI>May</HI> last, <HI>1696.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>A true Copy, by <HI>Adington Davenport,</HI> Clerk.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></P>
<P><PB N="59" REF="000801_0059_0FAA4FDFB36A79C0"/>Dr. <HI>Benjamin <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ivants</HI> Speech, in the first part of the Pleas <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Presentment, is as followeth, <HI>viz.</HI></P>
<P>To the Presentment of the Grand-Jury, exhibited against <HI>Tho Maule</HI> this present Court, always saving to himself the liberty of such further Pleading and Defence, as by Law are due unto him, <HI>viz.</HI> First, That the uncertainty of matters alledged in the said Presentment is so notorious, that he that runs may read them; and the Lord <HI>Cook</HI> says, <HI>The Law requires certainty in all cases,</HI> especially such as are Penal to the Lives or Estates of the Subject, which un∣certainties are. <HI>Secondly,</HI> That neither County, Year or Day are laid in the said Presentment. <HI>Thirdly,</HI> That the Presentment is not laid to be made for the King, who if any one hath Offence by whatever in this case alledged against the Defendant; neither is his Majesties Name or Stile used in the Presentment, as is necessary, and required particularly by the Laws of this Government. <HI>Fourthly,</HI> That it is not laid upon Oath, as it ought to be, if it hold a man to his Answer. <HI>Fifthly,</HI> That the Jury had no Plantiff to inquire for, they being sworn, <HI>Well and truly to try, and true Deliverance make between our Soveraign Lord the King, and</HI> Thomas Maule <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Prisoner at the Bar.</HI> And Yet the Kings Name and Stile entirely omitted in the Presentment aforesaid. <HI>Six<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ly,</HI> That if it were true the Defendant should have said, as is laid to his charge in the Indictment, <HI>That there was as great Mistakes in the Scriptures as in his Book,</HI> yet this can charge no fact by Law punishable upon him, the Presentment wanting an invendo or meaning, whether they were the holy Scriptures or words of God, since there are prophane as well as holy Scriptures, and the Defendant may be supposed, in Construction of Law, to intend as well prophane as sacred Scrip∣tures. <HI>Seventhly,</HI> That it was not laid to be against the Peace of the King, or so much as a Misdemeanor.</P>
<P>To these Arguments Judge <HI>Danford</HI> answered, <HI>That the Present∣ment was according to former Ʋsage, and their Custom, and that want of form could not destroy the Indictment, or hinder the coming to his Answer.</HI></P>
<P>Judge <HI>Cook</HI> said, <HI>As to the Invendo, that it would have been necessary if the particular Quotations had not been named, which he did believe</HI> Thomas Maules <HI>Counsel would not deny to be the Books of the holy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, which was conceded unto.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="60" REF="000801_0060_0FAA4FE0D06E6BC0"/>Then was <HI>Anthony Chickley,</HI> the Kings Attorney, called upon, to know what he had to say to it on the behalf of the King, who only said, <HI>He would answer to the third Exception brought against the In∣dictment,</HI> viz. That it wanted the stile of the K<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng, <HI>affi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ming it did not want it,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ounding his assertion on the Pream<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le of the Indict∣ment, it being said, <HI>At a superiour Court held at</HI> Salem <HI>for our Sover¦<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ign Lord the King.</HI></P>
<P>Reply to this was made, on the behalf of the Defendant, That the Preample had no relation to the Body of the Presentment, since the Presentment was presumed to begin at these words, <HI>The Grand Jury do present.</HI></P>
<P>The Court, after some further debate, over-ruling the Pleas, the Prisoner is left to say for himself.</P>
<P><HI>Thomas Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le</HI> to the Judges on the Bench, as followeth, <HI>viz.</HI></P>
<P>To you who have set your selves to be Judges in this case, against me, as you are invested with Magistratical Power by Commission from the King, I do respect you, out wherein you do assume to your selves the Power of the Bishops Court, as in this case, I do no more value you than I do Jack-straw. And i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> approve your selves wise me, you ought to mend the many Rents by you already made, thro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gh the mis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mannagement of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> com∣mitted to your Charge, before you proceed to make a further breach upon me, who has not given you any just occasion so to do, whi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h if you are resolved to make a Rod for me, that it may be easie, for the more ease of your own that is to come, for it is said by him that cannot lye, <HI>The same measure that men make, the same shall be made to them again</HI>; and if your Power, by which you act against me, do long continue, he that now enjoys a good Estate, under your Government, in seven years time, after this rate, may not be left worth a Grote; for as you are set to watch over the People, things are at that pass, through your means, that they have the greater need to watch over you, otherwise they are like to be undone by the heavy burdens you lay upon them.</P>
<P>Then the Cause, with the said <HI>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>les</HI> Book, and a Speech made to this purpose by Judge <HI>Danford,</HI> was committed to the Jury, <HI>viz. You have now heard the Cause, which with the Book is now committed to your hands, why have taken a solemn Oath to do the thing that is right
<PB N="61" REF="000801_0061_0FAA4FE0F3CAB290"/>
in the sight of Gods as near as you can; therefore you ought well to co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣sider the horrid Wickedness of</HI> Thomas Maules <HI>setting forth the Book now before you, in which there is contained a great deal o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> blasphemous matter against the Churches and Government of this Province. You well know, that when the Husband-man hath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> great ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e and labour to fence in his fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld of Wheat, and there comes a ravenous Creature and makes a Gap through the Fence for other like Creatures to go through and spoil the Corn, and to trample down and lay waste the Husband-mans Field, will he not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se his ut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ost endeavour to destroy such a ravenous Creature that doe so? how much the more are w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to preserve the Hedge of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> good Husband-man with which he hat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, by his Ordinances, and good Government, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>enced and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> aged his Churches and People in this Province, against which t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e wicked work of</HI> Thomas M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ule <HI>doth wholly t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> all good in Church and Common-wealth, which God ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> planted amo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gst his People in this Province; w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ich Cause with the said</HI> Maules <HI>Book i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> now before you, to do that which is right relating thereunto, as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ear as God shall inable.</HI></P>
<P>In answer to which Speech, <HI>Thomas Maule</HI> made this Reply to the Jury, and said, Jury look well to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rk which you are now going to do, the Cause is now committed to you, who are to be Governed by the Kings Law; no Law of our Nation have I broken, as to y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u will appear; the Book has no evidence in Law against me, further then to you it doth appear, I have writ or caused to be printed any thing contrary to sound Doctrine, and Inconsi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tant to the holy Scriptures of Truth, which if you take up with any part of these Judges unjust Cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ge against me, and say, there is such like matter in my Book as they cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ge me with, you may seek to the Printer for satisfaction, for of any such like matter in the Book I know not, and my hand is only to my Copy, which now is in another Government, in the hands of the Printer, and my Name to my Book made by the Printer does not in Law evidence to prove the same to be <HI>Thomas Maule,</HI> no more then the Spector Evidence, in Law, is of force or validity to prove the person accused by said evidence to be the Witch, but rather con∣clude the Spector to be the Witch; therefore Jury look well to your Work, for you have sworn, <HI>True Tryal to make <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Verdict give,</HI> which if you miss of doing me Justice, the fault will lie on
<PB N="62" REF="000801_0062_0FAA4FE1B1CF7ED0"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> part; for these my Accusers on the be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch, are but as Clerks to conclude your Work with Amen.</P>
<P>In some small time the Jury brought in their Verdict for the Prisoner, whom they found <HI>not Guilty,</HI> At which the Judges seemed much disatisfied therewith, and ass<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the Jury, <HI>how that could be, having the Book before them? who answered, That the Book was not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Evidence, for that</HI> Thomas Maules <HI>Name was there unto for by the Printer, and the matter therein contained not cognizable before them, they not being a Jury of divines, which this case ought <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI></P>
<P>Then Judg <HI>Danford</HI> made this Speech, <HI>That t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o,</HI> Thomas M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ule <HI>had escaped the hands of Men, yet he had not escaped the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of God▪ who would find out all his Evils and Blasphemies against his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and People, and for which Wickedness God did reserve him or further Judg∣ment to come upon him.</HI></P>
<P>In answer to which, said <HI>Maule</HI> replyed, <HI>That he was no way guilty of their Charge, but had great cause to praise God or his deliver∣ance by the Jury, who were made Instruments of fre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> out of the hands of them, who had mani<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ested <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Works against the People of God, and the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bject, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> be one had done</HI></P>
<P>In which time of the said Reply, Judge, <HI>Danford</HI> called out, <HI>Take him away, take him away.</HI></P>
<P>The Reader may hence understand, that the distance of these Persecutors from the King, and much further froms Gods Truth, is the cause that by them, many of the People of God and the Kings Subjects suffer, more then they would do, were they where their complaint could readily be heard by the King, who would not suffer his Subjects to be persecuted under the Anti-christian Power of the New-England Church, who yet continue the old stroke, according to their Power, against the <HI>Quakers,</HI> at this very time of liberty of Conscience, respecting to Religion now allowed by the King and Powers of <HI>England,</HI> as for instance, they now do suffer in their Jurisdiction, especially in the Town of <HI>Linn,</HI> where for the Priests maintenance, they compell the <HI>Quakers</HI> Oxen, their Pots and Platters, with the of other Houshould goods more worse in the respect, then of the first two wiked Priests we read, <HI>Sam.</HI> 2.12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. For which sin God will reward the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

