<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.lib.umich.edu/tcp/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2005-09-22</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Check TEXT for LANG attribute. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for signatures. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Check LETTER tags. Check Ls. Check TABLEs. Check LISTs. Check NOTEs. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs and duplicates. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Converted 113 $-groups to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="N00718">
<STC T="E">865</STC>
<STC T="W">j670a</STC>
<BIBNO T="aas">99009262</BIBNO>
<VID></VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="000865_0000_0FABF163AF289608"/>
<PB REF="000865_0001_0FABF164A2164D98"/>
<P>TRƲTH RESCƲED FROM <HI>Forgery</HI> &amp; <HI>Falshood,</HI> BEING An Answer to a late Scurrilous piece Entituled THE CASE PUT AND DECIDED &amp;c.</P>
<P>Which Stole into the World without any known Au∣thors name affixed thereto, And renders it the more like it's <HI>FATHER, Who was a Lyer and Murtherer from the beginning.</HI></P>
<P>BY SAMUEL JENINGS.</P>
<P>Printed at <HI>Philadelphia</HI> By <HI>Reynier Jansen</HI> 1699.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="reply">
<PB N="2" REF="000865_0002_0FABF1652B1B04D8"/>
<HEAD>TRƲTH RESCƲED FROM <HI>Forgery</HI> &amp; <HI>Falshood,</HI> &amp;c.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Impartial Reader,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>Had the <HI>Authors</HI> of the <HI>Libel I</HI> am now to answer, been so just to me and the <HI>World,</HI> as to have sent their <HI>Names</HI> along with it, it might have saved me much, if not all, of this Labour; they having (especially of late) so signalized themselves, by divers memorable actions, that hardly any whom fame hath reached with the knowledge thereof, will hesitate in giving them their <HI>Character,</HI> and I think it not a little to my reputation, that mine and theirs are so diffe∣rent. And though IOHN TATHAM, THOMAS REVELL and NATH. WEST-LAND did at last, when I had staged the <HI>Author</HI>' or <HI>Authors</HI> for Forgery and Falshood, come forth, and own themselves the <HI>Authors,</HI> yet their <HI>Libel</HI> being before dispersed without a name, and mighty fall into some hands, who were Strangers both to the <HI>things</HI> and <HI>Per∣sons,</HI> I find it necessary to pursue it with this. What induced these angry <HI>Counsellours,</HI> to fall upon me in this <HI>Boorish</HI> manner, at this time, is plain, from the burthen of their <HI>Complaint</HI>; That the <HI>Authority</HI> which they have assumed is not <HI>recognized,</HI> which I know is a great vexation to men of their temper and circumstances, whose ambition is to rule, and their leisure from other employments such, as may be a temptation to them, like <HI>Locusts</HI> to live upon other Mens labours: To wich I having shewn some aversion, they there∣by fondly take an occasion to magnifie my <HI>Interest</HI> with others, to an excessive extream, and make me <HI>Author</HI> of all
<PB N="4" REF="000865_0003_0FABF34E63D412C8"/>
the <HI>Interruptions</HI>▪ and <HI>affronts</HI> they have me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> with, in the exercise of their <HI>sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m Authority.</HI> My share of it I am wil∣ling to own; but not to exclude others, to whom for their fidelity to their <HI>Country,</HI> belongs a share of that regard, that<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s due to men, that will not basely and meanly truckle, to any pretentions, where <HI>Royal Authority</HI> is wanting: For which reason the two last <HI>General Assemblys</HI> of this <HI>Provin∣ce,</HI> have not thought fit to recognize the <HI>Authority</HI> by which these men act; and how far they have approved themselves true men and Friends to their <HI>Country,</HI> who have opposed their Private sense, to the declared sense of the <HI>Province</HI> by their <HI>Representatives,</HI> will (I hope) in a little time be more fully discovered, and rewarded according to its due demerit. Let this suffice for an <HI>Introduction,</HI> I shall now proceed, to touch upon the severall parts of their <HI>Libel,</HI> as it lyes before me in order, and begin first with what they call, and would have the World to believe, to be the <HI>A∣w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rd.</HI></P>
<P>That there was such a thing as a Difference, betwixt <HI>Edward Billing</HI> on the one part, and the <HI>Proprietors</HI> and <HI>In∣habitants</HI> of <HI>West-Jersey</HI> on the other, is certain; which they have misrepresented in their <HI>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>le-Page,</HI> and render it to lye betwixt <HI>Edward Billing</HI> on the one part, and some <HI>West-Jer∣sians</HI> headed by me on the other part, Whence I can not but observe, that when they have a mind to reproach me, they'l make me as big as a <HI>Province,</HI> that they may load me with the blame of a <HI>Province,</HI> and presently (to serve their own turn) confine me again, to such narrow limits, as may render me very dimin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tive; but when they have said and done all they can, <HI>By the grace of God, I am what I am,</HI> 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 15.10. But to proceed; How basely doth it look, to betray the Reader into a belief, That it was only a <HI>Facti∣on</HI> of <HI>West<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>Jersians,</HI> headed by <HI>Samuel Jenings,</HI> that oppo∣sed <HI>Edward Billing,</HI> and thence sprung the <HI>Controversy?</HI> But to undeceive my <HI>Reader, I</HI> must let him know, That it was no less, nor no other, than the <HI>General Assembly</HI> of <HI>West Jersy,</HI> which I no otherwaies headed, than as being
<PB N="5" REF="000865_0004_0FABF34EF4237150"/>
at that time their <HI>Governour,</HI> which made the other Party, who accordingly commissionated me and <HI>Thomas Budd,</HI> to go to <HI>England,</HI> to negotiate their affairs there with <HI>Billing, Georg Hutcheson</HI> at the same time offering himself as a <HI>Vo∣lunteer,</HI> to our assistance. Pursuant to our <HI>Commission</HI> and <HI>Instructions,</HI> we proceeded in the <HI>Voyage,</HI> and by the Grace of GOD, arrived in a good and short time a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> our <HI>Port</HI>; and when we came there, meeting with <HI>Billing,</HI> we imparted our business to him, which was, in the name of the <HI>Proprie∣tors,</HI> to make a demand of the <HI>Government,</HI> to whom he had as much sold it as the <HI>Soil,</HI> and taken their mony for it. This message was very ungrateful to him, who resolved (as the consequence hath shewn) to cheat us, in what we esteemed the best part of our bargain; For at that time, the <HI>Soil,</HI> without the <HI>Government,</HI> would have been of no value to the <HI>Purchasers.</HI> And though before our arrival, he was the great <HI>Complainant,</HI> and threatned high what he would do, if his <HI>Authority</HI> should be disputed, yet finding now, that it was like to come to that indeed (for so were we in∣structed, viz. if he refused to comply with our just demands, to complain against him at <HI>White-Hall or Westminster-Hall,</HI> as able <HI>Counsell</HI> should advise) and fearing nothing more than his, and well knowing, that his Actions could not abide so severe a <HI>Test,</HI> makes it his business with might and main to prevail with our <HI>Friends,</HI> to use their endeavours, to take up this business, and make a more private end of it, if they could, or at least, to prevent our procedure against him in the way we intended. Upon which a proposall was made, by some of the <HI>Persons,</HI> who were afterwards <HI>Arbi∣trators</HI>; That we would submit the <HI>Controversy,</HI> to the de∣termination of a certain number of <HI>Persons,</HI> to be equally chosen. To wich we replyed, we had no such power nor direction from our <HI>Principals,</HI> but were it so it had affected us only, we should chearfully do it. They urged some reasons, which I shall here omit to give, why it was not then a proper time to Prosecute such an affair, in the way we intended; But if it was not in our power, to submit
<PB N="6" REF="000865_0005_0FABF34FB3DD09E0"/>
the decision wholly to them, in the name of the whole, yet we might do it on our own proper account: With which <HI>Thomas Budd</HI> first closed, and then I was disabled, not having power to act alone, and therefore complied also; Although my compliance with this <HI>Proposall,</HI> I must declare, to be an Act of necessity, and not of choice; and rhough I put an high value upon concord amongst <HI>Brethren,</HI> yet that relates chiefly to <HI>Religio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> concerns, and may be inviola<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly maintained, notwithstanding our different sentiments, in <HI>Civil</HI> affairs. Thus we submitted, and they undertook to hear and determine our <HI>case,</HI> which accordingly they did, and delivered the <HI>Award</HI> into my hands, the eleventh day of <HI>October</HI> 1684., where it hath remained ever-since, and still is, being an <HI>Original</HI> and signed with the <HI>Arbitrarors</HI> own hands. But finding a Printed thing steal into the <HI>World</HI> with∣out a name 'under the visor of the aforesaid <HI>Award,</HI> I took the Pains to compare them, and find at least thirty eight varia∣tions, some of which not being very material, I shall pass by, and account them the act of the <HI>Pen man,</HI> in trying to correct and amend the sen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e; who will hardly allow, that any man (at least in these Parts) understands it like him∣self. But others there are, that seem to be designedly and knavishly foisted in, of which nothing is to be found in the <HI>Award</HI>; Which wen I had considered' I Published a few lines in <HI>Manuscript,</HI> declaring; That what was published in print as the <HI>Award,</HI> was <HI>Spurious and false</HI>; Which oc∣casioned the Publishing of divers in that manner on each side, with which I shall not much meddle now, except to touch a little upon their last Paper, the rest being already answe∣red.</P>
<P>I come now to give some Particular Instances of their <HI>For∣gery and Falsehood,</HI> and begin with Page 3., where they make the <HI>Award</HI> to spaek thus:
<Q>That whereas S. <HI>Jenings</HI> and the Assembly in <HI>West-Jarsey</HI> had Positively acknowledged <HI>E. Billing</HI> as Governour, and acted about two years by vir∣tue of his Commission and Power, and <HI>S. Jenings</HI> as his Deputy engaging to serve him, and preserve his Interest in
<PB N="7" REF="000865_0006_0FABF35097B8F7B0"/>
that capacity; Now after all this they accepting <HI>E. Billing</HI> as Governour <HI>only in trust,</HI> as they alledge, in order to have him assign his Power and Government to the People; which not being obtained with his consent, <HI>then they re∣jecting him the said</HI> Billing, <HI>and chusing S.</HI> Jenings <HI>Gover∣nour in his stead, and his accepting thereof,</HI> WAS A BE∣TRAYING HIS TRUST; as also rejecting <HI>W. Welch,</HI> since deputed by <HI>E. Billing,</HI> without giving <HI>E▪ Billing</HI> any previous notice of these their designs and proceedings against him and his interest, <HI>These we judge Irreg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lar Proceedings, Unfair and Unwarrantable, Unsafe and wor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y of blame in</HI> S. Jenings <HI>and all Persons concerned therein.</HI></Q></P>
<P>Here I charge my <HI>Adversaries</HI> with downright FORGE∣RY and FALSHOOD, there being no such words in the whole <HI>Award</HI>; as <HI>betraying of trust,</HI> of which they seemed so fond, suiting their malicious design so well, that to give it the greater <HI>Emphasis,</HI> they put it in Capitall Letters; But being now discovered, and their Forgery detected, serves only to render them Capitall in malice and abuse: Nor doth it excuse them to say, as in one of their Papers they do,
<Q>That not any thing is couched in the said Printed Award; no not even that noted reflection upon <HI>Samuel</HI> in Capital letters, but what we will prove to be true, when occasion shall require &amp;c.</Q>
But this is still to do, and this I leave as a task upon them to perform, when they shall think the occa∣sion requireth. I am glad I am so much before hand with them, having Proved my charge against them before seve∣rall credible Witnesses, who for their private satisfaction, have compared what they have Printed, with the true <HI>A∣ward,</HI> and (I believe) will not refuse to give evidence, to the truth of what I here assert, if it be desired; and I do here∣by further promise, to give the like satisfaction, to as ma∣ny as shall soberly request it. But, say they,
<Q>The <HI>Award</HI> now Published,—as received from their [the <HI>Awarders</HI>] hands, so was transmitted hither for information, and is by us made publick, for the same end, without the least variati—on. And is it more reasonable to relie upon his vera∣city,
<PB N="8" REF="000865_0007_0FABF3512F1EBE80"/>
in this matter, than the worth and reputation of those honourable <HI>Gentleman</HI> in <HI>England,</HI> that sent it hither verbatim as We have Published it &amp;c.</Q></P>
<P>Thereby implying as if the <HI>Award</HI> they have Printed is of equal force and validity with the other. To which I an∣swer, Theirs can be but a <HI>Copy,</HI> as appears by its date, being four daies after the <HI>Originals</HI> were delivered into the hands of the <HI>Parties</HI> concerned, and therefore not of equal credit with the <HI>Original</HI>: But my business is not to consider what it is, nor how they come by it; my complaint and charge is That they have Printed and published to the World, in the name of eight of my Friends, a thing called their <HI>Award,</HI> with <HI>divers Additions, Omissions and Variations,</HI> and that <HI>in divers of the most considerable passages in it,</HI> tending greatly to slander and reproach me. and this I call <HI>Forgery and Falshood,</HI> and shall leave it upon them, till they can more fairly throw it of, than yet they have done.</P>
<P>And again in page 3, where they say:
<Q>These we judge Irregular proceedings, unfair and unwarrantable, unsafe and worthy of Blame in <HI>S. Jenings</HI> and all Persons concerned therein.</Q></P>
<P>There is no mention made of <HI>S. Jenings,</HI> nor any blame laid upon him, but in conjunction with the <HI>Assembly,</HI> who are Blamed for chusing, and he for accepting their choice of him for <HI>Governour.</HI> But I am glad of this oppretunity, to clear that point, which I doubt not to do, to the satisfaction of any indifferent person; and to acquit my self, and the <HI>Assembly</HI> too, from any just blame upon that occasion.</P>
<P>But here I expect to meet with an <HI>Objection,</HI> viz. But why then did your <HI>Friends</HI> blame you in their <HI>Award,</HI> and were not they <HI>Divinely</HI> inspired in what they did? I answer; Be∣cause I find my <HI>Adversaries</HI> harp so much upon that, and make such a perverse, or rather malicious use of it; I put it upon them to prove, when ever our <HI>Friends</HI> have placed their Conduct in <HI>Civil</HI> affairs, so high; No, we can very well admitt of different sentiments in those things, without any braech of <HI>Religious</HI> union; and this being partly a <HI>Law-case,</HI>
<PB N="9" REF="000865_0008_0FABF351F086DDE8"/>
upon which the judgement of these <HI>Friends</HI> was groun∣ded, it is not utterly impossible, but they might be some∣what mistaken in it: However, it should have lain un∣toucht for me, had not I thus unexpectedly, as well as un∣fairly been assaulted afresh, and recriminated by the Award. But to meet with this from any <HI>Members</HI> of <HI>West-Jersey,</HI> that would be thought to be tender of her <HI>Rights</HI> and <HI>Prive∣ledges,</HI> for the sake of which I suffered what I did, in de∣fence of them, is very strange; especially considering how much I was importuned, and in a sence forced, for the pre∣servation of the Peace of the <HI>Province,</HI> into a compliance; which I should think, cannot be forgotten by one of my <HI>Ad∣versaries,</HI> at least, who had not the least share, in advis∣ing what was done; from whom I did not expect such a re∣turn, for former kindnesses shewed him, by me and others: Who in the time of his necessity, enjoyed all the places of profit, that he was capable of in the Government, by the favour of those, over whom he hath since made his insults; by which means, he hath justly drawn upon himself, the hatefull <HI>Epithet</HI> of <HI>Ingratitude,</HI> a thing common to men of his temper, which having branded him with, at present I shall leave him.</P>
<P>But to proceed, you may perceive by the <HI>Award,</HI> that the <HI>Agents</HI> of the <HI>Province,</HI> did alledge when in <HI>England,</HI>
<Q>That they accepted <HI>E. Billing</HI> as Governour <HI>only in Trust,</HI> in order to have him assign his Power and Government to the People.</Q>
Which is all very true and reasonable; for it was to such People, as had before bought and paid for it, and <HI>E- Billing</HI> himself, when he First obtained the grant from the <HI>Duke,</HI> endeavoured to make us believe, <HI>that he received it but in trust, and would use it no otherwise,</HI> and excuses thae taking it in his own name, alledging, <HI>It must he in a single person, and he could not obtain it otherwise</HI> Which there was no reason to do, had he not been consci∣ous to himself, that the right of it did appertain to others. And <HI>William Penn,</HI> one of <HI>E. Billings</HI> Trustees, of whom we bought, and well knew the Rights of the People, whose
<PB N="10" REF="000865_0009_0FABF352B603AEB8"/>
Interest was the great means of obtaining the Grant of the <HI>Duke,</HI> alwaies declared; <HI>that he solicited for it in the name of the People, that they might be able to make good what they had sold them.</HI> And <HI>Sir William Jones,</HI> on whose opi∣nion the <HI>Duke</HI> much relied, gave it as his opinion, <HI>that the Right belonged to the People</HI>; Upon which the <HI>Duke</HI> Frank∣ly ordered, <HI>That a Second Grant should be given</HI>; The in∣tent being only to confirm but not to destroy the former. And lastly, than which nothing can be more clear; The Second Grant, by which the powers of Government were more clearly granted to <HI>Billing,</HI> was never proposed to be sought for, but at the request and charge of the <HI>Proprie∣tors</HI>; For, saies <HI>Billing</HI> and some of his Trustees in a le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>er now in my hands, <HI>it will cost much money to obtain it, and when gotten, you shall have the benefit of it.</HI> This I think is enough to say for proof of this Point, though I could say a great deal more, but shall use what brevity the case will bear.</P>
<P><HI>Edward Billing</HI> having thus obtained the grant as aforesaid, sends over a <HI>Commission</HI> to severall persons, in which I was first named, and in case of mortality, the rest to succeed in their order as <HI>Deputy Governours:</HI> Now to shew with what caution this was accepted, and no otherwise, but vvith a <HI>saving our Right,</HI> the <HI>Records</HI> of the first <HI>Generall Assembly</HI> held in <HI>West-Jersey</HI> will shew. But before that <HI>Assembly</HI> was called, I knowing it to be against the Rights of the People, for him to grant <HI>Commissions,</HI> and assume the place of a <HI>Go∣vernour,</HI> I called together as many as I could, of the most antient and considerable of the <HI>Inhabitants</HI> here, as soon as I had received the <HI>Commission,</HI> and freely gave my sense of it, and told them; <HI>my resolution was, never to impose it on them nor make any use of it, except they apprehended, it might be of service to them:</HI> Upon which the thing was conside∣red, debated, and at last concluded, <HI>that it was better, not wholly to reject the</HI> Commission; <HI>but to accept it as afore∣said, that some face of</HI> Authority <HI>might be kept up, to a∣void the confusions of an</HI> Anarchy. Some are yet alive, to
<PB N="11" REF="000865_0010_0FABF3536D9CDD58"/>
affirm to the truth of this, though most of our antient <HI>Inha∣bitants,</HI> are by death or otherwise removed. But besides all this, when <HI>Billing</HI> sent his <HI>Commission,</HI> he sent a long Letter with it, in which are contained the <HI>Apologies</HI> before men∣tioned, declaring, <HI>It was his intent suddainly to come, and settle the affair, to thae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hearts content of all concerned</HI>; and to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ack all this, a Ship was then newly arived, in which were Passengers, <HI>William Biddle, Elias Farr and Benjamin Scott,</HI> with divers others, but these I mention as of most note, and intimate with <HI>Billing,</HI> who declared, it as their sense; <HI>That he would he as good as his word, and that he was put upon a necessity, of accepting the Grant as he did, and that it was requisite his Commission should be accepted for the time, till his arrival, which they judged would he short∣ly.</HI> Thus I have shown the manner and reasons of accepting that <HI>Commission</HI> which I think makes it evident enough, to be but <HI>in trust</HI>; I come now to shew our reasons for reject∣ing it.</P>
<P>When <HI>Billing,</HI> by this soft and crafty dealing with us, had drawn us on to recognize his <HI>Authority</HI> (which he thought had been without condition or teserve, for kno∣wing him to be hot-headed and rash as well as Indigent, we gave him no notice of it, least in a Frenzie he should Sell the Government, and so make it more troublesome to us to re∣cover; but expecting of him here, thought We might best deal with him upon the place) he now begins to treat us in other terms, and to let us know, <HI>he did not intend to part with the Gouvernment</HI>; Of which We complaining to him, of his dishonesty to us; in his next he tells us, <HI>That it was as much as our necks and estates were worth, to assume</HI> (what he before had owned to be) <HI>our Right.</HI> This opened the eyes of all, undeceived those that aforetime had been best opinionated of him, and the next <HI>General Assembly</HI> when Sett, did generally declare, <HI>They would no longer submit to his Authority,</HI> but immediately assert their own right, and chuse their <HI>Governour</HI> themselves: Which they did; pitching upon me. How unwillingly I yeilded to serve them
<PB N="12" REF="000865_0011_0FABF354593B6D48"/>
in that <HI>station,</HI> several then present cannot have forgotten; although I was satisfied of the Justice and equality of the thing, and that it was no evil in it self, yet it might carry another aspect, with those who had only heard a superficial account of it.</P>
<P>I have now shown, why we received, and why We rejected <HI>Edw. Billings</HI> Commission; the next is to inquire, how far We (viz the <HI>Assembly</HI> and my self) are criminal for it: But especially my self, who (by the forgery of my <HI>Adversaries</HI>) am represented to the World as <HI>a Betrayer of my trust</HI> to <HI>Billing</HI>; To do which, in common understand∣ing it must be presupposed, that I acepted a <HI>trust</HI> from him, which I deny ever to have done; for what I did in accep∣ting his <HI>Commission,</HI> was to serve the <HI>Country,</HI> and at their re∣quest, as I have before shewn; nor had I any reason to do it for his sake; who was much a Stranger to me, and from whom I never received any reward for it, and to be yet more plain; the Infamy that he was under was such, that to serve him, would have been a blemish upon my reputa∣tion: Yet there was a necessity that We should acknowledge, that the Government was in him, though but <HI>in trust,</HI> else how could We expect, that he should reconvey it to the <HI>Purchasers,</HI> as by solemn engagements bound. So that upon the whole, the <HI>trust</HI> was in <HI>Billing,</HI> and not in me, and it was he that <HI>betrayed his trust,</HI> and not I; nor can I see, how any blame is justly chargeable upon me, or that <HI>Assembly</HI> that renounced his <HI>Authority</HI>; seeing to have done otherwise, had been to strengthen him in his Injustice to the <HI>Province,</HI> or rather to have made our selves Parties with him, against our own Right▪ And now I have done with this part, wherein I have been so plain and candid, as I hope wil satisfie the Impartial, and for others, I regard not their clamour.</P>
<P>And whereas the <HI>Award</HI> saies,
<Q>And <HI>S. Jenings</HI> as his [<HI>E. Billings] Deputy</HI> engaging to serve him, and preserve his interest in that capacity &amp;c.</Q>
I answer, I know of no en∣gagement of that kind, that was ever put upon me, and if
<PB N="13" REF="000865_0012_0FABF355060590A0"/>
any such expression did fall from my Pen, in a private let∣ter to <HI>Billing</HI>; it was, before it was discovered, that he intended to set up a corrupt Interest, in opposition to the just Rights of the People: For at the time he made large prote∣stations, <HI>That he would promote no other Interest than that</HI> of <HI>the Common-waelt</HI>; Which had he stuck to, I should have served him in it: But can any body believe, I was quite so sensless or pros<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igate, as to engage to serve any Interest that he should promote, without any regard to the Justice of it; I hope not: But the controverting of this point for∣merly, gave occasion to an Ingenious Friend of mine to say:
<Q><L>He that will Judge aright, most know as well,</L>
<L>As things, the times wherein each thing befell.</L></Q></P>
<P>I intend to touch upon one thing more in that <HI>Sham A∣ward</HI> that my <HI>Adversaries</HI> have Printed, and so to leave it. It relates to the second Paragraph of the <HI>Award,</HI> page the 3d., at the close of which they note in the name of I know not who, that
<Q>Whence (I suppose it should be whereas) this sentence above cited was hastily razed out of the <HI>Original</HI> the 11 of 8 mo. 1684. 'Tis, our judgement that it were better and more clear to be incerted. The Sentence is this. Neither do We understand that such a grant as was expect∣ed was attainable, when the 2d. grant was solicited for.</Q>
The design of incerting this is easily seen, to be to cover <HI>Billings</HI> head, from a stroke that otherwise would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>evita∣bly have fallen upon him: For, knowing that the Right of the thing sought for belonged to the People, which also is acknowledged in the <HI>Award,</HI> page the 2d. and 4th.; it could not but look ill in him, so much as to take it in his own name, if it could have been otherwise obtained: But whose judgement it is, that <HI>it were better and more clear, that that Sentence should be inserted,</HI> I know not; for they have placed it under, and after the names of the Arbitra∣tors, and I would hope, that it is none of their act, nor have I any reason to believe it to be so, since I am sure, there is nothing of it in that they delivered to me, and I am not willing to entertain a thought, that after the time
<PB N="14" REF="000865_0013_0FABF35A386539B0"/>
was elapsed, and the Award given, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> add to, or alter, what was before so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> they should I <HI>judge</HI> such an action to be <HI>Irregu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and Unwarrantable, unsafe▪ and worthy of blame in all Per∣sons concerned therein.</HI> But before I pass from this, I must note, that whereas any 8 of the <HI>Awarders</HI> had power to de∣termine, there is no more than the bare number, several of those who were appointed, hearing little of the Case, and some none at all, others were dissatisfied with the <HI>Award,</HI> and thought it much too easy on <HI>Billing's</HI> part, and therefore refused to sign; And yet it will not follow, but they might al be good men, and perfectly agree, in all the necessary prin∣ciples &amp; fundamentals of the <HI>Christ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an Religion,</HI> I shall shew re fully anon; and in the folly of my <HI>Adversaries,</HI> in insi∣nuating the contrary.</P>
<P>I have now don with the <HI>Award</HI> it self, and am come to the <HI>Observations, and Animadversions,</HI> my <HI>Adver∣saries</HI> have made upon it, the first of which, seems to be the work of some <HI>Apostate Quaker</HI>: But be it as it will, my intention is to detect the folly and falshood of it, where I find the <HI>Observator</HI> praying his <HI>Reader</HI> to observe,
<Q>That by the <HI>Award</HI> of those eminent <HI>Quakers</HI> (as he in scornfully calls them▪) the Government was in <HI>Billing,</HI> and not in the People of <HI>West-Jarsey.</HI></Q>
This is true, but the matter is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> so much, in whom it was, as in whom it ought to be: And this was the ground of our complaint against him, that he had abused us, in taking it to himself, and detaining it from us. But I must desire this <HI>Observator</HI> fur∣ther to observe, That though they did acknowledge it was in him, yet not right fully, and therefore they enjoyn him
<Q>To go so far as he is able, and lawfully can do to their (viz the <HI>Proprietors</HI>) just satisfaction.</Q>
See <HI>The Case put</HI> &amp;c. Page the 4th. And they give reasons for it, and great and va∣lid ones too, as in the first Paragraph page the 2d. viz
<Q>That <HI>E. Billing</HI> hath, by concessions, signed by himself, with other words and circumstances, as also by Letters Written by <HI>Gawen Lowry, Nicholas Lucas &amp;c.</HI> to the <HI>Proprietors,</HI> given them ground to expect that they should
<PB N="15" REF="000865_0014_0FABF35B42724820"/>
have and had the Government with the Soyl.</Q>
Here I confess <HI>Billing</HI> hath been too hard for us; for had We only given him an expectation on the consideration; as he did us of the Purchase, We had been of equall terms with him; and why not as much reason for the one, as the other. But to return. The first reason the <HI>Arbitrators</HI> assign for his doing as aforesaid, is, because of the <HI>Concessions</HI> made and <HI>Signed by him self,</HI> which were made the bait to catch buyers, and I believe few purchased before they had seen them; which concessions lodged the whole power of Govern∣ment in the <HI>Generall Assembly,</HI> and were to be so inviolably observed, <HI>that whoever shoud but attempt to break them, was to be deemed an Enemy to the peace and Priviledges of the</HI> Province: yea, so sacred were they esteemed, <HI>that if any refused to sign them, they were not to be admitted to the pos∣session of any Land, though before bought and paid for.</HI> Secondly <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>couragement given by the Sell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s, in di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>vers letters <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> affirming, <HI>that they had the Govern∣ment with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and were ready to sell, and make a good title to both</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Because of <HI>some words</HI> (they say) <HI>in some of their Deeds, giving</HI> an <HI>expectation that the Proprie∣tors should or might have the Government or power to elect a</HI> Governour <HI>among themselves.</HI>
Thus it is evident, that these <HI>Awarders</HI> did grant, That though the Legal part of the Government was in <HI>Billing</HI>; yet, as they supposed, the equi∣table part belonged to us, And though they seemed to doubt, whether he could legally and safely perform, to a Punctil∣lio, all that he had given us an expectation of, <Q>yet (say they) We all agree, that he is thereby bound to perform to the <HI>Proprietors,</HI> so far as he legally and safely may do. And also We judge, that the said <HI>Billing</HI> ought to go so far as he is able, and lawfully can in all things to their just satisfaction.</Q>
(What is this, but to divest himself so far as he could, and invest the <HI>Proprietors</HI> with the Govern∣ment: But I know they proceeded upon a notion, that this he could not safely or legally do, wholly (which per∣haps was a thing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itter to have been argued by <HI>Lawyers</HI>) and
<PB N="16" REF="000865_0015_0FABF35D249B2B88"/>
therefore they prescribe)
<Q>That he shall make and confirm unto them [<HI>the Proprietors</HI>] such Fundamental Laws, con¦cessions and provisions, consonant, and not repugnant to the Laws and Government of the Realm of <HI>England,</HI> as may fully secure them from all abuses, oppressions and enchroachments upon their freedoms and liberties, both as men and <HI>Christians,</HI> by and from himself; his heirs or Assigns, according to the contents of his own letter dated the 15 of 8. mo. 1680. sent with his last grant from the <HI>Duke.</HI></Q>
What is here enjoyned, has never been perfor∣med, by <HI>Billing,</HI> nor any of his <HI>Successors,</HI> which were it done (I suppose) would satisfie very fully all the <HI>Proprie∣tors,</HI> and well disposed <HI>Inhabitants</HI> in the <HI>Province.</HI> I have insisted the longer on this head fully to clea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the point, not intending to touch it any more.</P>
<P>What the <HI>Observator</HI> saith, of my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>condemned by</HI> the Awarders <HI>for betraying my trust</HI>; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> it is in its self a <HI>Falshood,</HI> and piece of the <HI>Forgery</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> upon them, I have said enough to it already, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>erefore pass it by, But the last part of this first paragraph must detect for its falshood, finding it there charged;
<Q>That I affirm the Government to be in the People, thereby encouraging and exciting the people to rebellion against the present <HI>Go∣vernour,</HI> and other their lawfull <HI>Rulers,</HI> to the great ob∣struction of the peace and prosperity of the <HI>Province.</HI></Q>
Sure∣ly this <HI>Observator</HI> is much a stranger, to the reason of the <HI>Province's</HI> not owning the present Government (for so is the act of the is <HI>Representatives</HI>) Did We break upon that foot? N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y, did We not desist from urging that point? the first Assembly that sate after <HI>Jeremiah Basse's</HI>▪ arrival, on purpose to try i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> We could come to an accommodation, and had he had the <HI>King's</HI> approbation, he had been recog∣nized, as the minutes of that <HI>Assembly</HI> will shew. There∣fore this charge is as wrong as falshood can make it, to say nothing of malice: Nor have I made it my business to <HI>excite</HI> others <HI>to disobey the Government</HI>: Which if I had, I should have counted no <HI>Rebellion,</HI> because, I never thought
<PB N="17" REF="000865_0016_0FABF35D3B77C140"/>
the <HI>Authority,</HI> by which they acted, lawfull; Which ha∣ving said, shall hereafter say little in my own vindication, to any charge against me, for non subjection to the Govern∣ment, esteeming it now almost too late, for any man to give a reason for that; it's rather now their part that exercise that <HI>Authority,</HI> to consider of a reason for their so doing.</P>
<P>What is said in the next paragraph concerning <HI>P. Fret∣well</HI> and <HI>T. Gardiner,</HI> who are termed <HI>two of my Minions amd Quondam Justices.</HI> I shall say little to, further than this, that I know divers of the things suggested against them to be false, and believe so of the rest, and cannot think their reputation hurt by it, since the names of their <HI>Accu∣sers</HI> are known. However, there may be a fit time to look into those things▪ when the <HI>wheel,</HI> I lately advised them <HI>to consider the motion of,</HI> has advanced its nether parts a little more. Methinks if there were a <HI>Conjurer</HI> amongst them, they might ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, and avoided many absurdities, they have fall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> in this short liv'd <HI>Usurpation.</HI> The rest that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> a <HI>hence it is,</HI> I shall say little to, because I perc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> know not whence it is, that the things they mention have arose. And as to that of <HI>Salem,</HI> I believe they can never prove what they say, there may be a time to call for it, if they can. What is said concerning <HI>a great meeting, held at my Plantation house in</HI> December <HI>last,</HI> I shall not gratifie my <HI>Adversaries</HI> so much, as to give them any account of it, further than in a general Way, that I hope it hath not proved uneffectual.</P>
<P>But I would fain know What these Busy Bodies have to do, to call in question the actions of that <HI>Assembly,</HI> where they say, that <HI>I and my faction refused to sign the Association of fidelity to King WILLIAM?</HI> I ask my <HI>Adversaries,</HI> if they ever knew any <HI>Quaker</HI> that did or could sign such an <HI>In∣strument?</HI> But although We could not sign that for Con∣science sake, something being in it, that We could not comply vvith; yet We did sign to a Declaration of our Al∣leigance and Fidelity to the <HI>King</HI> and Government, such as the <HI>Governour</HI> vvas pleased to accept and commend, and I
<PB N="18" REF="000865_0017_0FABF35E0BB281C0"/>
suppose was since transmitted to <HI>White<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>all,</HI> and no dislike shown to it, that ever We have heard of; So that I must tell them, It's a saucy, as well as a busy part, for them to meddle with it. But the great charge is yet behind viz <HI>That I am a great Jacobite</HI>: This is not the First time that these fools have been nibling at this; but finding their proof formerly to be gouty and lame, they let it fall, but now renew it again, thinking themselves cock sure, and that they can prove it with a Witness, which they thus attempt to do viz.
<Q>He covenants with those to whom he sells his Land, in their Deeds, to pay their Quit Rents to the late King <HI>James,</HI> a known Enemy to the Kingdom; this all who please may see recorded in the Registers Office at <HI>Bur∣lington.</HI></Q>
This is a piece of pure envy, as well as folly; whether it hath any shadow of truth in it I know not, It's long since I signed any <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eed: But <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> it to be true; where's the offence? The Quit-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to him when <HI>Duke,</HI> and were none of the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of the Crown. But to expose my <HI>Adversaries</HI> a littl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> consider how considerable these profits may be, which I have been so care∣full to secure to King <HI>James.</HI> I suppose, by what I have heard from others, it's not more than one Deed, of the ma∣ny I have executed, that<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s thus faulty, and that perhaps for one hundred acres, or perhaps less; for I am wholly a Stranger to it on my own knowledge, but suppose it should be two hundred; What will it amount to? Our whole <HI>Province</HI> pays but Tenn Nobles a year to the <HI>Lord</HI> of the <HI>Soyl,</HI> be it to whom it will: So that this proportion will hardly be a half penny in twenty years. Now judge <HI>Reader,</HI> This is the test, they say, I have given of my being a <HI>Ja∣cobite</HI>; I am sure, they have given a far greater of their malice, and sometimes I have thought, that it was necessa∣ry, that such a day as this, should be put into the hands of these and such like men, that they might fully discover themselves, which being done, they might receive the correction of their own Folly, and all men might abhor them.</P>
<P><PB N="19" REF="000865_0018_0FABF35EAB8D8940"/>In the next place I am charged with <HI>having got away the Book of the Laws of the Province,</HI> for proof of which they say <HI>my Friend</HI> H. Grubb <HI>informs them fo.</HI> I shall leave this <HI>to Henry</HI> to acquit himself as he can, for be sure he denies it to me; but whatever he saies, I say it's false, and so much for that.</P>
<P>I am now come to my <HI>Observator's</HI> Lastly, which I sup∣pose was reserved for a Clintcher, and saies
<Q>It is not to be doubted, but when a Committee of both houses did debate <HI>S. Jenings</HI> and his Parties pretentions to the Government, at the Assembly held in <HI>November</HI> 1697. It did inspire great boldness to <HI>Jenings</HI> and his Faction to proceed as they have done, that the then Governour <HI>Hamilton</HI> did plead so sti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly for them and their pretended Right, and had not one word to offer on behalf of the Society, for which his Zeal on their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and against the Society, they ho∣nestly answered <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> expectation with a present of 200 pound.</Q>
Methinks, how lavishly soever, they had used their tongues and Pen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s against me, they might have spa∣red our late <HI>Governour,</HI> especially being absent. But, certainly this is suffered, that the world may knew, the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly, rage and rudeness of these men, to be such, as that there is nothing so mean, unmanly and base, that they wil stick at, if they can but hope, thereby to malign and injure those to whom they are disaffected: But seeing it is so generally expected and desired, that <HI>Collonell Hamilton's</HI> approach to this Place, may be near, I shall say the less to it; but must say so much, That he is much traduced and abused in it; nor do I believe, that any body, besides these three or four men, whom prejudice hath thus corrupted, will or can say, that in that conference, any thing fell from <HI>Collon. Hamilton,</HI> indecent or disregardfull towards the <HI>Society.</HI> But to render it a Compact or Combination (which it must needs be if I understand their dark sentences) is such a piece of villany, as none, but those of their own herd, would offer to suggest: For if the <HI>Governour</HI> ex∣pected, and We <HI>honestly answered his expectation, with a
<PB N="20" REF="000865_0019_0FABF35F6E14A950"/>
Present of</HI> 200 <HI>pound,</HI> for the reasons aforesaid, I can make no other construction of it' But however, I hope I shall now ride quietly, and injoy the use of my Horse, without further reflection; for if the 200 pound, was given upon the consideration they have now assigned, then it was not for the Horse, and they must be mistaken in one: But what if it was for neither? Which I believe no body doubts but themselves, how ill then do they deserve, at the hands of those they have thus stigmatized? And therefore it will be their wisdom (in my opinion) to make sure of their evidence, for what they asse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, against the time that it may be required of them. I shall not trace my <HI>Observator</HI> much further, having followed him to <HI>the Mobb here, and scum of England</HI>; where I intend to leave him, as very fit compa∣ny for him, if I am not much mistaken in my guess.</P>
<P>I am now come to their <HI>Animadvers<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI> and I hope near a close of my work, finding it now <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> out of season, to controvert the matters therein contained; Providence ha∣ving found out a much better way of decision than that of any man's Pen: For since the main design and end of them, is, like so many shores, to support their tottering <HI>Authori∣ty,</HI> which I now see is like to fall flatt, maugre all their Props, it makes me the less concerned to remove them; yet not wholly to pass them by, I shall reduce them to these following heads, which I think comprehend most of the matter contained in them: And since the <HI>Award</HI> is the foundation on which they are built, I having already shown the Injustice and Injury done to me, by the <HI>Forgeries</HI> and <HI>Falsehoods,</HI> contained in what they have Printed, and called the <HI>Award,</HI> I shall pass that by and consider.</P>
<P N="1">1. <HI>Their charge of Non-Conformity to the</HI> Award.</P>
<P N="2">2. <HI>The emptiness of their silly conceit, and false, as well as foolish suggestion</HI>; That, Because our Friends Hold and maintain, a neeessity of the Immediate guidance of Gods Holy Spirit, in all Religious Performances; <HI>that therefore it must follow,</HI> That We pretend the same in all our civil affairs; <HI>Which is on their part to prove.</HI></P>
<P N="3"><PB N="21" REF="000865_0020_0FABF3607230F7F0"/>3. <HI>That every dissent in opinion from the Judgement of each other in things natural and common▪ proceeds from</HI> a spi∣rit of error, <HI>and is matter of</HI> scandall and disgrace.</P>
<P N="4">4. <HI>That We Preach up our Friends as the</HI> Messengers of Truth and not inferiour <HI>to any of the Holy Apostles.</HI></P>
<P N="5">5.
<HI>Their repeated charge of Rebellion</HI> <Q><HI>and that I should tell the present</HI> Governour <HI>to his face,</HI> That I neither liked him nor his Commission, did therefore from thenceforth denounce perpetual hostility against him, and should not cease to make War upon him, until I had driven him out of the Government.</Q></P>
<P N="6">6. <HI>Whether</HI> Jeremiah Basse <HI>had the</HI> Kings <HI>approbation, according to the true intent of a late</HI> Act <HI>of</HI> Parliament, <HI>in that Case provided.</HI></P>
<P N="7">7. <HI>How far it concerns us to inquire into it▪</HI></P>
<P N="8">8. <HI>Whether they or We have transgressed the late</HI> Act <HI>of</HI> Parliament, <HI>as it is suggested, we have done.</HI></P>
<P>And lastly, <HI>Their indecency, after all their abuses, to take upon them, to act a</HI> Religious <HI>part.</HI></P>
<P>First, <HI>Their charge against me and my Friends, for Non-conformity to the</HI> Award. To the which I answer, Neither <HI>Billing,</HI> nor his <HI>Successors,</HI> did ever perform their part, as I have before shewn, and our part depending upon a con∣dition never performed on their part, I take to be a Release to us. However our not recognizing the present <HI>Government,</HI> was never on that foot, as is plain from what is already said.</P>
<P N="2">2. <HI>The emptiness of their silly conceit, and false, as well as foolish suggestion; That, Because our Friends, do hold and maintain, a necessity of the Immediate guidance and assistance of Gods Holy Spirit, in all Religious performances; that therefore it must follow, that We pretend the same, in all our civil and common concerns, which is on their parts to prove.</HI> And if they fail in this supposition, which is the foun∣dation of all their structure; then the inferences drawn from it, must be unnatural, weak and idle: And that they are mistaken in this, I affirm, and charge it upon them as a
<PB N="22" REF="000865_0021_0FABF365C36E0958"/>
falsehood; let them acquit themselves if they can.</P>
<P N="3">3. <HI>That every dissent in opinion, from the Judgement of each other, in things natural and common, proceeds from a spirit of errour, and is matter of scandal &amp; disgrace</HI> This being another inference, drawn from that false supposition, must <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all with it, and be numbred amongst the rest of the falsehoods and abuses put upon us. Surely these <HI>Adversa∣ries,</HI> had shewn more wit, as well as honesty, if they had not personated the <HI>Quakers,</HI> and spoke so many things in their name, till they had known them, and their Princi∣ples better.</P>
<P N="4">4. <HI>That We preach up our Friends, as the Messengers of Truth, and not inferiour to any of the holy Apostles.</HI> That We own <HI>our Friends as the Messengers of truth,</HI> That are employed in the Gospel Ministry, is true. And let me ask them, Pray whose <HI>Messengers</HI> are your <HI>Ministers,</HI> if not <HI>Messengers of Truth?</HI> But <HI>that We preach, or believe them, not to be inferiour to any of the Holy Apostles</HI>; I utterly de∣ny, and if my <HI>Adversaries</HI> cannot prove it, I must call this a falsehood also.</P>
<P N="5">5. <HI>That I should tell the present</HI> Governour <HI>to his face, That</HI> I <HI>neither liked him, nor his</HI> Commission <HI>&amp;c·</HI> And what of all this; I believe I might say that, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> something like it, and when all is done; How will he help himself? But I suppose this is a fault, my <HI>Adversaries</HI> are little guilty of, viz., to speak their resentments to the faces of their <HI>Adversaries</HI>: They are too full of falshood and flattery for that. But that I should say, <HI>I did therefore from thenceforth denounce perpetual hostility against him, and should not cease to make war upon him until I had driven him out of the Go∣vernment</HI>; is a notorious B—, there being at the same time and place, I believe, not less than a dozen persons, who heard what discourse passed, betwixt <HI>Jeremiah Basse</HI> and me, and believe none beside <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> B.</HI> himself, will say, That I said any such thing: Could I and some others whom they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, have used that liberty, I believe those arrogant Insulters might sooner have been reduced to better manners:
<PB N="23" REF="000865_0022_0FABF366E61530F8"/>
But upon his telling me, <HI>He believed</HI> I <HI>would use my endea∣vours to remove him from the Government, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> in</HI> Coll. Hamilton <HI>again</HI>; I did tell him, <HI>That he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> hand at guessing, and that he might depend upon</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> And though I hope it<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s nigh to be effected, yet I cannot be so vain as to imagine, that any interest tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ould make either pro or con could be much available; however I own, my hearty wishes, with many others, have been for it, and nothing willingly omitted, that might contribute to it, the benefit of which (I hope) We shall soon have the enjoy∣ment of.</P>
<P N="6">6. <HI>Whether</HI> Jeremiah Basse <HI>had the</HI> Kings <HI>approbation, accordng to the true intent of a late</HI> Act <HI>of</HI> Parliament, <HI>in that case provided.</HI> To which I shall Presume to make to other answer, than what the <HI>Provincial General Assembly</HI> have done, at then two last sittings. At the first of which, to the best of my remembrance it was Resolved, <HI>Nemine Contradicente,</HI>
<Q>That he had not the <HI>Kings</HI> approbation, neither as the <HI>Act</HI> of <HI>Parliament</HI> directs, nor after any other or circumstantial manner, and for that reason refused to re∣cognize him <HI>Governour.</HI></Q>
And though some few that were <HI>Members</HI> of that <HI>Assembly,</HI> did afterwards crouch, after a base and beggarly, treacherous manner, for thet sake of places or profit or honour, and some of these very persons, were again upon the last <HI>Assembly</HI>; yet the number did not exceed five out of near fifty, but what declared themselves as much dissatisfied at this sitting, as they were at the for<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mer, in the case aforesaid.</P>
<P>But how vain and frivolous their arguments, deduced from the case of the late <HI>Governour Hamilton,</HI> Because, <HI>he was not approved nor sworn according to the Act, which took p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ace sometime before he was superseded,</HI> is very obvious, and his case with <HI>Jeremiah Basses</HI> hol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s no paralel. For when <HI>Co∣lonel Hamilton</HI> was e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>alled <HI>Governor,</HI> there was no such <HI>Act,</HI> and his <HI>Authority</HI> was good without it, and this <HI>Act</HI> was never transmitted hither, by order of the <HI>Crown,</HI> to weaken it; So that it remained good <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ill, and he was not
<PB N="24" REF="000865_0023_0FABF366F6F66F40"/>
obliged to know, that there was any such <HI>Act</HI> in being, unless it had been sent, as aforesaid. And as to his <HI>not ob∣taining a</HI> Dedimus Potestatem, <HI>to enable him to take the Oath &amp;c.</HI> I think it had been a very preposterous thing in him to have sought it; It was as much as concerned him, to have obeyed the commands of his <HI>Sovereign,</HI> when requi∣red; Which, I dare say, he would never have refused: But this being never done, nor any law appearing to enjoin it, I think it not improper to use the old maxim viz, <HI>Where there is no Law, there is no transgression.</HI> But this is none▪ of <HI>Jeremiah Basse's</HI> case; He comes immediately out of <HI>England,</HI> where he might, and ought to know, and doubt less did know, that there was such an <HI>Act</HI> in force, and that it was his duty to obey it, and that his <HI>Authority</HI> could not be good without it; Yet notwithstanding presumes (he saies by advice of some of those he calls his <HI>Council</HI>) to publish his <HI>Commission,</HI> and impose his <HI>Authority</HI> upon us; to which I shall have occasion to speak a little more anon.
<Q>But (say my Opponents) 'tis manifest by the <HI>Dedimus Potestatem,</HI> which the now <HI>Governour</HI> brought along with him—that he comes to this Government, approved of by his.</Q>
<HI>Majesty</HI> Now they begin to bring out their strong reasons; but let us try them a little· That Instrument, did no more but give power, to persons within named, to administer the Oath, to the <HI>Governour</HI> for the time being: That might have been any body else, as well as him, and to be sure could never be intended for him, seeing it was given, at least three months before the date of his <HI>commission,</HI> and it's most probable, was committed to the care of the <HI>Society</HI> of <HI>West-Jersey,</HI> to be by them sent hither, for the service intend<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed. So that; if his being the <HI>Messenger,</HI> to bring the <HI>De∣dimus Potestatem</HI> hither, be a manifest and undeniable proof of the <HI>Kings</HI> approbation, I must yeild the point; and thus I leave it What they say of
<Q>His Instructions from the <HI>Lords Justices,</HI> signed by the <HI>Lords Commissioners</HI> of the <HI>Treasu∣ry</HI>—And a letter from his <HI>Majesty,</HI> addressed to him in the stile of <HI>Governour</HI> of <HI>New Jarsey</HI> (as also) the printed <HI>Ga∣zets</HI>
<PB N="25" REF="000865_0024_0FABF367C4139058" MS="y"/>
published by Authority, wherein his <HI>Majesties</HI> ap∣probation of him, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Governour</HI> of the <HI>Jer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ys</HI> was davertized, and several other writings, Instruments and Testimonials, which (they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>) are as so many unquesti∣onable vouchers and irrefragable proofs; that he comes to his Gouvernment approved of by his <HI>Majestey,</HI> accord∣ing to the said <HI>Act</HI> of <HI>Parliament.</HI></Q>
I say, all this I know nothing of, and knowing the <HI>Asser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers</HI> so well, have no reason to credit it. Nor do I believe, that any of the writings or Instruments aforesaid, had any particular rela∣tion to him; but were intended to the <HI>Governour</HI> for the time being. So that I see no reason (from all that they have offered to prove his approbation) to recede from my former opinion; That he neither had, or, which is more, is never like to have it.</P>
<P N="7">7thly <HI>How far it concerns us to inspect whether he hath or hath it not.</HI></P>
<P>I have alwaies observed, these have been the two m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an Engines, these <HI>Janisaries</HI> have used, to batter down the opposition they have met with, to their <HI>Authority.</HI> First, They would labour to perswade <HI>that he had the Kings ap∣probation, if not so formally as the</HI> Act <HI>directs, yet he had what was tantamount to it.</HI> But if this b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at would not take, then the second was, <HI>It concerns none here to enquire or look into it; Is he the less a</HI> Gouvernour <HI>if he wants it? He only forfeits his thousand pounds.</HI> I confess I could never be brought over to this opinion, and that for this reson; That seeing it hath seemed meet to the wisdom of <HI>England,</HI> to enact, That no subject shall be any longer permitted, to appoint a <HI>Gouvernour</HI> over their fellow subjects, without the <HI>Royal</HI> approbation, and allowance declared in the s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d <HI>Act</HI>: Who is he that shall dare presume, to commission any person, at any time, to exercise the necessary <HI>Regal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s</HI> of Government? Or who is he that being so commissio∣ned, dares to exercise such <HI>Authority</HI> without it? Is not this to bid defiance to the <HI>Authority</HI> of <HI>England</HI>; especially since <HI>America</HI> is expressly within the intent of the <HI>Act.
<PB N="26" REF="000865_0025_0FABF36A1289DD68" MS="y"/>
But</HI> (say they) the <HI>Act relates to trade, and not to Govern∣ment.</HI> But I must tell them, That what belongs to the constitution of a <HI>Governour,</HI> must needs very sensibly affect the Government, if the having a well qualified <HI>Governour,</HI> be any advantage to a Government, or if to have an ill one, be the contrary. And farther, I think it looks a little unhandsome, if not disloyal, for them to suggest, That the <HI>King</HI> regards the advantages of trade more than the weal of his subjects; For as Parents value their Children above their Inheritances, or Worldly ad∣vantages, so we ought to beleive, that the <HI>King</HI> as Fa∣ther of all his subjects, in a Political sense, more regards their well being, than all the advantages of trade. Why should we not then thankfully embrace the <HI>Kings</HI> bounty to us, who will himself be satisfied, who, or what they are, that are so posted, and not suffer every little fellow, to make his Insults over his Subjects And I still hold my o∣pinion, That if any shall attempt it, it is most lawfull, and loyal for the People not to submit to their <HI>Authority</HI> who pretend to any so high as that of a <HI>Governour,</HI> especi∣ally by their <HI>Representatives,</HI> when legally met together; in whom resides a considerable share of the necessary powers of Government, and who must act along with him, if any thing in <HI>Legislation</HI> be acted. So that I am still of opinion, That it very much concerns them to be satisfied, in order to their own safety, as well as preservation of their Previled∣ges, whom they ioyn with, in acts of so high a nature, and to do otherwise were s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pine negligence, and unworthy of the trust to which they were elected. I shall not follow them further on this subject at this time, believing th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <HI>Pen-man</HI> has lost his labour bestowed thereon, and that his sophistical endeavours will prove abortive, as most of his projects have hitherto done.</P>
<P>Yet I shall take a little notice of the slant blow, they give at such little souls as <HI>Samuel Jenings</HI>; which I could <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> well have passed by, but that I thought it was a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> opportunity to lay hold of, to shew the magnanimity of
<PB N="27" REF="000865_0026_0FABF36B15BA60C0"/>
these great towering Counsellours: Who upon the report of <HI>Coll. Hamiltons</HI> being superseded by <HI>Jeremiah Basse,</HI> did express their resentments of it with great reluctancy, were the first that moved <HI>Coll. Hamilton</HI> to convene the <HI>Assembly,</HI> to consider if any thing could be done, to prevent so mise∣rable an exchange: When the <HI>Assembly</HI> met, were the men that solemnly promised to the <HI>Governour</HI> and <HI>Assembly,</HI> to use their Interest, if <HI>Jeremiah Basse</HI> should arrive, un∣der the circomstances as was reported before an other <HI>Assem∣bly,</HI> to disswade him from publishing his <HI>Commission,</HI> till we heard again from the <HI>Society</HI> in <HI>England,</HI> to whom we had written, and that <HI>Coll: Hamilton's Commission</HI> might not be thereby superseded. How real they were and how they have acquitted themselves like men of common honesty, to mention nothing higher, is so well known in these parts, as renders an information useless. But before I have done with this, I must give another instance, of the fidelity and greatness of these men; in wich I must make a little digres∣sion, while I inform, or rather remind my <HI>Reader,</HI> That, the controversy betwixt the <HI>Sucessours</HI> of <HI>Billing,</HI> and the <HI>Proprietors</HI> here, was never yet determined; which hath occasioned jarrs and misunderstandings, to be kept on foot betwixt them and us; to prevent which for the future, these <HI>great souls</HI> did agree, at the then <HI>Governours</HI> motion, together to write a perswasive Letter to the <HI>Society,</HI> to grant us what we requested, and believed was our right: This was performed, signed by the <HI>Governour</HI> and his <HI>Council</HI> (of wich these men were a part) delivered in to the house of <HI>Representatives,</HI> to be sent to <HI>England,</HI> and accordingly was sent; Yet these very men, my present <HI>Adversaries,</HI> sent another privately about the same time, to disswade the person that both they and we had addressed, as aforesaid, from granting our re∣quest. Now what thinkest thou, <HI>Reader,</HI> of the sixe of these mens souls? Had they dealt thus with a private per∣son, it had been very detestable; but to do it to a <HI>Pro∣vince,</HI> is a thing so unaccountable, I shall leave it without
<PB N="28" REF="000865_0027_0FABF36B8BFE4C18" MS="y"/>
a name.</P>
<P N="8">8thly <HI>Wether they or we have transgressed the</HI> Act <HI>of</HI> Par∣liament <HI>as it is suggested we have done.</HI> This is so plain a case, that I shall leave it to the decision of my <HI>Reader,</HI> ha∣ving said so much already on this head: But if to cont<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d for obedience to the requirings of the <HI>Act,</HI> be a Trans∣gression of it, we will submit to their charge.</P>
<P>Lastly, <HI>Their Indecency, after all their abuses, to take upon them to act a</HI> Religious <HI>part.</HI> This puts me in mind of the old Proverb, viz <HI>When the Fox begins to preach, be∣w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re the geese.</HI> The best of it is, there is not many here, that much affect the <HI>Relígion</HI> of these men, but especially that o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the <HI>Penn-man</HI>; if yet he may be supposed to have a∣ny at all. But that nothing might be wanting, that falsehood and flattery could furnish them withal, they pretend, that what they do, is, in tenderness to the people and inhabi∣tants of the <HI>Province</HI> of <HI>West-New-Jarsey</HI>; than which not∣hing could be more remote from them, and is so appa∣rent, that I think none by these means will b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> deceived by them.</P>
<P>And now for <HI>Conclusion</HI>: I shall (as I have promised) touch a little upon the last paper these men posted against me; which I find so full of scurrility and railery - that I scarce know where to touch it without fouling my fingers. It doth indeed render them <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sters of</HI> their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and the extravagancy of their abuses to me in it are such, as makes it the less needfull for me to make any defence against it. For when any have so debaucht-their tongues or pens, as to have no regard to the truth of what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey say or write, instead of blemishing those with whom they con∣tend, they brighten them, and only hit themselves a box on the ear: For which reason, I can very contentedly be silent, to all the scorn, reproach and falsehood they would dis∣guise me with; knowing that men of candour will see-for themselves, and not be imposed upon by such notori∣ous▪ ungenerous and s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eaking <HI>Adversaries.</HI></P>
<P>I perceive they are uneasy, that I still insist upon
<PB N="29" REF="000865_0028_0FABF36C43602A90" MS="y"/>
my charge of <HI>forgery</HI> against them, from which I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> never acquit them, nor will all their shuffling, wrigli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>, twisting and twining extricate them from the guilt of it. They ask a question of me, which I cannot answer viz "Did we receive or forge the <HI>Award?</HI> They might be guilty of the worst part of it, for ought I know: But as I have said before; it concerns not me to enquire how they came by it, but they printed and published it, forged as it is, and on whom should I charge the guilt of this foul act, but on them, the justice of which, I leave to the censure of my <HI>Reader.</HI></P>
<P>Their reflections upon those judicious persons that I mentioned, whom they render <HI>Comical</HI>; and Ianus <HI>like with to faces each,</HI> I shall not meddle with; knowing them to be sufficiently able to make their own defence, if they think themselves abused by it.</P>
<P>I find they would have the world beleive, and there∣fore say
<Q>They solemnly declare [that what they have done] was not from any resentment or disaffection to me, or any other particular person or persons.</Q>
To which I shall not answer a word, but leave my <HI>Reader</HI> free, to judge of the truth of it upon perusal. I judge, with the like sincerity they mention the <HI>Awarders,</HI> with a shew of respect; which serves only as a further discovery of their hypocrisy, who have at times, so freely expressed resentments against <HI>Quakers</HI> in general.
But they proceed to point at othes: under the same denomination <Q>who for their Probity, Veracity, or other wise, co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pared with them, will not appear better than spurious, a re∣proach to the name, but as boils and botches to the body they hypocritically pretend to.</Q>
Here I am willing (though not for their merit) to spare a little those <HI>common tools</HI> who signed along with the <HI>Pen-man</HI>; believing, that in reality they have been little more concerned, than the <HI>Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> that it<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s fabled▪ the <HI>Monkey</HI> made use of the Paw of for hot service<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to save his own. But to return, Methinks this man should have been very cautions of
<PB N="30" REF="000865_0029_0FABF36CF24621E8" MS="y"/>
exhibiting such a charge against others, knowing his own circumstances; and how well they are known to others here; Who for his—has been spued out of the most corrupt body pretending to <HI>Christianity,</HI> or like a bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>h or s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>h dropt from it: And though I know he would thus mask it, viz, That it is allowable and commendable for men to reform; yet his not attempting it till under Impeach∣ment carries no good nor honest aspect with it.</P>
<P>And here I should breake off and conclude, were it not that I am charged with <HI>murther</HI>; I am glad that the charge is no higher than <HI>murthering English and sense</HI>; better so than to murther <HI>English</HI> in the worst <HI>sense.</HI> But here I must tread softly, least it revive old jealousies, and look to my own safety; being threatned (though I hope it is not ominous) in these words.
<Q>There fore shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> come upon thee, thou shalt not know from whence it riseth; and mischief shall fall upon thee, thou shall not be able to put it off.</Q>
I hope my <HI>Adversary</HI> may be mistaken; but if it should be otherwise, I should not be the first, that has been suspected to fall after that m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ane<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> nor have I any GOLD to spare to allay his furie or Purchass his favor. But still my trust and confidence is in that <HI>Arm</HI> I mentioned in my first, and shall conclude with it in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>his knowing that in the end, it will be too strong for all i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Opposers and Deriders.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>S: J.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

